<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1925-08-22">Aug. 22, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Good News from Greece.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0380</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0380.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1925-08-22">Aug. 22, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD NEWS FROM GREECE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>EDITORIAL.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly our readers recollect that Saloniki for many, many years through its articles trumpeted the moral and material benefits that Greece could get from the Greeks in America.</p>
   <p>The Greek of America is not what many blind-folded persons thought he was, just a good for nothing pseudo-progressive who acquired a few thousand dollars in the land of plenty and thinks that he is somebody, but an entirely different type of Greek that they knew not as yet. Now they call him American Greek.</p>
   <p>His first name (American) is not acquired as readily as we call a man Mister or Sir, but is acquired only by fundamental assimilation of American ideals, principles, knowledge, actions and progress.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0381.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Greeks on the other side the waters see now (after they took the veil off their eyes) that this American Greek utilizes his American acquired knowledge and pushes his mother land on to progress and prosperity.</p>
   <p>Our articles, which displeased the bigoted from time-to-time governments of Greece, brought out the naked truth of the Greeks in America-that the real progress of Greece depends upon this reborn Greek who is imbued with a truly American spirit of progress and enlightenment. We urged, begged and trumpeted the deaf ears of the past governments of Greece to pay attention, very much attention, to Greeks in America and accelerate their progress by sending to America the proper, well informed and broad-minded national representatives who will render every possible service and assistance to the struggling masses of Greeks who took the road up-hill single-handed, without motherly love, sympathy and encouragement.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0382.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The voice of our articles fell upon the ears of politico-charlatans who underestimated and ignored the potential powers of the American Greeks. Alas! They did not learn the lesson of the former Kaiser and his blind bigots who had underestimated the Greatness of America, saying: (as they were informed by their stupid diplomats to the United States). America is nothing; America has no army, and if she gets one, it will be raw material (untrained). Our army will defeat the world. The result is universally known. God blessed America for its so-called raw material, otherwise the world today would be under the scepter of Kaiserism.</p>
   <p>What we hear and see now in Greece could have been done many years ago, if the American Greek had not been ignored by the ever stupid governments of Greece.</p>
   <p>Many of those who, for one reason or other, did not wish to be permanently established in the United States, preferring sunbathed Greece, after acquiring a certain amount of American dollars, returned to Mother Greece to spend the rest of their lives.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0383.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But those Greeks are reborn. America the Great made them an entirely different type, as we said above. So instead of living the rest of their lives idling and prattling, they go into business utilizing their American knowledge. New business springs up everywhere the American Greek goes. Stores of American type and method are springing up that Greece never dreamed of. Villages and towns are built a la American. Automobile roads penetrate the thickest forests and groves for American automobiles to travel; electrification, new water works, bridges, laundries, new hotels a la American; sanatoriums and what not are materializing through the activities of the formerly ignored Greek of America.</p>
   <p>The present government of Greece begun to take notice and reckon with the activities of those Greeks from America. They are now accepted and recognized not as before, but as progressive and enterprising American Greeks.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0384.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>How things change! Why did Greece not recognize this advantage before, as we urged begged and trumpeted with our articles? However, it is better late than never. Greece will do well to cultivate the ground for the American Greek, not only in Greece but here also. By doing so, Greeks who are permanently established here will love and help their mother land in spite of their marriage to their adopted country.</p>
   <p>The present Greek government has already begun profiting from the mistakes of its predecessors, to pay attention to the American Greek, and will do, as they say, their utmost to promote friendly, amicable and mutually beneficial connections with the Greeks in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
