<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-01-13">Jan. 13, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Honorable Vasilios A. Mamonas Consul General of Greece in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0504</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0504.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-01-13">Jan. 13, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE HONORABLE VASILIOS A. MAMONAS CONSUL GENERAL OF GREECE IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last week the Honorable Vasilios A. Mamonas, the new consul general of Greece in Chicago, arrived from Paris. Mr. Mamonas is a scion of one of those ancient and aristocratic families of Greece which devoted themselves to national politics. He studied law in Greece and after the completion of his studies visited Switzerland, London, Paris, and Berlin, remaining abroad for a number of years to study the political sciences.</p>
   <p>After the successful completion of his studies in foreign countries he returned to Greece, where he passed his examination and was appointed judge in the consular court of Constantinople. In this position he served to the best of his ability for a period of ten years up to the outbreak of the World War. With the declaration of the World War Mr. Mammonas was transferred with the rest of the Greek staff to Switzerland, where under the Greek consul, Mr. Alexandri, he acted as legal advisor for the consulate. From Switzerland he was called to the Paris Peace conference to represent Greece; from Paris he was sent as consul general to Berne, the capital of Switzerland, where he remained for two years and handled many international affairs of confidential nature. Mr. Mamonas is forty-four years old and speaks, besides his mother tongue, French, English, German, and some Italian.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0505.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We hope and pray that the Greeks who are under his supervision will through his kindly offices find their dreams realized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
