<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-07-24">July 24, 1926</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Greek Literature</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0312</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0312.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-07-24">July 24, 1926</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">GREEK LITERATURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greeks were not the first people who found out how to till the earth well, or to fashion metals, but they were the first people who tried to make reason the guide of life.</p>
   <p>Proof of this is found in the very existence of the Greek cities. While other men were living in tribes or under despotic Kings, the Greeks had already gathered themselves together in cities. Societies ruled, not by force, but by the persuasion of an equal law. Another proof of this is found in the Greek books. There we find writers of all sorts, poets, historians and philosophers, habitually striving to get at the reason for events. Greek literature has an interest such as belongs to no other literature. It shows us how man first set about systematic thinking. It shows us how some questions which have been solved since, and others which are still being discussed appeared to the people who first seriously tried to answer them.</p>
   <p>But the Greek books are not merely interesting as showing the methods and aims of early thinkers. They contain results, too, which have had the deepest and widest influnece on the whole of modern life, in religion, morality, science, politics and literature.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0313.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The thoughts of the great Greek thinkers have been bearing fruit in the world ever since they were first uttered. In some special sciences, the work done by the Greeks remains a basis of study to this day, as in ethics, logic and geometry. It is from Greek historians and Greek orators that we read some of the political lessons most directly useful for our own time. Neither the history of Christian doctrine nor the history of the Christian church can be fully understood without reference to the character and work of the Greek mind. Under the influence of Christianity, two principle elements have entered into the spiritual life of modern world; one of these has been Hebrew, the other has been Greek.</p>
   <p>The chief types of poetry, such as epic, lyric, dramatic, the chief types of prose as historical, philosophical, oratorical, are such a matter of course now that we are apt to think of them as existing in the nature of things.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0314.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But some of them did not exist at all, and others existed only in crude terms, when the Greek genius began its work. One after another, as the need of expression in each kind was felt, each of these types was perfected by the creative force of Greek genius. In Greek literature, then, we have not merely a literature very interesting in itself; we have the fountain of all Western literature. The influence of Rome on modern literature has in instances been more direct than that of Greece. But if its influence is traced by its broad stream it will carry us back to a Greek source.</p>
   <p>The Greeks were a physically beautiful race, with great quickness and fineness of perception, which made them feel at once, anything that was exaggerated or absurd, or as we say, in bad taste. One of their favorite maxims was "Mithen Agan" equivalent to (Do not indulge in excess). They were naturally obedient in all things to a sense of fitness and measure- what they called "Kairos", a word which means literally"precision"; the instinct of drawing the line at the right place. So when they built a temple, this instinct kept them from making one part of it too large in proportion to another, or from adding ornaments in the wrong places; <pb facs="5422062_6_0315.jpg" n="4"/>and this is the reason why such a building as the Parthenon at Athens, with its noble simplicity and symmetry, is perfect of its kind. Or if a Greek made a statue, not only did he make the limbs and features on just the right scale for each other, but he refrained from trying to make the stone express more than it fitly could, or do duty for a picture. In the same way, when they wrote books, the Greeks were guided by their sense of fitness. They felt that it was out proportion, and therefore ugly, if the words were greater or rarer than the thought.</p>
   <p>Above all, the Greeks felt that a writer ought to be clear and precise. So, in the best work of Greek writers, we generally find these two things. First, the style is of the right kind for the subject; in poetry, for instance, the epic style is kept distinct from the lyric; historical prose is not written like oratory. Second, the writer tries to be clear. He chooses the words befitting the thought, he does not enslave the thought to the words.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0316.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Greeks excelled, as we have seen, in an instinct for beauty and in the power of creating beautiful forms, and, of all the beautiful things which they created, their own language was the first and most wonderful. The Greek mind was very bright and keen and was accustomed to feeling fine distinctions and light shades by very simple means, and yet with perfect accuracy. By using our turn of phrase instead of another, which would have been equally correct, or with the help of those little words called "participles" which answered to the play of eature or tone of voice in talking, or even by a slight change in the order of the sentence, a Greek could mark with delicate precision the meaning which he meant to convey.</p>
   <p>This peculiar power which the language acquired of being easily bent into the exact shape of the thought, entitles Greek to be called the most flexible of languages. But as the field are better for a botanist than the best collection of dried flowers, so we must go to the Greek books if we would see the language in the feelness of its elastic life. No one who is a stranger to Greek literature has comprehended how perfect an instrument human speech may be.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
