<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-09-15">Sept. 15, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Arcadia Greek Society of Chicago and the Tuberculosis Sanatorium of Taygetos, Greece</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0920</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0920.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-09-15">Sept. 15, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE ARCADIA GREEK SOCIETY OF CHICAGO AND THE TUBERCULOSIS SANATORIUM OF TAYGETOS, GREECE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3- Not very long ago a prominent Chicago Greek, Dr. John Volicos, a Cretan, impelled by the ever-increasing spread of tuberculosis among Chicago Greeks, founded the Taygetos Sanatorium in Greece. But institutions of this kind need unusual financial support. Many of our compatriots afflicted with this dreadful disease leave America aided by contributions of fellow-Greeks who defray the cost of transportation because they know that the patients are financially exhausted. Consequently the sanatorium cannot meet its operating expenses if it is not supported by public contributions and endowments. For the tuberculosis patients, hoping to get well, spend here whatever money they have and then by means of contributions are shipped to Greece.</p>
   <p>For this reason Arcadia, one of the oldest Greek societies in Chicago and one which is ever ready to do good, held a general meeting last week and <pb facs="5422062_6_0921.jpg" n="2"/>discussed ways and means of supporting the Taygetos Sanatorium. After listening to the constructive and humanitarian speech of Dr. Volicos, the society's physician, they, with unanimous voice, agreed to take the lead among all the societies and to contribute systematic financial support to this institution, thus affording an example to other societies and organizations in the United States, that they may do their Hellenic duty likewise.</p>
   <p>The Arcadia Society has many times in the past gone outside its circle and assisted not only individuals in need but also other organizations. We hope and pray that other fraternities, societies, and organizations all over the land will follow the example of this splendid association and come to the assistance of the tuberculosis sanatorium of Taygetos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
