<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-10-03">Oct.3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Chicago Journal and the Salt</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0750</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0750.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-10-03">Oct.3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHICAGO JOURNAL AND THE SALT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our friend Knapp, of the Chicago Journal staff, has again attempted to insult the Greek race.This time it has been done so tastelessly that we readily offer him the saltshaker for which he has asked.</p>
   <p>In a recent article he has recounted the battles in which great numbers of humans have been slaughtered.One of the examples he has written about is the Battle of Plataea, in which 300,000 Persians took part, and only 40,000 survived.The learned Mr.Knapp repudiates this historical fact, and has nerve enough to print his opinion in a newspaper.He probably thinks that at the end of a battle the Greeks piled up the dead bodies of the enemy and their own men and counted them, as did the Texas Indians [sic]. For the sake of accuracy we reprint the exact statement of Mr.Knapp.</p>
   <p>"The Greeks stormed the Persian camp after the Battle of Plataea, and the slaughter was probably greater than at Cannae, although the history of <pb facs="5422062_6_0751.jpg" n="2"/>Herodotus says that of 300,000 men only 40,000 escaped. This statement must be received with a grain of salt.</p>
   <p>"At Himera a whole city was wiped out by the Carthaginian hordes, the Greeks dying in their tracks, with slain enemies heaped around them, like the Texans at the Alamo."</p>
   <p>These false statements, which are injurious to the glorious history of Ancient Greece, have been believed, of course, by some people who are not familiar with Greek history. However, the learned American public--especially the university professor--has declared them to be infamous lies and deliberate misrepresentations of fact.</p>
   <p>Saloniki does not forgive such insults made by an ignorant reporter who obviously does not like the Greek people. We urge the Chicago Greeks to refrain from purchasing or even reading the Chicago Journal. It is not the first time this paper has cast slurs upon the Greek race of yesterday and <pb facs="5422062_6_0752.jpg" n="3"/>today.</p>
   <p>Call the Journal and protest! Show them we are ready to defend our country's honor!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
