<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-10-22">Oct. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Ambassador Koromilas Admonishes the Greeks</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0829</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0829.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-10-22">Oct. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">AMBASSADOR KOROMILAS ADMONISHES THE GREEKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago cannot forget the personality of Mr. Koromilas, the Greek Ambassador, or his fiery patriotic appeal to our people on his visit to us last year. Since his arrival in the United States he has inspired the Greek people to carry on their settlement work in America with courage and faith. Many of us had expected to see a man of words instead of deeds--a man with a sentimental message from our homeland. Instead, he has surprised us by proving himself a worthy representative of Greece in America; a man of genuine patriotism; a man of action. He has shown that he hates demagogic methods, that he loves the truth though it may hurt many of us.</p>
   <p>Some time ago, we remember, he had the courage to defy the leaders of our many divided and disunited organizations and appealed to the Greeks of Chicago, to the Greeks all over America ,to organize and become unified by adopting his proposed plan of organization on a national scale. He took the initiative in suggesting a workable plan whereby our local church communities were asked to <pb facs="5422062_6_0830.jpg" n="2"/>surrender their rights of self-government and independent organization so that they could accept an extensive and nationwide plan of organization binding together all the Greek forces throughout America.</p>
   <p>Some time ago, he surprised us by praising the practical spirit of the Bulgarians, the enemies of Greece, in order to make us, too, think of a practical scheme to organize our lives and institutions in America and thus be enabled to assist our native land in her efforts to rearm and effect internal reconstruction.</p>
   <p>Now, according to the reports of an American daily in New York, in speaking before several units of Greek army volunteers, he mustered the courage to question the sincerity of purpose of many persons and organizations in this nationwide drive for volunteer recruits. He also disapproved of the methods used in organizing these volunteer brigades.</p>
   <p>Very few thought that our distinguished ambassador could speak the naked truth to us without fear.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0831.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the first place, he said that we Greeks, even here in America, are unable to govern ourselves. This, he said, is easily proved by our divided and quarreling communities which are governed by two or more factions, each with its own community leaders and priests. Those who are disgusted with these violent passions and hatreds, which are caused by not more than ten or fifteen ambitious and unscrupulous agitators should adopt the organizational plan of Mr. Koromilas.</p>
   <p>As far as the volunteer brigades are concerned, he said, their organization is very inadequate and seemingly they are the product of momentary enthusiasm. They were not organized with the real intention of helping our homeland. Such volunteer groups as have been formed in Chicago, for instance, have been occupied with electing officers, distributing high-sounding patriotic publications, and contending for other honors. However, the Ambassador did not say that these military units should be dissolved or that they cannot benefit our people, especially our youth and our homeland. What he did suggest is that the volunteer brigades rid themselves of all political quarrels, that they offer the responsibilities of <pb facs="5422062_6_0832.jpg" n="4"/>leadership to patriotic, able, and experienced men.</p>
   <p>If war were declared suddenly and mobilization ordered, it is very doubtful if these brigades could be brought together and sent overseas ready for combat service or further military training, because they have not had the necessary military leadership and elementary training here; and chiefly, because, many of these brigades have been allowed to disintegrate and disperse. Naturally, many of our youth have had some sort of training in marching, drills, gymnastics, and elementary tactics. We were advised not to purchase any guns, uniforms, etc. because, according to international law, we would not be permitted to take them to Greece if we decided to serve in her armed forces.</p>
   <p>The best way to serve our country would be to train here without any guns and uniforms. In the meantime, the money which we could save could be sent to the Greek government or contributed to any local patriotic fund for the military needs of Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0833.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Ambassador said that the insignificant sum of $120,000 which has been collected thus far from the Greeks throughout America must be augmented considerably if we are to make any impression in Greece. We were also told not to allow the many small organizations waste or mishandle the money which is destined to go to Greece. Many would really like to have the Ambassador apportion the collections which are to be taken up in the various cities or towns of the United States. In this way and by honest administration of the campaign, a large amount will be collected and no chance will be given for extravagance, waste, and graft.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
