<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-07-31">July 31, 1926</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">Habits of the Lacedemons</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0308</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0308.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-07-31">July 31, 1926</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">HABITS OF THE LACEDEMONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Napoleon the Great, wishing to know the habits of the Maniates dispatched two Greeks to that principality of Greece with his Imperial credentials, so they would not be molested by the Turks. After their return to Paris the two Stefanopoulos brothers published in French a book titled "The Journey to Greece."</p>
   <p>The citizens of this principality are cognizant of neither extreme poverty, nor too much wealth. Bravery by them is considered an indespensable virtue to maintain liberty. Bodily exercises make them swift, and simplicity in living makes them vigorous. Having no courts and no Judges, they have acquired the habit of respecting one another, and judge amongst themselves any insult or offense. An apology made for an insult, is considered cowardice. The punishment for an insult, sometimes drags two families into a bloody war.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0309.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Frugality constitues their wealth. In their dealings, they have no contracts or any other written documents. Their verbal promise to pay is considered inviolable. They hold nothing holier than honor. A lack of respect for woman is taken as cowardice. The dishonoring of a woman must be paid with bloodshed. The woman knows that she must first respect herself, in order to be respected by others. The conduct of the mother is thought to be the best example for the daughter. The women refrain and abstain from shady clandestine meetings and intrigues. However they are not insensible to th darts of Aphrodite, nor unresponsive to the ardent looks from the eyes of youth. Indeed both sexes participate in mutual respect. The inhabitants of each village or hamlet, live as children of one big family. If a fellow citizen has a big family and not enough produce to keep the family from actual need, the Priest of the village, goes from door to door for contribution. The name of the needy family is not mentioned to any one, and the contributions are delivered to the family in great secrecy.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0310.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Hospitality is a cherished virtue of these people.</p>
   <p>If a stranger or a victim of the Turks, comes to a town of this principality, the hospitality of the inhabitants is great, but he must prove his identity, lest he be unworthy and the bringer of corruption.</p>
   <p>During the intellectual darkness of Greece, when it was under the yoke of the Turkey, Priests were the only teachers of youth, and every ablebodied man including the Maniates fought the war for liberty. Bishops not only urged the people to love their country, but took part on the battlefield, in order to encourage the fighters for liberty.</p>
   <p>The two Stephanopoulos brothers recited what they heard in a school in Mani.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0311.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Priest (teacher) What are you?</p>
   <p>Pupil: A free man, because I am master of my thoughts and my will power.</p>
   <p>Priest: On what do you base your liberty?</p>
   <p>Pupil: Upon the memory of my Spartan progenitors.</p>
   <p>Priest: What are the duties of Maniates?</p>
   <p>Pupil: First, to respect old age, and assist according to our power. Second, to love, honor and with all our power to assist and aid those who gave us life. Third, to run and pay our obligations without being forced. Fourth, to respect and honor marriage; married women to be esteemed as inviolable; girls as sacred persons. Fifth, to maintain our liberty, love our country and be ready to die defending her.</p>
   <p>Upon those lofty principles the soul of the youngster is molded, and the result was that Greece acquired world-wide fame. That part of Greece is still distinguished for producing Greeks who do not know what fear is. Not only males but females equally. Bravery, morality, philosophy, art, music, and self-sacrifice were common to all the Greeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
