<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1927-10-01">October 1, 1927</date><title level="a">Greek News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1927-10-01">October 1, 1927</date><title level="a">GREEK NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many Greeks of Chicago are very anxious to know something about their relatives, who are amongst the refugees from Asia Minew and Eastern Thrace. The Saloniki prints the following for the benefit of all concerned:</p>
   <p>The Great masses of Refugees, about 1,500,000, transferred to Greece, are now, for the most part, settled in fairly comfortable homes and developing land allotted by the Government. Schools and Churches are erected in every settlement. The refugees brought with them their household arts, such as the cottage industry, pottery, embroidery, weaving, etc. They are reproducing the beautiful rugs of Smyrns on Greek soil. Some are going into business for themselves. Going into business is a special aptitude of the Greeks. In part the growth of Saloniki, Greece, is due to this new element which has come to Greece. Salonika now has a population of 500,000.</p>
   <p>Greece is today on the verge of a veritabale rensissance. Granting peace within, and without Greece, may look forward with confidence to the most prosperous spech in her history, not even excepting the Golden Age of Phidias and Pericles. An important factor in this development is the attention given to improve methods of Agriculture.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0268.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There has been built up a notable agricultural school, headed by a veteran, Dr. John Henry House, with his wife and son as assistants. It has a property area of 150 acres, 23 buildings and a community of teachers. Boys from 12to 18 years old are given instructions, in the best methods of farming, and in general and technical lines.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
