<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-09-21">Sept. 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Masked Opposition</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-09-21">Sept. 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MASKED OPPOSITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are writing about some so-called "leading individuals" in our Greek-American community who are audacious and impertinent enough to pose as ambitious and zealous organizers and leaders of our affairs and institutions in Chicago. It is not difficult to detect their hypocrisy and their hidden purposes. We shall not point them out by name, for they have been, and some of them still are, "prominent leaders" in our community life, and consequently they are well known to the Greek people. They are men who have always insisted on their anti-Venizelist principles, men who pray and dream of the ultimate triumph of German might, men who desire to have the exiled King Constantine restored to the Greek throne; these are the same people who a year ago sent the famous telegram to Secretary Lansing to persuade him not to recognize the revolutionary Venizelist government at Saloniki; these men, by their sympathy for King Constantine, have supported indirectly the Bulgarian propaganda here; these men are Greece's <pb facs="5422062_6_0633.jpg" n="2"/>enemies, America's enemies, and enemies to the Allied cause; these men were paid to declare that the Allies made a forced occupation of Greece and that Venizelos is a dictator. These are men who have never repented; they have never been heard praising or even appreciating the work of Venizelos, which has realized the desires of the Greek race for world freedom and the American and Allied aspirations for justice and liberty for all; these men never shed a tear even when they attempted to break up the huge political rally in our city when Messrs. George Kafantaris and Aravantinos, the official representatives of the Venizelist party in Greece, began speaking for the appeasement of the divided and hostile political factions among our Greek people. Now, these men have the nerve to pose as organizers of the Greek community in Chicago!</p>
   <p>Worst of all, these men bear the insignia of a false loyalty. They are cooperating with several of our Venizelist friends. Some of the latter are true Venizelists, true republicans, who are ashamed of having to work with people of this sort. The human mind can scarcely imagine such a gross <pb facs="5422062_6_0634.jpg" n="3"/>pretense.</p>
   <p>We are puzzled by the conduct of some of our friends. They have extended a friendly hand to the fanatics, the emotional and empty-headed royalists, in their effort to reorganize and reconstruct the unfortunate Greek community in Chicago. Patriotic duty has been sacrificed for the sake of a farcical and unattainable community organization. The principles of party and the interests of country are considered less important than the welfare of our Chicago community. Reason has gone stark mad and must be committed to the insane asylum. The hurrahs for Mr. Venizelos have been changed to jeers and boos. Prudence and judgment have been confused and led astray. Duty has lost its way; it has forgotten its mission; it has died by its own hand. Christians and heathens together are carrying bricks to build a church! How horrible!</p>
   <p>The newly arrived emissary of the Orthodox Church of Greece, the Metropolitan Meletios Metaxakis, has asked the pastors of our three church communities for <pb facs="5422062_6_0635.jpg" n="4"/>a detailed report on local religious and social conditions. Our distinguished guest, no doubt, is eager to know the reasons for our internal and civil strife and for the continuous and catastrophic antagonism among us. He will be horrified when he hears that this so-called "organization" of our community is ultimately destined, because of its very nature, to frustrate the work which he is authorized to undertake in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
