<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1913-08-09">Aug. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Funeral of James Floros</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_1041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_1041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-08-09">Aug. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">FUNERAL OF JAMES FLOROS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Funeral services for James Floros, the prominent Greek manufacturer who was shot and killed under such dramatic circumstances last Wednesday night, were held yesterday in the Greek Orthodox Church of the Annunciation.</p>
   <p>Thirty beautiful wreaths of flowers were placed around the coffin. The largest wreaths were those of the Confectioners Association and the Greek Church of the Annunciation, which he had served long and faithfully as president and vice-president, respectively. The weeping and lamentation of the widow, brothers, and other relatives moved all to tears.</p>
   <p>The three [Greek] pastors of Chicago, Reverends Leon Pygeas, Ambrose Mandelaris, and Constantine Hadzidimitriou, and the choirs of the three Greek churches took part in the impressive funeral services. The eloquent Reverend Hadzidimitriou <pb facs="5422062_6_1042.jpg" n="2"/>delivered the funeral oration, which was full of lofty religious sentiments and ideas. He attacked man's vanity and foolish anger.</p>
   <p>About two thousand people escorted the funeral procession to the Union Depot, from where a special train took the deceased to his last resting place at Elmwood Cemetery.</p>
   <p>At the side of the grave where thousands of people had gathered, Dr. Constantine Kallionzis and Mr. Peter S. Lambros, publisher of the Greek Star, spoke briefly, extolling the virtues of the unfortunate victim. Dr. Kallionzis reviewed the outstanding events in Floros' life. He said that Floros was born in Perpini, Lacedaemon, Greece, in 1875. At the age of sixteen, Floros came to America, where he took a business course. By hard work and sheer ability, he became the founder of the Rousetos and Floros Ice Cream Company. He did <pb facs="5422062_6_1043.jpg" n="3"/>patriotic work as adviser to the Greek Youths' Volunteer Regiment, and he was instrumental in organizing the Confectioners' Association, of which he was president. Mention was made of the great services he had rendered the Greek Church of the Annunciation as vice-president of the Board.</p>
   <p>The tragedy and the profound disturbance occasioned in our community by his death will be remembered long after the deceased has been laid to rest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
