<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-11-13">Nov. 13, 1926</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0300</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0300.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-11-13">Nov. 13, 1926</date></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek Symposium in Honor of Mr. Henry Morgenthau.</p>
   <p>p. 1. Over one thousand Greeks of both sexes, held symposium at the Sherman House in honor of Mr. H. Morgenthau.</p>
   <p>This magnificent and stately symposium was given by the united chapters of Ahepa, in conjunction with the Greek communities, and all the Greek schools of Chicago. Mr. Demetrios Poulakis, as Master of Ceremonies, introduced the first speaker, Mr. A. A. Pantelis, Attorney, who oratorically described the noble work of Mr. Morgenthau.</p>
   <p>Following Mr. Pantelis, Mr. Kyriacopoulos eulogized the philanthropic work of Mr. Morgenthau, adding that the Jewish race had been assisted by the Greeks many times and he mentioned the historical event when Alexander the Great redeemed 95,000 Jews, who were held as slaves by the Egyptians, paying in cash for their liberation. Mr. Tselos, representing the Greek Students' Society, Plato, was the third speaker. Then came Dr. N. Salopoulos, who represented the united Greek press of Chicago. Miss Evagelia Metou, followed, representing the societies of young Greek ladies.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0301.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Attorney Andrew Vlahos, representing the Greek communities, and the Greek schools of Chicago followed. Mr. S. Zaph, former President of the County of the Greek Professional Men spoke; also Mr. Spanon, who represented Ahepa.</p>
   <p>After the Greek orators, Mr. Frank Loesch, President of the Near East Relief branch in Chicago, in a brief and effective speech, depicted the vitality of the Greek race.</p>
   <p>Mr. Morgenthau, who was the next speaker, in an extended speech, brought before the eyes of the audience, in detail, a picture of his noble work. The last speaker of the occasion was Mr. Spiro Kotakis, who, by a brilliant oration in Greek, conveyed to the distinguished guest of honor, gratitude of the Greeks for his humanitarian aid.</p>
   <p>The six year old daughter of Mr. John Karagianis recited a beautiful peom on the occasion.</p>
   <p>(Full)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
