<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-05-17">May 17, 1924</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Greek-American Assembly to Celebrate the Declaration of Republic in Greece. to the Greek People in Chicago and the Suburbs.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-05-17">May 17, 1924</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">GREEK-AMERICAN ASSEMBLY TO CELEBRATE THE DECLARATION OF REPUBLIC IN GREECE. TO THE GREEK PEOPLE IN CHICAGO AND THE SUBURBS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A splendid event took place today in the country where we first saw light.</p>
   <p>There, today, the resurrection of Greek Democracy, from the darkness of past centuries, took place; there, today, the political liberty of the citizen is declared and assured in full; there, today, the will of the people has materialized and triumphed; there today, independent thought is practiced by the Greek people.</p>
   <p>The champions of political liberty, in Greece, overthrew the political edifice of the Dynasty, laying on March 25th,1923 the corner stone of Greek Democracy, through a pan-Hellenic plebiscite.</p>
   <p>Greece, today, entered the ranks of the Democratic Nations, as member of the vanguard that gaurds the progress of civilization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0421.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The news of the event was greeted with joy by Hellenism all over the world and the people of many nations turned an admiring eye upon the land of Pericles.</p>
   <p>But the Greek people in America, who have tasted and know Democracy, by living, breathing, and prospering in the domain of Democracy i. e. The United States of America, have double reason to be jubilant and proud. Our Mother-Greece is in line with America the Great, our adopted country.</p>
   <p>The Greek people of Chicago and the suburbs are informed and invited to meet together in mass to demonstrate and express our feelings of joy and pride in celebration of the event. This general convocation will take place on May 25th, 2 P. M. at the Garrick Theater.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0422.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During the celebration distinguished Americans will participate, who feel proud of the regeneration of Democracy in Greece. Consuls of friendly nations are invited and have accepted our invitations to attend. The Greek clergy of Chicago, the councils of all Greek communities and Greek organizations will be there.</p>
   <p>An eminent American will preside at this coming celebration. His name and the names of the orators will shortly be announced in the program.</p>
   <p>The Executive Committee</p>
   <p>of Thirty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
