<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-02-14">Feb. 14, 1931</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Electra</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-02-14">Feb. 14, 1931</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">ELECTRA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, the Sophoclean tragedy, Electra, was presented to the throngs of Greeks and others at the Studebaker Theatre, by Madame Marika Kotopouli, one of the greatest actresses who has graced the boards of a local theatre in recent years.</p>
   <p>So great was the crowd, that many not finding seats were compelled to leave.</p>
   <p>Sophocles, Electra, the immortal Greek Tragedy in its purity was not presented, last Sunday, but a mutilated German-made Electra. In the version of "Electra, employed by Madam Kotopouli as a vehicle, little remained of that which is Greek, in the essential meaning of the term. Gone are the repose, the ancient and noble lines, the sustained movement under the level and unfaultering hand of fate towards an appointed end, that distinguished the drama of the classic era.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0043.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In its place is to be found a reverted modernity, a text absurdly modernity, a text absurdly psychologized, the febril sentimentality of an age that prides itself upon sophistication. The hands laid by Hugo Von Hofmannsthal upon the Electra of Sophodes a vandals' hands.</p>
   <p>To the interpretation of the Electra of her choice, Madame Kotopouli brought historic powers that are, to say the least, extraordinary. Viewed in relation to the text employed, her reading was superb, but neither text nor impersonation was wholly in harmony with the spirit of the original drama.</p>
   <p>Electra's was a hatred that ate into her soul and found, in the Sophoclian text, relatively measured expression. Von Hofmannsthal, quite obviously, mistook his heroine for one of the Eumenides, and it is as such - as a flaming fury that Madame played her.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0044.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Weighted with implications of sorrow, supreme and unappeasable, the impersonation was poignant in the extreme.</p>
   <p>Further analysis serves no special purpose. The public will better profit from the writers' impressions, if it is said that the audience, Greek and barbarian, alike sat spellbound during the several hours of the drama held by the power of a supreme impersonation. The performance, scheduled to take place, in two weeks at the Chicago Opera House, is anticpated with pleasure by the general public. The fact that the lines are spoken in Greek is of negligible importance.</p>
   <p>If Madame Kotopouli was not suffereing from "Xendmania", and had presented the Sophoclean, "Electra", in its purity in classics Greek, undoubtly it would have been a greater success, as well as, an honor to herself since she possesses wonderful dramatic talent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
