<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Biography of A. George N. Spannon, Attorney-At-Law</title> by Miss L. Murphy, Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1937-09-03">Sep. 3, 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0959</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0959.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>BIOGRAPHY OF A. GEORGE N. SPANNON, ATTORNEY-AT-LAW</title> By Miss L. Murphy, Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1937-09-03">Sep. 3, 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. EARLY HISTORY</p>
   <p>Mr. Spannon is a young man of Greek parentage, who was brought up and received his early grammar and high school education in the cities of Lynn, Gleuseter, Holyoke, Springfield, and Boston, Mass. Mr. Spannon is married to Mary Marie Maneaty, a graduate of Northwestern University, and lives with his wife at 7312 Ridge Boulevard, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>2. COLLEGIATE AND PROFESSIONAL EDUCATION</p>
   <p>Just prior to the World's War, he attended the University of Boston for, approximately, one and one-half years. Following his discharge from military service, entered Valparaiso University, Valparaiso, Indiana, attending said institution for two terms. Thereafter he entered the University of Chicago, the College of Liberal Arts, and graduated therefrom in 1923 with a degree of Bachelor of Philosophy (Ph. B.), having majored in the field of political science and economics. Thereafter he enrolled in the University of Chicago Law School, and graduated therefrom in 1926 with a degree of Doctor of Jurisprudence (J. D.).</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0960.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>3. SCHOLASTIC ATTAINMENT</p>
   <p>While attending the University of Chicago, College of Liberal Arts, he was awarded the first prize, after a competitive examination, on the subject of Civil Government, held under the auspices of the Department of Political Science.</p>
   <p>4. PROFESSIONAL CAREER</p>
   <p>Mr. Spannon is a member of the Bar of the State of Michigan, admitted in September, 1925, and a member of the Bar of the State of Illinois, admitted in October, 1926. Since his admission to the Bar of the State of Illinois, he engaged in the general practice of law, until 1929, when he entered into a partnership with Stanley C. Armstrong, a former Assistant Attorney General for the State of Illinois and a former Assistant Corporation Counsel for the City of Chicago, for the general practice of law, under the firm name of Armstrong &amp; Spannon, and is now a member of said law firm, with offices at 201 N. Wells St., Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0961.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>5. WAR SERVICE</p>
   <p>Following the entry of the United States into the World's War, Mr. Spannon was appointed by the Secretary of War, as Special War Agent, attached to the Department of Intelligence, War College Division of the General Staff, and was honorably discharged from the military service following the Armistice.</p>
   <p>6. PUBLIC SERVICE</p>
   <p>Served, by appointment, the City of Chicago, as Assistant City Attorney, for a period of one year, and as Assistant Corporation Counsel, for three and one-half years.</p>
   <p>7. MEMBERSHIP IN PROFESSIONAL, WAR SERVICE, SOCIAL, FRATERNAL AND POLITICAL ORGANIZATIONS</p>
   <p>A. Professional: Member of the Chicago Bar Association, the American Bar Association, and the Illinois Bar Association; also, a member of the University of Chicago Alumni Club and the University of Chicago Law School Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0962.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>B. War Service: Formerly a member of Hellenic Post and now a member of Joyce Kilmer Post, No. 780, Department of Illinois, of the American Legion, having served Hellenic Post as Junior Vice-Commander and Judge Advocate, and now Junior Vice-Commander and Chairman of Committee on Public Relations of Joyce Kilmer Post No. 780.</p>
   <p>C. Social: Member of the Hamilton Club of Chicago, Collegiate Club of Chicago, and the Plato Hellenic Collegiate Club of Chicago.</p>
   <p>D. Fraternal: Member of Kappa Iota Pi and Delta Pi Epsilon, college fraternities; member of Hellenic Lodge No. 1084, A. F. &amp; A. M. of Illinois; member of the Ahepa, a national organization, fraternal in character, composed principally of citizens of Hellenic extraction, with chapters in every large city and state of the Union, having served the organization in question, in many official capacities, particularly that of Supreme Governor of the Ninth and Tenth Districts for two terms and as a member of the Supreme Lodge, the supreme governing authority of the organization, for a period of two years.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0963.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>E. Political: Formerly a member of the Sixth Ward Republican Organization, and now a member of the Fiftieth Ward Republican Organization.</p>
   <p>8. GENERAL POLITICAL ACTIVITIES</p>
   <p>A. While residing in the Sixth Ward of the City, and a member of the Sixth Ward Republican Organization, he was instrumental in organizing the South Side Hellenic Republican Club, of which he became Secretary, and later organized the United Hellenic Republican Clubs of Cook County and Illinois, of which he became the Secretary, and served as such for a period of four years. He has been very actively engaged in all Republican political campaigns since 1926, and was a member of the Speakers' Bureau of the Republican National Committee during the presidential campaign in 1928 and during the presidential campaign in 1932, and spoke in a number of cities and states in behalf of the Republican nominees.</p>
   <p>B. In 1932 Mr. Spannon was a candidate, at the Republican Primaries, for the office of Secretary of State, and in 1936, at the Republican Primaries, a candidate for the office of State Representative, from the Sixth Senatorial District.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0964.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>9. GENERAL, SOCIAL AND FRATERNAL ACTIVITIES</p>
   <p>While in college, he helped to organize and was one of the charter members of the Kappa Iota Pi fraternity at Valparaiso University, Valparaiso, Indiana. Following his enrollment in the University of Chicago, he organized and was one of the charter members of the Delta Epsilon Pi, a collegiate fraternity, composed, largely, of students of Hellenic extraction, which new has a number of chapters in colleges and universities of the middlewest and weastern states. Prior to and following his graduation from the University of Chicago, he helped organize and perpetuate the Plato Hellenic Collegiate Club of Chicago, a social organization composed largely of boys and girls of Hellenic extraction, students, as well as graduates, from colleges and universities within Chicago and the State of Illinois.</p>
   <p>In 1926, under the auspices of the Order of Ahepa and the active cooperation of the Near East Relief Committee, he became Chairman of a city-wide committee, for the purpose of conducting certain public functions, teas, dances, etc., in order to raise funds for the benefit of the Asia Minor refugees, whose interest <pb facs="5422062_6_0965.jpg" n="7"/>and well-being were espoused in America, by the Near East Relief Committee. In 1930, when the depression became widespread, and while Mr. Spannon was then Supreme Governor of District No. 10 of the Order of Ahepa, organized a Relief Committee, composed of representative citizens of Hellenic extraction, in cooperation with the United Charities, and other social and relief agencies, for the purpose of raising funds and soliciting food and clothing for those in need, and carried on such services for, approximately, a year thereafter and until relief was taken over by the public authorities.</p>
   <p>Aside from the activities mentioned above, Mr. Spannon became and is new actively engaged in many other social improvement and neighborhood organizations, whose purposes are social, as well as civic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
