<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1927-12-17">December 17, 1927</date><title level="a">The Greek Communities of Chicago.-</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1927-12-17">December 17, 1927</date><title level="a">The Greek Communities of Chicago.-</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is known from ancient times that the Greeks never united, unless an outsider attacked them. Then, all the animosities antipathies, egoism, and differences is political opinion, were forgotten and set aside. They would fall upon the common enemy, fighting in unison and bring home Victory.</p>
   <p>The same political division exists amongst the Greeks of Chicago, and renders them fanatics. The division is not because of the affairs of our State, but because of the two prevalent political factions in Greece, the Venizelist and Antivenzelists. And the trend of such division will eventually become the cause of the division of our Church.</p>
   <p>Oh! Greeks of today, living in the greatest country of the World and having an opportunity to see and immitate that the Republicans and Democrats are not two different nations, but they are, before, during, and after the elections, Americans. They don't fight Americanism, but they only oppose the Republican or Democratic platforms. Oh! Greeks of Chicago, unite yourselves in one national body, thus not only Greece will be benefited by our united action, but also all of us right here, and we will be able to go forward in political, commercial, educational and religious endeavors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
