<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-12-13">Dec. 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Grand Reception and Dance for Miss Europe</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0070.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1930-12-13">Dec. 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">GRAND RECEPTION AND DANCE FOR MISS EUROPE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- Last Sunday, Miss Alice Diplarakou, who recently was crowned "Miss Europe," arrived in Chicago and was received by hundreds of Greeks of both sexes who were waiting at the station, loaded with enough flowers to beautify a small town.</p>
   <p>The distinguished beauty, under the auspices of the Greek Ladies' society, St. Andrew, was directed to the Hotel Stevens. Greeks and more Greeks from Chicago and the suburbs, visited the Grecian beauty and paid due respects, as is their custom, to the descendant of Aphrodite, who possesses not only beauty, but charm, grace and intelligence as well.</p>
   <p>Six thousand Greeks, mostly members of the fair sex, crowded the Aragon Ball Room, where a dance was giving in honor of the graceful queen. Hundreds of Grecian girls, with loads of chrysantheums and roses of the best variety, formed two lines right and left, and for an hour waited for the arrival of Miss Diplarakou. When she came, pandemonium broke out. Really it was an apotheosis.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0071.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Grecian girls, attired in garments, which revealed rather than concealed the form of their body, and with marbel-white arms hugging the huge chrysantheums and roses, stood like perfect statues to receive the queen.</p>
   <p>At the head of the two lines, two girls impersonating Columbia and Greece, and holding the flags of the two countries, stood in military order to salute the coming beauty.</p>
   <p>The tantalizing echoes of the music and the anxiety of the crowd to honor the scion of Sparta transformed the atmosphere of the ballroom into a magical panorama. And when Miss Alice at last reached the stage, which was not visible because of so many flowers that were on it, and began to address the people, Homer, only, would have been able to describe the sentimental expressions of the Chicago Greeks. The Grecian beauty, in eloquent and pure Greek, thanked the Greeks of Chicago for the honor given to her, and expressed her pleasure that our beautiful Greece is publicized.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0072.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The music began again and spread its melodious and romantic echoes to the dancing pairs who in every turn watched the honor guest, who sat on the stage like a strong magnet, and scattered flowers to the dancing crowd.</p>
   <p>The crowd, other than the Greeks, who came to see how the Greeks pay tribute to beauty, agreed with the poets and writers of the past, that Greeks, really know how to entertain that which is pleasant to the eye.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
