<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-12-08">Dec. 8, 1928</date><title level="a">The Need of Representation in the Greek Parliament</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0203</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0203.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-12-08">Dec. 8, 1928</date><title level="a">THE NEED OF REPRESENTATION IN THE GREEK PARLIAMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- We have commented on the question of representation of Greek communities, abroad, in the Greek Senate. We have dealt with the same question on other occasions and we are the first ones who have projected this idea. We also held lectures in regards to the proposition. We have treated the subject not from an idealistic point of view, as much as from a realistic.</p>
   <p>We think that it is time, now, to dwell again on the matter of sending representatives from America to the Greek Parliament in Greece, while the question is discussed there. We have considered the fact, that those in Greece have thought of the Greeks abroad, seriously. They have considered it just and necessary that we in America have a voice in the National representation. Thus far, unfortunately, the Greek people abroad, although having been recognized as a great economic factor, in Greece, were not thought of as being entitled to have an opinion upon Greek matters.</p>
   <p>The shaping of things political proved that the Greek people abroad are not only watching with close interest politics in Greece, but, being removed <pb facs="5422062_6_0204.jpg" n="2"/>far from the narrow partisanship, can judge general matters with more calmness.</p>
   <p>More important still, finding themselves in far wider commercial and industrial fields, they know more than those in Greece, where conditions do not allow the people to learn the modern methods and systems used in various branches of commerce and industry. These facts are indisputable and for these and many other reasons we think that the opinion of a representative from abroad, in the Greek Parliament, can be very beneficial to Greece. But the need of the representation of the Greek communities abroad, in the Greek Parliament, is not to be considered in the light, alone. This representation aims primarily at serving the interests of the Greek communities whose bonds with Greece are very strong and often need Governmental care.</p>
   <p>Those in Greece cannot possibly know the needs of Hellenism abroad, unless they hear and learn of them from the representatives of Greek communities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
