<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-07-06">July 6, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">What Became of the Money Collected at the Dance Given for the Benefit of the National Navy of Greece? Has Been the Cry of the Star for the Last Three Months</title><title level="a" type="sub">At Last the Answer Comes - Prognostications of the Star Come True - Consecrated Funds Wasted (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0897</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0897.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-07-06">July 6, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT BECAME OF THE MONEY COLLECTED AT THE DANCE GIVEN FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE NATIONAL NAVY OF GREECE? HAS BEEN THE CRY OF THE STAR FOR THE LAST THREE MONTHS</title><title level="a" type="sub">At Last the Answer Comes - Prognostications of the Star Come True - Consecrated Funds Wasted (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under no consideration will the Star deviate from its course. When the affairs of the community are in jeopardy, and when the good name of the Greeks and the interests of Hellenism are attacked by scoundresl, whether they be fellow-Greeks or others, whether friends or enemies of the Star, this newspaper will not keep things under cover in order to save the face of the wrong-doers. Greeks and others, friends and enemies alike will be exposed for the benefit of all. We respect neither Greeks nor friends when their conduct is improper.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0898.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For the last three months the Star, in issue after issue, has requested a public accounting of the proceeds of the dance given for the benefit of the Greek Navy funds. We were called braying jackasses by those who were dilatory in performing their manly duty.</p>
   <p>We do not wish to imply now nor did we wish to imply three months ago, that the collected money was pocketed; far from it. But we do wish, as journalists faithful to our principles, to inform the public where its money went. The money collected at the dance was raised for a specific purpose which affects all Greeks everywhere, not only the Greeks of Chicago. It was raised for the sole purpose of augmenting the funds of the National Navy of Greece. Therefore the three months' cry of the Star has been motivated by our duty to the Hellenic race and not by any personal desire to stain the character of the committee in charge.</p>
   <p>At last, with the help of Jehovah, the committee has made a public accounting of the people's money: $1,595 net profit, $1,663.65 expenses! That is to say, $1,663.65 was expended in order to clear $1,595. In other words, the total proceeds were $3,258.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0899.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Nobody disputes the honesty and the integrity of the honorably committee in charge of the affair, and the Star does not entertain the slightest thought of any irregularities, but this is where the shoe pinches. From a business standpoint the affair was not successful or well managed. The extravagance and the waste were excessive. From the patriotic standpoint the affair was a disaster. It does not require a dance to arouse enthusiasm in Greeks so that they will contribute money for the needs of Mother Greece. $1,663.65 of this consecrated money was squandered either through ignorance or through the desire of those in charge to acquire publicity and recognition as patriotic leaders. In either case the consequence of their folly reflects upon all of us. The dance was not necessary at all to raise money for the Navy. Time and time again it has been proved that the Greek is a real patriot. He needs no coercion or inducement to go to the limit in his patriotic duty. Why then the dance? Why the waste of this consecrated money? Dances and other entertainments are given as inducements when public sentiment is lukewarm. All that was necessary in order to raise money for the Navy was to rent a hall for twenty-five or fifty dollars and obtain free advertising in the Greek press.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0900.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On previous occasions four, five, and six thousand dollars have been contributed in the twinkling of an eye out of the love and generosity of the Greek soul for Mother Greece.</p>
   <p>Before the dance was given the Star brought out in vivid colors the unpractical aspect of the whole affair and patriotically suggested the procedure which has always been fruitful, - that is, the Masonic Temple program. Our suggestions and pleas for the success of the affair fell upon deaf ears. And for the outcry which we have raised for the last three months in demanding an accounting we have malignantly been called braying jackasses. But to err is human; let us forget our differences and profit by our mistakes. Let us not in the future follow the same unpractical, unprofitable and improper procedure.</p>
   <p>We hope that our achievements in the future will be such as to compensate for our errors in the past.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
