<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-03-25">March 25, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Greece the Eternal.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0141</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0141.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-03-25">March 25, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">GREECE THE ETERNAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1.- Hellas! A land in which I saw the first light and the light of ideals towards you, from the land of wealth and things gigantic, all Greeks, in blood and spirit, turn their minds, today, in order to glorify you, to praise and worship your grandeur.</p>
   <p>We turn towards you, today, when, on your soil of freedom, your children, and our brothers who are there, begin the Centennial celebration of Greek independence. We do this in order to seek and invigorate our Greek ideals from the inexhaustible spiritual fountain.</p>
   <p>Hellas! My eternal country! You, oh, eternal Hellas, possess the secret of a perpetual spiritual spring, because you alone possess the secret of real freedom. You alone, Hellas, possess the secret of eternity through your worship to the only Spirit worthwhile and venerated on the part of free men and women.</p>
   <p>When, Hellas, my country, the hordes of the enemy, thanks to the mistakes of your children, (who for a moment forgot the worship of the Spirit, <pb facs="5422062_6_0142.jpg" n="2"/>thought of the flesh and feared death), soiled your memory of your traditions and you were running, bleeding and tearful from the fields of Greek, Asia Minor, all foreigners who love you for the beauty of your Spirit, were horrified, for a moment, over the calamity. They had breathlessly expected, with untold sorrow, Hellas, my country, that, that storm would have swept you to anarchy and destruction.</p>
   <p>However, those whose veins are filled with your blood,-Oh, Mother of gods, did not lose faith, and never thought, for a moment, that the fear of the Aliens and hopes of your enemies could be realized. Because we know that Greece, which gave the spirit to the world, could not be carried away by a material force in an epoch such as the present one.</p>
   <p>Because it is from you, Hellas, my country, from which all men of thought draw today, as in the past, their inspiration. And because now, when you have accomplished the liberation of your children, all men of thought follow with pleasant approval, the peaceful accomplishments of your distinguished son that glorifies the world's history of statesmen. With firm confidence they expect him to once again lead the spiritual way and guide materialistic humanity to the level which it had been led twice in the past.</p>
   <p>E. Kont.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
