<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-14">Sept. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Lederer's Speech at the Funeral of Dr. Basil Lambrakis</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Published in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0977</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0977.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-14">Sept. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">DR. LEDERER'S SPEECH AT THE FUNERAL OF DR. BASIL LAMBRAKIS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Published in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is most difficult for men in a scientific world of endeavor--devoted to the conservation of human life and the relief of suffering multitudes--to envisage death as a reward for such effort. But, the spiritually-minded physician, whose every effort in the preparation for his life's work means sacrifice, seeks no great earthly reward. He is merely pursuing an ideal. A physician, truly, is that messenger designated to relieve the afflicted. In Doctor Basil Lambrakis we had the true physician; a man not only qualified in his profession, but a man who well represented the cultural attributes and refinements of his people.</p>
   <p>After his arrival in this country, he immediately sought friends in circles which were befitting those ideals which had been inculcated in him during his long years of study in European universities. We welcomed him to the University of Illinois College of Medicine, where he gave freely of his time in teaching <pb facs="5422062_6_0978.jpg" n="2"/>and in caring for the unfortunate sick. His genial personality, his interest in his work, and the finesse of his manner were contagious to those who were fortunate enough to come into contact with him.</p>
   <p>We, his colleagues, feel that we have lost in Basil a representative worthy of the title "physician," which has been handed down through the ages--a true Hippocrates, whose philosophy he carried out in a modern way. Dr. Lambrakis was a rider in the front ranks of his profession whose ride was brought to a standstill. He was swept out of the saddle prematurely, before he reached his goal. There was not even time to tell him that the work was well done. We can only gather here to hear the kind voices of his friends and to say: "His work is done." Rest was never intended for that rider so constantly in the saddle; because while we live, we work, for to live is to function. And what more is there in living but to work and give service?</p>
   <p>Today, we of the University of Illinois, pay homage to our dear departed colleague, Basil Lambrakis, who is perhaps too far, but strangely near to us in <pb facs="5422062_6_0979.jpg" n="3"/>spirit, urging us ever to carry on. To this end we pledge ourselves, thus building a monument more enduring than bronze.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
