<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-04-12">April 12, 1924</date><title level="a">The Reign of Lucifers in Greece</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-04-12">April 12, 1924</date><title level="a">THE REIGN OF LUCIFERS IN GREECE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek community in Chicago and elsewhere is divided in two warring camps. Royalists and anti-Royalist, with the latter predominating in numbers. The activities of both camps, for preponderance, were the actual cause of the division of the Greek Orthodox Church in the United States. Both camps assumed that they were right, that is according to their convictions. The Greek Press in the United States was accordingly, divided pro and con. Many articles were blazoned for and against the Royal family of Greece. Not only laymen were bitterly against the opposite camps, but also clergymen and professionals. And why not?</p>
   <p>In the past as well as now, differences of opinion existed in every stage of society.. Medical men, in the past and now, differed in their opinion and signed, with their action, the deportation papers of thousands of people to the other world. Reputable scientists in the past and now were and are so divided. Theists and atheists, Christians of many denominations and anti-Christians, are not immune to such a division of ideas actions and functions that so-called differences of <pb facs="5422062_6_0425.jpg" n="2"/>opinion is beneficial to the development of mind, if it does not become fanaticized. The truth and reality of anything will be known not by assertions but by systematic explorations; oppositions and contra-oppositions to the truth will reveal the truth.</p>
   <p>This newspaper for many years, trumpeted for the case of the Greek people here, the advantages and the myriad of disadvantages of having kings in Greece.</p>
   <p>Who and what are the Greek kings? What does history tell us about kings in other parts of the world? We brought out the naked truth of the doings of the Greek Royal Family and asked our readers to be guided accordingly. The newspaper, Saloniki, consequently was not permitted to reach royally dominated Greece. But the Greeks of America, in which we were most interested, read our astonishing articles and of course many, many Royalists changed camps. Nevertheless, many of them still cling to their fixed idea of Royalty (as other people in other lands today still cling) and were not ready to give ground, which they obstinately held; logic and truth were ignored. Then, naturally, fanaticism stepped in and the results, in this case or any other case in this country or any other country, are very well known to us all.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0426.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A week ago last Sunday thousands of Chicago Greeks celebrated the declaration of Democracy in Greece. Greece is liberated from the Royal Lucifers, and all the Greeks in Chicago and elsewhere will do well, for their interest and welfare, to be united in one camp and under one roof.</p>
   <p>The following matter of fact revelations will remove the slightest doubt in the minds of those brother Greeks who might still maintain the usefulness of Royalty.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow, Sunday, the Greek people are called to conform and ratify, through public vote, the declaration of the Democratic form of government in Greece, and the abolition of the murderous and traitorous dynasty of Glyxenburg, which for sixty years brought so many national misfortunes and catastrophies upon Mother Greece, that even a legion of Lucifers would have been unable to better the doings of these Royal monsters.</p>
   <p>However, during the reigning period of these Lucifers, there were many writers who, for thirty pieces of silver from the Royal stables, falsified history, and in a most unusual, shameless manner praised and extolled George the First, founder of the Greek Dynasty, and his descendants. Royal stable poets, also, in rhymes <pb facs="5422062_6_0427.jpg" n="4"/>eulogized the patriotism and ingenuity of those monsters.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the Helenic people do not know even one per cent of the anti-nationalistic activities of this blood-dripping dynasty, the Royal Stable politicians and their cohorts, in falsifying events and data, have acclaimed George the First as constitutional king, and his doings as fatherly. Also his son, Constantine, heir presumptive to the throne, as generalissimo laureate.</p>
   <p>The press in Greece never dared to expose the facts of the Royal stables, but Saloniki, being published in the land of the free, for many years revealed the intrigues, conspiracies, diabolical schemes, secret treaties, assassinating cabals and other satanic doings of the Royal family of Greece which were taking place in the Royal stables.</p>
   <p>The Historical article of Mr. George Arvanitis titled "The Dynasty of Glyxenburg against Servia which we have published in the past and from which we now reprint excerpts, reveals the astonishing facts of the Kings of Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0428.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>On October 19th, 1863, there arrived in Greece the Danish Prince, Christian Wilhelm, as King of the Hellenes under the name of George the First, becoming the founder of the Glyxenberg Dynasty in Greece. He brought with him two secret treaties with England against Greece. His first task was to keep the war powers of Greece in an atrophied condition, so that she would not embarrass Turkey. His second, to demolish the forts and fortifications of the island of Corfu. For this he was receiving 1,000 £ Sterling per month.</p>
   <p>These obligations of the Greek Crown to Great Britain were not known to the National Assembly or to the Greek people. They were revealed in the House of Commons in England when the 1,000 pounds and the secret treaty with the newly crowned King of Greece became debatable and the Commons wanted to know more about it.</p>
   <p>Mr. Smollet, an M. P. said, "Under such circumstances, my dear friend and colleague, Mr. Gavey (great Philoturk) would have been the proper king for Greece." Gladstone admitted, in the House of Commons, that the Danish Prince knew and acknowledged these obligations before leaving Copenhagen.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0429.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>George the First succeeded in keeping the war power of Greece in an atrophied condition by the following methods.</p>
   <p>1st. By holding the portfolios of the Ministry of War and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. The polemic office of the palace, in peace time was organizing the corruption of the army officers, through Royal favors. In war time it destroyed their effectiveness by putting them under the immediate control of his sons and lieutenants, and giving them contrary orders than the ones authorized by the respective ministers.</p>
   <p>2nd. By keeping the nation unprepared, by the ruse of national economy, so that in case of a popular clamor for war against Turkey everything would have to be done in a desperate hurry, thus preparing an inevitable defeat of the heroic fighters of Greece, who many times were demoted and thrown in prison for disobeying Royal orders, when they could clearly see, that, victory was snatched away from them by obeying the Royal orders given by the sons of the King, who controlled the army.</p>
   <p>3rd. Morally disarming the nation with Royal propaganda, George the First, King of the Hellenes, preached to his people that Thessalonica rightfully <pb facs="5422062_6_0430.jpg" n="7"/>belonging to Austria, and Olga, his Queen, advocated that Constantinople belonged not to Greece, but to Russia.</p>
   <p>4th. The systematic opposition of George I against Servian and Greek alliance. George the First, after the year of 1897, entered into a secret treaty with Austria, signed by George Theotokis, Royal Prime Minister, by which the King of Greece guaranteed Greece's inertia and inactivity, if and when Austria invaded Thessalonica, and Austria guaranteed its dynasty against any uprising from within Greece. This treaty, as we will see later, was modified in 1899, to protect the King from dangers arising from without.</p>
   <p>This is revealed by a document which was published as a book in Vienna in 1913, telling all about the "assassination of George the First", and the circulation of which was prohibited both in Austria and Greece.</p>
   <p>Saloniki, in 1917, published the contents of this treaty, but the newspaper's circulation in Greece was prohibited by Royal decree.</p>
   <p>Just because this secret treaty still remains unknown to the people in Greece, we are obliged to reprint it, believing it to be an imperative necessity for the Greek <pb facs="5422062_6_0431.jpg" n="8"/>people to know the truth, by which true unity will be restored.</p>
   <p>The modification of the treaty, to include further protection for the Greek King, was signed, October 13, 1899, by Franz Joseph....and George the First, and countersigned by the then Foreign Minister of Greece, Mr. Athanasius Romanos.</p>
   <p>Articles 1, 6, 7, 8 and 10 should be read twice. By doing so, any doubt still clinging to the minds of the Royalists or to the uninformed populace, will be eliminated and thus peace and unity will again reign among the Greek people.</p>
   <p>N. Salopoulos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
