<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-06-19">June 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Academic Philosophy, -Morality.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0329</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0329.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-06-19">June 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">ACADEMIC PHILOSOPHY, -MORALITY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Owing to the perpetual babbling of some of our Greek moralists, it is the imperative duty, of this publication, to dig into the archives of academic philosophy, and unearth the truth of the disputed theme. Morality, is not divine, but a philosophical creation, for the improvement of society, hence anything that is good was and is attributed to having a divine origin.</p>
   <p>Our own ancient predecessors, when their liberty was lost, and they had no voice in the administration of the affairs of the State, became estranged separated. Those who were inclined towards to morality, endeavored to better themselves; those inclined towards the libidinous followed the other road. So, the first followed the academic dogma the others became Epicurians. And the Epicurians predominated. It is not surprising, therefore, that the debased Conqueror Demetrios was proclaimed a God. Since, the fall of the ancient religion, and the new one not yet arrived the academic philosophy has offered important services to the human race.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0330.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Where philosophy left off, and father of all, but under no consideration can we regard him as of human form." Just because the Academy was based upon such principles and the moral foundations were unshaken, the followers of that institution were personages of distinguished character and mind. Nevertheless, we cannot say that the Academy conceived all the dogmas, for some of them were conceived by the ancients. You find everywhere the relation of the academic to cynic philosophy. Academic philosophy sprang from the cyric philosophy. Therefore it may truthfully be said that the Academy broke up cynicism.</p>
   <p>The dogmas of the Academy not only agreed with the cynic philosophy, but with that of Plato and Aristotle. At the beginning it was the physical dogma of Philosophy, Socrates advocated the moral dogma, and Plato, the dialectical, or logic.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0331.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Zenon was the first to introduce, scientifically, the three branches of philosophy, although they were in existence previous to him.</p>
   <p>The Academy and its members are still distinguished for their creative philosophical system; Morality was advocated and taught as the only virtue. The various manifestations of pathos, were not elements of life, but diseases of the soul. The wise one, it was said, was a free person, noble, and possessing an abundance of life. Only the governing soul was willing to compete, and be ready to make sacrifices. By this teaching an effort was made to bring to earth the high ideal of Plato's Republic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
