<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1913-10-04">Oct. 4, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">To the Call of Mother-Greece</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0769</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0769.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1913-10-04">Oct. 4, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE CALL OF MOTHER-GREECE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2 -- Twice a week hundreds of Chicago Greeks leave their families and their business and depart for Greece to fight her battles for victory.</p>
   <p>The organized committees and the Greek ladies' societies are always on hand to see our boys to the station and bid them farewell. Mothers, wives, sisters, sweethearts, and sympathizers are there to kiss their loved ones good-bye and wish them every good thing in the world.</p>
   <p>The picture at the station is very pathetic. Robust young Greeks, dressed in smart uniforms, holding their proud heads high, presenting an air of importance and superiority, exchange greetings with relatives and friends. Mothers holding handerchiefs wet with tears, on their faces a mingled expression of pride, joy, and grief, kiss their sons good-bye and urge them to write.</p>
   <p>Wives and sweethearts embrace their loved ones, oblivious of what is going <pb facs="5422062_6_0770.jpg" n="2"/>on around them. Others, who have no families here, are cheered and hugged by ladies who are there as sympathizers and friends.</p>
   <p>It all makes a magnificent picture, and the word "Victory" is written on every face. When the last call of "all aboard" is uttered, pandemonium breaks loose, with cheers, cries, good-byes, "We'll wait for you," and "Tell Mother-Greece we are with her, for ever and ever," "Hurrah for Greece! Hurrah for America! Hurrah!"</p>
   <p>The Chicago boys are gone, responding to the call of Mother-Greece, and those of us who stay behind are in duty bound to see that they are properly taken care of. Good-bye, brother-Greeks! The Chicago Greek community is body and soul behind you. Good-bye!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
