<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Legion of Unredeemed Greeks</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE LEGION OF UNREDEEMED GREEKS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek people of Chicago are happy and honored to receive the representatives of the unredeemed Greek populations in Macedonia, Thrace, and Asia Minor.</p>
   <p>They have come here for the purpose of arousing the interest of the Greek people of America and Chicago for our struggling homeland which is also in the throes of war. They have come to solicit our community's moral and material support.</p>
   <p>Messrs. N. Kyriakides and Chris. Basilakakis are the official representatives of the Central National Committee at Athens for the alleviation of the suffering and the solution of the problems of the unredeemed Greeks who are trying to win their self-determination within the various countries in which they have been living for hundreds of years.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0637.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Greek people of Chicago, of the United States, of free and unredeemed Greece, are following the work of the Greek committee and the Legion of Unredeemed Greeks with great and absorbing interest.</p>
   <p>Saloniki especially, representing the genuine patriotic sentiment of the Greek colony of Chicago, greets the arrival of our two distinguished Greek emissaries and visitors with a warm heart.</p>
   <p>We are confident that these two gentlemen and their collaborators will do their utmost to free the unfortunate Greek population from the Turkish and Bulgarian yoke. They are men of tested ability, forceful leaders, and inspired patriots.</p>
   <p>We are informed that they have called together the representatives of the Greek organizations composed of those who hail from Asia Minor, Thrace, and Epirus, the unredeemed and subject Greek territories. Those Greeks of <pb facs="5422062_6_0638.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago who came from these territories are ably and strongly represented in this international conference. The delegates and representatives are preparing to send a memorandum to the President of the United States and to Congress, in which they will claim for the unredeemed Greeks the rights of self-determination, self-rule, and absolute independence from foreign and oppressive domination. We take the liberty to suggest the organization of a well-trained and well-equipped National Greek-American Legion of Unredeemed Greeks, composed of volunteers. Such an organization will give more weight to the memorandums and appeals that are voted upon and issued from time to time.</p>
   <p>In these days of warring nations, violent upheavals, and world disorder and dislocations, liberty is won only by deeds and action; memorandums, frantic appeals, and protests have been superceded by the force of arms.</p>
   <p>We are far from our homeland, but we have never stopped loving it; we have <pb facs="5422062_6_0639.jpg" n="4"/>never ceased to think of it but with yearning and nostalgia. We have shared in its prosperity and now we must share in its tragedies and difficulties.</p>
   <p>While the Greek armies, supported by volunteer corps of men from Asia Minor, Thrace, and Epirus, are fighting desperately and valiantly on the battlefields of Macedonia to avenge the massacres, persecutions, and the oppression of five long and dreadful centuries--sufferings which have been lately, systematically and deliberately inflicted by the savage hordes of Turks and Bulgarians with the connivance of the Germans--while our cruelly butchered parents, children, brothers, and sisters have not found a grave as yet, but are the prey of carnivorous beasts on the fields and in the streets, must we, the unredeemed Greeks, remain passive and unmoved spectators of this horrible tragedy?</p>
   <p>If, when Mr. Kyriakides submits his memorandum to the President of the United <pb facs="5422062_6_0640.jpg" n="5"/>States, he could also submit a list of volunteers from the various Greek organizations in Chicago and in America as a whole, we have not the slightest doubt that the President would gladly give his support in the organizing, training, and equipping of a Greek division of troops to be sent to the battlefields of Macedonia. We know that there are many thousands among our men who are eager to serve Greece in its titanic struggle.</p>
   <p>The Polish people in the United States have organized a Polish Legion, trained and equipped by the United States Army, and sent to France to fight on the battlefields side by side with the United States and Allied armies. The United States Government and the Allies have officially recognized this excellent military legion. This shows how the Polish people are acting to liberate their brothers and free their war-ridden country.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovakians also have their own army in France despite the fact that <pb facs="5422062_6_0641.jpg" n="6"/>they have no country and no great military means of their own. They are fighting both Lenin, the Russians, and the Germans. As a consequence, the Allies have officially recognized the re-establishment of the Czech nation, consisting of Bohemia and Moravia, and in addition, they have promised the reconstruction of Serbia.</p>
   <p>And now we, the Greeks in America, can profit by the examples set by others. It is our duty to assist our unredeemed brothers by force of arms, with our blood as well as with our money.</p>
   <p>We, too, are fighting the battle of our life. We are fighting for our existence as a nation. We are confident that humanity, justice, and civilization will prevail. So, let us persevere, let us sacrifice our all for what we hold most dear.</p>
   <p>Already the Greek armies are waging a victorious war in Macedonia. Our hearts <pb facs="5422062_6_0642.jpg" n="7"/>and souls are deeply moved by the faith, valor, and courage of our armies in the homeland.</p>
   <p>Greeks everywhere! Enlist in volunteer corps and form a legion which shall do its part in offering freedom and independence to our unredeemed Greek brothers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
