<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1916-04-12">Apr. 12, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Greeks from Abroad Approve of Loxias's Attitude</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0740</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0740.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1916-04-12">Apr. 12, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">GREEKS FROM ABROAD APPROVE OF LOXIAS'S ATTITUDE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.-- Loxias's articles regarding the struggle that is going on in Greece between King Constantine and the Greek nation are read and approved of in many parts of the world. They are headed "Constantine vs. Greece."</p>
   <p>Innumerable letters of congratulation are received at our office from fellow -Greeks in Egypt, South Africa, Kamerun, Australia, Madagascar, Manchuria, and many Balkan capitals.</p>
   <p>Chicago Loxias does not serve the interests of the so-called Greek crown but the interests of our beloved Greece and of Hellenism the world over. Kings and queens may come and go, but Greece must remain at all costs. Our articles have shown very clearly that King Constantine wants Greece to commit suicide, that is, to go to the assistance of his brother-in-law, his beloved Kaiser.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Journal last week in a great editorial analyzed the whole situation and unfolded the intrigues of the Greek King,and item by item its article <pb facs="5422062_6_0741.jpg" n="2"/>coincides with what Loxias wrote three months ago. If you are in favor of Greece and of Hellenism, mail Loxias to your friends and relatives who are outside the dominion of King Constantine. Oh, brother-Greeks the world over, stop and think a minute! Which is holier to you-the foreign King or your native Greece? The answer is one and only one: Greece and Greece alone.</p>
   <p>Below I reprint what the Chicago Journal said yesterday.</p>
   <p>"UNCLUCKY HELLAS</p>
   <p>"All Greece appears to be furious over the invasion of Greek territory by the Bulgars, who are fighting with Germany, but up to the date of writing Constantine refuses to order the invaders driven out. Crowds are parading the streets of Athens denouncing the royal government and crying aloud for war against the invaders of Greek territory.From every part of the <pb facs="5422062_6_0742.jpg" n="3"/>country come disquieting rumors. The Venizelist papers print the news of the invasion inside a band of mourning, but indeed the history of Hellas for more than a year past deserves to be bordered with black.</p>
   <p>"Greece is in some ways one of the most unfortunate lands in Europe. It is unravaged by war, but the long mobilization of its army has bankrupted the treasury, its cherished and at one time attainable dream of the union of the Hellenic race is vanishing, its liberties have been outraged by a dull despotic king. And now when its ancient enemies are within its gates, the unlucky country seems obliged to choose between submitting to the outrage and embarking on revolution."</p>
   <p>To our fellow-Greeks of Chicago Loxias suggests that it will be injurious if not destructive to permit the community here to be divided into two factions. Those who are inclined to follow the policy of King Constantine must bear in mind that the outcome will be disastrous, and in Heaven's name, for our interest and welfare, we must not be divided. We are sons of Greece, all of <pb facs="5422062_6_0743.jpg" n="4"/>us, and not sons of kings and queens. Our adopted country will not want us to be divided and to fight one another. The interest of the Chicago community will be served best if we remain Greeks and do not become Constantinites or anti-Constantinites. Let us reason with ourselves and not rock the boat. Chicago Greeks must remain united.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
