<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1927-12-31">December 31, 1927</date><title level="a">Character</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0250</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0250.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1927-12-31">December 31, 1927</date><title level="a">CHARACTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The ancient Greeks were distinguished for their character. History tells us that the great achievements of the Greek Race, were attributed to their adamant character. They never retreated from the execution of their duty, whether in war, peace, politics or domestic affairs.</p>
   <p>The Spartan mother in handing her son the shield to go to war, said to him, "you return either with it, or on it". Motherly love played no influence upon the execution of duty. The mother's as well as the son's character were above all things.</p>
   <p>A nation composed of such citizens, indeed will shine as a star to the rest of the world. The administrators of the affairs of the State, the fighting Generals, the leaders of religion, the men of letters, philosophy and science were men of character. Greece could not have accomplished all the great achievements enumerated in the annals of history without the iron character of all its citizens.</p>
   <p>Character is not the privilege of the rich, the educated, the religious, the scientist and the blueblooded, but is for every one to shape and mold. Poverty <pb facs="5422062_6_0251.jpg" n="2"/>adversity, obstacles, impediments and even tyrrany, could not sway the man of character, hither and thither.</p>
   <p>The Great Persian King with 11,000,000 men marching against the Greeks who were only 300,000 fighting braves, through his plenipotentiaries, commanded the Greeks to surrender their arms, pointing out to the Greeks that it would be an utter impossibility for them to fight the Persians of 11,000,000. The Greeks answered with two words, which translated meant, "come and get them."</p>
   <p>The steel character of the 300,000 Greeks routed the 11,000,000 Persians. Hundred of thousands were slaughtered and captured.</p>
   <p>Character, cannot be inherited, given or bestowed, it is not an education taught in schools, or an intellectual superioity and preponderance, but it is the hammering and molding of one's self, it is the inseparable and indivisable part of the ego; it is subject to our own individual creation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0252.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Is the Greek of today distinguished and proud of his character, as the ancient Greeks were? The Greek of America regret fully, I must say, is not one hundred percent equal to his progenitors.</p>
   <p>(Notations of the Editor to the Greek Youth.)</p>
   <p>In our present stage of evolution, and especially in our present era, (the gross materialistic era) a man is measured and esteemed according to the amount of dollars he possesses. Present day humanity has blinded itself by the scintillating brilliancy of the almighty dollar, as it is called, kneeling down and worshiping it as a God. Virtue honesty, integrity, and character are melting away before the overburning desire of getting dollars.</p>
   <p>Oh! new generation of the Greeks, hold yourself erect and don't bend your head in reverance to the dollar. In this universal cataclysm raise yourself up, liberate yourself from the prevalent illusion, grab your shield and go straight forward to victory, show once more that the sons of Greece, living in their <pb facs="5422062_6_0253.jpg" n="4"/>adopted country, will lead the world to a new civilization. Virtue could not and cannot be subdued by materialism. Become a paragon to all. In your every day life, in your dealings, and in all your actions, utilize the dollar, but do not worship it. Virtue, eventually will come out victorious.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
