<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-08-25">Aug. 25, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Greek Committee Appeals to All Natives of Lyrkeia in the United States for Contributions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0922</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0922.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-08-25">Aug. 25, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO GREEK COMMITTEE APPEALS TO ALL NATIVES OF LYRKEIA IN THE UNITED STATES FOR CONTRIBUTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1--Fellow-Lyrkenians:</p>
   <p>We the undersigned committee, duly appointed and authorized by the general assembly of our fellow-Lyrkenians which met in Chicago on August 11, 1905, solemnly appeal to every fellow-Lyrkeian in the United States to submit his contribution in the general campaign now being conducted to raise funds for municipal works and other improvements in our native land.</p>
   <p>We all know that our Mother-Greece is still struggling for existence, for it is only seventy-five years since she was liberated from the Turkish yoke. The national revenue of our beloved Greece is quite limited; hence her inability to construct public works in every part of the nation. But you and I know, as sons of Greece, that it is our sacred duty to come to her assistance and if need be to sacrifice ourselves also. verything that we have to-day we owe to our native Greece,--parents, religion, language, <pb facs="5422062_6_0923.jpg" n="2"/>education, and life. And everything that we possess to-day in our adopted country is the result of that vigorous Greek seed of progressiveness which here in our new country has found fertile soil in which to germinate and to accomplish wonders.</p>
   <p>Can we forget our native land in the midst of our prosperity and progress? Would it be Hellenic to turn a deaf ear to the sweet imploring voice of the Enlightener of the world? The answer is no. We cannot and will not forget her, and it is not Hellenic to turn a deaf ear to her. Every Lyrkeian in this land is requested by the Chicago committee to send in his name with a ten-dollar contribution to the campaign.</p>
   <p>The Committee:</p>
   <p>Dr. K. P. Kalliondges D. B. Raptis G. P. Flessias</p>
   <p>G. P. Kalliondges A. B. Raptis P. G. Damalas</p>
   <p>B. P. Kalliondges Th. G. Boutselis B. P. Kotsopoulos</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
