<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-11-12">Nov. 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Results of the Election Remain Indisputable</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-11-12">Nov. 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE RESULTS OF THE ELECTION REMAIN INDISPUTABLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- Although the results of the election in Greece are already known to us, a complete official report will not be received for a few days. This delay is due to the complicated electoral system over there.</p>
   <p>The facts, however, will remain the same; that is, the liberal democratic parties, united by the efforts of Mr. G. Kafantare, have already secured 165 deputies, and according to the reports which are coming in they will have even more. That this will be the result is evident because these liberal democratic parties have piled up in various electoral districts surplus votes the total of which will call for more seats in the assembly. Consequently there is no danger that the total of 165 deputies already secured will be diminished; on the contrary, there is every indication that the number will be larger.</p>
   <p>Accordingly those rumors to the effect that the final results will increase the strength of the Royalists at the expense of the Democrats are totally unfounded. They arise from ignorance of the electoral system or from a <pb facs="5422062_6_0303.jpg" n="2"/>desire to confuse the Greeks in America and to inculcate in their minds the feeling that a disaster has occurred.</p>
   <p>The facts which demonstrate the victory of the democratic parties remain indisputable, just as indisputable as the fact that such a victory creates a strong opposition to exercise parliamentary control over the Government's actions.</p>
   <p>The Contradictor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
