<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-07">Sept. 7, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Community Shocked by Death of Doctor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0980</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0980.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-07">Sept. 7, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">COMMUNITY SHOCKED BY DEATH OF DOCTOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek community of Chicago was deeply shocked to learn of the tragic death of one of its finest and most brilliant members. Last Thursday Doctor William Lambrakis was killed when his automobile turned over on the highway. His unfortunate wife has had one of her legs amputated as a result of injuries received.</p>
   <p>The members of the immediate family were informed of the tragedy Thursday night. Sunday morning American papers carried a lengthy notice of the accident, the Doctor being very well known and respected in the finest American circles. It is very doubtful if any Greek read the sorrowful news and remained dry-eyed. In fact, refusing to believe it, many spent all day Saturday phoning one another--hoping to be told that it was a mistake.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0981.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This tragedy has robbed society, not only of a fine individual, but also of a great professional man. It is doubtful if any other Greek man--in any field--in such a short time has won such a great place in the hearts and minds of the people.</p>
   <p>William Lambrakis was born in Sparta November 5, 1898. Finishing high school in Sparta, he enrolled in the Medical School of the University of Athens, receiving his degree there. Fired by a desire to become outstanding in his profession, he pursued special studies in Germany and Vienna. He then returned to his native land and married. Immediately thereafter, he and his wife came to America and settled in Chicago. Here the Doctor quickly won recognition as an ear, nose, and throat specialist. The doctor was on the staff of the Columbus Hospital and was famous for his surgical work.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0982.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>His brilliant career was brought to a violent end by his untimely death at thirty-five years of age.</p>
   <p>The only one missing from the funeral was his crippled wife. Aside from her, practically every Greek in Chicago went that he might pay his last respects to the beloved Doctor. Among the mourners, leading American doctors and surgeons were present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
