<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1922-11-18">Nov. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Prelate Leon Pegeas</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Necrology)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_1034</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_1034.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-11-18">Nov. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">PRELATE LEON PEGEAS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Necrology)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Thursday morning, November 16, the most beloved and highest ranking member of our clergy in Chicago, the Reverend Prelate Leon Pegeas, passed away. He became ill twenty-four hours before his death, which was caused by heart failure. The sad news was transmitted by telephone to the Chicago Greek community during the early hours of the morning. Our fellow country-men, who had received his blessings and enjoyed his precious company for fifteen years, awoke to the distressing and shocking news that the man whose mild and noble features and personality delighted and inspired all, was gone forever.</p>
   <p>All hurried to town for further information. They greeted each other with, "Life [be]unto you."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_1035.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Truly Father Leon, as he was greeted by everyone, was a man whose personality inspired and imposed itself on everyone everywhere. He was a man of noble stature, widely cultured, simple in his nobility and kindness, humble and most willing to be kind to all.</p>
   <p>He was also characterized by devout patriotism and Greek feeling which because of the recent national disasters contributed to his death. It was impossible for him not to enjoy the love and esteem of all. Therefore, his funeral, which will be announced by specially appointed committees, will be a most magnificent one--to be attended by all the people. This will be one of the noblest funerals in our community's [history]. Besides the organizations, the Socrates School, of which he was president while he was pastor of the West Side Greek Community for a number of years, the board of directors of the Church and the West Side community are making arrangements for the funeral. Many other prominent members of our Chicago community are also working toward the same end.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_1036.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The detailed arrangements of the funeral will be made known to the public by means of programs which will be distributed.</p>
   <p>The only surviving relatives of the deceased are: the Rev. George Petrides of Detroit, Mr. and Mrs. Augerinos, and a few others in Athens. Saloniki is deeply grieved by the national loss, the death of our beloved Father Leon.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note:</p>
   <p>Prelate Leon Pegeas was a representative individual of great influence among Chicago-Greek people.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
