<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-01-16">January 16, 1926</date><title level="a">Anti-Hellenic Propaganda. by Dr. K. Haloulos, Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0363</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0363.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-01-16">January 16, 1926</date><title level="a">Anti-Hellenic Propaganda. By Dr. K. Haloulos, Chicago.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are two political parties in this country just as there are two in Greece. Here they are called, Republican and Democratic, in Greece they are called, Venizelists and Anti-Venizelists.</p>
   <p>The Anti-Venizelists, owing to their hatred of the name Venizelos, self-styled themselves as Royalists. The intrinsic desire and aim of the leading Royalists, is not to restore Monarchy, but to win and dominate the political horizon of Greece. The intrigues, and schemes of the political factions in any country, are known to be boundless.</p>
   <p>Owing to the fact that the former King Constantine was beloved by the populace, the Royalists called themselves the followers of Constantine. The Greeks of Greece and America are divided into two camps the Venizelists and the Royalists.</p>
   <p>Prince Paul, the son of Constantine, who is visiting our city, is followed and acclaimed by those Greeks of Chicago, who are advocates of the Constantine <pb facs="5422062_6_0364.jpg" n="2"/>or Rayolist party, and are opposed politically to the other party, the Venizelists.</p>
   <p>King Constantine, was beloved by the people of all parties while he was ruling as a King, but was sent to exile when he attempted to govern the Greeks. He became a victim of circumstances, ensnared in the wiles of a political faction, which used the Dynasty as a tool for its own preponderance. King Constantine was dethroned. His son, Prince Paul, now claiming the Divine Rights, of his politico-dynastic family of Greece, attempts to perpetuate the division of the Greeks with his anti-Hellenic propaganda. He wants to rule the Greeks.</p>
   <p>Silly youth, and silly royalists, don't you see the political game behind the screen of Royalty? A nation which is divided by any dynasty into two factions, sooner or later, will have no dynasty.</p>
   <p>The attempts of the Prince in Chicago, to prolong this propaganda and set Greek against Greek, with the hope of gaining power, cheap political power, and eventually restoring the Dynasty, does him no good.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0365.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Greece is now a Republic. The Greeks, sooner or later, will do away with this division, Venizelists and Royalists, and will unite as one mass under one Democratic government for all. I do sincerely feel sorry for those who, in their political dizziness, forget who they are and where they are, and follow a foolish young man who wants to become a King.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
