<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1912-10-19">Oct, 19, 1912</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">For the Balkan Conflagration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0784</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0784.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1912-10-19">Oct, 19, 1912</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">FOR THE BALKAN CONFLAGRATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Monday two hundred young Greeks from Milwaukee headed by their chief officer Demetrios Vaskas arrived in Chicago, united with the waiting reserved body of two hundred Chicago boys, and departed for the war front. The Chicago group was headed by Lieutenant Constantopoulos, reserve officer of the Greek army.</p>
   <p>Today three hundred Milwaukee Greeks headed by Dr. Kountanis, reserve lieutenant, arrived in Chicago to report for duty.</p>
   <p>George Matallas, salesman of Albert Pick &amp; Co. and reserve artillery lieutenant bids farewell to his customers and many friends and departs with the Chicago contingent.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0785.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>D. Manousopoulos, commander of the North-Side division of the Panhellenic Union reports that $5,184. were raised yesterday, and were sent at once to New York to pay passage from America to Greece, for the volunteers, who swarmed their from every part of the United States.</p>
   <p>Loxias'note to the Greek business men in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Each and every business man in Chicago must outfit and provide passage for one reservist. Mother-Greece is calling us. Four thousand business men in Chicago, must outfit and provide for four thousand fighting Greeks, fighters that are ready to shed their blood for the Father-Land. Chicago leads in volunteers. The voice of Greece is calling you for help. Do you hear it? Do you hear the beautiful, sweet and motherly voice of Greece?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
