<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1936-07-10">July 10, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Social.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_1046</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_1046.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1936-07-10">July 10, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, July 5, more than three thousand Spartans and other friends, who observe the patriotic activities of the Laconian element, came to the picnic of the Pan-Laconian Union, which was given in Harms Park. Everywhere around,you could see hand-shakings and faces of the sons and daughter of historic Sparta, who had come together to express their mutual friendly feelings, and entertain those who honored them. They also felt very glad for the Spartan element that plays such a big role in Chicago, both from the national and social point of view.</p>
   <p>Greek-American dances continued until late into the night and more than two hundred Spartans composed the different committees that were there "on the job" to entertain and please all. The whole affair, under the direction of Andrew Fashea, proved to be the most successful of all picnics held in Chicago.</p>
   <p>An athletic program was under the direction of Andrew Anastassakis, in which the Lacons distingushed themselves and proved to be possessed with traditional merit.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_1047.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Great enthusiasm and interest was witnessed in particular during the initiation ceremony of officers of the "Council of the Pan-Laconian Union". The officers are: Andrew Fasheas, president; Demetrios Papagiorgion, Vice-President; John Katsovitis, Secretary; George Diacoumeus, Treasurer. (The names of those that compose the council follow--Translator.)</p>
   <p>The Greek Star, that pays due tribute to all the Greeks without exception, and has been recognized as the Pan-Hellenic organ for a third of a century, registers exceptional honor and pleasure, because from a local point of view, it belongs to the phalanx of Lacedaemonians. The Greek Star is proud of being also an organ of the Spartans, with a Spartan manager, and declares that the Lacons are the forerunners, the Vanguards, the Columbuses of Hellenism; that it is to the Spartans all the Greeks ought to look to with due respect.</p>
   <p>The Spartans were the first immigrants the pioneers of every national and religious idea. They paved the way of prosperity and activity of the thousands of Greeks now living under the folds of the glorious American flag.</p>
   <p>P.S. Lampros, Manager of the "Star".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
