<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-11-15">Nov. 15, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Macedonian Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">Funds to Greece</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0870</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0870.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-11-15">Nov. 15, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK MACEDONIAN SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Funds to Greece</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Tuesday forty-two British pounds, the equivalent of two hundred and ten dollars, were sent to the Greek Government through the Greek Minister of Finance. This sum is to be deposited with the National Naval fund. The check was drawn at the Geocaris and Stamatides Bank by a special committee appointed by the Greek Macedonian Society which is doing its best to support every worthy cause.</p>
   <p>Although we cannot express any great pride in the smallness of the contribution and in the disinterested attitude of our community toward the drive, we consider this small sum the beginning of more substantial and generous contributions on the part of our magnanimous and patriotic fellow citizens.</p>
   <p>It is really encouraging to see that this society is giving evidence of the advantages that are to be gained when members of a nationalistic society are united and co-operating for the common interests of the Greek Community of <pb facs="5422062_6_0871.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago as a whole.</p>
   <p>What a great sum of money could be collected and used for the welfare of our fatherland as well as for our own local institutions and well-being if all the classes of our community: clergy, professional men, businessmen, and laborers undertook to contribute to a common fund, such as has been started by the small but active Macedonian Society.</p>
   <p>Let us again warn our community against the clamor of a group of so-called Greeks who are nothing more than pseudo-patriots and hypocrites who on the one hand encourage help to Greece while on the other hand no effort is made to work and organize for the success of the current drive.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
