<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-12-27">Dec. 27, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Anatolian Narration Greek Patriarch and the Archrabbi</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0060</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0060.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1930-12-27">Dec. 27, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">ANATOLIAN NARRATION GREEK PATRIARCH AND THE ARCHRABBI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.- A Greek patriarch, who was distinguished for his humorous witticism, especially where Jews were concerned, in a narrow religious gathering, cornered an Archrabbi of Constantinople and rubbed it into him.</p>
   <p>The Greek told the Jew that he had an unusual dream. The gates of Paradise were left open, and a Jew, discovering it, took advantage of the helplessness of the sleeping door-keeper. He stealthily entered into the holy place.</p>
   <p>When the elite and the chosen discovered the intruder a great scandal was created. How to expel the Jew without noise and without force? Force is unknown in Paradise. St. Peter called St. Paul for consultation and after looking over certain racial documents, both said, "Eureka."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0061.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>St. Peter commanded an Armenian, who was coming towards that direction, carrying a valuable Persion rug, to walk around the gate and in a loud voice, offer his rug for sale for a few dimes. The Jew inside the gate, true to tradition, (as the documents revealed to Peter and Paul), stretched his neck to hear and convince himself that the peddler really was selling the Karastan rug for such a small price. When the Armenian repeated the heralding, the intruder jumped out of the holy place and begun to jew the Armenian down. St. Peter,smilingly, bolted the gate and ordered an extra lock to be made in case of emergency.</p>
   <p>The Patriarch abruptly stopped the narration of his dream feeling that his adversary had had enough ridicule. But the Rabbi, who until then was listening attentively, said; "Holy Father, I think you did not finish the whole story of your dream, or you might have been disturbed and embarrassed by the Jew's misery. It happened that the continuation of your dream appeared to me as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Jew after buying the rug returned and found the gate double locked. Upon his persistent asking for admittance, St. Peter, through the pigeon <pb facs="5422062_6_0062.jpg" n="3"/>hole, informed him that he must be baptized before any consideration would be made in his behalf. The Jew gladly complied with the suggestion and requested St. Peter to dispatch a Greek priest to perform the baptism. St. Peter gladly told the Jew to wait and turned to find a Greek priest.</p>
   <p>"Hours passed and the poor Jew begun to doubt the sincerity of St. Peter, but, at last St. Peter, perspiring,appeared, and with hurt feeling advised the Jew not to wait any longer, for he could not find a Greek priest in all the mansions of Paradise."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
