<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-10-14">Oct. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Democracy in Greece</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0526</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0526.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-10-14">Oct. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">DEMOCRACY IN GREECE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Answer to the Royalists, the Most Estimable American Newspaper, the Chicago Tribune, Published the Following Letters:</p>
   <p>Chicago, Sept. 29.</p>
   <p>"Replying to P. Armiriotis, P. Lambros, and N. Kokinis, who expressed through the Tribune their opinion that Greece was not yet fit for democracy, I beg to call to their attention the facts which prove that all Greek kings have done more harm than good; it would therefore be unwise to stick to them.</p>
   <p>"As far as Mr. Venizelos is concerned, of late he favors a democracy. There are no royalists left since the collapse of Greece, except those whose pecuniary interests are involved. If Greece had had a president during the World War, would we have experienced the misfortune and catastrophe, had it not been for <pb facs="5422062_6_0527.jpg" n="2"/>the pro-German policy of King Constantine, a brother-in-law of the late Kaiser, and his activities through the German propaganda [bureau] which poisoned the pro-entente sentiment of the Greek people, and so prepared the defeat of Venizelos in the election of November, 1920?"</p>
   <p>G. Salopoulos</p>
   <p>Neenah, Wisconsin, Oct. 5.</p>
   <p>"Please allow me a few lines in your columns to answer your reporter's interview of September 29 with some Chicago Greeks on the question of a Greek republic.</p>
   <p>"A Mr. Nick Kokinis stated that 85 per cent of the Greeks in Chicago are royalists. This is far from the truth.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0528.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"It is an insult to the U.S.A. and the American people to allow any foreigner to remain in this country who feeds his ignorant brain with American history to no purpose, fills his empty stomach with American beefsteaks and pork chops, and his empty pockets with American dollars, and then has the nerve to support any king. Such foreigners have no right to share in the opportunities of this blessed country, and they ought to be kicked out of here, sent back there to slave for their beloved kings if they please, and leave this country to be governed as it has been for 146 years.</p>
   <p>"I admit that there is a small percentage of Greek royalists in this country and their excuse for being such is that the Greek people in general are not intelligent enough to be governed by a republican form of government--at least not yet. To this I will say, the Greek people may not be as intelligent as the Americans, but I am sure that they are at least more enlightened than the Chinese. Still the latter enjoy a republican form of government. As for me, I am satisfied with my adopted country and I am here to stay."</p>
   <p>Yours truly,</p>
   <p>Harry Farmakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
