<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1910-01-28">Jan. 28, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">License to Stay in Foreign Countries</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0812</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0812.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1910-01-28">Jan. 28, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">LICENSE TO STAY IN FOREIGN COUNTRIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is much talk in the American press concerning the Greek government's decision to collect license fees from Greeks living in foreign countries. According to the recent legislation passed by the Greek parliament, the Greek residents of the United States must pay license fees to the Greek government through the latter government's consular and diplomatic representatives. It is not known how the American press got this information which caused them to deal with the matter at some length. The entire press writes that such a matter is not only unjust but also illegal. The name of Mr. Labros Koromilas, the Greek Ambassador at Washington, as well as that of many Greek leaders in New York and Chicago is connected with this controversial subject. It is pointed out that the Ambassador himself first thought of this plan to tax the Greek immigrants. Furthermore, it <pb facs="5422062_6_0813.jpg" n="2"/>is reported that he requested or suggested to the Greek government that it enact and enforce a law to that effect. Such a levy will undoubtedly benefit the Greek government financially, for millions of dollars could be collected from the more than 400,000 Greeks of America.</p>
   <p>As soon as this plan was made known, nearly the entire Greek population of America accepted it most favorably. Of course, there were many who opposed the idea and who were very skeptical about the possibility of enforcing such a law which, according to their contention, would interfere with the independent and private administration of the Greek-American colonies in America.</p>
   <p>The entire Greek press of America accepted the enactment of such a law joyfully; it defended the proposed measure with enthusiasm and energy; and it recommended that the Greeks of America pay willingly the imposed tax for license to stay in this country. The only Greek newspaper that <pb facs="5422062_6_0814.jpg" n="3"/>declared itself against the practicability of the law was the powerful Atlantis Daily, America's greatest and oldest Greek newspaper, on the ground that the imposition of such a tax is unjust and arbitrary. As usual, the Atlantis Daily expressed its honest and blunt opinion on this subject, saying that the Greek government has no right to interfere with the affairs of the Greeks of America.</p>
   <p>A few days ago, however, because of pertinent articles which were published in the New York World and other American newspapers throughout the country, attacking the proposed action on the part of the Greek government, our Chicago colleague, Panhellenicas, directed a violent attack against the publisher of the Atlantis Daily, Mr. Solon Vlastos, accusing him of betraying the sacred plans and ideals of our homeland. The truth is, however, that no one knows who betrayed the plan and the idea to the American press. The publisher of Panhellenicas insists that the publisher of Atlantis committed this abominable and treacherous act. The latter, however, openly denies this accusation, saying that all that has been said <pb facs="5422062_6_0815.jpg" n="4"/>and written against him are enemy plots to defame his character and discredit his newspaper.</p>
   <p>The Greek Star and the Greeks of Chicago do not wish to take any side in this quarrel. We do not wish to criticize the act of one nor the conduct of the other. We leave it to the public to judge who is right. The Greek-American public is intelligent enough. It can examine the facts of the case in order to discover the truth. Only then will it be able to put everyone in his place.</p>
   <p>Already, because of the antinationalistic attitude of Atlantis, as some prefer to call it, many demonstrations and mass protests have been made in which Atlantis's Solon Vlastos has been denounced as the one responsible for exposing what the Greek government intends to do with our fellow countrymen here. The Greeks of Chicago have joined the others in blaming Mr. Vlastos for the expose.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0816.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>If you have ever been paid to sit as a juror in court, you must have heard the judge say: "Do not condemn before you can prove that the accused is guilty." In this instance the Greek public should do the same. Unfortunately, however, the public is not sufficiently enlightened, because the majority of the press, which directs public opinion, writes and speaks in its own interests. That is why occasions arise, when on the one hand we see the Greek so enthused that he eulogizes a person to the skies, while at other times he hurls curses and anathema's at that same man. It really does not take much effort to discover how sensitive the Greek is when it comes to questions involving his patriotism. By merely saying that such and such a man is a traitor, all are ready to club and destroy the traitor and save the country. Sometimes, the trick succeeds and the accuser rubs his hands with joy, because under the pretext of false patriotism he has succeeded in destroying a despicable traitor.</p>
   <p>In the same way, today, under the same pretext some "superpatriots" and <pb facs="5422062_6_0817.jpg" n="6"/>newspaper writers shed crocodile tears and with pharisaical hypocrisy exploit the poor people in order to take revenge on their enemies and win the sympathy of the people. So, gradually, their infernal plans are put into effect.</p>
   <p>It is known that Atlantis has become a most powerful organ. This fact has given a few, who can find no other way to live, cause to persecute that newspaper by whose destruction they hope to profit. But if Atlantis has gotten where it is now, there must have been some one to support it and that one has been the Greek people of America.</p>
   <p>Another strong reason for Atlantis' progress is the collection of $75,000 among the Greek people, fifteen thousand of which came from our people in Chicago. No other Greek newspaper has taken the initiative to solicit money for the urgent needs of our mother country. Now, we must contend with a renegade, a false prophet, and a false patriot who, unfortunately, was tolerated in Chicago for many years, and who is <pb facs="5422062_6_0818.jpg" n="7"/>stirring up trouble among the Greeks of America again. Of all people, Mr. Argyros has the impudence and the audacity to accuse Mr. Vlastos of betraying the Greek ideals. This is the man that sold out his country to our enemies, the pro-Bulgarian propagandistic committees, for a mere song. He was kicked out of New York for using all kinds of tricks to publish a daily Greek newspaper.</p>
   <p>May we advise the Greek people of Chicago not to get excited over some accusations by worthless characters.</p>
   <p>If we had actual proof of Atlantis's guilt and of the World's real motives in condemning the plan of taxing the immigrant, we would be the first to attack those who would betray us and harm our interests.</p>
   <p>The World's editorials and loud outcries cannot disrupt diplomatic relations between our two countries, nor can they prevent us from adopting any plan which would enhance the welfare of our Greek colonies in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0819.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>All of us are aware of the fact that voluntary contributions to any legitimate cause is not prohibited by law. The Irish people send thousands of dollars annually for the liberation of their country. The Catholic Church in America sends thousands of dollars to Rome. Similarly, every European immigrant group sends millions of dollars to their homelands. Never has the American government sought to prevent us from sending money to Europe, why, only last year some well-wishers accused Atlantis and caused it to suspend its publication until the local authorities and the government recognized the newspaper's right to solicit funds for patriotic causes. The difficulty arose when we launched a nationwide drive to build and send a battleship to Greece as a gift from her sons in America.</p>
   <p>Let us not raise too much fuss over the issue of the proposed license. If there are any evils or misunderstandings, The Greek Star and our intelligent leaders will intervene to set things right. In any event, we shall not allow the traitors, false patriots, intriguers, and sycophants <pb facs="5422062_6_0820.jpg" n="9"/>to confuse our people or poison their minds.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, we would like to call the attention of Mr. Solon Vlastos to the incident of the stay-license.</p>
   <p>Neither the Atlantis nor anyone else has a right to represent the 400,000 Greeks of America, unless they enjoy their confidence and unless their interests are upheld. No doubt the taxing of our people and the stay-license which are intended to benefit our homeland do interest all of us very deeply.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
