<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1904-07-08">July 8, 1904</date>, p. 3
<title level="a">Chicago Greeks Form Patriotic Society, the First in the United States.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0945</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0945.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1904-07-08">July 8, 1904</date>, p. 3
<title level="a">CHICAGO GREEKS FORM PATRIOTIC SOCIETY, THE FIRST IN THE UNITED STATES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With delight and pride the Greeks of America will hear that the Greeks of Chicago have founded a patriotic society under the name of Military Association.</p>
   <p>The object of this newly-organized society is to assist financially the National Defense Society of Athens, Greece. The membership fee is fifty cents per month. The accumulated money from fees and from benefit dances and similar activities of the society will be sent semi-annually to Athens without deducting any expenses for the operation of the society. The expenses of the society will be taken care of by contributions of the executive board. So every dollar collected will be sent for the national defense of Mother-Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0946.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Military Association will conduct each year a Pan-Hellenic dance, an excursion, a Lottery, and a bazaar to increase its funds. Lectures, mainly patriotic but also on social, commercial, and professional subjects will be delivered in the society's hall by prominent Greeks of Chicago and elsewhere, who will be invited for that purpose.</p>
   <p>At the meeting which took place yesterday all the foremost Greeks of Chicago were present, and chose by ballot the following officers and officials of the Military Association:</p>
   <p>Crown Prince Constantine of Greece, president; J. Georgiadis and N. Giannakopoulos (reserve officers of the Greek Army) first and second vice-presidents respectively; St. Lambardakis, general treasurer; Messrs. A. Apostolakos, N. Karellas, and K. Loumos, treasurers; Messrs. Kyriakopoulos and Koliopoulos, secretaries. Members of the board were elected as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0947.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Messrs. Geo. Koutsoubos, D. Kalogeropoulos, K. Koutsogiannis, Andrew Vlachos, Christ Vretos, G. Kokinovrachos, A. Papchristofilou, B. Varelas, G. Surlis, A. Bolas, J. Demetriadis,and J. Adinamis.</p>
   <p>Star's Note:</p>
   <p>The management of this paper sincerely congratulates the initiation of this splendid idea. It is about time for the Greeks of the world to come to the assistance of Mother Greece in a Pan-Hellenic way and strengthen the treasury of that famous and glorious country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
