<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1921-04-16">Apr. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Memorial Services</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1921-04-16">Apr. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">MEMORIAL SERVICES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Memorial services for those who died in the struggle of Asia Minor for the cause of freedom, were held on Sunday, April 10. At two o'clock large groups of people began to fill the Hod Carriers Hall. They were impressed by the solemnity of the event, and prayed that the struggle in which their brothers were killed had not been in vain. They prayed that the Daphne wreath of patriotism and freedom, that was waved by the leaders of freedom on the battle grounds of Macedonia, Thrace, and Ionia, would not be defiled by crooked Athenian politics.</p>
   <p>After the playing of both the Greek and American national anthems the people stood and cheered for the long life and freedom of their brothers and neighbors in Asia Minor.</p>
   <p>Mr. Salopoulos (editor of Saloniki) gave a speech, blasting indictments against the murderous tactics of the Athenian government. He was cheered enthusiastically.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0560.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then followed an interlude of music. Mr. C. Paleologos was the next speaker. His speech will be in the next edition of Saloniki. He was followed by Mr. Avgerinos, a young soldier and patriot, who told of the situation in Greece and the necessity for its solution.</p>
   <p>At five o'clock the meeting ended, and everyone hurried to read the latest news report of their country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
