<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-02-18">Feb. 18, 1928</date><title level="a">A Beautiful Hymn for the Greeks of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0230</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0230.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-02-18">Feb. 18, 1928</date><title level="a">A BEAUTIFUL HYMN FOR THE GREEKS OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- There has been published lately a most exceptional work, under the title, How I see Greece, by that well-known Greek scholar, Michel Roda, in which the following interesting article is to be found about the Greeks of America.</p>
   <p>"Blessings and glory to the Greeks of America. While we are ballyhooing in the coffee-houses about the 'status quo', present conditions, and general nonsense, the Greeks of America, the Lacons even more than the Gortinians, contribute their money which they earned by struggles and sweat, for the construction of roads and other works of common benefit.</p>
   <p>"Here come the Lacons of America, with their practical minds, their stirring patriotism and their humane ideas and say: Since the Greek state has not the money or does not think of liberating the populace from the scourge of rocks and precipices, here are millions at the disposal of Laconia--cut the fetters of its martyrdom.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0231.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Come on then, let us look closer for the reality, to the private economic sacrifice, and, as it is possible, to demand the making of a huge statue from marble of the mountain Penteli; this statue to symbolize the industrious qualities and patriotism of the Greeks in America; and to set it up in the central square of Sparta, or on the highest summit of Mt. Taygetos.</p>
   <p>"There is a plan--there are plans all over Greece--but there are no roads. There is no Sparta-Kastania road to the North and by the fect of Taygetos to be extended up to Leontari where it will be connected with the railroad line. This junction would be a real benefit for the populace, because Laconia through Leontari would have acquired free access to Megaloupoli.</p>
   <p>"For the construction of this important road the inhabitants of Pellani county will contribute money from the funds sent to them by their compatriots in America. The Greeks of America do not indulge in 'hot air' talks and unfulfilled promises, they help materially when things of importance are to be done.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0232.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"George Papageorgacopoulos, who went from Longaniko to Sparta, Sept. 7th, stated, --as I was informed by the province engineer, Mr. Bersis,--that he would contribute 1,000,000 drachmas for the construction of the road, Kastania-Leontari.</p>
   <p>""This sum I shall deposit in a few days in one of the Banks here,' said Mr. Papageorgacopoulos.</p>
   <p>"Mr. Antonopoulos, Treasurer of the Pellanites organization in America, verified the statement of Mr. Bersis. Mr. Antonopoulos has stated, that, with his early return to America he will convince the council of their society in Greece, to consent to the contribution of a large sum for the construction of this road, from the many millions of drachmas they have in their treasury for the erection of works of public benefit, especially of schools in Georgitsa.</p>
   <p>"The good work, however, does not end with the above project in view. The road, Sparta-Skoura, twelve kilometer long was accomplished by public funds. The remainder up to Gortsa, a distance of ten kilometers, was covered by funds sent for that purpose by the society of Gortsans in America, which amounted to 1,500,000 drachmas.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0233.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Seven kilometers of this road are already completed and there is only one more bridge to be put up by the State. The good work continues! Shortly the road, Gortsa-Zouenan, of seven kilometers, is to be started by money from America by the Zoupeniotes. The cost of this road is estimated at more than 1,000,000 drachmas.</p>
   <p>"From there the inhabitants of Geraki will undertake the extension of the road for twelve kilometers up to their town through money of their compatriots from America. From there, it has been decided, the road will be built further up to the village, Vrahioti, where the connection with the highway, Sparta-Monembasia, will be realized, and an access to the sea shall be attained. Before undertaking the road the inhabitants of Geraki will hasten the construction of a real place in which they will concentrate their schools. For the realization of this job 800,000 drachmas have been received from the Society of Geraki in America."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
