<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-05-08">May 8, 1926</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-05-08">May 8, 1926</date></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anecdote of the Greek Clergy. The Ottoman and the Monk.</p>
   <p>p. 7. A simple but wise Greek Monk, when Greece was under the yoke of the Turks, was always indispute with a Turkish Governor regarding the virginity of Virgin Mary.</p>
   <p>The Turkish Governor amused himself with the simplicity and frankness of the Monk, whenever he met him. One day the Monk was stopped, while he was out for a walk, at the command of the Governor, who was sitting under a tree of a coffee house, with other officials of his jurisdiction sipping Turkish coffee. In a mocking way the Turkish Governor asked the Monk, "What is your Virgin Mary doing now?"</p>
   <p>The Monk, graciously but not serfly, saluted the tyrants and in his simple manner said, "My Virgin Mary, right now, is making an escalator." The Governor laughed heartily and ironically and asked the object of the escalator.</p>
   <p>The Monk said, "For the Greeks to go up and the Turks to go down."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0338.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The faces of the Turks were reddened with anger, and one of them attempted to beat the Monk. But the educated Governor stopped his Turkish colleague with the following statement, "It is an utter impossibility for small Greece and its great patron Virgin Mary to overthrow the dynasty of the Great Ottoman Empire."</p>
   <p>The Monk again politely affirmed, "Wait and see."</p>
   <p>Three years later, when Greece overthrew the tyrants, and every man, woman, and child carried a gun and ammunition, a wholesale slaughter of the Turks began. The Governor took refuge in the cellar of the Monk. The Monk in his simple and unsophisticated manner reminded the Governor that the utter impossibility became a demonstrated verity, and furthermore, that it was the wish of the Virgin Mary, that the Turkish Governor life be spared.</p>
   <p>Later day historians wrote that the Turkish Governor was baptized and became a Christian.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of America and, in fact, Greeks all over the World take great pleasure in narrating the myth, pointing out the divine powers of the Virgin Mary and the humanitarian and merciful ways of the clergy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
