<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1921-10-18">Oct. 18, 1921</date><title level="a">Editorial- the Reception of Mr. Venizelos.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0556</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0556.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1921-10-18">Oct. 18, 1921</date><title level="a">Editorial- The Reception of Mr. Venizelos.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The arrival of Venizelos in America is a matter of great importance to the Greeks in this country, and we desire to emphasize, that the reception of Venizelos by the Greeks of America ought to take on a national character. It must be a reception by all the Greeks regardless of party beliefs and convictions.</p>
   <p>Partisanship has no place before the personality of Venizelos, abroad. And we say, regarding partisanship, that we have in mind not only those whose party principles are opposed to those of Venizelos but also those whose principles are in accord with Venizelos.</p>
   <p>That which we often emphasize in these columns is namely, that partisanship for the Greek of America is something tragic when it takes the form of a partisan reception of a statesman, who enjoys fame and esteem among foreign people. It would be something deplorable and humiliating for Hellenism in America.</p>
   <p>Aside from the fact that Venizelos, according to his own statements, has <pb facs="5422062_6_0557.jpg" n="2"/>retired from politics, the politicians of all nations, when abroad, lay aside their party affiliation and travel as patriots simply, representing the nation to which they belong.</p>
   <p>We regret, through necessity, to have to repeat ordinary things which we much desire to be known and felt by all. Unfortunately, the pressing rush that is driving us and the vehement party passions dominating us, make it necessary for us to remind both sides and so avoid absurdities that we fear, very much, may happen with the arrival of Venizelos here.</p>
   <p>Because, we must not, for any reason, exhibit ourselves to the eyes of others as divided in our national matters and separated abroad, according to party lines in our native land, trying to impose our will on our land by pointing out, from a distance of a thousand miles, what is to be done there and how Greece ought to be governed.</p>
   <p>We are duty bound, when abroad, to watch closely the Greeks at home, if <pb facs="5422062_6_0558.jpg" n="3"/>we are to be a part of the whole Hellenism, but the moment one part wants to impose its will upon the whole, that means that the whole does not seem worthy of being.</p>
   <p>With no intention, whatever, of hurting the feelings of those who boast of being Liberals and Venizelists, we say to them with all sincerity and courage, that the occasion shows that they will do a great harm to the reception of Venizelos if they act with party feeling.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
