<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1923-10-13">Oct. 13, 1923</date><title level="a">Editorial- the Greeks of America Must Send Representatives to the National Congress.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0453</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0453.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1923-10-13">Oct. 13, 1923</date><title level="a">Editorial- The Greeks of America Must Send Representatives to the National Congress.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The revolutionary government issued a decree whereby the Greek people are to be called on, in a short time, to elect their representatives for the Constitutional Congress. But, the Greek people are to be found not only within the confinements of the Greek Kingdom, but also in the large communities abroad, particularly in Egypt and America.</p>
   <p>In the United States there are about 500,000 Greeks, who compose a large and vital part of the Greek nation, and who are bound very closely to Greece by great interests and very ardent devotion. We cannot, therefore, understand for what reason 500,000 Greeks here, as well as those in Egypt and Europe, will be deprived of the right to send representatives to a National Congress, which is to decide many very important matters concerning the whole Greek Nation, and not the Greek State, alone.</p>
   <p>The right of representation for the Greeks living in foreign countries, at the National Congresses has been recognized ever since the establishment of the <pb facs="5422062_6_0454.jpg" n="2"/>Greek State, and it was only in the last National Congress that they were not represented. That Congress was originally proclaimed to be a revisional one and afterwards was declared a National Congress with larger constitutional powers.</p>
   <p>In this case, however, of a convocation of a National Congress, right after the ousting of Constantine and abolishing of the former existing regime, the sending of representatives from abroad also was discussed, extensively, (so far as we remember), and a decision was rendered under the administration of Mr. Krokida, for the sending of representatives to the oncoming National Congress by large Greek communities living in foreign lands. If, however, this matter was silenced in Greece, completely, and the government did not take into consideration the Greeks abroad, also, as regards their participation in the oncoming election of National Congressmen does not mean that we have to allow it to pass in silence, and not support our rights as Greeks to participate in the election of the General Congress of the Greek Nation.......</p>
   <p>Although we consider it unnecessary to enumerate the arguments and reasons, in support of the project, of having representatives sent from abroad <pb facs="5422062_6_0455.jpg" n="3"/>because we believe that the fact of the Greeks abroad longing for and being interested in Greece is alone sufficient to entitle them to the right of participation in the General Congress of the Nation, to be convened shortly in Athens. However, for the sake of discussing the subject.....We shall develop extensively the reasons....not only by a series of articles of our own, but also by soliciting contributions of those who are able to deal with this very important matter.</p>
   <p>Because we believe that this matter is one of common interest, and ought to be one of real concern to the Greeks of America, and because by its means they would have the opportunity to express their patriotic sentiment and desire to serve. The question of sending representatives from abroad is not only that of sentiment, but of the serving of the many interests of our Greek state to which we feel firmly attached in sentiment interest, and duty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
