<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1923-06-16">June 16, 1923</date><title level="a">An Announcement of the Chicago Greek Democrats. to the Greeks of America.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1923-06-16">June 16, 1923</date><title level="a">An Announcement of the Chicago Greek Democrats. To the Greeks of America.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greeks of America, having come from the very vitals of the Greek State and having set their mind, watchfully, on every move of their fellow-countrymen in Greece, it is natural to think and feel like those over in Greece, and to watch all events transpiring there. They ardently and enthusiastically, in each case, express their thoughts and sentiments and actively participate in the political activity of Greece.</p>
   <p>It is evident, therefore, that, in the expression and propagation of the democratic ideas in Greece, and the formation of a Democratic party, there the Greeks of America also cannot remain inactive and uninterested in this political move; especially when it is a case of political ideas and the establishment in Greece of a Democratic regime.</p>
   <p>As due to the environment in which they live, Greeks feel and think democratically and from close affiliation enjoy the benefits of the Democratic form of Government.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0462.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Animated by such principles and thoughts, the Democratic Greeks of Chicago gathered in public meeting and resolved to accept the invitation of a Democratic Association, whose purpose is, "the Organization of the Democratic Greeks of Chicago," so that in complete cooperation with the headquarters of the Democratic Association in Athens, we may contribute towards establishing a democratic form of government in Greece.</p>
   <p>It was high time, we believe, for the Greeks of America to have their real political opinions expressed. They should line up under a banner of party principles and not as heretofore, in individual groups, which either, under the pretext of old deals, politicianism or new-politicianism, have always looked up to certain individuals from whom they have been expecting every thought and every motive.</p>
   <p>It is mainly to such party ideology that grave evils befell Greece, of which the most horrible is the splitting of the Nation into two irreconcilable camps, that for the sake of individual aspiration and domination, became the cause of incalculable calamities.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0463.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Association of the Greek Democrats of Chicago is open, today, for all the Greeks who would endorse the Democratic ideology and discard their old principles of serving individual groups.</p>
   <p>We have no doubt that the Greeks of America will promptly endorse the principles of the Democratic Party, because only through them can we acquire sound and impartial opinions and render valuable services to Greece.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, they will contribute to bridge the political chasm, for under the banner of Democracy the opportunity is given to all to unite, in oblivion of the past and looking towards the more important future.</p>
   <p>A Greek political organization with such principles appears on the scene for the first time among the Greeks here, and its thoughts should be met with unhesitating approval. The Greek of America have shown themselves always to be prompt in serving the interests of Greece. Let us cooperate in bringing about the unification of all Greeks under the banner of Democracy.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0464.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Chicago, June 9, 1923.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis, president.</p>
   <p>Christ Maliris, Vice president.</p>
   <p>P. Chronopoulos, treasurer.</p>
   <p>A. Sousanis, secretary.</p>
   <p>N. V. Demopoulos, J. Haramaras,</p>
   <p>J. Papanickolaou, A. Matiatos,</p>
   <p>D. Ayvalis. ----Members of the Council.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
