<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1912-11-02">Nov. 2, 1912</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">The Grand Gathering. Panhellenic Meeting for War Needs All Greek Societies Will Participate.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0781</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0781.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1912-11-02">Nov. 2, 1912</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">THE GRAND GATHERING. PANHELLENIC MEETING FOR WAR NEEDS ALL GREEK SOCIETIES WILL PARTICIPATE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Upon the request of the greatest part of the Greek community in Chicago, that had not the opportunity to participate at last Sunday's celebration of Greek victories in the war, a Panhellenic assembly will be organized to be held on Nov. 4, 1912, at 7 P.M., in the North-Side Turner Hall. On this day the whole Greek community will offer prayers, decide on war needs, and all matters concerning the Balkan expedition.</p>
   <p>The executive boards of the Panhellenic Union, the Greek Restaurant Keeper's Ass'n, the Confectioner's Association, the Florist's Society and the Ecclesiastical Society Annunciation, are the organizers of this forthcoming Panhellenic gathering.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0782.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Speakers of the day will be Mr. W. C. Burns, Dr. C. Theodorou, and D. S. Eutaxias, publisher of Loxias.</p>
   <p>The executive committee of the affair is as follows:</p>
   <p>Dr. John Volicos, Dr. L. Diamesis, Dr. S. Tremoulis, Dr. A. Sanitaas, P. Rousetos, Th. Tsamalis, H. Koumoundjes, Th. Kourlas, John Rifakis, John Venizelos, N. Kursumes, D. J. Manousos, G. Economopoulos, D. Perdikas, John Cocales, Tr. Kotsovelos, Const. Geortsos, John Askounis, S. Spyropoulus, J. Metsoulas, N. Stathopoulos, B. Constantakis, G. Kassimatis, B. Kotsonis, D. Kalogeropoulos, John Yangas, Ch. Kastanis, D. Lambrakis, K. Bolas, D. Machairas, G. Giannacopoulos, G. Diamantopoulos, P. Economou, G. Vulumanos, G. Batsakis, K. Kotsovitis, P. Latsis, J. Drepanas, B. Koutsogiannis, J. Lambropoulos, K. Augerinos, N. Koutroulis, N. Athanasakos, J. Raklios, H. Trochatos, and J. Maropoulos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
