<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1930-01-11">Jan. 11, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Ahepa, American-Hellenic Progressive Association and Gapa, Greek-American Progressive Association Are Organizing Three Excursions to Greece.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0157</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0157.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1930-01-11">Jan. 11, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">AHEPA, AMERICAN-HELLENIC PROGRESSIVE ASSOCIATION AND GAPA, GREEK-AMERICAN PROGRESSIVE ASSOCIATION ARE ORGANIZING THREE EXCURSIONS TO GREECE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The chapters of Ahepa and the lodges of Gapa all over the United States are informed by the headquarters of the Orders, that systematic efforts have been made for the organizing of three excursions on a large scale to Greece.</p>
   <p>The first will be Ahepa's, which is scheduled to reach Athens on March 20. On March 28 the Gapa's excursion will reach the port of Peraeus, and during April, the biggest excursion of all will reach Greece. In this last group will be eminent Greek-Americans of the professional class; bankers, representatives of the press, representatives of the government, both local and national, besides Greek youths of school age accompanied by their parents.</p>
   <p>The United States Government has honored the expedition by offering an American transatlantic vessel for the use of the excursionists. The first stop will be at Patras, the next at Missolonghi, and then at Athens, where they will be met by the <pb facs="5422062_6_0158.jpg" n="2"/>reception committee headed by Mr. Kountouriotis, former President of the Greek Republic. The distinguished visitors will receive a cordial welcome.</p>
   <p>The preparations in Greece have taken on a national aspect, because of the magnitude of the plans for the reception and entertainment of the visitors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
