<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-05-04">May 4, 1929</date>, p. 3
<title level="a">Athens Gives Warm Receptions to Ahepans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0194</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0194.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-05-04">May 4, 1929</date>, p. 3
<title level="a">ATHENS GIVES WARM RECEPTIONS TO AHEPANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The city of Athens, with opened arms received the thousand Ahepans from America, who paid a visit to Greece as a gesture of good will and friendship.</p>
   <p>According to the schedule of the reception program, the Ahepans gathered in the porticos of the university, where 100,000 people were crowded to witness the ceremony of the pageant. At 10:30 a.m. the mayor, heading the civic authorities and the governor of Athens, arrived to officially receive the excursionists. As was prearranged, 45 aeroplanes in formation, circled above, dropping pamphlets on the cheering crowds bearing the inscription "Welcome Ahepans." At 10:45 A. M. the parade began, and encircling the principal streets, the procession reached the Cathedral of Athens, where the Archbishop of Athens held a doxology.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0195.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The crowded streets and side-walks were impassable, but when the multitudes noticed the American flag coming and were informed of the approaching arrival of the American minister to Greece, followed by American Legionnaires of the Athens Post, they divided to make room for the popular and well-liked American minister.</p>
   <p>Mayor Patches delivered the welcome address and with well-chosen words, eulogized the greatness of America. He terminated his speech with "Long Live America and Long Live Ahepa," amid a great applause. The crowd became unmanageable when the American minister spoke:</p>
   <p>His presence and speech electrified the Athenian people, who in turn showed their sentiment in appreciation of America.</p>
   <p>The president of the Order of Ahepa thanked the Athenian people, the civic authorities and the Greek government for their friendly attitude towards America and Ahepa.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0196.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Day after day the Greeks from America were entertained by various societies of the Greek capital and the girls of the Lyceum gave a performance in honor of the excursionists, at which many dignitairies were present.</p>
   <p>A symposium was given in which practically all the prominent and foremost people of Athens participated. The Premier of the Greek nation arrived at the symposium at 11 P.M.</p>
   <p>Senators, ministers, high officers of the army and navy and dignified members of the judiciary were conspicuous everywhere.</p>
   <p>Mr. Venizelos, with characteristic oratory inflamed the grand assembly. He spoke of America's greatness of what the world owes America, and what effect such excursions as this of the Ahepans has upon the people. He thanked the American Greeks for these ever-ready willingness to help mother Greece, and requested them to carry back to America what the Grecian people and its government think and feel toward America the Great.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0197.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>He reminded the visitors to tell the American people, that Greece, in spite of her financial predicament and the huge burden she undertook to rehabilitate 1,500,000 refugees, did not fail to meet her obligation to America, but continues to pay, and will pay every penny borrowed from America.</p>
   <p>The American minister followed the prime minister and thanked him and the Greek people for the good words said about America. Other distinguished speakers eulogized the American Greeks and the glory of America.</p>
   <p>The temple of Demetra, at Eleusis, a few days later, was the scene of another spectacular ceremony for the Ahepans, at which the authorities were compelled to use military tactics to handle the cheering crowds. Here again, the American minister Hon. Gould delivered a speech, telling the Greek people of the amicable ties that unite America and Greece.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
