<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-01-13">Jan. 13, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Opening of Registered Letters in Greece Comments of the Chicago Postmaster Star's Suggestions to the Post Office Authorities of Greece</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0935</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0935.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-01-13">Jan. 13, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE OPENING OF REGISTERED LETTERS IN GREECE COMMENTS OF THE CHICAGO POSTMASTER STAR'S SUGGESTIONS TO THE POST OFFICE AUTHORITIES OF GREECE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- There is not a single day of the week on which our office does not receive complaints from Greeks in Chicago and elsewhere about the dastardly practice of some of the mail-carriers in Greece of opening registered letters sent from America and taking out money or of failing to deliver the letters at all. Such a practice reflects upon the entire postal service in Greece and upon the Greek Government as well. This practice ought to be stopped, and the guilty persons should be severely punished.</p>
   <p>Mr. Molley, the Postmaster General of Chicago, whom the Star interviewed at his invitation, said, "The Greek postmen cause more trouble than any other postmen of foreign countries. I know of the recently enacted treaty between the United States and Greece which provides for the issue of postal money orders, but this does not deprive anybody of his right to send money by registered letter. It is incredible that the Greek Government should tolerate such a practice. The postal service cannot entirely depend upon <pb facs="5422062_6_0936.jpg" n="2"/>the honesty of its employees but must have a method and a system which will compel honesty. It has been said that opening letters or failing to deliver them has been a practice here, but I will ask any Greek to testify upon oath, and he will say that not only registered letters with money in them but even unregistered letters containing cash always reach their destinations within the limits of the United States. It is evident that the above-mentioned practice is prevalent not here but abroad. It would be to the advantage of all concerned if the postal authorities in Greece would inaugurate the spy system and eliminate such postmen, who are the black sheep of the service."</p>
   <p>The Star immediately recognized the importance of its interview with this wise and honorable American and took steps to urge the Greek Government and the postal authorities in Greece to remedy the situation and thus preserve the prestige and the dignity of the country. The practice of some few rascals employed by the Greek Post Office, either clerks or postmen, brings dishonor upon the entire system and is something new in the annals of postal service in Greece, and we hasten to say that it must be stopped now and forever before unpleasant repercussions ensue.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0937.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are very anxious to hear that the Greek Government will take drastic measures to punish these so-called honest men in its service who have evidently been corrupted by the influx of the almighty American dollar.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
