<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-11-11">Nov. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Election in Greece and the Hellenism of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-11-11">Nov. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE ELECTION IN GREECE AND THE HELLENISM OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- It is about time for the Greeks in America to realize that the results of the election in Greece should be respected, for they are the decision of the Greek people. They should not be received by us with the feelings of winners or of losers just because the outcome conforms to our own petty notions or runs counter to them.</p>
   <p>Those newspapers which, motivated by their political affiliations, try to falsify the news by submitting to their readers various eccentric interpretations of the results of the election are doing so in order to hold their readers in ignorance and to suggest the idea that some disaster has occurred. They transgress the limits of reasonable belief. They are seeking to promote their small personal interests, their own malicious aims. After all, the facts - the results of the election in Greece - more than speak for themselves and disprove every word of these journals which will not admit defeat. The acknowledgment of defeat is in itself a manly act, but they lack the courage to make the admission and in consequence are revealed as liars and impostors.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0305.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is imperative that all American Hellenism shall forget its political disputes and apply itself to the task of restoring Greek-American communities. At the same time it must acknowledge that by the votes of the Greek people a Government is about to be formed in Greece; it must address that Government with courage and confidence and request of it a solution of the ecclesiastical problem so that the unity which has long been desired and the peace which unity implies may materialize among the Greek communities of America.</p>
   <p>The Contradictor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
