<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-10-11">Oct. 11, 1930</date><title level="a">The Greek Theater in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0089</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0089.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-10-11">Oct. 11, 1930</date><title level="a">THE GREEK THEATER IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is not the first time that we have dealt with this subject. We always have considered the question of the Greek Theater in America of great importance, because we believe that, side by side with the church and the school, the Greek Theater, contributes towards the maintenance of our national traditions, in this country, and in itself, constitutes a bond between Hellenism at home and abroad.</p>
   <p>The Greek Theater in America, in order to fulfill such a purpose, must be equal to the eminence of its mission, a mission that, up to now, unfortunately has not been realized.</p>
   <p>To be sincere, the Greek population of America always had longed to see a good Greek Theater, but, unfortunately, their hopes belied the performance and those who undertook to present it disappointed them and caused them to believe that there is no Greek Theater fit to be compared with The Theater of America. In short, up to now, theatrical groups have caused the Greek population to have the idea of a Greek Theater take a very low place in their minds.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0090.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This is the bitter truth, and worst of all is that the Greek people of America find it very difficult, after so many disappointments, to show again enthusiasm and become prompt supporters of the Greek Theater. Support will be had only if some great name of Pan-Hellenic appears in the Greek Theater here, if some great and famous Greek Troop of Greece comes here. In short, a star of the Greek Theater must come here in order to restore the confidence and love of the Greek people for the Greek Theater, and elevate the latter to the height where it belongs. It is necessary for Kyveli or Kotopouli to come to America so that the Greeks of America may be shown what a Greek Theater is like.</p>
   <p>We are happy, today, to announce that the great Greek dramatist, the one that has stirred the Greek people by her acting for many years, Marika Cotopouli, with her troop, is coming to America to give a series of performances this year, in New York and Chicago, and to show not only to the Greeks, but also to the Americans the Greek Theater and its value.</p>
   <p>Because, Marika Cotopouli, will teach ancient Greek drama, also, for the American public, and thus we will show the Americans that modern Greece possesses, in addition to its theater, values of art and dignified beauty that can be justly classified among the greatest arts of the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0091.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is indisputable that our great dramatist, Marika Kotopouli, is the one capable to present the Greek Theater to the international world and particularly to the American public, which loves Ancient Art, and the Greek Letters, and which, we have no doubt, will appreciate and even admire the power and skill of the Greek artist.</p>
   <p>The coming into America of Marika Kotopouli, with her troop, must be considered a great event for the Greeks in America, and for the Greek Theater, generally, because we expect this event to create impressions and provoke criticism that will promote the idea of modern Greece with the American people and show that the Greek people do not lag behind in civilization, and that they do not cease to develope the fine arts, but keep on, always conscious of their great traditions.</p>
   <p>The Greek Daily, in particular, feels glad and proud in having helped by its service towards bringing about the coming of the artist to America. (etc. Trans.)</p>
   <p>(Literal)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
