<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1905-09-29">Sept. 29, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The So-Called Greek Literati in Chicago. Either Go Back to Greece or Go to Work.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_1074</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_1074.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-09-29">Sept. 29, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE SO-CALLED GREEK LITERATI IN CHICAGO. EITHER GO BACK TO GREECE OR GO TO WORK.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4. -If there is anything debatable under the sun, the Greek literati of Chicago are ready for it. If the subject is atheism or theism, they will take either side in order to keep busy debating. If the topic is the laws of this country, of which they know nothing at all, these affable Greek logicians tackle it for the sake of argument, and bla, bla, bla, all day long. And if there is nothing to discuss, they create an argument by asking you what language departed souls speak when they are freed from the material to the immaterial, and if you are not interested in this idle talk, they ask what your opinion is about thought-currents and so forth. Fiddlesticks, nonsense, and unproductive chatter! How they pay rent, laundry-bills, and other necessary items only Minerva knows. Of course, as for food and tobacco, they get it gratis from their fellow-Greeks, who are amused by the glib-tongued literati.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_1075.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago Greeks of this class, who maintain that it is beneath their dignity and their station of life to do manual labor for a living, are former normal-school teachers, students of colleges and universities, public-school teachers, and others who were caught by the emigration to America fever and landed here.</p>
   <p>That they are physically unequipped to do manual labor is an indisputable fact, but necessity knows no law. With regard to their disdain of doing any work which tends to diminish their dignity and is unbecoming to their station in life, the Star reminds them of what Socrates said, "Ergon ouden to oneides; aergia to oneidos-No work but only idleness is a disgrace."</p>
   <p>For their own sake the Star suggests that they either go back to Greece or go to work and make themselves useful and independent citizens of this great country, whose motto is "work and prosper."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
