<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-01-27">Jan. 27, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">To Members of Greek Communities Abroad Who Deposit Money in Banks in Greece</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0494</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0494.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-01-27">Jan. 27, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">TO MEMBERS OF GREEK COMMUNITIES ABROAD WHO DEPOSIT MONEY IN BANKS IN GREECE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is known to all members of Greek communities in the United States and Canada, as well as to all the people of Greece, from the highest official to the humblest citizen that for a number of years the Greeks of these communities abroad have labored with almost superhuman industry and have sent the major part of their savings to banks in Greece to be there held on deposit, for the following reasons:</p>
   <p>(1) Because Greeks abroad thought that through the devaluation of the drachma they could gain by speculation;</p>
   <p>(2) Because they thought that banking establishments in Greece and the management of them were in the same class as to safety as banking establishments here;</p>
   <p>(3) Because they satisfied their patriotic feeling when they deposited their money there and thus promoted the commerce of Greece and the improvement of its public affairs by putting more money into circulation over there; and</p>
   <p>(4) Because they believed that at any time when their enterprises here ceased to prosper, they could depend upon their savings in Greece if they wished to retire.</p>
   <p>But how these unfortunate depositors have been deceived! The majority of them <pb facs="5422062_6_0495.jpg" n="2"/>made deposits which were to draw interest and sent remittances in foreign currency, English, French, or Italian, and the banks in Athens not only accepted these remittances in accordance with their regulations but also promised in writing in each case to pay back capital with interest in the same currency in which the deposits had been made, that is, to remit to the depositor a draft on London, Paris, or Rome. We take the liberty of publishing part of a letter received by a member of our Chicago Greek colony, which reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"We are requested to notify you that according to a law enacted in Greece in regard to bills of exchange deposits of foreign currency in our banks are returnable only in drachmas. Therefore if you wish us to remit in drachmas the amount which you have on deposit, we are willing to do so; if not, we shall have to decline to make the remittance".</p>
   <p>I believe that the Greek Government must ultimately decide for the interest of its citizens, to repeal the law above mentioned, and the sooner the better. Likewise the banks should stop making distinctions between Greek and American citizens, especially when they wish to withdraw their deposits. They should stop making them go through so many details, such as notarized affidavits, consular formalities, and multiplicity of signatures, since, instead of being considered a form of service <pb facs="5422062_6_0496.jpg" n="3"/>beneficial to depositors, the banks come to be regarded as tyrannical plagues, and all the more so because when withdrawals are made from American banks, the transactions are accomplished with order, safety, accuracy, efficiency, and all possible facility. Moreover the banks here can themselves verify the indentity of the person who wishes to withdraw his savings, and the withdrawal is approved of on the spot.</p>
   <p>The Greek banks would have been fortunate if they had followed the procedure above. All people are and shold be equal according to law. And still more Greek citizens should have the same privileges in Greece which they enjoy here.</p>
   <p>We should effect an absolute change of method so that people might receive some protection for their interests, since upon the people these establishments are founded through the people, by the people and for the people everything is governed. We hope that between the Greek Government and the Greek banks will devise some arrangement by which the interests of their citizens abroad will be protected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
