<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1914-04-25">Apr. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Queen Eleonora and the Greeks</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Chicago Journal, Apr. 23, 1914)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0761</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0761.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1914-04-25">Apr. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">QUEEN ELEONORA AND THE GREEKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Chicago Journal, Apr. 23, 1914)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3</p>
   <p>The offer of Greek veterans now living in Chicago to enlist for the Mexican disturbance surprises no one who knows the warm love which the Greeks in America feel for the land of their adoption. They would make a most efficient force. Probably there will be no need to accept their offer, but at least it should serve to foil a very clever and very mean conspiracy against the good name of their native country.</p>
   <p>Queen Eleonora of Bulgaria is about to visit the United States. She will be warmly welcomed, as any such visitor deserves to be. But it has been clear for some time that her trip will be made the excuse for an attempted "vindication" of the Bulgars and for attacks on Greece and Serbia. It is the plan to lay all blame for the Balkan atrocities on the troops of these <pb facs="5422062_6_0762.jpg" n="2"/>two nations, to repeat every discredited falsehood that was ever derived of Sofia, to represent the Bulgars as abused angels and the Greeks as destroying demons.</p>
   <p>Every American official who has anything to do with the Queen's visit should let it be known at the very outset that no such campaign of vilification will be tolerated. If Eleonora wants to take the stump for her country, let her do so; but in that case she must expect to be received as a lecturer, not as a queen. The hospitality extended to a visiting sovereign must not be used to cover attacks on the good name of Greece, a friendly nation which has furnished the United States with nearly half a million loyal citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
