<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-09-04">Sept. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Greeks of Chicago, Their Pro-German Consul-General, and the Greek Government (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0643</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0643.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-09-04">Sept. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEKS OF CHICAGO, THEIR PRO-GERMAN CONSUL-GENERAL, AND THE GREEK GOVERNMENT (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek community in Chicago, with the exception of a handful of Royalists, has time and time again revealed its patriotism and devotion to this great Republic, which opened its arms and received us when we entered its ports as immigrants. Freedom of religion, of traditions, of language, and likewise freedom of thought were given to us when we landed here. Protection was given to us just as soon as we became bona-fide citizens of the Republic. And last but not least, all the opportunities in the world were given to us without discrimination that we might work and prosper. No other country under the sun would do for immigrants what America has done and is doing right along. The majority of the immigrants were illiterate. The country provided day and night schools for our enlightenment. And in short, these immigrants of all races within a limited period of time have made their influence felt in every station of progress and of life.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0644.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The great majority of immigrants are appreciative and thankful and eventually are absorbed by the greatness of the country, becoming an integral part of the whole.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago and all over the country ( do not wish to discuss any other nationality), to speak sincerely and openly, did not come here to be assimilated by the greatness of the country but to earn a certain amount of money and go back to their beloved Greece. But they deceived themselves. Year after year American justice, liberty, and greatness have molded the immigrant Greek into a new entity. And today he proclaims that it is an honor to be an American, and that he is proud to be one.</p>
   <p>But a citizen has certain obligations to fulfill and duties to perform for his country, and one of the most divine of his obligations is patriotism. No nation could continue to exist without the patriotism of its citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0645.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago and elsewhere have distinguished themselves by their patriotism for their adopted country. It is a great honor to the Greek race to know that the Greeks of America have performed their duties and fulfilled their obligations to the greatest and most humitarian republic in the world. Those who honor their country are honored by all.</p>
   <p>With chagrin I admit, and I blush to say it, that some Greeks in Chicago and elsewhere are not grateful to our country and do not share the honor accorded to other Greeks. And not only are they not grateful, but either directly or indirectly they are acting and working against the country. They were and are under the spell of German propaganda. I try to find some excuse to justify and mitigate their dishonorable behavior, but I cannot discover an iota of justification. I am afraid that I cannot find any other term to describe them but the word traitors.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0646.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>These are the Greeks who call themselves Royalists or Loyalists. Fortunately they are very few in number, but nevertheless they mar the good and honorable name of the faithful and grateful Greeks. Indeed, I must make it clear that these so-called Royalists are not, at heart, against the country, but their foolish notion of clinging to their devotion for the dethroned King Constantine, who was notoriously active as a tool of the Kaiser's, has created an unpleasant situation. A citizen who really loves America will not be devoted to an individual who is openly known as a Germanophile. Their argument to a certain extent is valid. But in times like these, when the country is making every effort to win the war, we have no patience with arguments. You are either for America or against America.</p>
   <p>These Greeks are known to the Government, and every action of theirs is scrutinized. The fact that they are not in jail reveals that the Government has nothing definite and tangible against them. But they still remain devotees of Constantine.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0647.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>And the newly-arrived Greek consul general, who as a diplomat of Greece ought to be friendly to America and to its cause, by reason of his attitude and his activities has been classified by Greeks friendly to America and by Greek-Americans in the debased category of pro-Germans.</p>
   <p>He, as Constantine's tool, has not openly opposed America, but on the other hand, though the diplomat of a friendly nation, he has not uttered a single word in favor of America or in praise of those Greeks who are fighting in Uncle Sam's army. That reveals very clearly that he is not a friend of America's. He is not interested in her victory. But he is interested in the activities of the Chicago Royalists. He and the Greek consulate are surrounded by those Greeks, Constantine's devotees. Has he been a friend to America since he came here? If he had been, his friendship would have been manifested in some way.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0648.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The Greek community of Chicago has requested the Greek Government to remove the unworthy diplomat. The request was made for immediate recall and punishment.</p>
   <p>But the wise old Greeks in the old country knew better than to do that. The diplomatic authorities of the Government, not wishing, for the sake of both countries, to rock the boat and create an open scandal, instead of recalling the consul transferred him to an insignificant post in South America. And his place here will be taken by Mr. Xanthopoulos of Tokyo, who is on his way to Chicago.</p>
   <p>Those who are familiar with diplomatic activities know that transfer to such a post means diplomatic oblivion and eventual dismissal from service for the good of the service.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0649.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>After all, the wise old Greeks knew better than the Chicago Greeks as to the best disposition of this consul general who was unfriendly to America.</p>
   <p>The Greek Government has further shown its wisdom by dispatching the Greek ambassador to Chicago to deliver speeches and hold gatherings for the Liberty Loan campaigns and by urging Greeks residing here to enlist in the United States Army, complying with the wishes of the Greek Government. So the gap was closed; what the Greek consul did not do for America was done by his superior, the Greek ambassador, His Excellency George Rousos. Well done. The stigma is washed away, and we bid our undiplomatic Chicago diplomat farewell on his way to oblivion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
