<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-11-15">Nov. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Advice to Grecian Youth.</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Adamantios Koraes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0390</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0390.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-11-15">Nov. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ADVICE TO GRECIAN YOUTH.</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Adamantios Koraes</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.--"Increase O youth your zeal to enlighten your country and to restore to it its ancient glory!</p>
   <p>"Do not forget that you are the descendants of Homer, Aristotle, Plato, Demosthenes, Thucydides, Socrates, and myriads of other great men! Think of what these admirable men endured to honor their country and themselves, and how they are honored even to-day so many years after their death by the nations of Europe and by the world at large.</p>
   <p>"Many of them went abroad like you to gather whatever useful things they could find among other nations to enrich their country."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0391.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Be careful not to be deluded by your youth in your selection of things foreign lest you return with empty hands or bring back the vices of aliens.</p>
   <p>"Surely all foreign nations have innumerable good things to offer but there are also many temptations to distract inexperienced youth.</p>
   <p>"Take for your example the honey-bee which picks up whatever is useful, not the fly which is attracted to filth.</p>
   <p>"Moderate indulgence in honest pleasure is recreation and relaxation and prepare one for more work and better work, but the abuse of pleasure diminishes the ability to work, enervates the body, and finally stultifies the mind.</p>
   <p>"Beware lest voluptuousness transform you into beasts as it did the friends of Ulysses, who were turned into swine by Circe.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0392.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Read constantly Prodicus's account of the life of Hercules and follow the example of the modest and decent virgin who represents Virtue; avoid the careless and shameless woman who dares to call herself Happiness!</p>
   <p>"The country does not expect of you stoic apathy or monastic hardships but asks you to lighten the blind and to clothe the naked. You cannot illuminate your country nor clothe its nakedness unless you use philosophical modernation.</p>
   <p>"In those days there were youths like you who attended the schools and studied in the daytime and worked by night to earn their living.</p>
   <p>"You do not have to fear such poverty to-day, you have but to show that you are willing to learn and the country will provide bountifully that you may not suffer while you are studying."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0393.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Therefore be careful in your conduct that you may be a credit to yourselves and an honor to your families and your country. You will succeed in all these things if you do not overestimate the value of trivial things."</p>
   <p>"We feel that it is our duty to repeat to our readers, both the Grecian youth and all other Greeks in America, this timely advice of the sage Koraes to the young students of his time."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
