<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-12-06">Dec. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Communities in the Greek Senate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0205</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0205.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-12-06">Dec. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK COMMUNITIES IN THE GREEK SENATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1. --- The news about the representation of Greek communities abroad in the Greek Senate is of great importance to the Greek people, both at home and abroad.</p>
   <p>The Greek Senate, which besides the senators elected by the various provinces also admits representatives of certain classes, grants in addition the right of representation to the various Greek communities abroad, such as the great Greek centers of the Americas and of Egypt.</p>
   <p>The right of Greeks abroad to be represented in the Greek Senate is of great national importance because it keeps tight the bonds between Greeks abroad and Greeks at home. Moreover, the voice of the former will be heard in Greece on questions requiring the Government's care and aid.</p>
   <p>For it must be understood, after all, by us abroad as well as by those at home, that so long as we wish to remain Greeks, and Greece wishes to have Greeks abroad, the bonds between the two sections must be more <pb facs="5422062_6_0206.jpg" n="2"/>tangible. Lack of any tie between the two will necessarily bring about as time goes on the estrangement of those living abroad from those at home.</p>
   <p>And it is not a question of moral ties alone, which will be preserved as long as the patriotic sentiment of Greeks abroad endures. It is also a question of material interest, which require real representation and interpretation and nobody but representatives from the communities abroad can represent them and interpret them.</p>
   <p>This question we have treated at length in these columns on other occasions, urging the dispatch of representatives to the Greek National Assembly. We said emphatically at that time that the question of the representation of the Greeks in America involves not only patriotic sentiments but also material interests, and that it is only on this basis, namely, with the idea of serving these material interests that it is worth while to discuss the expedition of representatives to our national center.</p>
   <p>The Greek people abroad, especially those of America, were in duty bound <pb facs="5422062_6_0207.jpg" n="3"/>to demand a place in the National Assembly even if the idea had not occurred to those in Greece. However,now that the latter of their own accord have granted seats in the Greek Senate to Greeks abroad, we must all receive the news with joy, and we believe that we reflect the sentiments of all the Greeks in America when we say this.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
