<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-03-27">March 27, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Activities of the New Greek Ambassador to the United States</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0864</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0864.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-03-27">March 27, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE ACTIVITIES OF THE NEW GREEK AMBASSADOR TO THE UNITED STATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As soon as His Excellency, the new Greek ambassador to the United States, Mr. Lambros Koromilas, set foot on this great, friendly, and hospitable land, the excellent personal and diplomatic qualities of the distinguished emissary of our beloved country were quickly detected. His abounding and inexhaustible energy and his personality made a most favorable impression on the American Foreign Office as well as on the Greek people of the United States.</p>
   <p>On his recent visit to Chicago, the Greeks of this populous and thriving Midwestern metropolis were greatly encouraged and given new strength which of late has been waning dangerously threatening to deaden our national <pb facs="5422062_6_0865.jpg" n="2"/>consciousness and keen sense of patriotism.</p>
   <p>Not only the Greeks of Chicago, but also our immigrants throughout America find a great and able defender and protector of their rights and interests in this country in the person of Mr. Koromilas.</p>
   <p>This outstanding Greek intellectual, accomplished linguist, and shrewd diplomat has the rare ability to make many friends among the official diplomatic corps. He is thus in a position to promote the interests of Greece and support the Greeks who are making marvelous progress outside their homeland.</p>
   <p>His outstanding record as Greek consul-general in Saloniki, especially, during the recent serious terroristic Bulgarian uprising and revolts in <pb facs="5422062_6_0866.jpg" n="3"/>Macedonia made for him an international reputation as a brilliant administrator who protected the rights of the persecuted Greek minorities in war-torn and ravaged Macedonia, which is claimed as a national territory by the Ottoman Empire, Bulgaria, and Greece.</p>
   <p>For Mr. Koromilas' able handling of the minority problem in Macedonia, the Greek Government promoted him to the high post of ambassador to the United States.</p>
   <p>Only a few days ago, a Greek by the name of Kalambokas was murdered in Ely, Nevada by an American for no reason at all. After a few minutes questioning at the police station the killer was freed. This man was going about the streets of Ely unmolested and freely afterwards, while the Greeks of that city were deeply grieved and profoundly resentful of the fact that such a criminal was at large.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0867.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This incident, however, reached the ears of our new ambassador at Washington and immediately he made a thorough investigation of the case and was convinced that the accused murderer was guilty. After vigorous protests and insistent demands to the United States Government, he succeeded in having this murderer arrested, tried, convicted, and imprisoned for the unjust and wanton killing of a fellow countryman.</p>
   <p>Ever since his appointment as ambassador, Mr. Koromilas has intervened repeatedly in behalf of the Greek people of Chicago and has requested the American government to give impartial treatment to the poor and exploited Greek immigrant. The prompt action of the ambassador in the above incident proves that one of the greatest and most pressing needs of our people is being satisfied, namely, the protection and safeguarding of the life, property, honor and happiness of the Greek laborer and small businessman in America.</p>
   <p>God and the ill-treated Greek immigrant only know how much prejudice and <pb facs="5422062_6_0868.jpg" n="5"/>intolerance exist in this country against the Greek nationality. We have all suffered much and have been stigmatized for many reasons in nearly every state of the union. It cannot be denied that on several occasions quite a few Greeks, as individuals, behaved very badly and disgracefully toward the Americans. However, we say that these were exceptions to the general rule. As a general rule and as a whole, the Greek immigrants in the United States have given a good account of themselves. They have proved that they are deeply grateful for the privilege of living in this great rich land. The opportunities and recognition which are offered our people by many Americans in business, industry, and government are deeply appreciated by all of us. On the other hand, the industry, thrift, honesty, patience, and perseverance of the Greek laborer whether he be working on a railroad gang, in mine, factory, or in the peddling trade has made an excellent impression on the native-born American.</p>
   <p>The Greek Star and the Greek colony of Chicago, which it represents and <pb facs="5422062_6_0869.jpg" n="6"/>whose sentiments and desires it voices, are happy in the thought that the American press and the Government of the United States have praised our new ambassador highly for his courage and forthrightness in standing up for the rights and interests of the Greek immigrants of America.</p>
   <p>We are fortunate and proud to have a great Greek patriot like His Excellency, Mr. Lambros Koromilas amongst us. The fate, the happiness, and progress of the Greek immigrant in America depends to a large extent upon the guardianship and vigilance of such true leaders.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
