<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-03-01">Mar. 1, 1924</date>, p. 2
<title level="a">From Greece.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-03-01">Mar. 1, 1924</date>, p. 2
<title level="a">FROM GREECE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Greeks who were in Athens during a celebration given by the Hellenic people to express their gratitude to the United States, tell us how the Greeks really feel towards America. The Chicago Greeks were delighted and proud to see how the Greeks of the Old-country sincerely manifested their deep-rooted appreciation for the Grand U. S. A.</p>
   <p>Besides other interesting events in the celebration, thousands of refugees' orphans paraded before the American flag which they saluted in a stiff and snappy way, at attention, as if they had grown up and were trained soldiers of that glorious flag. They danced Greek dances and played American games and used much American slang, to the delight of the hundreds of thousands of people who gathered at the Zapeion for the occasion. Mr. Venizelos, prime minister of Greece, in addressing the youngsters extolled the greatness of America and in burning words, in the name of Greece, expressed his gratitude for what the American people have done for Greece, and in a pleading voice urged the orphans, when they grow up, to remember and love the grandest democratic and philanthropic republic of the world, the U.S.A., their benefactor.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0433.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The distinguished statesman of Greece, who at intervals when occasion arises, reveals his feelings and thoughts of America, turned his eyes to the great multitude of people and said. "It is your holy duty oh! Greece, to see that the present and future generations of you, will bear witness to the granduer of the United States of America.</p>
   <p>The enthusiasm of the masses went sky-high when a salute of the flag was asked by the Premier. From what took place, one might have thought that those great masses of people were not Greeks but Americans saluting their flag and giving honor to it.</p>
   <p>Editor. Bravo to brother Greeks for expressing their true sentiments to our adopted country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
