<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-05-13">May 13, 1928</date><title level="a">The Greeks Atroad</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-05-13">May 13, 1928</date><title level="a">THE GREEKS ATROAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 8.- Athens, April 20.- We are going through a period of new national rejuvenation. We are taught again by history that we are the only people on earth who so successfully confront, for centuries, time and evolution. We prove again that we are the only people who, as the phoenix of mythology, are reborn from the asked and resume our former being and impetus, indefatigable, imperishable with the Greek character unchanged.</p>
   <p>Our last experience is not the only one. In our eternal career we have been confronted with dangers, we have overcome obstacles and we underwent catastrophes that would have buried in the dustbin of the past any other nationality.</p>
   <p>We Greek people differ from all others. Our exceptional endowment is that we have the power to overcome even the greatest hardships and to successfully resist the most furious temoests.</p>
   <p>We, the Greek people, have always been distinguished for our national spirit, our national pride, and our national independence. We have always been proud <pb facs="5422062_6_0217.jpg" n="2"/>of our nationality and solidarity towards it. No matter in what corner of the globe they were to the found, the Greeks distinguished themselves. To no people on earth have we ever admitted subjugation nor have we assimilated with any. The national pride has retained and preserved the national idea.</p>
   <p>Now, after a long and hard experience, we, the Greek people, are going through a period of rejurmation, regaining and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> our steps towards new progress, new heights, new glory.</p>
   <p>Fortunately, even today, the Greek people are nationally united. The Greeks of the independent state, those under foreign rule, and those spread out, have kept the national spirit in fact.</p>
   <p>The new period and international situation, social and political, however, has today added difficulties in the greak task of national rejuvenation.</p>
   <p>Today, unlike the past, the Interest and individual initiative is not enough. The new difficulties in evidence must dictate new systems. Helleniusm today must march on, organized on up-to-date foundations and with a system able to counteract every difficulty of these new conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0218.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Greek people today must constitute an organization having the Independent state as a center and the whole world as a circle of activity, wherever there are Greeks. The new Greek state must be the official representative of all Hellenism.</p>
   <p>The Greek communities wherever they happen to be from now on, must not be considered as out of the state and under foreign rule. They must, as Greek provinces, bind themselves with the Greek capitol by official representatives sent to Greece as delegates of the national will of the Greeks abroad.</p>
   <p>New seats must be added to the Greek parliament for the Greek representatives from abroad. Their voices must be heard from the Greek parliament's rostrum. The latter must not be deprived of the rights of sovereignity of the Greek people, inasmuch as they also preserve the Greek spirit, have national interest, are national factors and contribute to the national prosperity and progress of Greece.</p>
   <p>The narrow conception coming from the narrow boundaries of the independent state must be eliminated. If it is time for the official representation to include all the Greeks in the world. Let the meaning of the state in the <pb facs="5422062_6_0219.jpg" n="4"/>task of the national rejuvenation be of secondary importance and let the idea of the nation prevail.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
