<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1907-01-11">Jan. 11, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">What Immigration Has Brought to Chicago-The Youthful Spartan (From the Chicago Chronicle)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_1057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_1057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-01-11">Jan. 11, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IMMIGRATION HAS BROUGHT TO CHICAGO-THE YOUTHFUL SPARTAN (FROM THE CHICAGO CHRONICLE)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.. It is not necessary to go to libraries to read accounts in books of the world-famous bravery of Spartans, and there is no reason to wonder or to doubt whether the Spartans were really so valiant as they are reputed to have been, for right here in our city we have had the honor (thanks to immigration) of receiving recently a Spartan whose stoicism amazed the doctors who treated him for hydrophobia.</p>
   <p>This new immigrant to our city is John Brookas, fourteen years old, who came from Sparta, Greece, six weeks ago.</p>
   <p>Young Brookas, who lives at 208 Binn Street, was bitten by a mad dog last week, and he is now at the Pasteur Institute under the care of half a dozen specialists who have become very much interested in the case.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_1058.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>According to neighbors who witnessed the battle between the dog and the boy the youthful immigrant fought the mad dog's attack with incredible courage until he fell unconscious but never uttered a single cry. At the hospital, where the doctors were stupefied by the young immigrant's fortitude, their gray heads shook in amazement when John said through an interpreter, that his courage was a Spartan characteristic.</p>
   <p>Editor's note: It is unusual and wonderfully fortifying to read in the American press an item about Greeks which contributes to the reputation of Greeks, for such reports furnish examples for others. But America has among natives and immigrants an abundance of extraordinary people, and when an instance presents itself as in the case of the Spartan boy, we are astonished to know what colossal potentialities are hidden in this infinite country of ours.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
