<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-03-10">Mar. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Large Contributions in Chicago for the Refugees in Greece</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-03-10">Mar. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">LARGE CONTRIBUTIONS IN CHICAGO FOR THE REFUGEES IN GREECE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2- The Greek Relief Committee believes it to be its duty to thank all those who by their donations have afforded relief to the many great trials which our unfortunate brothers, refugees from Asia Minor, have undergone.</p>
   <p>It desires particularly to thank first the Young Ladies Philarmonic Association, which not only has rendered much encouraging assistance but has also devoted the proceeds of its last dance amounting to $1,350 to the welfare of the refugees.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0476.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It thanks, in the second place, the Chicago Association of the Greek Liberal Democrats which has contributed all the proceeds of its recent dance and has also raised subscriptions totalling $5,000 among its members.</p>
   <p>Third it thanks the churches of the North and South Sides, which not only have offered their contributions but have also helped the committee to raise subscriptions among their communicants.</p>
   <p>Fourth it thanks the American business organizations, the Moody and Waters Company, the Case and Martin Company and the B. A. Railton Company for their generous contributions.</p>
   <p>Fifth, it thanks the Greek newspapers, which have dedicated so much of their valuable space to this hallowed enterprise.</p>
   <p>We hope that other associations will follow the generous example of those mentioned above and send their contributions by mail to the Greek Relief Committee, 127 North Dearborn Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0477.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is well known that the total amount contributed will be doubled by the Near East Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>The Greek Relief Committee up to the present time has received in individual and general contributions in Chicago the sum if $19,899.65.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
