<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1922-09-29">Sept. 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Greeks Here Divided</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1922-09-29">Sept. 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">GREEKS HERE DIVIDED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[This verbatim copy is related to the translation from the Greek of the Scrap-book of P. S. Lambros, 130 North Wells Street.]</p>
   <p>Chicago Greeks are not in favor of a Grecian republic at this time, according to views expressed last night. The consensus of opinion is that love of the king is inborn in their race. Interviews follow.</p>
   <p>P. Armyriotis, Greek Consul: I am much in favor of a Greek monarchy. The Greeks at this time have not the experience to maintain a republic. Thrace should never be given up for any price.</p>
   <p>Peter S. Lambros, publisher of the Greek Star: I agree with Venizelos that Greece is not yet ready for a republic. We have as examples Russia and Ireland. Greece will be a democracy with Venizelos the actual ruler. Thrace is the <pb facs="5422062_6_0536.jpg" n="2"/>native land of Themistoeles. Not a Greek living would countenance giving up Thrace.</p>
   <p>Nick Kokinis, president of the Greek Community of Chicago: I have never considered the possibility of Greece as a republic. I feel,and I think that eighty-five per cent of the Greeks here agree with me, that the king is very dear to the Greek people. His troubles were caused by Venizelos.</p>
   <p>James Michalaros, editor of the Chicago Greek Daily: By all means a republic. That is the policy of this newspaper and of ninety-five per cent of the Greeks in America.</p>
   <p>Anthanasius A. Pantelis, lawyer, 155 North Clark Street: There is no question in my mind but that a republic would be better. The people of Greece are competent to govern themselves.</p>
   <p>The Hellenic Liberal League of Chicago sent a cablegram to the president of <pb facs="5422062_6_0537.jpg" n="3"/>the revolutionary government in Greece last night urging that bloodshed be avoided and saying that the royalist government must go.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
