<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-01-24">Jan. 24, 1931</date>, p. 6
<title level="a">The Origin of Lucky Games.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0055</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0055.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-01-24">Jan. 24, 1931</date>, p. 6
<title level="a">THE ORIGIN OF LUCKY GAMES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Writers, poets, historians, intellectuals and others, whenever in doubt of the authenticity of a thing, turn their eyes upon ancient Greece, for the solution of the disputed problem.</p>
   <p>Games of chance were known during the Homeric era. That the games of chance were created by ancient Greeks, is indisputable judging from the devotion and love of the modern Greeks for such games. Greeks are known the world over as gamblers.</p>
   <p>Games of luck were played at the Symposiums. Our ancestors held Games of chance after eating, and after offering their sacrifices to Dionysus (Bacchus), God of wine and revelry. The modern Greeks, being true scions of the ancients, inherited the habit of gambling, and owing to our present civilized facilities, have developed it into a real art.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0056.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to make it appear lawful and respectable, they have clothed it with the toga of religion, so women and boys also could gamble but with immunity. For example, the first day of the new year St. Basil's day, men, women and children played the games of chance, not only in public places, if the law permitted, but in their homes. The salutation was "Chronia Pola" ("A long life to you").</p>
   <p>Noted, among the ancient games, were the "Skaki" and the "Dice" But in spite of their devotion to "Dice" the Greeks failed to create a God as patron of the game, as was usually done. Maybe, Athena owing to her wisdom, was the dual goddess.</p>
   <p>Other games in which great sums of money changed hands, were the cock fight and thrush fight. The cock and the thrush had to fight each other for the amusement of the Greeks but the real object was that it provided a chance to gamble.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0057.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Greeks, true to their ideals of spreading civilization to the four corners of the globe, did not fail to enlighten the land of Latius with their games of luck. Rome, therefore, glorified the games of luck with Caesar, Augustus and Claudius as the biggest gamblers of their time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
