<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-05-18">May 18, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal from the Soldiers' Mother to the Greeks of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-05-18">May 18, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL FROM THE SOLDIERS' MOTHER TO THE GREEKS OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5- Dear fellow-countrymen; With the courage of a new immigrant I have come to America. I have come to a civilized center of mankind from the country which first diffused the light of civilization. I have come to find my fellow-countrymen, to move them to action in behalf of the humanitarian work which is being done for their brothers.</p>
   <p>On the long journey to this country I became acquainted with many people who live here, people from Chicago and from other parts of America. Suffice it to say that they did not discourage me. No; they gave me hope of strong moral assistance from them in this country. But I did not want to appear indiscreet, and consequently I went to the press to ask its assistance first. Unhesitatingly and nobly the press responded.</p>
   <p>The National Herald's answer was positive and final: "We will help you with all our might"; and when I read this sincere statement, I felt relief and a revival of my hopes for success.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0284.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A sorrowful, pleading address in the style typical of such appeals I cannot force this pen of mine to write. It darts and runs about just as we ran about together during the years of 1912 and 1913 - lovingly together - united as true children of the same country should be. No; those soft, carefully chosen, touching words which are usual in appeals I have never been able to cultivate to stir people's hearts and so achieve my aims. And now I shall tell my interested fellow-countrymen how it has come about that after so many years I am making this journey.</p>
   <p>Since last August I have been building the sanatorium at Korfoxelia, Arcadia, in a secluded spot above the village of Magoulians, so that the tubercular patients will cease to pollute our beautiful villages, the scenic landmarks of Morea. They will all be sent to the sanatorium hereafter.</p>
   <p>We have secured three hundred acres covered with fir-trees. This coming November the edifice will be finished. The total cost will be 2,500,000 drachmas (about $25,000) for the main building and one wing; the other wing will be constructed later. From Greece and the Greek communities in <pb facs="5422062_6_0285.jpg" n="3"/>Egypt I have already collected 3,500,000 drachmas (about $35,000). Fortunately the Spetseropoulos brothers of Tripoli, who have already donated 1,200,000 drachmas (about $12,000) to the general fund, will undertake to supply the furnishings of the right wing.</p>
   <p>My collections are destined first for internal equipment, - heating, Roentgen rays, lighting, water-supply, cooking apparatus, etc. After this is taken care of, the money collected from Greeks in America will be applied to guarantee free nursing to the patients in the third-class wards. In the five first-class wards and the several second-class wards which we shall have the patients will be charged for places.</p>
   <p>You must remember that since the late wars our country has spent 60,000,000 drachmas a year ($600,000) for the care of officers who were sent to other countries for nursing, whereas the poor soldiers were neglected because they lacked the almighty chevrons. Today our country defrays the medical expenses of these same officers, though it no longer sends them abroad. It is the barely subsisting soldiers for whom I am working, and for whom I shall continue to work. I feel for them; I know what misery they have gone through, besides the misery of our wars. The sanatorium will be a sanctuary for these sufferers.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0286.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Greek Red Cross is already actively engaged in instructing girls in nursing. The sanatorium will enable these girls to learn nursing by themselves, and later they will be taken in hand by the visiting nurses.</p>
   <p>I am proud and happy that my persistence in constructing a philanthropic sanatorium makes it possible to combat tuberculosis in Greece in a systematic way, something which should have been started long ago.</p>
   <p>Now then, help me, good fellow-countrymen. I am not asking how much you can give. No, for there are many of you, many Greeks in America. A dollar, even half a dollar when sent with good wishes will contribute to the success of my undertaking.</p>
   <p>So that everything may be in order, I have created a committee to work out the details in handling your contributions. This committee has arranged everything in the following manner. Contributions should be sent to The Bank of Athens, Committee Treasurer, 25 Pine Street, New York. There they will be applied to the account of "The Sanatorium's Mother," and every contribution sent will be acknowledged, for on the day when the <pb facs="5422062_6_0287.jpg" n="5"/>donation is received, a receipt bearing the letterhead "The Sanatorium's Mother" will be sent to you. I shall be kept informed of all your letters, and all your names with the amounts contributed will be submitted to the National Herald for publication. Anonymous contributions will also be published.</p>
   <p>My plans are and always have been to set out from Chicago and to go wherever there are Greeks, not restricting myself to the large cities, and to end my collecting in New York. I want you all to see the moving pictures which I took in Athens, Corinth, Tripoli, Magouliana, Korfoxelia, and Betzova. You will be much interested, and some of you will see pictures of your own particular district of Greece.</p>
   <p>And now I believe that the simple and sincere purpose of my collections has been approved of, and approved of enthusiastically. Remember your far-away fatherland. Remember your brothers. Remember the great cruel war.</p>
   <p>New York, April 27.</p>
   <p>With Love,</p>
   <p>Anna Papadopoulou.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
