<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-01-09">January 9, 1926</date><title level="a">Greece and the Divine Rights.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0369</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0369.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-01-09">January 9, 1926</date><title level="a">Greece and the Divine Rights.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greeks are regarded as the pioneers of the civilization that the world is enjoying today. They are the fathers of literature, arts, and science. Wherever you turn your eyes, you will find a mighty monument of tribute to Greek culture.</p>
   <p>Oh, Ancient Greece! the giver of light to the World, are you going to let Modern Greece be ruled and governed by a band of imported foreigners? A King from Denmark, who was put in control of the Throne; a Queen who was brought from the pig-headed Hoenzollern tribe to rule the Greeks.</p>
   <p>A lady of that so-called Greek Royal Family was delivered to a Rumanian Prince, against his will. The man had a wife and a child at the time, but his Mother Queen Marie, another scheming royal woman, compelled this Carol, as that is his name, to marry the lady from the Greek Royal Family.</p>
   <p>But this Royal Family is not Greek. There is not a single drop of Greek blood in the veins of these so-called royal foreigners, who are, and who have <pb facs="5422062_6_0370.jpg" n="2"/>attempted to foist themselves upon our race.</p>
   <p>Another Prince of this family sold himself to an old woman by the name of Leeds. Her son also bought another member of this so-called royalty. And they all now have money enough to wander around the Capitols of Europe, claiming royal prerogatives. Indeed, they are asserting the Divine Right of Kings.</p>
   <p>Evidently the Greek Jehova has failed to hear their cries of Divine Rights. This band of royal parasites, these international refugees or tramps, have their faces turned to the United States, coming to this country, for God knows what. But to the intelligent Greeks of America, who have worked and fought their way, from the very bottom, upwards, their visit here, only means one thing. They want money, and with their propagandism, they are attempting to again install themselves upon the backs of the Greek race. Nay! Nay! their hopes are vain; best for them to go to work and earn an honest and decent living, and forget the silly idea of the Diving Rights of Royalty. It may be, that they can sell their titles of royalty, to gullible and stupid wealthy Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0371.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is said that they have worn out their shoes, running between the capitols of Europe seeking aid and consolation for their Kingly, Queenly, and Princely jobs, the practical minded men of Greece separated them from.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of today will follow the Greeks of the past, the originators of Democracy, and never permit those royal fakers and parasites to suck their blood anymore. Long live the Greek race!</p>
   <p>If the Greeks are not able to function without the thrash which was dumped upon them from Denmark, Germany, Rumania, and Russia, it is high time that they turn themselves over to Turkey or some other Balkan Power and be slaves. But I'm confident Greece will rule itself with full blooded Greeks at its head and not by the drains of an international family.</p>
   <p>Long live the Greek race! Royalty go to work, and stop grafting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
