<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1909-05-20">May 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Lottery Ads in Papers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0843</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0843.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1909-05-20">May 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">LOTTERY ADS IN PAPERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- The discovery that thousands of Greek and Italian newspapers sent to Chicago from Europe contain advertisements of lotteries spurred the federal authorities yesterday to begin a scorching investigation of reports that lottery tickets are sold here in large numbers. The Greek lotteries are maintained by the government and the advertisements bear the signature of the Chief Clerk of the Minister of Finance at Athens.</p>
   <p>It was asserted yesterday by a man who has frequent business dealings with Greek shops on Halsted Street that $200,000 has been taken from the United States by means of this Greek national lottery to build the Greek navy. The Greek immigrants who have recently come to America are said to be the principal patrons of the lotteries. Agents are said to visit fruit stores and shoe-shining shops to sell tickets.</p>
   <p>The advertisement, which is carried in Greek newspapers sent from Athens to Chicago, freely translated, reads as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0844.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Lottery: For the benefit of the navy and the antiquarian societies for the year 1909. Tickets, 4 francs each. Every ticket is good for four drawings. Total prizes $200,000. First drawing Feb. 26, 1909; Second, June 28; third, October 25; fourth, December 31. Tickets are sold in the government sub-treasuries, banks, railway stations and newspaper offices. For any information apply to the office of the Minister of Finance. Signed: G. N. Kophinas, Chief Clerk to the Minister of Finance."</p>
   <p>Post-office Inspector James E. Steward declared that the post-office officials would investigate and take steps to prevent the circulation of Greek newspapers bearing lottery advertisements through the mails.</p>
   <p>"I did not know any such papers were being circulated," he said. "It is clearly in violation of the law and we will stop it at once."</p>
   <p>District Attorney Sims declared he would investigate the alleged sale of lottery tickets among immigrants who have recently come to Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0845.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>John Cocalis, manager of the Oriental Restaurant, said that the reports must be exaggerated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
