<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-07-08">July 8, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Our National Representation in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0325</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0325.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-07-08">July 8, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">OUR NATIONAL REPRESENTATION IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Once before in this column we aired the matter of our national representation in America, and we remarked with sorrow that it fails to measure up to the needs of the Greek nation and of American Hellenism. What impelled us to deal with this matter was the indifference which we have observed on the part of the Greek consul in Chicago, Mr. Depasta, and of the Greek ambassador at Washington, Mr. Simopoulos, to every Greek movement in this country and their aloofness from the life of American Greeks.</p>
   <p>This phenomenon has never before been observed in America. None of the predecessors of Mr. Depasta or of Mr. Simopoulos ever failed to display their interest in matters which touched the Greeks in America; they never failed to take active part in the community and social life of the American Greeks; and in many other ways they showed their interest in Greek-American affairs.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0326.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It appears, unfortunately, that this situation is the result of no superficial circumstance; this phenomenal indifference of the official representatives of Greece may be traced to the Central Service of the Greek foreign office, if we are to judge by an article in the Open Forum of Athens, written by a Greek statesman, Mr. G. Exentare. An excerpt from the article follows:</p>
   <p>"Very sad to relate, it is apparent to the most superficial observer that the staff of the foreign office fails to measure up to the task of performing its duties. Except for a very few, who might be counted on the fingers of one hand, those who have secured employment there in late years are inferior beyond description, - without seal, without diligence, and without serious appreciation of their duties. The polite rivalry which accompanies a warlike period, eagerness to serve, and respect for superiors and subordination to them are all absolutely lacking in these public servants. Discipline has become lax. The new employees, who obtained their positions with exceptional ease, lack even the most elementary equipment; they are as ignorant as they are inexperienced; they display unusual indifference to their duties and not seldom become insolent to their superiors and to the public.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0327.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The oldest employees neglect their work; and as for the rest - dizzy and confused with the frequent changes caused by party combats - they cling to their positions as seafarers cling to a wrecked boat. They are preoccupied with their anxiety to hold on to their jobs and therefore avoid as much as possible all argument and antagonism."</p>
   <p>From this clear picture it is apparent that those observations which we have made at other times with reference to the representatives of Greece in America are more applicable to the Central Service of the ministry, and that we are not the only ones who complain about conditions. Obviously, if the Central Service was really what it should be, it would not have tolerated for so many years this indifference in its representatives, especially in America, where the personages of Mr. Consul and Mr. Ambassador might play a great part in encouraging national efforts toward the improvement of public affairs.</p>
   <p>Mr. Exentare in his article gives us the reason for that attitude toward American Greeks which we have observed in the Greek consul in Chicago and in the Greek ambassador at Washington, and we see these influences in operation today in the Greek foreign office, where disorderliness and indifference are the least of their evil effects.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0328.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As things are, the best that Mr. Pangalos can do for the present is to get rid of both the embassy and the consulate in America. By doing this he will at least save thousands of dollars, for under existing circumstances it makes no difference whether he has a consulate in Chicago or not. Certainly, if the Central Service itself of the Greek foreign office is incapable of performing its duties, it is only natural to expect the same incompetence in the foreign representatives of Greece.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
