<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-03-12">March 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Turks Also Want to Fly Correspondence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-03-12">March 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE TURKS ALSO WANT TO FLY CORRESPONDENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Constantinople. February. Kemal, in the historic address with which he proclaimed the opening of the National Congress, made a statement intentionally absurd. Having eulogized the doutful value of the treaty of Locarno, he said: "From what I have demonstrated to you, gentlemen, you understand that we must lay serious emphasis on the importance of our national defense. The strength of our army, our navy, and our air force is the main factor destined to insure Turkey's advance on the road to peace and reconstruction!"</p>
   <p>.... Foremost are the army, the navy and the air force! Everything else is secondary and may thrive on crumbs from the military table. Characteristic of the military spirit prevailing in Kemal's state is the following incident:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0350.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One of the cinema theaters of Peran was to exhibit an American film, "Chaplin the Soldier."....To the disappointment of Charlie Chaplin fans, it was prohibited.</p>
   <p>This morning with my tea I sip in the terrific conclusion of the editorial of Dzoumhuriet. "Only arms will insure peace," it says.</p>
   <p>Among other things the airplane fascinates Kemal. On the day before yesterday we commemorated the flyers who lost their lives in the last war; there were military parades and many speeches for the occasion as well as many write-ups. It was a day of apotheosis for the airplane. The war minister Rezep Bey made a significant speech in Angora, (Quotations from his speech follow - Translator) which had loud repercussions in the press. But the most important and revealing statement was the article of the representative Phalih Rifki in the semi-official Hakimet Milie of Angora.</p>
   <p>The title is poetic, "Our Wings," but the contents are sanguinary and anti-poetic, as is the case with every war-fancy. "The whole world," it reads, "recognizes today that in future wars the weapons of air and <pb facs="5422062_6_0351.jpg" n="3"/>of chemistry will play the primary role. The chemist and the air fleet will not try to bomb a location or a ship or to find out the movements of the enemy. It will be a question of how to discover an air contrivance so powerful as to asphyxiate and poison large masses of human beings, whole cities, whole populations. This gas will flow over tremendous areas, will flow into residences, and into cellars hermitically sealed, and will overtake unfortunate human creatures in their places of refuge no matter how remote.</p>
   <p>...."We Turks do not lack courage and initiative. We began very late. We woke up at the moment when our needs were serious and our means insignificant. Now we must organize our air defense in the shortest possible time; the whole nation must bend to the task, collectively and individually."</p>
   <p>But lack of chemists casts a shadow over the dream of the bloodthirsty Turkish representative. "But our chemists?" he exclaims, "our factories that will supply our means of offense and of defense? Where are our technicians to handle these matters? Where are the Turkish chemists?"</p>
   <p>Certainly we are not the ones to answer.</p>
   <p>Th. Athanasiadis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
