<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1920-03-13">Mar. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The New Theseus</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1920-03-13">Mar. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW THESEUS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Peace Conference in Europe lost its idealogy in a labyrinth of intrigue and self-interest. The Minotaur of European diplomacy, is about to attack Greece and Armenia. Their only hope is in the appearance of a Theseus. And he has already appeared. He comes from Athens with logic, patriotism, bravery, and brilliance as weapons. He stands fighting for the reign of truth and justice in Greece, both in domestic and foreign affairs.</p>
   <p>The man who faced King George in Crete and gained the freedom of his native island; the diplomat, who told the truth to the Greek populace, despite the bitterness of that truth; the Christian who united the Balkan countries against the Turkish tyranny, and who through sacrifices preserved peace among them; the man who preferred to gain the enmity of a monarch, in preference to sacrificing his country's honor; the man who answered the German envoy in Athens with these words: "Gentlemen, my country is far too small to commit so great a crime."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0603.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This man is Eleftherios Venizelos. He has seen large nations treading upon the face of justice; he was present at the sacrifice of ideals and obligations; he saw friends turn against each other and their countries; he saw the depravity and injustice prevailing in European diplomacy. Nevertheless, he did not lose confidence in truth. He still believes that truth can be found even in politics.</p>
   <p>For the last twelve months he has attended the Peace Conference. He prevented an Italo-Greek War and defended Armenia. In world affairs he sided with the American policies.</p>
   <p>Venizelos stands with his eyes fixed on a future diplomacy based upon truth and integrity. Calm and prophetic, he visits the diplomatic circles of Europe, endeavoring to ensure peace not only for the present, but to put it on a granite basis, for the future.</p>
   <p>The young Theseus from Athens went to London armed with unwavering faith in the victory of justice. Up to this moment he has not lost this faith. He believes America and England will support his ideas, which are in the favor of the Angle-Saxon race.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
