<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1925-11-28">Nov. 28, 1925</date>, p. 2
<title level="a">Appeal of the Chicago Consul-General of Greece for Contributions for Air Defense of Greece.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0374</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0374.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1925-11-28">Nov. 28, 1925</date>, p. 2
<title level="a">APPEAL OF THE CHICAGO CONSUL-GENERAL OF GREECE FOR CONTRIBUTIONS FOR AIR DEFENSE OF GREECE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The establishing of air defense in Athens is known to you all. Mother Greece, as well as other nations, realized the importance of air defense, and despite her financial problems she established a school of aviation for national air defense, at which officers of the army and navy are specially trained for that purpose. She placed a large order for aeroplanes with the recently established Greek aeroplane factory and also a large order abroad.</p>
   <p>The Committee of National Air Defense, knowing the tremendous financial burden of the government which was brought about by the refugees' problem, laid down plans to raise money by contributions from the people of Greece and Greeks all over the world. Each city, county and state of Greece is contributing money for one or more aeroplanes for national defense.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0375.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Hence the Greeks of America are requested to shoulder part of this farreaching aviation program.</p>
   <p>I, not only as a representative of Greece but as a Greek to a Greek, invoking your racial sentiments, and in the name of our common cause, appeal to your generosity for contributions, knowing in advance that the reverberating voice of our Greece, reaching all of us in every part of the world, will be heeded and that a response will be made.</p>
   <p>I, as a representative here of Greece, feel proud that my fellow-Greeks always took the lead in national and racial affairs and exemplified themselves to the rest of our brother-Greeks all over the country.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0376.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Owing to my personal knowledge of the patriotism, munificence, capability and energetic efforts of the leaders of our communities, lodges and organizations, I deem it a privilege and an honor to request these leaders and their respective councils to take the initiative as they see fit, and begin collections of contributions from our brother Greeks, who are always ready and willing to respond to the wishes and needs of our beautiful Greece to protect her dignity, independence and borders from invasion.</p>
   <p>Assuring you of my wholehearted and undivided support and service to the aforesaid cause, I beg to remain.</p>
   <p>With great esteem,</p>
   <p>Geo. Depastas,</p>
   <p>Consul-General of Greece.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
