<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1920-06-12">June 12, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Greece Has a Future and Must Be Led by Capable Men</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0593</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0593.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1920-06-12">June 12, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">GREECE HAS A FUTURE AND MUST BE LED BY CAPABLE MEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few weeks ago, we received news from San Remo that Greece had been enlarged to include Epiros, Macedonia, Thrace, Nisos, and Mikrasia. This is the realization of our national dreams, and those of our forefathers.</p>
   <p>This is repayment for our country's tears and spiritual bondage during the five hundred years of Turkish tyranny.</p>
   <p>Now that the repayment has been made, we are faced with the great problem of governing and upholding our country through the future years. How are we to do this?</p>
   <p>The above question is the most important one existing for our country. Those five hundred years of slavery are only a moment in comparison with <pb facs="5422062_6_0594.jpg" n="2"/>the great task that faces us today and in the future. When a mansion is to be built, plans are required--when an army is to make a march, leaders are required--and so, when a new country is being organized, there is a need for leaders who are wise, brave, and experienced.</p>
   <p>Greeks! We are about to build a palace--not a hovel. We intend to build a ship that can sail in any sea of the world--not a canoe.</p>
   <p>There is a need for brave and educated men; not for those who pretend to know all--and yet know nothing. The leader of our country must be well-educated and progressive. Rallis, Skoulides, Gounaris, and Stratos [these are names of some of the followers of King Constantine]are not for us....the Turks govern themselves and others; the Bulgarians also; the Serbians are also capable of ruling. Then why can't the Greeks rule themselves and their protectorates with wisdom and success?</p>
   <p>Greece has a wonderful future. It will be a great one if every artisan, designer, and every scholar will undertake to help his own field. Bankers, <pb facs="5422062_6_0595.jpg" n="3"/>builders, merchants, professionals--all must unite their efforts to sponsor the progressive spirit, and to conquer ignorance and backwardness in our country.</p>
   <p>Stratos is not capable of ruling new Greece, neither is Gounaris, Stratigos, or Rallis. Men must be found who possess integrity and intelligence. They must be unbiased and think in terms of sincerity, not in terms of hate and greed. Hate and greed are personal, and not national feelings. Such feelings cause a country to wither and deteriorate.</p>
   <p>Fellow-Greeks--if you wish Greece to progress--throw off your mental shackles, remove all thoughts of Constantine from your hearts, place your hands over your hearts and swear to help the progress of Greece along the road laid out by our forefathers.</p>
   <p>Venizelos did his duty. Find another like him to carry on the work. Beware, however, of many of our Greek politicians, who are really undertakers. There <pb facs="5422062_6_0596.jpg" n="4"/>exist many who are national grave diggers. We pronounce a curse upon anyone who would choose them. The country needs men, and men need a country. The Greeks have fine men--make an effort to find them. If you do not do so, our nation will be ruined by bad foundations, and it will fall into the hands of those who can bring only death and disaster.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
