<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-02-03">Feb. 3, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Message from the Greek Consul General in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-02-03">Feb. 3, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A MESSAGE FROM THE GREEK CONSUL GENERAL IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.-3...........This message concerns the greeks who reside within the Chicago Greek consul general's jurisdiction, that is the greeks resident in the States of Illinois; Ohio, Kentucky, Minnesota, Iowa, Missouri, Knasas, Nebraska, North Dakota, and South Dakota. According to the Greek consular law all greek citizens who reside in America or in other foreign countries must register with their respective consulates and must also pay annual dues for their certificates of Greek citizenship (article 118 of the consular law and article 15 of law 764).</p>
   <p>The fulfillment of the above requirements is not only the duty of every greek citizen who is devoted to his country and respects its laws but is also beneficial to citizens of Greece for many reasons. Unfortunately up to the present time many of our fellow-citizens, through carelessness have not fulfilled these requirements. But in the crisis through which our country is now passing, when it is facing many economic problems, it is the supreme duty of all who are devoted to their native land to hasten to fulfill their legal obligations and materially to assist their country.</p>
   <p>I am making an appeal to the noble and patriotic feelings of Greek citizens who are under my jurisdiction. Since by reason of their remote location and the pressure of business they cannot come to the greek consulate in Chicago, I have made up the <pb facs="5422062_6_0491.jpg" n="2"/>form printed below and those who cannot come to the consulate may draw up a similar form and mail it to us in order that they may be enrolled in the general consulate's register, and in return we will mail to them certificates of Greek citizenship. At the same time those who heretofore have not paid dues for certificates of citizenship are required to pay for the years 1922 and 1923, an amount of $6.60, that is, $3.30 per year.</p>
   <p>The period within which this payment must be made expires at the end of February, 1923; after that date there will be a penalty of $10.00 in addition to the amount above mentioned (article 118 of the consular law). Greek citizens who reside in Ohio, Michigan, Missouri, or Kansas may send their forms filled out to the Sub -Consulates of the districts in which they reside. All greek citizens are required to renew each year their certificates of Greek citizenship and to pay their annual dues. We therefore request that each year hereafter, beginning with January, 1924, they will remit their annual dues by postal money order.</p>
   <p>I place my confidence in your noble feelings, in your love for our beloved native land, and in your devotion to it.</p>
   <p>I remain with love and highest regards,</p>
   <p>The Consul General,</p>
   <p>V. Mamonas.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0492.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The form which you must fill out and send in includes the following information:</p>
   <p>1. Name.</p>
   <p>2. City or village of birth.</p>
   <p>3. Township or community.</p>
   <p>4. County.</p>
   <p>5. Date of birth.</p>
   <p>6. Trade or profession.</p>
   <p>7. Present address.</p>
   <p>8. Single.</p>
   <p>9. Married.</p>
   <p>10. Name of wife.</p>
   <p>11. Children(name and age of each).</p>
   <p>12. Signature and date.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
