<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-05-17">May 17, 1930</date><title level="a">Important Facts of the Excursion of the American Legionnairies to Greece.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0121</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0121.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1930-05-17">May 17, 1930</date><title level="a">IMPORTANT FACTS OF THE EXCURSION OF THE AMERICAN LEGIONNAIRIES TO GREECE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4 The news, of the forthcoming excursion to Greece of the American Legions Hellenic Post and of Greek Veterans of the 1912-1922 wars, is received very enthusiastically by the Government of Greece and by the general public.</p>
   <p>Through the fact of the Hellenic Post being a part of the American Degion, and the excursion presenting an American national aspect, the Government and people of Greece are preparing to receive the excursionists with honors and open arms.</p>
   <p>The Government called a special meeting of the ministers and speedily a lot of 20,000 square feet in the center of the capitol, for the American Legion's building. The corner stone of this building will be laid in a brilliant ceremony by the coming Legionnaires. At the ceremony each and every veteran will be honored with a special medal given by the Government of Greece, as a token of the idealism of the two countries.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0122.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Further more the Government will dispatch a part of the Greek Navy to the open sea to greet and escort the Legionnaires to the port of Phaleron. Preparations for the enthusiastic reception reveal the importance of the event.</p>
   <p>The United States Legation and the Allied Ambassadors will take an active part in the reception of the Legionnaires.</p>
   <p>Indeed it would be a fantastic spectacle to see 2,500 American soldiers of the Army and Navy marching on the streets of Athens and headed by American Generals and Admirals.</p>
   <p>Touching as it may be the presence of the veterans of the 1912-1922 wars, with the rest of the excursionists and with the whole country, will celebrate the closing festivities of the Centennial of Greek Independence.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0123.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Hellenic Post, with the cooperation of the Tourists Exchange, Pharos, of New York, has chartered the boat, Saturnia, which is considered one of the best, for the forthcoming excursion.</p>
   <p>The reduced round trip fare, which is only for the Legionnaires and veterans of the Greek wars, includes the entire expense of the seven day sojourn in Greece. The Post further succeeded, due to the generosity of the American and Greek Governments, in having free passports issued for the excursionists. It succeeded in having free hotel accommodation and meals for one week in Athens, free service of automobiles, free buses, free small boats, and everything free for visits to historic and important places in and around Athens. And above all a free American uniform for the Legionnaires.</p>
   <p>The Greek Government and the people look at this coming excursion as a good will expedition, tending to render the contact of the two countries more friendly than ever.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0124.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The event is looked on with enthusiasm due to the fact that an American man of war will beautify the waters of Greece and the populace is buying American flags to decorate houses in honor and as a friendly gesture towards the United States which is highly esteemed and truly loved by every man,woman and child of Greece. American greatness and American idealism are engraved in the hearts of all Greeks.</p>
   <p>Legionnaires and Greek veterans all over the country who wish to participate in the excursion communicate with the Hellenic Post of the American Legion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
