<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-01-19">Jan. 19, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A Greek Banker in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0247</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0247.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-01-19">Jan. 19, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A GREEK BANKER IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have in our community a Greek banker, Mr. Karydias, a high ranking clerk of the Ionian Bank, who is touring America for the purpose of studying the economic conditions of the Greeks in this country and their banking relations with the Greek banks.</p>
   <p>The question of the economic relations of the Greeks of America is of such importance that it ought to have attracted the attention of responsible bankers in Greece. The economic interest between the Greeks of America and Greece could as is known be greatly promoted the incalculable benefit of both.</p>
   <p>Greece today more than ever before needs foreign capital and offers many opportunities to all who can invest either small or big sums regardless. Much capital was attracted to and invested in Greece for public works, from which big profits are foreseen for investors.</p>
   <p>We cannot see why the Greeks of America could not avail themselves of these opportunities <pb facs="5422062_6_0248.jpg" n="2"/>and do what the foreigners are doing.</p>
   <p>But for the money of the Greeks of America to take that direction, it is necessary to make their economic bonds with Greece tighter. The bankers are most suitable to serve as go-betweens, for they are in the position to present sound information regarding enterprises in Greece.</p>
   <p>We have dwelt upon this most important subject repeatedly. The Greek government, however, judging by its representatives here, may think of anything but availing itself of the benefits to be derived from such a proposition on a large scale.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we consider the coming of a banker from one of the most dependable banking institutions of Greece a happy event, and Mr. Karydias with his experience and wisdom will realize, undoubtedly, the great economic power of Hellenism in America. He will understand what interests of importance will be served by getting the economic bonds of Greece and Greeks of America closer together.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
