<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1921-10-29">Oct. 29, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Venizelos Visits Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0552</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0552.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1921-10-29">Oct. 29, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">VENIZELOS VISITS CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At 10:45 A. M., last Wednesday, Eleftherios Venizelos, his wife, and his staff, arrived in Chicago on the Grand Central.</p>
   <p>The liberal leader and former prime minister of Greece was met at the station by a crowd of 10,000, bearing banners and flags; some of them had come early in the morning in an effort to see their idol. The American press even commented on their loyalty and patience.</p>
   <p>So unexpected was the arrival of Venizelos that hotel accommodations had not even been arranged for, and a suite was gotten at the aristocratic Blackstone Hotel at the very last minute. The Hotel gave him a reception that is usually reserved for royalty. His rooms were decorated with fragrant and beautiful flowers.</p>
   <p>Mr. Venizelos insisted upon privacy and a minimum of attention, as he wished to be treated as an ordinary traveler.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0553.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The people were so anxious to see him that Venizelos and his party had to leave by a side entrance and make their way to the hotel. They were discovered, however, and the people cheered him with "Zito (long live) our Liberator, our Father, our Saviour."</p>
   <p>Order was restored only upon the appearance of the benign face of their idol. At his side was the Metropolitan Meletios of Athens, who blessed the multitude with such tenderness and reverence, that handkerchiefs were much in evidence. The party then proceeded to the hotel.</p>
   <p>After lunch, he received a few callers, and then went for a walk through the large department stores, where he was recognized because his pictures had been published so often in the American Press.</p>
   <p>At night, a committee arrived to plead with Mr. Venizelos, that he allow a dinner to be given in his honor. But their efforts were in vain.</p>
   <p>The next day he visited places of interest in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
