<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1927-11-26">November 26, 1927</date><title level="a">The Deeds of Mrs. Sikelianos.-</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0258</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0258.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1927-11-26">November 26, 1927</date><title level="a">The Deeds of Mrs. Sikelianos.-</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago will have an opportunity to see, hear, and admire, Mrs. Sikelianos in person.</p>
   <p>The Honorable Lady, who comes from a well known and well to do family of New York, is now a citizen of Greece, is highly educated, and master of both the English and Greek languages. For the love of Greece, she left this country and became a Greek citizen. She came back to America recently attired in national costumes, going everywhere, giving lectures without making collection or accepting donations.</p>
   <p>Her object is to regenerate Ancient Greek Civilization, and inspire enthusiasm and respect for Greece, not only amongst the New Generation of Greeks but amongst all in America. By doing this she gives a moral benefit to the Greeks in America, and material benefit to Greece.</p>
   <p>Her lectures created a desire for many Americans and Greeks to visit the soil of the Mother of Light, (civilization) thus creating an abundant ingress of gold in the business life of Greece, and according to information we recieved from Greece, you hear the American language spoken, in practically every street <pb facs="5422062_6_0259.jpg" n="2"/>of Athens...</p>
   <p>Let us not forget that our Greece is poor, and needs gold, and every visitor and tourist that comes to Greece is, either directly or indirectly a benefactor to Greece and her sons the world over.</p>
   <p>Greeks of Chicago and vicinity do not fail by any means, to hear our benefactress, Mrs. Sikeliamos,</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
