<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-01-22">Jan. 22, 1931</date><title level="a">Marika Cotopouli Strives to Give Greece New Golden Age in Drama</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Irma Kraft</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0051</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0051.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-01-22">Jan. 22, 1931</date><title level="a">MARIKA COTOPOULI STRIVES TO GIVE GREECE NEW GOLDEN AGE IN DRAMA</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Irma Kraft</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- The theater in Greece has much to contribute to modern drama. The Western world has little knowledge of its aims and its developments, its desire to approach the standards of its golden years. Modern Greece aims at the resurrection of these standards. A few of its standard bearers seem to be slowly approaching their aims.</p>
   <p>Among the leaders in this movement is Marika Cotopouli, director of her own theater in Athens. At this theater Cotopouli produces modern and classic plays, trains young actors, designs scenery and costumes and guides the taste of the Greeks toward her goal. Her avid curiosity concerning the plays of all countries has brought to Athens more than 500 dramas from the theaters of the world. She wants to place these plays in juxtaposition with the dramas of her native land and by contrast to cause the Greek audiences to see the value of their heritage.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0052.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Her Athenian audiences do not always like her choice of modern plays. Often they feel the inadequacy of the works of modern playwrights but they are true to their classics, and their loyalty to Sophocles and Aristophanes never wanes.</p>
   <p>When a modern experiment has failed Mme. Cotopouli has only to announce "Elektra" or "Iphigenia" to be given in the great open Stadium at Athens and an audience of 15,000 appears. With contentment they relieve their classic dramas, knowing that in these dramas all of life has been explored. Yet Mme. Cotopouli continues to experiment. She feels the need of acquaintance with modern world developments. She feels the need for her own art and so she produced "The Adding Machine" as well as "La Tendress" by Henry Battaille, "Journey's End" as well as "Le Simoun" by Lenormand. She wants her theater to be an everchanging Kaleidoscope of new and old, of tragedy and comedy, a fluid thing in which the thought of today ranges its glib assurance alongside the decisiveness of yesterday.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0053.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mme. Cotopouli is in New York on the first stage of her world journey. She has brought her twenty-five actors and settings for many plays. She will go from here to London, Paris, Berlin and Moscow. She has come on a journey to bring her own wares and to digest the wares of others. She is studying English with the same intensity with which she mastered French. Yet always at the back of her consciousness is the aim of bringing back rich gifts to Greece. Greece is her altar, and it was of the Greek theater that we talked as she rested a few hours before her performance of the Hofmanstahl "Elektra."</p>
   <p>"Of all the people in the world--and I have been in almost all countries--" she remarked, "the Greeks seem to take their theater most seriously. It is a very large part of their lives. Greek critics are the most severe in the world. Their standard is perfection. If they do not like a play or a production they are cruel-ruthless. They notice every detail and they demand the best.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0054.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Yet the public, also, has its own method of criticism. If it does not like a play or a production the audience says so at once, while the play is being performed. They cry aloud against an actor, or the dialogue, or the set, or they get up and leave the theater and demand their money be returned. They argue aloud and often quarrel between the acts in the aisles and in the lobby. They are tremendously in earnest and want to know if the authors opinions are sound.</p>
   <p>"Yes, our public and our cities are difficult to please and they impose on us the necessity of always doing our best."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
