<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-12-15">Dec. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Rise of Democracy in the Homeland (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0436</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0436.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-12-15">Dec. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE RISE OF DEMOCRACY IN THE HOMELAND (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The monarchic propaganda continues preparing new plots, so that the Greek people may start new conspiracies and revolts thus to cause the intervention of some foreign power and the postponement of elections.</p>
   <p>The armed convention of the social outcasts last Sunday was a lamentable phenomenon of their social and moral downfall; these people do not possess any form of virtue, not even that which distinguishes man from animal.</p>
   <p>With all this, tomorrow will bring that historic day when the Greek people will take the turn to reach for liberty. We hope that the Greek people, with their vote, will prove that, inspired by the ancient Greek spirit of freedom, they will raise the flag of democracy.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0437.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thus they will show that they remember our glorious Greek history and national pride and that they will cease to be playthings for a bloodthirsty foreign dynasty and foreign propaganda, and that they cannot be influenced anymore by the royal bugbear of Europe with which different politicians have tried to scatter fear.</p>
   <p>Greece needs the friendship and the esteem of nations and not that of kings, whose meseonic thrones are being shaken by the weight of stupidity, insanity, demoralization as well as by the weight of conspiratory tasks and national crimes.</p>
   <p>Yet many politicians have been found who submitted to hysterical convulsions and very touching emotions without knowing what impression the declaration of Greek Democracy would produce upon the Sultan of Zoulos, the Emir of Afganistan, Serbia, England and France.</p>
   <p>Let us first examine the effect of a Declaration of Democracy in Greece upon Serbia. The Serbian people also inspired by democratic ideas are ready to declare democracy and will salute Greek Democracy although they have a king.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0438.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Serbian people will be very glad to see the dynasty of the Glicksburgs come to an end in Greece because they have not forgotten that the late king of Greece, Constantine, tore the sacred treaty of Greece with Serbia by urging the Ambassador of Bulgaria in Athens to strike from the rear an assassinating and fatal blow at his own ally, Serbia.</p>
   <p>It is also true that the king of Serbia, Alexander, went to Paris to visit the President of Democratic France, Mr. Millerand and the Premier Mr. Poincore, with the plea that they should retain his brother-in-law, King George of Greece on the throne. In other words, Serbia is also being threatened by a declaration of democracy. Is it possible that the President of French Democracy is willing to betray democracy?</p>
   <p>On the other hand the English people, being democratic and liberal, would obtain a very good impression of Greece if its government was democratic. We also believe that the king of England will not try to defend the royal stables of Athens. It is also well known that Lloyd George of England has protested against any royal intervention in the problem of the government of Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0439.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>With conditions being as they are, we salute the Sunday of tomorrow as the starting point of a new national life and new hopes for a national regeneration.</p>
   <p>Mr. Salopoulos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
