<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-07-13">July 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek National Lloyd</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0655</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0655.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-07-13">July 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK NATIONAL LLOYD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are very pleased to learn that a large maritime insurance company has been established in Piraeus, Greece, with branch offices in Chicago. The official name of the company is National Greek Lloyd. The corporate capital investment of this new insurance company is 50,000,000 drachmas. (Translator's note: Exchange rate at this time: one dollar to five drachmas.)</p>
   <p>This important and rich enterprise has attracted the attention not only of the rich but also of the people at large. Requests for the opportunity of subscribing to the stipulated investment capital of fifty million drachmas surpassed by far the number anticipated.</p>
   <p>Although under the present war conditions about two-thirds of the ships of the once great and world-wide Greek merchant marine has been sent to the bottom of the ocean, torpedoed by the Kaiser's relentless and unsparing submarine warfare, <pb facs="5422062_6_0656.jpg" n="2"/>nevertheless we hope that the Greek maritime trade will recover and progress by leaps and bounds.</p>
   <p>We all know that in spite of our own King - Generalissimo Von Constantine's love for his "kind and tender" brother-in-law, the German Kaiser, "by divine right Emperor of Pan-Germany," the latter was kind enough to torpedo and destroy our prosperous sea trade and ships. We know, however, that the day is not far when the world will crush this absolutism and barbarity, that we and all other nations which have sustained so many frightful losses will be avenged. It is perhaps needless to inform our public of the serious losses that Greek merchants, exporters and importers in Chicago have suffered because of the torpedoing and sinking of merchant vessels on the high seas.</p>
   <p>We all admit and admire the unprecedented success of this newly established company. It will be one of the greatest and most indispensable financial institutions of Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0657.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>By the participation of the general public as stockholders in the National Greek Lloyd, it is proved that the people in Greece, in America, and particularly in Chicago, have absolute and implicit faith in the financial institutions which serve the interests of the nation at large. This is the way in which security, confidence, development, and business profits and prosperity are assured.</p>
   <p>Saloniki wishes the Greek National Lloyd success and great progress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
