<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-01-24">Jan. 24, 1928</date><title level="a">A Ray of Light from Greece Greece Points the Real Way Towards Peace</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_6_0245</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0245.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-01-24">Jan. 24, 1928</date><title level="a">A RAY OF LIGHT FROM GREECE GREECE POINTS THE REAL WAY TOWARDS PEACE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- Capt. Constantine Melas, retired, has been in Chicago since yesterday with the purpose of securing (as the American newspapers write), the cooperation of Americans interested in "World Peace," as to the organizing of a "Young Peoples Association" in Greece, whose purpose will be to join together the hope-bearing youth of the world into a strong movement that will result in bringing about peace.</p>
   <p>Mr. Melas, as conditions reveal, has in mind that it is impossible for peace to come through diplomatic activities. Diplomacy seeks a "formula" for peace, Mr. Melas quoted. It only succeeds in building a greater navy, creating larger armies and declaring more new wars. Permanent peace will come by educating the youth. Only by educating the young people all over the world to love peace and to resist the plots of diplomacy (servant of material interests), the world will be able to profit through a real and permanent peace, according to Mr. Melas' belief.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_6_0246.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Greece was the first nation in history to hold the 'eternal torch of light' of real civilization," said Mr. Melas.</p>
   <p>He then proceeded to uncover to us "Eternal Greece" as the nation that is once more resuming the "Torch of Knowledge" and "Civilization", and calling for all the nations to follow her in the struggle to mark the way for the establishment of Peace and Love.</p>
   <p>"Greece," Mr. Melas said, "has started this movement with the Young Peoples Association, but Greece in this act needs also the cooperation of the American people. The young people of European nations might refuse to follow one purely Greek organization, but they will enter into it when other nations are represented. We hope that we will have the cooperation of all the nations in this movement for 'World Peace'."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
