<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-08-05">August 5, 1878</date><title level="a">Letter from Congressman Lorenz Brentano to the Editor of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0917</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0917.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I V</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-08-05">August 5, 1878</date><title level="a">LETTER FROM CONGRESSMAN LORENZ BRENTANO TO THE EDITOR OF THE ILLINOIS STAATS-ZEITUNG.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Permit me, through the columns of your esteemed paper, to address a few words to my German fellow-citizens and especially to those who are living in the third district.</p>
   <p>I have brought an action for slander against Richard Michaelis, the editor of the German evening paper, Freie Presse....</p>
   <p>Last spring, two years since I returned from Dresden, where I possessed as highly esteemed a position as ever an American Consul in a foreign country has held, the then Minister of War, Don Cameron, wanted my position for his protege, a former rebel officer and relative of the famed rebel, Ambassador Mason, who was captured on the English steamer Trent, and so I had to leave....</p>
   <p>During the summer, without my knowledge, a movement was started to elect me to Congress...</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0918.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I would not have been a German, if the German national virtue, pale jealousy had not immediately filled the chest of many a Teuton; how can a German be called to any eminent position here without causing a number of his dear fellow countrymen no end of pain and sorrow, that just this one and not they themselves should have received this honor....</p>
   <p>I entered the campaign under the most adverse conditions... But the most critical thing was the mood of the Germans on the North Side. The discontent with Grant's administration had reached its culmination point. The Republican Presidential candidate could not awaken either enthusiasm or confidence. "Tilden and Reform", was the battle cry with which the German words went into the fight and remained master of the field. That major power in election campaigns the Staats-Zeitung, which had supported the candidacy of my opponent two years ago and had gained success for him, could not give me energetic support in the measure, which I badly needed.</p>
   <p>In spite of the secret intrigues of invidious personal enemies, I not only concentrated the entire Republican vote on me, but in addition, I received <pb facs="5418474_4_0919.jpg" n="3"/>almost three hundred votes more than the Republican Presidential candidate.... Hardly had I returned to this place when the abuses and calumniations again started. The editor of the Republican Freie Presse did not have enough space in that paper for abuse, and so he writes every morning in the Democratic Volksfreund....</p>
   <p>A humiliating sensation creeps upon me, when I look at these yellow filthy rags Freie Presse and Volksfreund. You may travel from the Canadian border to the shores of the Pacific, visit every city in which the German element is represented, and no where in the Union will you find a newspaper containing such a flood of vulgarity and meanness as are evidenced in Chicago by these scoundrels. In no other city of the Union could such sheets protract their miserable existence, even for a few weeks. It seems as if the times of a victor Wilhelm Frohlich had come back. Even at that, this man who finally ended his life in his own filth in a New York police station, was at least consistent in politics. But here the same subject edits simultaneously, a Republican evening, and a Democratic morning paper. What would they say in our old fatherland, what would they think of us, if they saw these filtny characters, products of the art of printing.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0920.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>I, unlike my slanderers, have no newspaper at my disposal, and have no choice but to appeal to the protection of the law, and so I am sueing the slanderer Richard Michaelis for libel in the district court.</p>
   <p>He now can ruin me for all time, if he can prove that I accepted even one cent of bribery, but if he cannot prove it, he will stamp himself as an infamous and shameless scoundrel....</p>
   <p>In the House of Representatives there are at present only five members born in Germany, four of them in the Democratic, and only one in the Republican Party. To prevent the reelection of this one, lies and slander are employed, and the scoundrel, who is willing to use these infamous tactics, is named Richard Michaelis. It is now up to the Germans of the North Side to come out and show if they want to permit themselves to be influenced by liars and defamers.</p>
   <p>Signed</p>
   <p>L. Brentano</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
