<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-04-22">Apr. 22, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">German Democrats Protest against the Law of Compulsory School Attendance.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0281</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0281.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-04-22">Apr. 22, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN DEMOCRATS PROTEST AGAINST THE LAW OF COMPULSORY SCHOOL ATTENDANCE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The chief topic for discussion at the meeting last night of the German Democrats in Jung's Hall, 106 Randolph Street, was the school law for compulsory attendance, and the attitude which the Democrats should take in the coming election toward this law. After business matters were taken care of, L. Nettelhorst was requested to explain his views about this law to the audience. He briefly stated: "If one reads the English press, he may be inclined to believe that the Americans favor the law of compulsory attendance, but this is not the case. This idea is a foreign plant, and the Americans have little sympathy for it. A similar law has existed since 1872, but it was never executed. When, however, the Board of Education received many complaints that numerous children grew up without education, the proposal was made to enforce the old law. A committee was appointed to investigate the matter, and this law, which causes so much disturbance, was the result of its efforts. If I remember, correctly, the offensive clause was not in the original law." The speaker then refuted the assertions of the English newspapers, that the Germans protest against the instruction of English in public schools. He stated, that this is not true, and that every German desires that his children learn the English language, but he insists, that he be at liberty to have his children educated where he pleased. All favor compulsory <pb facs="5418474_4_0282.jpg" n="2"/>attendance of school and no reasonable person could have any objections against the study of the English language. But all parents should assert their liberty to send their children to the schools which they prefer, and which offer the greatest advantages.</p>
   <p>The next speaker, Max Stern, likewise commented upon the injustice of this law, because it would close all private and parochial schools. He expressed himself as in favor of compulsory attendance, but exhorted all to agitate against that law, and to demand an amendment, at least, so that parents can not be arrested for violating the law, if they send their children to private schools where they have sufficient opportunity to study English.</p>
   <p>Emil Hoechster adressed the assembled Democrats, and pointed out that this law has been enacted in order to close all German private and parochial schools. "It is necessary," he said, "that the Democrats take a definite stand against this law, in order to frustrate the plans of the narrow-minded nativists."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
