<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-11-07">Nov. 7, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[The Great Fire]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0701</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0701.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-11-07">Nov. 7, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[THE GREAT FIRE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After an absence of almost a year and a half Mr. A. G. Hesing arrived yesterday in the city. His arrival formed the topic of conversation and of the most lively satisfaction, like nothing else since the great five. The walk through street for him became a triumphal parade. Though tired from the journey, he had no moment for himself.</p>
   <p>The impression the ruins first made upon him was quite overwhelming. He had not formed an adequate mental picture of their extent, before seeing them. His own losses he finds greater, the cheerfulness and spirit of sacrifice of the population stronger and more admirable than he expected.</p>
   <p>One of his first acts was to go to the headquarters of the fire proof ticket. His entrance caused a prolonged demonstration and soon he was called upon to make a speech. Mr. Hesing said: "The news of the disaster found me in Salzburg. My first impression, after I had talked over my own losses with my family, was that it would be the greatest calamity if the Staats Zeitung should come out for any local political group. After the time of uncertainty on the ship I hastened <pb facs="5418474_4_0702.jpg" n="2"/>to the offices of the New York papers and was glad to see from the columns of the Staats Zeitung to my joy that just that had happened what I so deeply hoped for. My desire is that local politics may remain banished from Chicago as long as a single house that burnt down is not rebuilt. I am with all my heart and soul fire proof and hope for an overwhelming and brilliant victory of the truly fire proof ticket."</p>
   <p>His friends of the 15th Ward left Mr. Hesing no rest till he had promised them to address a meeting in the hall, corner of Cornell and Rose Streets. Mr. Hesing said among other things:</p>
   <p>"When I hoard that my house, my furniture, my business, my mortgages, my shares in insurance companies, etc. had been destroyed in the flames, I said to my family: 'I fear only one thing, namely that perhaps in spite of everything a partisan election will be held.' The Illinois Staats Zeitung has been from its inception on a strict party paper, and has never refused support to a regularly nominated candidate. I have been a voter since 1844, and have voted for <pb facs="5418474_4_0703.jpg" n="3"/>Whigs and, since she existence of the Republican Party, for Republicans. Tomorrow is the first time that I will vote for Democrats on the fire proof ticket; and I rejoice in being able to vote for such Democrats.</p>
   <p>After landing in New York I visited some of my creditors saying to yet funds to maintain my business on a large scale. They impressed on me the necessity to work is in Chicago with all my strength for Joe Medill as mayor, because one has everywhere confidence in Medill. Medill brings the city credit and money. Medill has an enviable national reputation.</p>
   <p>I don't want to belittle anybody, but I have warned this C. C. P. Holden more than 50 times and earnestly remonstrate with him that he must be a representative of the citizens and of the inhabitants of the west side, and not an agent of the Illinois Central Company monopoly. If the becomes mayor, he will subordinate the will being of Chicago to the special interests of the I. C. R.R. company. Medill has rare business efficiency. The Chicago Tribune has become, since he entered it, the best, the leading paper in the country. He never wanted the office of mayor. He proposed Mr. Henry Greenebaum and recommended him strongly as a very <pb facs="5418474_4_0704.jpg" n="4"/>useful man in the present circumstances. When it became evident that unanimity could not be reached on the nomination of Mr. Greenebaum, Medill let himself be prevailed upon to accept the nomination himself. It is up to you if you want to have an honest mayor or not.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
