<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-08-17">Aug. 17, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">German Republicans Organize to Support Fifer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0250</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0250.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-08-17">Aug. 17, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN REPUBLICANS ORGANIZE TO SUPPORT FIFER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the lofty protectorate of Fifer's adjutant general, "Doc" Jamieson and the State Central Committee which he commands, the German American Republican Union of Illinois was organized yesterday at the Grand Pacific Hotel. That this fight which the Germans wage against the promotion of the "Knownothings" who rule the Republican Party of Illinois at present, could not unite all the people of German origin under one banner was to be expected. We still have some Germans in Iowa, who did not vote for a Horace Boies, merely because he was a Democrat. And so, there will also be many Germans here, who fool themselves by believing that the leading minas, i. e., the Republican Party, is candid about the school question and having been faithful to the party before, as they or friends happened to derive benefits, public employment, etc., from chem or expect it in the future, it is but natural that they should subscribe to the Republican principles, even in this German fight. But, that we should find men at that Pacific Hotel meeting who fought Fifer's nomination only a few weeks and months ago, on the pretext that "no German with a conscience could vote for him", is amazing. It is not a surprise, however, if a Party-press uses all its power to fight a man and resorts to the most serious charges but after the nomination, extolds him to the sky. The Irish, the <pb facs="5418474_4_0251.jpg" n="2"/>professional politician, they do likewise, and execute such summersaults with great dexterity, the German prefers reasoning, he cannot favor one candidate today and tomorrow another, merely because he is the "party nominee".</p>
   <p>We can see the probable reason for the installation of a German Bureau which functions as a branch of the German Republican Union, it is no doubt their intention to regain the Germans and particularly the Lutherans who left the ranks by the thousands. If the Lutherans look into the significance of some leading names, then they will recognize a certain handy-man of Gov. Hoard and Spooner of Wisconsin who did yeoman service for the Bennett Law and in token of their esteem for his valient assistance, is about to be re-nominated as Wisconsin's Governor.</p>
   <p>Jamieson, Fifer, the nomination of ignoramuses, like Berry, Evans, Ferguson, Dorsey, Patton, a German Committee which boasts of such honorable gentlemen, and "played out" free booters with a Wisconsin past for a background, who may now doubt the sincerity of the Republicans?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
