<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1868-04-14">Apr. 14, 1868</date>.
<title level="a">Inspectors and Places of Registration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1868-04-14">Apr. 14, 1868</date>.
<title level="a">INSPECTORS AND PLACES OF REGISTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following is a list of places of registration and supervising inspectors of election.</p>
   <p>First Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Simon W. King, B. B. Tuttle, S. S. Benjamin. Place of registration--49 Wabash Avenue.</p>
   <p>First Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Charles F. Chilson, Peter Regitz, A. Banyon. Place of registration--98 South Wells Street.</p>
   <p>Second Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--W. T. Hancock, Isaac Howland, C. C. Garber. Place of registration--Southwest corner of State and Van Buren Streets.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0060.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Second Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Joseph Butler, William H. Young, Anton Berg. Place of registration--Northwest corner of Van Buren and Sherman Streets.</p>
   <p>Third Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--John D. Jennings, Joseph Pollock, George A. Meech. Place of registration--Taylor Street, in the rear of 504 State Street.</p>
   <p>Third Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--N. S. Bouton, E. R. Fowler, Dr. Hahn.</p>
   <p>Fourth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--George C. Morton, W. R. Schroeder, R. A. B. Mills. Place of registration--Buell House, southeast corner of State and 22nd Streets.</p>
   <p>Fourth Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--W. P. Comstock, Morgan, L. Keith, Samuel Boerger. Place of <pb facs="5418474_4_0061.jpg" n="3"/>registration--Old Engine Number Nine, corner Cottage Grove Avenue and 26th Street.</p>
   <p>Fifth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Henry Schmitz, Henry Morris, John Bannon. Place of registration--680 Archer Avenue.</p>
   <p>Fifth Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--James Clary, Thomas McMahon, Christian Freund. Place of registration--131 Archer Avenue.</p>
   <p>Sixth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--B. G. Gill, Nicholas Linden, William Jauncey. Place of registration--Maxwell Street Engine House.</p>
   <p>Sixth Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--W. W. Washburne, B. Weichselbaum, Anton Schaefer. Place of <pb facs="5418474_4_0062.jpg" n="4"/>registration--Home of Michal Fitzgerald, northwest corner of Polk and Canal Streets.</p>
   <p>Seventh Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--George Heart, Christian Tegtmeyer, Gotthard Schaaf. Place of registration--Corner of Mitchell and Union Streets.</p>
   <p>Seventh Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--A. Bruening, William Frazier, Edward Murphy. Place of registration--Blue Island Avenue Engine House.</p>
   <p>Eighth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--R.P. Deerickson, Michael Reddinger, Theodore Clowry. Place of registration--Corner of Blue Island Avenue and Sampson Street.</p>
   <p>Eighth Ward--Second District Inspectors--R. M. Guilford, William Boehmer, W. I. Onahan. Place of registration <pb facs="5418474_4_0063.jpg" n="5"/>--Home of James Bridgeman, Polk Street near Centre Avenue.</p>
   <p>Ninth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--H. Weinkopp, Samuel McColter, Daniel Worthington. Place of registration--Washingtonian Home.</p>
   <p>Ninth Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--A. St. John Campbell, Thomes McNamara, J. Pike. Place of registration--West Lake Street Engine House.</p>
   <p>Tenth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Pleasant Amick, A. G. Loewe, Hiram M. Chase. Place of registration --West Jackson Street Engine House, between Clinton and Jefferson Streets.</p>
   <p>Tenth Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Alvin Salisbury, George W. Bohannon, A. L. Amberg. Place of <pb facs="5418474_4_0064.jpg" n="6"/>registration--Engine House, corner Washington and Clinton Streets.</p>
   <p>Eleventh Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--William Weimann, George Morey, Henry Grace. Place of registration--Corner of Carroll and Desplaines Streets.</p>
   <p>Eleventh Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Peter McGinnis, A. L. Bennett, A. W. Klein. Place of registration--Corner of Halsted and West Indiana Streets.</p>
   <p>Twelfth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Charles H. Duensing, Louis Schultz, A. O. Bryan. Place of registration--336 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>Twelfth Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--James McGrath, W. G. Sturtevant, H. Thies. Place of registration-- <pb facs="5418474_4_0065.jpg" n="7"/>421 Elston Road.</p>
   <p>Thirteenth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Fred Bensinger, Eben Woodruff, Henry Rose. Place of registration--Engine House on Larrabee Street near North Avenue.</p>
   <p>Thirteenth Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Thomas Shirely, Peter Mahr, James Curry. Place of registration--(not given).</p>
   <p>Fourteenth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Robert Engel, Louis Berger, John McHughn. Place of registration--Corner of Larrabee Street and Clybourne Avenue.</p>
   <p>Fourteenth Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Henry Jahns, Philipp Steinmueller, John Ries. Place of registration--Fritz Frillmann's Saloon, corner of Division and Wells Streets.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0066.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Fifteenth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Henry Wendt, J. C. Grant, Dr. Boyer. Place of registration--North-west corner of Chicago Avenue and Wells Street.</p>
   <p>Fifteenth Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--William McClark, W. S. Golsen, Lorenz Baer. Place of registration --Corner of Rush Street and Chicago Avenue.</p>
   <p>Sixteenth Ward--First District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Joseph Briggs, Elihu Granger, Andrew Nelson. Place of registration --Corner of Franklin and Indiana Streets.</p>
   <p>Sixteenth Ward--Second District</p>
   <p>Inspectors--Fred Heintze, Martin Green, Patrick Smith. Place of registration --North Market Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
