<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-01-12">Jan. 12, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Traeger Takes Active Stand</title><title level="a" type="sub">Declares Himself in Favor of the Nomination of Carter H. Harrison</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1038</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1038.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-01-12">Jan. 12, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">TRAEGER TAKES ACTIVE STAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Declares Himself in Favor of the Nomination of Carter H. Harrison</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Former coroner and City Treasurer, John C. Traeger, declared himself in favor of the nomination of Carter H. Harrison, at a meeting of the newly founded Carter H. Harrison German-American club, held last night.</p>
   <p>Mr. Traeger presided, but refrained from mentining his own candidacy for City Treasurer in the Harrison party. This, regardless of the fact, that several speakers of the evening invited him, in flattering words, to accept the nomination.</p>
   <p>Then the former City Treasurer arrived at the meeting place, he was enthusiastically greeted by approximately 150 persons who attended.</p>
   <p>In the address delivered, Mr. Traeger, declared himself entirely in favor of <pb facs="5418474_4_1039.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Harrison's candidacy. Mr. Harrison, he said, carries on the same friendly attitude toward German suggestions and ideas, as his father did before him. Continuing his address, he said, when the State of his health and pressing business prompted him to refuse the candidacy for mayor, it was his firm intention, not to take any part in the present campaign.</p>
   <p>"But," he declared, "speaking to you, who represent the German-American citizens of Chicago, I feel inclined to come out of my self-imposed retirement, and assist in the campaign."</p>
   <p>Election of officers of the club, followed his address. Those elected were: Mr. Traeger as president; Mr. Charles Mr. Wellermann, vice-president, North Side; Mr. August Pfaff, vice-president West Side; Mr. Mathias Schmiedinger, vice-president, South Side; Mr. Theodore N. Philipp, secretary, and Mr. Oscar F. Mayer, treasurer.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1040.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the conclusion of campaign discussions, John C. Traeger's nomination for the office of City Treasurer, was proposed by Mr. A. C. Clapproth. Mr. Traeger, declined, however, to accept the honor, for reasons already stated, but he recommended another German-American for the nomination. Many protests were heard then-among them, the voices of the following speakers: Alderman Peter Reinberg, former Alderman Adam Meyer, Dr. George Leininger, Mr. William Rothmann, and Mr. Josef Weber, who insisted that no other candidate could receive as many German votes as Mr. Traeger. It was finally decided that a committee of ten men would meet with Mr. Traeger, for further discussion of the matter, today.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
