<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-08-18">Aug. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A Heavenly Virtue</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1338</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1338.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-08-18">Aug. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A HEAVENLY VIRTUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has been noticed with a great deal of satisfaction that Chicago has made a rather successful attempt to attract public attention again. This time, however, adding to the laurels of its good reputation. It has been suffering from just the reverse circumstances--without any let-up--for a considerable time. This city's reputation as a breeder of political and economic corruption and what not, has been preserved and perpetuated by our reformers, the reform-press, and by the get-rich-quick concerns.....But, despite this malicious publicity no startling news of corruption, or of this or that racket, have been added to Chicago's damaged reputation.</p>
   <p>Moreover, our city showed of late a marked change toward tameness as compared with the annals of its history of the past, and it is certainly far from leading the list of vice, as compared with other large and even smaller cities. Here is a hope that it will remain so. As already pointed out, a slight improvement of these conditions has been noticed <pb facs="5418474_4_1339.jpg" n="2"/>lately, namely, Chicago is showing the world in general that it still commands its attention, which manifests itself in sufficient ambition and progressive spirit indicated by one week's flying exhibitions held here recently, the spectacular display by our Army on the shores of Lake Michigan, the sane and safe July 4, the establishing of its own Grand Opera, etc. And more of these praiseworthy enterprises are to follow soon. For instance, the opening of a high-class German Theatre is a certain thing for the near future; the subway and the outer harbor are also receiving serious consideration.</p>
   <p>Irrespective of the highly redeemable points, the moral improvement of Chicago has not been properly acknowledged; its outstanding virtues have not found the well-deserved publicity. How about a prize contest? The Association of Commerce-that mighty connective that represented Chicago on many other occasions, either with pride or otherwise-should take the initiative to bring about a prize-winning contest, including cities large and small in the competition for the distinction of being the most virtuous one. A separate reward should be issued for each virtue. Chicago could, however, fearlessly enter into that contest <pb facs="5418474_4_1340.jpg" n="3"/>because it would undoubtedly prove the shining light and recapture its prestige at home as well as abroad. Our city would certainly be the recipient of several first prizes. On the other hand, despite the recent improvement of enterprise and progress, Chicago could not pride itself with reaching the pinnacle. For the ability of the city administration, not much can be said, neither can much be said in favor of the outward cleanliness of the city. But Chicago would be awarded the grand prize for its predominant spirit: "Live, and let Live," and for its kindness and consideration at all times. Our almost childish faith would also be outstanding, but the grand prize of honor for patience could positively be awarded to none other than Chicago.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
