<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-09-21">September 21, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Governor Tanner and the German-American.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0760</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0760.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-09-21">September 21, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">GOVERNOR TANNER AND THE GERMAN-AMERICAN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Governor Tanner has issued a list of all those eminent citizens, who are invited as representatives of the State to the present at the naming of the new battle-ship "Illinois." Among the 150 Chicagoans are about 12 Germans, Donnersberger, Otto Young, J. P. Altgeld, C. Guenther, A. M. Rothschild, F. Cooper, M. Rosenfield, J. Tosenthal, H. C. Lytton, E. Mandel, H. Enrich, F. Amberg, W. Boldenweck, M. Ullrich, W. C. Seipp, and T. Ochne.</p>
   <p>It is obvious that the German-Americans are not represented proportionately, but the reason for this is perhaps the fact that our Governor has few friends and followers among the German element of the city. Even among those invited may be a few only, who would consider themselves friends of Tanner; the majority of them would protest against being called friends of the Governor. There will be, presumably, no complaints be heard from private German citizens regarding this lack of consideration.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0761.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But Mr. Tanner also invited representatives of large clubs. He failed to put on the list the "Germania Maennerchor", and for this reason some of the members of this organization became very indignant and asserted that Mr. Tanner insulted the Germans in Chicago by his inconsiderate actions.</p>
   <p>However, it must be assumed that the Governor had no intention of doing so, because as a politician he will avoid giving offense to any party or citizens, particularly if a simple act of courtesy only is necessary to achieve this.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
