<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-20">Feb. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Elections and Voters</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-20">Feb. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ELECTIONS AND VOTERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The April elections will be of great importance to the citizens of Chicago, for reasons which need not be discussed in this treatise. Hence every citizen should participate in the elections and not take the standpoint that his vote will have no effect on the result of the election anyway. It is just because many citizens were governed by that thought in the past that Chicago has reason to be dissatisfied with its self-rule for some years. It is true, the exercise of one's right to vote is not a legal duty; however, it is a moral obligation. Whoever is remiss in the use of his franchise has no right to complain about mismanagement, for through his own indifference he is an abettor.</p>
   <p>There are three classes of voters: absolute partisans who always "go along" with their party; lukewarm partisans who, as a rule, "go along" with their <pb facs="5418474_4_1310.jpg" n="2"/>party, but occasionally make a side leap or detour; and independents who adhere to no certain party and cast their ballot in favor of any candidate whom they deem fit for office. These independent voters constitute about twenty per cent of the electorate, and the whole election campaign centers about them and the lukewarm partisans, since these two classes of voters often decide the issue in places where parties are about equal in numbers.</p>
   <p>Naturally the votes of the independents are sought most, because it is impossible to foresee how they will vote. They maintain their independence by remaining away from the primaries in which the candidates of the various parties are nominated. If they voted in the primaries they would indicate a preference for a certain party. But they pay a Teat price for their independence. For they forego their right to help choose a candidate. They content themselves with choosing between the parties at the election, without making use of their privilege to assist in the selection of the candidates of the party which receives their vote.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1311.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There may be a difference of opinion in regard to the real value of primary elections. They were instituted in order to eliminate the nomination of candidates by party caucus. In these caucuses, which were meetings of party leaders, candidates were appointed by bosses. The public had no say in the matter. Very often the interests of the public were disregarded in these nomination conferences, and the chief object of instituting primaries was to remove this evil. There is, however, room for serious doubt in regard to the effectiveness of the measure. There are many who believe that primary elections have changed the old way of electing candidates but very little. They point to the fact that in reality party leaders still select candidates. It is true, other candidates have the right to seek nomination in the primaries, but the party organization exercises considerable influence upon its followers, and candidates who have the support of the organization usually have a better chance of winning in primary elections than "independent" aspirants. But it must not be forgotten that the institution of primaries has undoubtedly caused party leaders to be more careful in their choice of candidates, since an unpopular candidate would have but little prospect of being nominated.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1312.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Another, much underrated danger in connection with primary elections lies in the possibility that members of a political party can bring about the nomination of an opposing party's candidate who has no prospects of success in the regular election, and thus pave the way to victory for their own candidate. To avoid this danger it has been ordained by law that a voter who has cast a ballot in favor of a candidate in a primary election may not vote for a candidate of another party in a primary until after two years. However at the regular election, thanks to the secret ballot, a voter may support any candidate he wishes to. It is evident that this primary law is of doubtful value, since a voter may change his place of residence at will, and in consequence many removals take place, especially in cities and densely populated sections, bringing many new voters to the polls at each primary.</p>
   <p>There is no sure remedy against this abuse of the primary. The best known remedy is the participation in primaries by the entire electorate. Only if all voters participate in the primaries can the result correspond to the will <pb facs="5418474_4_1313.jpg" n="5"/>of the people. Therefore, it is the duty of all eligible voters to take part, not only in the regular elections, but also in the primaries, and to register promptly, so that they will not be prevented from voting. To be independent, to be considered the deciding factor by a party, and to be coaxed and implored by the party, may cause a feeling of elation, but it should be considered more important fully to do one's duty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
