<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-02-01">February 1st, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A New Phase of the Altgeld-Harrison Dissension.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-02-01">February 1st, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW PHASE OF THE ALTGELD-HARRISON DISSENSION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As shown elsewhere in today's Abendpost edition, in the telegraphic news-section, we published a brief report to the effect that Mc Goorty, Democrat, in the lower house of the State legislature, presented his municipal ownership bill, which confers the right upon all cities, towns and villages in Illinois, to acquire all public transportation systems, including telegraph and telephone service. The author of the bill explains, his proposed law will be of primary benefit to Chicago, as it will enable this commonwealth to convert the street car company into a municipally owner corporation. He, Mc Goorty, fully shares the opinions of Mayor Harrison, since the latter is a convinced adherent and ardent defender of the municipal ownership idea. This last remark is surely made with prudence, and it requires no exceptional political perspicacity, to recognize its purpose. As is generally known, Ex Governor Altgeld proclaims himself to be the original advocater of the municipal ownership plan. But now, there suddenly appears the Harrisonite Mc Goorty and presents his bill at the State legislature, which virtually takes the wind from the Ex Governor's sails! Even in the life of party-politics a great deal depends on the "fix it" ability, with which the "correctness" is then practically utilized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
