<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-01-18">Jan. 18, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">Reducing the Salary of County Employees</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1637</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1637.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-01-18">Jan. 18, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">REDUCING THE SALARY OF COUNTY EMPLOYEES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We hope that the Republican delegation [Translator's note: The author evidently refers to the elected members of the State Legislature.] will not forget that before election the Republican party promised to reduce the salaries of certain county employees who have been receiving their wages in the form of fees.</p>
   <p>In former times, when there were not many court cases, the amount they realized was not too great; but under present conditions these fees represent a sum which is far in excess of the value of the services which the respective workers render. we believe that a special law should be enacted to regulate the salaries of the Cook County employees to the extent that whenever it is possible, a fixed sum should be established as their pay, and when this is not possible, as for instance in case the fees are not paid in advance, the fees be reduced to such an extent that the resulting income would not be as large as it is now; then there Will not be as much dishonest competition among the aspirants to these <pb facs="5418474_4_1638.jpg" n="2"/>offices. Since the present incumbents declared before they were elected last November that they would willingly submit to a reduction of pay, it is the duty of the Legislature, especially the delegation from Cook County, to take them at their word, and put an and to the ridiculously high salaries which have long been a cause of offense.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
