<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-28">Sep. 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Altgeld on State Institutions.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1079</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1079.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-28">Sep. 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">ALTGELD ON STATE INSTITUTIONS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Special Dispatch to the Illinois Staats Zeitung. Jacksonville, Ill., Sept. 27. Tarmers from the outlying districts and citizens from nearby towns and villages gathered hare today to be present at the "Ratification-Festival," which was announced for today by the Democratic party. Great enthusiasm prevails and the principal speakers, Judge Altegeld, Congressman Springer and M. T. Maloney were greeted with prolonged applause.</p>
   <p>Mr. Altgeld spoke mosely about conditions in state institutions, three of which are in Jacksonville. More than one million dollars per year are provided for them, yet, if the reports of their superintendents are reliable, they do not fulfill their requirements. According to the statement of the Secretary of State, June 30, 1890, the State's Hospitals for the Insane held 3,750 patients, and 1,833 demented persons, epileptics, idiots, etc., were placed in the poorhouses where they were neglecte in the most shameful manner.</p>
   <p>About one-half of the yearly funds which the legislature provides, are not used for the definite purposes for which they were intended. Instead of spending it for benevolent care the money finds its way into the pockets of political employees. Let us assume that every male and female guard receives</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1080.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>$25 per month, then we have a yearly expense of $200 and as $420,041.50 is paid for salaries, it follows that 1,400 people must be on the payrol; nearly one employee to every four inmates.</p>
   <p>It is evident that too many persons are hired and that these institutions have not been managed for the benefit of the unfortunates but are there to provide emoluments for political beggars. It is very significant that all these establishments give an accurate and detailed list of all expenditures, but where salaries are concerned, we find the simple, curt quotation: "Salaries, $11, 687.78; wages for employees, $6, 412.36." (Home for the Blind, in Jacksonville.)</p>
   <p>To whom the money is paid and for what, that cannot be unravelled. The statements of the superintendent and treasurer of the Deaf-Mute Home, here in Jacksonville, the Central Hospital for the Insane, also in Jacksonville, and others, are edited in a similar vein. Apparently it is not desired that the people of Illinois should know who the employees are, what they do and what they are paid for, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1081.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From that one must conclude: Either there are three times as many employees as are needed, or more than twice as much is paid for salaries as should be, or large sums which were labeled as salaries and wages were spent for other purposes and illegitimate uses, which the superintendents do not care to divulge. At all events the money is not used for benevolence as intended but flows into the pockets of favorites or political party hangers-on for whom it was not appropriate. The world's history teaches us that under such conditions the supervision, discipline amongest the employed, and the care to which the unfortunates are entitled, suffers.</p>
   <p>The speaker then throughly scrutinized the conditions prevailing at the insane asylum in Jacksonville and come to the conclusion that there must be laxity in its management. The superintendent should not be held responsible, as he is appointed, hence, must follow and obey instructions while attendants who owe their positions to political influence, will show little respect for his authority.</p>
   <p>After Mr. Altgeld referred to two separate instances which exposed the insane hospital at Jacksonville in a glaring and post penetrating light, so that the deplorable conditions present there under its politically appointed leadership <pb facs="5418474_4_1082.jpg" n="4"/>become apparent to all, he concluded his speed wish the remark: "The fact that even the Governor of the State of Illinois does not dare to interfere, proves the existence of a ring which is wore powerful even than the Governor. If the people of Illinois are not satisfied with existing conditions, then it is up to them to break the power of the ring which dominates the nominations and controls the elections."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
