<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-28">Sept. 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">How They Squirm! German Democrats Protest.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-28">Sept. 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">HOW THEY SQUIRM! GERMAN DEMOCRATS PROTEST.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the sorrowful experiences of the Republicans in Illinois and Wisconsin which the year 1890 recorded in the book of time, one would think, that they might desist in the future from resorting to Machiavellian machinations and divers trickery to bamboozle the German-Lutherans with the usual sprinkling of sand in their oculars - because they happen to be the apple of contention just now.</p>
   <p>The interim was long enough for the Republicans to perceive, that the Lutherans are fully conversant with the salient features of this fight, can differentiate the kernel from the chaff in the school question.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0242.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The shallowness, hypocrisy and utter unreliability of the Fiferians comes conspicuously to the surface when they apply their crass and inept methods to circumventing the main issue.....and the Germans only know the question too well, no smoke screen, (bluish haze, verbatim) no hocus-pocus will do; if it's tried, they will be offended, since it mounts to an underestimation of their intelligence.</p>
   <p>This is about the tenor of the answer which a representative of our paper gave to the esteemed contemporary, "Doc" Jamison, Vice Mayor of Chicago, when the latter spoke of his brilliant discovery from which he endeavored to garner political capital. "We shall prove," said he, "that most of the prosecutions under the Edwards law are to be found in Democratic counties, under Democratic judges, at the instigation of Democratic officials."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0243.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Illinois Staats Zeitung at the time did give cognizance to that colossal discovery by "Doc" and incidentally quoted what William Tatge, the well-known attorney had to say about the persecuted Lutherans, whose legal representative he was, being a member of their school committee.</p>
   <p>The lawyer said: "It is not quite clear to me just what effect this would have on the decisions regarding the school fight. It is well nigh insanity if the Republicans wish to shift responsibility on to court officials who by oath are obliged and compelled to enforce the law in conformity to its text and so......Democratic officials must obey Republican laws. A law, if passed, must be followed; the judiciary which lives up to it is not to be censored but those who made it are culpable. The Republicans......cannot use such an excuse."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0244.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is an unwelcome question, an issue of some kind must be conceived to eliminate it, so superficiality is resorted to School compulsion, yes or no? Fifer, the a acrobat gave the cue, and the chorus of Knights will soon chant the melody. While Fifer and associates ignore the question: "Whose fault was it that the law of 1891 was not superceded, as promised," Altgeld appears and defines the position of the Democrats in a concise manner which precludes all doubt and reproach.</p>
   <p>German Democrats Protest.</p>
   <p>The executives of the German Democratic Central Association voiced their protest yesterday morning against the unjust proceedings of the Republican Judge Hawes, (who also is a candidate for re-election), because of his rabid, nativistic conduct towards Germans who wish to be naturalized..</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0245.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The protest:</p>
   <p>"As the German-American-Democratic Association of Cook County has made it its duty to obtain the naturalization of the immigrated Germans, and intends to continue this work to the best of its ability, in order to enable the new arrivals to participate in the benefits which American citizenship offers, and in order to absorb this new element in the civic ranks of our newly adopted homeland with its manifold duties and privileges, and:</p>
   <p>"As this Association is under the leadership of men who subscribe to the principle that thorough conscientiousness is the chief pillar of our liberal institutions and that only by adhering to it can the continuity of our American Republic be assured, and that therefore they will never resort to any circumvention of the law in order to enable immigrants to acquire admission to citizenship by illegal means and:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0246.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"As we require the highest civic virtue and conscience to its fullest extent in the German people in general as also in its migrating sons, characteristics which preclude legal infractions at the very time they endeavor to become affiliated with a new fatherland by resorting to perjury, (in connection with existing laws), therefore:</p>
   <p>"Be it resolved that the German-American-Democratic Association of Cook County denounces the distrust which certain judges display towards German applicants who intend to become citizens and are being subjected to extensive and mostly useless questioning, often of an abusive nature, calculated to create confusion and difficulties, an ordeal which is intended to scare honest, irreproachable and honorable men, particularly those who are not conversant with the English language and legal phraseology, and therefore become enmeshed and ensnared by vague and ambiguous questions which are bound to produce discrepancies and thereby place the petitioners in a ridiculous, shameful position, causing injured feelings which prevent them from persisting in the attempt to secure the opportunities we offer them, the realization of the right to vote.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0247.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"We emphasize 'voting' as we feel assured that it is strictly a political strategy, which certain parties inaugurated because of their intense fear over the strengthening of the German-American vote, and we condemn the aforementioned proceedings on the grounds that it is an abuse of the law and judicial powers in the interests of a political party for the furtherance of their nativistic purposes.</p>
   <p>"We condemn it as illegal and improper, that representatives of a political organization are given an opportunity through court officials to ascertain the names and addresses of naturalized citizens for the undeniable purpose of utilizing this information for party expediencies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0248.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"We declare that it is incompatible with the high status of the law and the honor of judges, that political wire-pullers without legal or official authority, can dictate judicial functions and proceedings.</p>
   <p>"We will use all our power to combat such usurpation which restricts the rights of immigrants, who are entitled to the opportunity to become citizens."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
