<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-05">Nov. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Right to Vote or Duty to Vote?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1218</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1218.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-05">Nov. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">RIGHT TO VOTE OR DUTY TO VOTE?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a disgraceful fact that only a small fraction of those entitled to vote participate in the election. Most of those who actually vote are citizens who belong, directly or indirectly, to a party organization, or are indebted in some manner to these organizations. There are probably some independent voters who do their duty, but the overwhelming majority of these stay away from the polls. They do this from indolence or under the threadbare pretext that their vote would not change the results of the election. This is, of course, nonsense. If all these indifferent people took part in the election, their influence would be very noticeable. In a democratic state structure like that of the United States, every citizen should be compelled to vote. It should not be left up to the citizen, whether he is to vote or not, but the right to vote should also be an obligation.</p>
   <p>It is regrettable that many of those entitled to vote, who keep away from the elections on principle, must be counted among the most alert intellectually, if <pb facs="5418474_4_1219.jpg" n="2"/>one may judge from the criticism which they are in the habit of directing at the decisions or actions of organs of government elected by the people. They reserve the right to criticize, but refuse to vote and thus take the responsibility for their opposition. There can be no real democracy unless all citizens who are entitled to vote participate actively in the elections. If this does not happen the political bosses and their machines get the upper hand. Under these circumstances an independent candidate, no matter how qualified he is for the position he seeks, seldom comes off victorious in an election. Ordinarily a candidate has no prospect of being elected unless he has one of the two big party organizations behind him, and before he can gain their support, he must either have rendered great service to the party, or be content to become their vassal in the future.</p>
   <p>That this is so must be attributed to the fact that those voters who do not belong to a party organization prefer to stay away from the elections. The parties reckon on this, and their calculations are usually correct. These absent votes might often turn the scale, if they were cast. Of those eligible to vote, only a part took the trouble to register; and even of those who did register, only a <pb facs="5418474_4_1220.jpg" n="3"/>few appeared on election day to cast their votes. In times like the present, every citizen who has the welfare of his fellow countrymen at heart should consider it his duty, to cast his vote. Only if this is done can we speak of a government of the people. Nobody can improve his position by giving an excellent exposition of his views, or by abusing the Government and its administration, if he does this in a saloon. Let him express his views by the way he votes.</p>
   <p>Many peoples have been deprived of the right to take part in national affairs because they did not know how to preserve this right and make wise use of it. This fate will overtake every people that does not guard its rights. A man who voluntarily renounces his right to vote is one of the gravediggers of democracy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
