<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-08-08">August 8, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">Edmund Jussen on the Address of the German American Republican Club.</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Editor of the Illinois Staats Zeitung:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0608</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0608.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-08-08">August 8, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">EDMUND JUSSEN ON THE ADDRESS OF THE GERMAN AMERICAN REPUBLICAN CLUB.</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Editor of the Illinois Staats Zeitung:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On today's edition of your paper I read the address of the local German-American Hayes and Wheeler clubs. The address begins with a lie. Right at the beginning it says, "This time the Democrats of the Southern States stand against us in their full strength, united as in the times of Pierce and Buchanan with their political fellows in the North." I must admit that I am not a little astonished, that the German-American liberals did not find it under their dignity to take advantage of this most miserable of all thread-bare arguments of the Republican wire-pullers. How can they only compare the disputed questions and parties of today with those of the days of Pierce and Buchanan, without being afraid that the <pb facs="5418474_4_0609.jpg" n="2"/>German voter will take this as an insult to his intelligence and will view these machinations with contempt? Today the vast majority of the German-Americans and thousands of American Liberals of the Year, 1872, are enthusiastically in favor of the Democratic presidential candidate, determined to stop the flow of corruption and the misadministration through a violent overthrow of the ruling party. Under Buchanan the issue was the spreading of slavery, - today's battle cry is honesty and thrift-ness in public affairs, death to corruption, and a long lasting effective and energetic reform.</p>
   <p>But the only idea of the Republican Club is: The North must be instigated, to renew the pre-war disputes, to rekindle the resting passions, to inflame again old grudges, and to arouse against the present Democratic Party all the old prejudices. I repeat again, such tactics are unworthy of a real German-American Liberal.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0610.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>How a German-American Liberal, who in the year of 1872, supported Greeley and allied himself with the Democratic Party, not because Greeley was at that time the best qualified man, but simply because the Republican Party was so rotten and corrupt.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
