<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-18">Mar. 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The State Public Utilities Commission Should Be Abolished (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0455</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0455.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-18">Mar. 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE STATE PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION SHOULD BE ABOLISHED (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the Albany legislature instituted the first public utilities commission for the State of New York about ten years ago, a useful future was predicted for the new office. At present nearly every state legislature in the Union is considering a bill to abolish its public utilities commission. Whence this change of attitude, this condemnation of such bodies?</p>
   <p>It is not difficult to find the answer to this question. Until the year 1917 these commissions were called upon to decide only isolated cases, in most instances such as related to improvement of service, increase in wages, hours of work, and similar matters. Although their activity in this respect caused no general offense, many cities considered it an <pb facs="5418474_4_0456.jpg" n="2"/>infringement upon their right of self-government, and steadfastly and emphatically denied that there was the least necessity for state control over purely local matters. However, since such commissions have approved of raises in the rates and prices of many utilities for reasons resulting from the War, the number of cities that demand home rule has increased considerably. It is hardly possible to determine by past experience whether or not the commissions' efforts at mediation (they were to be mediators according to the laws by which the office was created) have been successful generally in settling controversies between municipalities and corporations. But in Illinois the situation is much clearer. Until the time when the State Public Utilities Commission was instituted, municipal and local communities did not have authority to prescribe rates for the services rendered by privately operated utilities. Rates and prices were established by agreement between the community and the corporation. It may be readily understood that under such conditions the rates which a corporation charged for services which it rendered in <pb facs="5418474_4_0457.jpg" n="3"/>one community often differed from the rates which it charged in another. Thus it was possible for one community, owing to conditions, or because it insisted that certain terms be maintained, to obtain service at cost price, while other communities were obliged to make up for the loss thus sustained by paying unreasonably high rates.</p>
   <p>The sponsors of the six-year-old Illinois utility act once said that it would put an end to such inequality and to the confusing and unjust system of favoritism; that it would empower the Commission to establish just, reasonable, and adequate rates and thus protect the public from fraud and, at the same time, procure a reasonable profit for the corporation. The act contains twenty-eight sections and twenty-two thousand words. It treats every point very thoroughly and very exactly. A part of one section is of special interest to us. It directs the Commission to establish a fair evaluation of each property, and to disregard watered stock or securities which are not represented by tangible property. Everything is <pb facs="5418474_4_0458.jpg" n="4"/>treated so exhaustively that nothing is left to guesswork or supposition. Furthermore, it was especially emphasized, at the time, that the act would create a commission which would consist of well-paid officials who were to be appointed by the Governor, and would, therefore, have no connections with local politics.</p>
   <p>These predictions did not come true, at least so far as Chicago is concerned. It would have been impossible to increase gas rates and elevated fares under the terms of the law, if the Commission had first conscientiously computed the value of the companies' property and had reasonably estimated their cost of operation. Nor was the prediction that the Commission would be unaffected by local politics fulfilled. No doubt what happened was what the legislators expected. The appointments of a governor are no less political than those of a mayor, and State politics are so closely interwoven with the politics of the larger cities, especially with the politics of the largest city of the State, that even the "cleanest" politician <pb facs="5418474_4_0459.jpg" n="5"/>could not separate the binding ties. And this task becomes very difficult when the governor of a state has been a citizen of the largest city prior to his accession to office, and when he intends to return to the largest city after having served his term.</p>
   <p>Only a very few of the arguments which are advanced in favor of the Utilities Commission can stand the test of a rigid examination. On the contrary, there seems to be good reason to ask why men living upstate should be better acquainted with conditions in Chicago than men who were born in that city, make their home there, and are well acquainted with the wishes of the inhabitants. There can be no doubt that a Chicagoan has a greater sense of responsibility toward Chicagoans than a farmer from Mattoon or a party leader from Peoria. And public opinion, expressed in the local press and at the polls, will have a more decided influence upon a local commission than it would have upon a governor's appointees who have no inner relation with the people whose interests they are to protect.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0460.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>In the interest of Chicago, as well as of ever other municipality, it is to be sincerely desired that the legislature soon take the measures necessary to abolish our State Public Utilities Commission.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
