<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-04-16">April 16,1872</date>.
<title level="a">The Hecker Meeting in the Hall of the Turn Society Vorwarts.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1599</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1599.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-04-16">April 16,1872</date>.
<title level="a">THE HECKER MEETING IN THE HALL OF THE TURN SOCIETY VORWARTS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting was opened by Dr. Schmidt. Schmidt declined the chairmanship; Franz Lackner was elected to preside. On taking over his office Mr. Lackner made a speech:</p>
   <p>"We who are not actuated by any personal interest, whom the well-being of the country and a feeling of duty alone drive to participate in politics, - we have long felt that it is time that the people take the reins of the party in their hands. In view of the terrible corruption inactivity begins to be a crime. We declare war against the administration:! Reform is our battle-cry and with that we will victoriously advance! From German throats this cry has issued, and already the whole of Germandom stands united!(?)"</p>
   <p>(Footnote: The Illinois Staats inserts the question mark).</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1600.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After Hecker's speech resolutions were adopted containing the following main points:</p>
   <p>Preservation of the Federal Consititution and the utmost possible decentralization; civil service reform, adoption of the one term principle, (for the presidency), and energetic repression of the monopolies; tariff for revenues and restriction of all prohibitive and force legislation.</p>
   <p>A permanent committee was formed, composed of Dr. Ernst Schmidt, Louis Schultz, Wilhelm Ruhl, Gustav Korn......Franz Lackner, Hermann Lieb, Georg Vocke, Richard Michaelis, Gonrad Seipp and others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
