<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-12-11">Dec. 11, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Haiti (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0413</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Corrected date value.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0413.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-12-11">Dec. 11, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">HAITI (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Hoover in his message to Congress recommended that a commission be sent to Haiti to investigate conditions.</p>
   <p>One cannot ascribe considerable originality to this suggestion. Such procedure have been inaugurated before but as for tangible results--well, that is something else again.</p>
   <p>When one realizes that the government of the Negro republic has been under American control for fourteen years, then one cannot claim that the intervention of the United states has been overly successful.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0414.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At present there are eleven hundred marines on the island. As a matter of fact, war would prevail there if the Americans with their superior equipment, were not in control of the situation.</p>
   <p>If the proponents of the intervention policy maintain that American occupation of Nicaragua and Naiti has produced peace, then, of course, we must admit the fact. It is true. Both republics enjoy Uncle Sam's particular patronage, and there is peace and tranquility--as long as the natives perceive the futility of warring against the constituted authority.</p>
   <p>In reality, the Americans did not succeed in stabilizing either republic. The reasons underlying this failure were recently given <pb facs="5418474_4_0415.jpg" n="3"/>with assounding frankness by the well-known General Smedley D. Butler, while speaking in Pittsburgh. The General, in giving an account of the "rule of the marines" in Nicaragua, explained among other things:</p>
   <p>"When it became necessary to elect our people, then the opposing candidates were designated as bandits. Very simple. Our ticket always wins. In a certain district our candidete was exceedingly unpopular. We ascertained that only four hundred people were willing to vote for him. What can you do in such a contingency? The election was announced just five minutes before the people were admitted to the polls. The four hundred men who were not opposed to our puppet were gathered outside and, after they had done their civic duty, we closed the polling place. It was all done in a few hours."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0416.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This is, of course, a very simple method, but lasting results cannot be obtained thereby. The public is compelled to accept a certain administration whether it likes it or not. Of course, there are elections, but these are obviously mere farcical formalities, since the victorious delegates and officials are not elected by the people. The candidates are nominated and escorted into public office by the American army of occupation.</p>
   <p>That is the record of the American marines--our soldiers--under General Butler in Nicaragua.</p>
   <p>In Haiti, not even an attempt was made to preserve the semblance of a voting system. The procedure was just too bothersome, and therefore no elections have been held since 1917.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0417.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Under such circumstances, it appears to be rather superfluous for the President or Congress to send an investigating committee to that sunny island. If they desire to know why these republics are dissatisfied under American dominion, then they need only read General Butler's speech.</p>
   <p>That conditions in Haiti and Nicaragua are identical is readily ascertainable by scrutinizing the occasional dispatches about the present disorders.</p>
   <p>The reason for the dissension and the dissatisfaction of the people is attributed to President Borno's administration.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0418.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>He is the gentleman who was conducted into office and who was assured continuance in political life up to the present day by our American blue jackets.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
