<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-31">Oct. 31, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of German-American Democrats in Lincoln Turner Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0082</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0082.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-31">Oct. 31, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF GERMAN-AMERICAN DEMOCRATS IN LINCOLN TURNER HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last evening the organization known officially as the German-American Democratic organization of Cook County, Inc., held an election meeting at the Lincoln Turner Hall. Among those present were a large number of men and women who are well-known in German societies, in the singing and turner societies, the great fraternal organizations, the Schwabenverein (Swabian Society), and so forth.</p>
   <p>The chairman, Ernst Buhler, who is an attorney and a member of the School Board, introduced the various speakers during the course of the evening. First on the list was Mayor Kelly who, like many other candidates, had to attend another large meeting and therefore arrived in the Hall only a few minutes after 8 P.M. He was followed by various candidates in next Tuesday's election, among them Alderman John Toman, candidate for sheriff; Michael J. Flynn, <pb facs="5418474_4_0083.jpg" n="2"/>candidate for county clerk; George Seif, candidate for membership on the board of the Sanitary District; and John Traeger, who is a candidate for county commissioner. The Municipal court candidates, Joseph J. Drucker, George Weiss, and Joseph B. Hermes, were also present, and--the last of a long list--Fred W. Brummel, for whose candidacy Mr. Gustave A. Brand and already spoken. Other candidates, who could not be present in person, because they had to speak at other mass meetings, found friends and party members to speak for them, and explain the excellence, etc., of the candidates.</p>
   <p>The fundamental idea in all the speeches can be summed up in these words: "Vote for the entire Democratic ticket to prove that you support President Roosevelt's program." This thought was also expressed by Congressmen A.J. Sabath and Leonard W. Schuetz, of the Fifth and Seventh Congressional Districts, respectively, who also urged the election of former Congressman James McAndrews of the Ninth District. A pleasant interlude in the long program of speeches was provided by the excellent and well-received offerings <pb facs="5418474_4_0084.jpg" n="3"/>of the singing societies Harmonie, Orpheus, and Geusfelder Liederkranz, under Director [Karl] Reckzeh, and the songs of the singing society of the Hermanneschwester, under Director Taegtmeyer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
