<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title>,
<date when="1876-09-24">Sep. 24, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">Free.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1154</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1154.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title>,
<date when="1876-09-24">Sep. 24, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">FREE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At 4 o'clock yesterday afternoon, the prison doors opened for A. C. Hesing, Burroughs, Powell, Dickinson and Abel. Although the pardon papers had not arrived as yet, Federal Attorney Bangs was kind enough to notify the distillers that after payment of their fine, they might spend Sunday at home. All could not avail themselves of this privilege.</p>
   <p>Only Burroughs, Dickinson and Abel were able to pay their fine. Friends were on hand for Hesing and Powell, and at 4 o'clock the sheriff had received the order from Bangs to free the prisoners. Here is the report of the pardon clerk.</p>
   <p>"To the General Federal Attorney.</p>
   <p>"Sir:</p>
   <p>"I have examined the applications for pardon of A. C. Hesing, G. Burroughs, Henry B. Miller and Simon Powell, and I find that:</p>
   <p>"The accused pleaded guilty, in the belief that they would all receive the same punishment;</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1155.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"That 1,200 South Chicago citizens signed a petition asking the pardon of A. C. Hesing upon the ground that the latter had done so much for the city, state and county;</p>
   <p>"That 6,000 citizens from Chicago signed a petition asking the pardon of A. C. Hesing, upon the ground that the sentence was very severe;</p>
   <p>"That 2,000 citizens from Chicago, Galena, Springfield and other cities signed a petition because A. C. Hesing has been for so long such a highly respected citizen;</p>
   <p>"A petition by the Hon. Monroe Heath, mayor of Chicago and by 21 of the 36 aldermen;</p>
   <p>"A petition by 18 of the 19 members of congress from Illinois;</p>
   <p>"A petition by 68 citizens of Chicago of Bohemian descent.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Alexander T. Gray,</p>
   <p>Clerk for Pardons."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1156.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Federal Attorney General Taft added the following lines to the letter of Mr. Gray:</p>
   <p>"In consideration of the report of the district attorney in regard to A. C. Hesing, S. T. Burroughs, H. B. Miller and S. Powell, applicants for pardon, I recommend reduction of the punishment of all of them to three months incarceration and scaling down of their fine to $1,000.</p>
   <p>Alphonso Taft,</p>
   <p>Attorney General."</p>
   <p>In a few days Jacob Rehm will be the only distiller still in jail. His pros-pects of liberation, before the expiration of his sentence, are not very bright.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
