<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-21">Feb. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Irish-Americans Work with Germans for Hesing's Nomination.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0198</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0198.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-21">Feb. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">IRISH-AMERICANS WORK WITH GERMANS FOR HESING'S NOMINATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large meeting of the 30th ward citizenry, mostly people of Irish and German descent, met at Scheidt's Hall, 116 W. 51st Street yesterday evening to start a Washington Hesing Club. A list of prominent ward citizens is published. (19 names listed.)</p>
   <p>After Mr. Lorenz Scheidt opened the meeting, Mr. Carl Bechstein, president of the 18th Ward German-American Branch Club, spoke most enthusiastically for the Hesing's candidacy. He had made the long trip to the 30th ward in order to present during the organizational proceedings and to help the cause on general principles. He expressed his heartfelt satisfaction that the Irish and German inhabitants work hand in hand for a common cause. He stressed <pb facs="5418474_4_0199.jpg" n="2"/>the great importance of the coming election and designated Mr. Hesing as the most suitable aspirant to that office. In his closing remarks he was very emphatic that no one should fail to vote during the primary, as the fate of the candidate depends on that more than anything else.</p>
   <p>The assembly then resolved to be known henceforth as the Washington Hesing 30th Ward Club. Election of officers followed. M. J. Keegan was chosen as president. (Elsewhere Keegan's initials have been printed as F. J. in the same article and mentioning the same person. M. J. is probably correct as this appears oftener - Transl.) J. J. Costello became secretary and L. Scheidt, treasurer.</p>
   <p>It was indeed a most fortunate choice, as Mr. Keegan is one of the best known, respected and energetic men of the 30th ward. In speaking to his <pb facs="5418474_4_0200.jpg" n="3"/>audience, he proclaimed himself to be a Democrat from head to toe as his friends and neighbors well know. He has no aspirations to seek any public office but he has made it his business to work for Mr. Hesing's election. Mr. Hesing has many friends among the Irish inhabitants of the 30th ward as was shown by the large number who were present here. The time for action is at hand; we must not be satisfied to give Mr. Hesing our assurance of support only, that is not enough, we must endeavor to achieve something, on our own accord, individually. Everyone should work among his friends in a most energetic manner to obtain the proper results on election day.</p>
   <p>A long resolution, listing all the favorable attributes of the candidate, followed and was accepted with much enthusiasm. The 3rd ward: An enthusiastic meeting of more than 400 bona fidevoters declared themselves for Hesing.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0201.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>All seats in the spacious Arlington Hall, 31st Street and Indiana Avenue, were taken, and after 8 o'clock the hallways and contiguous spaces were filled, so that one may well claim that the Democracy of that district was fully represented. After Lawyer Braham submitted Carter H. Harrison's register of sins to a thorough perusal and expounded it unmercifully, W. C. O'Neill appeared and analyzed the recent Democratic victories. That mighty problem, the tariff-reform, which Grover Cleveland regarded as the life and death question of the Democratic party in 1884; the continuance of our personal liberty, and the rights of parents in regard to educational matters concerning their children; all these and kindred subjects under-went his scrutiny, and finally, he proclaimed Washington Hesing as the principal crusader who brought these questions to an issue and gave the Democratic party its present greatness.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0202.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Amidst jubilant acclaim Washington Hesing obtained the endorsement of the 3rd ward Democrats. (A list of prominent citizens and businessmen who were at this meeting is appended in the publication. Transl.)</p>
   <p>The young Democrats of the 15th ward and the German-American Club of the 31st ward hold meetings tonight.</p>
   <p>Mr. C. S. Darrow and other eminent American and German speakers will be on the rostrum at the 5th ward meeting, Liberty Hall, Union Avenue and 30th Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
