<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-06-14">June, 14, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">Atrocious Malice of Republican Officials</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-06-14">June, 14, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">ATROCIOUS MALICE OF REPUBLICAN OFFICIALS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last year, as at present, considerable complaint was made about the malicious conduct of the Republican federal officials when tavernkeepers apply for their licenses. Of course the law stipulates that licenses shall be obtained in May. But in spite of the announcements in the newspapers many people are absolutely unaware of this and expect that notifications about reissuance of licenses will be mailed as heretofore. Besides this, people are accustomed to being treated by the city with considerable though not excessive leniency and therefore do not expect that a few days' delay in payment will be punished by a severe fine.</p>
   <p>Of course, order must be maintained, and a small addition of a dollar or two as penalty would readily be consented to. Had that occurred, then probably <pb facs="5418474_4_1560.jpg" n="2"/>no one would have argued about it. However, if people are fined fifteen to twenty dollars, and it can definitely be established that they have tried to pay for their licenses promptly but have been prevented by cases beyond their control, then they are fully justified in registering a strong protest.</p>
   <p>A saloonkeeper who is well known for his usual punctuality told us that he had called at the revenue office in May to pay his license fee. While he was waiting in line with numerous applicants preceding him, the office was closed. On another day he waited again as long as he could, but he had to leave because of other urgent business. After that it was impossible for him to come to the city for several days. He was summoned to appear before Commissioner Hoyne, who assessed a fifteen-dollar fine. Another [saloonkeeper] had gone to town to pay his fee and was suddenly recalled because of his wife's approaching accouchement. The payment was therefore delayed, and he had to shell out twenty ducats to pay a fine.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1561.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A third saloonkeeper entirely forgot the date but remembered it a few days after June 1, borrowed the money quickly in order not to be late, and was ordered to pay a nineteen-dollar fine. Instead of paying it he expressed his sentiments--the truth--most vigorously. The officials at first refused to accept the fee without the fine, but when the gentleman reappeared with an attorney, they complied, and the additional assessment was ignored.</p>
   <p>We could cite dozens of similar cases, but these will suffice for the present to show the maliciousness of the Republican officials and how the public is bled at every opportunity. After all, the fine does not reach the national treasury; it bulges instead the pockets of the federal commissioner and the tax collector. We advise any one who comes into conflict with the authorities in a similar manner to defend himself most vigorously. Usually it helps.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
