<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-06-28">June 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A Movement in Favor of Pardoning the Anarchists.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-06-28">June 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A MOVEMENT IN FAVOR OF PARDONING THE ANARCHISTS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The movement for the pardoning of the anarchists, Neebe, Fielden, and Schwab, who are in the penitentiary at Joliet, has been recently revived. A meeting was held in Ullrich's Hall, attended by delegates of 134 organizations- athletic clubs, labor unions, song clubs, and others - where a petition, addressed to the governor, was submitted. A committee of twenty-one members was appointed, and the petition turned over to them. Sub-committees will likewise be appointed and requested to carry on the agitation. The appeal which resulted in the previously mentioned meeting was signed by Dr. E. Schmidt, J. J. Altpeter, J. Gloy, M. M. Trumbull, Chr. Meier, S. A. Schilling, H. Linnemeyer, F. A. Stauber, and P. Peterson.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0262.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is stated in the appeal that Governor Fifer has not given a definite answer to the petitions addressed to him relating to the release of Neebe, Fielden, and Schwab, but that a general intercession, originating from all classes of society, would definitely make a favorable impression, and, undoubtedly, succeed, because the public is recently more favorably inclined towards the pardoning of the men in question.</p>
   <p>The meeting was attended by about 400 people. General M. M. Trumbull was elected chairman, and C. Meyer, secretary. The letter, which was addressed to Governor Oglesby on May 8, 1887, and signed by Judges Gary and Tuthin, and States Attorney Grinnel, in which they ask for mercy for Neebe, Fielden, and Schwab, was read by Trumbull to the audience.</p>
   <p>Besides the Chicago organizations, others from Aurora and elsewhere were represented.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
