<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-31">October 31, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">The Illinois Staats Zeitung Publishes the List of Candidates on Whom Both Parties Have Agreed, and Comments:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0045</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0045.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-31">October 31, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">THE ILLINOIS STAATS ZEITUNG PUBLISHES THE LIST OF CANDIDATES ON WHOM BOTH PARTIES HAVE AGREED, AND COMMENTS:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the mayoralty, Joseph Medill has been proposed. He, not long ago, pressed in the Tribune the candidacy of Mr. Henry Greenebaum in the warmest and most emphatic terms. It has therefore certainly not been animosity against the Germans which gave Medill the nomination, but exclusively the desire to satisfy all classes of society. Medill is a man of honor whose highest ambition is to see his name connected with the reconstruction of Chicago, and just as he in good faith proposed the name of the German Henry Greenebaum, so Greenebaum and all good Germans will stand by him faithfully.</p>
   <p>For the office of police commissioner, Jacob Rehm has been nominated in place of Fr. Gund. Not because any member of the committee doubted the honesty and the good will of Gund, but because Rehm's executive ability, practical experience, and knowledge of men seemed greater than Gund's. Everyone of those who voted against Mr. Gund is in sympathy with him and expects that he, who <pb facs="5418474_4_0046.jpg" n="2"/>has lost so much in the fire, will find a proper position in the city administration. The same is true of Fritz Metzke who had to be passed by, in spite of the zealous boosting by his German friends, for Rumsey who happens to be better known in American circles.</p>
   <p>Of the other Germans on the list nothing needs to be said. Everybody knows them as men of the highest integrity. J. H. Pahlmann, Christian Wahl, John Herting, and Joseph Roelle have been proposed as county commissioners, and better men than they, it would be hard to find. On the list of city offices stands the name of Georg von Hollen......</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
