<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-26">Apr. 26, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">[German-American Journalism]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-26">Apr. 26, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">[GERMAN-AMERICAN JOURNALISM]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>April 25 was a very important day for Richard Michaelis, the Prussian-American Judas Iscariot. This journalistic cossack finds himself now in the role of Hamlet: to be or not to be, that is the question. He will either enter into possession of large sums of money with the aid of the most atrocious lies, and grow fat at the people's expense, or be scoffed and laughed at until he becomes politically extinct and, consequently, starve and end in misery.</p>
   <p>The decision of this question is in Judge Tuley's hands. An injunction has been issued against the Freche (fresh) Presse to restrain this organ of a Prussian stool-pigeon from receiving a large sum of money for publishing municipal announcements, since Mike's paper is a disgrace to all Germans of Chicago, and any announcement in its columns is of no value, since the number of subscribers of the scrap of paper is highly problematical.</p>
   <p>Mike tried to suppress this fact yesterday when Judge Tuley set him a term to explain his side of the case.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1421.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Impertinent as a bug Mike declared in writing, getting his lawyer Colonel Stevenson to read his declamation, that he had in twenty-four streets alone as many subscribers as the Arbeiter-Zeitung and Staats-Zeitung combined.</p>
   <p>This exaggeration in collective style is too dumb to be contradicted. There are assertions so disgustingly asinine that a person with five senses cannot but throw them in the waste basket or, even better, in the deepest part of a dungpit. This statement is yesterday's pyramidal lie of the journalistic Muenchhausen, Richard Michaelis.</p>
   <p>The only real question is whether it is lawful to use money of the city treasury for publication of announcements in German.</p>
   <p>A positive answer to this question is given by a law enacted in 1863, as well as numerous decisions by judges in other states. The legality of this practice is argued by Mike's attorney and Corporation Counsel Hutchinson.</p>
   <p>Ex-Corporation Counsel Adams, however, referred to a Superior Court decision,</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
