<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-05-17">May 17, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The School Question before the German Citizens Club of the St. Jacobi Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0551</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0551.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-05-17">May 17, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCHOOL QUESTION BEFORE THE GERMAN CITIZENS CLUB OF THE ST. JACOBI CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The members of the German Citizens Club within the Evangelical-Lutheran St. Jacobi Church held a meeting in their church yesterday to obtain a better understanding of the school question, which will be the cardinal issue of the coming state election. The speaker of the evening was Emil Hoechster. He treated the important subject in a manner that could be easily understood, and he spoke convincingly as well as exhaustively. His speech was not a political one, although Hoechster is a Democrat. He based his discussions upon the resolutions of the German Lutherans which had been published previously. According to the speaker every good citizen is in favor of a sensible compulsory school law regardless of his political or religious affiliation; but, further, every good citizen will fight to keep church and state completely separated. The speaker asserted that under the present school law the schools of the churches are under the control of the state, and for this reason this law must be repealed.</p>
   <p>The speaker expounded the attitude of the Democratic as well as the Republican party in respect to the school question, and supported his statements with facts, <pb facs="5418474_4_0552.jpg" n="2"/>showing how unreliable, if not treasonable, the Republican Party had proven itself in this matter. The Democratic party, demanded however, from the beginning the unconditional repeal of the school law and this demand is expressed very definitely in its present platform. The old compulsory school law is to be substituted by a new one, similar to the new law in Wisconsin. This is not only demanded by the churches, but by every citizen who has an understanding of these problems.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
