<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-09-23">Sept. 23, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">[Political Matters]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-09-23">Sept. 23, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">[POLITICAL MATTERS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Turn Society "Vorwarts" celebrated last night its fifteenth anniversary arranging an evening of festivities. Represented by their delegates were the following Turn-Societies: Aurora Turn-Society, the Turn-Gemeinde, Bohemian Turn-Society, Grand crossing Turn-Society, The SWISS Male Chorus, Liederkranz Eintracht, and many others. Mr. Simmen opened the evening with a short welcome, stressing the importance of the celebration and benefits derived from the activities of the Turn-Societies and their work in the cause of freedom. Then he introduced Mr. Wegemann as President of the meeting, who in turn gave a short but spirited speech. Mr. Rubens gave a toast to the American Fatherland. Mr. Eissner of the "Freidenker" (Free Thinker) replied to it saying: Although we are living under a republican form of government (A government by the People!) much is left to be fought for. Merely existing is not satisfying, we are desirous of higher ideals. We strive for a Socialist State,based on righteousness, truth and humanity. He was greatly applauded for his speech. Mr. Wegemann followed with a toast for the platform and principles of the American Turn-Societies saying: Despite the great progress of modern times in the field of various sciences, prejudices belonging to the Middle Ages, have still not been conquered. The rising sun on the firmament of Liberty is penetrating through dark clouds, but there is still much left to be done. Therefore Turners! Courage and onward with your work.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0296.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Huhn of Belleville replied to this with an excellent radical talk. He gave a short sketch of the history of the Turn-Societies. The revolutionary socialistic foundation is the origin of the Turn Societies. They differ from the Turners of Germany, in that they are always ready to take the stand against repression; they once adopted the abolitionist platform fighting for it with their own lives. One of the outstanding accomplishments of the Turners was their separation from political parties and their declaration of independance. Their motto at first was: Freedom, Equality and Brotherhood: This motto, should still be theirs: (Much applause). Mr. Rubens read then an address of welcome for Mayor Harrison. To the toast given by Mr. Goldzior to the city of Chicago, Mayor Harrison replied:- "I agree with you my friends, that there is much to be improved, in our much praised Republic. I am looking forward to the day when true freedom shall triumph. I am confident that this overpowering idea of a new freedom shall have its birth in our magnificent city". (Applause). A toast to our youth given by Mr. John Glog was replied to by Mr. Schuricht.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
