<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-02-18">Feb. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Attention Germans!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1033</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1033.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-02-18">Feb. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ATTENTION GERMANS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Five thousand German-Americans citizens unamimously accepted a resolution submitted at a mass-meeting held Feb. 15 at the North Side Turner Mall.</p>
   <p>Four years of Republican mismanagement convinced every voter of our city that the welfare of Chicago rests with the Democrats. The greater the responsibilities which the Democratic party is assuming, the more caution is exercised in the election of the man who will be destined to represent and lend to victory the Democratic party in the coming campaign.</p>
   <p>We German-Americans attending the meeting at the Turner Hall on February 15th, announce, after a careful study of conditions and conscientious comparisons of the party's candidates, that we consider Carter H. Harrison as the most desirable candidate, deserving of the support of every Democrat; especially that of the German voters. Not a shadow of doubt can mar the prediction that Carter H. Harrison, the able leader of the Democratic party, will travel the <pb facs="5418474_4_1034.jpg" n="2"/>road to victory and thus establish a much needed liberal, honest, and businesslike administration for the City of Chicago. The foregoing prompted us to the decision that all the German-Americans present at this meeting must seize every opportunity afforded then to assure the nomination of that able leader and fearless opponent of the gas clique, Carter H. Harrison, the dependable friend of the German people, Under his guidance, the April victory is certain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
