<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-03-19">Mar. 19, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Who Pays for Campaigns?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1229</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1229.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-03-19">Mar. 19, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">WHO PAYS FOR CAMPAIGNS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Campaigns were formerly one of the few redeeming moments in the life of a democratically ruled community. There was music, there were parades and fireworks, and above everything else, there was beer. Any one who marched in the parade or even carried an artistically designed and illuminated banner inscribed: "Vote for Mike Flannigan, the People's Friend," could rest assured that he would not have to suffer with thirst that glorious evening. The beer was bought with money that came from taxpayers' pockets, but it was kind of the politicians to return part of the people's property in liquid refreshment.</p>
   <p>This simple, primitive way of buying votes is no longer in vogue. Today a different method is used. Donating beer has been eliminated. However, votes cost a good deal more in our days. Congress furnished a remarkable example of vote-buying last week. As everybody knows, a congressional election will be held again in November, and since most of the present inmates of the Capitol have no objection to continuing their efforts in behalf of the people and to exhausting <pb facs="5418474_4_1230.jpg" n="2"/>themselves in the service of the public, they will be candidates for re-election.</p>
   <p>Campaigns cost money, and the first question that arises is, Where can the money be got? The nation's noblemen who sit in the Lower House of our august parliament have appropriated the goodly sum of $2,200,000,000 which the Government is to distribute in the form of green backs among our war veterans. There is little prospect that the bill which provides for the distribution of that amount of money will be passed; but that is not important. The important matter is that the members of the House of Representatives will have shown their good will, and later on, in the campaign, they will be able to point to their good intentions. After this very promising beginning the gentlemen's appetite for campaign money grew.</p>
   <p>So they decided simply to throw the Administration's economy measures, to which they had obligated themselves, into the wastebasket. Previously they had agreed to accept a reduction of fifteen per cent in their salaries. Now they have resolved to take back the noble sacrifice which they had placed on the altar of <pb facs="5418474_4_1231.jpg" n="3"/>their country in the interest of economy. Their immediate aim is to grant to the employee of Uncle Sam a five per cent increase in pay, a second increase of like proportion on July 1, and a third increase later--if the condition of the federal finances permits.</p>
   <p>Thus only five of the original fifteen per cent in salary reduction remains in force, and this remainder also is to be wiped out as soon as possible. Incidentally the members of Congress are also employees of the Federal Government. So they have granted themselves an immediate increase of five per cent and a further increase of like amount to begin July 1.</p>
   <p>Should one ask them for what purpose they need the money, they would probably answer that there is an election in November, and they need the money for the campaign. Since Congress has 531 members, the aforementioned law will provide the tidy sum of $531,000 for the campaign. Besides, it secures the good will of other federal employees, and that is by no means of small importance in an election.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1232.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Now the House of Representatives had the authority to do what it did. However, it is unfortunate that the people must bear the expense; but our high officials have long ago weaned themselves of consideration for taxpayers. In reality former campaign methods--music, parades, fireworks, and free beer--were much nicer. Above all, they were much cheaper and much more effective.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
