<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-09-18">Sep. 18, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A Difference between German Lutherans and Catholics on the School Question</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0547</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0547.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-09-18">Sep. 18, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A DIFFERENCE BETWEEN GERMAN LUTHERANS AND CATHOLICS ON THE SCHOOL QUESTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is not surprising that the recent Roman Catholic Bishop's pastoral, which was read in all the Illinois and Wisconsin Catholic churches last Sunday, has aroused much feeling among the German Lutherans and inspired the determination among the Lutheran laity to assert its independence of that clerical interference with purely secular affairs, which stood out so conspicuously in the pastoral. Mr. Gestefeld is unquestionably right, when he says in the interview printed in yesterday's Tribune - viz.,</p>
   <p>The German Lutherans will be affected in a manner, which neither the Catholic nor a great portion of the Lutheran clergy will relish. It will inevitably produce revival of a purely Protestant sentiment among the Lutheran laity, which will be of no advantage for their clergy. Among the Lutherans as well as in other dominations outside of Roman Catholicism, the pew is far more conservative and far more under the influence of tradition than is the pulpit.</p>
   <p>Lutheran ministers may not be frightened at the idea of a temporary alliance with the Roman Catholic church, which promises them a political recognition of the power of their own church; but their flock will absolutely refuse to follow them <pb facs="5418474_4_0548.jpg" n="2"/>into anything like friendly relations with the papal church. If there is one thing that is borne and bred into the bone of German Lutherans, it is opposition to ecclesiasticism of any kind, and, aside from the Baptists and Congregationalists, there is no Christian denomination as thoroughly democratic as is the Lutheran.</p>
   <p>There is a radical difference between the Lutheran and Roman Cathclic churches as regards the public schools and the question of taxation necessary or their support. The Lutherans are the old original friends of popular education and are in favor of compelling children to attend school and study the elementary branches. They were so in their own country. They have always been so in this. Their record on this point is time nonored and unbroken. While they wish their own schools for the religious instructions of their children, they are neartily in favor of the public schools though no religion is taught in them. They are willing to be taxed for their support, even when they do not patronize them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
