<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-02-06">February 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Mass_Petition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0491</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0491.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-02-06">February 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MASS_PETITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The old fight against the address book of the fanatics as the mass-petition of the prohibitionists was called in Chicago, must be renewed this year. Although it is hard to believe that the enemies of a legitimate sale in alcoholic drinks, at respectable inns, have collected sufficient incontestable signatures of registered citizens. Mass petition will be submitted to night, without any doubt, to the election commission and then it makes a start.</p>
   <p>Representatives of the decent retail liquor trade, and of the breweries, will most probably protest against the petition on technical and practicalgrounds and the election commission, respectively County Judge Owens, will finally decide whether the petition contains sufficient names to put to a vote the question: Shall the City of Chicago become an Anti-Saloon territory? The Secretary of the United Societies and Chief Reporter of the Municipal Court, Anthony J. Cermak shrugged his shoulders yesterday and expressed his opinion that the prohibitionist, this year as in former years, promised a mass-petition with sufficient names. But that they might fail again. " Up to the last <pb facs="5418474_4_0492.jpg" n="2"/>moment they try to encourage each other and to collect more signatures, more campaign material, and for all 'cash', " said the former representative and alderman, who has stood for years in the front lines in the fight against bigotry...</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
