<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-04-29">Apr. 29, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">Special Session of City Council</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-04-29">Apr. 29, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">SPECIAL SESSION OF CITY COUNCIL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Alderman Woodman presented an order for four hundred dollars in favor of Charles S. Perry for special services rendered as health officer during the past eight months. The order was unanimously approved.</p>
   <p>On recommendation of Alderman Comisky the Council reviewed the report on the election held April 21, 1863. It appeared that the following persons were elected to office.....</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The next paragraph of this article contains a detailed report on the election. In the next paragraph a summary report is given, and I shall select from it the names of Americans of German descent.]</p>
   <p>Friedrich Mehring, Collector, for two years; John Schank, Assistant Engineer of the Fire Department, for two years; Constantin Kann, Alderman of the Fifth <pb facs="5418474_4_1205.jpg" n="2"/>Ward, for two years; George Himrod, Alderman of the Tenth Ward, for two years; Christ Cusselmann, Alderman of the Twelfth Ward, for one year; David Aleckner, Alderman of the Thirteenth Ward, for one year; George von Hollen, Alderman of the Eleventh Ward, for two years; Valentin Ruh, Alderman of the Fourteenth Ward, for two years; Anton Hottinger, Alderman of the Fourteenth Ward, for one year; Henry Gymer, Constable of the Second Ward, for one year; M. Flemming, Constable of the Sixth Ward, for one year; Louis Herbst, Constable of the Twelfth Ward, for one year; John Hettinger, Constable of the Fourteenth Ward, for one year.</p>
   <p>Adjournment followed</p>
   <p>A. J. Marble, Clerk.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
