<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-03">Apr. 3, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">City Council Election of the Sixteenth Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-03">Apr. 3, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">CITY COUNCIL ELECTION OF THE SIXTEENTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Socialist candidate, Christian Meier, has been elected alderman from the Sixteenth Ward; he obtained a decided majority, while in former years not even a bare plurality could be registered for the Socialists.</p>
   <p>Meier owes his election to Democratic politicians like Schoeninger and Republicans like Schaffner, who insisted upon nominating an unpopular man at the Ward meeting, and did not rest until the incumbent, Schweisthal, was renominated.</p>
   <p>The majority of the people in the Sixteenth Ward are not Socialists, and a popular candidate place in a opposition to Keier, could easily have beaten him. But as there was only a choice between Schweisthal and Meier, hundreds of people voted for the Socialist, and justifiably so, because Meier is at least <pb facs="5418474_4_1131.jpg" n="2"/>not a tool of the temperance people and of the bigots; whereas Schweisthal, as a member of the City Council favored the "Snooping bill" which Mayor Health vetoed. Therefore many devout Catholics (hence, by no means Socialists) of St. Michael's and of St. Joseph's Church voted for Meier rather than for their own ardent fellow believer, Schweisthals.</p>
   <p>Dr. Schmidt, of course, also received a large majority of the Sixteenth Ward vote. But this can be attributed to his popularity. In contrast, the Socialist, Sibley, did not obtain as many votes as either the Republican or Democratic candidate for City Clerk, although many non-Socialists voted the straight Socialist ticket, as a favor to Mr. Schmidt, [mayoral candidate]. But despite the support given Schweisthal by the regular Ward politicians of both old parties, he had 212 votes less than the lowest number of ballots given to a Socialist in the Ward.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that Meier's conduct in the City Council will meet with the approval of the non-Socialists who voted for him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
