<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-01-24">Jan. 24, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Democrats Want German-Americans as Their Candidates E. J. Kruetgen and Oscar G. Mayer for the County Board but Both Decline</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1006</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1006.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-01-24">Jan. 24, 1930</date>.
<title level="a"> DEMOCRATS WANT GERMAN-AMERICANS AS THEIR CANDIDATES E. J. Kruetgen and Oscar G. Mayer for the County Board but Both Decline</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The democrats of Cook County intend to put up a list of candidates which probably will contain the following names: County Board, Michael Zimmer; County Treasurer, P. A. Nash; Sheriff, John E, Traeger, Jr: Clerk of Municipal Court, Joseph Gill; County Commissioners, Mrs.G. E. Plumb Oscar Mayer, Ernest Kruetgen, and Peter Augsten.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cermak, president of the County Board, so we have been informed, has invited Mr. Ernest Kruetgen to become a candidate for the office of County Commissioner. Mr. Kruetgen, however, declined this offer because he does not wish to hold a public office, according to our report.</p>
   <p>Mr. Oscar Mayer likewise refused to run as a candidate for the office of County Commissioner.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1007.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Cermak admitted that the Democratic party of Cook County would like to have these two prominent representatives of the German-American citizens of Chicago as candidates on their ticket. As these two gentlemen have refused, the party must seek two other prospective candidates of the same caliber.</p>
   <p>The Rodenberg Candidacy</p>
   <p>A meeting of prominent German-Americans and the delegates of various societies was held yesterday at the Steuben building. Possibilities were discussed of inducing William A. Rodenberg, former Congressman of E St. Louis, I11., a pronounced "wet" and a German-American, to accept the candidacy for United States Senator on the Republican ticket. Rodenberg has not yet given a definite answer, nevertheless it was resolved at yesterday's meeting to establish a Rodenberg headquarters at the Steuben building.</p>
   <p>William Rodenberg who was Congressman of his district for twenty years, retired voluntarily in 1923.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1008.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In case Rodenberg should accept the candidacy, four candidates will oppose each other on the Republican ticket: United States Senator Deneen, Congresswoman Hanna McCormick, Newton Jenkins, and Rodenberg.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
