<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-02-24">Feb. 24, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">Cameron, Amberg &amp; Co. a Fruitless Attempt to Begin the Investigation.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-02-24">Feb. 24, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">CAMERON, AMBERG &amp; CO. A Fruitless Attempt to Begin the Investigation.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Joint Committee appointed by the County Commissioners and the Citizens' Association to investigate the charges made some time ago by the Staats-Zeitung, was called for yesterday afternoon at two o'clock, in the rooms of the secretaries, who have been conducting a preliminary investigation.</p>
   <p>About an hour after the time set for the meeting, two County commissioners, Ayars and Hoffmann, and Mr. Field, of the Citizens' Association, had put in an appearance, Mr. McCaffrey and Mr. Franklin MacVeagh being out of town, and Mr. A. M. Wright being sick.</p>
   <p>Without waiting for the Committee to organize, Mr. Ambler, the Secretary, proceeded to read his report to the assemblage, which consisted, besides the gentlemen named, of Messrs. Cameron, Amberg, and Cushmann, supported by their counsel, Leonard Swett, and of Mr. Cestefeld, the representative of the Staats-Zeitung, and several newspaper reporters.</p>
   <p>The following is the report:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1514.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The secretaries, who were directed by the Joint Committee of the County Commissioners and the Citizens' Association to take such preliminary testimony in the examination of Cameron, Amberg &amp; Co.!s accounts with the County Board, so as to provide a basis for further and more explicit investigation, report that they have gone over, in the presence of the accused and the accusing parties, all the invoices and papers obtained from the County Clerk for the years 1874-'75-'76, and have compiled a list of all the objectionable items pointed out by the agent of Mr. Hesing, who brought the charge.</p>
   <p>They have also requested the said agent to file with them a detailed specification with the amounts of the alleged overcharges extended opposite each objectionable item, that they might embrace the same in their report to you; but as he has declined to comply with this request, they now ask further instructions.</p>
   <p>J. C. Ambler</p>
   <p>W. H. Hornaday</p>
   <p>After the document had been read, Mr. Gestefeld inquired if the members of the Committee who were present, considered themselves a quorum.</p>
   <p>Mr. Field thought not, and Mr. Commissioner Hoffmann moved that the Committee adjourn, as no quorum was present.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1515.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Leonard Swett rose and addressed the Committee at length. He thought that the members present could well decide the question whether Mr. Hesing should be required to file with the secretaries a specified statement of the charges he had to make against his clients. He desired very much that they would decide that this had to be done, as it would help much to facilitate business. There was, however, a legal question involved in this matter, which he thought this Committee was not competent to decide. The contract required Cameron, Amberg &amp; Co. to furnish certain articles at certain prices, some of them far below cost.</p>
   <p>Mr. Field thought the Committee would have to find out whether Cameron, Amberg &amp; Co. were guilty of the charges brought against them. Mr. Swett replied that no charges to which an answer could be given had been brought forward by Mr. Hesing, and his agent now refused to give them.</p>
   <p>Mr. Gestefeld then addressed the Committee. While he protested against having any arguments before a "rump" committee, whose action would be of no account, he desired to say something in reply to Mr. Swett.</p>
   <p>Access had been given the representative of the Staats-Zeitung to the documents which obtained full proof of the charges made, and he had pointed out to the secretaries in the course of the investigation such items as he considered needing <pb facs="5418474_4_1516.jpg" n="4"/>investigation on the part of the Committee. The same facility had been given to Messrs. Cameron, Amberg &amp; Co., who had noted down every item objected to. He thought he had furnished enough specifications, and preferred to withhold his evidence until the Committee was ready to receive it.</p>
   <p>The meeting then broke up, after a few fruitless efforts to set a day on which to meet again.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
