<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-10-05">Oct. 5, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Political Cinderella (Excerpts from Editionial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0775</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0775.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-10-05">Oct. 5, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLITICAL CINDERELLA (Excerpts from Editionial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among ten candidates as judges who were put up at the Democratic Convention yesterday, just one is of German origin. At least three candidates are, without doubt, of Irish origin and how many others have also Irish blood in their veins, may be inferred. The only German who was honored by this "Model convention," had to be proposed by the Irish "Colonel Donovan." So Ireland was so gracious to throw also a crumb to the Dutchman. The generous extent of these favors can only be evaluated by the one, who know that on the North side, which is bossed by "Colonel Donovan," for every nine Germans there is but one Irishman. And still, those nine-tenths can secure attention only with the so-called support of that one tenth! The Abendpost has no intention to start a race war against the Irish, or to say anything bad about them. What they amount to in politics, they owe, besides their own activity, chiefly to the indifference and laziness of the German voters. And nobody can be offended at their carrying their battle for existence into politics.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0776.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If anybody deserves to be rebuked, it is not the Irish but the Germans, who take offense that they are vassals of a clan, which is only superior to them by their boldness, but they do nothing at all to call attention to themselves. By this inactivity they commit, in fact, an injustice towards the land of their choice. It is their duty to this country to give their vigor, their knowledge and skill to public affairs, and not to let elements come to the foreground, which become degraded and corrupted through politics. No one is a good citizen in a democratic republic who only pays his taxes and possibly goes twice a year to the polling place. The principle of self-government becomes a farce, when so-called good citizens leave all political affairs to a gang of egotists who are politicians by trade.</p>
   <p>Through the humiliations to which the Germans in Chicago are repeatedly exposed, in spite of their numerical strength and their great economic importance, they should come to their senses and recognize their mistakes.</p>
   <p>Without organization, they will always remain the "Cinderella" which they have thus far been.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
