<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-05">Nov. 5, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Boess Case</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-05">Nov. 5, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOESS CASE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sklarek scandal in Berlin broadens in ever widening circles, and one cannot predict who will be involved in it. It is a sordid affair, not only for those who are directly concerned but the capital itself is adversely affected.</p>
   <p>Although there have been several scandals in Germany, the people there are not quite accustomed to them. Scandals in Germany are not as common as here. Perhaps such matters are taken more seriously in Germany than here, - Chicago, for instance. Of late Chicago has been rich on scandals, and this is a fact which no one can deny. We have had a large variety of them in our city. It was here that our public, the taxpayers, became indignant when we lanced one of these sore spots. We hinted an investigation, and the state's attorney's office pretended to be quite willing to hail the culprits before the courts.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1277.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But here this procedure represents a tortuous road, a veritably endless distance, and at best we drag a few scapegoats before the judge. And these accused men hardly know what it is all about, since they are only puppets.</p>
   <p>The real culprits are seldom apprehended and as a result they are quite indifferent about the scandals arising about them and remain serenely in office.</p>
   <p>Quite often public officials invite an investigation of their activities in order to clear themselves of suspicion. During the proceedings, they usually absent themselves from office and even resign until such a time as the affair is definitely settled.</p>
   <p>The Mayor of Berlin did this, although it appears there is little probability that he was in any way involved.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1278.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is said that some relatives had derived profits in business deals with the Sklareks. But these are assertions which require proof.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, upon his return to Berlin, Mr. Boess immediatedly entered a suit against himself and resigned until the case is settled.</p>
   <p>Now the truth can be ascertained, whether the city's leader is guilty of any infractions or whether the affair is just based on political machinations, as he and his supporters claim.</p>
   <p>That his political adversaries will capitalize on the occasion is of course natural, even when it is more than likely that their assertions are based on false rumors or exaggerations, and at most the Mayor can only be reproached for his laxity in not having exercised sufficient control over his subordinates.</p>
   <p>Such a supervision is just about impossible in a large city administration. <pb facs="5418474_4_1279.jpg" n="4"/>Like our Mayor Thompson in Chicago, the Mayor of Berlin has to depend on his department heads. The difference between Berlin and Chicago is simply this: In Berlin investigations and disciplinary measures are in the order of the day, and even the suspected parties institute action against themselves, regardless of whether they are guilty or not. In Chicago, however, either nothing happens or the State's attorney's office is let free to interfere in the incident or to ignore it.</p>
   <p>Usually the latter will be the case when political benefits demand it.</p>
   <p>A number of German newspapers in mentioning the Sklarek affair allude to it as a "hog pen." If, perchance, they would have to write about our politicians in similar cases, then they will be at a loss to find a suitable headline. Obviously, it behooves them to be a little more frugal with their strong exclamations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
