<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>.
<date when="1881-03-07">March 7. 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Stauber McGrath and the Illinois Staatszeitung.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>.
<date when="1881-03-07">March 7. 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Stauber McGrath and the Illinois Staatszeitung.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If any clear thinking person was still in doubt, as to the corruptness of the Illinois Staatszeitung, they must, after reading the article Stauber-McGrath, appearing in today's issue of that paper, alter their viewpoint, as to the honesty of the editors, of the paper mentioned. It is well known to this clique, that Frank A. Stauber, was the rightfully elected alderman of the 14th ward. They know, that on election day, in the presence of a number of witnesses and of a policeman, the election judges, who reported the result of the election, to the central bureau. The villians of the Staatszeitung knew, that the judges of the 7th precinct of the 14th ward, the night after the election, contrary to the law, and with the aid of swindler Malone opened the box containing the ballots, and changed them to suit their infamous designs, in other words, forged them. They, the felons of the Illinois Staats-zeitung knew, that the voters of the 7th precinct of the 14th ward, decided on Stan-ber's election, and that of the 116 votes cast for him, only 59 were given him by the election swindlers. Those criminals at the Illinois Staatszeitung also knew, that the election Judges Gibbs and Walsh, were committed to the criminal court, after a grand jury investigated the case, and pronounced them guilty. They also knew, that the majority of the corrupt city council, did not take much interest in the proceedings, connected with the examination of the Stauber's election contest, for they knew, that the rightful member of the city council, would be Stauber and not McGrath. They knew further, that citizen Linnemeier, who accused McGrath of swindling Stauber of votes, <pb facs="5418474_4_1476.jpg" n="2"/>for which he had proof, won the case against him, in Judge Moran's court. Notwithstanding all these facts, the vagabonds of that newspaper, shielded that swindler-companion McGrath; furthermore, they endeavored to put Stauber in a false light, one of suspicion, and to question the rightfulness of his case.</p>
   <p>This "criminally-inclined newspaper", in the words of their Party president Garfield, shall not be successful in their criminal plans against the Socialists. They are mistaken if they assume, that the Socialists can be swindled out of their rights. Furthermore, the Socialists are not satisfied merely with McGrath's removal from office, and the rightful holder Stauber installed, but the Socialists will not cease in this case, before they succeed in the dishonorable expulsion of McGrath. The Socialists will also see to it, that the election swindlers Gibbs and Walsh, in spite of their friendship with Mills and all the other swindlers of the city, shall get behind the prison doors. The Socialists will work unceasingly, toward the punishment of the corrupt and criminal gang, which has up to the present time, influenced the city council, and made it possible for McGrath, to fill the position which usurpt. The Socialists will also expose, all the persons guilty of dishonesty, and connected with the Illinois Staatszeitung, to the German population of Chicago. The Socialists have not yet closed the Stauber-McGrath case. The corrupt majority of the city Council, and the Illinois Staatszeitung, shall have a chance, to marvel at the energy, patience and ingenuity of the Socialists.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1477.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It requires time, but things will change for the better, and the election swindlers will feel the heavy hand of the Socialists, once and forever. -</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
