<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-07">Nov. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Electoral Corruption.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1392</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1392.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-07">Nov. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">ELECTORAL CORRUPTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From the headquarters of both of the large parties comes the alarm signal "The other party is trying to win the election by bribing the masses."</p>
   <p>These mutual suspicions will certainly not increase the respect of foreign countries for the United States. One thing, however, is certain, namely, that the Republican party has more means at its disposal for such a vile purpose, than the Democrats.</p>
   <p>It is, indeed, very fortunate that many of the states have in recent time introduced the Australian election system. This system makes bribery very difficult.</p>
   <p>In Illinois, for instance, the election agent is forbidden to come closer to the ballot box than one hundred steps. No voter can get a ballot on the out side, but it is given him inside, in the place of election, officially. Then he can secretly select his candidates upon the ballot in the booth, put it into the ballot box without any marks of recognition. Thus no man can control the votes of the citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1393.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even if a voter is sufficiently corrupt to accept a bribe, it is by no means certain that he will vote accordingly. It could, for instance, happen that a dirty member of the Democratic Party still might make his cross in the circle of the Democratic Party thus voting for all Democratic candidates, although blood money from Republicans may be in his pocket.</p>
   <p>Another form of much feared bribery is the practise of obligating voters of the opposing party not to vote, by giving them stipulated amounts of money. But how can the voters be prevented from voting under previously described conditions? And would voters be willing to expose themselves to the suspicion of being bribed?</p>
   <p>Similar election rules prevail now in many other states. The criminal law of Illinois disposes of these matters as follows: ...</p>
   <p>"It should not be very difficult to remove the much-mentioned and much-feared danger of mass-bribery, if sufficient carefulness and alertness prevails."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
