<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1929-12-08">Dec. 8, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">What Chicago Needs (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0419</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0419.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1929-12-08">Dec. 8, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT CHICAGO NEEDS (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The system of administration of the state, city, and county is such an involved and complicated affair that it represents at best a cumbersome machine, particularly when the various over-lapping functions are considered. Even under ordinary loads, the mechanism performs with difficulty, and when, as at present, extraordinary conditions present themselves, the separate parts refuse to function at all. If this continues, the contraption will break down completely.</p>
   <p>The responsible factors are first and foremost our deplorable boodle politics, secondly the diverging interests between city and county, <pb facs="5418474_4_0420.jpg" n="2"/>finally the immense increase in population.</p>
   <p>In earlier years, when most of the people lived on farms or in hamlets, the system was satisfactory. At that time, everybody knew the candidates personally and could make his selection accordingly. This condition does not prevail today. The officials elected are unseen. and for this reason, an ever-increasing array of officers are inducted into public positions--an array consisting of men who, for one reason or another, are unsuitable. And obviously, in performing their work, they do more harm than good.</p>
   <p>In the old days it was customary for the state to interfere in the administration of small communities; at least such powers were vested in the state, although they were rarely applied. In managing a city of the size of Chicago, the exercise of such powers would undoubtedly prove detrimental, particularly since these laws have multiplied in the course <pb facs="5418474_4_0421.jpg" n="3"/>of years.</p>
   <p>Is it not plain nonsense that the state is authorized through its transportation commission to interfere with the streetcar system of the city? And that even the government has the right to dictate fares within the confines of a municipality, should a local company see fit to appeal to a federal court?</p>
   <p>This complicated system has succeeded in establishing within Cook County several hundred public corporations endowed with taxing powers. And now we face the spectacle of administration branches fighting about "who" should repair a certain street and why it should be repaired. Consequently, the street is impassable for months and remains closed to traffic. Such conditions are intolerable in a cosmopolitan city.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0422.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Every one of these hundreds of bureaus has its own tax-supported officials. How many would be dispensable if the entire county, or at least the city, were ruled by a single administration?</p>
   <p>As matters stand, all these superfluous employees countermand and counteract each other thereby retarding Chicago's progress. Then a Chicago bureau chief gives an order, one may be reasonably certain that the ruler of another department will withhold his assent. And since the ponderous system needs this additional signature, the work must be postponed until circuitous methods provide a solution. Affairs of that kind could and should have been settled long ago.</p>
   <p>One official announces that he intends to perform certain necessary labors for which he desires funds. The next asserts he knows nothing <pb facs="5418474_4_0423.jpg" n="5"/>about it, and finally the treasurer refuses to make any disbursements fearing he may be held personally liable. In this manner Chicago will revert to the wilderness era.</p>
   <p>After all, the treasurer's apprehensions are not groundless, nor are they as illogical as may appear at first. Every Chicagoan knows how money has been squandered of late, and the treasurer is again fully aware that public's patience is exhausted and that administration expenditures are being closely scrutinized. It is not his fault if essential work must be omitted. If he has scruples about spending money, especially when the expenditures called for are not specifically authorized and are of doubtful legality, then he not only protects himself against prosecution, but he actually acts in the interests of the public. He is merely performing his duty. The delays are solely due to the system, a complicated maze through which even the officials cannot make headway. <pb facs="5418474_4_0424.jpg" n="6"/>And an even worse plight is in store for the public.</p>
   <p>The fact that the city and county administration presents such an involved, laborious structure enables dishonest politicians to pursue their clandestine fishing in murky waters. Unperturbed, they garner profits at the taxpayer's expense.</p>
   <p>In other city affairs we face almost equally serious difficulties. A part of our political gentry (the public seems pretty sure about this matter) seeks the support of the criminal element which always gathers in cosmopolitan cities.</p>
   <p>Our baneful prohibition amendment has done much to increase such knavery. If unprincipled politicians form an unholy alliance with <pb facs="5418474_4_0425.jpg" n="7"/>scoundrels, then they are honor bound eventually to express their gratitude. And this, too, occurs, manifesting itself in devious ways. Numerous court cases provide us with ample evidence: consider just how often the real culprit is apprehended. Even during the prosecution of criminals, the influence of these henchmen, who are never brought to the fore, manifests itself. And here the antiquated legal Modus Operandi asserts itself for their benefit. The state law to the rescue!</p>
   <p>Laws and jurisprudence protect the defendant more than the plaintiff. In no other land can procedures be so continually deferred, oftentimes as much as thirty times or more. They drag along for years, until all important witnesses have died or moved, thus leaving the prosecution powerless while the accused emerges as a free man.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0426.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>American judges have had an opportunity recently to observe Canadian procedure. They were awe-struck by the inexorable promptness prevailing there, by the quick retribution which followed the perpetration of a crime. But our judicial mechanism is so corroded that it cannot fulfil its task, even if judge and prosecutor try their utmost. Such an effort, however, is not usual, since they, too, are elected officials and as such are under political influence.</p>
   <p>The only solution for the present plight affecting our citizens consists in a radical simplification of the administrative and judicial organization, as well as a general purging of all offensive elements.</p>
   <p>Fewer candidates should be elected, and those in office should give proof of their labors. An honest budget should be drawn up and adhered to. All juggling and transferring of funds must cease. Loans by subterfuges <pb facs="5418474_4_0427.jpg" n="9"/>which circumvent the taxpayer's wishes should be definitely eliminated. Judicial affairs need simplification, and punitive measures must not be subjected to the usual delays.</p>
   <p>Judicial candidates should not be nominated by parties. Their selection ought to depend on appointment. An authorative body of legal luminaries or experts, or some committee which can guarantee the candidate's qualifications should be entrusted with their selection, not a group of power-thirsty, money-hungry politicians.</p>
   <p>Every conceivable political influence must be abolished wherever the judiciary is concerned.</p>
   <p>While these reforms do not cover every contingency, they nevertheless provide a beginning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
