<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-21">May 21, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Good and Bad News</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Germans Shall Be Satisfied</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1123</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1123.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-21">May 21, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD AND BAD NEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Germans Shall Be Satisfied</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since Monday, the beginning of Mayor Harrison's term, he spent days and days with office seekers, was besieged by friends of politicians who supported the party and so there was practically no time for official business. Yesterday there was a lull, comparatively speaking, although there was always someone present who wanted to put in a good word for himself or a friend; but there were no delegations, and so this reporter had a chance to speak with the Mayor.....</p>
   <p>Reporter: "It appears surprising that you have not yet appointed a German to office, and it is rumored that you intend to ignore the Germans entirely."</p>
   <p>Harrison: "You will do me a great favor, if you declare that the job of oil inspector is to be given only to a German, a German of the North Side. At first, I intended to draw lots, because three gentlemen were well recommended, but I discarded the idea. Shortly before the council held its session, <pb facs="5418474_4_1124.jpg" n="2"/>information was given me--facts I had to know--but rest assured no one but a German will be given that position,"</p>
   <p>Reporter: "And what about the gas inspector?"</p>
   <p>Harrison: "So far I have had no time to consider the matter. There are several applicants, but I am not in a hurry. As far as I know, Mr. Siebel, a German, is on that job, and the longer I postpone the appointment, the better for the Germans. The same applies to the weighmaster, Mr. Karls. One can readily see, I am in no hurry to make a change. The Germans shall have no cause for complaining!"</p>
   <p>In continuing the interview, the mayor repeated that he does not intend to make any changes....in subordinate positions until the various department chiefs have become thouroughly familiar with the work.</p>
   <p>The reporter then saw the new comptroller, J. F. Gurney, who was "very glad to meet a representative of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung".....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1125.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The next interview was with Building Commissioner Waller.</p>
   <p>He is of a dignified appearance and likes to quote the Bible; one of his traits is modesty. He declared that he is fully aware that he must learn much to do justice to his position, but he hopes that with his long experience with contracts and public business he will become a capable and useful official of the city. He said he is not proud because he was given this position, but that he will be after having served the term in a conscientious manner.</p>
   <p>In regard to changes in personnel, he said that this will not be done until he has become thoroughly familiar with all phases, and any such changes will be be made by the Mayor.</p>
   <p>The reporter could not locate the new city collector, William J. Onahan. Onahan has appointed Charles White, the former cashier, as first assistant, and will have an opening for the former assistant coroner, Captain Girr.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
