<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-27">Mar. 27, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Local Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0320</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0320.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-27">Mar. 27, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">LOCAL POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republican Club of the Sixteenth Ward held its meeting yesterday at 311 Larrabee Street. Fred. Karstens presided, and a fairly large crowd was present. Prior to the arrival of the speakers, various persons entered into a discussion of the aldermanic question and several protests were registered against Schweisthal because he always sided with the monopolies. The chairman declared such conversation to be out of order. Then Colonel Scribner gave a lengthy speech, highly recommending Schweisthal.....</p>
   <p>General Schaffner then explained why the Republican Club had nominated a Democrat for alderman. He said no capable Republican was willing to accept the nomination and there was no alternative but to nominate Alderman Schweisthal again, since he had proved himself to be an excellent member of the City Council, and never had been influenced by party politics.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0321.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Alderman Schweisthal was present and spoke also. He regretted that his nomination caused dissention. He did not seek the nomination, but accepted upon insistence of the Republicans. Continuing, the gentleman expressed awareness of the fact that the nomination also met with objections in Democratic ranks, because of his [Schweisthal's] refusal to recommend a Democratic worker for the office of street inspector in place of the Republican, Imhoff, who is filling it very satisfactorily at present, and because he [Schweisthal] could not be induced to make campaign contributions to the Democrats last fall. Schweisthal did not make these donations because certain Democratic candidates did not appeal to him. Likewise, said the alderman, Mr. Washington Hesing had also spoken in a derogatory manner about the candidacy because of Schweisthal's strict adherence to policies of reform and economy, which had prompted him [Schweisthal] to give all of the city's printing work to the lowest bidder rather than to the Staats-Zeitung. The alderman said that he hopes to be elected, regardless of the opposition, and promised to prove to the citizens that the welfare of the ward as well as that of the entire city, is his sole interest. Adjournment followed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
