<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-11-09">Nov. 9, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">German's Achieve a Great Victory</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0811</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0811.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-11-09">Nov. 9, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN'S ACHIEVE A GREAT VICTORY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>November 8, 1892 will remain a day of proud memories for the Germans. The German votes are chiefly responsible for the overthrow of the Republican party, which is the party of the monopolists and the alien-haters. Thus, the voters aided Grover Cleveland, the representative of true liberty and justice, to his brilliant victory. Thanks is due to the Germans of Illinois, that this old Republican state decided in favor of Cleveland.</p>
   <p>The success of the Germans in regard to the state election is equally outstanding. Notwithstanding the most desparate efforts of the opponents, their bitter attacks, and the disloyalty of strictly English-American election districts, Altgeld is the victor. This is a triumph also for the German school the German language, and for the equal rights of Germans in general. Polish and Czech voters cooperated with the Germans of Illinois most heartily and energetically. A large share of this glory of triumph belongs to them.</p>
   <p>The Democratic party must never forget, that the achievement of such colossal results would have been unthinkable without the aid of the large groups of <pb facs="5418474_4_0812.jpg" n="2"/>independent voters. It is therefore its sacred duty to carry out those principles, which induced the independent citizens to cast their votes in favor of the Democrats.</p>
   <p>In connection with this the Illinois Staats-Zeitung may assert without boasting that these brilliant victories within and without the state are likewise her victories. It is the most extraordinary election victory to her credit since November, 1873. At that time she recaptured a free Sunday for Chicago. Now she helped to fight very effectively in the struggle to uphold and preserve liberty and equality for the foreign-born citizens, whose welfare also affect the welfare of the republic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
