<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-08-31">Aug. 31, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Altgeld Exposes the Lies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-08-31">Aug. 31, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">ALTGELD EXPOSES THE LIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have reported already how the Republican party press hounds (yellow press in English) heaped calmany on Altgeld and tried to make out a case. First he was a Socialist and Anarchist, then a greedy millionaire who demands his rents in pure gold and finally, he was not even a soldier.</p>
   <p>Altgeld, who does not interfere with the slander press and lets it continue until it becomes lest in its own meshes, replied again to one of those lies yesterday. He has been pictured as an enemy of the workers and that, in spite of the fact that Altgeld has shown great interest in the labor question years before he ever thought of becoming a candidate for the Governer's office. His speeches and articles on social problems - for the betterment of the labor situation are among the best on the subject.</p>
   <p>The Republicans circulate a story that in the construction of the Unity Building, he used convict-labor and that at present he is exacting a building for $75,000, the material of which has likewise come from the penitentiary.</p>
   <p>Judge Altgeld replied to this yesterday, in the following manner:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1096.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A web of lies, from beginning to end: Every part of that building has been made or handled by union labor only. I am not building a new house. During the construction of the Unity Building, every contractor was required to use union labor. All marble work was furnished by Sherman and Flavin who own and operate their stone cutting establishment; none of these parts ever saw the Joliet prison.</p>
   <p>It was my ambition, and its realization cost me considerable money, to create a building in the Unity Block which was constructed by union labor in its entirety.</p>
   <p>I am not inclined to pay much attention to all the barking of the unconscientious, slanderous party press, but this calumny needs a reply, if only for the sake of my friends, who are defenders of free labor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
