<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-09">Nov. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Rejection of the Traction Ordinance (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-09">Nov. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE REJECTION OF THE TRACTION ORDINANCE (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of the expensive advertising which certain interested persons and circles found themselves called upon to publish in favor of the ordinance for the reform of the city's traffic facilities; in spite of long-winded editorials in the great daily newspapers, the citizens of Chicago have rejected this much-praised compromise politely but firmly. They would not let themselves be fooled, even if the future of the city's traffic--should the Fisher Plan not be adopted--was painted in dark and dismal colors. According to Virgil, even the old Trojans did not trust the Greeks bringing gifts. Why should the citizens of Chicago, who have had the worst experiences imaginable with the traction companies, not also be imbued with an ineradicable distrust of these companies? It would be a miracle if it were otherwise. The fact that certain personages and political powers <pb facs="5418474_4_0466.jpg" n="2"/>tried to move heaven and earth to accomplish their ends, would have made a blind person suspicious, and would have made him all the more convinced that the proposal should be rejected.</p>
   <p>And, without doubt, it was the smartest thing for the citizens to do. The proposed plan contained too much camouflage to give hope for an ideal solution of that unpleasant problem. And the traction companies have fooled the people too often with the charters granted them, and with their agreements, for citizens to fail to see the joker now. The citizens of Chicago want to put an end to this unpleasant traction problem, once and for all, by taking over the companies themselves and they want to do it without camouflage, such as they regarded the proposed management by traction and bank presidents to be. They will still have to wait a few years until this is possible. But, after all, what difference does that make? They have had plenty of opportunity to practice patience and the time until the charters expire will not last forever.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0467.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But the citizens can surely expect the traction companies to approach them with new proposals and compromises more and more frequently as the expiration dates draw near. It remains to be seen whether an agreement would then be advisable.</p>
   <p>But, regardless of whether we have to wait for the charters to expire or whether a compromise is made, the citizens should insist under all circumstances, that the rules of the charters now in force be carried out in detail. It is erroneous to assume that the citizens will have to be contented with inadequate transportation now that the agreement has fallen through. The public has the power to demand, from the streetcar company as well as the elevated company, a strict adherence to the statutes. All that is necessary is that enough pressure be put on their representatives in the City Council to cause the city to use its authority, something that has not happened yet. At no time do the <pb facs="5418474_4_0468.jpg" n="4"/>citizens have to hang on straps in crowded "sardine cans," or wait for dawdling streetcars on windy street corners two and three times longer than the official schedule calls for; or tolerate the unspeakably filthy cars. It is only necessary to overcome this sheeplike patience and to step emphatically on the toes of the city fathers, to see this pressure directed where it belongs. For it is their duty as representatives of the citizens to see to it that agreements concluded with the latter are kept not only by the city but also by the party of the second part.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
