<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-01-08">Jan. 8, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">[Judicial Lakity]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1511</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1511.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-01-08">Jan. 8, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">[JUDICIAL LAKITY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The miserable court procedure appears again in its crass reality as shown by the Court of Appeals in the City's suit against Gage's bondsmen. Because of a technical error which crept in when the application for bond was made, (that is, bond was not offered exactly within the prescribed period nor in acceptable form, and the city council not suspicious of anything, accepted the security), it now develops that Cage and his bondsman are to go Scot free, while a hundred thousand taxpayers will be condemned to pay a loss of $600,000. Very wise, ye noble and just judges:</p>
   <p>All that is missing now is an eulogistic comment on the part of our judicial leaders, in consideration of the fact that Gage did not take all the money which came into his possession. According to the Court's verdict, Gage was entitled to all of the money. Gage was not a city treasurer anymore, because he offered bond too late--missed by a few days. Consequently, he [Gage] was a plain citizen <pb facs="5418474_4_1512.jpg" n="2"/>and if the City was so foolish as to entrust as to entrust him with its funds, then it would have been perfectly proper, if he had refused to return even a single cent.</p>
   <p>Verily, if one reads about such decisions, then one understands the attitude of the ancient Germans after the Heamann battle--when the tongues of Roman lawyers were split or perforated with glowing pins--and that, in modern times, "contempt of court become increasingly frequent.</p>
   <p>It appears if the courts actual seek public disdain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
