<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-04-06">Apr. 6, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The Result of the City Elections</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0866</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0866.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-04-06">Apr. 6, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THE RESULT OF THE CITY ELECTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's city elections, which followed the presidential election so closely, showed that the two are absolutely independent of each other. Chicago had cast a majority vote of 5,000 at the presidential election, but increased that majority vote yesterday when it elected the Democratic mayor.</p>
   <p>The principle points in the defeat of the Republican candidate for mayor were these:</p>
   <p>1... Bold Klu-Kluxing in wards, especially in wards one and two, in which gambling dens and other low variety entertainments are under the protection of Mayor Harrison. The Republican voters of these wards have not been extended more courtesy at the polling places, than is extended to the Negroes in the South. Of course the "repeaters" attended strictly to their business too, supplying the party with as many votes, as was deemed necessary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0867.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>2......large number of the American Republicans, namely, the Grant-Logen men, were only slightly interested in our city elections; any have not voted at all. Harrison himself is honest enough to admit that he owes his election to this last mentioned fact.</p>
   <p>3... The infamous lies spread by the dischivous Daily News about the Republican candidate. Whose lies created the wrong impression among the Germans, that Clark. if elected, would become a tool for the temperance advocates. And the publication of the supposed statement by Mr. Clark, that he is determined to enforce the State Sunday laws, was also a malicious invention of that paper. Moreover, that scandalous paper went on spreading lies by stating that Clark had made encouraging promises to the same effect to Mrs.Carse, whom he had actually never seen. The News was finally forced to admit that those statements were fictitious; this acknowledgement, however was made after the damage done had become irreparable. The saying: "A bold lie with enough of backing is just as effective as though it were the truth," is well applied here.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0868.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>4... The Socialists, whose votes were controlled by Grottkau and his companions, were bought for the democratic mayor. Their votes may be compared to merchandise, over which their leadors may freely dispose. Nevertheless, this is certain, that in the future the Socialists' votes can not be disregarded. Of course, not all the voters belonging to the Socialist party could be bought, but they do follow their leaders blindly, and without questioning their intregrity.</p>
   <p>5... Considering the successful election of the Republican alderman, we arrive at the conclusion, that in order to make their own election certain, they could not give the expected support to Mr. Clark, the Republican candidate for mayor.</p>
   <p>Thus the defeat of the Republican ticket is explained. That Mr. Harrison ascribes his re-election to his great superiority, is beyond doubt. Moreover, he considers his re-election as proof of public confirmation of his boast that Chicago has never before had a more perfect mayor than he is. We are, however, of a different opinion, but he has been given two more years; ample time to reform.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
