<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-05-03">May 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Necessity of Organizing.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-05-03">May 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NECESSITY OF ORGANIZING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are living in an age when organizations and associations have become everyday occurrences. That which is beyond the reach of the individual man, is sought to be reached by joining forces. This is the basic principle of every company of shareholders as well as of every trust company. Political, social and art societies, have been founded upon the same principle, and so have church organizations. In turn, each of these organizations is run by the so-called "machine" which works toward reaching the goal, for its respective association.</p>
   <p>The German Democrats of Chicago have also joined forces, to do their share of agitation, toward the forthcoming election campaign. They united for the purpose of indorsing Bryan and "free silver" and to agitate against the trusts, and expansion. These German Democrats have done the best thing possible, in their effort for final success. The German can only, when strengthened by unity, exercise their influence upon the political parties of their choice.</p>
   <p>The German Republicans have found their political adversaries' action so <pb facs="5418474_4_0168.jpg" n="2"/>praiseworthy, that they decided to follow their example. They will organize, not only in Cook County, but throughout the State of Illinois, to from a close phalanx.... The citizens of a Republic are the makers of their own political structures. The Germans could not boast of much, if they could not be thoroughly convinced, that they, as a politically organized group, could exercise influence upon the party with which they are associated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
