<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-07-06">July 6, 1876</date>,
<title level="a">Fourth of July Speech by Edmund Jussin.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-07-06">July 6, 1876</date>,
<title level="a">FOURTH OF JULY SPEECH BY EDMUND JUSSIN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>My German-American fellow citizens:</p>
   <p>I accepted your invitation, as a free citizen of this Republic without fear of the party whip to tell the whole unpainted truth. Finally I am here with you, my German-American friends, to face this misfortune and this disgrace dauntlessly and to consult with you, how we could cure the disease, which endangers the life of the Republic, in the quickest and safest way.</p>
   <p>Scarcely had the public in its illusion, what a great general also must be a great statesman, elected the present president, when the cause of corruption bon. The St. Domingo speculation, the credit mobilier and the pious Schuyler Colfax, the infamous arms trade with France, and the whole immense swindling at the New York Custom House were some of the few rotten excrescences of his first term in office. The whole army of his partisans, at the hend the leading administration politicians, shouted their approbation and with <pb facs="5418474_4_1521.jpg" n="2"/>the help of the well oiled civil service machine elected him for his second term as chief executive of the Republic. Now the dance began at its best. The corruption began to expand in such a manner and way, it grew into such a horrible bcess on the body politics of the Republic, that on account of its weight and expansion it finally burst. And out crept the war Secretary Belknap and the private Secretary Babcock, then countless members of the whiskey ring and at last the brilliant Mr. Blaine, Speaker of the House of Representatives and Republican Presidential candidate. I said the abcess burst from its own weight. Let me be just and truthful. Only one doctor was present, who gave a helping hand and at a spot made a powerful incision, Benjamin H. Bristow, the only man of the party, who had the courage to set the knife and cut away the cancerous ulcer, and as recompense and thanks for doing the country a great service, he was thrown overboard by the ruling party.</p>
   <p>It has come so far in many districts of the country that the prospective candidate is not judged by his ability, but by the large sums he is able to distribute amongst his voters and the so much praised ballot boxes have become a bare farce, and have tarnished our good name in foreign countries. Go over to <pb facs="5418474_4_1522.jpg" n="3"/>Germany and listen towhat they have to say about us. Twenty five years have gone by since I said goodbye to the old fatherland, and as a matured man, as an enthusiastic partisan of the Republican form of government I touched again for the first time my native soil. I thought to find amongst the men of Germany many disguised Republicans, but not one has revealed himself to me in my two years sojourn. And with the exception of the Social Democrats, Germany has no Republicans. Even the rebels of 1848 become good monarchists, and put the constitution 1 monarchy far above the Republican form of government.</p>
   <p>Above all we do not want to be led about by the nose by unscrupulous politicans, and by those who maintain that the union is in danger of being dissolved by Southern slave barons. The war is happily over, the rebellion is dead as a door nail and they can not make us believe, that it is necessary to chew the old argument of 1864 again. Should the time come again for which at present there is not even the remotest possibility, the German Americans would be the first at the place where the drums are sounded to join the colors of the union. Meanwhile, the time has come to fight an evil, which is more important, and that <pb facs="5418474_4_1523.jpg" n="4"/>is the all destroying corruption that has penetrated into all ranks..The first step in that direction should be the election of an energetic man as chief executive, a man, who has proven his ability as reformer, and from whom it is to be feared, that he would permit corrupt congressmen to obstruct his plans of reform. The platform does not do it, the man himself must be the guarantee of the reform.</p>
   <p>Who this man is, who alone of the up to now nominated candidates it could be, I leave to your own judgment.</p>
   <p>However with the restoration of honest officials our task is not colored yet, we also ask for honest money, no faithless, lying paper promises, of which every decent business man would be ashamed, if it were carrying his name. What concerns this point so are the German-Americans in so complete agreement that it is unnessary, to lose one word about it. The German by birth has so thoroughly honest a nature, that these paper deceptions always have been repugnant to him.</p>
   <p>Another mighty question I would mention, of which in the near future we must obtain a solution. I mean the complete and unlimited religious and social freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1524.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Since the last 25 years we have in always recurring struggles fought against Sunday sulkers and believers in temperance, but so far the enemy has not been quite conquered, and we should lose no opportunities, either in private or in public life to impress upon those gentlemen with the pointed noses, sharp cut lips and white collars the German point of view, and at every election we should break thru their thin lines with a strong German phalanx. And with the same energy with which we reject the assumption of the sulkers and hypocrites, we also should fight, at any time or any place, encroachments of any religious sect, no matter which one, on our public school system, because our public non-denominational schools are one of the strongest pillars of our freedom the guarantee of tolerance and of the complete separation of church and state.</p>
   <p>These are a few of the most important problems confronting us in the jubilee year of the centennial festival of American independence. I know, that the German-American especially joins in the fight with enthusiasm, to fulfill his duty, because the Germans more than any other element of this great nation is the leaven of reform, and values the principle of morality in politics, true progress and true freedom higher than all the riches of the world and higher than property, home and money.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
