<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-03-13">Mar. 13, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Plight of the Drainage Commission</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1288</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1288.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-03-13">Mar. 13, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE PLIGHT OF THE DRAINAGE COMMISSION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is no new revelation that the city's Drainage Commission is in great financial difficulties. However, the Commission itself seems to have been, until recently, quite oblivious of its dilemma. That department did not concern itself in the past about the sources from which funds must be eventually obtained in order to comply with the Federal Government's demands for a sanitary sewage-disposal plant and in order to operate the plants already completed.</p>
   <p>In order to procure funds in any form, it has been necessary since January 1 that the taxpayers and citizens agree on money appropriations through a referendum. The Drainage Commission is naturally opposed to this procedure, and has therefore made a plea to the State legislature to lift the existing restrictions. The Commission naturally expected consideration of its plea <pb facs="5418474_4_1289.jpg" n="2"/>by the recently elected legislators, despite the fact that many of these were incumbents.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, the plea as presented is audacious in its every aspect. The Commission announces its inability to fulfill agreements because of the lamentable lack of funds, and therefore requests to be permitted--in defiance of existing laws and without the consent of the voters--to make new loans, such loans being necessary if the sanitary sewage-disposal plant is to be constructed. However, no explanation or accounting is given in the bill for the empty safe,nor is it explained why no funds are now available. Moreover, the Drainage Commission did not make the slightest attempt at a plausible excuse for the criminal mismanagement prevalent up to the November election. Such detestable conduct in administrative affairs naturally provoked the voters, who decided against further appropriations for the sewage-disposal plant.</p>
   <p>It cannot be denied that the present members of the Drainage Commission are <pb facs="5418474_4_1290.jpg" n="3"/>vastly different from those who used millions of dollars of public money for political graft. Notwithstanding the fact that some new blood has been injected into the veins of the management--blood which we sincerely hope is less tainted--no complete change has been effected thus far, and only the future will prove whether the new element will predominate and will indefinitely control the Commission's actions. The citizens are, of course, skeptical and mistrustful, and any move on the part of the Drainage Commission to regain a free hand in money matters, will meet with strong opposition....</p>
   <p>The funds required for the erection of the sanitary sewage-disposal plant ordered by the Federal Government must be made available. It is hardly possible to retrieve the money which public officials have squandered, and thus taxpayers are obliged once more to supply funds for the structure in question. Proper measures for the control of expenditures, which would also guard against repetitions of misappropriations of public funds, must <pb facs="5418474_4_1291.jpg" n="4"/>be taken. If this advice is not heeded, millions of dollars might again flow through channels having nothing to do with the present purpose.. . . However, debts incurred by the Drainage Commission should not be paid from funds which must now be raised. This question will be discussed later, when the persons guilty of spending public funds without any accounting shall be exposed. It may not be too late to recover some of the squandered money.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
