<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-02">Nov. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">West Side and Lincoln Park (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0428</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0428.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-02">Nov. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">WEST SIDE AND LINCOLN PARK (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At next Tuesday election, citizens of the West Side and the northeastern part of the city are called to vote on a bond issue of the Park Board; in fact, two bond issues are to be decided by the voters.</p>
   <p>The West Side Chicago Park Commission wants to build a so-called super highway and, as the work involves an expenditure of twenty million dollars, a bond issue becomes necessary. The plan has been amply commented by the press and has been the subject of discussion at many civic meetings. Opinion is divided. Some consider it desirable and recommend it while others have serious scruples about it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0429.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even the residents of the West Side do not favor it unanimously. They contend that such a highway is not likely to benefit their particular section. It is more apt to benefit the central part of Chicago and districts of the near West Side, in other words, only the downtown area.</p>
   <p>That the West Side is bound to have certain benefits is of course not denied, but whether these benefits are commensurate with such tremendous expenditures, presents a very doubtful problem.</p>
   <p>The Abendpost regards this proposition like all previous ones. It admonishes its readers to take particular heed of the city's present financial condition and of the fact that the country's treasury is in no better shape.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0430.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After all, twenty million dollars is a large sum, and the citizens of the West Side should seriously consider the proposition before deciding to shoulder such a tremendous debt and responsibility.</p>
   <p>The bond issue involving Lincoln Park has found considerable favor among the interested landowners of that district. The bonds are popular there. There exists also the probability that the present bond issue of three million dollars will be favorably voted upon. The money is to be used for park improvements, or rather, to extend our park system.</p>
   <p>But also in this case the Abendpost considers it its duty to make a recommendation to its readers, namely, don't vote for this bond issue until you have thoroughly considered the present financial situation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
