<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-22">Dec. 22, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Denouement at Springfield (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0402</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0402.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-22">Dec. 22, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">DENOUEMENT AT SPRINGFIELD (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Springfield legislature has adjourned until the end of its term. On January 4 of the coming year, the newly elected legislature convenes to resume its work. There will be much to do, for the old legislature failed to do much of the work it should have done.</p>
   <p>Of the large number of laws recently passed, there are a few which stand out. Of importance for Cook County was the replacement of five appraisers by one man and the change in the board of revisions. This change, made at the instance of private creditors of the debt-encumbered public offices, met with very strong resistance in the legislature. It was delayed for a long time, but finally the legislature had to submit to the financial dictatorship of the large banks. The appraisers, Just elected, lost their jobs, The tax planning is now in the hands of the one elected appraiser, Jacobs, who has so far distinguished himself <pb facs="5418474_4_0403.jpg" n="2"/>by his insight and vigor.</p>
   <p>The second act of the legislature was the repeal of the state laws on prohibition. This bill has not become a law as yet, for Governor Emmerson had the nerve to oppose the will of the people and to veto the bill. But the attitude of the legislature is proof that the idea of prohibition has, in the State of Illinois, begun to shake on its foundations. At a time when the out-come of the presidential and congressional elections could only by guessed at, this was a valuable feather in the cap of the opponents of prohibition. As the veto was the work of a Republican governor, it did much to estrange the voters of the state from the Republicans and to drive them into the camp of the Democrats. This had a great deal to do with the Democratic victory of last November. Emmerson's veto bore fruit. Had the bill been signed, the results of the election might have been different.</p>
   <p>The legislature accomplished very little toward the solution of important taxation problems. For a long time there has been talk of introducing state income <pb facs="5418474_4_0404.jpg" n="3"/>taxes. There was a sharp conflict over this issue, but finally a bill providing for state income taxes was passed. Governor Emmerson signed the bill, but it was declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court of the state. Sales taxes did not get even that far, because the majority in the legislature was against them. The legislature seemed maladroit in general as far as taxes were concerned. They could not understand that it has become necessary to subject the state's entire fiscal legislation to a fundamental revision. The attempt to doctor up particular sections was foredoomed to failure. It is not the individual taxes that need changing, but the entire system of taxation which is anchored in the state constitution. The introduction of modern fiscal legislation is impossible without the calling of a constitutional convention, which has been due for some time. The new governor will perhaps make an effort to bring it about.</p>
   <p>The new legislature neglected to reapportion the election districts in accordance with the results of the last census of the population. This reapportionment, for which we have been waiting for decades, and which has always been <pb facs="5418474_4_0405.jpg" n="4"/>impeded by the rural majority in the legislature, is a striking breach of the state constitution, which provides for reapportionment after each census. This would prevent densely populated Chicago and Cook County, as well as the adjacent counties, from receiving representation in the state legislature which corresponds with the numbers of their population. The popular majority of the Chicago district is still represented by a minority in the legislature. Here, too, the new legislature is facing an important task as soon as the weighty problems caused by the difficult circumstances now prevailing have been disposed of.</p>
   <p>No one is going to weep for the old legislature. The things it achieved were, in general, mediocre. It remains to be seen whether the new one is going to be any better.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
