<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-09-14">Sept. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Deutsch-Amerikanische Demokratische Organisation Von Cook County, Inc.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0085</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0085.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-09-14">Sept. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">DEUTSCH-AMERIKANISCHE DEMOKRATISCHE ORGANISATION VON COOK COUNTY, INC.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At Bismarck Hotel, Tuesday, September 18, there will be a big meeting to recruit members, to which all German-speaking Democrats are cordially invited.</p>
   <p>It is in the interest of citizens of German descent that we secure as many members as possible for our organization. All nationality groups of Chicago are already hard at work for the fall campaign. They have large organizations. The German element must first create such an organization. Because of the large number of voters of German descent, the Germans of Chicago should be the strongest national group.</p>
   <p>We appeal to the German element to join the Deutsch-Amerikanische Demokratische Organisation (German-American Democratic Organization), so that we may finally have some influence in the political field. The biggest hall in Chicago should prove too small for a mass meeting, if all our German fellow citizens would wake up and join together into one great body.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0086.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To the next meeting for recruiting members, every member should bring five to ten sympathetic friends and neighbors of German extraction, including Austrians, Swiss, Luxemburgers, Sudeten-Germans, German-Hungarians, German-Russians, etc.--in one word, all German-speaking people. Also, married women and girls entitled to vote are heartily welcomed by the Deutsch-Amerikanische Organization, and invited to co-operate with us actively. At the meeting next Tuesday, the following candidates, well known to Chicago's Germans, will be the speakers: Robert M. Sweitzer, candidate for County Treasurer; Clayton F. Smith, candidate for president and member of the County Board; Fred Brummel, candidate for member of the Board of Tax Appeals; John Toman, candidate for the office of Sheriff; John Traeger, Jr., candidate for the office of County Commissioner.</p>
   <p>All the candidates mentioned above will set forth their programs, and will be very glad to meet fellow Democrats of German descent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
