<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-08-07">August 7, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">In Halles Honor. the President of the Schoolboard Halle. Honored by Germania Club with a Banquet.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1049</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1049.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-08-07">August 7, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">IN HALLES HONOR. THE PRESIDENT OF THE SCHOOLBOARD HALLE. HONORED BY GERMANIA CLUB WITH A BANQUET.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "Germania Men's Chorus" arranged yesterday evening, to celebrate the election of its esteemed member, G. H. Halle, as President of the Municipal Board of Education, a banquet at which Mr. Harry Rubens, with his usual poise presided. After the third course, Mr. Rubens presented the guest of honor, a silvermounted ebony chairman gavel. In a complimentary speech, he expressed the satisfaction, which all friends of Mr. Halle felt over the fact, that he, after several years of activity with the School-Board, achieved the position, for which he is so well qualified, namely: to become its head. Mr. Halle, gave his thanks in warm words for this distinction. The gavel, the sign of his dignity, he promised to use for the benefit of the school children, and in the interest of the citizens.</p>
   <p>Banker E. S. Dreyer the next speaker, extolled Mr. Halle as a representative <pb facs="5418474_4_1050.jpg" n="2"/>of energetically-determined German-Americans, who in a foreign country, through fitness, recognition, and success are able to achieve their aims. Judge Theodore Brentano speaking as a German-American lawyer, pointed to the German-Americans, who made a name for themselves in the country's History, as prominent judges; he mentioned Franz Lieber, Bernhard Stallo, Gustav Korner, and Arnold Krekel. As far as the German-American judges of Chicago are concerned, you may rest assured, that they will always strive, to bring honor to the German name. President George Schneider, of the "National Bank of Illinois" was the next speaker. He gave credit to Mr. Halle for his personal work and public spirit, and expressed the hope, that he will always strive for the retention of the German language in the schools. Dr. Karl Binz, the German Consul declared in a short speech, that as a German, he is proud that a countryman succeeded in achieving such a prominent position abroad, as Mr. Halle occupies at present, in the educational field of Chicago. The last speech of the evening was delivered by Mr. Joseph Brucker. He gave a spirited lecture about energy, only those who are energetic, are successful in life, sleepyheads crammed with knowledge, can not be used for anything.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
