<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-03-01">March 1, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">German Democrats. the Beginning of a Solid Organization.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-03-01">March 1, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN DEMOCRATS. THE BEGINNING OF A SOLID ORGANIZATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That task which has been in progress for some months, to unite all the German Democrats into a solid unit, so that they can acquire the political importance they deserve, continues and shows prospects of eventual realization. Yesterday the German-American Democratic Club of Chicago was organized. It represents a Central Alliance of the German-American Ward clubs which will be brought to life in the near future. Several....are already in existence. The Germans regardless of their party beliefs, cannot be admonished too severely that it behooves them to function as a unified political army, where questions of state are involved. Numerically they are strong enough to appear as a power whose just demands must be conceded when they present themselves as a united front.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0288.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The German-American Democratic Club proceeded slowly with its work only, since in this instance the object is to create an encompassing organization of a permanent character, which shall always be a protectorate for the German Democratic voter. A Central Club will act as an administration for each of the separate Branch-clubs which will be organized in every ward. Now, the German Democratic voters should align themselves with these ward clubs, for the purpose of bringing all the German Democrats into the ranks, so that they form a self-contained unit which can influence conventions, the primaries, and general elections.</p>
   <p>At yesterday's meeting of the Central Club the paragraphs of the constitution were debated and accepted. Mr. Charles Kern presided as chairman pro-tem Carl Haerting was temporary secretary and C. H. Sigmund, treasurer. Mr. E. Hoechster addressed the assembly in which he stressed the club's objective, as previously elucidated.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0289.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The meeting was well attended and a large number enrolled as members. The contemplated election of officers was postponed yesterday, since it is desired to obtain leading German Democrats for the official positions. A committee of 5 has been appointed to indorse suitable candidates and next Friday it will present them at the scheduled meeting; during the interim however, it will interview the prospective leaders. The club asks for the hearty cooperation of every German Democrat, that he support this movement by his active membership, as only a united organization guarantees the realization of the German rights and demands.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
