<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title><date when="1890-03-11">Mar. 11, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">German American Citizens' Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0839</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0839.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title><date when="1890-03-11">Mar. 11, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN AMERICAN CITIZENS' UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following circular is being widely circulated among the German-Americans of the city:</p>
   <p>It is an undeniable fact that the position of the German-Americans in the political life of the Unites States is like that of Cinderella, because of the little interest taken of the political affairs. The lack of interest, however, has no other cause than the one-sideness which rules American politics, and which causes the leaders or representatives of political parties to suppress or misrepresent the statements or other utterances of their opponents, it being one of the fundamental characteristics of the German people to hear both sides before passing judgment. It was the recognition of this fact which prompted the organization of the "German-American Citizens' Union", for the purpose of encouraging independent of partisans, and free from demagogy of any kind, political action on the part of German-Americans, and to direct their influence towards marking the political parties the servants instead of the masters of the voters. Since the German-American press is too partisan to be capable of serving the purpose of the movement, the German-American Union will do its work by arranging public meetings, in which political and other public questions are to be <pb facs="5418474_4_0840.jpg" n="2"/>discussed by representatives of all parties or sides, in a dispassionate manner, thereby giving their hearers the best possible opportunity for forming their own opinions.</p>
   <p>The first of these meeting to be devoted to a discussion of the impending municipal election, will be held Mar. 18th in Uhlicks' Hall, North Clark St., and will be addressed by Mr. Gauss, the well-known Republican orator, by Gen. Hermann Lieb, one of the war-horses of the Democratic party, and by J. J. Altpeter, the recognized representative of Socialist principles. All there are all eminently fitted to instruct their hearers on their duties and responsibilities from their various party standpoints. No resolutions will be offered at this meeting, nor will any candidates be nominated, it being the sole purpose to enable the German-Americans to take an active and intelligent part in the nomination of the best men for the municipal offices to be filled.</p>
   <p>Theodore Gestefeld, President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
