<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-20">Oct. 20, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[The Great Fire]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0705</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0705.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-20">Oct. 20, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[THE GREAT FIRE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some of our readers object to our dewlling on the special danger that threatens the German North Side in consequence of the catastrophe of October 9. However, we regard that as our duty, and expect that at no far-off time all those who resent any pitting against each other of the interests of various parts of Chicago (because the common calamity (in their opinion) should silence all special concerns) will thank us for having championed the German interests.</p>
   <p>Mr. S. S. Hayes, whose own interests lie entirely on the North Side reminds the readers of the Times that Wm. B. Ogden already sometime ago published a plan under the title New Chicago which could really be boiled down to a proposition to transfer the center of the city farther South, and to make the North Side a railroad suburb of Chicago. Where up to now German business men, craftsmen, and workers found a pleasant home. There, numberless railroad trains would speed over hundreds of tracks, smoking machine shops, mills, lumber depots, would take the place of friendly flower-framed little houses, and while the millionaires and the wholesale trade would "perhaps" gain, the Germandom of Chicago would "certainly" receive its death blow. New Chicago would then indeed become a second New York, but that in the worst sense of the word; that is to say one in which the English speaking population would look down on the German speaking people as on a subordinate class, while <pb facs="5418474_4_0706.jpg" n="2"/>they themselves would politically succumb to the Irish. The preservation of Chicago as a city in which the German element has power and social standing as one of equal birth depends on the reconstruction of the North Side.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
