<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-28">Apr. 28, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">One of Many Cases</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1292</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1292.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-28">Apr. 28, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">ONE OF MANY CASES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The cases are multiplying which prove that abuses exist in connection with parole legislation in the state of Illinois. These abuses threaten to become a country-wide scandal. The latest case is that of a convicted gangster by the name of Frank Dillon, who pleaded guilty of highway robbery and was sentenced to the penitentiary for a minimum of ten years.</p>
   <p>What a penitentiary sentence for a minimum of ten years means, is shown by an examination of this case. On November 15, 1920, Dillon and another bandit were arrested, caught in the act. Twice bond was posted, twice the bonds were declared forfeited, and twice the forfeiture was rescinded. In such manner, with the usual postponements, the case dragged on until March 3, 1922. One day later Dillon was sentenced. He was sent to Joliet, but, three months later, his case came before the Supreme Court, so that he posted <pb facs="5418474_4_1293.jpg" n="2"/>bond and was again a free man! Even the Supreme Court of the United States considered the case for a while but finally refused to interfere.</p>
   <p>This did not prevent Dillon from continuing to enjoy his freedom, however. Somehow, he could not be caught and sent back to prison. When he was recently sought by the police he gave himself up voluntarily and jeerlingly presented a pardon from the Governor. Of a sentence carrying a minimum of ten years, which under the circumstances should have been a sentence for life, the man served all of three months, and then, while he was a fugitive from justice, wound up by being pardoned by the Governor. Like earlier scandals of a similar nature, this latest pardon of a dangerous and notorious criminal furnishes us with an astounding picture of the cool unconcern with which the board of paroles and pardons treats all views and concepts of justice. The man in the governor's chair, it seems, will sign a pardon for any criminal, without discrimination, if the latter is on the right side, i. e., can exert political pressure, or has friends who will exert it for him. Under such circumstances it is not surprising that the number of crimes committed becomes almost infinite, <pb facs="5418474_4_1294.jpg" n="3"/>that the courts are overcrowded, that police protection does not function, that efforts of the state's attorney bear an unfortunate likeness to those of the circus nag which runs round and round in a circle without ever arriving at a goal.</p>
   <p>The cynical statement that Chicago could, with no effort at all, lose fifty per cent of its population if all who belonged in jail were actually sent there, does not seem to be wholly without foundation. In the light of recent events it would be wrong only because the Governor would set most of the prisoners free again, if, by some happy chance, such a house cleaning took place.</p>
   <p>The situation is well-nigh hopeless. It has come to such a pass that the citizens are helpless in the face of such conditions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
