<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-02">Nov. 2, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Victory Is Certain!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Enthusiasm of German Voters in Democratic Mass Meeting at Mueller's Hall.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0226</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0226.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-02">Nov. 2, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">VICTORY IS CERTAIN!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Enthusiasm of German Voters in Democratic Mass Meeting at Mueller's Hall.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Never before in the history of Chicago has such a grand and enthusiastic meeting taken place among the Germans on the North Side, as the one last night, which was held under the auspices of the German Democratic Central Union.</p>
   <p>Great enthusiasm prevailed during the meeting, because a glorious victory is very definitely expected. The Germans of Chicago are found again in the front lines in this battle for justice and liberty. On the evening of Nov. 8th the banners of victory will wave lustily, wherever Germans are living.</p>
   <p>Several thousand German voters assembled last night in Mueller's Hall. The German Democratic Clubs of the 22nd, and the 24th Wards and the regular <pb facs="5418474_4_0227.jpg" n="2"/>Democratic Club of the 24th ward - all these, many hundreds of men, marched into the hall with drums and music. Upon the platform were a number of very prominent citizens... Mr. W. Hesing was elected chairman by acclamation. He was received very sympathetically, and delivered the following speech:</p>
   <p>"Honorable Citizens:</p>
   <p>"Although it was my intention for several reasons to stay in the background in this campaign, yet I could not refuse the high honor extended to me, namely to make the opening speech at this brilliant assemblage of my German fellow-citizens. You are proving your sincerity and zeal in regard to public affairs by being present in large numbers. You are striving to get more and more information about those problems which vitally concern state and nation in this compaign. Permit me to state briefly my own position, and the attitude of the newspaper I represent, in reference to these important questions:</p>
   <p>"As you all know, the Illinois Staats Zeitung was a strictly Republican party paper for decades, under the leadership of G. Schneider, L. Brentano, A. C. Hesing, and H. Raster, as long as this party adhered to its original <pb facs="5418474_4_0228.jpg" n="3"/>principles, including freedom for all, and a reasonable protective tariff for the encouragement of our industries. The Staats-Zeitung successfully fought within the ranks of the Republican party, the puritanic element which was striving for predominance and abhorred free enjoyment of life. But finally, it severed all connections with the Republican party when personal liberty was attacked by it, when it favored prohibition more and more, when it fought against a free Sunday in Chicago, and when it enforced prohibition in Kansas and Iowa. The Illinois Staats Zeitung then became, and is now, an independent paper, persistently defending personal liberty, and fighting any party anywhere, which endangers freedom. But it also fights for a moderate tariff, protecting all industries alike. This alone will, in her opinion, make decent wages possible for our workers. She is still standing upon these principles today...</p>
   <p>"The Illinois Staats Zeitung supports the candidates of the Democratic party because the Republican party proved itself unliberal and intolerant toward prohibition and the Sunday questions; and because it forsook its glorious past, denied its true principles, and is increasingly inclined to support the alienhaters. On the other hand, the Democratic party and its candidates have promised, freely and honestly, to defend personal liberty, and to fight for the rights of parents in matters of education. Besides, G. Cleveland stands upon <pb facs="5418474_4_0229.jpg" n="4"/>the same ground, as far as the tariff is concerned, as the Republican party formerly did, and the principles he defends are the same as those supported by the Staats-Zeitung."</p>
   <p>Hesing then discussed the school problem, receiving a thundering applause.</p>
   <p>"The Germans", he asserted, "know the reasons for this campaign battle. Two years ago the liberals won a brilliant victory over the bigots by electing our esteemed fellow citizen, H. Raab, with a majority of 35,000 votes.... We have no time to rest upon our laurels. Again a serious battle is before us, but we are not afraid of the outcome. We shall again be victorious, for, whenever justice and liberty are at stake, the Germans stand united as a nation of brethren. Down with the Edward Law: Freedom is our highest possession: Under the banner of Cleveland and Altgeld we shall win!"...</p>
   <p>The next speaker, J. Goldzier, was then introduced by Hesing... Goldzier said: "I am touched very deeply by the praise I received from Mr. Hesing. I trust that you will have the same opinion of me, after my term as your representative is over, provided, of course, I am elected to Congress.</p>
   <p>"We are at the end of this important election campaign. The time for speeches <pb facs="5418474_4_0230.jpg" n="5"/>is almost past, but the time for action is at hand. The moment is approaching when you shall use the weapon which will make you masters of the situation. This weapon is the ballot.</p>
   <p>"The Germans have a very specific interest in the present struggle. Wherever the problem of personal liberty is involved, we find the Germans always in front ranks.</p>
   <p>"On the one hand we have the Republicans, serving certain elements, which are trying to enslave us with medieval conditions; and, on the other hand, we have the Democrats who are bravely fighting for personal liberty and religious tolerance. We have noticed from year to year, and from day to day, how the elements separated. Those who see in people, born on German soil, only second rate citizens, have all become a compact mass under the Republican banner.</p>
   <p>"How long shall we tolerate such crude and unkind treatment? Are we Germans inferior to citizens born in this country? Are the Germans filling the poor houses and jails? Have the Germans not always been advanced in culture? Or is the German-American culture of more recent date than the Anglo-American? Did the Germans neglect to contribute their share in throwing off the English yoke, and in establishing a republic here? Was not General on Steuben one <pb facs="5418474_4_0231.jpg" n="6"/>of the most dependable advisers, and one of the ablest and bravest generals of George Washington? when the shackles of slavery were destined to fall from the colored people, were not the Germans among the the first to enlist as volunteers? Many a hill in the South covers the son of German parents.</p>
   <p>"But what is our reward? During the Civil War, German regiments with German commanders were highly welcome, but now the Republicans dare to forbid us our German schools. The basic principles of the Republican party are absolutely wrong. There is a tendency toward aristocracy among them, attempting to create a favored, governing class, and an inferior class to be governed. The Republicans do not adhere any more to the constitution, which was drawn up by the founders of this great republic. According to the constitution, all power is in the hands of the citizens, and no other power exists than that conveyed by the people to their representatives. According to Republican principles it is peremissible for the state to interfere with strictly personal matters of private citizens; but the Democrats hold that well encroachments ought to be repelled."...</p>
   <p>The speaker concluded with the assertion that the Democratic party would do justice to the German-Americans in the future, as it always did in the past, <pb facs="5418474_4_0232.jpg" n="7"/>and that it is, therefore, the duty of all Germans to vote for Grover Cleveland, and J. P. Altgeld, as well as for all candidates on the Democratic ticket.... The enthusiasm of the German Democratic citizens was great.</p>
   <p>Horfmann urgently exhorted the audience to come and vote on the day of election, and to prove to the people what the Germans can accomplish, if united...</p>
   <p>Ph. Stein was next introduced to the meeting by Mr. Hesing. He is a candidate for the judgeship of the Superior Court... Candidate Bartling and Strum addressed the audience likewise. The Germans can be proud, indeed, about what they did last night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
