<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-05-30">May 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Unjust Attacks Upon German Lutherans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-05-30">May 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">UNJUST ATTACKS UPON GERMAN LUTHERANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not only English-American, but also German-American Republican papers continue to attack the German Lutherans of Illinois with unjust accusations, instead of being glad that these respectable people have restricted their fight against the Republican Party of the state only and left the national organization unmolested. But irrespective of their moderation the German Lutherans are being accused of forcing a whole church into political partisanship. In view of the previously mentioned facts, this accusation is not only unjust, but also absurd.</p>
   <p>The German Lutherans are also being charged with furnishing a bad and dangerous example by their interference as a church in the affairs of state, which must inevitably lead to very bad results. The masses of the Lutherans should protest vehemently against the unreasonable and impious activities of those men, who now promote party politics in the name of the Lutheran Church... These and similar newspapers try to create a wrong impression, as if the Lutheran manifesto for the Democratic ticket of the state election were the machination of only a few individuals, while in reality it was the unanimous opinion of the masses of Lutherans, and was only confirmed and expressed by their voluntarily chosen delegates.</p>
   <p>In regard to the supposed meddling into the affairs of state by the Lutheran Church, <pb facs="5418474_4_0268.jpg" n="2"/>it must be said that it is not an attack of the church against the state but rather a compulsory self-defense of the church against the unjustifiable encroachment of the state upon the rights of the church.</p>
   <p>The German Lutherans of all religious denominations are the most zealous in defending the complete separation of church and state, and they have always been in favor of such separation even since their ritual dispute in Prussia... Since that time they have been opposed to every amalgamation of church and state. For this reason they have never participated in the activities of American sects to force upon the state certain laws in regard to the keeping of the sabbath or Sunday. The very small minority of German-American Lutherans, who take part in such matters, do not belong to the large German-American synods, but are affiliated with English-American churches.</p>
   <p>The German Lutherans in the state of Illinois and Wisconsin organized a political front only after their religious liberty, and with it, their parental rights were infringed upon. They did so with considerable force in order to achieve a favorable decision for their cause as quickly as possible, as well as to remove the necessity of interfering with matters of state and state elections as a church. They have already succeeded in this in the state of Wisconsin and will succeed here <pb facs="5418474_4_0269.jpg" n="3"/>shortly....</p>
   <p>Since this battle of the Lutherans is not only for the purpose of keeping church and state separated, but also for the preservation of German, therefore, they deserve the hearty support and co-operation of all German-Americans.</p>
   <p>German Republican newspapers should leave the provoking of these good citizens to the knownothings, and the haters of Germans....</p>
   <p>Such and similar accusations are not only unjust, but also frightfully absurd from the standpoint of political utilization, because they can gradually serve the purpose of embittering the accused against the national politics of the Republican Party of Illinois, so that their fate will be just as well sealed as the state election is already sealed as far as the respective action of the German Lutherans is concerned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
