<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-04-21">Apr. 21, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">The German Idea.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1108</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1108.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-04-21">Apr. 21, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN IDEA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very interesting story under the title "The German Idea" was published in today's issue of the Times. The scene took place in the ante chamber of "his excellency, Roche, the man with success". Following is the report of the Times: Among other clubs in Chicago, there is one known as the German-American Republican Club with about 150 members. Modesty is the main characteristic of this organization; each of the members quite willing to accept a fat job at the City Hall, provided that the salary is high and the work light.</p>
   <p>The executive committee of this club met yesterday at the private office of the county clerk, Wulff, in order to ascertain what offices were assigned to the Germans. Present were: Richard Michaelis, Adolf Hottinger, Franz Amberg, Hermann Benze, George Weibinger, John Buchler, Alderman Tiedemann, Henry Wulff, Fred Forch, Jacob Forch, and many more German Republicans. During a lengthy discussion which followed, indignation was voiced over the nomination of Americans to the offices comptroller, corporations' attorney, and that of the manager of the water department. It was finally agreed upon, that Otto Diehling should receive the oil inspector's office with annual salary of $15,000.00. Engen Seeger was proposed <pb facs="5418474_4_1109.jpg" n="2"/> for the office of gas inspector. Mr. Seeger has resided in Chicago for only thirty months and is at present clerk in the marriage license bureau with an annual income of $2,000.00. His well wisher and protector is Michaelis of the Freie Presse. C. T. Brentano is the committee's choice for the office of attorney for special assessments.</p>
   <p>"What do you think of the demands of the German Republicans?" This was the question asked "Col." George Davis by the Times reporter. "Oh," said Davis, "The Dutch are all right." This from the Times! These vagabonds who, never in their lives have done any honest work, but have maintained themselves in luxury by drawing large salaries from public funds, represent the type of men who are enemies of Socialism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
