<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-01-21">January 21st, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Politics and Administration. Altgeld's Answer to State Senator Shunway's Letter. the County Officials Are Supposed to Receive Higher Salaries.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>DIE ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1899-01-21">January 21st, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Politics And Administration. Altgeld's Answer To State Senator Shunway's Letter. The County Officials Are Supposed To Receive Higher Salaries.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As may be generally known, J. N. C. Shumway, State Senator of Christian County, a former staunch supporter of Altgeld, asked him to favor his party members of the interior of the State, by explaining his motives; why he, the Democratic Ex- Governor, chooses to run as an independent candidate for mayor of Chicago. Mr. Altgeld answered the letter immediately, and his reply, condensed, is as follows: "You ask me, why I really fight the City hall machine. A profound sense of duty towards my party is the primary reason. Three questions in Chicago form the entire basis."</p>
   <p>1.) Those of political decency and self-preservation.</p>
   <p>2.) The treachery towards, and the complete destruction of that powerful reform movement, which the Democratic party now advocates, and</p>
   <p>3.) The question, whether the right shall be denied to Chicago, to try to improve its condition and that of the next generation, in regard to street car transportation.</p>
   <p>As soon as the inauguration of the present City administration was completed, <pb facs="5418474_4_0517.jpg" n="2"/>it insisted upon controlling the primary and the convention. For this express purpose, most of the members of the County Central Committee were placed on the City pay-roll and with the aid of this Committee, which had to select the election districts and appoint the election judges, it became an easy matter to obtain the desired control of the nominating convention. In June 1897, ended the term of all circuit judges. We had just won in the city; the current was on our side and every where was ample evidence, that we would also elect the new judges. The City Hall faction however put up weak candidates, so that the party protested, which turned into a revolt among the Democrats and the upshot of it was, that we were thoroughly beaten. Last fall, the same cause produced the identical result; we lost the state, the control in the House of Representatives of the state and besides, several state in the Senate. Through this debacle, the Republicans gained control of the entire election-machine in the city, and furthermore also five thousand berths for their party were pullers. That the next senator will also be a Republican, is likewise the fault of that near-sighted City hall clique. What serious-thinking man would consider it undemocratic, if, under such conditions one endeavors to give that "machine" the death-thrust?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0518.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And, since the City ball faction can control all the primaries, and with entire disregard of the party sentiment, it follows, that all opposition to this machine must be absolutely independent.</p>
   <p>It was I, who formerly induced my Democratic friends to consider Carter H. Harrison for the mayor's office, since I firmly believed, to have found in him a true friend of the free-silver coinage movement. And what did Mr. Harrison do, after he was elected mayor of Chicago? Within the first week of his office tenure, he selected not less than 9 adherents of the Gold cause for important places, and proved himself an obedient tool of the so-called Sound-money-men. Towards those, who after all, really elected him, he appeared cold and very reticent.</p>
   <p>Free institutions in this land must be founded on patriotic democracy. My entire existence is intimately connected with the great principles of such a democracy; and I cannot look on and remain inactive, if everything for which I worked and fought, is threatened by treachery and destruction. Who soever disregards the accepted principles of the party is a "bolter", but not he, who sacrifices everything, if necessary, to prevent the betrayal of such a platform. A political "machine" is a curse, if it serves base purposes.</p>
   <p>The attitude of the mayor towards the street-car question, will be submitted to <pb facs="5418474_4_0519.jpg" n="4"/>Chicago's citizens later. Harrison is opposed to municipally owned railroads. The railway companies share that belief. He tries to ignore the interesting question of a fare reduction as much as possible; so do the companies.</p>
   <p>He requests a high franchise from the street car companies and the latter are willing to pay it. In short, under Harrison's plan, the people would carry the same burden, as before. Only through municipal ownership will the population be enabled to obtain the lowest rates and the best of transportation; only through that will it be possible to end graft and corruption, which is always a by-product when private ownership has a monopoly of public service.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
