<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-01">Mar. 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The People's Ravished Franchise</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-01">Mar. 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE PEOPLE'S RAVISHED FRANCHISE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our recent Chicago Democratic primaries are reminiscent of those dark, dire and doleful periods of the Baltimore. Louisville and New Orleans Know-nothing regency, when vote frauds and destruction of ballots were the order of the day. There is a distinction nevertheless; here in Chicago the "new" citizens utilized the same demoralizing methods, only they fought their own "new" citizens who were political opponents. The originator and leader here, is none other than Carter H. Harrison. His conduct during the primaries was the pattern for his behavior at the ensuing convention. Anyone who objected to a fraudulently elected delegate was promptly silenced. Two years ago at our city convention such a system <pb facs="5418474_4_1369.jpg" n="2"/>was in vogue, therefore Harrison inaugurated a counter-convention which offered him the candidacy. But in this instance he crassly exceeded anything perpetrated heretofore, with deeds which he decried with abhorrence only two years ago.</p>
   <p>We have been informed from authortative sources, that the railroads contributed $30,000 to his campaign fund. This, then, explains the constant silence, on his own part as well as that of his newspapers, about the elevation of the railroad tracks. His ample speeches during the last weeks omitted any reference to these and other vital questions affecting the city's destiny, while his opponent, Washington Hesing, was very outspoken on these subjects. Fraud and force during the primary, insolent disregard for laws at the convention, that was Harrison's formula for success; he obtained the nomination.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1370.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, it was accomplished only after Hesing exposed the crimes of the fixers and main cogs from the stage at the city convention, when he refused to be nominated by such delegates. What value is there in these soothing promises given by such a convention: At best they are similar to the slick ice on the streets which is now so treacherously hidden by our rubbish and dirt. In all these seductive parables and proverbs designed to enmesh votes, how plainly the hate for Germanism emerges to the surface; Under the old pretext of the Know-Nothings who advocate economy and simplicity, the demand comes to the fore again that all "fads" be abolished from our public schools. It means dispensing with gymnastics, and eliminating German language instruction. Upon fraud, rabble rule, and hatred for Germanism, Harrison built up his candidacy to include the magnificent, municipal title of World's Fair mayor. He had to pawn his soul to the vilest and most dangerous elements of the populace, to the insatiable monopolies, so that he could, by hook or crook, squeeze out the candidate <pb facs="5418474_4_1371.jpg" n="4"/>of an honest party and obtain the nomination. A man who is the willing tool for the dregs of humanity cannot be entrusted with Chicago's administration. All our good citizens agree to that, irrespective of party affiliations. And no part of our public adheres to this more forcefully than those who voted for Cleveland on Nov. 8, last year, because he was the sworn, uncompromising enemy of corruption, and earned the intense hatred of the Tammany regime in the East and West; indeed a great testimonial which furthered his election.</p>
   <p>Chicago's Germanism has been honored by the fact that no genuine German occupies a place on the Harrisonian ticket; of course, the convention did not disbar them on account of their innate sentiments of Teutonic probity. We are aware, that its warped and wanton dislike of anything German was the motivation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
