<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-03-03">Mar. 3, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Karl Schurz Honcred by German-American Women's Club on 98Th Anniversary of Birth.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1020</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1020.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title> Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-03-03">Mar. 3, 1927</date>.
<title level="a"> KARL SCHURZ HONCRED BY GERMAN-AMERICAN WOMEN'S CLUB ON 98TH ANNIVERSARY OF BIRTH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 98th birthday of the German-American statesman Karl Schurz was festively celebrated at the Morrison Hotel by the German-American Women's Club of Chicago. Mrs. Frank Schaedler, founder of the club, made the festival speech. She celebrated Karl Schurz as the greatest American Statesman of German descent, and recited personal memories of those times when Schurz traveled through the country to give campaign speeches in favor of Grover Cleveland.</p>
   <p>After describing his extraordinary devotion to duty and his unflinching adherence to his adopted fatherland, she gave a short sketch of his life. Karl Schurz was born March 2nd, 1829, in Liblar, near Cologne, Germany, Owing to his participation in the Baden revolt, in 1849, he was forced to flee. In 1850 he assisted in the escape of Kinkels from Spandau. In 1852 he found asylum in the United States.</p>
   <p>Here he rose to the position of leader of the Republican party, and, in 1854, was nominated Lieutenant-Governor of Wisconsin. In 1862 he was appointed by Abraham Lincoln as ambassador to Spain. In 1863-1865 he fought as general against the South. In 1868 he was elected as United States Senator from <pb facs="5418474_4_1021.jpg" n="2"/>Illinois, and in 1877 he was appointed by President Hayes as Secretary of the Interior. He was also active as a journalist. He died May 14th, 1906, in New York.</p>
   <p>The chairman of yesterday's celebration, at which almost all of the 250 members of the club were present, was the president, Mrs. Otto Devors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
