<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-28">July 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">More Light [On Relief Graft]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1225</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1225.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-28">July 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">MORE LIGHT [ON RELIEF GRAFT]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The State's attorney of Cook County is finally going to permit a thorough investigation by the Grand Jury of the wholesale thievery which is said to have taken place in the Illinois Emergency Relief Commission. The decision must have been very difficult for the State's attorney, for it took him long enough to make up his mind.</p>
   <p>That something stank in the commission in charge of relief in Illinois has been an open secret ever since Attorney Peterson, originally entrusted with the prosecution of the relief grafters, offered his resignation to the arrogant gentlemen on the Relief Commission, and publicly declared that he could not continue, if the Commission put obstacles in the way of the prosecution.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1226.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Recently, a legislative committee took up the whole matter but nobody will maintain that this investigation, which is now completed, brought to light any more than was already known. The legislators shrank from bringing this ill-smelling affair into the open. The executive secretary of the Commission, Wilfred Reynolds, stated quite openly that the Commission could not be exposed, while Chairman Dunham was of the opinion that only minor irregularities had occurred.</p>
   <p>It was only after a local newspaper had started a vigorous campaign and printed evidence, that the authorities decided to take action, although for a considerable period of time accusations, some of which were serious, had been made against the Commission and its administration. The grand jury investigation will perhaps determine whether there is any basis in fact for these accusations. To have any great hopes of this would be foolish, however.</p>
   <p>Each month the Illinois Relief Commission spends the trifling sum of nine million dollars for charitable purposes. The taxpayer, who has to provide <pb facs="5418474_4_1227.jpg" n="3"/>this money, has the right, therefore, to demand that those who need relief actually get it, but that the Commission be, at the same time, as economical as possible. But what is actually happening? There are many complaints that there are inequalities in the distribution of relief; it seems that there are some who are especially favored, and others who are neglected. Just as many complaints are received about the arrogance of the relief officials, most of whom are trained case workers, who now feel called upon to give people--who once were well off, but who lost their fortune through no fault of their own--elementary advice on how they are to readjust their ruined existence.</p>
   <p>These professional relief workers are the guards against whom people are rebelling, especially down state, where, in some counties, four relief officials per county once did the work which fourteen to sixteen are employed to do now. Executive Secretary Reynolds, spoke before the Commission of one of his own inventions, an ideal system for administering relief. If only a part of this <pb facs="5418474_4_1228.jpg" n="4"/>ideal system consists of the above-mentioned increase in the number of officials, the taxpayer will be very grateful. On the other hand, the taxpayer will gladly welcome having more light shed on the way relief is administered in Illinois. He is curious to know how much of his tax-dollar is actually spent for relief, and how much is wasted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
