<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-15">Feb. 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">5th Ward German Democratic Club Endorses Hesing.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0208</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0208.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-15">Feb. 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">5TH WARD GERMAN DEMOCRATIC CLUB ENDORSES HESING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Democratic Club of the 5th Ward held its meeting yesterday at Germania Hall, Wentworth Ave. About 200 qualified voters, among them many Anglo-Americans, were present and all endorsed Washington Hesing most enthusiastically, as the new Democratic candidate for mayor.</p>
   <p>Senator Thiele, president of the Club, came especially from Springfield for this occasion, in order to preside at the meeting. His brother, Theodore B. Thiele, was secretary. Many prominent Germans were present, among them: John Krebs, vice president of the Club, and.... 14 others are listed. Senator Thiele gave the opening address in which he expressed his satisfaction about the interest which the 5th Ward has shown in this coming election. "Such a large attendance is definite proof in itself." His closing remarks were a hearty recommendation to nominate Mr. Hesing for the mayoralty.</p>
   <p>He was followed by Mr. Carl Haerting who made a torrid speech in the interests of Hesing's candidacy. He said:</p>
   <p>"The Democratic party cannot find a better banner-bearer than this energetic <pb facs="5418474_4_0209.jpg" n="2"/>and capable young man, whose personal influence in conjunction with the Illinois Staats Zeitung has been the principle force that brought a glorious Democratic victory to the city and state.</p>
   <p>"It was Mr. Hesing who, on the strength of his profound knowledge of the political situation throughout the city and stats, predicted this victory; he it was, who induced Grover Cleveland to consider the question of our personal liberty, the rights of parents in matters pertaining to their children's education, and to incorporate these matters into his platform. He also declared with true prophetic vision, that strict attention to these points would produce a 25,000 to 30,000 majority in our state. How this prophecy materialized is still within the scope of recent memory.</p>
   <p>"Washington Hesing, who enjoyed the full confidence of a man like Cleveland, is therefore qualified in all respects to become the leader of our city administration.</p>
   <p>"Must we always have a Carter H. Harrison forever into eternity?" demanded <pb facs="5418474_4_0210.jpg" n="3"/>the speaker, and with thunderous reverberations the public's answer rolled back: "No, no! Hurrah for Hesing!"</p>
   <p>Mr. Haerting then reverted to the weaknesses, party-treason and egotism of Carter Harrison, finally adding, that he must be permanently defeated, and this assertion was accepted with boisterous acclaim.</p>
   <p>Former Assemblyman August Mette was next on the program. He also took up the cudgels for Mr. Hesing and did it magnificently. He admonished his compatriots to take an active interest in the impending election, since we are concerned in "putting one of our men across."  Mr. Hesing, he averred, will be a better mayor than any our city has had heretofore.</p>
   <p>Ex-assemblyman Rohrbach made the declaration, that Hesing enjoys great prestige among organized labor of our city because of his desirable qualities, and the candidate will find ardent support there. Carter however, he pointed out, has always misled and betrayed the working class and obviously, labor cannot expect anything else from him in the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0211.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Schaefer reached heights of enthusiastic eloquence while extol-ling the virtues of Hesing, and his splendid testimony was rewarded with stormy approval.</p>
   <p>The following resolutions were then unanimously adopted by the impassioned assembly:</p>
   <p>"Whereas we, citizens of the 5th Ward, consider it timely to express our choice for the mayoral candidacy, we hereby publicly declare:</p>
   <p>"That we recognize Mr. Washington Hesing as a man who is capable in all respects and better able to unite the various factions within the party's ranks than any other.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, be it resolved, that we pledge ourselves to the task of furthering the interests of Mr. Hesing in every conceivable manner during this election and we hereby appeal to all citizens of the 5th Ward to take an active part in the primaries on February, the 27th."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0212.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Another meeting .... was announced for next Tuesday evening, at Schaefer's Hall,  2501 Hanover St. It will combine the Washington Hesing Fifth Ward Club with the German Democratic Club and a whole-hearted co-operation is requested. After the general meeting 35 gentlemen registered as new bonafide members which raises the club's total to 150 active participants.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
