<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Fackel</title>,
<date when="1888-09-02">Sept. 2, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">[Captain Schaack]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Fackel</title>,
<date when="1888-09-02">Sept. 2, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">[CAPTAIN SCHAACK]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Captain Schaack self-styled mayor or czar of the North Side, is supposed to get fired.</p>
   <p>We have the privilege of giving an accounting of everything that North-siders know, and say about this departing pasha of the North Side.</p>
   <p>Capt. Schaack is a many-sided genius, the most so in the advancement of his private interests, in baseness and in the invention of unbelievable fairy-tales.</p>
   <p>Schaack considers himself one of the strongest "pillars of society" of Chicago and comes right out with this conviction which was proved by his fire-proof love of truth during the Anarchists' trial.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1433.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Sense cannot be found in this Luxembourg Schaackal, intelligence or education is out entirely, but he possesses much malicious craftiness and brutality.</p>
   <p>Once in a while when necessary to improve his credit with the millionaires he has his henchmen find a dynamite bomb.</p>
   <p>Absolutely poor, he joined the Chicago police force eighteen years ago. Supposing he had drawn from the start $100.00 monthly salary, the total would not exceed $21,600. Now Capt. Schaack lived for eighteen years on these wages and what is more, he lived splendidly, and so where is his present fortune of $75,000.00 coming from? No inheritance was bequeathed this noble Luxemburgian, but we can prove how he got his money through partnership in his brother's private night-patrol service and through trade of jobs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1434.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As long as the imbecile Roche believed in Schaack's infallibility and fell in his snares, qualification or honesty did not play any role in filling jobs.</p>
   <p>Beahr, Schaack's nephew, became a policeman after being in Chicago for two years, only, which is unlawful, and advanced in an extraordinarily short period to Lieutenant.</p>
   <p>The Pasha - regime on the North Side was a complete one and when those who know will start to talk, a story will come to light that will be bubbling over with vileness, graft and corruption, of which the citizens have not the slightest idea yet. Politics is spreading among Chicago's police force like pestilence, dividing the same into two factions secretely fighting against one another.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
