<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-06-07">June 7, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">German Blockheads in the City Council.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-06-07">June 7, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN BLOCKHEADS IN THE CITY COUNCIL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For a sharp mind it must be a true entertainment to watch the behavior of the German aldermen in the city council. These good people have been highly flattered by the friendly consideration of the rich Americans. They gave been told by them, not to believe that they inteded to curtail the rights of the Germans. Our good German city fathers were lulled by such beautiful talk and before they realized it, they had sworn an oath that they would never attempt to understand not even to think, but would leave this hard talk to Aldermen Aldrich and Thompson, and would, of course, always vote as told by them.</p>
   <p>Due to German honesty, they have faithfully lived up to their vote. There is no regulation, no matter how harmful to the Germans, that they would not vote for. Aldermen Aldrich and Thompson propose that Hoyne should be declared mayor and although Colvin is willing to submit the matter to the courts at once, they have given the chairmanship to Hoyne. Later they kiss the whip, when Hoyne, as an insult to the Germans, appoints the German-hater, Derrickson, as comptroller.</p>
   <p>The poor German aldermen do not seem to know that if a new mayor should be <pb facs="5418474_4_1177.jpg" n="2"/>elected now and he should be a man like Aldrich or Derrickson, only a majority of the city council would be required, to bring conditions here under which our fellow citizens have to suffer so much in other parts of this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
