<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-03-31">Mar. 31, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">Clearing Up Misunderstandings.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0605</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0605.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-03-31">Mar. 31, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">CLEARING UP MISUNDERSTANDINGS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We wish to inform readers of certain local English and German newspapers that the candidate for the mayor's office is Monroe Heath and not A. C. Hesing. Any one who reads those papers is liable to misunderstand the situation. All those papers are full of insults, attacks and invectives - against whom? - against Monroe Heath perhaps?</p>
   <p>Not at all, but against A. C. Hesing and the Illinois Staats Zeitung. To all that is said regarding the lowering of city expenses and of taxes, their only answer is: "Hesing, Hesing, Hesing." In a vain appeal to common sense of the tax paying German citizens, who would rather pay 60 cents than one dollar in taxes, the stupid fellows hired by Perry Smith's railroad money only yell back: "The Staats Zeitung, the bad Staats Zeitung."</p>
   <p>Now as we said previously, A. C. Hesing is not a candidate for the mayor's office, but Monroe Heath. And as far as the Staats Zeitung is concerned, the reader should know, that it is advocating the reelection of a city administration which has taken the printing of city advertisements away from the Staats Zeitung. Only the most stupid idiot can under these circumstances accuse the Staats Zeitung of seeking its own interest.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0606.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Staats Zeitung has suffered only losses and received no benefits from the administration, the reelection of which it advocates. But as it has to pay a considerable tax on its building and its business, it takes the lowering of taxes as much to heart as any other taxpayer. Instead of $6,000,000 required to run the city under the Colvin administration, it would prefer to have the city get along on a $3,000,000 budget. Money saved is money earned, says a good German proverb. In times like these, any taxpayer will think as we do-that taxes reduced due to an honest administration is money saved.</p>
   <p>It is true, that in 1873 the Germans entered into an alliance with the Irish in order to repulse the Sunday tyranny. But the administration elected at that time soon left the path of reform to ally itself with the shadiest elements of both parties, dissipated the taxpayer's money in a most shameful manner and brought the city to the brink of bankruptcy.</p>
   <p>A change was imperative and the Germans understood it so well that last year they elected Mayor Heath and the reform candidates. Their expectations were fulfilled. The city administration is orderly, expenses have been pared, the taxes lowered and Sunday freedom gained in 1873, has remained unimpaired.</p>
   <p>What valid reason can be given to advocate the return of the former racketeers? <pb facs="5418474_4_0607.jpg" n="3"/>Gratitude pushed to such limits would indeed be stupidity. The only question in this election is if the city shall be ruled by Heath and the taxpayers or by Perry Smith and the tax spenders.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
