<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-06-14">June 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Abolition of the Spoils Systel.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1404</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1404.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title><date when="1892-06-14">June 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">ABOLITION OF THE SPOILS SYSTEL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thus reads the message of a circular. We do not deny that the platform contained therein distinguishes itself by a very commendable conciseness when compared with the platforms of the regular political parties, but it must also be admitted, that the three cardinal principles aim at something which is for the present unattainable.</p>
   <p>To demand the abolition of the spoils system is comparatively easy; but how can it be carried out? Let as take for granted that this new Columbia Party puts up a candidate for the presidency, and also elects him. What will happen? Will the party refrain from saying: "To the victor belong the spoils?" Would it retain all the men in office when it gets into power, no matter how hard they fought against it, and how difficult they made victory? What would this party do with those men, who fought courageously and loyally in the campaign battle - would it put them off by pointing to the principle in question? Who shall believe it? How long would such a party hold together? Politics is a business in this country, and the political party is a commercial firm. Each firm tries to convince the public of the superior quality of its merchandise and to purchase the same. To furnish those goods which presumably pleases the people <pb facs="5418474_4_1405.jpg" n="2"/>the most is a difficult task; and to persuade the people to buy it, requires much time, money, and effort. And all of this should be done without compensation? Those men who furnished the goods and sold it to the public should turn over the profit to others? Preposterous!</p>
   <p>Many decades will vanish into the ocean of time before the average American will understand, that one must fight for principles for the sake of principles, and that the victor must be satisfied with the awareness of being the victor....</p>
   <p>But do not misunderstand! We do not defend the spoils system, but it is too premature to make the abolition of the spoils system a major objective of our political parties.</p>
   <p>A political party aiming to abolish the spoils system would not be able to secure sufficient supporters to win, and if by chance it should be victorious once, it would be difficult to do so again, and live up to its program....</p>
   <p>The spoils system can be defeated only through protracted and laborious educational efforts in behalf of the American people, and by successful attempts on a smaller <pb facs="5418474_4_1406.jpg" n="3"/>scale. If once successfully banished from local politics it will not take very long until it becomes a thing of the past in our national politics. Our local history, however, has clearly demonstrated how little we can expect along that line. Irrespective of the many undeserved blows we have received from those political parties we have put into office and rank, we cannot part with party politics, and therefore, not with the spoils system.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
