<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-25">July 25, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Toupees Are in Evidence (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-25">July 25, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">TOUPEES ARE IN EVIDENCE (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Illinois Municipal League and the Illinois Teachers' Association have adopted a fighting attitude toward the groups who would like to limit taxes to one percent of the full value.</p>
   <p>They regard the whole idea as absurd. Their attitude is that no city or communal administration could exist on the revenue from such reduced taxes, and that this is purely a political measure intended to help certain office-seekers, in a word--absurd! But unfortunately, they say, there are many uninformed persons who have accepted this idea as a God-send, and therefore it is necessary to look into it. They advise the most astute resistance.</p>
   <p>The Municipal League and the Teachers' Association promptly composed a circular which they sent to the chief municipal officers. This does not surprise us; <pb facs="5418474_4_0383.jpg" n="2"/>the League obviously has the interests of the municipal administration in mind rather than the interests of the taxpayers. Apparently they believe that it is the duty of the taxpayer to pay whatever the municipal administration demands. It has always been thus; why should it change now? If at any time one does not pay, well, there is always a way out. It is easy to manipulate tax assessments, as was demonstrated in recent years. However, they feel that they might possibly warm up to this idea if care were taken to supply the municipal administrations with sufficient means to take care of the people.</p>
   <p>This attitude is understandable. Less understandable is the attitude of the teachers, although it, too, can be explained. It is they who should be the first to demand a well-regulated administration. They have been waiting long enough for their back salaries and will have to wait quite a while longer. It is one thing to receive money, but still another thing to spend it. But they, too, fear for their incomes, that is, for their salaries. There is a suspicion that these salaries are a little high in comparison with those of <pb facs="5418474_4_0384.jpg" n="3"/>other administrative or private employees. In addition, there is undoubtedly room for reforms which would considerably simplify the whole system, and yet make the school administration much more efficient.</p>
   <p>For the time being, the attitude of the two organizations must not be taken too seriously. The members of the League will have to become accustomed to the idea of managing with much less. Things will work out in the same way. They realize fully that conditions cannot remain the same. They know best the number of barnacles which cling to the bottom of the administrative ship, and which have to be taken along, although they are not useful. They know that this time something much different is at stake--that the question is whether the taxpayers will have a voice, or whether they will be forced to submit to the dictate of the party moguls.</p>
   <p>The teachers have taken the same course which they took seven years ago. They have learned nothing. At that time, in spite of repeated warnings, attempts were made to real-estimate the values of real-estate property in Cook County. <pb facs="5418474_4_0385.jpg" n="4"/>Increased taxes were expected to bring increased salaries. As a result, taxes were muddled and the teachers suffered great losses. But it seems that they haven't suffered enough. They have renewed their efforts, and must again oppose a reform which, although it might mean a small loss, would otherwise mean security for their incomes. As a result of their perseverance in working without salaries, they have gained many sympathizers. It would be advisable for them to keep these sympathizers. In the long run it is the taxpayer who gives them wages and bread. There is an adage which says: "Where nothing is left, there even the Kaiser (tax collector) can exercise no rights".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
