<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-06-24">June 24th, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of Delegates</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-06-24">June 24th, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of Delegates</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Movement in favor of introduction of "Referendum &amp; Imitiative" on Saturday, July 18th, there will , in Uhlich's Hall, corner N. Clark and Kinzie Streets, a meeting of Delegates of the German Societies takes place, to which the lately appointed Swiss executive-Committee has issued the following appeal: "In the name of the city's Swiss, who in the Massmeeting, declared themselves in favor of introduction of the two popular rights, the referendum and the initiative, in city and State, the undersigned temporary Executive Committee makes the announcement that on Sunday July 18th at half past 2 o'clock in the afternoon, there will be held in Uhlich's Hall, corner N. Clark and Kinzie Streets, a meeting of Delegates.- We therefore invite you to participate in this, the larger part of the city's Germans being represented and request you to send at least 2 delegates to same. We undertake to issue this invitation, because we feel entitled in the supposition, that the Germans of Chicago are in accord with their Swiss racial comrades; This conviction is based on the love for freedom, which as the annuls of History of our adopted country show, the Germans and Swiss, in times of distress, and danger, have always fought for the inalienable Rights of the people. Thanks to the tenacity, <pb facs="5418474_4_0521.jpg" n="2"/>with which the Germans insisted on the free exercise of their customs and habits, the personal liberty of this nation's citizens has been assured for practically all times. Referendum and Initiative, are therefore not Rights, which are given to the people as a favor by some authority, but they mean a direct expression of the people's sovereignity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
