<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-05-01">May 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">German Lutherans and Public Offices</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0785</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0785.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-05-01">May 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN LUTHERANS AND PUBLIC OFFICES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-Lutheran clergyman, Reverend T. Stephan, of Chicago, has been appointed by President Cleveland as Consul to Annaberg, and his co-worker, Otto Doederlein of Chicago, has been made consul to Leipzig. On account of a throat infection, Mr. Doederlein was forced to resign as clergyman several years ago and he has since been publishing a secular weekly magazine, the Rundschau.</p>
   <p>Both of these consular appointments created considerable sensation inasmuch as they are the only appointments of German-Americans made by President Cleveland at the present time.</p>
   <p>Our German-Lutheran friends fared just as well or even better with Governor Altgeld. Mr. A. Heuer, a Chicago German-Lutheran was appointed Park Commissioner of Chicago. Louis Wagner of Chicago, formerly a minister, but now a journalist and political promoter, received from Governor Altgeld the splendid position of Registrar at the Grain Inspection Office. In the same office, another German-Lutheran, W. Schroeder, was placed as clerk.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0786.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Chicago and Cook County, also quite a number German-Lutherans were appointed to public offices.....May we state here that there was no shortage of applicants among the German-Lutherans for these positions.....</p>
   <p>There were no objections to these appointments as far as the ability of the majority of the appointed German-Lutherans is concerned. It would be unfair to assume any connections between their religious beliefs and their political affiliations influenced their appointments.</p>
   <p>The fact that so many applicants of German-Lutherans were successful, and, especially the large number of applications, aroused general attention. It is, therefore, obvious that a German newspaper should not evade a discussion of this matter.</p>
   <p>The various successes are, of course, to a great extent due to the calculations of eminent Democratic politicians. Having benefited by the German-American Lutheran votes at the November election of last year, the politicians hoped to retain these votes.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0787.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is a question whether or not their calculations were accurate. However, we have reasons to assume that to the majority of the Lutherans believed that too many over-zealous candidates chasing after public offices created an unpleasant and objectionable impression. The great majority of the German-Lutheran participated rather reluctantly in the election campaigns of 1890 and 1892. They did it only to abolish the Edward Law, and to protect religious liberty, the rights of parents, and to retain the teaching of German in Illinois. This objective they obtained most gloriously after hard fighting.</p>
   <p>The German-Lutherans would certainly disapprove of having a number of their ministers apply for secular or public offices. Every reasonable person will admit, that Reverend Stephan received his political reward for his extensive promotional activities during the last election campaign. The appointment of Reverend Roth as chaplain of a penitentiary can only be filled by a clergyman. In regard to the other theologians, Wagner and Doederlein, who have also received appointments, it must be stated that they left the ministry years ago and have since been engaged in secular activities. Therefore, their former positions have no bearing upon their appointments to public office..... <pb facs="5418474_4_0788.jpg" n="4"/>Nevertheless, it will save our Lutheran friends many misunderstandings and misinterpretations if the job-hunting in their midst is stooped soon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
