<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-05-22">May 22, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">Who Lies?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-05-22">May 22, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">WHO LIES?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The readers will remember that the notice of Hollen's flight also mentioned the fact that he was a share holder of the Neue Freie Presse. The publisher of the Freie Presse branded this information as a lie. We are now, fortunately, able to prove our point, not only through the repeated assertions of George von Hollen but also through the signature of Richard Michaelis himself.</p>
   <p>Before his departure, George Von Hollen entrusted the settlement of his business affairs to the lawyer, A. S. Trude. The latter received recently several letters from him. Mr. Trude was kind enough to show us the following letter he received from Hollen:</p>
   <p>"Canada, May 17, 1876. Dear Mr. Trude, Far away from home, I am awaiting here the verdict of public opinion. When I look back, I realize that I have been a tool as well as a fool in the hands of gamblers and of designing politicians. The servile Chicago newspapers are on my desk and what hurts most is that some of them state that I have been a visitor of houses of ill fame.</p>
   <p>"As I see, the Staats Zeitung and the Neue Freie Presse had a quarrel about me. How does this bum Michaelis dare to deny that he received money from me <pb facs="5418474_4_1536.jpg" n="2"/>through blackmail? Perhaps this receipt for $300 which I am leaving in your hands, will shut his mouth."</p>
   <p>The first receipt reads as follows: "Chicago, June 2, 1874. Germania Bank of Chicago, S. E. Cor. Washington and 5th Ave. Pay to Geo. von Hollen on order three hundred dollars. Von Hollen and Kluetsch."</p>
   <p>On the back is written: "Pay to the order of Free Press. Geo. von Hollen". And the other receipt: "Free Press Printing Co. R. Michaelis." There is further the following item, written by Hollen when he mailed the note to Trude: "Blackmailed out of by R. Michaelis, Editor, Free Press (German Daily Newspaper)."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
