<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-10-29">Oct. 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">German Voters...For Altgeld and Cleveland a Powerful Demonstration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-10-29">Oct. 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN VOTERS...FOR ALTGELD AND CLEVELAND A POWERFUL DEMONSTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The candidate of the Democratic party. J. P. Altgeld, celebrated a brilliant triumph last night, attributable almost exclusively to the German element. At the central point of the 31st ward, under the auspices of the German Cleveland-Stevenson-Altgeld club of Washington Heights, a grand demonstration was given yesterday, in honor of the Democratic candidate for Governor, J. P. Altgeld. About 2,000 voters, almost all of them Germans, participated. From the neighboring towns, Pullman, Kensington, Fernwood, Dalton, Riverdale, Gano, Blue Island, etc., Democratic farmers, workers, and businessmen came to welcome Altgeld....</p>
   <p>Shortly after 7 P. M. the Democratic Club from Blue Island arrived with its president, J. Burke, as leader. These 400 men were dressed in white and blue uniforms, carried attractive flags, and made a good impression. Soon afterwards, the German-American Democratic Club of Washington Heights arrived to the sound of music.... The attractively decorated hall could not hold all of the people. The members of both Lutheran churches, under the leadership of their pastors, P. Budach and J. H. Patzer, constituted a considerable contingent....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0234.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Professor Clark called the meeting to order. A. Weigel was elected chairman. He deserves chief credit for the arrangement and splendid success of this mass-meeting.... Weigel then introduced Altgeld, who was greeted with much enthusiasm. The candidate spoke about problems of the nation and the state, and dwelt in particular upon the school question, stating that the repeal of the hated Edward Law could not be expected from the Republican party.... His speech made, obviously, a deep impression upon his audience... Mr. Altgeld can be certain to receive the votes of these German voterś....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
