<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-08-24">Aug. 24, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">They Are on the Job.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0157</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0157.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-08-24">Aug. 24, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THEY ARE ON THE JOB.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 8.. Lively propaganda disseminated by the German Republicans of Chicago is the outstanding feature of the present campaign. The German-American Central Clubs of Cook County held a meeting yesterday which was exceptionally well attended. Mr. Franz Amberg presided. Mr. Joseph Brucker reported on the excellent success the society has had in establishing new German-American Clubs and reorganizing a number of the old ones throughout the State of Illinois.</p>
   <p>To Dr. Markbreiter credit is due for this splendid work. The second report was read by Emil Willwerth, who was active in the reorganization of the German-Republican Club of the 13th Ward. Mr. Amberg suggested that a Propaganda Committee, composed of the younger set, be organized.</p>
   <p>Its aim would be to recruit the younger German element of Chicago for the Republican Party. The committee elected consisted of Messrs. John H. Logeman, Ward 25; Otto Follett, Ward 22; Emil Willwerth, Ward 2; David Schachtel, Ward 19; and Chris. Righeimer, Ward 7.</p>
   <p>The club has received letters of appreciation from Richard Yates; William <pb facs="5418474_4_0158.jpg" n="2"/>Mc Kinley and Theodore Roosevelt, as well as Graeme Stewart, member of the National Assembly of Illinois. Messrs. Yates, Stewart, E. G. Halle, and Judge Theodore Brentano were elected honorary members of the club....</p>
   <p>Joseph Brucker's proposal to organise German-American Glee Clubs was received with much enthusiasm. The Executive Board was then instructed to begin organization of the previously mentioned clubs. Mr. Herrmann, candidate for the office of supervisor, was introduced to the assembly as a member of the club.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
