<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-01-19">Jan. 19, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[Nativist Violence]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0672</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0672.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-01-19">Jan. 19, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[NATIVIST VIOLENCE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All the infernal hullabaloo of Tribune and Times, all the capon-like crowing of the Evening Journal, all the deep moral indignation of the Evening Post about the "horror" of Monday night, have been in vain. The infamous nativistic maliciousness has in vain been appealed to by the aristocratic money-bags against the just demands of the workers and small plot-owners.</p>
   <p>In its session of Wednesday night, the City Council has adopted a provisory fire limit which does full justice to the original demands of the Germans, even though it will not please a part of the 18th Ward. To make the Chicago Avenue, Wells Street and North Avenue, the fire limit on the North Side, was the compromise solution first proposed in the Illinois Staats Zeitung, and this the City Council has adopted uninfluenced by the howling of the know-nothing papers and the "violence" done to it by the incendiaries of the North Side.</p>
   <p>On the South and West Side it is simply the question of forbidding inside a certain area the construction of wooden houses on plots where formerly no houses at all stood. That is not by any means the same injustice, as if the poor people whose little wood houses were destroyed on the 9th of October were forbidden to restore them in the only fashion that is possible to them.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0673.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The gist of these happenings is simply this: That the nativists tried to exploit the great calamity by which Chicago has been afflicted to push the Germans into the corner; that in this endeavor the whole American press (with the single, honorable exception of a small evening paper, The Mail) fought against the Illinois Staats Zeitung, and branded a noisy demonstration as a "despicable uprising" and the Germans as rebels and criminals, but that in spite of it all, it has been defeated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
