<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-07-26">July 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Editor of the Sonntagpost:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-07-26">July 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Editor of the Sonntagpost:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fighting spirit prevailed among members of the German element who met in the cozy peasant room at the Bismarck Hotel on the evening of July 22. This spirit was introduced into the meeting by a certain society. Personal attacks, silly jealousies, and defamatory exclamations, were given free expression throughout the evening. However, as reconciliatory as the attitude of some were, especially since optimism prevailed, harmony will finally be achieved in that German controversy. There were also those who were caught by the antagonistic atmosphere which prevailed. Criticisms were numerous. The fact that invitations to the meeting reached the interested parties through the medium of the local press, was strongly attacked. However, this was done in good faith, and to assure the meeting the honor of the presence of the representatives of those great German groups, whose connections with the <pb facs="5418474_4_0102.jpg" n="2"/>Citizens Alliance was as yet not strengthened. For instance, the Turn Societies, the Singers, the Steuben Club, the Relief Alliance, the German Club, Lodges, and Churches, may have a chance to participate in the conference of the founding of a German-American National Alliance. Doubt has been expressed by the singing societies and others whether or not an organization designed chiefly upon the plan of taking stand in questions of local politics could be an important factor in strengthening the German-American solidarity. It would be incomprehensible indeed, if a prospective National Alliance, planning to participate in every important question for the benefit of the entire German element of this country, namely, the vital question of immigration, prohibition, etc., would not receive the unanimous approval of the German-American population.</p>
   <p>The organization to be founded would be practically a political one, with decided political functions as planned by the Citizens Alliance. However, according to the opinion of a group of friends of mine, as well <pb facs="5418474_4_0103.jpg" n="3"/>as myself, an organization founded on principles as those mentioned, is not justified to be put into operation, since no intelligent citizen wishes to be deprived of his personal right of expressing his political views, neither in this respect will he submit to the dictates of a National Alliance.</p>
   <p>As the representative of the United Singers of Chicago, and as representative of the Singers Alliance of Northwest, I shall be glad for the opportunity to consult with any person interested in the facts stated, upon request. I am certain that only through friendly discussion of this subject can we finally decide upon the right procedure in this matter.</p>
   <p>A. C. Wehrwein,</p>
   <p>6129 Prairie Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
