<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-08-17">Aug. 17, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[The Prison Commission]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0944</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0944.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-08-17">Aug. 17, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[THE PRISON COMMISSION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The brutality with which the Tribune and Times, and following them, also the Evening Post, have attacked the majority in the City Council for their actions in regard to the nominations of prison commissioners can be matched only by the stupidity with which these papers now try to present the complete refutation of their accusations as a victory.</p>
   <p>The situation was simply this: The City Council expected that among the four members of the commission there should be at least one German, or a citizen who can speak German. Mr. Mason, however, declared he would not name a German because then the Irish would demand one commissioner too, and he did not want to nominate two foreigners. This pronouncement made by Mr. Mason in somewhat undiplomatic form so that it could be (or, at any rate, was) understood as a declaration of enmity against all foreign-born, aroused antagonism. One saw in it nativistic spitefulness and accepted the propositions of the mayor with a diffidence that continued to grow, when Mr. Mason continued to send in only the names of native Americans, after he had been informed, that the Irish made no demand for a commissioner. He was advised that, if he would name John Herting, the Irish would be just as satisfied as the Germans, and that the two other commissioners might, in that case, be any two citizens agreeable to the mayor. However, Mr. Mason did not send in the name of Herting but of Louis Wahl. Very well, the Germans were satisfied, because Mr. Wahl is in every <pb facs="5418474_4_0945.jpg" n="2"/>respect as able and honorable a man as Mr. Herting. Mr. The Irish would have preferred the latter, because he is a Catholic, but they were willing to vote for Mr. Wahl, under the condition that at least one of the other commissioners would be a Democrat.</p>
   <p>Finally the mayor thought he could get his way if he pitted the Irish against the Germans; so he retracted the name of Wahl and instead sent that of Thomas Hoyne. Against Mr. Hoyne's high qualifications nobody had any objection - however, the Irish well understood for what an unworthy purpose they were to be used, and refused to betray their German colleagues. For this reason they voted against Hoyne.</p>
   <p>Now the mayor went back to his original proposition. But in the place of Mancel Talcott, he did not send in the name of S. S. Hayes, but, to spite the aldermen, Mr. Derrickson. Now the City Council decided to end the childish game, and to vote separately on the three names. So, Hammond and Wahl were elected almost unanimously, as they would have been from the beginning if the mayor in his stubbornness had not always coupled some unacceptable name with theirs. His obstinacy has been praised as "noble firmness" by the Times and Tribune. Their intention to sow enmity between the native and the naturalized <pb facs="5418474_4_0946.jpg" n="3"/>citizens, and so to open a road to a new, this time nativistic "Civic Reform" has come clearly to light. What motives the Evening Post has had to join in this maneuver is very hard to understand.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
