<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-05-18">May 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The German and the Irish</title><title level="a" type="sub">Protest against the Treaty with England</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-05-18">May 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN AND THE IRISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">Protest Against the Treaty with England</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Germans and Irish combined their forces in a protest meeting held at the North Side Turn Hall yesterday. The protest was directed against the planned treaty between England and the United States. The plan will be submitted to the United States Senate, in the disguise of an arbitrary court agreement, which in reality is the beginning of the laying of the foundation for an alliance, between England and the United States.</p>
   <p>Seven speakers addressed the intensely spirited meeting, which was conducted by Mr. Emil Hoechster. The chairman first explained the reason for this meeting, and then added that a friendly policy with all nations is unquestionably the right thing, but the United States must not sign any pact which is not based upon sound policy, least of all with England. It is no secret that the British Government is apprehensive of Germany and Ireland, therefore, she seeks the alliance with the United States. It is also true that the Germans and the Irish have been largely responsible for the grand development of our <pb facs="5418474_4_0137.jpg" n="2"/>country, for the defense of which they would always cooperate....Mr. Huss then explained that an arbitrary court agreement is usually nothing else than a forerunner of an alliance, not intended for the preservation of peace. An alliance is in other words a planned treaty. The history of England shows that it never had a friendly attitude toward our country, moreover, that she is mistrusted by other nations, as a consequence of her unethical policy. As an example, the speaker illustrated the attitude of the British Government toward the United States during the years of the Civil War....Selfishness is the real factor in the analysis of its present love for peace. Two so powerful national elements as the Germans and the Irish, cooperating since March 1898, must be able to enlighten the American nation and acquaint it with the dangers lurking from a treaty with Great Britain....The following resolutions were then passed:</p>
   <p>"According to an announcement from Washington, D. C., the Department of State will submit to the Senate for approval, the so-called Arbitrary Court Agreement bill, between the United States Government and the government of Great Britain, in the near future.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0138.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This, however, under the pretext that the alliance of the two greatest English speaking nations will further the world peace. Other nations consider this act as an announcement of a treaty between these two nations, especially since England, in a statement to its subjects, referred to it as the chief means by which to get protection from the Kingdom of Great Britain. Every true American must realize, therefore, that England alone would reap the benefits from the treaty, while the United States would thus create an ill feeling among the rest of nations, and thus would intensify the possibility of an armed conflict rather than achieve the contrary....</p>
   <p>In the interest of our own national peace and for the safety of our adopted country, the German and Irish citizens of Chicago propose that the President of the United States, the Senate, and the House of Representatives, reject the planned treaty, or pact with Great Britain and we, strongly united Germans and Irish, promise solemnly to fight any candidate at the ballot box, who, running as the Representative of the nation is in favor or would vote for the proposed treaty. This in itself discloses traitorous intentions, to throw us and our adopted country into a bloody conflict with other nations....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0139.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Furthermore, we are fully in accord with Speaker Champ Clark's recent declaration to ask the commercial treaty with Canada and later, for Canada itself, including all the country up to the North Pole....</p>
   <p>It has been decided to send a copy of these resolutions to the President, the Secretary of State, and a copy to each of the two Senators from Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
