<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-03-31">March 31, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Position of the Candidates in the Matter of Special Licenses</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0754</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0754.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-03-31">March 31, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">POSITION OF THE CANDIDATES IN THE MATTER OF SPECIAL LICENSES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thirteen of the thirty-one candidates have agreed if elected to vote for a change of the ordinance.</p>
   <p>The "Abendpost" has called on all candidates eligible as members of the City council in the next election regarding their position on the resolutions made at the recent protest meeting. Only one of the thirty-one aldermen Jonathan Ruxton of the 34th ward has declared himself against a special license to associations; according to his opinion, such action would increase greatly the danger of the dance halls. He also thinks it unlawful to give the permit to one association and refuse it to another. The Democratic candidate Finn of the 29th ward refused to state his opinion and said that the state law forbids the permit of a special license. Thirteen of thirty-one candidates have agreed to vote for a change of the ordinance if elected; so that social associations, against whose reputations nothing bad is known can obtain a special license to sell alcoholic drinks <pb facs="5418474_4_0755.jpg" n="2"/>at their festivals. It is expected that the remaining candidates according to their expressed opinions will also vote for the change.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
