<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1895-02-04">February 4th, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Local Politics.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0193</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0193.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1895-02-04">February 4th, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Local Politics.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-American Republican Central Club of Cook County completed its organization at a meeting held last Saturday evening in the Grand Pacific Hotel, by electing the following officers: President John C. W. Rhode, Vice President, North side: Felix Buschick, Westside: Ernest Wiedel, F. Sahlar, John Muchle. Southside: T. A. Moll . recording secretary: C. F. Hermann, Corresponding Secretary, Emil Willwerth, Ass't. Corresponding Secretary L. Kollilzki, Finance Secrretary, Robert Busse, Treasurer: L. Hebel: Sergeant at Arms: Otto Levi. A committee of five has been instructed with the preparations of a declaration of principles (platform) which should be read in the meeting next Friday. For the purpose of holding the Primary according to the Crawford laws, the Republican party leaders decided to adjourn the City Convention until the last week of February or the first week in March instead of the middle of this month, as was intended earlier.</p>
   <p>In the spring the offices of 20 Republicans and 14 Democrats of the City Council will expire. The Civic Federation will nominate candidates for the Town Council in all such wards, where the political parties have nominated objectionable candidates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
