<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-01-21">January 21, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">German-American Citizen Club.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-01-21">January 21, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN CITIZEN CLUB.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the auspices of the German-American Citizen's Club a meeting was held yesterday at the Oswald Hall, located at the corner of Halsted and 52nd streets, by German-American citizens. Due to excessive snow it was difficult to go anywhere, and this condition, undoubtedly, prevented many from attending the meeting, as very few, comparatively, assembled. Mr. Frank Dober presided, and announced that the purpose of the meeting was to unite the German citizens of the Town of Lake into a solid organization, thereby enabling them to have some authority at elections and to exert some influence corresponding with their numbers in local politics.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Pauly exhorted the German citizens most urgently to make united efforts, and also urged that all citizens should turn out to vote, as the Irish and other nationalities are doing. Likewise, the speaker stated it is necessary that the Germans elect a captain for each of the 39 precincts, in order to have a more solid organization. Mr. Pauly then proposed <pb facs="5418474_4_0291.jpg" n="2"/>to arrange a general meeting on the first Sunday in February in Oswald's Hall, and that invitations be sent out by the secretary. It was also decided to ask Mr. Christ. Seybe for the lists of voters in the different precincts, in order to obtain names and addresses of German citizens. At the next meeting a committee of five shall be appointed, and it will be the duty of these members to organize the German voters. Then the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
