<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-12-03">Dec. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Era of Licenses.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1326</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1326.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-12-03">Dec. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE ERA OF LICENSES.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The President has decreed that many articles which have been imported will, in the future, be allowed to enter the United States only under a special Federal permit called a license. This restriction of the Freedom of commerce is necessary, because from neutral countries many articles were sent into the United States by merchants to the profit, or at least the benefit of German citizens. This sort of giving aid to the enemy had to cease. The quickest way to stop it was to stop all imports but that course would injure American industry. For this reason, the familiar expedient known as the license system was resorted to. When every government official is scrupulously honest, unapproachable and exceptionally alert, then the license system approaches perfection. But it is so in theory only. In practice it is far from perfect. All men are not honest. Interpretation of regulations differ. The official who investigates the statements or conduct of the licenses, uses his own individual judgment. That may be influenced by events or premises not in <pb facs="5418474_4_1327.jpg" n="2"/>harmony with a strict compliance with the rules, and regulations of the Government. It is self evident that a system open to so many defects is not perfect. It is a compromise between the policy of free trade and that of absolute embargo. This compromise arrangement now covers our exports as well as our imports of many articles. It gives to our government (for the first time) very valuable information concerning our foreign trade, although merely incident. After peace is concluded the statistics now being prepared by our government will be of inestimable value to our exporters and importers. Thus the license system, notwithstanding all its faults, will prove a blessing.</p>
   <p>But its present value will consist, mainly, in the stoppage of aid to the enemy. If Americans are purchasing articles in Mexico, South American or neutral European countries, they shoud, at least, inform our government whether or not the money gained by the transaction will belong to enemies or to friends of our nation. If the former, no license should be granted for the importation or exportation of such articles. Should an American industry suffer in consequence, thereof, then the leaders in that industry should <pb facs="5418474_4_1328.jpg" n="3"/>discover other means of supplying the wants, and develop the resources of that industry, divorced from profits for our enemies. We cannot wage war with our right hand and give aid and comfort to the enemy through business done by our left hand, even if it be profitable to us as well as to the enemy.</p>
   <p>Therefore the exportation and importation, under such a license system, should be carried on under the strict supervision, by honest officials, who have at heart the welfare of America and the attainment of an early peace. The proverbial "butcher, baker and candle stickmaker" are all doing business under Federal licenses. So are hundreds of other trades. Even newspapers, which are partly business and partly literary concerns, must take out licenses. The long list of industries which are now "licensed" is steadily increasing. We have entered an era of licenses. And where will it stop? At present we hear few complaints. The body is just born and the public is in attendance mentally, measuring it and reserving judgment. Will the graft microbe flourish in it? Will the "influence" bug buzz around and still the voice of duty? Will the license system soon be no more than a formality, or will it continue to grant <pb facs="5418474_4_1329.jpg" n="4"/>to the deserving real "badges of honor" as was primarily intended? It remains the duty of those, who have to apply the license rules and issue permits, to be unbiased, honest, incorruptible, efficient and alert, in order that every license granted shall remain a testimonial of merit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
