<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-30">Apr. 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">City Council Committees</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0743</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0743.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-30">Apr. 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CITY COUNCIL COMMITTEES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new committees of the City Council are composed of the following members:</p>
   <p>Finance Committee: Richert, Schwartz, A. A. McCormick, Fetzer, Woodhull, Moran, Walker, Capitain, Lipps, Watson, C. F. Smith, A. O. Anderson, Wallace, [Joseph] Kostner, and Maypole.</p>
   <p>Local Transportation Committee: Capitain, McDonough, McNichols, Smith, Walkowiak, Franz, Bauler, Wallace, Lipps, Watson, Bryne, Fisher, Toman, Lynch, Guernsey, Olsen, and Schwartz.</p>
   <p>Committee on Gas, Oil, and Electric Light: Lynch, T. A. Hogan, McNichols, Novak, McDonough, Walkowiak, Bowler, Bauler, Walker, Wallace, Link, Adamowski, O'Tocle, Furman, Toman, Horne, and Pretzel.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0744.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Depot Committee: Lipps, Kenna, Schwartz, Guernsey, McNichols, Home, Touhy, Bowler, Walker, Capitain, Mulcahy, Eaton, Kostner, A. C. Anderson, and Cermak.</p>
   <p>Committee on Local Industries: Fisher, Fetzer, Klaus, Cullerton, Novak, T. A. Hogan, Smith, Bauler, Pretzel, Madderom, O' Toole, Clark, Horne, Olsen, and Steffen.</p>
   <p>Committee on Harbors, Piers, and Bridges: Woodhull, Kenna, L. B. Anderson Govier, Cullerton, AdamKiewicz, Shaffer, Kavanagh, Powers, Hibbeler, [John] Haderlein, Kaindl, Moran, Garner, and Lyle.</p>
   <p>Legal Committee: Cermak, Coughlin, McDonough, McCormick, Fetzer, Woodhull, Kaindl, Powers, Steffen, T. A. Hogan, Link, Crowe, Lynch, Kostner, Dorney, <pb facs="5418474_4_0745.jpg" n="3"/>Hibbeler, Lyle, and Garner.</p>
   <p>Committee on Streets and Alleys: Toman, Coughlin, L. B. Anderson, Mulcahy, Kunz, Adamkiewicz, Touhy, Fick, Moran, Krumdick Crowe, Dorney, Hibbeler, Lyle, and Garner.</p>
   <p>Committee on Licenses: Joseph H. Smith, L. B. Anderson,Kovarik, Coughlin, Adamkiewicz, Krumdick, Novak, Powers, Kaindl, Franz, Haderlein, Furman, O'Toole, S. M. Mogan, and C. F. Smith.</p>
   <p>Committee on Buildings: Rostner, Jackson, Mulcahy, Eaton, Madderom, Klaus, Krumdick, Pietrowski, Kavanagh, Powers, Fick, Crowe, S. M. Hogan, Hibbeler, and Armitage.</p>
   <p>Committee on Schools, Fire Department, Police and Civil Service: Clark, <pb facs="5418474_4_0746.jpg" n="4"/>Jackson, Madderom, Kenna, Cermak, Horne, Walker, Bowler, Pietrowski, Kavanagh, Adamkiewicz, Fick, Armitage, Link, McDonough, Adamowski, and Bryne.</p>
   <p>Committee on Sanitation: Fetzer, Kenna, Jackson, Cullerton, Shaffer, Kunz, Kavanagh, Franz, Klaus, Pretzel, Furman, A. O. Anderson, Passmore, Burns, and Adamowski.</p>
   <p>Committee on Elevation: Maypole, Coughlin, L. B. Anderson, Mulcahy, Govier, Shaffer, Fick, McNichols, and Hogan.</p>
   <p>Committee on Compensation: Watson, Richert, Kovarik, Kavanagh, Lipps, Garner, Moran, Fisher, and Toman.</p>
   <p>Committee on Parks, Playgrounds, and Beaches: Govier, Jackson, Kovarik, <pb facs="5418474_4_0747.jpg" n="5"/>Passmore, Pietrowski, O'Toole, Haderlein, Lyle, and Armitage.</p>
   <p>Committee on Prosecution of Gas Company: Capitain, Richert, Lipps, Lynch, Olsen, and McDonough.</p>
   <p>Committee on Police: Steffen, Touhy, Kaindl, Haypole, Guernsey, Bryne, Dorney, Eaton, Krumdick, Govier, Novak, C. F. Smith, Passmore, Burns, and Furman.</p>
   <p>Committee on Efficiency, Economy and Rehabilitation: McCormick, Steffen, Link, Woodhull, Schwartz, Walker, Olsen, Maypole, Adamowski, Clark, A. Anderson, Touhy, Burns, Bowler, Guernsey, Watson, Richert, Pretzel, Walkowiak and Novak.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
