<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-16">May 16, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The State Senate and Brentano (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-16">May 16, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE STATE SENATE AND BRENTANO (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With respect to the refusal in accepting former Congressman Lorenz Brentano of Chicago as a justice of the peace: The nomination of Messrs. Demars, Prindiville, and Hawkinson as justices of the peace in Chicago was unanimously accepted by the Republican members of the state senate at Springfield, although two of the three appointees are Democrats. Then Brentano was considered, as the Governor had also submitted his name. Brentano was present in the senate chamber.</p>
   <p>Senator White, Republican, of Chicago arose and said: "I hope the senate will not accept this nomination. Not so long ago, the nominee was a Republican in congress. When the Republicans did not nominate him again, he became a Democrat. Recently he came back into the Republican fold as a <pb facs="5418474_4_1127.jpg" n="2"/>candidate for justice of the peace for Chicago's North Side. If you accept him, he will again become a Democrat, so that Mayor Harrison will appoint him a police court judge. He is neither fish, flesh, nor fowl. A man who changes his views so suddenly for purely selfish reasons is unfit to be a justice of the peace."</p>
   <p>Then Democratic Senator Southworth of Montgomery country remarked: "I am opposed to a confirmation of Brentano's appointment, although I never heard anything about the man heretofore. Only a short time ago he was in congress, and now he has dropped to the low rungs of the ladder, and wants to be a justice of the pence in Chicago. Such an office seeker is unfit for a judicial position, even for as inferior one."</p>
   <p>Republican Senator Thomas of Belleville next said: "As far as I know, Brentano was a Republican formerly, became a Democrat for a short time, became aware of his mistake, and returned to the Republican ranks. I do not think that he <pb facs="5418474_4_1128.jpg" n="3"/>sinned so much that we should refuse his appointment, therefore I'll vote for him."</p>
   <p>Democratic Senator Neece Donough County asked to what party Brentano belongs at present.</p>
   <p>White replied: "That is difficult to determine. At this time--as far as politics is concerned--he is like Barnum's 'What is it' or ornithorhynchus paradoxus, which has the beak of a duck, fest of a duck and the body of a mammal. The Democrats can have it, we don't want it."</p>
   <p>The vote gave the following results:</p>
   <p>Only ten voted for Brentano's appointment, and twenty-four were opposed. Most Republicans voted against the appointment. Quite a few Democrats voted <pb facs="5418474_4_1129.jpg" n="4"/>against Brentano, among them Merritt, the Democratic leader, senator of Marion County.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
