<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-07-06">July, 6, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Henner</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">The City Council Has a Right to Reinstate Him</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0904</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0904.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-07-06">July, 6, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">HENNER</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">The City Council Has a Right to Reinstate Him</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The excitement and indignation about Fire Marshall Benner's unjust dismissal from the force is apparent in all parts of the city and it is almost impossible to find anyone who favors the mayor's act.</p>
   <p>Our reporter found two exceptions in Alderman Phelps and Comptroller Gurney. Both said that the mayor has a right to discharge a man who has refused to cooperate in enforcing economic measures. It would have required only a word or so, and Benner could have induced the entire force of the fire department to accept a small wage cut, and that would have made it easy to obtain pay reductions in other departments, so that the economy program could have been started without difficulty. By not doing that, Benner showed disobedience to the mayor, they argued, and that cannot be tolerated under any circumstances.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0905.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the citizens look at the matter from the proper angle, they will side with the mayor, even though the people regret at this time that a very capable, but not irreplaceable, man has lost his job. It will soon become apparent that the city can get along without Benner, according to Phelps and Gurney.</p>
   <p>Mayor Harrison</p>
   <p>The reporter then interviewed Mayor Harrison, and asked him if he had anything new to say about Benner's dismissal.</p>
   <p>"Nothing at all," said the mayor, "but I have found out since that, at the last legislative session, the charter of the city was amended, enabling the council, by a two-thirds majority vote, to reinstate a man after I had dismissed him. But I would not have acted differently, even had I known this at the time. Benner refused to co-operate in a matter which was entirely under my jurisdiction, <pb facs="5418474_4_0906.jpg" n="3"/>and so I had to discharge him.</p>
   <p>"I am convinced that any unprejudiced person will side with me, after thoroughly considering the affair. According to the law, economy becomes a dire necessity [sic], and I wanted to introduce economy measures in Marshal Benner's department; but he made it difficult for me, and actually refused to follow instructions. I cannot give the city a good administration if the officials do not concur in my opinions on financial problems.</p>
   <p>"When I entered office, I asked all officials to hand in their resignation. Police Commissionar Seavey tendered his resignation, and I refused to accept it after he gave me assurances of always respecting my wishes, and said that, if it should prove incompatible with his conscience, he [Seavey] would resign. I would have asked for a similar promise if Benner had resigned. He did not resign, and I let him remain in office until he disregarded my financial policy.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0907.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"I have no intention of being a dictator. I have shown, on many occasions, that I follow the advice of various department heads on matters about which they are better informed than I am. But financial questions must be decided by the comptroller and me.</p>
   <p>"You can rest assured, Benner's dismissal will soon be forgotten, but the city will be grateful for my economy drive.</p>
   <p>"Of course, I don't know what the city council will do. Probably an extra session will be called to receive my report about Benner's dismissal. I am going to get more information on the legal phases of the case, and will act accordingly.</p>
   <p>"However, I wish to say this: I regret to lose Benner just as much as any citizen does. I consider him to be an able official, who was a great credit to <pb facs="5418474_4_0908.jpg" n="5"/>the city and, particularly, the Germans. But discipline must be maintained, and so I had no alternative, even though the affair may cause temporary political repercussions. But, considering it from my angle, I have no other political ambitions than to administer my office in a conscientious manner, and, after considering the matter thoroughly, the people will admit that I acted accordingly.''</p>
   <p>Marshal Benner</p>
   <p>Marshal Benner had nothing to say which would shed new light on the subject. He was indignant, however, that the mayor hinted that Benner had acted question-ably when the fire hose contracts were awarded. He, [Benner] could only say that he never closed a contract on his own accord, and that he always obtained the approval of the mayor, the comptroller, and the committee.</p>
   <p>Also, Benner's Republican friends are being unjustly accused, since it was asserted that they had induced Benner to oppose the mayor. No one induced <pb facs="5418474_4_0909.jpg" n="6"/>Benner to disregard the mayor, and he always had complied in all matters where the mayor had jurisdiction. However he [Benner] refused to accept responsibility for the salary cut affecting the firemen, and he was not willing to advise them voluntarily to accept such a reduction, because he did not believe the mayor had a right to expect such action from a fire marshal. However, he had repeatedly told the mayor that, if an order were given to reduce the salaries, he (Benner) would enforce such an edict.</p>
   <p>The mayor, though, was not willing to issue such an order, but demanded that the firemen should accept the reduction voluntarily.</p>
   <p>The Law</p>
   <p>The law concerning the dismissal of officials appointed with the consent of the city council, contains the following provision:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0910.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"The mayor shall be empowered to dismiss any official appointed by him, upon a formal charge, if such a dismissal appears beneficial to the city in the opinion of the mayor, but the reasons for such a dismissal must be submitted to the city council in not less than five days nor more than ten days...."</p>
   <p>This stipulation was added to the city's charter during the last legislative session, and the mayor is thereby enabled to discharge officials as he sees fit.</p>
   <p>There is, therefore, nothing to prevent the city council from reinstating Benner, if two-thirds of the members vote in his favor. But this would not prevent the mayor from appointing a new fire marshal on August 1st, at the end of Benner's term. The city council, in turn, may postpone ratification of the new appointment, and so keep Benner in office for an indefinite period.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0911.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Alderman Tuley was asked yesterday what he thought about Benner's dismissal, a question which might prove interesting, since Tuley, in the past, has shown the same attitude as Benner, when salary reductions became an issue.</p>
   <p>But the Alderman refused to be interviewed. He said he would give no more interviews. "But," replied the reporter, "you know about the city charter, which gives the council the right to revoke a mayoral act by a two-thirds vote?"</p>
   <p>"I consider it a sensible provision"</p>
   <p>"Will you resign on Monday evening?"</p>
   <p>He smiled significantly, and said: "I wont be interviewed."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0912.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Alderman Daly was one of the few who sided with the mayor.</p>
   <p>"Benner was wrong", said the alderman, "he should have complied with the mayor's wish and resigned. Perhaps the mayor would have reconsidered the matter then, and this might have led to Benner's reinstatment. But I believe that anyone would have discharged Benner peremptorily, after he refused to resign. The city will have forgotten Benner in a few days, and will realize that we can have a good fire department without him."</p>
   <p>The alderman is probably mistaken. While there is no one who is indispensable, it will nevertheless take a long time for the city to find anyone as capable. But Mr. Daly is a good Democrat who, like Harrison, wants to make a political plum out of the fire department.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0913.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>The majority of Chicagoans know that Benner saved the fire department from the political morass, and no one whom the mayor might appoint as fire marshal will enjoy the confidence of the people to the extent Benner did.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
