<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-07-08">July 8, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">Our Gratitude to the Germans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0848</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0848.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-07-08">July 8, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">OUR GRATITUDE TO THE GERMANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The undersigned express their gratitude to the Germans of Chicago for the great service they have rendered them in the fight for the Normal School of Cook County. We openly acknowledge that it was the German element of this city and the county, which saved for us this wonderful institution. Owing to their great help, we didn't suffer defeat. With the one honorable exception of the Inter-Ocean, the entire English press was against us. As a rule, the editors of the English press agree on things in butcherdog fashion; but in this instance they have been in absolute harmony, against our cause, or, - what is still worse, - they remained passive and neutral. But the victory is ours, with due credit to German help.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0849.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our deep appreciation to the German press with the Staats Zeitung as leader in this fight. Mr. Raster's letter published in the Tribune and the Inter-Ocean on that decisive voting morning, added enormously to our victory, for many a member of the School Board was won to our cause through the medium of this letter. Many German people all of whom would be impossible to mention separately, like Messrs. Heinemann, Madlener, Stern and others, were unsparing in their efforts to help the good cause to its victory. The Normal School is founded upon the principles of the German system of education and is worthy of the interest of every German..........Long live German education and its well-wishers of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Charles H. Hann</p>
   <p>Charles Bary</p>
   <p>This letter was written in excellent German by the two English-Americans and reprinted in its original form. (Publisher).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
