<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-03-08">March 8, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">The German Democrats</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0284</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0284.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-03-08">March 8, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN DEMOCRATS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-American Democratic Central Organization held another exceptionally well patronized meeting, yesterday evening, at Jung's Hall, where officers were elected and plans promulgated to create a strongly unified, capable association.</p>
   <p>The following gentlemen were elected: Leo Austrian, president; and eleven other Germans, representing different sections of the city. After the election Messrs. Austrian, Haerting, Hoechster, and Hoffmann, addressed the assembly, stressing the necessity of a strong German- Democratic alliance, if anything was to be accomplished for the furtherance of the German language.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0285.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was a very lucid explanation. Mr. Hoffmann emphasized the importance of the aldermanic office and added, very candidly, that the citizens alone were at fault, if the monopolies and powerful corporations skin them alive. The only protection against such might was the alderman, who votes at the City Hall sessions and decides as to the distribution of the valuable privileges and franchises. That men, who live only by politics are often sent to such an important post and, that thereby a fertile field for corruption will be created, is caused solely by that terrible indifference which is displayed during the election of the convention delegates.</p>
   <p>At this time the Primary elections will be conducted in conformity with the stipulations of the Crawford law, therefore the citizens control the election in so far as it enables them to choose delegates for the convention who are not interested in political dickering, but who will support men of integrity only.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0286.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Every German Democrat should consult with his neighbor, as only through this activity of the individual, can the power of the multitude manifest itself.</p>
   <p>The organization will hold another meeting at Jung's Hall, next Monday, in order to settle the question of the German Democratic Ward Clubs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
