<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-22">Feb. 22, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The City Hall of Schilda</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1502</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1502.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-22">Feb. 22, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE CITY HALL OF SCHILDA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: The headline refers to the Schildbuerger (Schild citizens), noted for their stupidity in municipal enterprises, who built a city hall without making any provision for windows.]</p>
   <p>When the city council of Chicago applied the Schildbuerger method and decided that one half of the city hall-the part which belongs to Chicago-- should be built of an entirely different stone than the other half of the building--which is county property--our city fathers based their verdict on economy. Cheapness was the motive, first, last and above all. One might gather from this that the disreputable spirit "Cheap-and-Bad," so tenaciously fought by Reuleaux, found a sanctuary in our city council.</p>
   <p>The double building seems to be patterned after an Austrian prison suit, one leg grey, the other yellow, and the structure will be a dismal reminder to <pb facs="5418474_4_1503.jpg" n="2"/>our great grandchildren a century hence, a testimonial of economy perverted into foolish penury. Of course, none of these considerations are nearly as important as the fact that the grey pant leg costs less than the yellow one! Moreover, ominous indications are beginning to appear, tending to prove the saving theory fallacious. The people who contracted to supply the Bedford sandstone, are losing heart. They complain that the price which they set is not commensurate with the work involved in obtaining the stone; that costs are barely covered, and thus no more material can be supplied at the former price. Presumably, these gentlemen hoped--if they hold a contract for delivery--that it would be a simple matter to submit bills for extra expenditures, which would take care of any losses caused by a low bid. But they were disappointed in their expectations, because a close watch was kept on operations. Now the contractors are in a position where they must declare, "We won't play ball!"</p>
   <p>What about it? The stultification of our City Council is complete. That body has no recourse but to sue the guarantors--experience has always shown this to be unprofitable. In the interim, building construction ceases or <pb facs="5418474_4_1504.jpg" n="3"/>else the higher price will have to be paid, which will mean that the horrible grey stone will be used. Perhaps the most prudent procedure would be to dismantle the structure down to the foundation and rebuild it with another kind of stone. Whatever solution is resorted to, the botched half of the "Schilda" council building will cost more than the other half.</p>
   <p>Such things happen when public administrations subscribe to this tenet of which every intelligent citizen is aware, that that is cheapest which costs the least. The best is always the cheapest. But whenever public work is involved, one finds blind competition without regard for quality, but with cheapness as the only criterion. The work or the order must be given to whoever asks the least, even if every well-informed person knows that it cannot be honestly accomplished at the quoted price; or that the contractor, to break even, must either cheat on work or material, perhaps both. If such trickery is prevented, then operations must be discontinued.</p>
   <p>No experienced businessman acts in that manner where he builds for himself--and cities should act accordingly. Whenever the City Council attempts to <pb facs="5418474_4_1505.jpg" n="4"/>use sound judgment, then virulent, scandal-seeking papers, like the Chicago Times, speak of graft. Whenever the city finds that a person making the lowest bid lacks the experience and money to give proper security for the completion of any work, or when it is evident that his promises cannot be fulfilled, that bid is turned down and the city accepts the next lowest offer; then certain abominable papers publish accounts about the differences in price and regard it as money stolen from the taxpayers. This places the members of the Council under a moral obligation to accept the lowest offer, even if they are definitely convinced that it is wrong to do so, as the seemingly cheapest bids invariably prove to be the costliest in the end.</p>
   <p>In this manner countless public works in the United States were either bungled or the cost of erection was tremendously increased. [Unfortunately] our own "Schilda" city hall will not be the last to suffer from such practices.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
