<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-07">Jan. 7, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Election Frauds</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1251</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1251.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-07">Jan. 7, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">ELECTION FRAUDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since receiving proof that many frauds had been perpetrated, County Judge Edmund K. Jarecki [polish] has ordered a recount of the ballots which were cast on November 8. One cannot help but rejoice at the decision of the Judge, and we can only regret that more than a whole year will have elapsed before the recount can be made. Chicagoans are not learning for the first time that there is, and always has been, dishonesty in certain wards during elections. That's an old story. Occasionally, during the course of years, recounts have been made, but with few exceptions they have brought little to light. That is only natural. In the first place, it is not always possible to establish irrefutable evidence of error or the falsification of ballots after a long period of time, and then it is even more difficult to discover the perpetrator.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1252.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Several election officials have been fined or imprisoned during the past years for committing or aiding in election frauds. They were convicted of their crimes. However, were they the only guilty ones, or did part of the guilt lie with those unscrupulous party leaders who make hell hot for the election officials who cannot "add up" a winning vote in their precincts "for the party"? As long as the parties themselves do not advocate absolutely honest principles in this respect, and reward only those in their midst who secure the most votes for the party, without regard to the method or means employed, and as long as they permit these officials to serve at the next election, because these "party workers" are so successful, then all well-intended efforts of the County Judge to render elections more honest will not avail much. As long as gangsters and ex-convicts are employed as election officials the public need not wonder that the results of elections are "corrected" by such jailbirds. Only those persons whose honesty and integrity is accepted beyond all doubt should be permitted to function as election officials. And then, objections to the results of elections should be made as soon as possible after the election, and should be investigated just as promptly, so that every opportunity <pb facs="5418474_4_1253.jpg" n="3"/>to permit evidence to disappear will be blocked; for it is not new to find that great numbers of ballots vanish during recounts.</p>
   <p>The ballot is the instrument with which the citizen of a democracy participates in the government of his country. If he is robbed of the ballot, or if it is given to one of the members of the opposing party, he is defrauded of his citizen's right, and democracy becomes a mere farce. The parties ought to have just as much interest in honest elections as an individual citizen has. If they have not, then they are dishonest and usurpatory; for they rob voters of the right of self-determination, and seek to maintain themselves in power, not in order to promote the welfare of the public, but to gain their own selfish ends. Judge Jarecki's independence and justice have won him an enviable reputation. We may rest assured that he will also bring these virtues to bear in this matter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
