<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-05">Oct. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">German-American Democratic Organization of Cook County</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-05">Oct. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN DEMOCRATIC ORGANIZATION OF COOK COUNTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the so-called West Room of the Sherman Hotel a meeting of the executive committee of the German-American Democratic Organization of Cook County took place yesterday afternoon in which very many participated. The meeting was presided over by the president, Ernst J. Kruetgen.</p>
   <p>Leopold Neumann reported that a mass meeting of women is planned for October 28, at 1 P. M., in the Wicker Park Hall. Congressman William H. Dietrich has promised to address the meeting.</p>
   <p>There will also be a large German meeting on November 1, at 8 P. M., in the Social Turner Hall on the corner of Belmont Avenue and Paulina Street.Congress-man Dietrich will also be the speaker of the evening at this meeting, with Judge Henry Horner, the candidate for governor of the State of Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0096.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>An address which aroused enthusiasm was made by Joe Grein, the city inspector of weights and measures, who is in favor of making the German-American Democratic Organization a permanent institution in Cook County, and of extending it over the entire state, in order to unite all Americans of German extraction in a permanent organization which will suit them, and also in order to insure that the Germans find recognition after the elections.</p>
   <p>Other addresses were given by Judge John Charles Lewe, Miss Charlotte Slavitt, Walter W. L. Meyer, William Rothman, Dr. John Kercher, Lorenz Schlegel, John Traeger Sr., and Mrs. Marie Eidler.</p>
   <p>The members are requested to persuade their clubs to obtain campaign literature for distributional purposes from the headquarters at Hotel Sherman, room 604. So-called pledge cards for Congressman Dietrich will be obtainable at headquarters beginning tomorrow.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0097.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The members of the executive committee, which consists of eighty men and women, are actively at work in the clubs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
