<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-09-18">Sep. 18, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Are Politics Decent?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1415</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1415.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-09-18">Sep. 18, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">ARE POLITICS DECENT?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The statement of the Westliche Post: "We do not live to carry on politics, much less, however, can a decent person carry on politics in order to live", is decidedly controversial. It would indicate that no editor of a paper, particularly of a political party organ, could be a respectable fellow citizen. Especially Germans go too far in their criticism of politics and politicians.... Many of our best and most dependable politicians were, perhaps, originally compelled by their fellow citizens to enter politics. Eventually they were elected and sent to Washington, and because of their attempt to be honest and decent, they were reelected to Congress again and again, thereby neglecting their own private business or were forced to give up their practice, and become more or less dependent upon their salaries as congressmen. Do they not then carry on politics for their livelihood? But how exceedingly wrong would it be to assert that they are not decent and trustworthy!.....</p>
   <p>If no respectable person could enter professional politics, or make it his chief vocation, then devilish wicked conditions would prevail in our republic. On the other hand, we suffer, because not enough people are interested in politics, and, as a result, public affairs are relegated into the hands of certain Irish professional politicians, where decency is often scarce.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1416.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many successful business men have not the courage and willingness to sacrifice themselves so as to be politically active.</p>
   <p>This is true in a special sense of the Germans. They always appear to have reasons for complaints against politicians, because they always furnish the smallest contingent.....</p>
   <p>To carry on politics as a profession is just as honorable and respectable as to publish a newspaper or to be a lawyer or judge..., it depends entirely on how it is done. If our professional politicians are not at present what they should be, it is not proper to debase and scorn politics for this reason, but we should strive so that the general respectability, the sound common sense, and the intelligence of the American people should find a more superior expression in our official representatives. Let us repeat or emphasize again: It is not as bad as most people try to make it appear.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
