<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-11-05">Nov. 5, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Gut Heil !</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0186</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0186.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-11-05">Nov. 5, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">GUT HEIL !</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention of the Turn District, Chicago, passed yesterday two very important resolutions: First, to make an attempt to induce the three Chicago Turner Clubs: Chicago Turngemeinde, South Side Turngemeinde, and Central Turner Club - which belong to the Turn District, Indiana, to re-enter the District "Chicago." Second, to send a section of District Turners to the great Turner festival at Frankfort on the Main in the summer of 1908.</p>
   <p>The discussions were taken up at 10 A.M. yesterday under the Chairmanship of Dr. Hartung and came late in the evening to a conclusion. Present were 81 delegates. Not represented were Turner Clubs, Hammond, and LaSalle, Illinois.</p>
   <p>The question, who shall be recommended to the Mayor as representative on the School Board, was submitted to the Local Board.</p>
   <p>Delegate Paul Pause of the Social Turner Club made the following motion: "The convocation shall ascertain what party does come closest to the principles of the Turner League in the coming elections, for instance, in the feminist-movement - and shall ask the members to support this party."</p>
   <p>Immediately the addition was recommended that Turner Pause himself make these investigations and report at the next convention. But the joke is, that the election <pb facs="5418474_4_0187.jpg" n="2"/>is held tomorrow, and the next convocation in spring.</p>
   <p>After a short discussion, the motion was laid on the table.</p>
   <p>Turner Dr. Backhusen mentioned that a new school on Belmont Ave. shall be named after the father of Turning, "Friedrich Ludwig Jahn" and that it may be proper that a bust of Jahn be offered to this school by the Chicago Turners. It was resolved to order the Local Board to find ways and means for the acquisition of such a bust, probably by making collections in the clubs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
