<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1924-10-30">Oct. 30, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The German House</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0739</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0739.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1924-10-30">Oct. 30, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN HOUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German house erected for the World's Fair, will not be wrecked. A large number of representatives of German-American societies, and well known German-Americans of the city, called on the South Park administration this morning and after a long discussion obtained this promise. Quite a while ago the administration decided to raze the building, which was greatly damaged in the course of years by rain and wind. To prevent this the following representatives of the Germans called this morning at the headquarters of the South Park administration: A. F. W. Siebel, president of the German Club, Otto F. Reich, O. H. Lange, Henry Stuckart, Gustave Gehrandt for the Steuben Society, Herman Wollenberger, Chas. Hoepfuer for the Citizens' Association, Max Teich, Karl Roessler, Paul F. P. Muller, the builder of the German house, Oscar Ruh, president of the Lincoln Club, John Traeger Arthur Woltersdorf, John Weccard, Ernest Kruetgen, Bernard De Vry and Professor Schevill of the Chicago University. Several speakers dwelt upon the matter. They all agreed that the German house, which was a gift of the German Government, should not be neglected as such. Besides, the artistic value of the building was pointed out and particularly Professor Schevill laid stress on <pb facs="5418474_4_0740.jpg" n="2"/>the fact that the building was of immense value as teaching material to the youth, because it was built according to historical style. Naturally the beauty of the building for the park, and the object of interest of such a pure, architectonic piece of art has been stressed upon. The park administration decided, after Michael Igoe, a member of the board warmly recommended it, not to raze the building at present, but asked that a committee consisting of five members should be appointed, which shall submit a proposition, for raising the necessary money for the renovation of the house. After that a committee with Ernest Kruetgen as president, and Bernard De Vry as secretary was formed which will propose that, the raising of the necessary funds be voted upon at the next election in the spring. Meanwhile a strong press campaign will be initiated, in order to show the city's population, the artistic value of the building, and thereby to persuade them to vote in favor of its restoration. Paul F. Mueller, who built the house that time, stated that two hundred thousand dollars were needed, but that the building would then be solid and fireproof. The erection of the building during the World's Fair, cost two and fifty thousand dollars or one million goldmarks. All material of artistic value was sent from Germany.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
