<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-11">July 11, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Benner's Dismissal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0889</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0889.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-11">July 11, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">BENNER'S DISMISSAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Expectations of a settlement of the Benner case, yesterday evening, did not materialize....The council, upon whose vote the issue depended, instead adjourned......</p>
   <p>In his message to the council, the mayor...stressed the need of economy, and showed that the city was "in the red" to the tune of $200,000, and correspondence between the mayor and Benner was also submitted to the council....</p>
   <p>Opinions of Alderman</p>
   <p>Aldermen Dixon and Lawler were quoted....they are not Germans....and both consider Benner's action in refusing to influence the firemen to accept a wage reduction fully justified, and regard the mayor's request that Benner ask for a voluntary wage reduction as exceeding his authority.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0890.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The fire department is, of course, very much displeased with Benner's dismissal. The fire companies have held several meetings during the last few days, resulting in naming a committee which submitted the following resolution to the mayor yesterday:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, After thorough consideration, we consider a reduction of salaries essential, and give our voluntary consent thereto, in conformance to the Honorable Mayor's statement, based on laws applicable to the subject; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, On a former occasion, we unintentionally showed improper conduct, in that we, of our own free will and accord, refused to accept wage reductions because we had already suffered considerable loss in accepting 'scrip'; be it therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we voluntarily agree to accept a five per cent wage <pb facs="5418474_4_0891.jpg" n="3"/>reduction, retroactive for the last six months of the fiscal year, and we hope that this unanimous consent of the fire department to the mayor's wishes will prompt his Honor to heed our sincere request that our highly esteemed chief, Matthias Benner, be reinstated as fire marshal; and we hereby assure you that the members of the fire department will thus be grateful.</p>
   <p>"Cornelius Casey,</p>
   <p>"James Lefauour,</p>
   <p>"John Fitzgerald,</p>
   <p>"Committee."</p>
   <p>The mayor gave no detailed reply, but said that he would consider the matter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
