<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1874-05-08">May 8, 1874</date>.
<title level="a">[Political Matters]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0629</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0629.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1874-05-08">May 8, 1874</date>.
<title level="a">[POLITICAL MATTERS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Evening Journal in almost polite article, tries to prove that the Illinois Staats-Zeitung is making a mistake by leaving the Republican party. The Journal thinks that, essentially, the party is still the same as the one for the principles of which the Staats-Zeitung formerly fought. The disputes concerning the temperance question and the inflation should have no influence. These are no party questions and the Republican party has never incorporated them in its program. It is true many Republicans favor temperance and inflation but not the Republican party as such. If that were the case the Journal itself, would leave the party and join hands with the Staats-Zeitung.</p>
   <p>We answer that the essence of a party are not the principles put down on paper, but the opinions and actions of the majority of its members. If the majority of the members completely ignores the principles of its party, nothing remains of the essence of this party.</p>
   <p>This is the case here. Of the English speaking Republicans, at least two thirds are champions of temperance and of inflation.</p>
   <p>The German Republicans belonged to the Republican party as long as the primitive <pb facs="5418474_4_0630.jpg" n="2"/>purpose for which it was formed had not been attained. Not only has slavery been abolished, but its abolition has been permanently confirmed by the re-election of President Grant. The only remaining lofty national purpose to be fulfilled by the Republican party was the security of the credit and of the honor of this country, but this purpose, also, has been forgotten by the majority of the English speaking Republicans.</p>
   <p>The Journal warns us that the Democratic party is still worse. But we have no intention whatsoever of joining the Democratic party. We wish to form a new and healthy party. When, and in what shape, this will be accomplished, we cannot tell as yet. Once this has been done we hope to be able to receive the Journal into the new party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
