<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-07">July 7, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Protest against Benner's Dismissal</title><title level="a" type="sub">Meeting at the North Side Turnhalle</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0896</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0896.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-07">July 7, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST AGAINST BENNER'S DISMISSAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Meeting at the North Side Turnhalle</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Turngemeinde called a mass meeting to protest against Fire Marshal Benner's dismissal. Considering the time and hot weather, the hall was crowded; one notes readily what indignation was aroused by the mayor's act, and, particularly, how the Germans react.</p>
   <p>Emil Hoechster, the first speaker, opened the meeting and explained its purpose. Julius J. Cohen made a motion that the meeting should not be restricted to the members, but be a general, public meeting.</p>
   <p>The motion was accepted; upon Hoechster's motion, Jacob Boser was made chairman.</p>
   <p>Wilhelm Kuecken was elected secretary. Then Frank Schweinfurth addressed the assembly. He said that the meeting was called in support of the dismissed fire marshal, Benner, the most capable public official the city has had in years. Although it is hoped, that the city council will attend to the affair, <pb facs="5418474_4_0897.jpg" n="2"/>in the opinion of Schweinfurth that was not enough! Marshal Benner's work in the fire department, and therefore, his efforts in behalf of the city, were of such an outstanding character, that the citizens should not be indifferent now, that the man was discharged. Everybody was satisfied. The insurance companies had the greatest confidence in him, as shown by the reduced rates. Benner did not acquire wealth while in office; he worked conscientiously; no ill-gotten gain can be ascribed to him; he is a poor man; his life's ambition was to make Chicago's fire department the best in the world; it is an outrage how the mayor treated such a deserving man.</p>
   <p>Adolph Mueller declared that he was glad that the Chicago Turngemeinde had called a mass meeting. He considered Benner's dismissal an insult to Chicago's Germans.</p>
   <p>Alderman Wetterer assured the assembly that, at most, only two or three members of the city council will vote for Benner's dismissal when the question of ratification arises. He, Wetterer, as member of the city's committee on water and fire, knows what Benner was worth to the city. Benner's dismissal <pb facs="5418474_4_0898.jpg" n="3"/>was a political move, and the citizens should not tolerate the fire department to become a part of the political machine as formerly. He gave assurances that the necessary twenty-four votes for Benner can be counted on.</p>
   <p>Joseph Kaufmann said that he does not believe that Benner's dismissal was an economic measure as far as the mayor was concerned. Kaufmann expressed the belief that the dismissal was based partly on personal reasons and it may also be attributable to the promises every candidate makes during the campaign period. Benner just became a victim of the Democratic office seekers and it is up to the council to see to it that the city does not lose one of its best officials. The speaker then referred to Benner's qualifications in a most eulogistic manner, and asserted that, for the sake of self-preservation, it becomes necessary to insist on Benner's reinstatement, so that the fire department may be maintained in its present high state of efficiency. Benner's refusal to comply with the mayor's request will only serve to heighten the esteem all impartial people have for him. If Harrison believes that it is his duty to economize in the fire department, then it is his duty to take the responsibility for such measures; he should not shift <pb facs="5418474_4_0899.jpg" n="4"/>the blame on the marshal. Finally, the speaker said that he hoped the mayor would realize just what is involved, and reinstate Marshal Benner.</p>
   <p>Julius Cohen expressed the opinion that a general mass meeting would be attended by at least ten thousand citizens. Chicago cannot dispense with a man like Benner. We need more public officials like him-men who came up from the ranks--men who enjoy the confidence of all citizens. That Benner happens to be a German is of no importance; Chicago's Germans would have favored Benner just as unanimously if he had been an Irishman. Benner's ability in his field, his honesty, his work in behalf of the city, is what the Germans regard so highly, and that is why the Germans want the man to continue in office. The citizens of Chicago should not be satisfied until Benner is reinstated. Julius Cohen then made a motion to nominate a committee to submit suitable resolutions at the next session of the city council.</p>
   <p>Frank Schweinfurth favored the nomination of a committee, but considered it inexpedient to formulate resolutions, because the council's intentions have not yet been disclosed. He amended the motion as follows: The committee <pb facs="5418474_4_0900.jpg" n="5"/>should be instructed to submit resolutions to the city council when it is considered advisable.</p>
   <p>Kaufmann advocated sending a committee to the mayor. The mayor discharged Benner, and, through the power of public opinion, the mayor should be compelled to reinstate Benner. Kaufmann then made a motion that a committee should be nominated to present resolutions to the mayor, and, if he ignores the request, then a mass meeting should be called to voice a protest.</p>
   <p>Alderman Wetterer said that the mayor will probably submit to the city council today the appointment of Swenie as fire marshal. It would, therefore, be a good idea if the city council were to be informed about the resolutions adopted at this meeting.</p>
   <p>Kuecken considered Kaufmann's motion to be more suitable. The matter has not yet been placed before the city council by the mayor, and, so long as the affair is still within the jurisdiction of Harrison, he is the person to see.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0901.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Philipp Koehler said that it is advisable to "strike while the iron is hot," and that the council should be informed of the prevailing public opinion.</p>
   <p>After further debate it was decided to adopt Julius Cohen's motion, to nominate a committee of five (sic), which should draft resolutions and present them to the mayor and council.</p>
   <p>The chairman then nominated for the committee the following gentlemen: Cohen, Malzahn, Koehler, Barblinger, Walter, Schweinfurth, and Hoechster who, after a short time, presented the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>"Considering that Carter H. Harrison, mayor of Chicago, Suddenly dismissed the city's fire marshal, Mathias Benner, and</p>
   <p>"Considering that the aforesaid official conducted his office in a manner meriting the confidence of the city's inhabitants, and</p>
   <p>"Considering that we, as property owners who carry insurance, are vitally <pb facs="5418474_4_0902.jpg" n="7"/>interested in an efficient fire department, and</p>
   <p>"Considering that we believe our possessions to be best protected by a fire department under the leadership of Mathias Benner, be it</p>
   <p>"Resolved, that we request the honorable mayor to reconsider the dismissal of Mathias Benner, and reinstate him. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, that a copy of this resolution be presented to the mayor and the city council.</p>
   <p>The Committee:</p>
   <p>E. Hoechster, J. J. Cohen, Philipp Koehler, D. Welter, L. Malzacher, F. Schweinfurth, Wilhelm Berblinger."</p>
   <p>The resolutions were accepted and the committee, to which were added Messrs. Jacob Boser, chairman of the meeting, and Jacob Heisler, was requested to <pb facs="5418474_4_0903.jpg" n="8"/>present the resolutions to the mayor and the council, and the committee was also authorized to call a mass meeting, if the mayor refuses to rescind his order, or if the council does not act favorably.</p>
   <p>The committee decided to see the mayor today, before noon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
