<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-10">Mar. 10, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The City Election (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1134</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1134.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-10">Mar. 10, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE CITY ELECTION (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The City election which is to be held next April, can be a quiet, unexciting affair, provided the English-speaking Republicans act wisely and refrain from introducing either the temperance question or Sunday laws.</p>
   <p>All our unbiased citizens--those persons who are interested only in the general welfare of the community--are satisfied with our City administration under the leadership of Mayor Health. The municipal management is as honest and as economical as possible, considering that every political department endeavors to please the voters of its precinct. Despite the damage done by the pork barrel philosophy of the State Supreme Court, and the latter's determined efforts to lead us to bankruptcy, Heath has managed to devise ways and means to lessen the effect of the evil and to maintain the credit of the municipality.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1135.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Every honest taxpayer will be well satisfied if our present city administration remains in office for another two years; for the prospect of improvement by means of a change in the administration is indeed "lousy", as Uncle Braesig would say. But "liberty", public prosperity", and the "glorious principle of local option" etc., require that others be given an opportunity to rule, or, to adopt the language of professional politicans, that others have a turn at the trough. And thus the public must choose, for better or for worse, from the staggering number of unselfish patriots who became candidates merely at the insistence of their friends.</p>
   <p>That, as we pointed out perviously, could be accomplished peacefully, if the fanatical water-thirsty brethren would cease wrangling and causing unwarranted scandals. Through present political methods the party strength has shifted, and the remote possibility of Ropublican adversaries gaining public office becomes a serious potentiality which it behooves the English-speaking <pb facs="5418474_4_1136.jpg" n="3"/>Republicans to prevent. We assume that a majority of the latter political faction are not anxious for a repetition of the controversy which raged in 1873; but if they submit to the bulldozing tactics of the few but active bigoted water-zealots, and select candidates in conformance with the dry doctrine, then Republicans can only blame themselves if they are classified according to the same manner as the fanatical drys.</p>
   <p>The great majority of our Chicago Germans are Republican in regard to national policies, and the minority is composed mainly of Socialists, not Democrats. But there is one point at which their party allegiance ceases, and that point is reached when the English-speaking Republicans become tools of that horde of hysterical temperance brawlers--idiots during their more rational moments--who propose to degrade Chicago by changing it from a cosmopolitan city into what is ostensibly a water-consuming community, but is actually, though secretly, a whiskey-drinking hamlet.</p>
   <p>Let the mass of our soft-talking benign-smiling, English-speaking Republicans remember that the Republicans who speak German are just as staunch and immovable <pb facs="5418474_4_1137.jpg" n="4"/>regarding their own views on prohibition and Sunday laws, as the American water-hypocrites profess to be.</p>
   <p>Our Republicans can choose; if they desire to affiliate themselves with the Prohibitionists, then they must dispense with the German Republican vote and be satisfied with the prospects! Let them seek solace in the delusion that the Germans can be assured by such sonfidential twaddle as, "So and so is a Prohibition advocate in public only; but he really is a very liberal-minded man". Formerly, when the Germans were more gullible, they were quite often deceived by such fraudulent assurances, but experience is an able teacher, and the Teutons have burnt their fingers once.</p>
   <p>Remember well: The Germans are not aggressors. They request no favors, and have no intention of converting the water puritans. They are fully aware of the infeasibility of the task. What the Germans demand is merely the continuance of the status-quo--that the present favorable city balance created by the administration be maintained in the future. And all who disregard this justified proposition will <pb facs="5418474_4_1138.jpg" n="5"/>be classified as opponents, irrespective of regular nominations, and this will prepare the way for as thorough a debacle of our present day Republicans as candidates of the party experienced in 1873.</p>
   <p>The temperance forces will enjoy witnessing the nomination of dry candidates, and the Germans will experience the intense satisfaction of defeating the office seekers at the election. This applies as much to administrative positions as to the City Council.</p>
   <p>The German Republicans of Chicago are not looking for an argument with the Drys, but if the latter insist on the issue, then the Germans will accept the proverbial gauntlet and demonstrate to the gentlemen of the waterwagon what a "real setting down" means.</p>
   <p>If, consequently, our City administration is to be wrested from the present party <pb facs="5418474_4_1139.jpg" n="6"/>(Republicans), then the responsibility rests solely with those braying fools who again injected the question of temperance and Sunday laws.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
