<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-05">Dec. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Public Privileges</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1314</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1314.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-05">Dec. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC PRIVILEGES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Years ago a Chicago alderman made the following remark concerning the value of public privileges and their transfer to private corporations: "Very seldom do communities realize the value of those privileges. Only after the capitalists have become millionaires by exploiting them, do the municipalities begin to see that the people have been robbed of a great revenue and have received services in turn, which they themselves could have performed cheaper and more efficiently; which indeed they should have done."</p>
   <p>During the last twenty years the people of Chicago have had the opportunity to test for themselves how well-founded this statement is. We just want to mention the Ogden Gas Company, which managed to obtain its license by promising lower gas rates in competition with the People's Gas, Light, &amp; Coke Company, but which, within a few years, consolidated with the latter, thus <pb facs="5418474_4_1315.jpg" n="2"/>re-establishing the obnoxious monopoly. Then we have the Illinois Telephone And Tunnel Company, which offered to supply automatic telephone service one-third cheaper than the existing telephone company, but which showed such little interest in this service that it finally came to a standstill. Now the company manages a very lucrative freight service on rails in a tunnel eight to twelve feet high, originally and presumably built for telephone wires. Finally there is the Street Car Company which, after consolidation of the North - West-, and South-side Lines, obtained a license which contained the most generous concessions, promising, in turn, to keep the carfare fixed at five cents for twenty miles. Now the company is asking for a fare of seven cents without giving up any of its privileges.</p>
   <p>As the Waechter and Anzeiger reports, the Public Utilities Commission of Ohio has granted the Illuminating Company of Cleveland a net profit of eight per cent, and the property value of the company was not estimated at the price originally paid by the company, but at a price which took the prevailing higher prices for material into consideration. Accordingly, <pb facs="5418474_4_1316.jpg" n="3"/>the net profit is considerably more than eight per cent.</p>
   <p>"What immense fortunes the municipalities in this country are practically giving away by granting privileges to public utilities," remarks the abovementioned paper, "can be seen from the fact that in the case quoted, Cleveland's loss amounted to not less than nineteen and one-half million dollars. If the Illuminating Company had been managed by the City of Cleveland, at a rate of profit of nine per cent, with compound interest, she would have become sole and debt-free owner of the establishment within fifteen years."</p>
   <p>The lesson which the above should prove for Chicago is obvious, and should make an even more lasting impression when the further fact is considered that the streetcar fare in Cleveland will be reduced to three cents in the near future. The streetcars there, by the way, belong to the city and the handsome profits which result for the city treasury, with low fares and union wages, make a powerful argument against the campaign with which the <pb facs="5418474_4_1317.jpg" n="4"/>press, biased aldermen, and street-car company lawyers try to fool Chicago's voters.</p>
   <p>The license under which the streetcars are operating here expires within eight years. Nearly every obligation which the company entered into twelve years ago, it has fulfilled only reluctantly, or in part, or not at all, as the company itself has admitted. Regarding the reasons for these breaches of contract, opinions differ, but the fact itself is indisputable. It sufficiently explains the recent rejection of the traction ordinance sponsored by Fisher, Capitain, and Busby, with its exaggerated valuation of the streetcars and elevated lines, its thirty-year license, its increase of fares and the extra charge of two cents for transfers. In return for this, just as a thousand and one times before, the patrons had been promised "better transportation". And this in view of an admission by the city's traffic commission, that the corresponding regulations in the present ordinance, which are almost identically the same, either could not be enforced at all or only after a long and cumbersome fight in the courts.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1318.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Now there is talk about a new ordinance, about a better deal with the streetcar lines, about a better understanding of the public, etc. What a waste of effort! Chicago has learned that there is only one way to get rid of political machinations, of the State Utility Commission, of the country hicks in the Legislature and the aldermanic sceneshifters of the traction companies, namely, to let the city itself operate the streetcars. This is not only a probability within eight years, but, under the present ordinance, a certainty, provided the so-called traction fund is not diverted and is kept intact for its original purpose, the purchase of the street-car lines. Whether the city is to take over the management, too, may then be decided by the citizens. To those who fear that political influence could harm the service, let it be pointed out that the streetcar employees are united in one of the strongest unions and are not only capable but will be glad, at any time, to rap the knuckles of greedy political chiselers. The services which the streetcar companies are performing at the present time can hardly get any worse and, in the knowledge that their arrogant domination will come to an end as the present ordinance expires, the "straphangers" can say with the well-known <pb facs="5418474_4_1319.jpg" n="6"/>character in the "Beggar Student":</p>
   <p>"Go ahead, streetcar, show what you can do,</p>
   <p>Let's see who's stronger, I or you."</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The last quotation is just a facetious version of a line from some play].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
