<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-20">Mar. 20, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Our Rulers. Germans Have Twice as Many Votes Than the Sons of Ireland.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0790</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0790.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-20">Mar. 20, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">OUR RULERS. GERMANS HAVE TWICE AS MANY VOTES THAN THE SONS OF IRELAND.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some days ago the following question was put to us by a naive German: "Is the Democratic ticket, which will be presented to the voters on April 4th, the ballot of the Democrats of Chicago, the metropolis of the West of America? Or is it the ballot of the Irish in Dublin, the capital of Ireland.</p>
   <p>This question is not entirely out of place, because if the ballot is examined, we find no end to the Ryans, O'Briens, Murphys, and similar names. We may spontaneously ask the same question.</p>
   <p>Never before have our rulers, the men from the Emerald Isle, made us realize their domination as much as just now. And this happens only a short time <pb facs="5418474_4_0791.jpg" n="2"/>after German votes elected them to power in county and state! Never before have our rulers, the men from Ireland, acted so rudely, so that every sense of justice and decency, and even the faintest sign of modesty is absent. In spite of it, they expect very definitely that on April 4th, they will become the rulers of the city also.</p>
   <p>Nothing is more reprehensible and contemptible as race hatred and prejudice! Nothing is more foreign to Germans, demanding tolerance for themselves, than to fight another race, which is a part of the American commonwealth: But it is an entirely different matter, if these Germans, and other nationalities which feel as they do, rebel against another nationality, whose pushing forward in American public life is entirely too impertinent. This particular nationality has pushed its worst men to the front in public affairs, and as a consequence, very many of the other citizens are disgusted.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0792.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Some time ago the German-American Democratic Central Union, and all its branch organizations, protested against the attempts of a single nationality to monopolize all the public offices. To this protest our so-called rulers replied by overloading the ticket, which is already 75 per cent Irish, and which will be given to the voters on April 4th, with more Irishmen.</p>
   <p>And if these men of Irish descent at least were men whom every citizen could respect, and to whom all could look up to with confidence, it would be different.</p>
   <p>But alas: Who are they? Tim Ryan, Mike McInerney, Jimmie Crawford, "Black Hill" Fitzgerald, Mike O'Brien, Mike Ryan, Pat Wall, Billy O'Brien, John McGillen, Mike Bransfield - these are some of the principal candidates and chief representatives of that impertinent element, and, unfortunately, of the Democratic Party of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0793.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The following official statistics, arranged according to wards and nationalities, shows the number of votes cast by Chicago citizens at the recent presidential election. (The following statistics is abbreviated, giving totals only, while the original is covering each ward separately, and otherwise giving full details - translator).</p>
   <p>Registered Voters at the Election, Nov. 8, 1892.</p>
   <p>American-born citizens - all wards - total.............131,335 Naturalized citizens - all wards and all different nationalities total...128,212.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0794.jpg" n="5"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Total</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Naturalized</cell>
     <cell>citizens</cell>
     <cell>- Canadians</cell>
     <cell>all wards -</cell>
     <cell>........</cell>
     <cell>6,693</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Germans</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>.........</cell>
     <cell>45,005</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Irish</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>23578</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>English</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>7,844</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Scots</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>2,555</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Swedes</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>10,838</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Norwegians</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>4,832</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Danes</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>2,333</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>French</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>643</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Bohemians</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>5,721</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Poles</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>4,865</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Austrians</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>3,280</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Russians</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>2,903</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Italians</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>1,032</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Dutch</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>1,600</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>All other nationalities all wards</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>1,933</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Grand total of registered voters in Chicago</cell>
     <cell>...............</cell>
     <cell>259,547</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0795.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The study of these statistics is interesting as well as instructive. It establishes by numbers - which can not lie - a comparison between the Germans and the Irish voters, and it evidences the fact that the Germans in Chicago have twice as many votes as the Irish.</p>
   <p>Let us more closely examine the statistics. First of all we find that there are only 3,000 less naturalized citizens in Chicago than native citizens. If we add to the 128,212 naturalized citizens all of those German-Americans and Irish-Americans who, although born here, still remain loyal to the principles of their forefathers, we have a total of 180,000 foreign-born voters against 7,000 natives. These are bona fide citizens, who really vote.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0796.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>According to the above statement, the Germans cast 45,005 votes last fall. If we add to this number the Austrians (3,280), the Swiss and Luxemburgians, we arrive at a total of 50,000 foreign-born voters of German origin. This alone is one-fifth of the total vote. And adding to this number the Germans born in this country, who are, most frequently, the best German-Americans, we may rightfully claim one-fourth of the total votes.</p>
   <p>And they want to deny to this powerful group the right to have something to say regarding certain subjects to be taught in the public schools!</p>
   <p>The total number of votes of the Irish, Swedes, Norwegians, Danes, Bohemians, and Poles does not exceed the German votes alone, and yet , the Swedes and Bohemians tell the school board that their language has as much right to be taught in the public schools as the German. <pb facs="5418474_4_0797.jpg" n="8"/>Statistics show what power we have in public life, if we only understand how to make use of it.</p>
   <p>If we examine the wards and pick out those which have over 1,000 voters from any nationality, we find that the 5th, 6th, 7th, 9th, 10th, 14th, 15th, 16th, 20th, 21st, 22nd, 25th, 30th and 33rd are predominantly German. There are only three wards, namely the 19th, 23rd, and 29th, where the Irish exceed the German votes, and only in three more wards, the Irish have over 1,000 votes. The Poles have in only one ward more votes than the Germans, and that is in the 16th ward. However, their excess is not as large as is usually believed, because they have only 200 more votes than the Germans. The Bohemians are stronger in the 8th ward, and the Swedes in the 23rd ward. Nothing demonstrates more definitely the impertinent behavior of the Irish than the above given statistics.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0798.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>There is the 5th ward, dominated by D. Corkery, Mike Branefield, Pat Wall, and Jim Daly. They did not permit the Germans to vote at the primary election, abused them and boasted of their power. And yet there were 1,859 German voters as against 1,166 Irish. The 5th ward is a German ward, and the German should not tolerate Irish domination.</p>
   <p>There is the 6th ward, always considered by Billy O'Brien, the notorious alderman, as the exclusive property of his Irish "boys." Billy Joyce, Billy O'Brien, and others should study the official statistics, which give the Germans 2,371 votes, and the Irish 2,298 only. The desire of the Germans in that ward to be represented on the town ticket should have been heeded. However, Billy O'Brien ignored Geo. Thurn, and that was sufficient.</p>
   <p>The 7th ward has 1,542 German voters against 623 Irish. But if the Germans in that ward make a move, the Irish clique suppresses it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0799.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Ed. Cullerton, Bat. Baldwin rule the 9th ward, although the Irish have only 762 votes against 1,639 German votes.</p>
   <p>The worst situation prevails in the 10th ward. Jack Cullerton, "Chick" Curran, and other Irishmen dominate here, and the 2,385 German voters must be subservient to 839 Irishmen.</p>
   <p>The strongest German ward in Chicago is the 14th ward, which has 3,676 German votes, and only 211 Irish, but at times of election, 175 of the 211 Irish voters become political candidates.</p>
   <p>God have mercy on the 15th ward: The candidates for alderman are Pat Money and Mike Ryan. The latter is the "boss" of the ward by the grace of Carter Harrison. Ryan is one of the 575 Irishmen to whom 3,054 Germans are submissive.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0800.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>Poles and Irishmen rule the 16th ward..., although there are 2,450 Germans, 2,631 Poles and only 218 Irish in the ward.</p>
   <p>The 18th ward is in the power of John Gaynor, John Brennan, Bill Mahoney, and Steve Griffin, because they have 50 votes more than the Germans, i. e., 738 and 674, respectively.</p>
   <p>There are only 9,393 Irish, 3,906 Bohemians, 3,500 Poles in the whole West Town. Together they have not as many votes as the Germans, who have a total of 19,737. Yet the Germans are expected to vote for a Democratic town ticket, where not a single German is listed, but three Irishmen and one Bohemian instead.</p>
   <p>And now we come to North Town, the undisputed "kingdom" of Chase, O'Mally, Donovan, John McGillen, and Captain Farrell. What an absurdity 7,468 German voters bow to 2,236 Irishmen!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0801.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>The 20th ward, the "property" of Colonel Harry Donovan, by the grace of Altgeld, has 217 Irish voters and 2,111 German voters. However, the rulers of the 20th ward are Irish, and there is no doubt about it.</p>
   <p>John McGillen of the 21st ward rules with his 182 Irish, the 2,445 Germans, and each one of the 182 Irish is a politician or a candidate.</p>
   <p>"Boss" Farrell of the 22nd ward has only 210 Irishmen against 2,577 Germans, but Farrell and the other 209 Irish dominate the ward.</p>
   <p>Lakeview alone has kept itself free from the domination of the "ruling race." Nowhere else in Chicago are politics more decent than in the beautiful suburb. There is the 25th ward with 1,291 Germans and 231 Irish, and the 26th ward, the second strongest German ward, with 3,370 German and 199 Irish voters.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0802.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>Town of Lake is next. Mike McInerney, Tom Gaham, Tom Byrne rule here without interference. The Irish have 4,162 in the three wards comprising Town of Lake, and the Germans have 3,856 votes, but the latter have nothing whatever to say.</p>
   <p>In South Chicago, the 33rd ward is the last of the predominantly German ward. Here the Germans attend to the voting, and the Irish take care of politics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
