<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-15">Feb. 15, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A Moratorium in Prospect (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0390</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0390.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-15">Feb. 15, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A MORATORIUM IN PROSPECT (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A bill which is of the utmost importance to many homeowners is before the General Assembly in Springfield. This bill provides for a moratorium on mortgages. It ordains that action shall be postponed until after December 31, 1935 in all cases in which foreclosure proceedings have been filed but have not yet been decided. It applies also to all requests for foreclosure that will be made prior to that date. In other words, the bill is intended to grant homeowners who are in danger of losing their property a moratorium of nearly two years.</p>
   <p>The homeowners against whose property foreclosure proceedings have been started are to request postponment within thirty days after the law becomes effective. The bill is in harmony with the aims of the Home Owners' <pb facs="5418474_4_0391.jpg" n="2"/>Loan Corporation, but it goes farther. The H.O.L.C. endeavors to save the home of a homeowner while the provisions of the moratorium bill apply to all owners of houses. Again, the H.O.L.C. can act only if both parties, the homeowner and the owner of the mortgage, declare that they agree with the conditions of the H.O.L.C. If the holder of the mortgage refuses to extend or renew the mortgage under the conditions specified by the H.O.L.C., he is at liberty to file foreclosure proceedings in court.</p>
   <p>Thus the bill supplies two important deficiencies of the present legal measures intended to protect homeowners. No doubt, the enactment of the bill will work certain hardships on many mortgage owners. However, it should be passed, not only in the interest of homeowners, but also in the interest of a sound and stable real-estate market.</p>
   <p>Before the great crash speculators increased the prices of lots and houses, and consequently rents reached exorbitant heights. However, the process <pb facs="5418474_4_0392.jpg" n="3"/>of deflation has reached its final stage. Real-estate prices have sunken into fathomless depths, and the market is so demoralized that it is hardly possible to sell a building at any price. Forced sales have contributed greatly to this sad state of affairs. The whole real-estate market, not only homeowners, but also mortgage holders, would benefit if the process of deflation were brought to a close now. A two-year moratorium will serve to stabilize the real-estate market and will, in the final analysis, redound to the benefit of mortgage holders, for if the process of deflation is not halted, the value of many houses will fall below the face value of the mortgages and the mortgage holders will have to suffer the losses.</p>
   <p>Interested persons and firms are doing all they can to induce the Assembly to pass the bill and reports from Springfield indicate that prospects for its passage are favorable. In his message to the Assembly, Governor Horner also recommends that the bill be enacted. An open hearing on the bill will be held in Springfield on February 20, and parties interested will then have the opportunity to voice their opinions on the proposal before the members of the Assembly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
