<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1876-12-03">Dec. 3, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">The Mayor and the Police Superintendency</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0923</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0923.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1876-12-03">Dec. 3, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAYOR AND THE POLICE SUPERINTENDENCY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is well known that Mr. Elmer Washburn, whose character is too well known to require comment, is most warmly urged by a large number of our best citizens for the office of police Superintendent, and should a vacancy occur, the Mayor would in all probability have to yeald to the pressure brought to bear on him in favor of the former. But people who claim to be well informed insist that Mr. Washburns' enforcement of the Sunday ordinance a few years ago, in strict obedience to the orders of his superior officer, has, in the opinion of the Mayor, made him so unpopular with a certain class of our people that his appointment would impair his own (the Mayor's) popularity. Men who are in daily converse with Mr. Heath assure us that they have it from his own lips that he is afraid that his standing among the German's in this city may be injured should he appoint Washburn.---</p>
   <p>Now, I wish to say that, if Mr. Heath is prompted in his action by such apprehensions as these, he not only labors under a very serious mistake, but offers a base insult to the Germans. It is true that they made war on the obnoxicus Sunday ordinance, but they know enough to discriminate between an oppressive law and an officer whose sworn duty it is to execute the same. They know that Mr. Washburn simply obeyed the order of his superior, the <pb facs="5418474_4_0924.jpg" n="2"/>Mayor of the city, no more and no less than any of the numerous police officers of German birth did, who, has they not obeyed the same, would have been removed. The Germans, having come from a country which prides herself in having a truly model civil service are in favor of civil service reform here, and if any one principle of public policy is more firmly rooted in their minds than all others, it is, that every officer of the law must set the first example of strict obedience to the law, and that an officer who fails herein is simply a perjured villain. If Mr. Heath cares to know the true sentiment of the Germans in this city and their opinion about Mr. Washburn, I advise him to go among the quiet, law-abiding business-men of German birth who abound in our midst and to make proper inquiries of them, but not to take the impression of the lawless spirit of a few German saloon-keepers as a fair representation of the views held by the bulk of the Germans.</p>
   <p>There are in this city four daily German papers, he of which, the Illinois Staats-Zeitung, the most influential of all, has in several articles warmly recommended Mr. Washburn for his integrety and efficiency, another, <pb facs="5418474_4_0925.jpg" n="3"/>the Freie Presse, may also be said to be favorable to him, since it has, on former occasions, spoken of him in terms of the highest praise, and the other two papers do not oppose him, unless it has escaped my attention. Nine-tenthes of the order-loving German people in this city would be exceedingly gratified to see our police force placed under the efficient hand of Mr. Washburn, and if Mr. Heath, having been elected last spring with the aid of the reform element in our city, now fancies that, in order to secure a re-election next year, he has to cater to the influence of a handful of German saloon-keepers by retaining Hickey against the protest of our best citizens, he will find that he has seated himself "between two stools, you know."</p>
   <p>German-American</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
