<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title>, (Illinois Staats Zeitung, Sun. Ed.)
<date when="1893-07-23">July 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Judicial Election.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0529</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0529.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title>, (Illinois Staats Zeitung, Sun. Ed.)
<date when="1893-07-23">July 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE JUDICIAL ELECTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The anticipation of a serene and unexciting autumnal election seems to be unwarranted. Ten judges will be elected, as provided by the legislature... And now Cook County is overrun by a horde of shysters, especially of the Democratic variety. Any swineherd, provided that he has illegitimate influence or professes allegiance to the green flag, feels qualified to be a judicial candidate. The Boyles, the Bradys, the Robinsons are all candidates once more.</p>
   <p>The Bar Association recognized this peril to our judiciary. Our tribunals are already an Irish institution but still worse is the fact that ward politicians, who at best held sway in the police courts, now wield the scepter over life and death, property and possessions. The Bar Association therefore nominated 20 lawyers; two of them, Buty and Vocke, are very capable German attorneys.</p>
   <p>Every member of the Association has the right to nominate 10, i. e, five Republicans and five Democrats. Those which club elects, will be the 10 official candidates. The Republicans are:..... Otto Butz, (elsewhere the name is printed Buty, but Butz is probably correct, as the letter y practically never appears as an "end" letter in a German name. Translator.) and <pb facs="5418474_4_0530.jpg" n="2"/>William Bocke, the two Germans.... ten names are listed.</p>
   <p>The Democrats: .... only Irish and English names appear .... ten are given.</p>
   <p>It is not likely that the Democrats will revert to the former "non-partisan practice" whereby each party was given half a share, which virtually made elections superfluous. Even the Republicans do not favor it as they believe that their ticket, headed by Judge Gary, will sway the masses in their favor.</p>
   <p>It is a good slap for Altgeld and the Democrats may be beaten through that scheme. They are not aware, evidently, that they are treading on dangerous ground. Attempts to arouse prejudice have seldom benefited any aggresive alarmist in a Chicago election.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
