<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-09-19">Sept. 19, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">German-American Liberty League Solicits Support for J. Hamilton Lewis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-09-19">Sept. 19, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN LIBERTY LEAGUE SOLICITS SUPPORT FOR J. HAMILTON LEWIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-American Liberty League, which was organized only last week, and of which leading German-Americans of Chicago have become members, can already look back to the successful results of their solicitation, because in the course of the last few days, a number of German societies and clubs with their entire membership have again joined the League.</p>
   <p>Several hundred thousand solicitation cards are today in the hands of German-Americans, requesting them to join the League; the cards contain the following: "Whenever the most vital interests of the country were at stake, the Americans of German extraction took up a position to prevent many unfortunate happenings. Again it is our duty as citizens of this country, to prevent the oppression of our freedom as citizens, to prevent a further plundering of our Constitutional rights as citizens, and to preserve the liberty and welfare of our people. To reach this goal, the League has indorsed a candidate for United States Senator of Illinois, who is a champion of our principles, and who has obligated <pb facs="5418474_4_0105.jpg" n="2"/>himself to do this also in the future. This candidate is James Hamilton Lewis. Therefore come and join us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
