<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-16">Jan. 16, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Moral Foolishness</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1342</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1342.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-16">Jan. 16, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">MORAL FOOLISHNESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago never has had a more miserable administration than the present one. Not a single branch is healthy; the Board of Education, the Water Department, Building Inspection, Police, everything is rotten. Did we ever have such intense political interference in school affairs as under this Mayor?</p>
   <p>Some months ago an explosion on an upper floor of a building on Dearborn near Washington Street, snuffed out several lives and a large number of women and girls were endangered because all exists were cut off and no fire-escapes existed. At the time we heard considerable rumbling at the City Hall. It subsided after a few days. The building inspectors were censured severely and admonished to insist that all property owners provide the necessary safety equipment, as specified by law.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1343.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then drowsiness asserted itself again, and everything slumbered peacefully until a rude awakening presented the terrible catastrophe anew. The Vorwaerts Turnhall members showed and proved the malfeasance of our officials.</p>
   <p>Mayor Harrison knows his register of sins is brimful; he is aware that his popularity is waning even among those he could deceive by various demagogical, adroit, and brilliant artifices. They are deserting the fold.</p>
   <p>At this juncture, the crusade of the "moralists" appeared as a most opportune specter; Harrison can now display his might, akin to Pilatus, and wash his hands in innocence while exclaiming, if that is possible under my "liberal" administration, what can you expect from the Republicans, who are infinitely more susceptible to the prohibition forces, the Presbyterian and Methodistic views, than the Democrats led by Harrison?"</p>
   <p>That holy war against the saloon-keepers who fail to close at the midnight hour, and the disreputable taverns which certain Republicans started and <pb facs="5418474_4_1344.jpg" n="3"/>somehow manage to continue, might, after all, develop into a good cause if these warriors would learn to differentiate a little. Most of these beerpalace owners, probably ninety-nine out of a hundred, would be only too glad if they are compelled to close their portals at twelve o'clock, because whatever the Skatbrothers [Skat, a German card game, played by four persons, Trans.] and other bar flies consume after midnight, does not pay for the light. The majority of the small saloon-keepers function as bartenders; they have no help and must be near the faucet again early in the morning.</p>
   <p>Other conditions prevail in places which are frequented by type-setters, printers, newspaper carriers, etc. They find a saloon a necessity. Here they may rest. Heat is available during inclement, frigid weather, and rain-soaked clothing can be dried. But these havens of refuge were also closed by Harrison's order, because "all must be treated alike."</p>
   <p>It is a combination of maliciousness and stupidity; but he will capitalize on it by creating dissatisfaction in the city, and that is an asset during the next <pb facs="5418474_4_1345.jpg" n="4"/>mayoralty campaign.</p>
   <p>When the time approaches, Harrison will go to every saloon and hall, make liberal promises, and incidentally depict the Republicans as the creatures who made him a party to the closing campaign, which should be a warning not to vote for any Republican; otherwise they jump from the frying pan into the fire.</p>
   <p>Now, if the Republicans happen to be so asinine as to select a mayoral candidate who has dry tendencies, then Harrison's election is as natural as sunshine after rain.</p>
   <p>The Republican Party can only win if their prospective mayor is known as a good businessman with a liberal attitude. Chicago is a cosmopolitan city and the 10,000 strangers who visit us daily intend to be amused, and they have no inclination to tolerate any disturbance in their pursuits, neither by crooks who relieve them of their money nor by a cudgelwielding police <pb facs="5418474_4_1346.jpg" n="5"/>heralding the midnight hour and insisting that the citizens march to bed.</p>
   <p>It would be lamentable if the present wave of moral nonsense should prolong the Harrisonian city administration for another two years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
