<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-07-07">July 7th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">"The Truth Deserves Honor"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0782</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0782.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-07-07">July 7th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">"The Truth Deserves Honor"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mayor Harrison had to make seven nominations for the School board. He proposed the re-election of four former members and sent in only three new names. What the attitude of the completed school board to the so-called fads and especially to German instruction will be, cannot be foretold with complete certainty. As, however, the native papers applaud the mayor," the other side" is imagining that his nominations will at least be not beneficial to the cause of comtemporary and progressive education.</p>
   <p>Therefore the good Carter is called faithless and dishonorable by those German friends whom he won in the last election. It is thrown up to him, that he deceived the Germans without whose aid he could not have been re-elected; finally he is threatened that this not even six months old friendship may turn already into enmity.</p>
   <p>Now so far the "Abendpost" had no reason, to take back a single word of what it said about Carter Henry Harrison, during the last election; on the contraty, this newly elected "best man" acted at several public occasions in a way, that is not proper for the head of the World's Fair City under any circumstances. And what was <pb facs="5418474_4_0783.jpg" n="2"/>laudable under his administration so far, cannot be put to his personal credit, but only to the credit of Corporation Attorney Kraus. But the Abendpost cannot see that this egotistic old gentleman committed also an act of faithlessness towards "the Germans". etc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
