<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-08">June 8, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Sweitzer's Dismissal</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-08">June 8, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">SWEITZER'S DISMISSAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The removal of Robert M. Sweitzer from the position of county treasurer has given rise to all kinds of wild rumors. The public is apparently not inclined to accept the reasons for his dismissal given by the county board. It can hardly be denied that the county board acted in accordance with the letter of the law. It removed a man from an elective county office because he had been guilty of irregularities in a previous office. This does not imply that Sweitzer did not administer his office as county treasurer in a manner beyond suspicion; but the county board seems to have taken the view that Sweitzer, because of the irregularities he committed as county clerk, is disqualified for any public office.</p>
   <p>The county board turned to the state's authority for a decision. According to the latter, the county board had the right to depose Sweitzer. But the <pb facs="5418474_4_1213.jpg" n="2"/>public thinks that many other things are behind the affair than are seen on the surface. Actions of this kind are, as a rule, blamed on political wars within the party, and a similar suspicion was heard in the Sweitzer case. But it stands upon weak ground.</p>
   <p>First of all, Sweitzer's successor in the office as county clerk, Michael Flynn, was responsible for the funds. If he had not uncovered the deficit, he would have been blamed for the deficit himself, and no one would expect that of him. It has been argued that he should have been a little more considerate, and given Sweitzer a little more time. Whether this is justified remains to be seen. Second, it is not customary in politics for a group of politicians to get rid of a fellow politician in such a manner. There certainly are many politicians who would gladly strangle a fellow party man. But before the public they appear as friends and brothers, in the interest of the party.</p>
   <p>When all is said and done, the Sweitzer affair has become quite a scandal. <pb facs="5418474_4_1214.jpg" n="3"/>The large masses of the voters know only that a large sum of money is missing, and this circumstance is going to cost the party many votes at the next election. Yet it is possible that, in the action of the county board, there were motives at work that are still unknown to the public. The public will, perhaps, soon find out what happened behind the scenes, for it seems that Sweitzer is not willing to accept his removal without a struggle. The moment he decides to relieve his feelings, the whole truth will come to light.</p>
   <p>It cannot be denied that similar irregularities have frequently occurred in political offices, above all in our good city of Chicago. But, in the majority of instances, the culprits were clever enough not to be caught. According to the figures of the county board, there are more than four hundred thousand dollars missing from the funds. That is a large sum of money. What became of the money? It is known that Sweitzer was very trusting and generous. The public has a right to expect that the affair will be fully and wholy clarified, for it was said that Sweitzer helped many a party man with campaign contributions. These things must come out, if need be, through a court trial,</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
