<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-04">Oct. 4, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[Political Matters]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0049</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0049.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-04">Oct. 4, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[POLITICAL MATTERS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German citizens of the western part of the 16th ward, the so-called Bavarian settlement, yesterday had their first meeting at 775 N. Halsted street, in order to consult and come to an agreement on who would be the best man to represent the common interests of this large and in part still "original" district of Chicago. The hall was filled to its capacity; about 100 prominent, long-time citizens, mostly German, discussed animatedly the selection of candidates.</p>
   <p>Mr. Carl Haussner was elected permanent chairman, and Mr. George Menzel, secretary - both by acclamation. Mr. Snyder gave the main address. He proved that no city district was so neglected by the City Council from beginning on as the Bavarian settlement. This German district counts for nothing in the eyes of the honorable aldermen. The numerous population has to pay more than its share into the city treasury without getting anything in return. Because it is a German district, nobody had thought to connect it with the city sewers or the gas and water pipes. Never since the district was settled has an alderman come from there. They hail without exception from the aristocratic eastern part of the 16th ward; and so it has come about that in the east everything has been fixed up and the value of real estate has been multiplied. <pb facs="5418474_4_0050.jpg" n="2"/>While the western, German part, in many ways seem only a village, even though the people must pay the high city taxes.</p>
   <p>These conditions have engendered the determination to nominate this time a man from the Bavarian settlement as alderman; in the place of Tyler, Mr. B. Miller was recommended, and accepted the nomination. To report on other suitable candidates for alderman a committee of five was nominated, consisting of Messrs. Peter Regitz, Mathias Mathis, Edward Schmeisser, H. Russer, and J. H. Snyder.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
