<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-06-20">June 20, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">End of Whiskey Trial Close at Hand.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_1530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_1530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-06-20">June 20, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">END OF WHISKEY TRIAL CLOSE AT HAND.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before asking clemency from your honor for my client, A. C. Hesing, I wish to submit to the court several sworn statements.</p>
   <p>C. F. Pietsch says under oath, that he has been secretary of the Illinois Staats Zeitung since 1867. He has been an intimate friend of A. C. Hesing and was well acquainted with his personal affairs. He has kept the books for him and knows all his financial transactions since 1868. At the time of the big fire in 1871 Hesing owned five-eighths of all the shares of the Illinois Staats Zeitung, which shares brought him annually twenty percent interest. At that time he also owned half of the shares of the "Garden City Manufacturing Company" which brought in 1871 a profit of $65,000. Hesing also owned at that period some real estate worth about $25,000. Hesing had thus at that time a fortune of $250,000, free from debts. He lost a great deal of his fortune through the fire and through the bankruptcy of the Garden City Manufacturing Co., the obligations of which he took over. When he also lost the land on which the Simon-Powell was located, he was left completely penniless.</p>
   <p>Herman Raster says under oath, that he has been editor-in-chief of the <pb facs="5418474_4_1531.jpg" n="2"/>Illinois Staats Zeitung since 1867. He says that when the office of federal tax collector was offered to A. C. Hesing, the latter refused to accept the position but used his influence to have Edmund Jussen appointed. When E. Jussen had to resign, the position was offered once more to A. C. Hesing but he again declined to accept it.</p>
   <p>When the undersigned, H. Raster, was appointed district collector, although he was an intimate friend of A. C. Hesing, the latter never tried to influence him in favor of a distiller or in the appointment of storekeepers. That he, Raster, is acquainted with Jacob Rehm and that due to the latter he appointed S. A. Irwin as his chief deputy. That on different occasions Rehm tried to influence him in the appointment of subalterns and storekeepers.</p>
   <p>E. Jussen says that he was federal tax collector from May 1st, 1869, until May 1st, 1871. That while he was in New York for medical treatment, A. C. Hesing using his influence, had the position offered to him without his asking first. That while he was federal collector, he never was influenced by A. C. Hesing in his official activities, that he was never was asked by him to appoint storekeepers in the district. That while A. C. Hesing was at that time connected with the Keller distillery, he never asked for any favors for this distillery, That Hesing never attempted to induce him to act <pb facs="5418474_4_1532.jpg" n="3"/>dishonestly.</p>
   <p>That Jacob Rehm came to see him Feb. 21, 1871, and tried to give orders to him, E. Jussen, then federal tax collector, concerning the appointment of storekeepers. That E. Jussen refused to accept any orders and that he wrote at that time to Chas. B. Farwell about it, who then was a member of congress. Here is the letter:</p>
   <p>"Dear Mr. Farwell,</p>
   <p>"Your friend Jac. Rehm came to see me and criticized me on account of the appointments of my subordinates. I took it for granted that he was acting on his own, but his whole behavior indicated that he relied on a secret power. I wish to say that I am indifferent to his criticisms and that I shall take no orders from him.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>E. Jussen, Tax Collector."</p>
   <p>I never received any answer. But J. Rehm went suddenly to Washington and <pb facs="5418474_4_1533.jpg" n="4"/>shortly thereafter I was relieved of my office.</p>
   <p>Now, I wish to ask your Honor to try the defendant merely as a distiller and not as the master mind of the conspiracy. Hesing's political enemies may misrepresent the facts but they cannot alter the truth. Who was it, who wanted to use me as a tool when I was tax collector? I only mention that, to prove that Hesing was not the ringleader.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
