<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1876-06-16">June 16, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">The German Republicans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0613</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0613.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1876-06-16">June 16, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN REPUBLICANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention of German Republicans which assembled at Cincinnati, and at which twenty states were represented, draws conspicuous attention to the return to the Republican party of the majority of the Germans, who temporarily abandoned it in several states two years ago on account of local issues, involving principally temperance measures and the observance of Sunday. This return is of most vital importance to the Republican party, and the most hopeful element for its success in the approaching presidential campaign. It was natural that the Germans as a class should turn back to republicanism in a national contest, in spite of local disapproval.</p>
   <p>Even so eloquent and powerful a leader as Carl Schurz could not lead them away from the party in the national campaign four years ago, though the result of the last Ohio election showed that he could bring them back to it after they had once gone. There is no doubt that the new German allegiance to the party, indicated by the Cincinnati convention and in various other ways, is based on the belief that the Republican party is essentially progressive and reformatory; and this faith has been restored largely by the efforts of Secretary Bristow in the prosecuting of whisky thieves and purifying of public service. Though two or three Germans have been implicated in the Chicago <pb facs="5418474_4_0614.jpg" n="2"/>whisky frauds, they have nowhere received more general and outspoken condemnation than among the German people. The Germans, as a class, abhor all kinds of official peculation and jobbery, and the labors of Secretary Bristow have nowhere found greater appreciation than from them.</p>
   <p>A continued confidence on their part, that the spirit of these reforms will govern the next administration, will restore to the Republican party 99 100 of all the German votes that were lost to it two years ago in several of the states; and this German vote would be almost enough to assure victory. The Republican party is the most natural and congenial political refuge for the Germans in America, and they are in full sympathy with the political and religious freedom which the party represents.</p>
   <p>The platform adopted by the Germans in Cincinnati would not have been a bad one for the National Republican Convention, though containing some points of more particular concern to the Germans than to any other class of voters. It declared the supremacy of the nation and the subordination of the state government. It demanded the maintenance of every amendment to the Constitution made by the Republican party, and particularly the enforcement of the laws for the protection of all classes in the South.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0615.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It called for a civil service based on moral character and capacity, and not solely on political service. It set forth an emphatic opposition to all the heresies of inflation and repudiation. and maintained that there shall be no step backward on the road to resumption.</p>
   <p>It favored non-sectarian schools and compulsory education, which are among the more advanced ideas of the Republican party, and denounced every support of sectarian worship by the state or general government. All this is sound Republican doctrine.</p>
   <p>So far as the special demands of the Cincinnati German Convention are concerned, they are worthy of, and will undoubtedly receive the serious attention and active aid of the Republican party. One is, that the general government shall pass proper legislation for the protection of emigrants, since the Supreme Court has decided that such legislation is not within the province of the states; and the other is, that the existing treaties be revised with a view to secure a foreign recognition of more liberal rights under our naturalization laws.</p>
   <p>These demands are reasonable and in themselves entirely proper, and there is <pb facs="5418474_4_0616.jpg" n="4"/>no question but they will receive more consideration from a continued Republican administration of national affairs than from any other. There will be no difficulty, indeed, in holding the full German vote throughout the country, if the party can give reasonable assurance of the continued reform movements that distinguished the latter part of Gen. Grant's administration, and, if the various local party managers will simply refuse to admit temperance and Sabbatarian questions into national politics, where they do not belong.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
