<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-01-29">Jan. 29, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[The Chicago Fire and Prevention of its Recurrence]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-01-29">Jan. 29, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[THE CHICAGO FIRE AND PREVENTION OF ITS RECURRENCE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of the truly Liberian cold the mass meeting that the Chicago Workers Association had called for yesterday afternoon was pretty well attended. Mr. Louis Schwuchow, president of the Chicago Workers Association, opened the meeting. Dr. Ernst Schmidt was elected chairman, and Joseph Grunhut of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung, secretary.</p>
   <p>Dr. Schmidt said, "As President of this meeting, I will take the floor first and express my convictions without considering whether they correspond to those held by the organizers of this meeting or not. One of the aims of this meeting is that Germans from other parts of the city shall approve what the North Side did in two previous meetings and in their demonstration. We are asked to indorse everything that happened. I, for my part, cannot do so.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0646.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"I believe it would have been better for the good cause if the mass demonstration had not taken place. A procession by night can become dangerous, even if it is started by the best and most dependable elements. One cannot be responsible for all who run along; one cannot get at the rabble that uses the occasion for brawls, riots endexcesses. What young street Arabs do is attributed to decent quiet citizens. The biliousness of the Americans, aroused by their prejudiced newspapers, was ridiculous and absolutely unjustified. Instead of a mass demonstration, competition with thousands of signatures should have been organized. Effective speakers should have given the City Council " a piece of their mind" and explained to them the point of view of the masses.</p>
   <p>"I do not approve of a mass riot as a means to influence the City Council. If every party would do the same, would march with heterogeneous, masses to the City Hall and push its way into the Council Chamber, the situation <pb facs="5418474_4_0647.jpg" n="3"/>might become very dangerous. Such a procedure is very questionable and should not be taken too lightly. However, it has now happened, and in the future an equally effective way can be used that will be innocuous.</p>
   <p>"I am opposed to the new presented Fire Ordinance that the City Council plans to pass. It has become very one-sided, and therefore quite unsatisfactory. Why should one side of a street have to be built fire-proof, while on the other side and across the alley tinder boxes of any height may be erected? I think to lay the limits along streets is non-sensical. A law suit on the basis of this paragraph a very able attorney told me, would be decided against the city. The "gussets" that according to the present fire ordinance one will permit at several points, I think most dangerous. At the first big fire that the wind kindles and carries further we will have another conflagration in Chicago as we did have it, if built in the same "fire-proof" as before.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0648.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"One might question if the City Council cares at all whether the working people have the means to erect brick buildings or even pay rent for such costly buildings. On valuable plots in the business district low wooden houses won't be built in any case, because it would not pay, and to force owners of cheap plots to build comparatively expensive brick building on them, is very oppressive. A quiet objective deliberation seems now to have become impossible, thanks to the newspaper campaigns and the split in the City Council. All that we can hope to attain now is to narrow as much as possible the fire limits. The North Side has made its will prevail, but the West and South Sides are greatly injured. Whole districts there will remain unbuilt, because the means are lacking for stone buildings, and the construction of wooden houses is to be forbidden.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0649.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Where is there justice? The inhabitants of the West and south sides in very many cases are in just as difficult a situation as those of the North Side. There plots are to remain empty, new low wooden structures are to be prohibited, but the old rotten barracks may remain till they fall to pieces or burn. The Building Board act arbitrarily, capriciously and confusedly if not actually corruptly. I could have give dozens of examples. A German has little to hope from this Building Board. The fire limits should be decided according to the real value of the real estate, and should be self-regulatory. Hasty ordinances harm the worker, without finally profiting the rich man, if they don't remain dead letters altogether.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0650.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"A written petition to the City Council could still save quite a few districts of the South and West Sides for cheap homesteads for the workers. The tension between Americans and Germans must disappear. On both sides mistakes are being made. The discussion of this question has to be continued.</p>
   <p>"The American press has contemptuously look down upon the German protest, and has decried the mass movement against the original fire ordinance of Medill's as a Communistic riot. They don't know what they are doing. How can one present such a justified demand of the people as a crime?</p>
   <p>"I regret that in the German press, the word Communist has been used as an abusive term. By heaping abuse nothing can be proven; in any case nothing against the principle of that movement.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0651.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"The social development is not at its end. It is an empty illusion to believe that the gross contrasts between rich and poor can exist permanently. The day will come, when the social question will be handled by the masses in a more sensible fashion, and the inequality before law and justice will be done away with; when the name "Communist" will cease to be a term of opprobrium. I always have fought for common law, for equal law, and I am still doing so in my old age."</p>
   <p>The next speech was made by Mr. Wilhelm Rapp, who said, "My friends, I think nobody will expect me to enter upon details of the question you are discussing, as I have been back only two days in my old home-town. Since the great catastrophe it has been tried to take away by decree Chicago's cosmopolitan character. Nativistic tendencies have bared the poison fangs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0652.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"The German, by nature, is cosmopolitan, very likely to get peaceably along with others, very indulgent of their pretensions.</p>
   <p>"Chicago owes its political and social character to its cosmopolitan working class, that here feels contented. The German worker really represents the true all-American working class. The Germans have defended, as against the greedy land monopoly, the rights of the free working class and have prevented the big money-bags from gobbling up the plots of the laboring people and from bringing the worker into the same dependent position as in the big cities of Europe and, in part, in the East of the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0653.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"In marching ahead in cool determination, you, my friends, are the recognized and honored champions of freedom and of right generally and of the freedom and the right of the worker and the middle classes in particular.</p>
   <p>"To the fire limit question as understood in the East; I saw in Baltimore Germans and Americans, who rejoiced when the news came that the Germans of the North Side had been victorious over the nativists."</p>
   <p>Mr. Vocke's speech we will print tomorrow. A resolutions committee was named, consisting of Dr. Schmidt, Wilhelm Rapp and Wilhelm Vocke. Its propositions were unanimously adopted. Their text:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0654.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>"Resolved that we completely approve the measures taken by the Germans of the North Side against the original fire limit ordinance that comprised the whole city and that we endorse in every respect the actions taken by the Mr. A. C. Hesing.</p>
   <p>"Resolved that we demand of the City Council that it does justice to the interests of the small plot owners, both in respect to rebuilding of their habitations and the new construction that has become necessary for the growing laboring population of Chicago in all parts of the city.</p>
   <p>"Resolved, finally, that we will collaborate in pursuit of these principles with all our fellow citizens no matter where they have been born."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
