<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-09-03">Tuesday,September 3, 1878</date>.
<title level="a">Germans in the Next Congress</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Baltimore German Correspondent)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0914</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0914.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-09-03">Tuesday,September 3, 1878</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANS IN THE NEXT CONGRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Baltimore German Correspondent)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In our opinion, it is not absolutely necessary that Germans sit in the Congress of the United States. Since the Germans cast the largest number of votes next to the natives, it is fitting that in proportion a certain percentage of the elected belongs to them, especially as the number of immigrants, who actively take part in public life as American citizens, is steadily growing. It was therefore pleasant to see that for ten years almost no Congress was elected, in which not one or two German-born citizens were members, and to the 45th Congress even five Germans were elected, a fact which seemed to indicate that the Teutonic element of the nation is gaining in importance and political influence. This hypothesis has now to prove itself.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0915.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Germans in this country must show in November if they are able to elect the same or a greater number of their countrymen to the 46th Congress. So far, it does not look promising.</p>
   <p>Dr. Lorenz Brentano, from Baden, represents the Third District of Illinois (Chicago). In spite of being a new member, he distinctly distinguished himself last winter. He worked indefatigably for the benefit, not only of his own constituents, but of all the Germans, who, in any matter, asked for his help. He followed attentively the debates in Congress, and occasionally participated in the discussions. He was an active worker in the committee room and gained the gratitude of the Washingtonians, because of his efforts in their behalf. He left the Capitol in June with the consciousness of having fulfilled his duties. Hardly had he arrived in Chicago, when the German press dragoons swooped down upon him like so many vultures.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0916.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He was accused of all imaginable crimes and that he was not indicted is a great miracle.The most improbable slanders were reported about him.Fortunately. his opponents had started too early to waste their power. because all accusations could be promptly refuted from Washington. The old man has luckily a good stomach, but it is unpleasant just the same to have one's name dragged through the mud by such press bandits.</p>
   <p>On September 10, the nomination in his district will take place, and we hope that the Republicans of the Third District, in spite of the slanders, will honor him with the renomination, which he so richly deserves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
