<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-07-01">July 1st, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The German Democrats</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-07-01">July 1st, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN DEMOCRATS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The beginning of the regular campaign will start in about three months, but the the German Democrats have already founded an organization and decided on the form of their campaign. The slogan is "Cleveland and Altgeld". The meeting at the Democratic Headquarters, 137 Monroe Street, brought a surprisingly large attendance; it was so crowded that the hall was too small for the occasion. The German Democratic Club of Cook County sponsored the affair. The meeting was called to order by Mr. Berblinger; Leo Austrian was elected chairman and Ervin Mack acted as secretary.</p>
   <p>The chairman emphasized that the Germans should take a greater interest than they have shown heretofore in the preparations for the approaching campaign. The lively participation at today's assembly plainly showed that the German spirit has been aroused. Joe Gruenhut favored the plan to organize Cleveland and Altgeld clubs in the various wards. General Lieb dissented. He believed it to be preferable to base the coming fight on principles rather than to limit it to personalities. "The time is ripe for the Germans to obtain the rank and <pb facs="5418474_4_0257.jpg" n="2"/>position which they deserve, considering their numerical strength and intelligence If Cleveland should be elected through the support of the North-western states and and should Altgeld be swept in to office in Illinois, then the Germans would share in this glory, since this attainment is only possible with German help. If the German vote decides the outcome of the next election, then all talk of compulsory school laws, Sunday blue laws, and prohibition will cease because all parties will then respect the power of the Germans and curry their favor. Only such an alliance can organize the storm troops, supply the proper speakers, and furnish material for propaganda. The German vote can only be won with arguments; brass-music and stentorian hurrah's are useless." Emiel Hoechster declared that the Democratic Party never had such an excellent opportunity as today. The National Convention has realized that the future of the party, as far as the Northwestern states are concerned, depends on the German element; therefore, the German principles have been incorporated in the platform. Considering these conditions, the time has never been more auspicious than now for the founding of a large German organization. He offered a resolution that such a league be brought to life by electing a chairman an executive, a finance and campaign committee, and also a press-committee. Messrs. Berblinger, Prager, Rummel, Skemper and Stern assented. A motion to postpone the election and have it acted upon at a general meeting was lost. Many of the speakers <pb facs="5418474_4_0258.jpg" n="3"/>especially Messrs. Haerting, Lieb and Berblinger, asserted that the organization should not limit its activities to Cook County or the state of Illinois, but it should colaborate with the German clubs of the North-western states, Wisconsin, Indiana and Michigan. Mr. Stern and Mr. Lange favored an organization of a more local character, something confined to Cook County only. Only later, as Mr. Haerting suggested, should organizations in the various congressional districts, patterned after the 1876 campaign, be formed.</p>
   <p>The election of officials brought the following results. Leo Austrian, president; Wm. Kuecken, vice-president; Dr. Leininger, vice-president; Bernh. Niebling, vice-president; Val. Schmittschmitt, vice-president; Chas. Siegwalt, vice-president; T. B. Thiele, secretary; V. S. Berblinger, secretary correspondence; Eugine Prager, treasurer.</p>
   <p>In the next session the Executive Committee will nominate the campaign committee which will not only have well-known Democrats for its members, but representatives of all classes and vocations are to be included. Its headquarters will be of a permanent nature and centrally located.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
