<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-05-12">May 12, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">Truce</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0926</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0926.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-05-12">May 12, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">TRUCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mass meeting of the citizens of the 14th ward was held with the intention of the mayoral election for the West Side. Mr. Gervin, opening the meeting, informed the gathered crowd that a notice appearing in the Staats-Zeitung was the cause for meeting here and to confer upon the city's affairs.</p>
   <p>Mr. Max Frohlich said: "We met here to confer and voice our opinion on the big question of the day. The man at the head of our city was elected in the year 1873 by a 12,000 majority votes for a two year term; during his office a new charter was adopted, stating explicitly that a mayoralty election shall not take place before the year 1877. The same newspapers which were in favor of the charter there by prolonging the mayor's term for one and a half year, are yelling the loudest for his removal."The speaker made known that the Supreme Court declined to proclaim a mayoralty election, therefore the city council did not give a written proclamation to that effect. The speaker said he considers Colvin as the lawfully <pb facs="5418474_4_0927.jpg" n="2"/>elected mayor and is of the opinion that everyone present shares this attitude.</p>
   <p>Mr. Maas reported that they were unsuccessful in locating Mr. Baumgarten, but that he had a chance to speak with him this morning when he already asked him to comply with the wishes of his voters or at least to state the reasons for his conduct. Baumgarten replied then, that according to the charter, Colvin has no legal claim to the office. Mr. Maas reminded him of not being a jurist: there is of course doubt as to which party is right, but in a case like this, his duty would be to favor the party which enjoys the preference of the voters.</p>
   <p>Rudolph Schwarslose said: "Alderman Baumgarten is not mindful of the wishes of his voters and when asked for an explanation, be even refuses to make his appearance, therefore it deems necessary to invite him to resign."</p>
   <p>John Buhler said: "I, too, am opposed to Baumgarten's tactics. The meeting is justified in demanding of Mr. Baumbarten to present himself to them and state the reasons which prompt his conduct."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0928.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the speakers opinion, Colvin has more right to the office than Hoyne. It also is to his credit that he endeavored to save us from Puritanism. Furthermore, he stated to the new city council his willingness to present his case before the Superior Court and thus bring about a decision in this affair. His proposition has not been accepted neither the other one, that those gentlemen who were so insistent in removing him from office would first pay their taxes, then he would gladly withdraw. To request of Mr. Baumgarten to resign does not meet with his approval, but he ought to be asked once more to come to the next meeting and explain why he supports Colvin's opponents.</p>
   <p>Resolved: The majority of the citizens of the 14th ward are of the opinion that Hon. H. D. Colvin, Mayor of Chicago, is legally and on the grounds of the law of 1872 justified in retaining the office of mayor until April of the year 1877.</p>
   <p>It is further resolved that John Baumgarten elected alderman of the 14th ward at the regular election has proven through his activities in the city <pb facs="5418474_4_0929.jpg" n="4"/>council to disregard the wishes of his voters, by voting for a man named Thomas Hoyne for the mayor's office, thus throwing the city into the rule of lawlessness and turmoil;</p>
   <p>Therefore it is decided that the citizens of the 14th ward disapprove in the highest degree the actions of Alderman Baumgarten, and respectfully but firmly demand of him as our representative to obey henceforth the wishes of the citizens of the 14th ward and thus casting his vote for the Hon H. D. Colvin to retain him as mayor of Chicago until the lawful expiration of his term, and in case said Alderman Baumgarten is not willing to comply with the wishes of his voters, then in the opinion of this meeting, he would no longer be worthy to represent the citizens of the 14th ward in the City Council, and request of him to resign from office immediately thus giving the citizens a chance to elect someone else in his stead.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
