<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-09-08">September 8, 1877</date><title level="a">The German-American Republican Club of the Eighteenth Ward.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0328</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0328.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-09-08">September 8, 1877</date><title level="a">THE GERMAN-AMERICAN REPUBLICAN CLUB OF THE EIGHTEENTH WARD.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A number of Chicago's taxapyers met with the purpose of establishing a German-American Republican Club. Mr. Lorenz Brentano, the appointed president of the meeting, gave a short illustration of the German-American relationship to the Republican party. The tie which bound the Germans to the Republican party since its existence, has during the last few years steadily grown weaker. This was especially noticed at the last election when his fellow-countrymen deserted in big numbers the Republican Party. But he believes that the excellent success of the reformed Republican Federal Government and of President Hayes will have power enough to bring back the Germans who turned their back on the Republican Party, and help her with the reforms which they desire so much; first of all the election of honest officials. A committee then proposed to nominate Mr. Lorenz Brentano as President, Mr. C. M. Staiger and Mr. C. M. Petrie as first and second secretaries respectively, and Mr. H. <pb facs="5418474_4_0329.jpg" n="2"/>Rheinhardt as Treasurer. This proposal was accepted.</p>
   <p>Mr. A. C. Hesing complied with the general request to address the meeting. He said: he did not come here with the intention of making a speech, but came to join a movement which he holds to be of great importance, although he would have preferred to remain in quiet activity.... It is a well known fact that since the year 1873 he hardly could have been looked upon as a Republican or at all interested in the party. Puritanism has swept through the Republican Party, threatening German rights. Thus they had to show their power. With what result, is well known. It was not easy to take a stand against a party with which he was associated since its establishment, and for whose development he had done so much. He had to do it to protect the personal freedom of his countrymen and does not regret it. He is not ashamed to acknowledge that he took a big part in the creation of the "People's Party", which came to such an infamous end. The "reform movement" of the <pb facs="5418474_4_0330.jpg" n="3"/>year 1869 against which he fought, gave Chicago the most corrupt city administration which it ever had. Colvin, whom he supported, plunged the city into debts, but the Republicans were coming to its rescue and he is happy to say that the Germans have again gathered under the Republican banner, adding to the glory of the party in its reform work. The fact that the Germans deserted the Republican Party some time ago was a good lesson. They learned that reform was imperative and this was shown in the attitude of President Hayes who displayed manliness and courage in freeing the American people once again. As in the case of the Federal Government, so will local conditions be helped by the reforms, which the Republican Party is trying to introduce. There are parties which hope for success, for instance, the Labor Party, but this newly organized party can not last. The Republican Party which solved the slave question, although the process was slow, will find a way to solve the social question also... He has come to the conclusion that a strong party organization is the utmost importance, therefore he will devote <pb facs="5418474_4_0331.jpg" n="4"/>the rest of his life to the service of the party and thereby serve the people of this country....</p>
   <p>Mr. Lorenz Brentano then spoke of the importance of the coming election. The citizens are almost more interested in local than in state and national elections, although their negligence is sometimes inexcusable. Much thought should be given to the election of county officials for they have the power over the citizens' money. The election of judges should not be taken lightly either; they can display a strong influence upon the welfare of society. It is hardly necessary to mention the importance of the County Clerk's office which has gone from bad hands into worse, revoltingly loathsome at the present. The profit of former years has changed into deficit now. At this point Mr. Hesing made known that the cost of the clerk's office exceeded $100,000 last year and according to information he had received, this sum will be exceeded by $10,000 this year. Mr. Brentano then asked the Germans to have faith in the Republican party to aid her in introducing reforms and in the election of <pb facs="5418474_4_0332.jpg" n="5"/>honest officials. If the Germans do their part at the coming election, they will earn the gratitude of the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
