<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-07-16">July 16, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">The Know Nothings of the Police.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_4_0936</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_4_0936.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-07-16">July 16, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">THE KNOW NOTHINGS OF THE POLICE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is now a year since Elmer Washburn came from Joliet to Chicago. We do not intend to give, today, a survey of his activities, we simply wish to publish some statistics, which will prove that Washburn is truly a know nothing.</p>
   <p>No one denies that one third of the population of Chicago is German. This fact warrants a corresponding number of Germans on the police force. In former years this has always been the case. A policemen stationed in a German district should be able to speak German as well as English. The official books of the police board show that since July 1st, 1872 there were appointed 139 new policemen while 85 were discharged during the same length of time. Thus an increase of 54 policemen. From the 139 policemen appointed during Washburn's time, 15 were Germans. From the 85 who left the police force 33 were Germans. In other words 10 per cent of the newly appointed are Germans, while among these who left 50 per cent were Germans. Of the 33 Germans who left the police force, 21 resigned or almost 68 percent, while 12 were dismissed, only 33 per cent. According to this the German policemen serve well. Since July 9th, when a start was made to get the new men granted by the city council, 38 policemen have been appointed. Of those 38 only 3 are Germans. Since July 9th, 8</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
