<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-02-19">Feb. 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">[Hungarians on the South Side Form Political Club]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0580</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0580.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-02-19">Feb. 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">[HUNGARIANS ON THE SOUTH SIDE FORM POLITICAL CLUB]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The role in political life played by the Chicago Hungarians who live on the South Side has been a rather sorrowful one. The Hungarians who live in this section are aware of the truth of this statement, because they have tried for the last twenty years to gain recognition in the field of politics.</p>
   <p>Political clubs were organized, but they were always of an independent nature. Thus when elections were over, the members of these independent organizations never received any consideration from the politicians who had promised them so much before election. The reason for this was that these organizations never declared themselves for either the Republican party or the Democratic party.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0581.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Another great shortcoming was the presence among the Hungarians of the South Side of self-appointed political leaders who would lead their followers into the fold of whichever political party paid them [the leaders] the most. Some of the politicians who were seeking office would make half-hearted promises, and when the election was over these office-seekers would tell the voters that they [the voters] had no right to ask for anything because they had already been paid.</p>
   <p>This is being written to inform the people of their mistakes in the past. We think that we must make an open admission of our political beliefs; we must openly state whether we are Republicans or Democrats.</p>
   <p>In the Hungarian community on the South Side of Chicago a Republican club has been formed. This organization intends to work and cooperate in every way with all other Hungarian Republican clubs throughout the city.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0582.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>All those Hungarians who are not yet citizens of the United States are urged to join this organization, because it will make arrangements to help them obtain their naturalization papers. The organization has also made arrangements to have teachers of civics available for those who want further instruction in the principles of American government.</p>
   <p>This organization wants to be strong, and it is the duty of every Hungarian-American citizen to help make it strong. The mistakes of the past should be a lesson to the people of the South Side.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
