<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1924-08-29">Aug. 29, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Admissions about the Klan</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0501</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0501.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1924-08-29">Aug. 29, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ADMISSIONS ABOUT THE KLAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The scorching fire of election has started and is lighting up the entire political world. Certain facts that concern millions of individuals have been hidden and have gone without explanation.</p>
   <p>Both platforms, the Democratic and the Republican, have discussed certain social and political questions, and have taken definite stands in regard to these questions, but have neglected to assume any kind of a position in regard to the latest menace of society, the secret organization, the Ku Klux Klan.</p>
   <p>During the Democratic National Convention, this question came near splitting the party. The Republicans decided to be non-partisans in regard to this question, which involves religious freedom, class distinction, and <pb facs="5422061_1_0502.jpg" n="2"/>race distinction.</p>
   <p>A certain faction of the Democratic party composed mostly of Irish Catholics, were all for coming out openly against the Ku Klux Klan.</p>
   <p>Bryan and McAdoo stopped this when they told the convention that this would be a great political blunder, thereby losing certain democratic States. In order to keep peace in the family, they left the Ku Klux question out of their platform.</p>
   <p>The candidates cannot avoid this important question.</p>
   <p>The people are anxious to know just where the candidates stand in this matter. They aren't looking for a diplomatic, flowery speech, but are asking for an explanation. The main question to be answered is: Are they for, or against the Ku Klux Klan?</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0503.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We know how LaFollette stands; he has condemned the activities, the organization and its entire bloody record.</p>
   <p>Last week, John W. Davis, the democratic candidate for president gave a campaign speech in the state of New Jersey, and in his speech he admitted that he had had many inquiries, in regard to his stand on the Ku Klux Klan situation.</p>
   <p>Like a gentleman and a scholar he openly declared himself.</p>
   <p>He said, - "That any time there is an organization, regardless of what name it might have, let it be Ku Klux Klan, or any other name, waving a standard of racial and religious discrimination, it immediately becomes an attacker of American principles. Therefore it should be condemned just as I will condemn it, if we aim to believe in American ideals."</p>
   <p>At the end of his speech he asked that Coolidge make a definite statement declaring <pb facs="5422061_1_0504.jpg" n="4"/>himself as to how he stands with reference to this question, in order that this question be eliminated from the political field.</p>
   <p>Naturally everyone will wait to see whether Coolidge will come out so openly to condemn the activities of the Ku Klux Klan.</p>
   <p>The immigrant is more concerned with this question than with anything else, because originally the Ku Klux Klan was formed to combat their entry into this country.</p>
   <p>The Catholics, the Jews and the Colored people, regardless whether they are immigrants or not, are the Klan's natural enemies. The Ku Klux Klan brand these people as criminals.</p>
   <p>In certain states they have very good connections. In certain cities and towns their activities are shameful, and they are living through a mania of hunting people. There is even murder attached to the name of the "Klan."</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0505.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It is a sad situation indeed when such an ignorant and unbridled organization such as the Klan breaks through the crust of civilization in a great country like the United States.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it is very important that our leading politicians declare themselves in regard to this issue, in order that such an organization be stamped out like weeds which bob up from time to time and later endanger the life of the entire nation.</p>
   <p>Therefore it is the duty of us immigrant American citizens to watch, and think seriously about which of the leaders of the two great parties will protect those rights which were given to us when we become citizens of this country. We must also see to it, that national peace is preserved, and advancement and security for all is assured.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0506.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>When we are assured of the man from whom we can expect these things on a liberal and progressive basis, we will join hands with that party in order to give more assurance for success, so that every inhabitant of the United States regardless of color, creed or nationality will have equal rights.</p>
   <p>Now we wait with curiosity as to what President Coolidge will have to say to this invitation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
