<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1924-10-30">Oct. 30, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Menken Waves the Flag</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0286</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0286.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1924-10-30">Oct. 30, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">MR. MENKEN WAVES THE FLAG</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note.--This editorial written with reference to an editorial which appeared in the New York World on October 28, 1924.]</p>
   <p>It is gratifying to find among our contemporaries writers of such intelligent, fairminded, and frank editorials as the one which appeared in the New York World. No doubt, the wise and courageous policy of its great editor, Joseph Pulitzer, now deceased, is not dead yet. The Hungarians in this country, as well as abroad, will notice that the powerful moulder of American public opinion, the world, has diagnosed the Hungarian governmental situation very precisely and correctly, and all the agents and hirelings of the Horthy regime, whether they are Americans like Mr. Menken or Hungarians, cannot mislead the intelligent Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0287.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As much as we deplore the officiousness of the Security League by annoying Countess Karolyi upon her entrance to America, we consider it as a great publicity stunt to her American mission. While we are convinced that her political convictions are anti-Bolsheviki, her lectures will prove beyond doubt the nature and character of her American mission, and the great and glorious type of Hungarian womanhood Countess Karolyi represents.</p>
   <p>If Countess Karolyi's American visit would be the very least injurious to the genuine American spirit, or to our American free and liberal institution we would ourselves favor her deportation, as we do not like to see Hungarians knocking our adopted country and hurting the reputation of all of us, but we warmly welcome Countess Karolyi as a true representative of Hungarian democracy, and the finest prototype of Hungarian womanhood, a rare specimen among the aristocracy of old Hungary.</p>
   <p>We heartily congratulate the New York World for their editorial. In the <pb facs="5422061_1_0288.jpg" n="3"/>vernacular of the day: The World said a mouthful. Let the Horthy regime and their faithful ally, Stanwood Menken, put this in their pipe and smoke it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
