<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-06-24">June 24, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Answering the Hungarian Businessman</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ignac Izsak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0252</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0252.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-06-24">June 24, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">ANSWERING THE HUNGARIAN BUSINESSMAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ignac Izsak</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In last week's Magyar Tribune, a Hungarian businessman objected to the speech I made in connection with the Burnside Magyar Home.</p>
   <p>The objecting businessman is far from the truth in his conclusions. If he remembers my talk, he should know that I did not condemn all Hungarian businessmen, but only those who have become wealthy through Hungarian patronage.....</p>
   <p>The fact is that most of the Hungarian bankers, realtors, owners of travel agencies, and other businessmen relied on Hungarian patronage in the beginning .....that later on, after they were securely established, they did acquire other customers does not alter that fact.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0253.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I repeat that whenever there is occasion to support a public cause, those who have gotten rich by the sweat of Hungarian workers' brows should be the first and heaviest contributors.</p>
   <p>I find it peculiar that we should always insist upon contributions from the working class, but when praise or honor is bestowed, the wealthy individuals believe that they should be first in line.</p>
   <p>The objector is mistaken when he places the blame for the failure of the North Side Magyar Home plans on me. I did not participate in the work because I saw that it was being carried out impractically. The officers of the United Societies decided to raise the money through collections. I told them at the meeting that the maximum amount that could be raised in six months in this way would be approximately five or six hundred dollars. My prophecy was fulfilled.....Any Hungarian is willing to give one or two dollars to assist orphans and widows, but if he is asked to invest fifty or a hundred dollars, he is entitled to get a clear <pb facs="5422061_1_0254.jpg" n="3"/>picture of [the plan for]its repayment.</p>
   <p>The objector is mistaken when he says that because the Bond Company took over the bonds, the responsibility of the Hungarians is over.</p>
   <p>The Bond Company has taken over the bond issue, not in order to hold it, but to sell it. If the Hungarians do not buy up the bonds, the Virgin Mary Society will have built the Magyar Home in vain, because it will not belong to the Hungarians, but to whoever buys the controlling shares. It is our duty to enlighten the Hungarians regarding this situation, because many of them are ignorant of the real facts. These bonds may be purchased on the installment plan, which makes it possible for the Hungarians in modest financial circumstances to become owners of the bonds of the Magyar Home.</p>
   <p>It is true that a few Hungarian businessmen of Burnside demonstrated their <pb facs="5422061_1_0255.jpg" n="4"/>devotion to their countrymen [by contributing to the Home], but in the end we have to admit that our American friends showed more good will and appreciation [of the situation]than many of our countrymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
