<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1917-10-05">Oct. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">America's Second Liberty Loan</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0709</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0709.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1917-10-05">Oct. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICA'S SECOND LIBERTY LOAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States government in order to finish the war in which it is fighting for world peace and to make the world safe for democracy is appealing to its citizens for another war loan which is the second of its kind since we entered the war.</p>
   <p>This second loan is nothing to be alarmed about and we feel sure that the people will subscribe to it with one heart and one soul the way they did with the first loan, because we all realize that this money is being used to end war for all time. This purpose can only be accomplished through the united strength of the people of this nation.</p>
   <p>We will not speak of how much individuals love their country or how much concerned they are about the development of the human race: the lodges and <pb facs="5422061_1_0710.jpg" n="2"/>societies should use their influence to induce their members to support the loan. If it is not successful, regardless how strong this nation might be, its general principles and aims will be completely shattered. Each and every lodge club, and other organizations must do something to secure the success of this loan.</p>
   <p>At this time the government wants to acquaint the foreign population with the necessity of the loan. The government has sent representatives to the foreign groups in order to acquaint them with the situation and from now on it is up to them to rally to the aid of our government. To support this loan it is not only a patriotic duty but also a good business investment. Its success depends on whether or not the public is fully acquainted with the facts. Every individual should purchase at least one bond.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian American citizens, as they always do, will find the path of righteiousness and recognize their patriotic duty. We all know that each and every citizen has his bit to do. The Hungarian American citizen knows that in the time of peace we should all be good law abiding citizens, and <pb facs="5422061_1_0711.jpg" n="3"/>now, in time of war, we all know that not to help our country is a great sin.</p>
   <p>The foreign American citizens will make it possible for this second Liberty loan to be just as successful as the first one. This success will be the most expressive proof of good citizenship, patriotism, and of our love of a peaceful home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
