<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1917-06-29">June 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Bread, Whiskey and Beer</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0089</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0089.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1917-06-29">June 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BREAD, WHISKEY AND BEER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently there were two very important news items revealed to the public. One of these came from Washington, D.C., stating that the House of Representatives had passed a resolution in regard to food regulation in this country. This regulation prohibits the use of barley or rye for the manufacture of liquor. The other news item comes from England with reference to their barley and rye crop being insufficient to amply supply the breweries. Since the law prohibiting the manufacture of alcoholic liquors will be enacted, it will make the country dry during the war. This law is not being brought about because this country's crop is insufficient to supply the needs of the nation, but it is because of our alliance in war with other nations. This makes it our duty to provide food to people living in those countries, especially England. So the government of this country needs to divide the crops in such manner that we will retain a certain amount, the rest to be divided among the allies. It seems as though the law enacted by Congress is for this purpose, but looks are <pb facs="5422061_1_0090.jpg" n="2"/>deceiving. The truth of the matter is that politics are playing its part. The Temperance League is going to make use of the situation, thereby making this move look like a patriotic move, but at the same time taking a great step towards their objective for which they have been working for some time.</p>
   <p>The English news item makes the resolution enacted by the House of Representative of the United States a laughable matter. The law prohibited the manufacture of alcholic liquors in the United States so England will be supplied with material to manufacture alcoholic beverages. In England beer or ale is considered one of the necessities of life for a worker. In the United States the law makers are not far-sighted enough to see this. In the name of the people of the United States they give up the manufacture of alcoholic beverages, in order that the Engligh people be supplied with plenty of it.</p>
   <p>Practically all the nations involved in the war have made restrictions with reference to the use of alcohol, but none of them have closed their breweries or wineries. The German people who have felt the effects of the war more than any nation can still drink beer and their beer is manufactured from barley just as ours was.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0091.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If the United States thinks that it is absolutely necessary to prohibit the use of barley by the manufacturers,we cannot speak against it. But this necessity can only come when and if the nations that consume our barley quit manufacturing beer out of it. England should be the first nation to do this. But if the English find that beer is a necessity, then it must be a necessity in the United States also.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
