<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-07-10">July 10, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Reorganization of the Hungarian-Jewish Congregation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-07-10">July 10, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">REORGANIZATION OF THE HUNGARIAN-JEWISH CONGREGATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first Hungarian congregation in Chicago worked very fruitfully for thirty years. When it was in its blossoming days, eighteen years ago, it built a most beautiful church on the corner of Marshfield Avenue and Polk Street. The priest was that prominent and well-known speaker and orator, Rabbi Moses Fischer who speaks eloquently in both Hungarian and in English, and he stayed with this congregation for twenty years, after which he was chosen to be the rabbi in a Hungarian-Jewish congregation in Detroit. Soon after he left, the Hungarian-Jewish Congregation disbanded.</p>
   <p>Furthermore the officers of this congregation became uninterested and sold all the property, the value of which amounted to some $60,000. Thus due to the lack of interest in the congregation, the people who belonged to it were slowly absorbed into other congregations, and they soon found out that these new congregations cared for their membership only until they had acquired the wealth of the Hungarian-Jewish Congregation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0143.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Soon after this happened a small group, under the leadership of Louis Gottlieb, a prominent Hungarian-Jewish lawyer, began [some]activities.</p>
   <p>It was decided that the old Hungarian-Jewish Congregation should be reorganized. We are glad to inform our readers that this reorganization movement has met with unexpectedly great success. The Hungarian-Jewish people realize that they have lost their congregation, and that they committed a grave mistake when they let their church fall into the hands of others outside of their own circle. They have reorganized under their old name, The First Hungarian Congregation.</p>
   <p>Up to date more than a hundred of the old members have rejoined. Temporarily they have rented a place at 4825 N. Kedzie Avenue for their place of worship.</p>
   <p>Their plans for the future are to build a large church, school, library <pb facs="5422061_1_0144.jpg" n="3"/>and a social center for their young people. This will not only bring pride and glory to the Jewish people of this congregation, but all Hungarians will be and should be proud of this proposed project. Therefore it would be a good idea if all Hungarian people who are of the Jewish religion, would join this newly formed Congregation, and thus help their great dreams come true in the very near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
