<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1935-03-20">March 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Festival of Ide of March on the South Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1935-03-20">March 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">FESTIVAL OF IDE OF MARCH ON THE SOUTH SIDE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4...............The memory of the beautiful March festival, which was arranged by the Association of the Hungarian Churches and Societies, will linger for a long time in the soul of those, who were witnessing it. In our preceding number we printed the whole program. Those, whose names were printed in the program, were actually on the stage. Usually the mayors of the world's biggest cities do not go farther than to promise their presence at such occasions, and then let themselves be represented by somebody else, but Mayor Kelly, of Chicago came personally to express the greetings of the city to the celebrants. Somebody in his suite remarked, that this was the first time, when a Kelly went on his St. Patrick's Day to another nationality's festival. He was greeted with a tremendous ovation. The singers sang, the dancers danced, the orators made speeches, everything went in the best possible order, without any interruption. The only orator, who was not on the program was listened to with the greatest attention. Joseph Csanady, secretary of the National <pb facs="5422061_1_0629.jpg" n="2"/>League for the Revision. He stepped upon the stage after the speech of Rev. Steve Balogh, and made the proposition, that the Hungarians of America send a petition to the League of Nations, demanding a plebiscite on the disposal of the former Hungarian territories, which were given to other countries, to the people in these territories could themselves decide where to belong. This proposition was accepted with the greatest of enthusiasm and the public authorized the Association of the Churches and Societies of the Chicago South Side and the League for Revision to construct the petition and to collect the signatures of the thousands and thousands of Hungarians, and then to foreward the said petition where they expect to get results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
