<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-10-16">Oct. 16, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Hoover's Prosperity Plan</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Martin Benedek)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0358</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0358.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-10-16">Oct. 16, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">HOOVER'S PROSPERITY PLAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Martin Benedek)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The people of America are waiting breathlessly for the results of Hoover's newest plan, with which he desires to solve the economic crisis and end this accursed depression.....</p>
   <p>President Hoover, after much deliberation, called together the majority and minority leaders of the House and the Senate and acquainted them with his plan, asking their approval....</p>
   <p>The plan is known to our readers. Its basic principle is to infuse the country's banking institutions with new life and to save the smaller banks from collapse.</p>
   <p>The fact is that if Hoover would have come forward with this plan a year ago, it would have helped solve the economic crisis and would have even brought back prosperity in a small measure. At that time some of us still had money in the bank, and the infusion would have helped to bring about the desired <pb facs="5422061_1_0359.jpg" n="2"/>results.</p>
   <p>However, we believe that it is too late now for this plan to do any good.....In the past year hundreds of banks closed their doors, burying the savings of thousands, which in turn added to the army of those whose buying power has diminished to zero.....The depression will not be over until the people again will have buying power...</p>
   <p>This serious economic depression is not only an American crisis; it is also connected with the world economic crisis that is at the throat of all with its threat of strangulation. If we look at the American situation from a broader point of view, we can see that our internal problem cannot be separated from the international question.....................</p>
   <p>The most important thing is to restore the confidence of the public.....</p>
   <p>Nor is the world economic crisis alone to be blamed for wholesale unemployment. The development of machines, which created a small group of millionaires and a huge army of unemployed, is also responsible. This situation <pb facs="5422061_1_0360.jpg" n="3"/>cannot be remedied through the banks, because it requires a radical change in the economic system of America. This situation can only be remedied by limiting production and by securing a more equitable distribution of this world's goods. This is the only way this country can extricate itself out of the chaos in which it is suffering.</p>
   <p>President Hoover's plan may ease the situation temporarily, but it cannot bring about a permanent cure.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
