<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Ten Commandments for Immigrants in Time of War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0717</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0717.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE TEN COMMANDMENTS FOR IMMIGRANTS IN TIME OF WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I</p>
   <p>You must never forget that no one asked you to come to the United States. You came here of your own free will to make a better living and to save a few nickels for your old age.</p>
   <p>II</p>
   <p>When you stepped on the shore of the United States you were on free soil. No one asked you what you were doing here, and no one stood in your way. It was up to you and you only what you were going to do in this country. The nation immediately became your friend. You received the respect due to a guest when you entered the United States. Respect your host, and your host will respect you.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0718.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>III</p>
   <p>Keep your thoughts to yourself. Maybe the pope knows everything, but you are not a pope, and this does not mean that you know more than he does.</p>
   <p>IV</p>
   <p>Do not get involved in any arguments in public places.</p>
   <p>V</p>
   <p>For six days do your work and attend to your duties. On the seventh day rest; that is what the Lord intended you to do. Six days out of the week are for labor, and during this time you should think of nothing but your duties. If you are engaged in respectable work, you will be considered a law-abiding citizen, so work for six days, and on the seventh day of the week devote your time to rest and to your family.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0719.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>VI</p>
   <p>Do not take part in any political movement. Trust the people whose duty it is to think for you. Be satisfied, for you will not be able to change things anyway. In war unity means strength.</p>
   <p>VII</p>
   <p>Have respect for the laws of the country which provides your daily bread. The laws defend your interests. Every law has a purpose. You must be familiar with the laws, and you must obey them.</p>
   <p>VIII</p>
   <p>Do not carry on your person any kind of firearm or other deadly weapon. Your only weapon of defense should be your self-respect.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0720.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>IX</p>
   <p>Keep your savings in the same place in which you had them in time of peace. Money should be kept in a bank and not on one's person or at the place where one lives. You yourself cannot guard your money so well as the bank can. The laws of this country insure that what is yours is yours only. Regardless of what the future may bring, your wealth will not be threatened by disaster in the United States.</p>
   <p>X</p>
   <p>Love your neighbor. All men are equal regardless of creed and nationality. We all came from the same parentage originally, and we are all brothers and sisters. After the World War will come brotherly love among the nations of the world. It is for this purpose that this country is fighting. No one asks you for sacrifice in this war; therefore you can lead a life of peace and happiness if you keep to the straight and narrow path.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
