<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-04-04">Apr. 4, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Announcement of the Hungarian Republican Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0527</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0527.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-04-04">Apr. 4, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">ANNOUNCEMENT OF THE HUNGARIAN REPUBLICAN CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hungarian Brethern! Voting Citizens! The Burnside Hungarian Republican Club appeals to you regarding the approaching elections.</p>
   <p>This Club represents organized political power and influence in our district. All the candidates of the Republican party acknowledge our organization and turn to us for support at election time. Every Hungarian whose sympathies are Republican would do well to join our Club, for it is a well-known fact that strength lies in unity. Just look around at other national groups, the Germans, Italians, Poles, and Czechs. They have had political representation in Chicago for many years thanks to the fact that they have co-operated with one another. Let us do likewise. Therefore, Hungarian brethern, rally around the flag of the Chicago Hungarian Republican Club and carry the demands of the Hungarian-Americans to victory.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0528.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Election day will be on April 8. Of the many candidates running for office, the one whose election interests us the most is Elmer Brown. He represents the Tenth Ward, our own camp. He worked himself up from the ranks of the working class, therefore, he understands the workers' problems. The workers can expect the greatest benefit and acknowledgment from him. He promised that,if he is elected, he will help us get any necessary favors.</p>
   <p>Therefore, on April 8, when voting for Ward Committeeman, vote for Elmer Brown.</p>
   <p>There will be a meeting in his interest on Friday at the Magyar Home. On this occasion Elmer Brown will address the voters. Free refreshments will be served after the meeting.....</p>
   <p>The Burnside Hungarian</p>
   <p>Republican Club</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
