<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-05-10">May 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Ideas of the Hungarian Patriotic Association</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0698</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0698.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-05-10">May 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">IDEAS OF THE HUNGARIAN PATRIOTIC ASSOCIATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From the great Hungarian loyalty demonstration day, May 5, ideas were formulated for a new organization which will be known as the Hungarian Patriotic Association.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian Patriotic Association is sanctioned by the State Council of Defense. This organization has been in existence for the past three weeks, and its power and strength was demonstrated by the large number of Hungarian people who turned out on their patriotic demonstration day. This last meeting and demonstration day has never been excelled by any Hungarian organization in the United States.</p>
   <p>Now this organization is trying to familiarize the Hungarian people with its ideas and principles. This organization was founded by the Hungarian people; their interests gave birth to the ideas of the Association, and these ideas <pb facs="5422061_1_0699.jpg" n="2"/>will be carried out by it. This organization has shown the people of the United States that the Hungarian people are loyal--that their emotions, thoughts, and actions are governed by loyalty. This organization believes that loyalty exists in the heart of every Hungarian, and that there is not a single Hungarian inhabitant of the United States who does not have reason for gratitude to this country.</p>
   <p>Hungarians are fundamentally a loyal people. This organization will not tolerate nor promote disloyalty. The duties of Hungarian-American citizens are the same as the duties of those who are native-born citizens of this country. Those Hungarian-Americans who are not citizens should also be loyal to this country, for by taking part in this war the United States is fighting for world democracy, a cause which should be championed by every nation, in order to make the world safe for democracy and peace.</p>
   <p>The United States has taken it upon herself to free the people of Europe, including the Hungarian people, although the Hungarian government has been <pb facs="5422061_1_0700.jpg" n="3"/>fighting as a German ally. The Hungarian people, however, are not free. They are governed by the country's capitalists, who for their own protection have forced Hungary into the war. The same persons who forced the Hungarian nation into war are the ones who oppressed the Hungarian people. It is the duty of the Association to acquaint the people with the facts of the war and the objectives for which the United States is striving.</p>
   <p>As far as this organization knows, no Hungarian organization has ever explained the intricacies of the war. Therefore the Hungarian Patriotic Association has been organized with this idea in mind. The Association has a great future, although now it is only a state-wide organization with Chicago as its local headquarters.</p>
   <p>This organization was built up by the Chicago Hungarians in order that the Hungarian people might show their appreciation as a group toward the United States. The Hungarian people in Chicago are fully satisfied that the United States is fighting to free all humanity from a reign of tyranny. This <pb facs="5422061_1_0701.jpg" n="4"/>organization does not believe in suppressing the facts of the war, but will take every opportunity to present a true account of the conflict.</p>
   <p>With this cultural work in mind, the Association will gain the confidence of the Hungarian people in their fight for liberty through the Hungarian-Americans. The Hungarians in the United States will fight for the victory of the United States; they will understand that Hungary would be fighting for the same cause that the United States is fighting for, if the German Junkers were not the overpowering rulers of Hungary.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: This article was written by Joseph Fekete, secretary of Hungarian Patriotic Ass'n.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
