<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-07-22">July 22, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Anna Roselle--Anna Gyenge</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (Italian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-07-22">July 22, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">ANNA ROSELLE--ANNA GYENGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Hungarians recently proved that they are progressing rapidly on the road to cultural achievement. A nation's cultural standards are measured by their love of good literature and appreciation of art. We would have to write another chapter about the enthusiasm of our American-Hungarians for literature, but we wish to write today about art, to be more explicit, musical art.</p>
   <p>There are two nations on this earth who cannot live without wine and song. One is the Italian and the other the Hungarian. It is wonderful the way immigrant Italians love art. If one of their number has unusual ability, they try to raise him to the highest level. Let us just recall the case of Valentino, who started out as a parquet dancer. When his first motion picture was released, the Italians crowded the theaters, day after day, wherever it was shown</p>
   <p>The majority of the audiences at the Chicago Grand Opera performances are <pb facs="5422061_1_0245.jpg" n="2"/>Italians, hence, with few exceptions, the performers, as well as the offerings, are also Italian.</p>
   <p>Undeniably, our Hungarians are increasingly getting to be interested in opera and classical music. Not many of our countrymen have attained world fame on the operatic stage; in fact, we know of only one, Ethel Gerster, who was famous thirty years ago.</p>
   <p>Only a few years ago, Anna Gyenge, whose stage name is Anna Roselle, made a meteoric appearance on the stage of the famous Metropolitan Opera House of New York.....</p>
   <p>At the present time, Anna Roselle is appearing in many famous operatic roles at the Ravinia Park Opera.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0246.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Chicago Hungarians!....Let us show our appreciation of our great artist by attending these performances. Anna Roselle has brought fame to the Hungarians. She is our own, the proud possession of American Hungarians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
