<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-10-16">Oct. 16, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">[President's Speech to Legion Convention]</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Horizon is Clearing (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0451</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0451.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-10-16">Oct. 16, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">[PRESIDENT'S SPEECH TO LEGION CONVENTION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Horizon is Clearing (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Coolidge's speech at the recent American Legion convention proved to be a bombshell.</p>
   <p>The liberals up to the present time believed that Coolidge belonged to the Ku Klux Klan.</p>
   <p>Now the truth has come out.</p>
   <p>President Coolidge is not a member of the Klan, and not only that, he is absolutely opposed to it. Coolidge openly stated that the activities of the Klan are entirely opposed to the priniciples and ideals of the American government.</p>
   <p>The President made a very timely statement when he said that Americanism <pb facs="5422061_1_0452.jpg" n="2"/>cannot be judged among the immigrants by the boat they came on, or the length of time they have been here, or by asking them to what nationality or creed they belong.</p>
   <p>To judge Americanism one must consider the immigrants, and determine what contributions they have made to the development of the United States.</p>
   <p>The President also brought up the religious question. He said that commerce and industry did not inquire as to your church affiliation, and your worth was not judged by your creed, but was determined by the value of your personal service to the organization.</p>
   <p>President Coolidge, in his speech, informed the Klan that there was no room for religious controversies in America. Religious controversies have never been profitable to any nation. The nations that tolerate religious controversies will be led to ruin and destruction. This has been proven by history.</p>
   <p>President Coolidge and all true Americans are working to develop this <pb facs="5422061_1_0453.jpg" n="3"/>great nation and not to hold it back.</p>
   <p>The development of a nation is only possible when the social life of that nation is harmonious.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
