<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-08-30">Aug. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">What the Idea of the Military Show Is</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0688</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0688.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-08-30">Aug. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT THE IDEA OF THE MILITARY SHOW IS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This Military Show, which is going to be held in Grant Park beginning September 2, through September 15, is one of the customs or requirements of the United States government. There will be more than twenty carloads of war equipment put on exhibition. Cannons, rifles, airplanes, torpedoes, bombs, and many other articles of war taken from the German captives and those used by the Allies.</p>
   <p>The government, through the committee on Public Information, wishes to acquaint the people with its ideas on war. With this assurance, the War Department, the Secretary of Navy, and the Department of Finance are cooperating to make this Military Show possible. In addition, there will be representatives from the Allies and also representatives of many patriotic associations functioning in the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0689.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All these different organizations and individuals are affiliated with the local branch of the State Council of Defense, and a committee of one hundred businessmen,representing the city of Chicago. Samuel Insull has been chosen president of this organization. He is also president of the State Council of Defense.</p>
   <p>This Military Show is not being sponsored for monetary reasons because the committee has established a fund of $125,000 dollars which has been set aside in order that the government will not have to pay the expenses of this Show.</p>
   <p>This military Show will not be a theatrical performance, neither will it try to perform any miracles.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0690.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We do consider this Show as having more or less an educational value, with its aim to educate the people of the Middle West in the following:</p>
   <p>That this War is the peoples' war.</p>
   <p>That the Germans are fighting, the type of war equipment they use, and their treatment of women and children, and the results thereof.</p>
   <p>How our boys are fighting, what type of guns they use, and how they are taught to use them.</p>
   <p>The most important point is to teach the people why this war is being fought, and why it is the duty of every man, woman, and child, to aid the boys who are fighting for this country over there.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0691.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This Show is for the veterans' benefit. The Middle West has done its part very nobly in aiding this country in this War, but until we can see how our boys face death over there, we will not know what War means.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
