<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1926-11-11">Nov. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">To Budapest by Auto.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0639</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0639.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1926-11-11">Nov. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">TO BUDAPEST BY AUTO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.... Leaving France, we had two distinct impressions. One was that the roads were excellent, and that it is a country of hatreds.</p>
   <p>Passing Nancy and entering Alsace, we found more and more people speaking German. Only the children speak French.</p>
   <p>Reaching German soil, we lost the feeling of traveling in enemy country. We felt at home in Munich, the Bavarian capital, Of all the Germans, the Bavarians feel most sympathetic towards the Hungarians. The Bavarian newspapers criticised France's anti-Hungarian propaganda and when Coty, the perfume manufacturer,wrote an insulting article in his newspaper, they called him the "insane poisoner."</p>
   <p>From Munich to Vienna the roads were still good, but when the good roads ended, the friendly feeling toward the Hungarians ended too. Austria still feels hurt that Hungary was taken away from her.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0640.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Burgenlandmany people speak Hungarian. The same complaint can be heard everywhere: Since Burgenland was taken away from Hungary and given to Austria under Woodrow Wilson's fourteen points, the new master only takes from one, but doesn't spend anything on, its new possession.</p>
   <p>We entered Hungary at Sopron, which is only a few hours per automobile from Budapest. The news reached us that the nation is again divided in two factions on the question of "Who shall be king?" One faction, the Legitimists wants Otto, son of the late King Charles. This group is under the leadership of Count Albert Apponyi. The other group, under the leadership of Julius Goembos, secretary of war, would like to have Prince Albrecht, Hungary's Prince of Wales, on the throne.</p>
   <p>Hungary's outlook today can't be said to be the best, but they are learning to be real Magyars. With a Magyar heart and soul they are striving to attain happiness for all in our country.</p>
   <p>William M. Meyer, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
