<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-02-04">Feb. 4, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">I Want Employment</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ignatz Izsak (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0391</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0391.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-02-04">Feb. 4, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">I WANT EMPLOYMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ignatz Izsak (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We often hear from life's tired warriors that work is a burden, but, nevertheless, we always think of unemployment with fear.</p>
   <p>The whole world thinks of America as the home of work, where all who want to work need never be unemployed.</p>
   <p>In spite of this we noticed the other day in Chicago's Loop, one of America's growing and throbbing metropolises, men with children in their arms, carrying placards with this surprising inscription: "I want employment!"</p>
   <p>We were astounded at this hitherto unfamiliar sight and asked ourselves whether anything like this was possible in happy America!</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0392.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But yes, it is possible, America, in spite of being as wealthy as Croesus, is subjected to the fluctuating laws of production and consumption as is the poorest country.</p>
   <p>Especially Chicago, whose population increases by tens of thousands of transients from the north woods and mining regions, during the winter months, cannot absorb this floating surplus.</p>
   <p>However, these people are also entitled to live and work!</p>
   <p>La Fargue, the eccentric author, wrote a book in which he expounds the theory that man has the right to be lazy. If La Fargue were only right and if we could still breathe the carefree and idle air of paradise!</p>
   <p>It is too bad that we had to leave because of the serpent whose representatives of today still make their tongue felt.</p>
   <p>The immortal book of Madach says: "Man! Struggle and hope!"</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0393.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Intellectuals and laborers are participating equally in the struggle. If, therefore, we must all struggle, then we all have the right to work. And if anything or anyone hinders the use of men's hands, then something is fundamentally wrong.</p>
   <p>The great Lincoln said that all those who are born to this life have a right to insure their happiness through work.</p>
   <p>Accumulation of wealth, which places the power of giving employment in the hands of a few families, brings catastrophe nearer by leaps and bounds.</p>
   <p>On one side we see insane waste, and on the other poverty and the shadow of future unemployment.</p>
   <p>As a temporary solution we advocate public works by the states, which would act as a reservoir for those working hands not employed by private industry.</p>
   <p>The other solution would be the control of the accumulation of wealth.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0394.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The government should handle the surplus wealth and thus give the opportunity to have such work done which would put a stop to the aforementioned sight. [Editor's note: Men walking with "I want employment" signs.]</p>
   <p>History repeats itself! If statesmen and the lords of wealth in their blindness won't see and understand such events, they have only themselves to blame.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
