<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-04-03">Apr. 3, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">About the Mayoralty Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Dr. Erno Lowinger)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-04-03">Apr. 3, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE MAYORALTY ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial By Dr. Erno Lowinger)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The day of the election battle is nearing. Every conscientious voter must decide for whom he will cast his vote. He has to decide who is the man best qualified to manage the affairs of our city during the next four years....</p>
   <p>Naturally, prepossessing campaign speakers endeavor to make up our minds, but the intelligent voters, the politically ripe citizens like the thousands of Chicago Hungarians, will not be sidetracked.....</p>
   <p>The fact is that the good reputation of our city is ruined. This is regrettable but true. It is also a fact that the murders of two hundred eighty-six gangsters are still unsolved. Not a day passes without a mysterious gang killing. Chicago today is known the world over as the home of gangsters.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0608.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Nobody can deny that this reputation is detrimental to Chicago and its population. It is damaging, both materially and spiritually. The damage is material because of the number of visitors lost to our city, since thousands of people are afraid to visit Chicago because of the possibility of falling victims to stray bullets. As a result, we lose millions of dollars annually and, although the loss is felt most directly by hotels, restaurants, and department stores, in the end we all feel it, too.</p>
   <p>New factories shun Chicago and build their plants elsewhere because the Saturday pay roll robberies have become so common here that the personal safety and financial security of the industrialists are at stake.</p>
   <p>This causes thousands of people to lose work opportunities. At a time when unemployment is so great, this adds to misery.</p>
   <p>We are on the threshold of the World's Fair. In two years there will be a <pb facs="5422061_1_0609.jpg" n="3"/>monumental exposition in Chicago. Not only the visitors, but the exhibitors as well, are terrified by the thought that they will have to come to Chicago.</p>
   <p>Please do not jump to the conclusion that the writer is prejudiced against Mayor Thompson or that he holds him solely responsible for the bad reputation of Chicago and for the unsolved gangster murders....</p>
   <p>The writer is convinced that, if it were up to Thompson, he would have all the gangsters behind bars and the reputation of Chicago would be the best.</p>
   <p>However, the consensus of opinion, regardless of political partisanship, is that the Thompson regime is at fault and must end if conditions are to improve....</p>
   <p>To these material losses, resulting from the bad reputation of Chicago, we must add the moral and spiritual losses. Our children read nothing in the newspapers <pb facs="5422061_1_0610.jpg" n="4"/>but accounts of banditry, murder, and the heroic deeds of the gangsters. And, while these gangsters violate the laws flagrantly, our children fill the prisons for minor offenses.</p>
   <p>The continuous crime wave created such a noxious atmosphere in Chicago that even small children play "hold-up" and "give-them-a-ride" games.</p>
   <p>This must be stopped on April 7, by electing a different man to the office of mayor, thus breaking away from the past and all its troubles and sins....</p>
   <p>The mayor is responsible for the police because he appoints the police chief. If the police are corrupt, the mayor is held morally responsible....</p>
   <p>[Anton] Cermak's strong and energetic personality will bring order in the ranks of the police. He declared in one of his speeches that he will be personally responsible for the efficiency of the police.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0611.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We taxpayers know that city taxes have grown year after year and the we have to pay these taxes out of our earnings.</p>
   <p>To curb the thoughtless extravagance of city officials and to reduce our taxes, we must elect a man whose record in the County proves that he is thrifty and that he saved the taxpayers' money.....</p>
   <p>As noted in the beginning of this article, there is no question now about party affiliation. The only consideration now is the future of Chicago, the personal safety of its citizens, and the good reputation of the city.</p>
   <p>The writer does not wish to convince any ardent Republican at this time that he is wrong. Let him ponder over the fruit of the Hoover Republican administration, the misery of the ever-increasing army of the unemployed. If he approves of it, let him be happy.</p>
   <p>Lo and behold the Republican prosperity they promised for 1928!</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0612.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We Hungarian-born American citizens must not allow cheap politicans to mislead us by mixing into this purely Chicago election any reference to our mother country's grievances.</p>
   <p>If the writer would think, even for a moment, that the situation of the Hungarians in Chicago or anywhere else would be worse if Cermak is elected mayor, he would drop his pen and his mouth would be silent. But this is not so.</p>
   <p>That Thompson was born in Boston and Cermak was six months old when his parents brought him to America from Bohemia, can't be the deciding factor in the election of mayor.....</p>
   <p>We are all sincere American citizens here who have rights and duties, and we must practice these rights and duties on April 7.</p>
   <p>Every sane-thinking Hungarian-born American citizen should vote for Cermak and the Democratic condidates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
