<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-06-03">June 3, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Do Not Kill by Ignacio Izsak</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0614</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0614.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-06-03">June 3, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">DO NOT KILL by Ignacio Izsak</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is an amazing phenomenon of mankind that since Cain killed Abel the spirit of destruction and murder has prevailed.</p>
   <p>From one end of the world to the other we see the struggle to spread the Christian gospel, and at the same time we note that parallel to these teachings, those countries that refer oftenest to the Prophet of Nazareth, are the ones planning general butchery.</p>
   <p>What humbug! What pretense!</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0615.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The slaughtering instinct does not apply to certain countries only, it can be produced by class wars due to economic interests. There have been countless cases, when labor leaders or passionate agitators, who exposed the exploitation of workers by heartless employers, were put to death through false evidence or perjury of witnesses.</p>
   <p>There is an obvious case now in America. Sacco and Vanzetti, who successfully led the strike of the Patterson, N. J. textile workers seven years ago, [sic] are the victims of "manufactured evidence."</p>
   <p>They are charged with the holdup and murder of a cashier. The evidence was only circumstantial, but the judge, who is partial to the owners of the textile factories, condemned them to death.</p>
   <p>The state has not dared to execute them yet, because American public opinion and sentiment are aroused.</p>
   <p>The case is in the hands of Governor Fuller now, and it is up to him to <pb facs="5422061_1_0616.jpg" n="3"/>grant a reprieve or order a retrial.</p>
   <p>Chicago Hungarians, with foresight, should take part in this movement also, to inform the world that they will form a bulwark, against the repetition of the sin of Cain whenever anyone, no matter where, is threatened with "retributive justice."</p>
   <p>We have received information that a committee is handling this case and we advise all Hungarians to go to the mass meetings in large numbers to show where our sympathies are.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
