<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1931-03-29">Mar. 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Rakoczy or Lenin?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1931-03-29">Mar. 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">RAKOCZY OR LENIN?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hungarian Bolsheviks also know Montecuccoli's wise saying, "to make war, money, money and more money is necessary" and although their warfare against organized society is considered banditry, they need money, especially that which is in someone else's pocket.</p>
   <p>For a while the apostles of Lenin contrived to get money through their newspaper the Elore (Forward), but lately they couldn't get enough so they concentrated their efforts on the Self Culture Club and the Workers' Sick Benefit Society, which they ruined in a short time.</p>
   <p>The funds of the Communist agitators are getting low, so they have <pb facs="5422061_1_0428.jpg" n="2"/>invented a new money making scheme. They have selected as their next victim the Rakoczy Sick Benefit Society. They smuggled a few Lenin idolizers in as members who tried to sow the seeds of discontent, but without success. Then they started a whispering campaign against the officers of the Rakoczy with the intention of getting them suspended from office and enabling them to put their satellites in their place. They have attacked through their paper, the Elore, Joseph Vasas, secretary, in particular.</p>
   <p>We trust the good judgment of the members, and know that they will rid themselves of these bolshevik wolves, but the trouble is that these wolves are in sheep's clothing, and are hard to recognize.</p>
   <p>It is our duty to warn the members of the Rakoczy against this attempt of the bolsheviks to undermine the peace of the organization. If they are allowed to do their destructive work, they will debase the memory <pb facs="5422061_1_0429.jpg" n="3"/>of our national hero Rakoczy. We cannot allow the Hungarian workers to rally around the bolshevik flag and let themselves be misled by the agitators.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
