<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-02-18">Feb. 18, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Transylvania under New Rule</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0648</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0648.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-02-18">Feb. 18, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">TRANSYLVANIA UNDER NEW RULE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Tribune learned that a noted attorney of Transylvania is here visiting his nephew, Dr. Andre Romoin, our well-known fellow patriot. The reporter of The Tribune was sent to interview the distinguished visitor. Doctor Hirsh, a very affable gentleman, answered the doorbell. After the usual introduction, the reporter began his interview. On the question as to the conditions in Transylvania, the reporter was given all the information necessary regarding Transylvania under Rumanian rule.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0649.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The interview was in part, as follows: "If you want detailed information," said the distinguished gentleman, "I must start from the beginning of the Rumanian rule in Transylvania, when General Geresen's Division marched in to Klossterburg. This was a very disgusting sight. The soldiers wore several kinds of uniforms. Some of them wore home-spun peasant garb. Some wore boots, some wore shoes, and some wore peasant sandals, while others were bare foot. Their horses were sick with scabies.</p>
   <p>The important thing to do first was to clothe the tattered militia. The next movement was the organization of the government Council, which issued a call to all Hungarian officials to take an oath of allegiance to the new <pb facs="5422061_1_0650.jpg" n="3"/>government. As a result of this call, the Saikels, who claim to be descendants of King Attila, were the first to take the oath. The others, Magyars and Jews, refused to take the oath, because they believed that the Rumanian rule would not last long.</p>
   <p>We cannot talk about public law, because there is none in a country like Rumania, which is governed by decrees.</p>
   <p>Speaking of corruption, is putting it mildly as it is practiced in Rumania. Everybody is practicing it from the lowest policeman to the highest official. To illustrate, I will relate an event which happened to me.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0651.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A Provisional secretary's office was established by the Rumanian government in Transylvania. The duty of this office was to issue permits for carrying provisions from one town to the other, even for his own consumption. The price of the permit was from ten to one thousand Crowns. It depended on the length of service of the party on duty at the Secretary's door. If the policeman were a new man; he would be satisfied with ten Crowns, but if he had been employed there for a longer time, he would have learned the game and would not accept less than one hundred crowns.</p>
   <p>The legal rules of the court are many. If two Rumanians are involved in a law-suit, as defendant and plaintiff, there is a regular legal trial. If only one of the litigants is Rumanian, the latter wins the case. If two non-Rumanians are the litigants, he wins, who pays most. I know of one case <pb facs="5422061_1_0652.jpg" n="5"/>in particular where one of my clients received three different decisions by three Ministerial decrees.</p>
   <p>I had a peculiar case when I applied for my passport.</p>
   <p>One forenoon, I wanted to see the Police captain regarding my passport, and, as a friend of the Police Captain, I thought it unnecessary to bow to the policeman standing at the entrance and ask permission from him. As I entered, the officer ran after me, trying to stop me, but ignoring his warning, I continued on my way. Then he grabbed me by my coat and rudely pulled me back. I, of course, became enraged, and slapped his face.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0653.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Naturally, I was arrested, and I had to use all my influence to save myself from the usual "twenty-five on the rack."</p>
   <p>Except for a few cases, there was no political persecution. Everybody had to keep his opinion to himself, because if some one criticized the government in the presence of a policeman or gendarme, he received the customary "twenty-five sticks on the rack" without any legal proceedings.</p>
   <p>The Rumanian people of Transylvania did not get what they expected from Rumanian rule. The intelligent and the richer people hoped to be given leadership. The poorer classes wanted land and expected an improvement in the general economic situation. Both classes, were disappointed, and are thoroughly dissatisfied now."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
