<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1933-04-14">Apr. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">[The Question of Pure Hungarians]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0179</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0179.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1933-04-14">Apr. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">[THE QUESTION OF PURE HUNGARIANS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is again a storm in our inner Hungarian circles in Chicago, and not of the type that would be to the advantage of the Hungarians in the city. We learn, to our sorrow, that some of our leaders have turned into knights of the dark and are wandering astray. This is injurious not only to the Hungarians of Chicago but to the Hungarians of America as well.</p>
   <p>We learned that there are Hungarians among us who would like to plant Fascism in the ranks of our people in Chicago, and they do that in the most cunning manner, showing themselves to the world as innocent lambs while endeavoring to raise partition wall between Hungarian and Hungarian.</p>
   <p>A man of character usually comes to the open with his colors--whatever they may be--and does not play hide and seek with his convictions. It seems that not all pure-blooded Hungarians know that cunning is a trait never present in the Hungarian character.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0180.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There happens to exist among us a Hungarian who, without any hesitation has had the temerity to tell one of his countrymen that one of his acquaintances is not a Hungarian at all, and speaks Hungarian only for the simple reason that he can speak no other language.</p>
   <p>Now, this is a shameful--one could even say, an idiotic--statement, for if that "real" Hungarian were to seek--even in Hungary itself--for pure Hungarians, he would find mighty few of them. In all Europe, Hungary is probably the only country where the people is so melted together from so many nations that one, could hardly, even with the help of a lamp, find a person of pure Hungarian origin.</p>
   <p>The fact that some one is not a Fascist or Anti-Semite does not necessarily mean that he is not Hungarian. On the contrary, in the eyes of any intelligent and sober-thinking cultured person, he is not only a real Hungarian but a perfect and straight-spined man as well.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0181.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Maybe this compatriot of ours, who is taking the role of knight, does not know what our greatest Hungarian [Count Istvan Szechenyi] has said: "There are so few of us, that we ought to pardon even the patricide".</p>
   <p>Those who intend to take active part in the public life of the Hungarian-Americans must, in the first place, know that the interests of the latter demand that there ought to exist the strongest possible link between them and should refrain from building walls of separation between us. The existence and the survival of the Hungarian-Americans depend on our effort to draw as many Hungarian-speaking and Hungarian-feeling persons as possible into our midst, as otherwise extinction will be the fate of Hungarian life in the future. It would be well for those who favor Fascism to keep this in mind.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
