<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1928-10-07">Oct. 7, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Chicago Tribune's Jubilee Issue</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 3 a (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1928-10-07">Oct. 7, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHICAGO TRIBUNE'S JUBILEE ISSUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czechs, it must be admitted, know all about the art of propaganda. The best example is the European issue of the Chicago Tribune in honor of the tenth anniversary of the Czecho-Slovak Republic.</p>
   <p>There was a great exhibition in Brunne celebrating the anniversary. Of the many exhibits the most colorful was the Jubilee number of the Chicago Tribune. The border of the paper was white, blue, and red, and on the cover page the doublestailed lion with the apostolic cross and the three mounds on its chest appeared.</p>
   <p>The contents of the paper are historical anodynes. We read among other articles in this propaganda the following:</p>
   <p>"A thousand years ago the nomad Magyars wedged themselves between two brother Slav nations.....When the Bohemian monarchy was defeated, the Slovaks fell under Magyar rule....Under the Przemyslidas, the Czechs were a defensive pillar for <pb facs="5422061_1_0216.jpg" n="2"/>Christian culture. They were members of the German-Roman kingdom and defended it against the barbarians of the East.....Vaclav II. ruled Hungary too.....The Czech kings became the victims of the jealousy of their Hungarian and German neighbors, they who allied themselves against the Czechs, and in 1306 the Hapsburgs replaced the ruling family of Przemyslidas."</p>
   <p>From the religious standpoint, of course, they write against Catholicism and praise their national religion:</p>
   <p>"Western Christianity, founded by Wycliff, had an understanding apostle, Jan Huss, who in 1415 died on the pyre by the order of the Constantine Synod, becoming the martyr of the Czech Church."</p>
   <p>The Donne at Kosice is called the fourteenth-century gem of Czecho-Slovak Gothic architecture.</p>
   <p>Of Michael Munkacsi (great Hungarian painter) they write:</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0217.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The most distinguished representative of Czecho-Slovak art, son of Mukacero, Michael Munkacsi, absorbed the love of political and intellectual freedom in the Czecho-Slovakian atmosphere."</p>
   <p>The contributors to this jubilee issue are Masaryk, Benes, Furlinger (Ambassador at Washington), Osusky (Ambassador at Paris), Arne Novak, Msgr. Sramek, Marshal Foch, Myron Herrick (American ambassador ), and Lewis Einstein (American ex-ambassador).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
