<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1934-07-22">July 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Two Chicago University Professors on Hungarian Culture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0801</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0801.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1934-07-22">July 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">TWO CHICAGO UNIVERSITY PROFESSORS ON HUNGARIAN CULTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. John Shapley and Dr. Alexander Shusko, professors of the Chicago University, have, in their research, come to the conclusion that long ago European civilization was not exclusively Latin and Greek, but was affected greatly by the people of Asia, particularly, the Turanians and Magyars.</p>
   <p>The distinguished professors made an intensive study in other lines of the culture of Hungary in the 11th Century. The Royal Crown shows unmistakably Eastern art. These eminent professors believe that the superior culture of the ancient Magyars will soon be recognized, evidenced by the important data which has been collected for years.</p>
   <p>This is the aim of Doctor Shapley and Doctor Shusko. Last Monday, they <pb facs="5422061_1_0802.jpg" n="2"/>invited some Hungarian leaders to confer with and urge their cooperation, and also to show results of their research to date.</p>
   <p>The activities of these two internationally known professors have met with little appreciation shown by the Hungarians, but we hope that their interest will be aroused soon, because, from a Hungarian point of view, this work is fostering a better understanding.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
