<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1935-03-10">Mar. 10, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Today, Yesterday, Day before Yesterday</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0726</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0726.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1935-03-10">Mar. 10, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">TODAY, YESTERDAY, DAY BEFORE YESTERDAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States is a peculiar country. It was founded on democratic principles and has set an example for all nations who fought for liberty and took their government in their hands. On the basis of these democratic ideas, this country created the Congress, consisting of two Houses, so that the Upper House, the Senate, may curb the enthusiasm of the House of Representatives. Administering justice over these bodies, it created the Supreme court, and delegated to this body composed of nine men, the privilege to nullify laws enacted by the Congress, if they feel so inclined.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0727.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Common sense dictates that Congress should know what it is doing because there are enough members in it capable of performing their duties, and they have ample time to thrash out thoroughly what is advantageous for this country. In the United States, however, this is not enough. The validity and constitutionality of the laws are decided by the nine men of the Supreme Court.</p>
   <p>If, in the gold decision, it had not happened that five votes were for the measure and four against it, in other words, if one man would have had different ideas, there would have been chaos in the financial affairs of the country. There is enough trouble at present about the constitutionality of the NRA and the New Deal.</p>
   <p>We are up to our necks in debate. Congress has passed laws which it believes will restore the country to normal, but it seems that the laws cannot <pb facs="5422061_1_0728.jpg" n="3"/>be made a vital part of the country.</p>
   <p>Congress supported the workers in the NRA measure, and insured them the right of collective bargaining. This unhoped for victory gladdened the workers' hearts, but their joys were short-lived. They see that this law has made many enemies for them. The government meant well, but could not carry it through.</p>
   <p>The workers should not lose hope. The road to progress has always been slow, but sure. As slavery was abolished, so will the modern industrial slavery not last long, no matter how the nine men of the Supreme Court decide.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
