<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1935-08-09">Aug. 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Voice of the People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1935-08-09">Aug. 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">VOICE OF THE PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have read in the columns of the Daily News what our compatriot, Frank Bologh, wrote about the deplorable situation of the Hungarian minority in Czecho-Slovakia.</p>
   <p>An answer to this was inevitable, from the standpoint of the Czechs, who refuted the allegations of Bologh. So far, this would be in order, but we did not count on a Hungarian who would use the columns of the Daily News to minimize and justify the acts of the Czechs.</p>
   <p>The person who wrote the article did not have enough courage to sign his name, but camouflages his identity in the signature of "Mr. Hungarian-American." We believe that the anonymous author is not a Hungarian, but <pb facs="5422061_1_0156.jpg" n="2"/>a Czech, who is trying to side-track American public opinion.</p>
   <p>We would be pleased to know that our guess is correct, because we would be sorry to think that a real Hungarian would quote our enemy. Palacky, Czech Historian, states that the Czechs only received the land that was rightfully theirs for thousands of years. On the basis of this adulterated history, the restoration of the Phoenician empire could be demanded, too.</p>
   <p>It is generally known that when the Magyars settled in Hungary, there were Slav tribes in upper Hungary, but they did not form a state and consequently had no government. Under the rule of the Magyars, they became an organized part of the government of Hungary. The stories of their persecution is not true, because the contrary is proved by the fact that during a thousand years of Hungarian "oppression" they were allowed to retain free use of their <pb facs="5422061_1_0157.jpg" n="3"/>language. What did the Slavs have to do with the Tartar scourge, only "Mr. Hungarian-American" could tell us.</p>
   <p>The Czechs in Northern Hungary would want the Hungarians to be resigned to their fate and bow their heads to Czech rule. To those who think such will ever be true, then mother country, race, and nationalism, mean nothing. They would embrace the universe but would spurn their mother. We do not know who the anonymous "Mr. Hungarian-American" is; if he is not a Czech dupe, but a so-called Hungarian, he deserves the condemnation of all true Magyars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
