<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-04-05">Apr. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Why I Do Not Join the Hungarian Loyalty League by B. Shenk.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0703</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0703.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-04-05">Apr. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHY I DO NOT JOIN THE HUNGARIAN LOYALTY LEAGUE by B. SHENK.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I confess that I do not write these lines with pleasure. It would be more pleasant to write about the opposite subject, Why I Joined The Hungarian American Loyalty League. But I feel that as a conscientious American citizen I cannot enter into the Loyalty League.</p>
   <p>I cannot accept the loyalty of the Hungarian League. It is not the kind of loyalty which would satisfy our citizens. The loyalty of the Hungarian league is without any conscience and rests exclusively on the servile feeling. We must not be loyal from a sense of humiliation or from gratitude as the Hungarian league proclaims, but from the conviction that the United States defends, in fact world justice so many times offended by Germany, and her allies. These latter powers have oppressed and abused small nations in selfish and universally dangerous political interests, and justice requires that the crimes committed by Germany against the other nations be punished.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0704.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So I am not loyal because the Hungarians are permitted to continue their work. The government of the United States did not even prevent the Germans from working. I am not loyal because the Hungarians did not have to register, as the Germans had to do. It would not be a cause for disloyalty. I am not loyal because the independence of Hungary depends exclusively upon the victory of the United States as stated by the loyalty league.</p>
   <p>All these are false pretexts to loyalty, the teaching of which does not serve the purpose of educating the masses of Hungarian Americans, who in Hungary and here are influenced by the Hungarian Junkers who are allies of the German Junkers. The Hungarians need to become free thinking men who are able to understand that it is in common interest to humanity to crush the rule of the European Junkers, and that this is especially in the interest of those who suffered under this system.</p>
   <p>Without any view of my citizenship, I am loyal because America did not require <pb facs="5422061_1_0705.jpg" n="3"/>this war. Germany pressed it upon America with provocations and deeds, face slapping every international law. During the first three years of the war Hungarian Americans were taught that the responsibility for the war did not rest on Germany and her allies, that was British propaganda, against the French and Italians because they did not lay their arms down before the Germans. They stopped this, but that alone does not satisfy me.</p>
   <p>I expected the loyalty league to restore with educational work the sympathetic feeling which the Hungarians have always felt for the French,British,and Italians. It would be a very easy task, only it must be explained that the war is caused by Germany. The wrongs committed by the Germans towards the other nations must be shown. If the loyalty league would do this educational work, to disrupt every ideological, psychological communication between the Hungarian Americans and the German Imperialist. If the loyalty league influenced by this higher view would put in the mind of the Hungarian American the principles laid down by President Wilson, I would join as a member of the league without any hesitation, but I am not the man to deny the real cause to <pb facs="5422061_1_0706.jpg" n="4"/>confess loyalty with pretexts, helping with it to cover the truth from the American Hungarians.</p>
   <p>In short I am loyal because it is in my personal,and in general human interest, that America and her allies gain victory over Germany.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
