<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-03-28">Mar. 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The New Hungarian Revolution</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0677</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0677.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-03-28">Mar. 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW HUNGARIAN REVOLUTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The forces of revolution that have shaken poor old Hungary have hurt the heart of every son and daughter of Hungary throughout the world. Naturally, we Americans of Hungarian descent, are hurt as a consequence of the sorrowful plight of our native land. We do not want to apologize for this terrible plunge that she has taken, as we are only distant observers of this great tragedy. Justification she hardly needs.</p>
   <p>As a drowning man grasps at a straw, Hungary, as a last resort for self-preservation, was driven into the arms of Bolshevism. Pressed in upon all sides by her enemies, lacking food and fuel, the approaching peace seemed to <pb facs="5422061_1_0678.jpg" n="2"/>be worse than all the horrors of the unfortunate War. Her ancient territory taken from her, stripped of all her economic wealth, tied down with old debts, she could not resign herself to be the broken shadow of her glorious, but stormy past.</p>
   <p>After a thousand years of continuous fighting to attain a place in the world, bleeding for, and defending Christianity of the western civilization against the heathen hordes of Tartars and Turks, with all the grave errors that she may have committed, she deserves something better than to be destroyed to the core.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0679.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us hope that this desperate step Hungary has taken will open the eyes of the world, and stimulate the realization of an honorable peace which is founded upon the well-known and universally accepted Wilsonian principles.</p>
   <p>In whatever direction events may develop and terminate in this great European turmoil, I have found assurance for Americans of Hungarian descent. In this immense turmoil abroad, the heart and soul of the American people responded to defend the cause. America understands the sad plight of Hungary, and places the blame where it belongs. To illustrate this point, I refer to two of our greatest exponents of American public opinion: The Chicago Daily Tribune, and the New York World. The first representing western thought, and the second,eastern reflection. The former representing the Republican anti- <pb facs="5422061_1_0680.jpg" n="4"/>administration sentiment, the latter the Democratic pro-administration sentiment. Both great in their influence, and outspoken in their views, the consensus of opinion of both papers is surprisingly uniform, fair-minded, and just on the question of this new Hungarian revolution. They do not condemn Hungary for declaring war again, and joining the Russian Bolshevik movement, but they clearly point to the French imperialistic tendencies, and to the outrageous claims of Hungary's surrounding enemies, the Czechoslovaks, the Serbians, and the Rumanians, as the undermining momentum which caused the explosion in Hungary.</p>
   <p>This honest expression of the American public's opinion demonstrates that Americans harbor no feeling of revenge or animosity toward Hungary, but quite to the contrary, there is an understanding and unbiased opinion here.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0681.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This also should be a lesson to Hungarians all over this great country, and should inspire us to more earnest devotion, more genuine patriotism, and unflinching faith in the United States.</p>
   <p>Note: This editorial was written for the Magyar Tribune, by Dr. Ernest Loewinger, who is a resident of Chicago, and a tireless worker in the interest of the Chicago-Hungarians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
