<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-09-04">Sept. 4, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">About the Liberal Resolutions of the Verhovay Aid Society's Conventio</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Dr. Erno Lowinger)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0184</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0184.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-09-04">Sept. 4, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE LIBERAL RESOLUTIONS OF THE VERHOVAY AID SOCIETY'S CONVENTIO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Dr. Erno Lowinger)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The writer, while on his vacation, received word about the national convention of the Verhovay Aid Society from the editor of the Magyar Tribune.....The Magyar Tribune has for twenty years been a frank, consistent, and fearless advocate of progressive ideas, and the writer has had many occasions to fight against anti-Semitism in Magyar-America during the past twenty-five years. Therefore, we feel that it is our duty to discuss the resolutions passed at the national convention of the Verhovay Aid Society at Pittsburgh. [Translator's note: The Verhovay Aid Society is a national organization with about 30,000 members, of which number there are from two to five thousand members in Chicago. The Society holds a national convention once every four years.]</p>
   <p>We, as loyal and sworn citizens of America, believe that the monarchial form <pb facs="5422061_1_0185.jpg" n="2"/>of government is antiquated, and is merely a superfluous, superficial, pompous nuisance to intelligent, mentally balanced citizens. The republican form of government, with the secret ballot, giving to the individual a wider field for his ambitions, is more suited to our taste.</p>
   <p>The Hapsburg dynasty--which ruled our mother country for centuries--was responsible for the fact that during its reign the Hungarians were the vassals of the feudal lords. The Hapsburg family is responsible for the dismemberment of Hungary at Trianon, and for the fact that Hungary, alone of the countries of Europe, is operated under a feudal system for the exclusive benefit of the landowners and clergy. It is the duty of all good Americans to protest against the restoration of the Hapsburgs. It is even more a duty for us, the Hungarian-born, to lift our voices against the restoration of the Hapsburg Dynasty so strongly that they will be heard all over the world and especially in Hungary. ....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0186.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This was done by the convention of the Verhovay Society in August at Pittsburgh.....It was a noble gesture. It was an honest American demonstration.....</p>
   <p>The other important decision of the convention was--by a majority vote of the delegates--that hereafter any Hungarian-American may become a member regardless of his religion. This means that the Verhovay has discarded its forty-five-year-old anti-Semitic tradition, its Verhovay-Istoczy heritage of the Middle Ages, and has adopted the liberal, progressive American spirit, opening its gates to all Hungarians, including the Hungarian Jews.....</p>
   <p>The spirit of hatred of Gyula Verhovay and Gyozo Istoczy, which pervaded Hungarian-American social life, was a dark blot and a paralyzing influence,a barrier to co-operation.</p>
   <p>We have been familiar with the intrigue and selfish motives which prompted <pb facs="5422061_1_0187.jpg" n="4"/>the toleration of this spirit of the Middle Ages in the Verhovay Aid Society for the past forty-five years. However, the losers by this arrangement were not the Hungarian Jews..... In every American city with a large Hungarian population,there were liberal Hungarian sick benefit societies that did not raise an artificial barrier between Hungarians and Hungarians; the Hungarian Jews in America were not denied their place in the social life of their Christian countrymen. Naturally, those who have wished to become members of the great Verhovay Aid Society have their chance now.....</p>
   <p>What causes the greatest pleasure to us in this resolution is the fact that it is a moral victory, with a definite spiritual value. We are glad that the older, calmer Hungarians' way of thinking has reached this layer of Hungarian-American society. We are glad that the liberal American spirit is gaining ground.....We are glad that the ideas of Gyula Verhovay and Gyorgy Istoczy, which came in the eighties, have at last been outlawed.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0188.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It is not easy for any nation's sons to come to the conclusion that in the end anti-Semitism is an evil and stupid political practice.....But to introduce anti-Semitism and make it permanent in the social life of American Hungarians is a sin. There are so few of us and we mean so little here that only unscrupulous, selfish climbers would think of disrupting our unity by advocating hatred. Anti-Semitism among the Hungarians of America means the weakening of our strength; it is against Hungarian interests.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian-American Jews have proved their love and loyalty toward our mother country.....We Hungarian-Americans of the Hebrew religion may become loyal and honest citizens of this great country, but when singing the "Star-Spangled Banner" and "My Country"--the national anthems--we include "God Bless the Magyars". Anyone who disturbs this unselfish and sacred sentiment with incitement to hatred on religious grounds does not deserve to be a citizen of America.</p>
   <p>We Hungarians in America are a minority among a hundred and twenty million <pb facs="5422061_1_0189.jpg" n="6"/>people, and we should be able to understand and sympathize with the five hundred thousand Jews among the eight million Hungarians in Hungary, where they live and if necessary die for their country.....The injustice of the Verhovay Society which for forty-five years has barred Hungarian Jews, has hurt.....</p>
   <p>And now, because the Verhovay Aid Society has put an end to this practice, we greet it with all the warmth of our hearts, and would like to wring the hand of each delegate and thank him for casting his vote for this liberal and progressive resolution.....The writer's sacred conviction is that God will bless the Verhovay Aid Society's work.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
