<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1922-10-08">Oct. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Class War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1922-10-08">Oct. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CLASS WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the future, we will discuss the problems of workers in our editorials from time to time. The Otthon recognizes the importance of social progress in this century, and especially in the next decade. We are glad to note that our worker readers are concerned about this subject. We would be sorry indeed if they would not think about it at all. It is too bad that many people are not able to think independently. These people try to cover up their ignorance by indifference. Our aim is to interpret the real meaning of articles pertaining to labor and social problems.</p>
   <p>Marxism Advocates Class War</p>
   <p>Marx groups men into two classes: the bourgeoisie and proletariat. This is the starting point of the Marx theory, and it is natural that <pb facs="5422061_1_0460.jpg" n="2"/>we, too, will begin our interpretation at this point. We wish to explain first what logic is. It is the method of thinking correctly in order to arrive at a definite conclusion about a given question. Wisdom begins where we are forced to admit our ignorance.</p>
   <p>We do not say that grouping men into two distinct classes is illogical, nevertheless, let us look into this matter closely.</p>
   <p>The time is past when there were historically privileged classes, aristocratic and bourgeois classes, who had privileges not enjoyed by the peasant class. In these times of economic and political equality, they cannot be divided into two groups from this standpoint, but they can be grouped according to wealth and poverty. However, where does wealth end and poverty begin? How many men are there, especially in America, who were poor yesterday and rich today? Is it right, therefore, to war against the capitalistic class?</p>
   <p>Since class distinction was abolished between men, there is no need <pb facs="5422061_1_0461.jpg" n="3"/>for class hatred, because there is so much inter-mingling that it would be a war of brothers.</p>
   <p>If we study class mingling among the immigrants, we find that their children are skilled workers in factories, also some are independent industrialists, merchants, judges, engineers, lawyers, and professors. The proletariat of Marx has progressed and entered the bourgeoisie. The children of the poorest fathers have become rich.</p>
   <p>After this interpretation, we ask is it not true that those who incite class hatred become the supporters of fraternal strife?</p>
   <p>It is another question why wealth is unequally distributed, and whether the teachings of Marx can serve as a remedy. This phase of the question will be discussed at a future date.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
