<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-06-01">June 1, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">About the World's Fair</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0227</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0227.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-06-01">June 1, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE WORLD'S FAIR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The World's Fair that will be held in Chicago in 1933 is arousing the interest of certain groups to a great degree. Even the Hungarians have announced their intention of officially participating in it. It is a good thing that all national groups are so anxious to do their share in this great enterprise, because it is to our mutual advantage. Chicago is our home, and the significance of the World's Fair is appreciated by the residents as well as by the city.</p>
   <p>We wish to advise the Chicago Hungarian participants that they should not overestimate their ability as they have done in the past. The manufacturing, commercial and cultural attainments of Hungary can best be exhibited by the Hungarian government. It has, no doubt, already made an appropriation for this purpose, and since this will be quite an important Hungarian undertaking, the Hungarian government will send its own representatives over here to arrange its exhibit.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0228.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago Hungarians are an integral part of the population of this city. They can show what they have produced and how far they have progressed in the last century. The manner in which we will show our accomplishments will be the task of the Hungarian committee to discover. We do not believe that we should promise, either in the American press or elsewhere, great or impossible things and in the end exhibit a smoky Csarda (inn or tavern), with a few gypsies and a few Hungarian-costumed couples dancing the Csardas, as representative of the accomplishments of Chicago Hungarians.</p>
   <p>In all probability, as was done at other fairs, a day will be assigned to each national group. To prepare for this one day is the most important duty of the Chicago Hungarian group. We offer a modest suggestion to the Hungarian committee. Hungarian music and song would be the most effective contribution of our group. Five years is ample time to train a good chorus and a Hungarian symphony orchestra.....</p>
   <p>As this great movement is neither political nor religious, let us add that everyone should be asked to take part. All the churches, political, social, <pb facs="5422061_1_0229.jpg" n="3"/>cultural, and sick benefit organizations should unite in an effort to produce something worthwhile....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
