<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-09-28">Sept. 28, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Hungarian Artists Hide Behind the Modern Social Barricade</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Arthur D. Miko</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0218</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0218.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-09-28">Sept. 28, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">HUNGARIAN ARTISTS HIDE BEHIND THE MODERN SOCIAL BARRICADE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Arthur D. Miko</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The problem of the Chicago Hungarian artists cannot be solved by one or two individuals. It concerns all those who are today groping in a strange intellectual sphere with their fantastic ideas.</p>
   <p>There are artists who are equal to the task of developing Hungarian culture, but they emerge from under the cloak of individualism only when their interests or material gains are concerned.</p>
   <p>All men are not alike, but I must admit that it hurts my feelings to see [that while our artists remain aloof, other] artists who have come from other countries become accustomed to American ways and are respected by their own people as well as by the Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0219.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These artists are natives of Russia, Czechoslovakia, Poland, Sweden, and Jugoslavia. But where are the Hungarian artists? I see the ruined remnants of Hungarian artistry behind the barricade.....</p>
   <p>I view with horror the Hungarians around me who submissively suffer indignities at the hands of inferior artists.</p>
   <p>We must defend our standards, because we are not at such a low level that we can be disparaged publicly.....</p>
   <p>Let us not allow Hungarian false pride to dog our footsteps. It is too bad that we meet some artists in American cultural circles who admit their nationality only because it serves their interests. We, too, could deny our Hungarian birth with the help of a thorough knowledge of the American language, but it is our duty to be true to our mother country and at the same time endeavor to make a favorable impression on Americans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
