<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-11-07">Nov. 7, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Open Forum</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-11-07">Nov. 7, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">OPEN FORUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(The publishers of the Magyar Tribune do not accept responsibility for items in this column.)</p>
   <p>A Statement</p>
   <p>To the Editors:</p>
   <p>In your previous issue, in the Open Forum, a malicious letter was published against the Chicago Hungarian Workers' Chorus; it was signed by the I. W. W. and the United Protective League. The Chicago Hungarian Workers' Chorus, at their business meeting of November 3, discussed this matter and decided to reject the accusations and brand the signatories of the letter as slanderers.</p>
   <p>What despicable depravity is needed to request respectable Hungarian organizations to boycott the Workers' Chorus! They (the I. W. W. and United <pb facs="5422061_1_0333.jpg" n="2"/>Protective League) are protesting because we did not support their political interests. The Workers' Chorus became the center of such undesirable publicity because they did not support the selfish self-interests of this group. The Industrial Worker (Bermunkas) acknowledges that they needed the money (raised by showing moving pictures of the Hungarian revolution) for Garbai's fare. They lie when they say that the Workers' Chorus is a Communist organization and they lie when they state that the Workers' Chorus uses its money for party politics and for drunken orgies. Not one cent of the Workers' Chorus was spent on anything except the salary of a teacher, rent for club rooms, sheet music and for wreaths for deceased members. Malignantly they assert that the club rooms, where the Chorus practices, is a "speakeasy.".... None of the I. W. W. members ever contributed anything to the Workers' Chorus, but the members of the Chorus always helped them whenever the cause justified assistance. The Workers' Chorus would have accepted the last invitation, too, if the proceeds of the affair were to have been turned over to the unfortunate ones, who are imprisoned, victims of class war, but the Chorus refused because that was not the real purpose.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0334.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This boycott is like the Pope's excommunication, for it neither helps nor hinders. The Chicago Workers' Chorus has always worked unselfishly, and the respectable Hungarians will not boycott them. We place our trust in our own strength and in the support of our fellow workers.</p>
   <p>Respectfully, by authority of the Chicago Hungarian Workers' Chorus.</p>
   <p>Andrew Pencz, president;</p>
   <p>Joseph Hernesz, Jr. secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
