<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-03-28">Mar. 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Before We Elect a Mayor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0563</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0563.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-03-28">Mar. 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">BEFORE WE ELECT A MAYOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There will be five candidates on the ballot seeking the nominations for the office of Mayor in the city of Chicago. They are: Thompson, a Republican, Sweitzer, a Democrat, Hoyne, an Independent party candidate, Fitzpatrick, the organized Workers' candidate, and Collins, a Socialist.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly, the principals in this fight will be Thompson, Sweitzer and Hoyne, and when the primaries are over, it will be a battle between Thompson and Sweitzer for the office of Mayor of the City of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0564.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now, two questions arise as to which of these two is better fitted for the position, and which one would have the welfare of the Chicago-Hungarian at heart. These are the important questions in the minds of the Chicago-Hungarian voters. Thompson has his good points and we can say the same about Sweitzer. Thompson, as mayor, worked hard and stood his ground well. While in office, he was not connected with any scandal, or outrageous graft situations. Many people do not like Thompson because he did not act in accordance with the ideas of the War press, but there are many people who like him for that reason.</p>
   <p>Both Thompson and Sweitzer are good business men. The press seems to be the severest critic of Thompson. It will be disappointed if he is elected.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0565.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thompson had promised the Hungarian people many things, but never fulfilled any of these promises, and consequently, many are organized to work against him.</p>
   <p>Sweitzer, at the present time, is County Clerk, and has shown his honesty, integrity, and benevolent heart to the city of Chicago and Cook County. Many people are biased because he is of German descent. But during the War, he fully cooperated and worked whole-heartedly with the State Council of Defense in organizing patriotic organizations among the Hungarians and Germans. We do not know if Sweitzer will keep the promises which he has made to the Hungarian people during his campaign, but we do know that we have among us <pb facs="5422061_1_0566.jpg" n="4"/>prominent Hungarian Democrats who fully and whole-heartedly endorse the election of Sweitzer. The Hungarians of Chicago commands a large number of votes. They should give their votes to those whom they think is the best man for the City of Chicago as a whole, and, particularly, to a man who will do something that will benefit the Chicago-Hungarians.</p>
   <p>This paper, and its staff, recommends the election of Sweitzer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
