<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-07-27">July 27, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Liberty and Democracy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Dezso Tomor)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0740</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0740.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-07-27">July 27, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">LIBERTY AND DEMOCRACY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Dezso Tomor)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The thoroughbred American is very proud of his liberty and the democracy that insures the greatness of this country.</p>
   <p>How free are we? How democratic are we?</p>
   <p>A few examples can illustrate the untruth of these elegantly phrased slogans said to be the American spirit.</p>
   <p>Prohibition is one proof of how little we respect the sanctity of personal liberty.</p>
   <p>The free spirit of labor and commerce, which made this country great, will be regimented now and the rest will follow rapidly.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0741.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Secretary of Labor has discovered that many children under ten years of age are wage earners. He wants to license newsboys and prohibit bootblacks from working.</p>
   <p>We are not saying that this attitude of the Honorable Secretary of Labor is right or wrong, but we do think that if the parents of these children-workers were employed continuously and paid a living wage, child labor would automatically cease.</p>
   <p>A shining example of democracy was given at Bailey's Beach in New York.</p>
   <p>The upper "400" wouldn't allow actors and actresses to bathe at their beach--in the ocean. In their eyes these people are not in their class, therefore, they are not fit to bathe in their company--in the ocean.</p>
   <p>Beautiful examples! Pride of liberty and democracy! <pb facs="5422061_1_0742.jpg" n="3"/>The most insignificant chorus girl is a worthier member of society, through her work, than any of the idle rich, who--because they have millions--think that they are better than those who produce the millions for them by the sweat of their brows.</p>
   <p>This is a picture of democracy in this beautiful adopted country of ours.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
