<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-09-18">Sept. 18, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Great Political Oratory</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0361</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0361.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-09-18">Sept. 18, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT POLITICAL ORATORY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is an accepted general American custom that whenever there is a holiday gathering, our politicians, one after the other, take the platform and make flowing speeches; and usually they evade any serious problem, limiting their topics to political ballyhoo.</p>
   <p>Last week, on Labor Day, there was no lack of oratory. However, the tone of the speeches was radically different from the usual cut and dried political phraseology.</p>
   <p>The chief point of interest is that all the orators chose the same topic. All the speeches were about the present terrible unemployment situation and each orator concluded, that something must be done to remedy the situation.....</p>
   <p>However, not one of the orators held out a ray of hope that the depression <pb facs="5422061_1_0362.jpg" n="2"/>will be over soon and that prosperity is around the corner, as they heretofore always insisted.</p>
   <p>On the contrary, each orator depicted the present situation in the darkest colors and said that there is no relief in sight; furthermore, they asserted that, if anything, conditions will become worse.....</p>
   <p>Unemployment in recent times has reached such proportions that it is unnecessary to exaggerate, because facts speak for themselves and because it is also impossible to conceal the figures. The situation today is not only serious, but positively critical.</p>
   <p>The above is acknowledged not only by the radical element, but by the staunch supporters of the capitalistic system.....</p>
   <p>Among others, Senator Borah said, "If you wealthy people will not voluntarily feed the hungry unemployed this winter, they will force you to do your duty.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0363.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is no alternative for you, because there is enough food in the warehouses. You have money; therefore you must give. If you refuse to give, the time will come when your wealth will be taken from you against your will."</p>
   <p>Even Senator Borah admonishes the privileged class, who are the masters today.....</p>
   <p>All the orators agree that the present system is antiquated, that it is necessary to substitute a new one. Nevertheless, it seems that they cannot get used to the idea and rise above the system into which they were born. This becomes apparent from the unsound, insecure plans offered by them for the solution of the problem. Seemingly they all acknowledge the seriousness of the situation; they all see the injustice in the fact that millions must go hungry in a country where comfort, luxury, and wealth surround them. But when plans to solve the problem are brought to the fore, the quick flame of enthusiasm dies down and words stick in their throats.....</p>
   <p>Suddenly they get frightened by reforms such as unemployment insurance, <pb facs="5422061_1_0364.jpg" n="4"/>taxation of the wealthy, old age pensions, and similar radical steps. Most of them would like to avoid all reforms by temporary relief action, alms, and gifts, although they know that even at best this will relieve the situation only for a short while.</p>
   <p>Even the president of the American Federation of Labor does not fight for new laws that would assure unemployment insurance and old age pensions to the workers. He only warns the government that such laws will become necessary if a less radical solution is not found soon for diminishing the number of unemployed.....</p>
   <p>In conclusion, we can perceive that in all the speeches, a feeling of uneasiness and fright, a foreboding of danger are apparent; but the brave, true, sincere tone which would demand a solution and point to the right direction is missing.....</p>
   <p>It is time for united and serious action, not mere words, so that this disturbing situation may be solved, because the zero hour is rapidly approaching.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
