<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-01-25">Jan. 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Hungarians and American Politics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0584</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0584.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-01-25">Jan. 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE HUNGARIANS AND AMERICAN POLITICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are only a few days left before the battle for the mayoral election is opened in Chicago. To be mayor of Chicago is the third most important job in the United States. The most important job is that of president of the United States, then that of mayor of New York City, and after this that of mayor of Chicago. The relative importance of these positions is measured by the number of jobs each has at its disposal. The mayor of Chicago has pretty close to five thousand jobs to give out. It is a known fact that Chicago is the most mixed and most cosmopolitan city in the United States, therefore it is reasonable that each nationality should organize its own political clubs in order that it may take part in the campaign and help the people get interested in the political life of the city.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0585.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is a rather serious proposition, but we cannot speak too seriously of the activities of the Chicago Hungarians. In American political life they are mere novices, and although there are quite a large number of Hungarian-American citizens in the city of Chicago, they do not understand the first thing about politics. This is the only reason for the sorrowful situation that out of ten thousand Hungarian-American citizens residing in and around Chicago, there is not a single one who has ever held a political position. It is true that there are a few men of Hungarian descent who have held and hold political positions, but they did not receive these positions through the backing of the Hungarians, but by their own individual efforts. With the other nationalities it is just the opposite. Each national group with the exception of the Hungarian, organizes and then demands that the group be well represented. It isn't a very nice thing to say and we do not like to write about it, but the Hungarian people are rather far behind. Individually we Hungarians are a fine race but collectively we enjoy no recognition in the American political arena. We have based this conclusion on what we observe among the Hungarians of Chicago, but the statement holds <pb facs="5422061_1_0586.jpg" n="3"/>true for the entire Hungarian population of America, with the exception of New York City.</p>
   <p>Sick benefit and church societies are the only organizations active and strong among the Hungarian people. They cannot, however, get mixed up in politics and there are very few if any that would be willing to enter the political field. As things now stand, when an election comes up Hungarian political clubs are formed, which disband immediately after the campaign is over.</p>
   <p>Now that the mayoral election is approaching, two Hungarian political clubs have been organized--one Republican and the other Democratic. Unquestionably, before elections are over there will be one or two others. The [political] position of the Hungarian people has not been properly cleared up as yet, and this is the reason why, as a group, they cannot pick a candidate of their own. It is our hope that as the election gets closer the different Hungarian groups will unite instead of pulling apart, for if they do not <pb facs="5422061_1_0587.jpg" n="4"/>unite, their political activities will never amount to anything. The ripening process in politics is very hard. It is necessary to have a little intelligence, a little cooperation, and a bit of common sense. Perhaps the politically ambitious Hungarians have come to realize this in the past few years. If they have, then it is time that they organize in a hurry and talk politics loudly and seriously. However, if they are just looking for glory and nothing else, they should hide themselves in shame, as they would only make a laughing stock out of the Hungarian people. It will kill us, and we do not want the hard-developing Hungarian name and future killed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
