<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-11-06">Nov. 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Shame on Us!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-11-06">Nov. 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">SHAME ON US!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The latest convention of the Verhovay Aid Association in Philadelphia adopted a resolution whereby the paragraph in its by-laws which prohibits the acceptance of applicants of certain religions as members becomes null and void, so that in the future Jews, too, may become members of the Association. We greet this decision as a sign of sensible perception, in step with prevailing modern ideas, and worthy of the leaders of America's greatest and most powerful Hungarian association.</p>
   <p>According to the by-laws of the association, this resolution becomes a by-law only when at least two-thirds of the districts accept it.</p>
   <p>We learn now, with great surprise, that District No. 21 in Chicago has rejected this decision of the convention, and we are afraid that if this example is followed by others, the whole action will be a failure. It is to <pb facs="5422061_1_0183.jpg" n="2"/>be regretted that only four out of thirteen delegates could think soberly; three others hid themselves under the cloak of neutrality, and the other six showed their backwardness and gave evidence of their poor mentality. Anthony Lachman, Steve Rozgonyi, Julius Szabo, and August Pentek were those who represented the progressive spirit, but to our regret, in vain, as they were unable to bring light into the dark souls of their apponents.</p>
   <p>And yet, Rome has already a Jewish mayor, Palestine has a Jewish governor, Hungary has a Jewish Minister of Justice, and one Chief Justice of the United States is also a Jew.</p>
   <p>We cannot say more about this affair than it is impossible to turn back the march of time. Everything runs fast at full gallop, and the coming event will swipe away all those backward, dark-souled men who do not want to or cannot understand the commands of Time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
