<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1935-07-28">July 28, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">One Million Signatures</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0625</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0625.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1935-07-28">July 28, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">ONE MILLION SIGNATURES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Szabodsog, Hungarian Daily has just announced that of the one million signatures, demanding the revision of the Treaty of Trianon, one hundred thousand signatures have been secured already.</p>
   <p>The Szabodsog has a helper, or competitor, in the person of Frank Bologh of Chicago. This compatriot wrote the following letter to the Chicago Daily News, which was published:</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0626.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Dr, Jerka, brother-in-law of the late Mayor Cermak, asserts that everyone living in Czecho-Slovakia is working and happy."</p>
   <p>I do not agree with him, because he did not mention the million Magyars in Czecho-Slovakia who are subjected to great suffering. These people cannot be happy, because every right is forbidden them that was granted in the Treaty of Trianon. They are not allowed to send their children to Hungarian schools and their life is made miserable in every conceivable way. Is this justice? I was compelled to emigrate when these "robbers" set foot on Magyar soil, because they took everything from us. This land was part of Hungary for a thousand years. I was fortunate to be able to come to this <pb facs="5422061_1_0627.jpg" n="3"/>land of liberty. I was spared the suffering that is the lot of those I left behind. I am indeed sorry that all those Magyars are not able to come here, too.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Daily News has a million readers, so our unknown compatriot did a great service for the revision, without collecting a million signatures. We congratulate him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
