<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-04-13">Apr. 13, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The a B C of American Politics by Lowinger</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0230</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0230.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-04-13">Apr. 13, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE A B C OF AMERICAN POLITICS by Lowinger</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The most important duty in the educators of American Hungarians is to interest them in American politics. We will illustrate the difficulties that have to be overcome in this struggle for education with an old experience.</p>
   <p>As is generally known, the battle is between two major political parties, the Republican and Democratic parties. That most Hungarians and other foreigners--even natives--do not know the basic difference between these two parties is not the greatest misfortune. In local and state elections it is usually the minority against the majority, the criticism of those in power by the opposition.</p>
   <p>One thing is certain, however, and that is that one individual cannot <pb facs="5422061_1_0231.jpg" n="2"/>belong to both parties at the same time. This fact is difficult for some Hungarian politicians to understand. They like to appear as nonpartisans, or they conceal their political affiliations. Both are considered bad politics in America. Sincerity is always better and more likely to inspire confidence.</p>
   <p>We were eyewitnesses in the case of one of our countrymen with political aspirations, who openly pledged himself to the interests of the Democratic party. This person was at the same time visited by a Republican campaign manager, and our compatriot signed his name without hesitation, pledging his support to the Republicans. Is this double-dealing ignorance or political immaturity?</p>
   <p>Whatever it is, it is not the correct procedure in trying to gain a foot-hold in American politics.</p>
   <p>We don't mean to convey the idea that the foregoing example is a typical Hungarian trait; the illustration, however, depicts the wavering character <pb facs="5422061_1_0232.jpg" n="3"/>of a beginner and we can find such individuals among any other national group. Undoubtedly, these faults of character could be corrected through education.</p>
   <p>There are some people who are inconstant to their religion, their creeds and their convictions for commercial reasons. They change their beliefs seasonally. Such people are found anywhere and they cannot be taught constancy in American politics.</p>
   <p>The majority of Hungarians, however, must learn that they should choose the party whose platform coincides with their ideas and interests; and once their selection is made, they should adhere to their choice. This is the honorable political method in America, advocated by the leaders of both great political parties. Both parties are fond of the voters, but neither party has any use for the citizen, who is changeable.....</p>
   <p>In America, anyone may voice his opinion..... That personal enmity should result from political differences is a sign of political immaturity.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0233.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Usually it occurs among primitive people who have not learned to control their impulses and who have no self control.....</p>
   <p>Some of us become angry at our compatriots because they are socialists or communists..... In the middle ages when the reformers' great struggle rocked the foundations of the Roman Catholic Church, bloody battles were fought. Today Catholics and Protestants live side by side in peace.....</p>
   <p>We Hungarians are quite temperamental and explosive. Our primitive, oppressed life as tillers of the soil for hundreds of years is the reason for the volatile nature of our Hungarian people.</p>
   <p>In America we live on a different schedule. Let us accept America as our adopted country, not only theoretically, but by acquiring its ways, its thinking and its procedures. Let us be as calm and analytical in political debate as the better class of native Americans are. Let us not allow our private lives to be disturbed by political differences. Let <pb facs="5422061_1_0234.jpg" n="5"/>us be faithful to our beliefs, consistent and honest in our political activities, but at the same time, let us be tolerant toward our political opponents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
