<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-12-09">Dec. 9, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A Letter to the Editorial Staff</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Time Has Come to Do Something for Our Culture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-12-09">Dec. 9, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A LETTER TO THE EDITORIAL STAFF</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Time Has Come to Do Something for Our Culture</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Weeks ago your newspaper conducted a series of editorials whose aim was to rouse the American Hungarians from their indifference to cultural activities. These articles described the true state of the Hungarians here. It would have been impossible to draw a clearer picture. It was as if Kossuth's flaming spirit inspired the editor in his efforts to stir the American Hungarians from their apathy, and if this does not succeed, let it sink into oblivion.</p>
   <p>Under the influence of these inspiring editorials, I believed and hoped that the local Hungarians would be aroused to remedy what they had neglected in the past. I waited and waited for the otherwise noisy, patriotic Hungarian leaders to take matters into their hands and organize the masses by arranging classes for the education of our Hungarians. Furthermore, I had hoped that as a result of these editorials our Hungarians would awaken to the need of a library and reading room.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0042.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I am greatly disappointed. These articles were read by the Hungarians and they were convinced of their truth, but when the time for action came they avoided the issues with the remark: "We will have time later."</p>
   <p>But we can't postpone it! The eleventh hour for action has passed. It is not enough to put out our chests and boast about what we do for the Hungarian cause just because once in a while we dedicate a few Hungarian flags or arrange social gatherings reiterating a few meaningless slogans. If we neglect Hungarian culture, progress, and learning, all the rest is nothing.</p>
   <p>Never before was there such a need for cultural activity as at present. Now, when Hungary, because of its reactionary government, is open to the world's criticism as the most unprogressive country, which allows students to be beaten and persecuted because of religious prejudice.....</p>
   <p>The whole world condemns Hungary for allowing such conditions to exist. The <pb facs="5422061_1_0043.jpg" n="3"/>American newspapers write columns censuring the Hungarian government. This is one of the reasons we American Hungarians have to save some of our cultural reputation.</p>
   <p>In Chicago there are at least thirty organizations, including churches. If each organization would contribute only five dollars a month, how easy it would be to have a permanent reading room, and by charging a small fee a library could be added. The Tarsalgo Society has two thousand books, the Glee Club six hundred, the Workers' Chorus over five hundred, and many Hungarian individuals would also be willing to give books so that the Hungarians could have a nice library. The societies could keep the books at their own club rooms, with the understanding that the Hungarians have access to them.</p>
   <p>How nice it would be if during the winter months we could have educational evenings once in two weeks with English and Hungarian lectures, debates and displays of art. If there is co-operation, we can realize these dreams.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0044.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Forward, Hungarian societies! Your important yearly meetings are near; discuss this nation-saving matter and be the first to do your bit. And all of your men and women who appreciate your Hungarian origin, join this movement to help save the good name of the country of our birth.</p>
   <p>An outspoken reader.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
