<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-06-05">June 5, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">What Is the Truth?</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ignatz Izsak (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0145</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0145.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-06-05">June 5, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS THE TRUTH?</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ignatz Izsak (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the month of July, the little city of Dayton, Tennessee will become historically famous.</p>
   <p>A world-wide controversy will take place. The scientific world has sounded a blast, and has invited those stubborn and blind people who believe the Bible to the letter to participate.</p>
   <p>The scientific people will be there with all their laboratory equipment and experiments, striving to prove their point of view.</p>
   <p>The Biblicists, church members, prophets, priests, martyrs, and the believers <pb facs="5422061_1_0146.jpg" n="2"/>of miracles will be there with Godly admissions and will try to frighten the scientists.</p>
   <p>The problem about which the battle is waging is the origin of man. The Biblicists claim that God was the creator of man. The scientists claim that man's origin is through evolution.</p>
   <p>Charles Darwin, an English scientist, was the originator of the evolution idea. He came from a family of a long line of clergymen. He was a modest, but rather religious man, and far from being an atheist. In his book, he endeavors to show that he is not involved in the history of creation, nor is he trying to make a story out of it. He is only probing into the fact that after the earth was formed so was life created. Through careful study, he came to the conclusion that the origin of life was in water, and from here all animal life started to develop.</p>
   <p>The believers of the Bible forget to mention that the Bible mentions the fact that it took six days for creation. All they say is that these six days <pb facs="5422061_1_0147.jpg" n="3"/>consisted of six minute divisions of a second, or in other words, when God said there shall Be, then it happened. But according to the Bible, He did not do this. He took six distinct days to develop the world, which is proof of the fact that He also believed in evolution. The six days of creation fit in with scientific principles.</p>
   <p>A man's life passes through a period of evolution. A person is born, then he passes through the childhood stage; the youthful stage; then comes the middle age stage, and finally, the old or feeble stage. Each of these stages represents a period of development in the life of the human being.</p>
   <p>We ask ourselves why is it that we cannot be born at the age of twenty and remain at that age?</p>
   <p>The believers of the Bible claim that everything is the act of God, and we should be satisfied with this.</p>
   <p>God is not as great as people imagine Him to be. According to the Bible, <pb facs="5422061_1_0148.jpg" n="4"/>Lot made a bargain with God when he bargained for the saving of Sodom and Gomorrah, and according to the Bible, God took this step in evolution with pleasure.</p>
   <p>Bryan claims that a jenny's milk is the closest to a human mother's milk. He also mentions the fact that man cannot create life as yet. The various individuals, such as Burbank, only produce variations in the types with which they experiment.</p>
   <p>Bryan forgets that if man could create life, all the ideas created by the people who believe in God would crumble like a castle built of cards.</p>
   <p>It is our belief that the ideas conceived by God were handed down to mankind through evolution.</p>
   <p>When we speak of evolution we do not mean to say that there is no Super Being, but we do say that it is a simple and modern conception of the creation and development of the human race.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
