<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-11-07">Nov. 7, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Factory Workers, Miners, Poor Hungarians!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0792</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0792.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-11-07">Nov. 7, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">FACTORY WORKERS, MINERS, POOR HUNGARIANS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>You who would like to be your own bosses, but have realized that no matter how long you have worked in factories or mines you will never be independent--think about our proposal!</p>
   <p>We have fifty thousand acres of first-class land in the northwestern part of Florida, and we offer half of this land for Hungarian colonization.</p>
   <p>Our climate is the healthiest, our water the best, our roads excellent, and our land located near two main railway lines. The state's Agriculture and Farm Bureau and other experts declare that our land is the best. Our winters last only six weeks, and the thermometer seldom drops to the freezing point. The summer season is mild; although we are in the South, we are close to the ocean and the temperature rarely rises to ninety degrees. There is enough rain, especially when needed, and there is never a drought. In the middle of January we are already planting potatoes.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0793.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We take our products to market from March until June, when the best price is paid for them. Furthermore, we can raise two or three crops on the same land, and it is not to be wondered at that often one acre of land produces a hundred dollars' worth.</p>
   <p>Our lands provide an assured livelihood for all, even older people, who wish to work.</p>
   <p>To the first settlers we give loans and provide credit; moreover, we furnish them with houses and let them use our tilled soil, thereby assisting them in getting a start. All we ask is that under the guidance of our experts they work industriously, so that they may become independent and help other of our Hungarian brethren to prosperity.</p>
   <p>We will sell excellent land, also, to those who have enough cash to start work without assistance. However, if the quota of the first settlers is already filled and some of our Hungarians do not have sufficient money to invest and become one <pb facs="5422061_1_0794.jpg" n="3"/>of the first settlers, we welcome them also and offer them very advantageous terms.</p>
   <p>In December of this year we wish to begin colonizing, but anyone who applies after that date will not be too late, although the advantages offered to the first settlers will be withdrawn.</p>
   <p>Write in English or Hungarian.</p>
   <p>Among the first settlers there are two Hungarian Reformed ministers, whose detailed plans have been accepted. They have made it possible for this company to offer such remarkable advantages to the agricultural Hungarian people. Write directly to us or to: Reverend G. Garay, 8506 Burley Avenue, Chicago, or to Reverend J. M. Hanko, Milwaukee, Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>The West Florida Land Owners Association</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
