<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-10-23">Oct. 23, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Have We All Become Insane?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Martin Himler)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-10-23">Oct. 23, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">HAVE WE ALL BECOME INSANE?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Martin Himler)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It looks as if everyone in this country is slightly insane.....</p>
   <p>Something new happened here two years ago. The social order's economic machinery has collapsed. The hoarded billions derived from mass production were not redistributed fairly among the people because the machinery owners did not allow it, and, as a result, the wheels of the machinery stopped. And no genius of the capitalistic social order can make the wheels go until it is acknowledged that the system must be changed.</p>
   <p>They do not want to admit that they are facing an economic revolution rather than an ordinary economic depression. Naturally, all our sages, millionaires, and politicians recommend different remedies to end the panic, but up to the present no one has been willing or has had courage enough to admit that a new deal for the workers is what is needed to end the depression.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0355.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even those who have been forced out of work by the high efficiency requirements [of modern industry] have a right to live, although this fact may not be to the liking of the ruling class.....</p>
   <p>And, since the unemployed cannot make a living out of the frequent promises of prosperity or out of the President's promises, bread must be provided for them in some manner. Not much bread but just enough so that their stomachs will not be entirely empty, because a man on an empty stomach will face a bayonet in desperation.</p>
   <p>Therefore, great public conferences are being conducted in an endeavor to figure out a way to provide bread for the hungry, ragged millions of the unemployed.....</p>
   <p>The "great engineer" who sits in the White House and who is a multimillionaire has all sorts of plans, and talks about the rugged individualism of Americans.....In his speech at Indianapolis he proposed a "twenty-year program" <pb facs="5422061_1_0356.jpg" n="3"/>and promised his audience that in twenty years, if this program is followed, prosperity and happiness will be our lot. The only thing Hoover failed to think of is where the unemployed will get their next meal.....</p>
   <p>However, we have in our midst politicians and statesmen who are endowed with a greater degree of social sense than our "great engineer," and we would expect them to have a broader understanding of the problem.</p>
   <p>Everyone considers Roosevelt, governor of New York, the great Democratic leader who wishes to be our next president, such a man. Roosevelt is the hope of the liberals. The citizens have not been altogether disappointed in Roosevelt.....He advocates raising the taxes on the rich by fifty per cent. If our government would follow this example, every needy person could be taken care of.....</p>
   <p>After these healthy recommendations, Roosevelt also deviated from the path of sanity. Because he is campaigning for the presidency, he assured the <pb facs="5422061_1_0357.jpg" n="4"/>capitalists that they need not be afraid of drastic action if he becomes the next tenant of the White House.</p>
   <p>Roosevelt lied when he said that the unemployed would be given work. Men on relief are ordered to parks and roads, where they idle away the time in superfluous work. Real work will not be given the reliefers; the contractors will get the real work so that our politicians can have their graft.....</p>
   <p>We begin to believe that Roosevelt is right when he asserts that only the weak-minded and backward people are out of work. If it were not so, if normal, intelligent, sane, conscious American citizens were suffering hardships in this land of milk and honey, such remedies as work relief could not be offered.</p>
   <p>It seems from the foregoing that we all are becoming more or less deranged mentally.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
