<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-11-22">Nov. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Louis Kossuth Leader of Hungarian Independence</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0682</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0682.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-11-22">Nov. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LOUIS KOSSUTH LEADER OF HUNGARIAN INDEPENDENCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Louis Kossuth, leader of the Hungarian revolution against Austria in 1848, who exiled himself after the uprising was suppressed, forwarded a message to the people of the United States before he visited this country. In this message were utterances of great importance, and predictions which, for the most part came true. For this reason, and for the unshakable confidence the former governor of Hungary had expressed in the sense of justice of this nation and for its bitter attack on Austria, vassal of Germany.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0683.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While writing in this country, the great leader for liberty first described events as they happened, and asserted that Austria had fought against the Hungarians not only with arms, and with the aid of traitors, but with diabolical plans and unceasing slander.</p>
   <p>Louis Kossuth addressed the American people in this manner: "Free citizens of America! You have given in spite of this slander your fullest sympathy to my country. Oh that you had been the neighboring nation, the Old World would now be free, and you would not be forced to endure those terrible "convulsions" again, and cross rivers of "blood" which are inevitable. But the end is with God, and he will choose the means to fulfill his purpose."</p>
   <p>These words, prophetic as they were, have come true, even in their negative <pb facs="5422061_1_0684.jpg" n="3"/>sense, that if America had been the neighboring nation, the old world would have been free, and we had not witnessed the present catastrophe.</p>
   <p>In another passage, the passing of the Hapsburgh is foretold, the message reads: "Francis Joseph, thou beardless Nero, thou darest say that Hungary shall not exist, but you and your treacherous house shall stand no longer, you shall no longer be king of Hungary. Be forever banished, you terrible traitor to the nation!"</p>
   <p>The disruption of a centralized Austrian empire is predicted as follows: "The sentiment of sympathy for our sufferings will inspire among the smaller states and race the wish for a fraternal confederation for that <pb facs="5422061_1_0685.jpg" n="4"/>which I always urged as the only safe policy and guarantee of freedom for all of them.</p>
   <p>The realization of this idea will hurl the power of the haughty monarch's history out of the past, and Hungary will be free and surrounded by four nations.</p>
   <p>Among the nations of the world, we owe gratitude and affection to the people of the United States, who, with their liberal government, inspired us with hope, and gave us courage by their deep interest in our cause and sufferings." Kossuth exclaims in his appeal: "Austria, even in her victory, has given herself a mortal wound. Her weakness is betrayed. The <pb facs="5422061_1_0686.jpg" n="5"/>world does no longer believe that it needs the preservation of this decoyed empire. It is evident that its existence is a curse to the welfare of society. Among all the races of the empire, there is none that does not despair the reigning family of Hapsburgh. When the empire falls, not a tear of regret will follow it to its grave, and it will surely fall. A shot fired from an American or English vessel from the Adriatic would be like a trumpet at the city of "Jericho."</p>
   <p>Describing the sentiment in this country some fifty years ago, Kossuth writes the following: "The President of the United States in whom the confidence of a few people have elevated to the loftiest station in the world, in his message to Congress announced that the American government would have been the first to recognize the independence of Hungary. And <pb facs="5422061_1_0687.jpg" n="6"/>the Senators and Representatives in Congress marked the destroyers of the liberty of my country with stigma of ignominy and expressed with indignant feelings their contempt for the conduct of Austria, and their wish to break diplomatic intercourse with that government. The summoned monarchs are before the "judgment seat of humanity."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
