<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1931-11-27">Nov. 27, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">In the Name of Culture!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1931-11-27">Nov. 27, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE NAME OF CULTURE!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now that the fall months are here and winter is approaching,we can notice great cultural activities in the life of associations--American and of other nationalities. Wherever we turn, we witness all kinds of scientific, social, and literary lectures. Only we Hungarians are lagging behind other national groups in this regard.</p>
   <p>We have to admit with regret that in our circles--with the exception of the radical worker organizations--nothing is heard of scientific lectures, even though we have many associations and churches whose duty is to cater to this need. When some of our churches and associations arrange something along this line (which is rarer than a white raven), the attendance is usually restricted to their own circle, and the venture, consequently, is a failure.</p>
   <p>This shows that there is something wrong among the Hungarians, and that we have to <pb facs="5422061_1_0063.jpg" n="2"/>remedy it. We cannot let the Hungarians become a people without culture.</p>
   <p>To attain success in this regard, it is necessary that our leaders unite with our churches and associations, so that jointly they may arrange cultural evenings for the Hungarians, on which evenings America's most eminent men--American and Hungarian--would hold lectures on topics dealing with different branches of science.</p>
   <p>This is the only plausible way to make possible for the Hungarians living here to march forward with the torch of Knowledge under the Star-Spangled Banner.</p>
   <p>Forward, Hungarians, to action!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
