<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-06-06">June 6, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Peoples' Meeting a Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-06-06">June 6, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">PEOPLES' MEETING A SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago-Hungarian Societies' committee held an open meeting for the Chicago-Hungarians Sunday afternoon at Wicker Park Hall.</p>
   <p>When the roll was called it was found that there were fourteen societies represented, although the larger part of the audience consisted of members of the I.W.W., the Social Labor Party, and the Social Party Association. The meeting was opened by Mr. Joseph Szoke, a fellow worker, who gave a short but very interesting talk. He spoke about the duty of American-Hungarian workers towards this country, at the same time reminding them of the causes that made them leave their homeland to seek their daily bread in a foreign country. Then Mr. Szoke, asked Mr. Armin Lowy to speak. He, too, spoke about the new Hungary, the bare constitutional routine of Hungary, an analyzed the causes of the War.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0476.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the conclusion of the speeches, the chorus representing the Social Party sang the Hymn of Revolution. All pending resolutions were read next and were accepted unanimously. After this, Ernest Klopstein delivered a masterful speech, in which he asked the Hungarian-American workers to start organizational work, showing clearly that a well organized group would be able to protect itself. Mr. Klopstein told his audience that it was impossible to accomplish any of their aims by fighting for them in the streets, but we reach our goal by working like the machines of industry. We must organize and work together.</p>
   <p>This last speech caused a slight disturbance among the societies, and quite a few arguments were started, pro and con. In order to quell the arguments, the meeting was called to order and then adjourned in order.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
