<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-07-24">July 24, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">American Rearing</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0120</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0120.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-07-24">July 24, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN REARING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have written time and again about the many American marriages that end in divorces. We believe that our young people are making a great mistake when they follow the American custom of disregarding parental opinion in the matter of choosing their mates.</p>
   <p>It is in this connection that we think the American method of rearing children is wrong. Not wrong in all respects, of course, for the physical training given to the American child is commendable. Nevertheless, the spirit—the atmosphere in which the young ones grow up—is dangerous.</p>
   <p>Family ties being loose, it is a daily occurrence to see children getting lost to their families as soon as they reach adulthood. Although the practice of teaching children to take care of themselves when they grow up is an admirable one, to expect them to pay for their room and board brings about discord.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0121.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We don't find so much fault in the system of bringing up children as we do in the deep-rooted mercenary greediness of the Americans, a greediness which results in the dissolution of family ties at the first clash.</p>
   <p>How different do the Europeans feel in family matters! To them the family is sacred. To illustrate this in a small way, the family of a European can't picture a meal without the presence of the head of the family, much less would any member of the family dare sit at the head of the table. We register with regret the sentiment that this feeling of respect will never prevail in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
