<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-07-01">July 1, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A Lesson in National Libel</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Lowinger (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-07-01">July 1, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A LESSON IN NATIONAL LIBEL</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Lowinger (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Debrecen court fined a woman, who had recently returned to Hungary, one hundred and sixteen pengoes for libelous remarks against the nation. The woman bought a threshing machine and hired out to a neighboring farm. The police would not allow threshing in the willage. Forgetting herself, the woman said "Such an outrage can happen only in Hungary."</p>
   <p>In our opinion, "nation" has a holier, more solemn meaning, and we believe that an impulsive, unconsidered remark does not constitute libel against a nation.</p>
   <p>Aside from the fact that we know that our readers are interested in what <pb facs="5422061_1_0250.jpg" n="2"/>is going on in Hungary and that therefore, it is our duty to satisfy their curiosity, we are fulfilling a mission when we present a true picture, from time to time, of our changed, unfortunate mother country.</p>
   <p>Let this little episode serve as a lesson to those of our brethren who have not yet been able to become accustomed to American ways, and who are continually criticizing, and finding fault with, everything here.</p>
   <p>America is not the ideal home of liberty either. Probably there is no such thing. And even though he [the Hungarian immigrant]does not have a palatial home, a cool summer garden where he can enjoy fine Pilsen beers with gypsy music, or distinguished friends with whom to play cards in the casino (which is probably the reason he came to America), it is better to be here.</p>
   <p>Let us admit that in the Hungary of today, in addition to the ten thousand <pb facs="5422061_1_0251.jpg" n="3"/>families who live on the fat of the land, there are millions of workers who would be only too glad to cross the borders. If anyone in Hungary would criticize that country as freely as the immigrant airs his views in America, then the whole population would be composed of prisoners and guards.</p>
   <p>It would be well if we were to give thanks to God for delivering us from such an autocratic government, and if we were to look gratefully upon The Star-Spangled Banner even while the noise of the firecrackers annoys our ears and outrages our sensibilities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
