<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-03-25">Mar. 25, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">"Awakening Hungarians"</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ignacio Izsak (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-03-25">Mar. 25, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">"AWAKENING HUNGARIANS"</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ignacio Izsak (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is not one unprejudiced Hungarian who would not admit that nothing was so detrimental to crippled Hungary as the "awakening Hungarians".</p>
   <p>This organization is composed mostly of individuals who never liked to make an honest living, but preferred the methods of extortion, robbery and murder through which their base passions were served.</p>
   <p>Since the [time of the] armistice we always voiced our opinion that Horthy was responsible for the sins of the "awakening Hungarians". He took advantage of the help that immature youngsters could give him in <pb facs="5422061_1_0260.jpg" n="2"/>his aim to become regent, and then did not keep his promises to them.</p>
   <p>These duped army officers organized "divisions" not controlled by the government. These divisions created a reign of terror..... Horthy dared to do nothing against them and in many cases provided them with letters of amnesty beforehand.</p>
   <p>Many of these disappointed persons came to America, and with a view to a more carefree existence, began to re-enact their original roles as "awakening Hungarians".....</p>
   <p>Chicago received its share of these "awakening Hungarians", who badly wanted to awaken our Chicago Hungarians.</p>
   <p>But they overreached themselves because our Hungarians are too same to be influenced by such humbug.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0261.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But because they wanted to "awaken," by any and all means, they found no better subject than those of us who didn't agree that Horthy was the new Messiah. They sent the most incredible reports to the "black cabinet" in Budapest.</p>
   <p>This would have been in order thus far--but....</p>
   <p>These gentlemen had a great and daring thought. They arranged a March celebration, not for the benefit of the fund for the statue of Kossuth, but for the more inspiring cause of aiding the widows and orphans.</p>
   <p>They had every right to do this, but they certainly didn't have the right to send invitations to the Jews because we have heard that they do not welcome Jewish visitors in their Club and especially do not tolerate them as members.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0262.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>They had even less right to send us an invitation!</p>
   <p>They had only one excuse, and that was that they were afraid that their followers wouldn't appear in great enough numbers, so it would be better to be on the safe side by inviting the Jews.</p>
   <p>Their calculation was correct!</p>
   <p>According to an unbiased report, thirty-five to forty per cent of those present were Jewish which proves that the Jews will attend functions conducted by the oppressors if they know that it is for the benefit of mankind.</p>
   <p>Awakening Hungarians! By inviting us, you have tacitly acknowledged that we are not despoilers of nations and trouble makers and that what we said <pb facs="5422061_1_0263.jpg" n="5"/>about the terror of the "awakening" era was true.</p>
   <p>If you have awakened to this truth and feel it sincerely, then we have to admit the mystic power of the Ides of March!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
