<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1917-03-15">March 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Hungarians Victims of Hyenas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0760</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0760.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1917-03-15">March 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">HUNGARIANS VICTIMS OF HYENAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The trusting and kind hearted Hungarians were very easy victims of the swindlers and had many hard earned dollars taken away from them.</p>
   <p>When immigration was at its height, the Hungarians thought that they were coming to this country as mere guests of America, therefore they did not think it necessary to learn to read and write the English language. There were, however, a few exceptions and out of these exception rose the swindling hyenas.</p>
   <p>The unfortunate immigrants could not look for work, they could not write English, they could not sell, they could not buy. In other words they could not do anything unless they consulted one of the people who could read and write both Hungarian and English.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0761.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The oldest and most profitable racket was the employment racket. When the poor foreigner came to this country he was very unfamiliar with working conditions. So these labor racketeers would sign them up as strike-breakers, or put them to work clearing forests or put them down in mines making them work under very unhealthy conditions, and the wages for the most of these jobs were nothing but slavery wages. But this kind of a racketeering is a thing of the past, mostly due to the fact that the Hungarian press and the government have gotten after them. But as this racket faded a new one took its place.</p>
   <p>The people gradually became acquainted with their surroundings and being of a thrifty class of people they began to save some money. So then racketeers invented new schemes to relieve the Hungarians of their wealth.</p>
   <p>With the development of fraternal organizations, such great depredations took place that these organizations remain as a sore spot in the hearts of the Hungarians. There was for example an organization that offered twenty-five dollars sick benefit and a <pb facs="5422061_1_0762.jpg" n="3"/>policy worth five-hundred dollars in case of death. This was purely a fraudulent scheme. When the time came to collect, the policy proved to be nothing but a one dollar railroad ticket. We know of localities where as many as twenty-five families were involved, each family paying twenty-five dollars cash for this supposed protection.</p>
   <p>Now there are other rackets such as stocks and bonds, property that does not exist, and patent medicines. One of the greatest foes of these rackets, the one that has cut this racketeering down a great deal is the Hungarian Miners News.</p>
   <p>This racketeering not only hurt the wealth of the people but it also makes it hard for the legitimate business man to sell reputable product. Now the better class of business people are starting to recognize the value of the business that might be had from the Hungarians in Chicago and other Eastern cities. We think it necessary to mention the Union Pacific Railroad and Fred H. Bartlett Realty Company, who have <pb facs="5422061_1_0763.jpg" n="4"/>lent a hand in doing away with the racketeering hyenas who preyed on the Hungarian people. These two organizations offered their services and are willing to give advice of any nature.</p>
   <p>We therefore urge the Hungarian people to learn from the experiences of others and do business with firms, organization doctors, that have a well established reputation. This article is meant to be an article to educate the Hungarian people to be on their guard against swindling hyenas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
