<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-04-11">Apr. 11, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The Chicago Primaries</title><title level="a" type="sub">Defeat of Hungarian Candidates; Mrs. McCormick Wins Decisive Victory</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0570</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0570.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-04-11">Apr. 11, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHICAGO PRIMARIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Defeat of Hungarian Candidates; Mrs. McCormick Wins Decisive Victory</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago primaries, which attracted national interest, were not just a regular election, but a fight within the Republican party.</p>
   <p>Mrs. McCormick's victory over Deneen was sensational. The support of the foreign-born contributed greatly to her victory.....The Hungarians, especially, manifested great interest in the results of the primary.</p>
   <p>Two Hungarian candidates took part in the internal struggle of the Republican party. Ignatio Izsak, candidate for County Commissioner, was one of the sixty persons after the ten posts for county commissioners.</p>
   <p>Otto Reich received the largest number of votes--over two hundred thousand.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0571.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Izsak received nine thousand six hundred votes. Of the half million Chicago Republican votes, this is two per cent. However, some of the contestants received even fewer votes than Izsak.</p>
   <p>It is regrettable that Izsak was eliminated from the list of candidates, but after all there were only ten nominations for sixty candidates and fifty of them had to be dropped out in any case.</p>
   <p>We are convinced that if all the Hungarian voters would have done their duty by Izsak, he would have attained a much better result. As it is, many people promised him their support and then voted for someone else. This is bad Hungarian politics and shortsighted tactics.</p>
   <p>Frank Palla, who ran for committeeman in the 43rd Ward, was defeated by Burmeister.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0572.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are all sorry about Palla's defeat, but in both cases--Izsak's and Palla's--victory was not to be expected. They wanted moral acknowledgment more than victory. They are to be commended for their courage.</p>
   <p>The Association of Foreign Language Newspapers, which endorsed McCormick, Reich, Savage, and Pedersen, is to be congratulated for the victory of these candidates, all of whom won by large pluralities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
