<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-01-27">Jan. 27, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The New Law Affecting Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0743</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0743.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-01-27">Jan. 27, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW LAW AFFECTING SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Attention, Sick Benefit Societies!</p>
   <p>The new law passed by the legislature at Springfield, Illinois, on June 27, 1927, and which is to become effective January 27, 1928, deals a death blow to our Hungarian fraternal organizations.</p>
   <p>We cannot go into a detailed explanation of the law because it consists of thirty paragraphs. However, we recommend to our sick benefit societies to take steps immediately to amend their by-laws to conform to the new law.</p>
   <p>Several societies have commissioned Joseph Fekete, Jr., attorney, to assist them in reorganization.</p>
   <p>According to the new law, a society must have at least two hundred members to allow for death and total disability claims to be paid. Such societies must <pb facs="5422061_1_0744.jpg" n="2"/>have a capital of at least one thousand dollars and must from time to time submit their books for inspection to State authorities, at the society's expense.</p>
   <p>Sick benefits in their present form are prohibited under the new law.</p>
   <p>The new method of reorganization [requires that] societies wishing to pay claims out of their own funds instead of collecting assessments from their members must have at least five hundred members and conduct their business in the same way as life insurance companies....</p>
   <p>All sick and death benefit societies must secure new charters and change their names to meet the requirements of the new law.</p>
   <p>Officers of the societies who fail to observe the new law, beginning January 27, 1928, will be prosecuted and are liable to fines ranging from twenty-five to five hundred dollars and imprisonment of thirty days to one year.</p>
   <p>Cultural, charitable, gymnastic, and other social clubs are not affected by this <pb facs="5422061_1_0745.jpg" n="3"/>new law. They don't need new charters and may continue activities under the old law of 1827.</p>
   <p>We have published only a few essential points of the new law to call the attention of the officers of societies to the necessity for immediate action to save our Hungarian organizations.</p>
   <p>We can readily see that our small societies are facing a critical phase of their existence, but with timely legal advice, the rights of the members may be assured.</p>
   <p>The First Hungarian Tarsalgo and Sick Benefit Society has already called together a special meeting for this week to discuss reorganization.</p>
   <p>This newspaper is glad to be of service to the societies, and we ask them to inform us of any change in policy and names of new officers, so that we may publish such news for the information of our readers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
