<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1928-09-23">Sept. 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Votes of the Foreign-Born</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1928-09-23">Sept. 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">VOTES OF THE FOREIGN-BORN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Daily News, in an editorial, discusses the allegations of certain politicians that the votes of the foreign-born citizens will be a decisive factor in the coming elections. The News remarks that seven and one-half million naturalized citizens will vote November 6, and that they will not be led like sheep, but will vote according to their individual beliefs.</p>
   <p>The Interpreter, a monthly publication which serves the interests of the naturalized citizens, concludes, after intense study, that the political views of the various foreign newspapers differ as widely as do those of the American publications. There is no possibility that the Polish, German, Swedish, Italian, and Hungarian naturalized citizens will cast their votes in blocs. Therefore, the Daily News sees no political problem in this question.</p>
   <p>The so-called political leaders, who claim that the people whom they represent will vote as they are told by these leaders, are wrong, because <pb facs="5422061_1_0491.jpg" n="2"/>the naturalized citizens do think for themselves and are interested in the campaign. They will vote as Americans and they are not all "wet" or "dry". There is no apparent difference in intelligence between them and the native voters.</p>
   <p>Now that the Daily News has brought up the question of the votes of the naturalized citizens, we feel it our duty to bring to light the lamentable fact that there have been persons calling themselves Hungarian political leaders who have misled political organizations. They claimed to bring in the votes if paid for their services. Year after year, especially during presidential elections, we had the opportunity to observe these individuals. They received good pay, but we doubt that the votes they were able to bring in were in proportion to the money paid them by the political parties.</p>
   <p>During the last few years Hungarian departments have been set up by the Republican party. The heads of these departments will see to it that such persons do not have the opportunity for such misrepresentations in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
