<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1931-06-14">June 14, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Back to the Land Movement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0787</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0787.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1931-06-14">June 14, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">BACK TO THE LAND MOVEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Probably there is more true appeal in the slogan "back to the land" than in any other. The movement to till the soil for a living is widespread all over the world and especially in the United States at present it is timely.</p>
   <p>This conculsion is actually true especially in the case of the Hungarian workers, who have suffered more during the year of depression than the people of other nations, if that is possible.</p>
   <p>Their condition is made bearable by the thought that they could return to their original means of livelihood, farming. The Hungariam immigrant loves the soil and knows how to till it better than any other nation's sons. Most of them emigrated, because of the shortage of land in Hungary. Through the years of laboring in the foul atomosphere of shops and factories their hearts were filled with a desire to be in the open under the clear skies and work on the land, which afforded them a more independent livelihood than the shops.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0788.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the long drawn out period of depression, many Hungarians have settled on farms, but they followed the general trend and settled either in the East or Middle West.</p>
   <p>The South was entirely disregarded until recently. We hasten to mention that the most desirable state is South Carolina. Geographically, it is located ideally. It is close to the big markets of the North. Agricultural possibilities outside of cotton and tobacco are various garden products. The climate is mild and frost occurs very rarely. The climate also has the advantage of evenness, because South Carolina has a long coast line and the Gulf Stream affects it favorably. According to official statistics, 250 days of the year can be devoted to growing, which means two crops annually. Cattle, sheep and hogs may be in the open almost the whole year. The transportation facilities of South Carolina are excellent. The whole state is interwoven by railroads and automobile roads are in the best condition.</p>
   <p>Thousands of acres of wonderful land is available. The state needs expert farmers and is more glad to have foreigners than any other state in the union.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0789.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In other words there is plenty of tillable land and not enough farmers. For this reason the sober, hard-working Hungarians are welcomed with open arms.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
