<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-02-03">Feb. 3, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Billy Sunday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_1_0038</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0038.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-02-03">Feb. 3, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">BILLY SUNDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An American author once said that Billy Sunday is the price that Americans pay for not requiring their ball players to be educated. As is well-known, Billy Sunday was once a baseball player who had an idea that the Holy Spirit descended upon him, and since then--either for the material advantages or in sincerity--he believes that he is God's special emissary in America.</p>
   <p>Billy Sunday is a typically American character. The attitude of the average citizen toward real culture, the limited education of most people, the demagogue's oratorical ability are all factors that favor him.</p>
   <p>The immaturity of American social life, in which commercial inventions are rated much higher than cultural creations, where a ball player receives <pb facs="5422061_1_0039.jpg" n="2"/>a larger salary than a university professor, the cinema star more than the country's president, etc., is an ideal ground for go-getters like Billy Sunday. Billy Sunday is a typical go-getter.</p>
   <p>While the other go-getters peddle houses, lots, tooth paste, and automobiles, Sunday and his followers sell fairy stories and, with uncouth ignorance, discuss questions which even great scientists have been unable to solve. Their methods are empty, consisting of high-sounding words that flatter their audiences and make them believe they are on the same level of intelligence with the leaders, who ridicule institutions that are above the general public and which they instinctively despise. They have no patience for criticism just like their mob audience. They are crafty because they appeal to the mob's instincts, not to its intellect.</p>
   <p>They would not deserve more attention than a street clown or soap box orator, but they are so loud that the whole nation is conscious of them.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_1_0040.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Their sermons are published in the newspapers, because it makes no difference to publishers how they become famous, whether by spreading humbug or the discovery of oil. Besides, it isn't the best policy to arouse the enmity of Billy Sunday or Mrs. McPherson by adverse criticism while they rule the masses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
