<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-01-14">Jan. 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Nice Piece of Work for Palestine</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0620</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0620.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-01-14">Jan. 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A NICE PIECE OF WORK FOR PALESTINE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Without creating a sensation, a brilliant piece of work, for Palestine has been done in Chicago, and it is worth while for our Jewish people in America to know about it.</p>
   <p>A few weeks ago the Courier received a report of a conference of Jewish Women's Organizations held on the 28th of last month at the Congress Hotel. The importance of this conference for Palestine becomes clear when the resolutions adopted by the conference are read.</p>
   <p>The resolutions are as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0621.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"As the Chicago Jewish Committee for Palestine Welfare was organized a year ago for the purpose of improving the living conditions of the affliicted Jews in Palestine, and</p>
   <p>"As the present horrors of war brought upon the Jews of Palestine destroyed the sources of business, by the European markets being closed to the products of their colonies, and threats to destroy all that has been accomplished there in the last twenty years, and</p>
   <p>"As we feel that now, more than ever, it is the duty of every Jewish woman in America to work along with the Palestine Welfare Committee and help alleviate the prevailing need, and to protect the pioneer work of our faithful comrades from destruction, therefore we <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0622.jpg" n="3"/>"Resolve: that the conference of the Jewish Women's Organizations shall decide on a Palestine Welfare Day or use other methods suitable for such a purpose, and that the funds raised on these occasions shall go for immediate relief for Palestine, shall be turned over to the Chicago Jewish Committee for Palestine Welfare. Mrs. Davis, President - Mrs. Dinkelman, Secretary."</p>
   <p>It must be remembered that the fifty Women's Organizations represented at this conference are not Zionist Organizations, - far from it, - and consequently, that to carry through this resolution required a good deal of tact and work. Mrs. Julius Rosenwald - and Mrs. Benjamin Davis, the president of the Women's Organizations, spoke heartily of Palestine at the conference.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Rosenwald is an active member and chairman of the Palestine Welfare Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
