<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-18">Aug. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Rabbis Declare Next Wednesday as Fast Day to Protest against the Persecution of Jews in Russia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0328</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0328.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-18">Aug. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO RABBIS DECLARE NEXT WEDNESDAY AS FAST DAY TO PROTEST AGAINST THE PERSECUTION OF JEWS IN RUSSIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago rabbis held a meeting last night at the Hebrew Theological College under the chairmanship of Rabbi Judah Leb Gordon. It was unanimously decided to adhere to the proclamation of the rabbis of Wilno and the Association of Rabbis of America who proclaimed next Wednesday a public fast day, as a protest against the persecution of the Jews and the Jewish religion in the Ukraine and Russia.</p>
   <p>This fast day will be observed by the Jews of all countries. Chicago Jews and the Jews of the entire world will dedicate that day to the ancient Jewish method of fighting enemies. It was also resolved that those who are not able to fast on that day should donate eighteen cents to the Help the Torah Association.</p>
   <p>It was further resolved that all rabbis should explain the significance <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0329.jpg" n="2"/>of this fast day in their sermons next Saturday in the synagogues.</p>
   <p>The proclamation, which the rabbis of Wilno have addressed to the Jews of all countries, reads: "The sufferings which we have undergone recently make us forget the terrible period of the war. Our hearts are broken by the dreadful reports which we receive from the Ukraine. Not since the time of the destruction of the Temple, have there been so many victims of hunger, of the sword, and of plagues. Besides this, there are laws against persecution of our holy religion. Internal and external enemies want to uproot the Torah; we had a similar experience in the time of the Emperor Antioch. Heders and theological seminaries are, in many places, being closed.</p>
   <p>"The Jews of all countries have the great and sacred duty of saving tens of thousands of people from terrible hunger. It is also their duty, according to law, to designate a fast day."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0330.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The proclamation requests the Jews of all countries to designate next Wednesday as a day of fasting. The proclamation is signed by Rabbi Israel Meyer Cohen (Chefetz Chaim), and Rabbi Chaim Ozer Grodensky of Wilno.</p>
   <p>The Rabbinical Association of America and Canada has issued a special appeal to the Jews of America and Canada to abide by the proclamation of the rabbis of Wilno.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
