<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-01-03">Jan. 3, 1905</date>, 7:2.
<title level="a">Jews to Assist African Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-01-03">Jan. 3, 1905</date>, 7:2.
<title level="a">JEWS TO ASSIST AFRICAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In extending a helping hand to the work of advancing the Zionist movement, which seeks to secure a legally assured home and national state for the Jewish people, the Order of the Knights of Zion at the closing session of its 7th annual convention last night decided to assist in the work of educating, protecting, and helping the Jewish people in need in this country.</p>
   <p>At the close of the convention yesterday resolutions pledging the order to loyalty to America and urging the study of American institutions and the faithful performance of the duties of American citizenship were passed unanimously, and the West Chicago Club House, 50 Throop Street, where the convention was held, resounded with cheers for several minutes.</p>
   <p>The convention reiterated the pledge of the organization to the cause of Zionism and passed resolutions that the Order of the Knights of Zion will abide by and follow the decision of the Congress of the Zionists of the world at Basel, Switzerland, next March, in regard to the offer of the British government to found a Jewish state under the sovereignty of Great Britian in Uganda, Africa is concerned.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0203.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Will Assist Chicago Jews</p>
   <p>It was resolved in accordance with several of the addresses made, that the Order of the Knights of Zion would now take more interest in the various problems which are of local interest to the Jewish people in this and other American cities. The work of founding libraries, Sabbath schools, and lectures will now be carried on more extensively and it was decided that the work of charity among the needy Jewish people should be unified and properly supervised.</p>
   <p>Prejudice against the Jewish people wherever it may exist is to be combated by bringing the truth concerning the Jewish people to the knowledge of all. The resolutions urge also that the officers of the order proceed without delay to remedy the existing evils in this and other cities which are especially injurious to the Jewish people and to see to it that attacks upon Jewish peddlers and others are stopped.</p>
   <p>Take Interest in Charter</p>
   <p>In this connection it was resolved that the organization take active part in the <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0204.jpg" n="3"/>making of new laws for Chicago and that it take special care to see that proper regulations are included in the proposed new charter to give the Jewish people protection from attacks and abuse.</p>
   <p>Hope to Dispel Prejudice</p>
   <p>"By actively participating in movements and matters which affect us as American citizens and by helping to dispel much of the prejudice against Jews among some people our order will be doing much and will still be within the true principles of Zionism," said Grand Master Zolotkoff. "We will do all in our power to help the grand cause which the late Dr. Hertzl advanced to such great proportions with the earnest and loyal co-operation of the good Jewish men from different countries. But we also take a hand in the condition of our people in this country and will work systematically to help them."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
