<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-06-22">June 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Samuel A. Ettelson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1282</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1282.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-06-22">June 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">SAMUEL A. ETTELSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Samuel A. Ettelson, who was later to become a state senator and member of the law firm of Schuyler, Jamieson &amp; Ettelson, is the son of Russian immigrants, and was born in Chicago on November 19, 1874. He received his public and high school education here, and then continued his studies at Harvard University. Adverse financial circumstances, however, necessitated the discontinuance of this study in exchange for profitable employment. He found work at the Public Library and remained there three years, during which period he attended the evening classes of the Chicago College of Law, from which he graduated in 1897. Since then, he has become a prominent member of the legal profession.</p>
   <p>His political convictions caused him to affiliate with the Republican political organization. There he encountered numerous obstructions, but nevertheless fought his way into prominence. Mr. Ettelson was captain of the Election Club of his electoral district during the year 1904. He was indorsed as candidate for State Senator by the Third Electoral District two <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1283.jpg" n="2"/>years later, and was elected by a great majority of votes. He was also chosen by the Ward Organization as Representative in the Party council. He is a member of the committee on banking and educational affairs, and committees on Cook County, insurance, legal, and tax questions, as well as on municipal administration.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ettelson is a member of the Hamilton, the New Illinois Athletic, and the Metropolitan Clubs, and is also one of the directors of the Jewish Orphanage. There he follows with great interest the development of promising talent, because he considers it his duty to give those youngsters a start on the road of life after their days at the Orphanage have ended.</p>
   <p>The passing of the bill which reduced the profit of publishers on school-books is also one of Mr. Ettelson's accomplishments.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
