<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-29">Nov. 29, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Oskar Von Miller, German Expert on Museums, Now in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0848</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0848.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-29">Nov. 29, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">OSKAR VON MILLER, GERMAN EXPERT ON MUSEUMS, NOW IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The plan for the great industrial museum which is to be permanently located in the Fine Arts Building at Jackson Park, which is now being renovated, was conceived by Julius Rosenwald, three years ago, when he visited the German museum in Munich and spoke with the designer and director of the institution, Oskar von Miller.</p>
   <p>Since then Julius Rosenwald provided five million dollars for the Chicago industrial museum, but he desired once more to secure the advice of the German scientist, and, therefore, invited Dr. von Miller to be his guest in Chicago. The Doctor arrived yesterday at 7:40, accompanied by his daughter, Lulu von Bomhard, and will remain for four days.</p>
   <p>Dr. von Miller informed a representative of the Abendpost that he had travelled to Tokio as the German delegate of the World conference, and, subsequently, accepted Rosenwald's invitation, visiting Honolulu, San Francisco, and finally <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0849.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago. He is highly interested in the Rosenwald project, primarily because the German museum in Muenchen, created by Dr. Von Miller, inspired the American Maecenas to establish a similar institution here. Dr. von Miller declared unhesitatingly that the American endeavor is destined to be superior to the German prototype. There is more money available to meet the necessary requirements, and there is also a model to help eliminate the mistakes made. The Rosenwald structure may therefore be the best of its kind in existence.</p>
   <p>Dr. von Miller and his daughter....saw the sights of the City yesterday and were feted.....In the evening they attended a banquet, given in honor of Dr. von Miller by Dr. Hugo F. Simon, German consul general.</p>
   <p>After a day of rest on Saturday, Doctor von Miller will visit the Fine Arts Building on Sunday and see the building which is to be the future industrial museum. He also told the reporter of the Abendpost that he had been invited to visit Philadelphia, Washington, and New York, and asked to relate his experiences since similar institutions have been planned in these cities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
