<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-16">Aug. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Levy Mayer and Mr. Fishkin Dead]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0991</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0991.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-16">Aug. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[LEVY MAYER AND MR. FISHKIN DEAD]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two Jews died in Chicago this week: one was a great and celebrated man, the other--the other was unknown; one was a millionaire, the other--a poor man. I refer to Levy Mayer and Mr. Fishkin. One earned half-a-million dollars a year, the other thirty dollars a week during the busy season, nothing in slack time. One lived like a prince, the other like a beggar. But one was only a lawyer and a businessman, while the other was full of great hope for the future of his people and of Palestine. The mind and the heart of one spoke only the language of numbers, the mind and the heart of the other spoke the language of sweet dreams and hopes, the music of the future. One worked, made money, plenty of money, millions of dollars--and died suddenly, so suddenly that he did not even have time to think about his death--which is very bad. The other hoped and dreamed all his life of the redemption of Palestine for the Jews, and lived to see his dream being realized, so that he died with a smile of satisfaction on his lips. Which of them was happier, the one who <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0992.jpg" n="2"/>was poor or the one who was rich--that question is too difficult for me to answer.</p>
   <p>I am convinced that in the life after death different questions are asked now than were asked previously. The first question that was asked of a Jew in the past when he arrived in the True World was: "Mr. Jew, have you behaved conscientiously?" (I know this on good authority--the Talmud itself.) This, as I have said, happened in olden times when the Jews did not think about their future, when everybody lived only for himself and worried only about his own affairs. Nowadays, it is different. Today every Jew has other business besides his own. Today, thank God, the Jews are busy with Jewish affairs, with the Jewish future, with Palestine. I believe that today in the True World they do not ask the old question any more, that is whether or not one has acted honestly; today, they ask a new question: "Have you done anything for your people and their future, have you done anything for Judaism, for Jewish interests?"</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0993.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When poor Fishkin appears before God and has to answer the question: "What have you done for your people?" he need have no fear. He gave twenty dollars a week for Jewish purposes out of his thirty dollars, but when Mr. Mayer appears before God and is asked the same question, what will he answer? He will remain silent and he will be afraid of the judgment of the Lord.</p>
   <p>What share did the Jewish people have of his millions while he lived, and what share will they have now that he is dead? None. The Jewish people received from Fishkin everything that poor Fishkin could give: his last penny, his last ounce of energy--everything, everything.</p>
   <p>Judaism will not disappear as long as there are Fishkins in this world. Judaism wouldn't last twenty-four hours if all the Jews were like Levy Mayer.</p>
   <p>The death of Levy Mayer will be lamented by lawyers and businessmen; the death of Fishkin will be lamented by all of us--by all the Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
