<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1900-02-24">February 24, 1900</date>. p.61.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1501</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1501.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1900-02-24">February 24, 1900</date>. p.61.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. I. K. Friedman, whose latest work "Poor People" will be ready for the public on Mar. 3rd, was born in Chicago. His family has always been affiliated with Dr. Hirsch's Congregation. He was graduated from the public schools of this city. Later, he started a post-graduate course at the University of Chicago, in philosophy and English. He soon tired of too much studying and left the University at the end of three months to enter his brother's florist shop.</p>
   <p>While learning the florist trade, he spent his evenings traveling through the long tracts of Chicago's slums. He probably knows the underside of Chicago as well as any one man in the city. The series of short stories, "The Lucky Number," published in 1896 was the immediate result of his observations and adventures. The book met with favorable acceptance, and the critics pronounced it original and powerful.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1502.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Friedman found business distasteful and left the flower shop to do newspaper work, a year and a half ago. He has been a special writer for the Chicago papers since then. His articles on the Chicago Ghetto, which appeared in the Tribune, won considerable praise for him.</p>
   <p>The author wearied of dealing with the lowest type of humanity and resolved to move up a peg and study tenement life. "Poor People," his second book and first novel, is the result. The book was begun and finished in a little over two months and has just been published. Mr. Friedman is conversant with ghetto folk and lore, and he has written a group of ghetto tales.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
