<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-08">May 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Successor of Rabbi Hirsch</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. B. Komaiko</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0956</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0956.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-08">May 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE SUCCESSOR OF RABBI HIRSCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. B. Komaiko</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the hour when the late Emil G. Hirsch was brought to eternal rest, the Jewish people not only of Chicago but also of other cities, raised the question: Who will be his successor?</p>
   <p>Speculations were made for such as Dr. Stephen S. Wise, Rabbi Nathan Cross, Reverend Dr. Ellenow, Abba Hillel Silver, and others who enjoy a good reputation among Reform Jews and liberal Christians.</p>
   <p>It is not our task to give an exact account of what the late Rabbi Hirsch accomplished for Judaism. We will say with firm assurance that he accomplished very little for the youth of his congregation, from whom he kept aloof. He addressed thousands of meetings with his marvelous oratorical power. At meetings called by Reform Jews, he would cut up the Orthodox Jewry; on the other <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0957.jpg" n="2"/>hand, when among the Orthodox, he would kibosh his Reform sheep. But he was always a hot nationalist when he addressed a Christian meeting.</p>
   <p>Whenever Dr. Hirsch spoke to Christians, he never failed to remind them of their debt to the Jews...</p>
   <p>For nearly half a century, he was the most popular orator in the Middle Western States. That is why everyone waited with much curiosity to see who would be appointed as his successor. And this curiosity turned into surprise when the Chicago newspapers carried the news that Rabbi Louis L. Mann, of Mishkan Israel Congregation of New Haven, would occupy the pulpit of Sinai Temple, from whence the mighty Dr. Hirsch had for many years thundered and stormed.</p>
   <p>Who is the thirty-three year old rabbi who has been suddenly promoted to a salary of fifteen thousand dollars a year (which means more)? We haven't heard of him as much as we have heard of Abba Hillel Silver or others.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0958.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These and other remarks can now be heard everywhere.</p>
   <p>Before we go somewhat into the personality of Dr. Louis L. Mann, it is necessary to mention that he is the son-in-law of Alfred M. Cohen, president of the Board of Governors of the Cincinnati Hebrew Union College.</p>
   <p>If the father-in-law helped his son-in-law in this match, let us congratulate him, as well as the Sinai Temple, because Dr. Mann belongs to the young generation of Reform Rabbis who are gradually bringing traditional Judaism back home.</p>
   <p>Dr. Mann was born thirty-three years ago in Louisville, Kentucky, of typically Jewish parents. While he attended both public and high school, he also studied Hebrew. At the age of seventeen he entered the Hebrew Union College in Cincinnati where in the course of his studies he learned the Talmud from the noted scholar Rabbi Shochet.</p>
   <p>In 1914 when Professor Getheil's book, Zionism, was published, Dr. Mann, then <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0959.jpg" n="4"/>still a student, gave a friendly review of the book, for which the enemy of Zionism, Phillipson, one of his instructors, expressed his dissatisfaction. Dr. Mann then replied, "Whether we like it or not, the Zionist movement came here to stay."</p>
   <p>After he graduated from the Hebrew Union College, he attended John Hopkins University, where he received his Ph.D. His seven years of services at the Congregation Mishkan Israel, New Haven, Connecticut, are highly commendable. Being at the same time professor of social ethics at Yale University, it enabled him to work for the Menorah, an organization for Jewish students. He has done a great deal in that organization by the way of making the Jewish students remain devoted to our traditions and acquainted with our history.</p>
   <p>As a speaker he is very impressive and wins the confidence of his listeners. He is honorable and friendly. He dislikes publicity. He believes in constructive work and feels that it is much more important, at the present moment, for <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0960.jpg" n="5"/>the progressive rabbis to work in their own backyard rather than wander in foreign pastures.</p>
   <p>The writer of these lines had the opportunity to read a letter written by Dr. Mann to a friend, in which he states:</p>
   <p>"Let us hope that the day will come when the Union prayer book will again embrace those sweet prayers that have been forgotten".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
