<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-07-29">July 29, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Zionist Membership Campaign in Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0350</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0350.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-07-29">July 29, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE ZIONIST MEMBERSHIP CAMPAIGN IN CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have often referred to the deplorable fact that in a city like Chicago, with a Jewish population of 300,000, there are only 1,000 registered Zionists. It would be ridiculous to assume that out of the 300,000 in Chicago, only 1,000 believe in Zionism. It is our firm conviction that all the non-reform and all the non-radical Jews are animated by strong Jewish sentiments and take a sympathetic attitude to Zionism. Thousands of them are Zionists by conviction and thousands of others are ready to help the Zionist movement though they know little about it. The main idea underlying the Zionist movement is known to nearly every Jewish adult. If approached in the right spirit, they would certainly come to aid Zionism, but before we can bring these <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0351.jpg" n="2"/>thousands of Jews in Chicago to the aid of the Zionist movement, we must first enroll them as members of the organization, in Chicago. Zionism is not a movement of recent date. In its present form it is already thirty years old and there isn't a Jew in Chicago who hasn't listened at least once to a Zionist speaker...and to this end the Zionist leaders in Chicago have decided to inaugurate a quick and snappy Zionist membership campaign to last a fortnight, in the hope that they will be able to enroll thousands of Chicago Jews as members....</p>
   <p>We do not doubt the Jewishness of the average Jew in Chicago. We believe that he is always willing to do his share for his people and therefore we do not doubt the success of the membership campaign....</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0352.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The success of the membership campaign depends also on the zeal, energy, and determination of the active Zionists....</p>
   <p>They may not all exhibit sufficient energy because of the assumption, after the decision of Sam Remo and the appointment of Sir Robert Samuels as High Commissioner of Palestine, that Zionist activities must consist of raising money for the Keren Hayesod.</p>
   <p>We wish to tell our active Zionists that this is an absolutely false assumption. The Zionist organization is still called upon to do political work and must exhibit more strength in order to enable the leaders to carry out the Balfour declaration. The power behind the declaration is not only Great Britain and the good will of the Western powers but <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0353.jpg" n="4"/>the Zionist organization, and without the latter the Balfour declaration would remain a scrap of paper. The Zionist movement is still confronted with many dangerous enemies from within and without, and if we let up, if we stop organizing our forces, the enemies of Zionism will scare success after success and the very life of Zionism will be jeopardized.</p>
   <p>The Balfour declaration is at present a document only and,as long as it is a document and not a reality, the Zionists in every locality are in duty bound to do their utmost for their organization, in order to strengthen the hands of the leaders. We still need the masses of the Jewish people to uphold our cause. It is therefore the sacred duty of every active Zionist in Chicago to participate in the coming membership drive, to do his very best to sell as many membership cards as possible. We can easily reach the old members but it is a more difficult task to enroll new ones.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0354.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>There are some 200 active Zionists in this city, all of them of standing and position, and there isn't one of them who is unable to sell 10 membership cards within a fortnight. Many of them can do more than that....</p>
   <p>Even then, of course, Zionism in Chicago will not be a mass movement, but if we have 3,000 enrolled members in good standing, the Zionist leaders will be in a position to start some real work. The Zionist administration in the city knows perfectly well what every Zionist can do in the way of enrolling members and does not mean to accept excuses and apologies, but will insist that the active Zionists do their duty....</p>
   <p>We must have a minimum of 3,000 members within a fortnight. We can have them if every Zionist in Chicago does his duty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
