<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-03-01">March 1, 1906</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1355</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1355.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-03-01">March 1, 1906</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Berthold Loewenthal Prominent Business Man Died.</p>
   <p>Berthold Loewenthal, an old settler and prominent business man died today, in his residence at 1829 Indiana Ave. He was born on August 6, 1830 at Michringen, Wurtemberg, and came to the U. S. A. in the year 1850 and lived for a short time at Cincinnati. He then went to Rock Island, where he founded the firm Block and Loewenthal and later took a partnership with the Rock Island Plow Factory. In the years 1856-1858 he was a member of the City Council of Rock Island. He came to Chicago in 1863, where he formed the firm B. Loewenthal and Co., incorporating the Garden City Tobacco Works. Shortly before the great Chicago fire he became a partner of the International Mutual Trust Co. and was elected President in the year 1870. The name of the bank was changed to International Bank in the year 1872. He was President of this bank until 1898 when the bank was incorporated with the Continental National Bank. He also had been elected as a Director of this bank, which office he kept until his death.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1356.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the years 1875-1882 he was a member of the Municipal Council for Libraries, and in the years 1877-79, treasurer of the West Park Board. For ten years he was President and for twenty-six years one of the directors and treasurer of the Chicago Sinai Congregation. He was also President of the Standard Club and treasurer and director of the Jewish Old Age Home. During 1870-1872 he was President of the United Hebrew Charities and for years was a member and director of the board. In the year 1861 he married Miss Nannie Kaufmann. He is mourned by his widow and two children, Mrs. Julia Wolf, wife of Albert H. Wolf, and Julius W. Loewenthal. Both live in Chicago. He lost four children by death. Mr. Loewenthal was ill since years but has maintained his intellectual energies until his death.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
