<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-12">Apr. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The People and the University</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-12">Apr. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE PEOPLE AND THE UNIVERSITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the Rabbinical conference held early this week in Chicago, the topic of a Hebrew University in Jerusalem was brought up for consideration in a wholly different and [rather] indirect manner. Although the Zionist National Movement still has many opponents among the spiritual leaders of Reformed Judaism, yet the motion for a Hebrew University in Jerusalem has almost no opposition.</p>
   <p>This was noted from the replies made by Dr. E. G. Hirsch to the enthusiastic appeal of Ethmor-Ben-Abbah for the New Palestine. What Dr. Hirsch said reads about as follows:</p>
   <p>"I am an American Jew and I have a right to be a Jew in America. There exists and there will continue to exist an American Judaism; there is a French, a <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0561.jpg" n="2"/>German and a Russian Judaism; and Judaism exists also in other countries. Let there also be a Palestinian Judaism.</p>
   <p>"Let there be a Jewish state in Palestine, which can develop Judaism under its own free, political, economic and cultural conditions. Such a Judaism undoubtedly will contribute something of value to World Jewry. As far as the establishment of a Hebrew University in a cultural center is concerned, no one would oppose it--on the contrary, World Jewry would support it. We will support such a spiritual center, even though our flag is the Stars and Stripes."</p>
   <p>Every Zionist, who possesses common sense, can agree with a clear conscience to what Dr. Hirsch said thus far. If the remarks of Dr. Hirsch are not comprehensive enough, it is not the fault of Dr. Hirsch, but rather of all other so-called cultural Zionists who fancy that a cultural center can be developed without a political and economic base.</p>
   <p>No scientific knowledge is required to see that a nation's culture is the <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0562.jpg" n="3"/>total of its experiences and accomplishments in the various branches of human endeavor. Its culture is the substance of the nation's accumulated wisdom of the past and its living influence in the present--for the development of that influence in the future. The thinker, the artist, the inventor, the poet, all of them must draw their sustenance from the life around them and answer to the demands of that life. In no university or cultural center in the world, can a branch of activity be developed that has no basis in the national life around it. Medical science, jurisprudence, theology and even philosophy are the products of life and its movement, for if they are not, then they remain sterile, without concrete value.</p>
   <p>So long as there is no active Jewish life in Palestine which may grow and develop freely, so long will there be no university in Jerusalem which can develop. At the most, such an institution could concern itself only with the wisdom of the past, but could have no bearing upon life itself.</p>
   <p>A Hebrew University in Jerusalem cannot be a so-called Yeshivah, concerning <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0563.jpg" n="4"/>itself only with what Jews have said and done in times past. It must build a connecting link between the past [and the present]--it must influence the future while at the same time it draws its spiritual sustenance from the Jewish life around it. It must answer all the practical, material and spiritual problems which life presents as accurately as is done by universities of all civilized nations.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the reply of Rabbi Julius Liebert of South Bend to Dr. Hirsch's remarks was strikingly apropos. "We are not Christian Scientists," he said, "and cannot imagine in the least how such a spiritual center can exist without a live nation from which to draw sustenance and to influence in return."</p>
   <p>If a motion for a Hebrew University in Jerusalem can be proposed and discussed, then thanks must be given to our first "Chalutzim" and to the activity of the Zionist Movement, which laid the basis for a Jewish political and economic life in Palestine. It was a very limited life, free only as far as the <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0564.jpg" n="5"/>whims of the Turkish Government permitted, but still the life of a people in miniature form. This life created Hebrew schools in the colonies, established the Hebrew Gymnasium (high school) in Tel Aviv and the "Tachkemani" in Jaffa. If not for the War, the Jewish colony would have established by now, if not a university, at least some vocational institutes, especially those which had a direct bearing upon life as it existed before the War--for instance, agriculture, chemistry, mathematics, commerce etc. After the War, if Jewish colonies are to be established, and the Jewish people to have the opportunity to rebuild the country as a free people, unhindered and unhampered by outside forces, developing their own political and economic life, then surely the new circumstances will require more advanced cultural centers than existed previously.</p>
   <p>The point we are trying to make here is that there cannot be growing and living cultural centers without an awakened people functioning freely.</p>
   <p>This opinion is in agreement with the words which we have so often and at every opportunity spoken, that some Jews are political Zionists without <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0565.jpg" n="6"/>knowing anything about it. Every "cultural Zionist" who declares that he is not a political Zionist contradicts himself. Nation and culture are inseparable, and if a culture is to be a live and growing thing, it must come from a people who are also alive and who possess the essentials of a living nation--territory, language and political independence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
