<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-04-04">April 4, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A Plan</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-04-04">April 4, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A PLAN</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(EDITORIAL)</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A young man who is very much interested in the Zionist movement, came to us the other day with a plan to help those Jews who want to settle in Palestine, but are lacking in the necessary means to carry out their plans. He proposes to get together a group of a thousand Zionists, of which each one would only have to pay ten cents a week. The work of collections, bookkeeping, etc., should be done by the members, themselves, without cost. Thus, within a year's time, approximately five-thousand dollars would accumulate in the treasury of the group. Then a drawing would take place, and the member that would draw the lucky number would receive, out of the organization's treasury, a farm in Palestine, with all farm implements, and also, traveling expenses for himself and his family. The money that the organization would expend on this member should be paid back in the course of ten years or longer, without interest. Until the entire amount is paid, the farm would belong to the organization. But in case the lucky member is not willing or is not ready to go to Palestine, he may have the privilege to transfer his claims to whomever he wants, but on the same conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0159.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We like that scheme very much, and for that reason, we consider it a duty to publish it. We can readily see the difficulty of bringing together a thousand members and to keep them together, or to hold the group in such a way as to insure at least, a thousand members at all times. The collection of money is another difficulty, but they are not inevitable difficulties that cannot be overcome. We are convinced that a group of active young men and women interested in the cause, could be successful in such an undertaking if they would go after it. When such a group would only last one year, and would really make it possible for a family to acquire a farm, many other groups would soon organize on a similar scale in different cities of America, and the cause of settling Jews in Palestine would bring about great approval and success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
