<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Vol.32,Wk.of <date when="1906-10-06">Oct. 6,1906</date>, Pp. 229--230.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1347</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1347.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Vol.32,Wk.of <date when="1906-10-06">Oct. 6,1906</date>, Pp. 229--230.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Joseph W. Errant is the Independent Candidate for Judge. Mr. Errant was born in North Carolina, on April 13, 1860. In 1874 he came to Chicago, and was an assistant in the Chicago Public Library until 1884. He studied law at Northwestern University, and, at the same time, taught in an evening school. He was admitted to the Bar in 1886, and has been engaged in general practice ever since. He is the author of the pamphlet entitled "Law Relating to Mercantile Agencies" and other treatises.</p>
   <p>From 1886 to 1888, he was the Attorney of the Protective Agency for Women and Children, and in 1888, founded the Bureau of Justice. The object of this Bureau was to secure legal protection for the friendless and the poor, to improve methods of procedure in the Courts,and also to establish a new order of courts in place of the Justice and Police Courts. He was engaged in this work from 1888 to 1893, and has also been active in the work of the Illinois Conference of Charities and Corrections. He was a member of the Chicago Board of Education from 1894 to 1897, and of the Civil Service Commission from May, 1893 to July 1906. He has also been President of the Commission.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1348.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He is a member of the Chicago and Illinois State Bar Associations, Illinois State Teachers Association, and the National Education Association. He is also affiliated with the Iroquois, Jefferson, City, Chicago Literary, and Law Clubs. He is a contributor to the Associated Jewish Charities and the Jewish Publication Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
