<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-06">Jan. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Honoring a Jewish Public Worker</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1029</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1029.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-06">Jan. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">HONORING A JEWISH PUBLIC WORKER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Joint Distribution Committee, of which Mr. B. Horwich is chairman and S. J. Rosenblatt the vice-chairman and active chairman during the relief campaign because of the absence of the former, and the Zionist Central Committee of Chicago representing all the Zionists in Chicago will tender a banquet to Mr. B. Horwich, the indefatigable relief worker and Zionist who has rendered great service to both causes and who has served loyally and faithfully the cause of relief since its inception and the Zionist movement. Mr. B. Horwich has in addition rendered great service to the Jewish community in Chicago and may be considered one of its pillars. If not for him many an important necessary institution in Chicago would not have been created. Mr. B. Horwich is actually the man of the Chicago Zionists, having been the first chairman of the first Zionist society established here some thirty years ago.</p>
   <p>At the time when Mr. B. Horwich convened the first Zionist meeting in Chicago <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1030.jpg" n="2"/>there was no Zionism in America at all. The Jewish generation of thirty years ago knew nothing of Zionism and knew nothing of the Jewish national movement. The bulk of our people at that time was mostly concerned with obtaining civil and political rights in Russia and the carrying out of the emancipation decrees in various European countries. It testifies to the farsightedness and political vision of Mr. B. Horwich that at the time when there was no Zionism in America at all, when there was even no talk of Jewish nationalism, he had already conceived the idea of Zionism and made an attempt to lay the foundation for the Zionist organization in Chicago and in America. A man of such farsightedness and such political vision and such energy and power of enterprise is a credit to our people and especially a credit to Chicago Jewry, and for this deed alone he deserves all the honor that can be bestowed upon a distinguished citizen.</p>
   <p>But Mr. Horwich has done much more than that for the Jewish community in Chicago and for Jewry in general. During his long career as a public worker he has participated in every Jewish movement, made himself useful for every great Jewish cause. He was, and still is, closely connected with every Jewish organization <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1031.jpg" n="3"/>and institution in Chicago and is still a leading relief worker and leading Zionist worker and a leading charity worker. It is no exaggeration to say that nothing Jewish is strange to his mind. He has not only a heart for his people and an understanding for their needs and troubles, but he has also an understanding of all the finer things in Jewish life and he is as greatly concerned with the cultural life of our people, as he is concerned with its political and economic welfare, for which too he deserves praise and honor because there are very few Jewish leaders in America who understand that a people like ours with its long and venerable cultural traditions cannot live on bread alone. A people like ours must always be spiritually active and alert in order to continue its great traditions. Mr. Horwich understands this well and therefore whenever he has a opportunity to do something for the finer things Jewish, for Jewish literature, for Jewish journalism, for Jewish scholarship he is always glad to do his share.</p>
   <p>As a relief worker Mr. B. Horwich accomplished wonders, both in the field of collecting and distributing money. Prior to the concluding of the Armstice <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1032.jpg" n="4"/>he concentrated all his efforts on soliciting and collecting funds for the relief, and since the conclusion of the Armistice he has visited Europe three times and has distinguished himself as a distributor of these funds. Wherever he came he made the Jewish community of Chicago popular, and his service in this field of Jewish philanthropic endeavor has been recognized by the Joint Distribution Committee and by all those who are interested in relief work. His devotion to the great cause, his alertness of mind, his wit have saved many a Jew and Jewess in the war and pogrom stricken countries from total annihilation, and whatever it is possible for one individual man to do in this field of work, he did. He disregarded his own health, his own interests, and his own time to come to the rescue of those whose last hope he was, and he accomplished his mission splendidly. The observations he made in Eastern Europe during his journeys there proved to be very valuable to the Joint Distribution Committee, and many of his suggestions have been adopted by the Joint Distribution Committee and acted upon. There are not many men like B. Horwich in the community, there are not many men like him among all the three million Jews in America. If there were, Judaism in America would <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1033.jpg" n="5"/>be much better off than it is and our communal and cultural life would be much different from what it is now. As a whole we have more communal leaders and better communal workers in Chicago than in New York, and we dare say that if not for Chicago's contributions to the cause of relief in men and money, none of the relief drives would be very successful. Mr. B. Horwich is one of the Chicago set of splendid relief workers, whose efforts, deeds and successes in the field of relief are a source of inspiration not only to Chicago Jewry but to the Jewry at large.</p>
   <p>Next Wednesday, January 11th, the representative men and women of the community will gather at Gold's Pompeian Banquet Hall to do honor to Mr. B. Horwich. He surely deserves this honor, because he has rendered great and yeoman service to the Chicago Jewish community, to the cause of relief, to the Zionist movement, and to the Jewish people at large. Honor to whom honor is due.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
