<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
Vol. 21, Wk. of <date when="1901-05-04">May 4, 1901</date>. p.394.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Vol. 21, Wk. of <date when="1901-05-04">May 4, 1901</date>. p.394.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Isidor Baumgartl was born in Hungary in 1860. At the age of 11 he came to America and settled in Chicago. When he was 17 he started his apprenticeship in business with Joseph Stein and Co., wholesale liquor dealers. In 1879, upon the death of the senior member, he was admitted to the firm, forming the partnership of Stein and Baumgartl. The organization prospered and in 1889 Mr. Baumgartl, with his associates, formed the Calumet Distilling Co., built a distillery at New Chicago, a suburb of this city, and founded a small village surrounding the plant.</p>
   <p>The distillery was operated until the Whisky Trust purchased it in 1891. In October of that year he incorporated the Monarch Brewing Co., erecting a large plant at 21st St. and Western Ave. This company was operated with such success that, in 1898, the plant was purchased by an American syndicate, and together with twelve other breweries, merged into the United Breweries Co.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1423.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The syndicate induced Mr. Baumgartl to accept the management of the company and he was elected president and general manager. He is still at the head of this vast enterprise.</p>
   <p>In 1900 he incorporated the Art Wall Paper Mills and erected a plant covering an entire block, and as president, he is bending his energies to make it the foremost wall paper mill in the United States.</p>
   <p>He was a member of the Board of Zion Congregation and is now connected with Isiah Congregation. He is also treasurer of the A. J. C.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
