<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-09">Feb. 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Rabbi Fisher's Twenty Years of Activity in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0965</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0965.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-09">Feb. 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">RABBI FISHER'S TWENTY YEARS OF ACTIVITY IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As has been previously announced in the Courier, Rabbi Moshe Fisher will soon leave Chicago for Detroit, where he will occupy the pulpit of the Hungarian Congregation Bnai Moshe. Rabbi Fisher is one of our pioneer rabbis, who came to Chicago at a time when the Chicago Jewry was just beginning to grow and expand. He participated in the development of the Orthodox Jewry here, helping with all his energy and sincerity to strengthen traditional Judaism, and to direct the course of those institutions which seek to administer to those who are deficient in Jewish faith and Jewish knowledge.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Fisher came to Chicago twenty-four years ago, to become rabbi of the Congregation Agudoth Achim Anshe Hungary and to serve as spiritual leader of the Hungarian [Jewish] community. This congregation on Maxwell Street near 14th Street asked the great Rabbi Simcha Safir of Pressburg [Bratislava] to provide the congregation with a spiritual leader, and the great rabbi, with whom Rabbi Fisher studied and from whom he received his rabbinical degree, found <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0966.jpg" n="2"/>no one who was more suitable and competent for this important position than his pupil, Rabbi Fisher. Rabbi Fisher was twenty-four years of age when he came here.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Fisher devoted all of his time to the task of improving and consolidating his congregation, and the Jewish community of Chicago as well. Thanks to his active work, the congregation soon began to grow, and three years later the membership built a large temple on Marshfield Avenue and Polk Street, which was the most beautiful district in Chicago seventeen years ago. Rabbi Fisher was also instrumental in bringing into being the Home for the Aged, of which he was a director; the Federated Charities of which he acted as a director for as long as it existed; the Mount Sinai Hospital; the Hebrew Theological College, and other institutions. He also devoted a large part of his time to the Adas Bnai Israel, an Orthodox youth organization, whose aim it is to attract the Jewish youth to the Jewish people and Jewish traditions.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Fisher participated in the Zionist movement and used all his influence and energy in behalf of this great Jewish ideal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0967.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Rabbi Fisher is not only a Hebrew scholar, but he is a man of considerable secular knowledge as well. He acquired his knowledge of Hebrew literature in the Pressburg Theological College, and his secular knowledge through private instruction. He is the son of Rabbi Emres Fisher, a rabbi in the city of Paks, Hungary, and a grandson of Rabbi Safir of the same city. His older brother, Rabbi Ephraim Fisher, is a rabbi in another town in Hungary and a younger brother, Rabbi Yoel Simcha Fisher, is rabbi of the Ohavah Tzedek Congregation, on Claremont Avenue in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Fisher told this correspondent: "I regret that I must leave the Jewish community of Chicago, which has many large Jewish institutions. I refer particularly to the Hebrew Theological Seminary, where I had hoped to educate my children. I envy the rabbis and civic leaders who are privileged to continue their work for Jewish knowledge. I hope that God will give me an opportunity to build such institutions in my new circle of influence."</p>
   <p>Rabbi Fisher is sorry to leave Chicago, and the Jewish community of Chicago certainly regrets the departure of one of its spiritual leaders and builders.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
