<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-04-01">April 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Professor Kallen - Zionist Agitator</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-04-01">April 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">PROFESSOR KALLEN - ZIONIST AGITATOR</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Zionists of Chicago are carrying on Zionist propaganda, and they are more active in their work this week, which is the week of the Passover holidays. A special Zion propaganda meeting arranged for the last two days of the Passover holidays, where Professor Kallen of the University of Wisconsin will be the main speaker in the interest of Zionism.</p>
   <p>This Friday evening is the opening of the first propaganda meeting at which Professor Kallen will be the speaker of the hour. He will also speak at a series of Zionist mass meetings. This series of mass meetings is sponsored by the Order of Knights of Zion, and this propaganda is mainly to get the Reformed Jews of the city interested in Zionism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0132.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So these meetings of course will be held in the Reform Jewish synagogues in different parts of the city. Professor Kallen in his previous lecture on "Bazalel," evening the 25th of last February, greatly inspired the audience with his logical and deep-thinking studies of the Jewish national question. He, by his philosophical explanation, also showed the audience the necessity for a Jewish nation for the realization of Jewish ideals. Immediately after that "Bazalel" meeting an organization was formed by the local Zionists to get together on a plan of organizing a series of mass meetings among the reformed Jewish element and to explain to them the meaning of Jewish nationalism.</p>
   <p>In addition to these lectures by Professor Kallen at these mass meetings, Mr. Max Shulman, the Grand Master of the Order Knights of Zion, will also speak.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0133.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Shulman is the one who deserves the credit of obtaining the honorable Mr. Kallen to come here to Chicago to lecture at this series of mass meetings in assisting the cause of Zionism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
