<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-11-05">Nov. 5, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Leon Mandel Dies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1269</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1269.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-11-05">Nov. 5, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">LEON MANDEL DIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After a prolonged illness of a year or more, Mr. Leon Mandel, the well known millionaire and philanthropist passed away, in Atlantic City. He was the founder of the Training School and one of the founders of the Associated Jewish Charities. Mr. Leon Mandel, President of Mandel Bros. passed away today at 2:30 P.M. at the age of 70 years.</p>
   <p>He leaves a wife and seven daughters who were at his beside for the last week until the end.</p>
   <p>Mr. Mandel was born September 10, 1841 in Kercheit, Germany. With his mother and four brothers, he came to Chicago in 1852. Three years later he formed a partnership with his brother, Simon Mandel, in a small dry goods store on Clark and Van Buren, which was destroyed in the big fire of 1871. Their second venture in business was again destroyed in another big fire in 1874.</p>
   <p>Their third business was opened on 121 State St. where the big department <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1270.jpg" n="2"/>store now stands. Mr. Mandel was very active in Jewish welfare organizations in Chicago. Twenty-five years ago, he realized the importance of having a training school in Chicago and with some very large donations was able to accomplish the building of this great Jewish training school in Chicago. He was also chairman of the building committee of Michael Reese Hospital. He was one of the first organizers of the United Jewish Charities and was also very active in city civic matters, contributing liberally to Grand Opera. He built Mandel Hall which is now a part of the University of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The funeral services will take place Tuesday evening at Mr. Mandel's home, 3409 Michigan Blvd. Rabbi Hirsch will conduct the funeral services, the deceased being vice-president of Sinai Temple and life long friend of Dr. Hirsch, Rabbi of the Temple. Burial at Rose Hill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
