<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-12-04">Dec. 4, 1905</date>, 8:3.
<title level="a">Jew's Day of Sorrow</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0699</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0699.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-12-04">Dec. 4, 1905</date>, 8:3.
<title level="a">JEW'S DAY OF SORROW</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reformed and orthodox Jews in all parts of the world to-day will join in commemorating by prayer and fasting and special services in synagogue and temple the slaughter of 15,000 and maiming of 100,000 Jews in the recent massacres in Russia. In the United States the observance of the memorial day will follow a form prescribed by the central conference of American rabbis. In many respects it will be the service and prayers for the dead prescribed more than 4,000 years ago. It will include the intoning by the cantors of the 44th Psalm and the 5th chapter of the Lamentations of Jeremiah and the prayers repeated at Yom Kippur.</p>
   <p>Business To Be Suspended</p>
   <p>At the Reformed temples special song service will mark the commemoration as well. Union memorial services will be held at 8 o'clock this evening at Isaiah Temple on the South Side and at the Temple Anshe Emeth on the North Side. At the former the services will be conducted by Dr. Joseph Stolz. The speakers will be Dr. E. G. Hirsch, Dr. Tobias Schanfarber, Dr. A. Yudelson, Dr. Abram Hirschberg and Dr. A. J. Messing. At Temple Anshe Emeth the speakers will be Dr. S. H. Bauer and Dr. Emanual Schreiber.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0700.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On the West Side among the orthodox Jews the commemoration will begin at 2 o'clock this afternoon. All Jewish shops, stores, and factories in the district between Canal and Robey streets and Madison and 18th streets will be closed from 2 until 6 P. M. In thirty five orthodox Jewish synagogues on the West Side special services will be held from 2 o'clock until 6. Besides the religious worship there will be speeches by orthodox rabbis, pastors of the Reformed temples and by laymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
