<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-06-22">June 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A.J. Sabath Achieves Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1280</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1280.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-06-22">June 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A.J. SABATH ACHIEVES SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A.J. Sabath was born in 1866 in Bohemia of Jewish parents, and with their consent, emigrated to America, when only 14 years of age. His earnest effort and patience, remarkable for one so young, were crowned with success. After putting foot on our soil, he came directly to Chicago, finding employment as a messenger boy in a shoe store at 18th and Halsted Streets. There he remained eight years, during which period he proved himself a valuable member of the business, and for which he was rewarded by rapid promotions, with the final appointment as business manager. In addition to his occupation, he did not neglect the continuation of his education. Then in 1887, he established a paint business in partnership with friends. Unfortunately, impaired health, as the result of his occupation, forced him to withdraw from that business two years later.</p>
   <p>As he regarded a thorough business education most essential, he enlisted as student in a business college. Being of the untiring type, he founded the Real Estate firm of Sabath &amp; Schlesinger in 1892. But the partnership <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1281.jpg" n="2"/>was dissolved in the year following, leaving the business transactions entirely upon him, which he conducted, nevertheless, with marked success until 1895.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, he made great progress in the study of law, receiving his degree as Jurist in 1891. [L.L.B. Lake Forest University, Who's Who. Editor's note.] He was appointed by Governor Altgeld as Justice of Peace in 1895, upon the recommendation of a group of Justices. As a humanitarian, Mr. Sabath has won the admiration of every citizen. Furthermore, this fact was responsible for the achievement of his excellent reputation as Justice of Peace, and as the presiding Jurist in the Police Court. He was elected Congressman in 1906, and twice reelected. During those times, he declined to accept offers of Judgeship in the Municipal Court. It is needless to say that his family rejoined him here as soon as circumstances permitted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
