<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>American Jewish Year Book</title>,
5664, <date when="1904-09-09">September 22, 1903 to September 9, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Edited by Cyrus Adler</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1376</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1376.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The American Jewish Year Book</title>,
5664, <date when="1904-09-09">September 22, 1903 to September 9, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Edited by Cyrus Adler</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCHES OF RABBIS AND CANTORS OFFICIATING IN THE UNITED STATES</p>
   <p>In Chicago. - (pp. 41 - 107). Agat, Isiah, Rabbi (since 1890) of Congregation Moses Montefiore. Born May 25, 1859, in Candau, Courland, Russia. Son of Moses Agat. Educated at Talmudical Colleges of Sager, Government Kovno, Bailystok, Government Minsk, Russia; under Dr. I. Hildesheimer, Berlin; at Gymnasium in Libau, Courland; and Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois. (B. Ph., 1898). Government teacher in Riga, Russia, 1879 - 1884; and Rabbi in New Haven, Conn., 1886-1888, and in San Francisco, Cal., 1888-1890. Address: 554 N. Robey Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1377.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Bauer, Sol H. - Rabbi of Congregation Anshe Emeth. Born January 1, 1863, in Poland. Son of Abraham Jacob Bauer. Educated in Stettin, Germany. Rabbinical diploma granted by Rabbi I. Trunk, Kutno, Poland. Was Rabbi at Jacobshagen and Wronke, Germany; Hamilton, Ohio; Schenectady, N. Y.; and of Moses Montefiore Congregation and First Hungarian Congregation, Chicago, Illinois. Address: 568 N. Lincoln Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Bernstein, Bernard. - Rabbi of Congregation Anshai Kanesseth Israel. Born September 12, 1836, in Russia, and educated there. Son of David Bernstein. Address: 178 Maxwell Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Braude, Abraham Samuel. - Rabbi of Congregation Ohave Sholem Mariampol. Born August 9, 1851, at Mitau, Courland, Russia. Son Selig Braude. Educated at the Talmudical College at Mitau. Rabbinical diploma granted by Rabbi Hirsch Rabinowitz, Kovno, Russia. Was Rabbi at Mitau. Came to America in 1891. Publication: Beth Abraham, commentary on Talmud and Midrash. Address 146 Johnson Street, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1378.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Felsenthal, Bernhard. - Rabbi Emeritus of Zion Congregation. Born January 2, 1822, at Minchweiler, near Kaiserslautern, Rhinish Palatinate. Son of Simon Felsenthal. Educated at Kaiserslautern and University of Munich (Ph. D.). Rabbinical diploma granted by Dr. Samuel Adler and Dr. David Einhorn. Rabbi in Madison, Ind., 1856-1858; of Sinai Congregation, 1861 - 1864; and of Zion Congregation, 1864 -1887. Publications: Kol Kore Bamidbar: Uber Judische Reform;A Practical Hebrew Grammar; Second Hebrew Reader; Judisches Schulwesen in Amerika; Kritik des Missionswesens; Zur Proselytenfrage in Judenthum; The Beginnings of Sinai Congregation; Judische Fragen. Address: 4809 Prairie Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1379.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Frey, Sigmund. - Born in Neu Raussmitz, Moravia, Austria. Son Hayim Frey. Educated at Gymnasium, Bruenn, Moravia. Rabbinical diploma granted by Dr. Samuel Gruen. Held positions in Philadelphia, Pa.; Chicago, Ill.; Springfield, Ill.; Wabash, Ind.; and Altoona, Pa. Publications: Homer and the Bible; Comparisons of the World's Literature and Rabbinic Lore; Covenant Consules, and so forth. Address: 7524 Union Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Heller, H. - Rabbi of Congregation Poale Zedek, Chicago, Illinois. Born in Bakau, Roumania, Address: 19 O'Brien Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1380.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Hirsch, Emil G. - Rabbi (since 1880) of Sinai Congregation. Born May 22, 1852, at Luxenburg. Son of Rabbi Samuel Hirsch and Louise Nickolls. B. A. (1872), M. A. (1875), University of Pennsylvania; Ph. D. (1876), University of Leipsig; LL D., Austin College, and L. H. D., Western University. Studied at the Berlin Hochschule Fur die Wissenschaft des Judenthums (Rabbi 1877); of Congregation Adath Israel, Louisville, Ky., 1878-1880. Professor of Rabbinical Literature and philosophy at University of Chicago since 1888. Editor of the Reform Advocate, Editor, Jewish Encyclopedia Department of the Bible. Address: 3612 Grand Boulevard, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Hirschberg, Abram. - Rabbi (since 1898) of North Chicago Hebrew Congregation. Born August 10, 1876, at Cincinnati, Ohio. Son of Maurice A. Hirschberg. Educated at University of Cincinnati, (B. A.); University of Chicago; and Hebrew Union College ( B. H.L, B. D., and Rabbi, 1898). Address: 294 La Salle Ave. Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1381.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Jacobson, Jacob S. - Minister of Zion Congregation of West Chicago, Illinois. Born October 4, 1840, at Rendsburg, Holstein. Son of Samuel Jacobson. Educated, Hamhurg-Altona, and London, England. Was teacher of Realgymnasium, Flensburg, Germany, 1862-1863, and teacher of the Jewish Congregation there. Rabbi of Washington Hebrew Congregation, Washington, D. C., 1866-1870; B'nai Jeshurum Congregation, Paterson, N. J., 1870-1872; Congregation B'rith Sholom, Easton, Pa., 1873-1881; Hebrew Benevolent Congregation, Atlanta, Ga., 1881-1888; and Congregation B'nai Israel, Natchez, Miss., 1888-1896. Principal of Englewood Hebrew Education Society, Chicago, Illinois, 1898-1900. Address: 144 Warren Ave., Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Levy, Abraham B. - Rabbi of Congregation B'nai Abraham. Born October 24, 1858, in Germany. Son of Leonard Levy, and Stella Bach. Educated under Dr. M. Lehman at Mayence; at Frankfort on the Main; at Berlin Lehrer Seminar; and the University of Georgia ( B. Ph., 1884). Was Rabbi at Frankisch Grumbach, Germany; <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1382.jpg" n="7"/>Erie, Pa.; and Waco, Texas. Founder (1880) and Corresponding Secretary Jewish Agriculturists' Aid Society of America. Address: 1180 Douglas Bldg. Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Messing, Aaron J. - Rabbi (since 1885) of Congregation B'nai Sholom. Born June 18, 1840, at Argenau, near Bremburg, Germany. Son of Rabbi Joseph Messing (author of a number of Hebrew books). Educated at Breslau and Graetz, Prussia, and Rostock, Mecklenburg. Rabbinical diploma granted by Rabbis E. Gutmacker, M. Feilchenfeld, and N. Caro. Ph. D., University of Rostock. Rabbi in Milletsch, Selesia; Mecklenburg-Schwerin; New York City (1866); and San Francisco (1867-1885). Publications: S'fath Eiver (Hebrew Printer), and Jorath Emeth (Catechism). Address: 4337 Vincennes Ave, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Newman, Julius. - Born December 16, 1851, in Hungary. Son of Joseph Newman. Educated at Budapest, Eisenstadt, and Pressburg, in Hungary. Rabbinical diploma conferred by Rabbi Schruber (Sofer), Pressburg, and Dr. I. Hildescheimer, Eisenstadt. Was Rabbi of Congregation Emanuel, for five years; of Congregation <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1383.jpg" n="8"/>New Light, for two years; and of the Hungarian Congregation, for six years; all in Chicago, Ill. Served in the Austrian Army, 1871-1873; as postmaster in Hungary, for two years; as correspondent for a Vienna newspaper, for three years. Address: 508 44th Place, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Newman, Morris. - Cantor of First Hungarian Congregation Agudath Achim. Born May 25, 1870, in Hungary. Son of Mayer Newman. Educated at Topolsary and Szatmar, Hungary. Held positions in McKusport and Scranton, Pa. Address: 412 West 14th St., Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Norden, Aaron. - Rabbi Emeritus of North Chicago Hebrew Congregation. Born June 8, 1844, at Lissa, Posen, Prussia. Son of Saul Norden. Educated at Lissa and Berlin. Rabbinical diploma granted by Rabbi E. Gutmacher, Graetz, Prussia. Rabbinical positions held in Baltimore, Md., Natcher, Miss., and Chicago, Illinois. Address: 4639 Vincennes Ave., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1384.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Rappaport, Julius. - Rabbi (since 1891) of Congregation Beth-E1. Born January 10, 1863, at Debreczin, Hungary. Son of Isaac Rappaport. Educated at Talmudical Colleges of Pressburg and Losoncz, Hungary. Rabbinical diplomas granted by Rabbi A. S. B. Sofer, Pressburg, and Rabbi Maier Perls, Nagy Karoly. Address: 87 Potomac Av., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Rosenblum, Joseph Nathan. - Rabbi of Congregation B'nai Israel. Born in Russia. Son of Chatzkel Rosenblum. Address: 114 Milton Av., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Schanfarber, Tobias. - Rabbi of Congregation Anshe Maarabh. Born December 20, 1862, at Cleveland, Ohio. Son of Aaron Schanfarber and Sara Newman. Educated at public schools of Cleveland, Ohio; University of Cincinnati (B. A); Johns Hopkins University; and Hebrew Union College (Rabbi); Was Rabbi at Toledo, Ohio; Forth Wayne, Ind.; Baltimore, Md.; and Mobile, Ala. Was editor of Jewish Comment, Baltimore, Md.; Jewish Chronicle, Mobile, Ala.; and Reform Advocate, Chicago, Ill. At present, editor of Chicago Israelite. Address: 4049 Grand Boulevard, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1385.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Schreiber, Emanuel. - Rabbi of Congregation Emanuel, Born December 13, 1852, at Leipzig, Moravia. Son of Hermann Schrubeiber. Educated at Gymnasium of Kremsier, Austria; University of Berlin; Talmudical College of Rabbi Moses Bloch, Leipzig; Rabbinical Seminary of Dr. I. Hildescheimer in Eisenstadt, Hungary, and in Berlin; and by Dr. A. Geiger, at the Berlin Hoechschule fur die Wissenschaft des Judenthums. Ph. D., University of Heidelberg. Rabbinical diplomas granted by Dr. Abraham Geiger, Berlin; Lazarus Adler, Cassel; Elia Grunebaum, Landan; Leopold Stein, Frankfort on the Main. Was Rabbi at Elbing, Prussia; Bonn, Germany; Mobile, Ala.; Denver, Colo.; Los Angeles, Cal.; Little Rock, Ark.; Spokane, Wash.; Toledo, Ohio.; and Youngstown, Ohio. Member of the Deutsche-Morgenlandische Gesellschaft; professor of Languages (1874-1875) at the Samson Schule, Wolfenbuttel; professor in College at Los Angeles; and professor at University of Little Rock. Editor, 1876-1881, of Die Judische Gemeinde und Familien-Zeitung (later Die Reform), and 1893-1896, of the Chicago Occident.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1386.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>Frequent contributor to the American-Jewish press on subjects connected with Jewish theology and history. Publications: "The Future of Judaism;" "The Social Positeon of the Jews;" "The Principles of Judaism;" "Progressive Rabbinism;" "The Jewish Congregation of Bonn;" "Abraham Geiger, a Biography;" "Self Criticism of the Jews;" "Criticism of Graetz's History;" "Moses Mendelsohn's Labors in the Cause of Judaism;" "Moses Mendelsohn's Labors in the Cause of Germany;" "Biblical and Post-Biblical History;" "A Word on the Condition of Judaism in Germany;" "The Talmud" (also treated in a series of English lectures); "Reformed Judaism and its Pioneers;" "Historians of Judaism;" "Moses Bloch;" "The Literature of Jewish Catechisms;" "Die Juden in Illinois;" "The Jews in Medicine;" etc. Address: 260 Seminary Av., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Shugam, William. - Minister of Congregation Bickor Cholem, S. Chicago, Ill. Born November 10, 1865, at Plumgian, Russia, and educated there.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1387.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Son of Meyer Shugam. Diplomas granted by Rabbis Z. Barith, Russia, and Jacob Joseph, New York City. Was Rabbi in Congregation Zichron Jacob, Baltimore, Md. Address: 8828 Commercial Av., S. Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Stolz, Joseph. - Rabbi (since 1896) of Isiah Temple. Born November 3, 1861, in Syracuse, N. Y. Son of David Stolz. Educated at public schools of Syracuse; University of Cincinnati (B. L.); Hebrew Union College (Rabbi and D. D.). Rabbi at Little Rock, Ark., 1884-1887; and of Zion Congregation, Chicago, 1887-1896. Member of Harper Educational Commission, and since 1899, Member Chicago Board of Education. Married Blanche Rauh, Cincinnati, June 24, 1900. Publication: "Funeral Agenda." Address: 157 42nd Place, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Yudelson, Albert B.- Rabbi of South Side Hebrew Congregation. Born August 2, 1869, at Prosehle, Poland. Son of Judah L. Yudelson. Educated at <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1388.jpg" n="13"/>Talmudical Colleges of Suvalki and Sakola, Russia, and at the University of the City of New York and Northwestern University. Rabbinical diplomas granted by Rabbis Z. Director, Sakola; H. Brinn, Chorzellen; Dr. Oppenheim, Thorn, Rrussia. Was principal of Hebrew Free School, Paterson, N. J., and superintendent of Hebrew Educational Society, Brooklyn, N. Y. Came to America in 1896. Address: 187 25th St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Zelesnick, Judel Michael. - Rabbi of Congregation Ohel Jacob. Born February 1859, in the Government Kovno, Russia. Son of Charles Zelesnick. Educated at Kovno. Rabbinical diplomas granted by Rabbis Jacob Kahano, Vilna, and Isaac Elchanan Spector,Kovno. Address: 91 West 13th St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
