<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-06-26">June 26, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0331</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0331.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-06-26">June 26, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Great Labor Organization Obligates Itself to Make the Tool Campaign of the Peoples Relief a Success.</p>
   <p>The Alliance of Lithuanian Jews, empties its treasury of $550 for the campaign - The Workmens Circle branches bring their first payments to a banquet and obligate themselves to raise a larger fund. - H. Schoolman of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union, and Sam Levin of the Amalgamated, promise to help through their unions. - United Hebrew Trades, appeal to their members to help in the work. - Preparatory report of the banquet given at the Morrison Hotel.</p>
   <p>The campaign of the Peoples Relief Committee in Chicago to raise $50,000 for the Jews in Ukrania, began Saturday night with a magnificent banquet at the Morrison Hotel. After the audience, which consisted of representatives <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0332.jpg" n="2"/>of labor organizations, and some individuals who are interested in relief work, had enjoyed the wonderful supper that was served, and had very warmly applauded the gifted violinist Mr. Alexander Kominski, the Chairman of the Relief Committee Mr. I. Lurie was honored with the title of toastmaster. He warmly and briefly explained the necessity of creating a tool fund for the Jews in Russia, and read a letter from Babroisk, which appeared in the Forward of last week, telling of the terrible hunger in Russia, where people had literally become cannibals. These bloody facts revolted the audience which felt that never before has the relief work been so necessary as at present.</p>
   <p>Dr. Z. Lorber, executive member of the Chicago Peoples Relief, touched the hearts of the audience, bringing tears to their eyes, by explaining the lonliness of the homeless Jews, who find their only shelter in God's houses - the synagogues, which take the place of their kitchen, bed-rooms, wash places. "At the same time these people are giving their children a Jewish education. The idealism of the students and teachers <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0333.jpg" n="3"/>continue in their work, not conquered by the torturing hunger and horrible surrounding conditions. Jewish traditions are kept alive." "We must come to their rescue," cried Dr. Lorber, "we are in a position to help them. In our garbage cans, here, the unfortunates, there, could find enough food to keep them alive."</p>
   <p>Mr. H. Schoolman, vice-president of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union, declared that while their workers are carrying on their own struggle, they are taking the greatest interest in the Jewish sufferers in Russia and Ukrania. The International Union, Mr. Schoolman assured the hearers, will positively abide by the decision of the convention at Cleveland, that every worker shall give one half day's wages for the tool campaign, which will amount to $10,000, towards the Chicago quota.</p>
   <p>The first donation at the banquet was made by Mr. Sam Geffen, as a representative of the Lithuanian Alliance. "The Lithuanian Jews of Chicago," <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0334.jpg" n="4"/>said Mr. Geffen, "realize that the sufferings of Jews in Lithuania are the least in comparison with the unbearable suffering of the Jews in Russia and Ukrania, and, as a start we determined to donate $550 toward the tool campaign." He was warmly applauded.</p>
   <p>Mr. B. J. Shapiro of the Poale Zion, declared, "Now everybody must partake in the work for the tool campaign. Up to now it was called charity, but the work we are doing, now, is truly constructive relief work." "How necessary and important for the Jews in Russia are the tools, that are being prepared for them here," said Judge Harry M. Fisher in a lengthy speech. He also related his experience in Moscow, when he was there with Comrade Max Fein. Many representatives of labor came to them from distant cities with requests for help from their brother workers in America. Each told his sad stories and left with the greatest hope in the workers in America. After the first outbreak they helped one another. That was in those days when Russian and Ukranian Jews were on their own feet.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0335.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>When the Jews in Russia receive tools from us they surely will be able to get on their own feet again. The workers here shall forget, for a while, their own trouble in sympathizing and helping the unfortunates in Russia and Ukrania.</p>
   <p>Comrade Leon Hanock, Secretary of the United Hebrew Trades, gave assurance of the help of his organization in the tool campaign. Mr. H. Ehrenreich, Manager of the Peoples Relief Committee in Chicago, after a brief successful speech, switched to the practical work of the banquet, asking to further the fund, and the representatives of organizations, immediately pledged their donations. Biyalistoker Branch, through friend Lepinski, $200; Branch 252 - W. C., and the Evanston Jewish Club, each $100; Moses Hess Branch National Workers Alliance, $500; American Brotherhood of Moihiloff, $50; Broisker Branch W. C. $50; Louis Schaffer, $25; Passovoi, $25; B. J. Shapiro, $25; C. Levinson, $25; Leon Hanock $25; Dr. Lorber, $25; M. Silbert, $25; Maltz $25; Katz, $25; Bradgis, $25; H. Schoolman, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0336.jpg" n="6"/>$15; P. Cohen, $15; Rubinstein, $15; Branch 2 Poale Zion, $15; N. W. Side Branch S. P., $10; Dr. Reinhardt, $10; A. Hillman, $10 and A. Winfield, $5.00.</p>
   <p>The tool campaign will last from June 25 to August 25. Do your duty, Jewish workers, help the tool campaign.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
