<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-03-04">March 4, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Professor Einstein Stops in Chicago on His Way to New York</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0253</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0253.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-03-04">March 4, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">PROFESSOR EINSTEIN STOPS IN CHICAGO ON HIS WAY TO NEW YORK</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Einstein was a word that could be heard frequently yesterday morning at the Union Station, when the famous Jewish scientist stopped here on his way to New York from California.</p>
   <p>A crowd had gathered at track fourteen, where the California train was to arrive.</p>
   <p>The delegations consisted of college professors, university students, clergymen and various pacifist-organizations. Everybody was anxious to meet the famous scientist, who is measuring the speed of the sun's rays, while dreaming at the same time of a better society, in which rich and poor would be treated alike.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0254.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Einstein is the real Prince of Peace, one woman of the crowd spoke up. He did not come to America to compliment us, but he came instead as an Ambassador of peace, to preach the gospel of good will among the nations.</p>
   <p>When the professor finally arrived, he looked in vain for Jewish delegations or for representatives from Chicago's Zionist organizations.</p>
   <p>Notables and reporters were gathered inside of the gate. There also was a delegation of women from the pacifist league. At their head were Mrs. Bertha Berger, wife of the late socialist congressman and Mrs. Moverick Lloyd. The delegates honored the scientist and his party with a most spontaneous demonstration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0255.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After having had his picture taken, Mr. Einstein had to listen to an avalanche of questions from the reporters. Asked if he liked the American people, he replied yes, but not the reporters. In a brief address, Mr. Einstein said: "I am a pacifist and I would like to see peace reign all over the world. I also favor peace between the Jews and the Arabs. Peace is essential to Palestine's growth."</p>
   <p>Mr. Einstein will arrive in New York tomorrow, whence he will return to Germany on the liner "Deutschland."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
