<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-11">Nov. 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Religious Murder Committee, Bailis Not the Murderer, Such Is the Verdict of Tsar Nicholas' Jury</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0663</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0663.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-11">Nov. 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A RELIGIOUS MURDER COMMITTEE, BAILIS NOT THE MURDERER, SUCH IS THE VERDICT OF TSAR NICHOLAS' JURY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Kiev, Nov. 10. Bailis is free, but not so the Jewish nation. Russia with her darkest forces could not condemn the innocent Mendel Bailis. But, she has condemned the entire Jewish populace as horrible people that use Christian blood for ritual purposes.</p>
   <p>The verdict of the peasant jury was as follows: Mendel Bailis is not guilty of the accusation, but, we state our firm belief that this is a ritual murder, although the murderer has not yet been found.</p>
   <p>When the jury gave its verdict, the Jewish martyr was so overcome with joy that he cried hysterically. This touched everyone present in the courtroom....</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0664.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As soon as those waiting in the streets heard the news they were immediately ready to start their wild work. Like demons they stood ready at any moment to shed Jewish blood. This was not permitted. They appeased their blood-thirsty desires with exclamations against the verdict of the jury. Their fury was not because the jury put a dark stain upon the Jewish people, but because they freed the innocent Jewish prisoner who thus escaped their set nets.</p>
   <p>From early morning the city was surrounded by soldiers. A strong guard encircled the courthouse permitting no one to enter except those connected with the trial. The mob shouted vehemently all day. The blood-seeking student, Golubov, the leader of the Anti-Semitic students, spoke with devilish wildness, inciting the mob to carry on pogroms. But for once there was a command from Petersburg not to permit any pogroms and the soldiers dispersed the crowd of people gathered there....</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0665.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The local Jewish community lived in constant fear from the time the jury went to make its decision. The fear of a bloody pogrom was such that one rarely saw a Jew in the street....</p>
   <p>Many Jews gathered in the synagogues and prayed while the jury was making its decision....</p>
   <p>Since this bloody accusation process began many Jews have left the city, all fearing pogroms. Those that remained, live in fear and terror, afraid that the government may not keep its word and at any time permit the bloody pogroms to have their way....</p>
   <p>The Russian Senate commanded that a suit be brought against 120 lawyers, members of the local lawyers' association because of the treason of daring to protest against the government proceedings in this blood accusation trial.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
