<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1894-01-27">January 27, 1894</date>. p.388.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1582</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1582.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1894-01-27">January 27, 1894</date>. p.388.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Referring to the appointment of Mr. Simeon B. Eisendrath as Commissioner of Buildings, the Herald says: "Mr. Eisendrath who has been appointed building commissioner by Mayor Hopkins to succeed Mr. Toolen, was born in Chicago in 1867. While attending the city high school, his scholarship was such that he was honored by the unanimous selection of the teachers of that school with a complete course at the Chicago Manual Training School. After attending the latter school for two years, he entered college, taking a course in architecture, in the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Boston, from which he graduated in 1887. Returning to Chicago, he spent two years in the office of Adler and Sullivan, the architects. Then he began the practice of architecture and, in the short space of five years, has acquired an extensive business. He has erected many buildings in Chicago and neighboring cities.</p>
   <p>In the first year of his practice, he was engaged as an expert by the county, to which he rendered valuable assistance in the successful prosecution of one of Cook County's most important boodle cases. In 1888, Mr. Eisendrath was appointed lecturer in the architectural branches of the Chicago evening high school. This position he filled so successfully that he was reappointed by the Board of Education for five consecutive years.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1583.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Owing to the large increase in his business, he was obliged to resign his appointment this year.</p>
   <p>Although one of the youngest architects in Chicago, Mr. Eisendrath has been intrusted with several important buildings of public nature. Besides several churches, he has erected the Michael Reese Training School for Nurses, the Home for Aged Jews, located at Drexel Blvd. and Sixty-second st. Mr. Eisendrath belongs to one of Chicago's oldest and best known Jewish families. He was not an applicant for the office of building commissioner and he assumes office with the understanding that he is wholly responsible for its management."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
