<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-01">Feb. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Truth Is the Best Policy for the Jewish People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-01">Feb. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">TRUTH IS THE BEST POLICY FOR THE JEWISH PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before leaving for Palestine, Dr. Chaim Weizmann, leader of Zionist policies, issued a statement in which he complained that our masses had not responded with the anticipated enthusiasm to the Balfour Palestine Declaration and that it was not being followed by a strong national movement for Palestine. He states that the Jewish people should have responded to the Balfour declaration as to the voice of Messiah. Such was not the case. Further, Dr. Weizmann is also disappointed in the financial condition of Zionism since the Balfour declaration. More than two years have passed since the issuance of the declaration and only a half-million pounds sterling have been collected for Zionist purposes.</p>
   <p>We understand Dr. Weizmann's viewpoint very well, but we also understand why the Jewish masses have not responded to the Balfour declaration as to the voice of Messiah.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0406.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Fifteen months have elapsed since the cessation of the war. During these fifteen months the Zionist policy has remained absolutely passive. Whereas the Arabs and Armenians have settled down in the last fifteen months, we have not advanced any further than we had a year or two ago. England keeps the gates of Palestine closed and lets no one enter. Hundreds of thousands of Eastern European Jews want to emigrate to Palestine, but are unable to carry out their plans.</p>
   <p>We do not maintian that it is the fault of the Zionist leaders, but we do say that the Jewish masses are greatly disappointed in the progress of the Zionist policy of the last two years. The Jewish masses are almost desperate--and desperate masses cannot become enthusiastic and from desperate masses no money is to be obtained.</p>
   <p>Then, also, it should not be forgotten that the American Zionist leaders, through an outbreak of quite unfounded optimism, have caused the apathy and skepticism <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0407.jpg" n="3"/>of the Zionist public. Even a few months before the British declaration was issued, Mr. Jacob De Haas declared that for the coming Passover the Jews would have their own government in Palestine. Today we are anticipating the third Passover and the Jews cannot even emigrate to Palestine.</p>
   <p>Then the Zionist leaders in America began to confuse the mind of the public with redemption funds, redemption conventions, etc. When one mentions Redemption to a Jew, the latter clearly understands what is meant. He believes that redemption is to be attained immediately. But for a number of years the Zionist leaders in America have proclaimed the Redemption and it has failed to materialize, nor is there any prospect of its materialization in the near future. And thus a suspicion awakens in the Jew that the leaders have taken him for a "sucker" and simply bluffed him. Words like Redemption should not be toyed with. For the last two thousand years Redemption has been the dearest word in the Hebrew language. In the word "redemption" is expressed so much sweetness of hope, so much pleasantness of expectation, so much consolation, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0408.jpg" n="4"/>that it is not to be toyed with, nor to be used for political expediency. It is self-evident that if England has failed, so far, to open the gates of Palestine to the Jews, it certainly is not the fault of the Zionist leaders who hope for the best. But if the masses do not believe any more in promises and redemption proclamations, then it is the fault of the leaders in America, who not only failed to tell the people the truth, but consciously gave utterance to things in which they themselves never believed.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the Zionist organization in America were "successful" in reducing the number of members from ninety-four thousand a year ago to forty-four thousand this year because they followed a "true" policy. We are an old experienced people and are accustomed to misfortunes. Nothing surprises us any more. Truth is the best policy for the Jewish people. It will be impossible to employ the methods of Tammany Hall in organizing the Jewish people for Zion's cause and the leaders of the Zionist organization in America should know this.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
