<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-28">May 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Mizrachi Convention Closed in High Spirits</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0502</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0502.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-28">May 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">MIZRACHI CONVENTION CLOSED IN HIGH SPIRITS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Cincinnati, May 25. A cable greeting from the Zionist share-holding committee,signed by Dr. Smarihu Levin and Jacobson, was received today from the Mizrachi Convention. The cable expressed the aspirations of the Mizrachi, that they might be able to fulfil the hopes of Orthodox Zionism throughout the entire world. Cables containing greetings from English and Dutch Zionists were also received at the convention.</p>
   <p>Lawyer Isaac Allen successfully presented the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>The Mizrachi should cooperate with other Orthodox organizations in the support of the Yisheva Reb Yitzchok Alchonon (a higher school) in <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0503.jpg" n="2"/>New York; Mizrachi meetings should be conducted in Hebrew; a Mizrachi bureau should be set up in Jerusalem and other centers; the Mizrachi will have no right to elect a Palestine commission without a referendum, unless time does not permit; that they support the five-day work week movement; that they open a Mizrachi Information Bureau for those who desire to emigrate to Palestine; and to limit the powers of the executive committee.</p>
   <p>Following the appeal of Rabbi Berlin and a timely report by Rabbi Fishman regarding Mizrachi work in Palestine, about twenty-five thousand dollars for the Palestinian Fund was gathered among the delegates of the convention.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Berlin reported that Mizrachi has twenty-nine branches, with a membership of twenty-eight thousand.</p>
   <p>He also announced that Rabbi Fishman will leave shortly for Palestine, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0504.jpg" n="3"/>and lauded this man's active work for the last four years with this remark, "Fishman was not only our secretary, but also the upbuilder of our organization." This received tremendous applause. Rabbi Fishman rose to state that he would not be in America if he had not been sent by Djemel Pasha and other Jews from Palestine.</p>
   <p>He also stated that Mizrachi is the only Zionist organization representing traditional Judaism. This was followed by a sharp attack on some Zionists who think "that without the Torah we can still maintain a Jewish nation." He added that thanks to Rabbi Hertz, Chief Rabbi of Great Britain, a devoted Mizrachi, Balfour made his Zionist declarations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0505.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"As to Palestine," Rabbi Fishman went on to say, "it is our misfortune that only part of the prophecies have been fulfilled."</p>
   <p>"We have broken the swords,but we have failed to forge them into plows."</p>
   <p>He suggested that we establish in America corporations for buying land in Palestine and settling it with Jews who will till the soil. He also made an appeal for the Jewish National Fund.</p>
   <p>A resolution from Rabbi Ashinski to protest against pogroms in Poland and Rumania was unanimously accepted.</p>
   <p>Copies were sent to President Wilson in Paris, and to Congress in Washington.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0506.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Rabbi Iskolski reported on the maintenance of parochial schools, explaining that over a hundred thousand dollars was sent from here for rabbis and Yishevoth (schools) in war countries.</p>
   <p>Ephraim Kaplan suggested that the Mizrachi establish a kindergarten in Palestine and an institute for Hebrew science and higher learning.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Meyer Berlin was unanimously elected president for the following year. Rabbi Abraham Lesser is honorary president. Gadolia Bublik is secretary; Wexman, educational secretary.</p>
   <p>In the executive are: Dr. Blustone, Rabbi Levensohn, Vilner, Rabbi Levenstone, Garfield, Borgenicht, Rabbi Ashinski, Rabbi Saul Zilber, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0507.jpg" n="6"/>Rabbi Rosenberg, Rabbi Gold, Braver, Rabbi Levin, Rabbi Elieser Moskin, Rabbi Rif, Rabbi Abramovitch, Sadovski, Ephraim Kaplan, and Samuel B. Ratenberg is the treasurer.</p>
   <p>The banquet in the music hall, given in connection with the convention, was a marvelous event. A group of the most prominent Jews in the city participated in it.</p>
   <p>The convention set aside half a million dollars for work in Palestine.</p>
   <p>It closed in great animation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
