<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-04-05">April 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Plan Is Liked by Chicago Jewry</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-04-05">April 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE PLAN IS LIKED BY CHICAGO JEWRY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The proposal to aid families who want to settle in Palestine on farms bought for them by a settlers' group to be organized in Chicago has been accepted, and a group is being organized at once for that purpose. A meeting has been called for Wednesday.</p>
   <p>Our editorial of yesterday regarding a plan to help families who want to settle in Palestine, but have no means to do so, had a much stronger effect than we expected. Even yesterday morning soon after the Sunday Courier appeared on the streets, different people came into our office and expressed their satisfaction with the plan. On the West Side much has been talked about it, and before a half day was over it was determined already by a number of Jews to start to work on that project at once, and to organize a group according to the plan published in the Sunday Courier. It was decided to organize that group during the holiday week.</p>
   <p>The first meeting, called by the founders, will take place next Wednesday evening, right after the holidays at the home of Mr. Max Shulman, 24 Newberry <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0156.jpg" n="2"/>Avenue. Temporary officers would be elected.The group will call for suggestions regarding an adequate name to be given that organization. Then an application for a charter will be signed by the group.</p>
   <p>For those who have missed reading the plan in yesterday's Courier, we shall briefly review it here: The plan consists of getting together a group of a thousand members, each of whom will pay 10¢ a week in dues.</p>
   <p>The work of collecting dues should be done by 40 members voluntarily. Each of the 40 collectors is responsible for 25 dimes every week. In the course of one year approximately five thousand dollars would accumulate in the group's treasury. Then a drawing is to be held, and the lucky members will be presented with a farm in Palestine, together with all necessary farm implements and traveling expenses for himself and his family. The money that the organization shall spend on him should be repaid by the beneficiary in the course of ten years, without interest. Until the full sum is paid back, the farm would belong to the organization. However, if the lucky member is not willing or not ready to go there himself, he may transfer his claim to whomever he may choose, but on the same conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0157.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>All Jews who are interested in this plan are requested to attend the first founders' meeting to take place at the place and time mentioned above.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
