<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-12">June 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Peace Delegates in Paris</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0462</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0462.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-12">June 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH PEACE DELEGATES IN PARIS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now that the Jewish Peace Delegation has disbanded, and each member has returned to his own country, it is time that we stopped a moment to consider what was accomplished in its three months of activities. The committee members were of different social and political elements of opposing natures. There were mediators of the old Jewish type, modern party leaders, social agitators, and even people who participate in everything but do nothing. Naturally, such a combination could not work very harmoniously together. Methods used by men like Nachman Sirkin could hardly suit a man like Judge Julian Mack; and those of Morris Vintchevski and Joseph Bearondes would not suit Louis Marshall.</p>
   <p>From the first it was decided that all members would have equal rights, voice, and influence. If the Jewish Congress in Philadelphia had been <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0463.jpg" n="2"/>conducted by party politics and party leaders, who were capable Jewish men, such types as Sirkin and some others would not have been elected to the Delegation. Persons who shoulder responsibilities about once in three months and do not even know how to conduct themselves in their daily life, cannot possibly represent our interests, the interests of the Jewish people, at this greatest diplomatic gathering in history. But our Congress was ruled by small cliques and a petty party spirit; therefore, lodge politicians became our representatives in Paris. By their presence they failed to prove that the Jewish people are politically capable and possess diplomatic personalities. Nevertheless even in this Delegation there were some men who were diplomats and polished. They, naturally, had to do the work for the others and therefore could not accomplish all that should have been done.</p>
   <p>The first error the Delegation made was to have arrived in Paris late, thereby missing important business and especially failing to be on hand in Paris to explain that medieval anti-Semitic reactionary politics is a <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0464.jpg" n="3"/>catastrophe not only for the eight million Jews in Eastern Europe but also for all Europe and for world peace. There was a time when the fate of Poland could have been decided in favor of liberalism, when the representatives of the Powers in Paris were undecided as to whether they would recognize General Pilsudski, or Dmowski and Paderewski. If our delegates had been in Paris a month ago, and had taken the necessary steps, they might have been able to sway the balance in favor, not of Paderewski and Dmowski, but of General Pilsudski, who would then have remained in power. We do not say that Pilsudski is a lover of Judaism. There is not a Pole in the world that has an objective outlook on the Jewish problem of Poland. But because General Pilsudski represents the liberal element, and not the interests of the clergy and lesser nobility, he is not interested in pogroms and it would be easy to get him to agree to end these pogroms.</p>
   <p>The delegates' second error was to have gone to Paris individually and without knowing each other. One member left for Paris fourteen days before most of the others. Another left a month later. It took several days for all <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0465.jpg" n="4"/>the members of the Delegation to meet, after having wandered about Paris for many days without knowledge of the others' presence. In a word, the presence of our Delegation in Paris could hardly have created a good impression, and perhaps it made no impression at all. Polish leaders in Paris, seeing the disorganization of the Jewish Delegation, knew that they had no one to fear, and that they could immediately start their intensive campaign of prevarication and insults toward Jews. For a long time political forces in Paris lacked co-ordination and the Poles therein found a fruitful field for their work.</p>
   <p>The third and worst error made by the delegates was inexcusable--a lack of accurate information. The Delegation was given a definite mandate from the Jewish Congress on the demands for definite political rights for Jews in Eastern Europe. Each delegate understood these demands in his own way; therefore, when it came to explaining how these could have been legally and legitimately granted, there was no one who could give any kind of an answer. The Delegation as such had no accurate picture of the contents of the <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0466.jpg" n="5"/>demands. The Poles took advantage of this confusion to advance their own aims--i, e., anti-Jewish aims.</p>
   <p>This by no means ends the long list of errors committed by our delegates. From a broader historical point of view, the worst error was that of localizing the Jewish problem, instead of associating it with the general Eastern European problem. What our delegation accomplished we shall soon know; and if anything really has been done, we shall have such men as Judge Mack and Louis Marshall to thank for it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
