<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-28">July 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Elias Greenebaum</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1056</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1056.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-28">July 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ELIAS GREENEBAUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Elias Greenebaum died recently at the age of ninety-seven. With his passing, the Jewish community in Chicago has lost a Jewish personality who encompassed [within himself], fifty years of Jewish history. The financial world loses in his passing an important representative, and Reform Jewry loses one of its most significant disciples.</p>
   <p>Our Eastern European Jews cannot understand a personality such as Greenebaum. They are unfamiliar with the peculiar commercial talents of the German Jews who, over a period of one hundred years, produced more financial wizards than any other great nation.</p>
   <p>Elias Greenebaum was not just a German Jew. He belonged to that group of German Jews who can point to a record of such men as the Rothschilds, the Hirschs, the Efroses, the Schiffs, the Guggenheimers, the Lewisohns, the Strausses, and a <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1057.jpg" n="2"/>large number of financial geniuses who not only amassed fortunes in millions of dollars for themselves, but also brought about great changes in the world of finance. The part these Jews have played for the last one hundred years in world history, can be seen from the following three facts:</p>
   <p>In 1865, there was much talk in Berlin of an immediate war with Austria. But Vienna was calm because Rothschild of Vienna informed the political circles of Vienna that he desired no war with Prussia, nor would he finance such a war. If Bismarck had not attacked Austria in 1866, there would have been no Austro-Prussian War. In that era, a man like Baron Rothschild of Vienna could decide whether or not Austria should go to war.</p>
   <p>After the Franco-Prussian War in 1870-71, France and Germany appointed two financiers to make the financial adjustments. The French financier was the Parisian Baron Rothschild; the German was Herr Bleichreder, the famous Jewish banker in Berlin. When the head of the French government, Mr. Thiers, heard <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1058.jpg" n="3"/>that Bismarck demanded five billion francs in indemnity from France, he became enraged and shouted: "If a person had counted five-franc coins from the time of Christ to the present day, he would still be unable to count out five billion francs." To this Bismarck answered: "My man (meaning Bleichreder), began his counting with the coming of Adam."</p>
   <p>And now peace has been declared between Germany and the Allies. Again two Jews acted as the financies. Mr. Klotz, the French financier, did the calculations for the Allies. Mr. Klotz himself is an Alsatian Jew. Herr Warburg of Hamberg, the famous German-Jewish banker, was the financier for the Germans. The English press admitted that had it not been for Lord Reading, formerly Sir Rufus Isaacs, the Jewish Lord Chief Justice, England would have lost the War on purely financial grounds.</p>
   <p>The contribution of German Jews to America in the field of finance is well known. The Federal Reserve Bank is linked with the name of Warburg and Jacob Schiff, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1059.jpg" n="4"/>who is even today the head of the greatest international banking house in the world.</p>
   <p>To this group of Jewish financiers belonged the deceased Elias Greenebaum. He began with nothing, and ended by founding a new Jewish financial dynasty in the Middle West. Of course, we cannot compare Elias Greenebaum with a man like Schiff. But, if we stop to realize that Greenebaum began his career with two cents and had no native commercial tradition, as Jacob Schiff had, then we must admit that Elias Greenebaum was an extraordinarily creative person in the field of finance. He can, therefore, be listed as a member of the above-mentioned group of German-Jewish financial geniuses.</p>
   <p>As a Jew, too, he can be included within that group. The generation of German Jews to which Greenebaum belonged was already partially modernized. The teachings, not only of Moses Mendelsson, but also of the first German reformers, were already popular in Jewish homes in Germany. The fundamental aim of that <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1060.jpg" n="5"/>generation of German Jews was to reduce Judaism to a charity business so that they might become entirely German. Since Jews are not a nation, but are a religious and philanthropic group, what keeps them from assimilating? Such was the philosophy of that Jewish generation in Germany. What it did accept from Judaism--the tradition of charity--it held sacred. Thus Elias Greenebaum concentrated his energies on Jewish charities, accomplishing much in this field. We may not be satisfied with the way German Jews of Chicago conduct their charitable activities, but we must respect their earnestness and the sacrifices they make for their philanthropic activities. Naturally, our present nationally minded Jewish generation cannot take Mr. Elias Greenebaum very seriously as a Jew, that is, as a political leader, but none will deny his devotion to Judaism as he saw it. As a philanthropist, he stands out as a noteworthy figure among Chicago Jews. Because of his deeds, future generations will continue to speak of him with respect.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
