<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
No. 13, <date when="1914-01-05">Jan. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Need of Nation for Jews Urged on Knights of Zion</title><title level="a" type="sub">Speakers Tell of 20,000 Members of Race Who Have Started Colonies in Palestine Plan Future Development</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0088</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0088.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
No. 13, <date when="1914-01-05">Jan. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">NEED OF NATION FOR JEWS URGED ON KNIGHTS OF ZION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Speakers Tell of 20,000 Members of Race Who Have Started Colonies in Palestine Plan Future Development</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That it is a necessity for the Jewish race to have a country was urged last night by delegates from the middle western states at the closing of the seventeenth annual convention of the Knights of Zion in the Chicago Hebrew Institute at 1258 Taylor St.</p>
   <p>The back to Palestine movement was started by Baron Rothschild and Dr. Theodore Herzl. In seventeen years forty-two colonies, with from 15,000 to 20,000 people, have settled in Palestine. Wealthy Jews the world over are buying up the land in and about Palestine and establishing factories in the cities. Plans had been made to establish a university in Palestine to provide culture for the future nation.</p>
   <p>With the regaining of their home, said Rabbi Mayer Berlin of Germany, the 13,000,000 Jews scattered over the world would be one of the great powers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0089.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"If Montenegro with 750,000 people, could dictate to Austria, if Portugal could overthrow a king in a night," said the rabbi, "then the Jewish nation, with its millions of people, should take its place in the world. As it is to-day no Jewish parents could expect to bring up a distinctly Jewish generation, as the minority always was lost in the majority, and every tradition dear to their forefathers was being lost in strange lands."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
