<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-07">Apr. 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Battalion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.B"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>V B</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-07">Apr. 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR BATTALION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The farewell dinner, which was given yesterday evening for the first hundred recruits in the Jewish Battalion, will remain not only in the memory of those who had the privilege of attending it, but will also serve as an historical event in the history of the Jewish revival. It will occupy a stirring page in the chapter of similar events, which have occurred in the last couple of weeks in London, New York, Philadelphia and other Jewish centers.</p>
   <p>In the presence of this small army of Jewish young men, who are eager and ready to risk their lives for the defense and preservation of Palestine as the future country of the Jewish people, all arguments and doubts of whether we are a nation or not; whether we need a homeland of our own or not, and the fear of, "What will the nations say," disappeared like smoke. All the healthy instincts of an alive nation were awakened, and the Jew <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0573.jpg" n="2"/>felt and spoke freely, without reticence, without fear, but with manly courage and pride.</p>
   <p>The young men who took leave of Chicago Jewry, before embarking on their long journey to Palestine, as soldiers of their own nation, under their own Zionist flag, felt a great responsibility as pioneer fighters, whose heroism and blood will be credited to the account of their own nation, instead of other nations, as has been done heretofore. They felt that their great sacrifice will do more than any contribution that others may make, to elevate their nation in the eyes of the world, and to whitewash the insults and contempt with which the world has looked upon the Jew for centuries.</p>
   <p>The guests who were present at this remarkable gathering--especially the older ones, the sensible, the fearful and the prudent--[all] wondered, not <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0574.jpg" n="3"/>believing their own eyes and ears, when they listened to the speeches. They were lost, not recognizing themselves in this wonderful atmosphere. They saw before them a new nation of Israel--heroic, courageous, capable of sacrifice--men who will give everything for their nation, even their lives, if it is demanded of them.</p>
   <p>And the British officers, who do know what it means to offer themselves for the sake of their country--even they were astonished by such manifestation of devotion, resoluteness and willingness to sacrifice. They spoke with feeling, deeply moving words of comradeship, and in a tone of true admiration, devoid of the cheap compliments which Jews are accustomed to hear from non-Jews. They revealed an honest and sincere attitude as toward a sister nation in paying their respects.</p>
   <p>This was truly a remarkable evening--a wonderful evening in which a scene from the rebirth of a nation was presented before our eyes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
