<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-10">Feb. 10, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A Colossal Demonstration</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0053</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0053.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-10">Feb. 10, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A COLOSSAL DEMONSTRATION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The wandering of nations is not anything new in the world's history. Never before has it been so tragic as the immigration at the present time. Two million people are being forced to leave their homes, their country, the place of their birth to which they are tied by thousands of bonds. Many of these wanderers are forced to leave their wives and children in order to look for new homes where they hope to improve conditions.</p>
   <p>Economic conditions were always the main problem of the immigrant. In the Slavic and Latin countries, this was the reason why the Jews emigrated. They did not leave on account of the shortage of food. The Jew came <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0054.jpg" n="2"/>to America or Canada not like the Irishman, who came here on account of a potato crop shortage or an industrial crisis. The Jew came to America to escape. It is characteristic of the Jew that he runs from persecution, from pogroms, from fear, and from restrictive laws, which rob him of his political and social equality. Formerly the Jewish immigrant came here, not on account of economic problems, but because he desired to raise and educate his children in a land of freedom. He wanted to enjoy equal rights. His great desire for equality did not let him rest until he had left his home, for no other reason than for a desire for political and social equality.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that immigration, after the war, will be the greatest in history. This means that at least a half-million Jews will immigrate to this country. The Jewish population in the war-stricken countries <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0055.jpg" n="3"/>is estimated to be in the neighborhood of 7,000,000 economically ruined people, hopeless and despondent; people who are unemployed, who have no means of making a livelihood for their families. Cities destroyed, Jewish homes in ruins, robbed of their earthly belongings. Is it any wonder that one out of every 14 will emigrate from the war-stricken countries and come here to this free land of ours? The destruction and disaster in Europe due to this war will very likely, after the war ends, make lots of employment for many of its citizens. But whom will this employment concern? Common laborers, stone workers, iron and steel workers in the steel mills. But the Jew is not represented in these industries. It is a known fact that 50 per cent of the Jewish population belongs to the working class, and being locked out of the mentioned industries, they have had to become hand workers - brush makers, candy makers, cigar makers, etc. All these industries in the war-stricken countries will, without a <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0056.jpg" n="4"/>doubt, be entirely paralyzed, and it will take considerable time before conditions become normal. So the Jewish worker must follow in the steps of the ruined small storekeeper and merchant, on the look-out for new markets for their labor.</p>
   <p>The future Jewish immigration will, without a doubt, be a "food immigration." We do not doubt that the Jewish immigration, immediately after the war, is going to be the greatest wandering of our Jewish people in the history of our nation, similar to the Jewish flight from the first pogroms in the year of 1882.....We must not forget the terrible plight which our nation is in at the present time. We must make preparations. We must begin to study out plans to do something for the coming Jewish immigration. We must see to it that the wanderers are cared for in a systematic manner....It is our duty to do everything in our power in receiving and welcoming our stranded immigrants.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
