<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-28">February 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Albert P. Kadison</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1242</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1242.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-28">February 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">DR. ALBERT P. KADISON</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the death of the seventy-three year old Dr. Albert P. Kadison, the Chicago Jewish community lost one of its oldest and most talented members who laid the foundation upon which the present activities of the Chicago Judaism is being built.</p>
   <p>The doctor was unknown to the younger generation. For the past fifteen years, Dr. Kadison was no longer a factor in the activities of the Chicago Jewish community, due to two reasons:</p>
   <p>1. His extreme age.</p>
   <p>2. A new generation appeared with new ideas and conceptions, and the doctor, with his views on Judaism in general and on Chicago Judaism especially, could not work in harmony with the new-comers. The old law of nature - that the old be replaced by the new - excluded Dr. Kadison from taking part in recent activities of the Chicago community.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1243.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They, however, who are acquainted with the development of the Russian-Jewish community in Chicago, they who have studied the history of the Chicago Jewish community since the Russian-Jews began to settle here, they know that Dr. Kadison was one of those who made possible an orthodox-Jewish community in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Among the first Russian-Jews who chose Chicago as their home, Dr. Kadison stood very highly; thanks to his intelligence, education, and natural qualities. Many of his contemporaries ignored the Russian-Jewish community. They declared themselves to be German Jews and segregated themselves from the then new impoverished Russian-Jewish community. Dr. Kadison did not do this. He devoted his abilities for the benefit of those who depended upon them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1244.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There was a time when Dr. Kadison was famous as one of the best physicians in Chicago and had, at that time, the opportunity of becoming very wealthy. He could have been one of the most prominent members of the Chicago Jewish-German community, but instead the doctor devoted his money, his time, and his energy to social matters. He spent his evenings establishing a Hebrew Literary Society, in devotion to Zionist work, in planning a new Talmud Torah, in mingling in politics as it was then understood and comprehended; there wasn't a simple Jewish activity in which Dr. Kadison did not participate pro or con.</p>
   <p>Self-evidently, Dr. Kadison, a product of the Haskalah movement, but one who did not live through or understand the Mendelssohnian philosophy of Judaism could not remain a Jewish leader. As an intelligent man of former times, he did not consider the opinions and demands of the public. He studied <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1245.jpg" n="4"/>masses and discovering that the sun of enlightenment does not shine upon them, he looked at them as ignorant beings. Personally, Dr. Kadison was a Jew with a true Jewish heart. He possessed all the qualifications with which the Jews have distinguished themselves. He was liberal in sharing his money with those who were in need. His house was always open to the hungry and the destitute. He died friendless and deserted, because instead of providing for his old age, he gave his time to the Chicago Jewish community. He died in poverty and want, because he distributed whatever he had. In the funeral procession will be found many who owe their lives, their repute, their existence and social standing to this corpse, who has been dead to society for the past fifteen years, and to his friends and family since Wednesday afternoon.</p>
   <p>Let us honor his memory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
