<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-24">Nov. 24, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The "Achoozo" Movement in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Reported by Mr. Max Schulman, the Chicago delegate to the Eleventh Zionist Congress in Vienna)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0651</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0651.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-24">Nov. 24, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE "ACHOOZO" MOVEMENT IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Reported by Mr. Max Schulman, the Chicago delegate to the Eleventh Zionist Congress in Vienna)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I have been requested by the American Delegation to place before the Congress a brief report about the aims and influences of the Achoozo Alliance, and what America does for our cause.</p>
   <p>Experience has taught us that no nation ever attained political independence unless it holds fast to its principles. In order to build a new community, there must be pioneers, since nations cannot be built upon donations or sympathy. We must have people who will be willing to volunteer and, if necessary,to practice what they preach. America is known as the land of practical undertakings. A group of ardent Zionists started a movement several years ago to organize an American corporation for the purpose of buying land in Palestine, not for others, but for themselves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0652.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was definitely proven that if an investment of from about $1400 to about $2000 was made, it would provide a sufficient income to aid the average family. Knowing the experiences of previous Palestinian ventures, the organization formulated a plan whereby its members do not leave for Palestine immediately.</p>
   <p>The money to be used is first distributed and made payable on a ten-year installment plan. Thus the land may be bought and worked until at the end of the ten years it will already yield an income. A group of forty families in St. Louis have formed the first group of American Jews who expressed their willingness to settle in Palestina. In the span of a few years, there has been established a fund of $40,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0653.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Land has been bought that is now the colony of Poreah.</p>
   <p>Mr. Simon Goldman, one of the organizers, sailed immediately to Palestine, to be joined there by Mr. and Mrs. Barushack, who, en-route to Palestine, are at present in Vienna for the Zionist Congress.</p>
   <p>Since the first company was formed, five other groups of 'Achoozo' have been organized in various states. New York, Los Angeles, and Cleveland, each has one 'Achoozo.' St. Louis and Chicago have two. The Chicago 'Achoozo No. I' consists of eighty determined members. In the two years of its existence, it has amassed $35,000 in cash.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0654.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The American spirit of enterprise is linked with the best resolutions of laying a foundation for a Jewish future in Palestine, not merely for the few, but for all of the Jewish folk.</p>
   <p>The prime feature of practical work in Palestine is also an answer to the assertion that Zionism is just a movement suitable for lands where Jews are oppressed and persecuted, but is not needed in America.</p>
   <p>This company is planning to establish commerce and marketing in connection with agricultural work. The St. Louis company has already a milk farm in Palestine, with a capital of $12,000. It would be wise of our financial institutions to aid these companies when they are in need of loans for purchases, for their work is all important.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0655.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We point out that the families who intend to settle in Palestine are preparing for the event in earnest. They teach their children Hebrew and seek to become acquainted with Jewish history.</p>
   <p>There is room in America for more than six companies, and it should be the duty of the incoming administration to found these organizations and strengthen their methods of practical activities in Palestine.</p>
   <p>In general, we have created a huge idea for our movement in this land. In Chicago, through the influence of Mr. Harry A. Lipsky, a member of the Board of Education, we were successful in having the Board name one of <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0656.jpg" n="6"/>Chicago's Public Schools "Dr. Theodore Hertzal" All newspapers have shown friendliness to our cause. Fraternal organizations are interested in our well being. Most of them, at their conventions, have adopted the 'Bazel program,' some even donating money for Zionistic purposes.</p>
   <p>The Progressive Order of the West, at its last convention, sent a contribution of $1500. The Western Star Order pays an annual sum to the National Fund. Our schools and temples are aligning themselves in our ranks, so that we may hope in the near future to collect in America the quota allotted her for the rebuilding of our National existence in our historical country, Palestine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
