<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-01">July 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">National Fund and Real Estate</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0687</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0687.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-01">July 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">NATIONAL FUND AND REAL ESTATE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bureau of the World Alliance of the Poale Zion protests against the misuse of money by the powers of the National Fund. The Directors of the National Fund have, again, loaned money to a group of real estate men, in order to build a new Jewish district in Haifa, (Palestine), which should be similar to Tel Aviv and Jaffe.</p>
   <p>The Poale Zion thinks that the National Fund was established for the "redemption of the land," for the naturalization of the Palestinian grounds, and for this ideal thought did the National Fund become popular among the Jewish masses. According to the opinion of the Poale Zion, it is a crime to utilize this national wealth for the purpose of helping individuals construct homes, which would enable them to "chaffer and speculate" and <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0688.jpg" n="2"/>rob the tenants by skinning them on rents, just as they are doing now in Tel Aviv which was built by the aid of the National Fund.</p>
   <p>Tel Aviv is the paradise of the real estate speculator in Palestine. Impoverished teachers become wealthy landlords with in a few years. The National Fund, however, did not gain anything from this gigantic real estate boom. Had the National Fund built Tel Aviv on the basis of its naturalization program, it would be in position today to build several other districts in Jerusalem and Haifa, and raise millions for the national wealth. But the Poale Zion alleges that, at present, the entire profits go toward private interests which look upon the National Fund as a Rothschild Administrative institution, and the Chovavi Zionist funds which were raised to aid individuals. And after all this, the real estate men of Tel Aviv have expressed their gratitude toward Zionism by not engaging Jewish laborers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0689.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Poale Zion further contends that if money is invested in real estate, the National Fund should always be the owner of the lots, and when the increase of population in the colonies multiplies the value of real estate, let the National Fund also profit by it. But the Poale Zion thinks that to loan money to individuals for speculation, which inevitably brings about poor conditions, is a crime which should be opposed by every conscientious Zionist, even if he is not a Socialist.</p>
   <p>Dr. S. Levine annuls all these complaints for the reason alone that they come from the Poale Zion. However, this does not prove that the latter is wrong. It merely shows that Dr. Levine, who was, in time of the first Russian Parliament, supposedly, a real radical who played up to the Poale Zion, has become, in the past eight years, a conservative. Such an answer under any circumstances, isn't worth anything.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0690.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is true that the Poale Zion group constitutes a small minority of the Jewish populace, but even the most wealthy and powerful among civilized nations listens to the claims of its minorities. This great nation often heeds the message of a poor individual, who might even be a foreigner.</p>
   <p>To ignore the minorities, to annul the claims from the opposition, because it has no authority in the management, is a sign that the present Zionist leaders are far from able to govern a nation. Dr. Max Nordie was right when he occasionally confirmed that a rapid growth of Zionism would be a catastrophe to the Jewish people, who are, as yet, unprepared for self-government. Dr. Nordie saw that a great many Zionists are in need of a lesson in democracy, and he knows that "like teacher, like pupil."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
