<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-02">June 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Sovereignty and Jewish Freedom</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-02">June 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SOVEREIGNTY AND JEWISH FREEDOM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In an official Paris dispatch it is stated that Paderewski, Bratiana, and representatives of other small states at the conference expressed their dissatisfaction with certain paragraphs of the Peace Terms, which demand that recognition be given to the rights of national and religious minorities. Paderewski and Bratiana, speaking for Poland and Rumania, argue that these paragraphs decrease and limit the sovereign rights of their respective countries and are therefore unacceptable. President Wilson, however, proved these arguments to be invalid. All countries which till now persecuted national minorities, especially Jews, must sign the Peace Treaty; they must undertake to give these minorities the rights which will protect them from persecution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0479.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It goes without saying that the abovementioned paragraphs are a limitation of sovereign rights because they deny the power to the nation to persecute its minorities. They are, in certain respects, a new interpretation of the so-called extra-territorial rights which still exist, even today in various Asiatic countries, as for example in Turkey, Japan, Siam, Afghanistan, etc. These Asiatic countries have such barbaric laws that the civilized world cannot recognize them as generally valid. When a European or an American commits an injustice or a crime, he is not sentenced by judges of an Asiatic state, but by the consular court of the state of which he is a citizen.</p>
   <p>If the civilized world would recognize Poland and Rumania as civilized states which administer one justice and one law to every <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0480.jpg" n="3"/>citizen, it would not then demand of them any constitutional guarantees for their minorities. Yet in spite of the popularity of a free Poland, that country is still considered half barbaric, for it cannot be trusted with the fate of millions of people who are non-Poles. Poland must, therefore, give guarantees not to carry on pogrom-politics against her national minorities. The same is true of Rumania and some of the new Slavic States. These demands for constitutional guarantees to safeguard minorities are primarily an affront to Poland and Rumania because they imply that these lands are considered as barbaric or semi-barbaric countries which cannot be given unlimited sovereignty.</p>
   <p>The pogroms raging for the past six months, of which the powerful diplomats in Paris possess documentary proof (photographs, reports from Red Cross messengers, and responsible eye-witnesses), contributed <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0481.jpg" n="4"/>considerably to bringing about the demanded guarantees from Poland and Rumania for national and religious minorities. Although these guarantees are not listed under national rights, nevertheless they are practically equivalent to such rights. Of these countries we have never asked more than what these paragraphs assure us: security of our culture, autonomy, constitutional defensive measures for our constitutional rights, and religious freedom. In Russia, for instance, our tax-money was often used to build Russian churches. The "Sabar" in Kovna, for example, was built from Jewish tax-money funds. In Poland and Rumania such diversions cannot occur now because the Jewish communities have the right to spend their incomes for their own Jewish community purposes. Also, the Polish government will not be able to interfere in internal Jewish affairs whether religious, social, or cultural. According to these paragraphs, Judaism as a cultural power is autonomous, and <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0482.jpg" n="5"/>Jews, as citizens of the country, must not be hampered in their rights because they are Jews.</p>
   <p>This is all well and good. We may thank the Peace Conference for the security which it guarantees us in the pogrom lands. The question is: Are these guarantees worth more than those which were issued in the Berlin Congress to give Jews equal rights in Rumania as Rumanian citizens, but which immediately proved to be mere "scraps of paper"? It is specifically stated in the above-mentioned paragraphs that the countries from which Constitutional guarantees for security of national and religious minorities are demanded are forbidden to make any separate laws for these minorities.</p>
   <p>On paper this looks attractive but in practice the aspect is entirely different. If Poland, for example, should today demand of Jewish <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0483.jpg" n="6"/>citizens that they submit birth certificates to establish voting privileges, half the Polish Jews would lose the right to vote because they have no such documents. Rumania at one time played this trick on Jews in Dabrudza. After the Jews had been promised all the rights of Rumanian citizens it was later announced that these rights were dependent upon the possession of birth certificates. Jews of Dabrudza, former Turkish citizens, had no such certificates and naturally were denied citizenship rights.</p>
   <p>Poland and Rumania may proceed to extreme lengths in order to evade fulfilling those duties to the Jew which they accepted in the Peace Agreement. The problem, therefore, is not a question of the Good Will of the Peace Conference which seeks to give us security in pogrom countries, but a matter of how to actualize <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0484.jpg" n="7"/>the contents of these paragraphs which give us the desired security on paper. Are the high officials ready to sever their relations with pogrom countries which disregard their obligations? Are they ready to adopt other forceful measures to force pogrom countries to respect the above-mentioned paragraphs? On the answer to this problem hinges the fate not only of a million Jews in Poland but of Judaism throughout Eastern Europe.</p>
   <p>We shall know the answer when the details of the Peace Agreement regarding pogrom countries become known.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
