<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-14">Aug. 14, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Congressman Sabbath Succeeds in Establishing a Station in Chicago for Immigrants</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0117</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0117.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-14">Aug. 14, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">CONGRESSMAN SABBATH SUCCEEDS IN ESTABLISHING A STATION IN CHICAGO FOR IMMIGRANTS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Immigration Commissioner Commineti authorized Congressman Adolph J. Sabbath to investigate the so-called Skeman Public School, on Monroe between Halsted and Desplaines Streets, as a place for an immigrant station.</p>
   <p>It is now an old desolated building being used for city storage.</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabbath had already, for many years, applied all his power and influence to establish a special station for immigrants in Chicago. The many immigrants, passing through the city, have no resting place. They are in danger of being robbed and deceived by the various parasites who live on the account of many greenhorns.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0118.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The government has finally been convinced of the necessity of such an immigrant place in Chicago, which should protect the immigrants from all human parasites and furnish them with the necessary conveniences.</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabbath will make a special trip to Chicago to negotiate for the old school building, in order to secure it as cheaply as possible.</p>
   <p>The station will have special dormitories, rest room, and a restaurant. A group of investigators and inspectors will be engaged to protect the immigrants at the railway stations from thieves, racketeers, and robbers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
