<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Vol. 21, Wk. of <date when="1901-05-04">May 4, 1901</date>. pp.389-390.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Vol. 21, Wk. of <date when="1901-05-04">May 4, 1901</date>. pp.389-390.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Simeon B, Eisendrath, the prominent architect, was born in Chicago in 1868. He received his early education here. While a student at high school he was selected by the teachers to receive the honorary scholarship at the Chicago Manual Training School.</p>
   <p>He later entered the Massachusetts Institute of Technology where he took the course in architecture. Then returning to Chicago, he opened an office in 1890, and began his practice. In a few years he built up an extensive business.</p>
   <p>During the first year of his practice, Mr. Eisendrath was engaged as an expert by the county, rendering valuable assistance in the successful prosecution of Cook County's famous boodle case. Fraudulent contracts in connection with county building operations were exposed, thereby saving many thousands of dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1425.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1889 Mr. Eisendrath was appointed lecturer in the architectural branches of the Chicago Evening High Schools. He built the Michael Reese Training School for Nurses, M. R. Hospital Annex, the Home for Aged Jews, and the Chicago Home for Jewish Orphans.</p>
   <p>In 1893 Mr. Eisendrath was made Commissioner of Buildings, by the Mayor of Chicago. While in office he instituted many practical and important reforms. In 1894 he was forced to resign because of the pressure of private business.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
