<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-18">August 18, 1913</date><title level="a">Remember the Words of Wise</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1238</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1238.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-18">August 18, 1913</date><title level="a">REMEMBER THE WORDS OF WISE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The honored rabbi of the Congregation Anshe Maariv, who writes the weekly column, "News and Survey" in the Chicago Israelite, has for quite some time sought for news about Chicago orthodox Jewry from non-Jewish sources. Therefore, whenever he makes a remark about the orthodox Jewish activities it appears to be topsy turvy.</p>
   <p>The Jewish orthodox public, especially the Jews on the West Side, know his tactics and, therefore, they do not think much about the rabbi's opinion, although the position of Rabbi Schoenfarber ought to make his opinion worth some consideration. If we are unable to agree on religious matters, there is certainly no reason why we should not understand ethics and manners. Rabbi Schoenfarber is active enough in everything pertaining to Jewish charity and consequently, whenever he voices an opinion in such matters his words should not only be given attention, but his suggestion should be put into effect.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the rabbi of Congregation Anshe Maariv shows his antipathy towards everything undertaken by the Chicago Jewish community. It cannot be determined whether this antipathy springs from envy, seeing that the so-called Russian-Jews are organizing their activities in such a manner that they will soon surpass the so-called German-Jews, or whether it springs from ignorance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1239.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whatever the reason may be, the rabbi of Congregation Anshe Maariv, when he discussed in the last edition of the Chicago Israelite the dishonesty among the new and old directors of the Hebrew Sheltering Home, showed that he does not know what goes on; that he got his ideas from the English daily newspapers, which have conveyed the matter from a sensational standpoint. When the rabbi said that the Federated Orthodox Jewish Charities wants to take away the Hebrew Sheltering Home mainly because of its large treasury, he made a statement which is untrue and which can only add fuel to the flames.</p>
   <p>It is fortunate that the Chicago Jewish community does not value the rabbi's opinion. They know that whatever he writes is worth no more than the space it fills; they know that if the honored rabbi intended to act conscientiously, he would at least, contact the Federation and find out the true reason for the misunderstanding. Therefore, what he says can neither do harm nor good. However, this is no excuse for a rabbi of a Jewish community, for an editorial writer of a Jewish newspaper, for a welfare worker, voicing his biased opinions on these matters. He should not forget the ancient maxim: "Remember the Words of the Wise".</p>
   <p>By this slander with which Rabbi Schoenfarer covered the Federation, he showed what he stands for, and as long as he will not make a public apology, he will be kept at a distance from Chicago's orthodox activities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
