<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-11-23">Nov. 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Zion Triumphs in Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-11-23">Nov. 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ZION TRIUMPHS IN CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Rosenwald's plan brought good results. Over $20,000 was raised at the only meeting yesterday morning at the Sinai Temple, and this sum, as significant as it is, was considered a mere trifle in comparison with the great moral triumph that Zionism has celebrated at the same time in this outstanding reformed temple in Chicago. This magnificent temple, seating over 3,000 was filled to its capacity, with many standing in the gallery. Each person found on his seat an envelop addressed to Mr. James Davis, treasurer of the Brandeis committee, containing a small leaflet which briefly explained the Zionist appeal to American Jewry.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0628.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The appeal of Mr. Brandeis touched the hearts of his listeners, and his explanation of why American Jews are duty bound to help build the home for Jews in Palestine.</p>
   <p>For the great success of this meeting, Dr. Hirsch deserves great recognition. He has shown great interest in this movement for Palestine, not only by serving this cause, but by his friendliness and willingness to give his temple and stage to Mr. Brandeis.</p>
   <p>When the ushers were preparing to collect the envelops with the subscriptions, Mr. Julius Rosenwald demanded the floor and declared that he did not approve of the contributions in a lump sum.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0629.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"What will be the result?" he asked. "The war may last a long time, who knows? And when it ends, Palestine, will then need help for a time before she gets on her feet. Therefore, I suggest that instead of a lump sum now, each one of us shall pledge himself to give a certain amount each month as long as the war lasts, and for twelve months thereafter." Mr. Rosenwald pledged himself to give $1,000 every month as long as the war continues and for twelve month after the war has ended.</p>
   <p>After this short and effective talk, Dr. Hirsch expressed his regrets that because the congregation does not pay him salary enough, he can not follow Rosenwald's example in subscribing for Palestine. The subscription cards the ushers collected from those present filled the large box, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0630.jpg" n="4"/>and the actual results will be made known tomorrow after being sorted and entered in a systematic order in the books.</p>
   <p>This meeting may well be recognized as a Jewish triumph for both Zionism and Sinai Temple.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
