<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-09">October 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Rabbis of the Entire World Swear That Blood Accusations Are False</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-09">October 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">RABBIS OF THE ENTIRE WORLD SWEAR THAT BLOOD ACCUSATIONS ARE FALSE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago rabbis, both orthodox and reformed, signed an oath yesterday: "Among Jews there is not even a single sect that uses blood for any ritual purpose whatsoever."</p>
   <p>This signed oath as well as similar ones from all over the world will be cabled to Mogotch, Hungary.</p>
   <p>This plan originated in Marianbad the 19th of Ab of this year. Rabbi Yakov Meyer, the sage of Salonica, was voted president. Rabbi Yosef Lebovitch from Mogotch, Hungary was appointed secretary. They appealed to all <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0679.jpg" n="2"/>the rabbis the world over to send in their testimony in this oath.</p>
   <p>The oath that was signed by reformed and orthodox Jewish rabbis in Chicago reads as follows:</p>
   <p>Whereas, at the present time there is now in process at Kiev, Russia the trial of Mandel Bailis regarding a blood accusation, and whereas, there are some Russians who claim that if the entire Jewish nation does not use blood for ritual purposes there still are certain sects that do, as the Chassidim who use the Kabbala;</p>
   <p>Therefore, I stand as witness and vow, as one who knows all Jewish sects, that there are no groups whatsoever that use blood for ritual purposes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0680.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We term this a lie. It is the reverse that is true. Blood is forbidden to be used according to the laws of the Torah and the Kabbala. No sect of Jews is exempt thereof. Any kind of blood is forbidden, especially that of human beings and there is no sect of the Jewish faith that observes any other religion except that expounded in the Torah.</p>
   <p>If Jews do have various divisions it is only a matter of being more or less orthodox, but all have one religion, one Torah. We,therefore, declare this accusation to be false, it contains not even one iota of truth.</p>
   <p>To This We Affix Our Signatures.</p>
   <p>To this, all the rabbis of Chicago, orthodox and reformed set their signatures. The declaration was cabled to Rabbi Lebovitch in Mogotch, Hungary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0681.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The request to sign such a paper came direct from Rabbi Yosif Lebovitch, secretary, to Rabbi Fisher of Agudoth Achim, whom he knows personally. Immediately a meeting was called of all the rabbis. Because there is not much time left it was decided to send this proclamation by cable and to mail another copy by post.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
