<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-24">Feb. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Literacy Test</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-24">Feb. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE LITERACY TEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Senate will soon vote on the Burnet Immigration Bill and the Literacy Test amendment, in which a demand is incorporated that every immigrant over sixteen years of age, male or female, must be able to read English or any other language, including Hebrew or Yiddish.</p>
   <p>If this bill should be adopted in the Senate by a two-thirds majority, the President of the United States will have no power to veto it.</p>
   <p>Those senators who are bitter foes of immigration are apparently exerting their influence on the other senators in order to gain the desired majority. They are doing this for two reasons: First, they fear that President Wilson will perhaps veto the bill; secondly, they intend to save the President from committing himself by gaining a two-thirds majority in the Senate, so that the President need not appear as a foe of immigration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0078.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Hence, notwithstanding Wilson's declaration, shortly after the Burnet Bill was adopted in the House of Representatives, that he is against the Literacy Test, his friendship with the defenders of the bill has not been lessened in the least. We cannot, therefore, feel any too certain as to his own position on this question.</p>
   <p>The question of the immigration bill is now being discussed in the national press. Various savants express the opinion that the whole riffraff about limiting immigration flows from impractical sources, as the country has not reached the stage where its population exceeds its geographical boundaries. The United States has an area large enough to accommodate twice its present population, the truth being that only 27% of its territory is now settled.</p>
   <p>From a moral point of view, it is pointed out that the United States has absolutely no right to do this. The country proper consists of immigrants, children of immigrants, and descendants of immigrant forefathers. Had the doors of America been closed before, these foes of the immigrant would not <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0079.jpg" n="3"/>be here today. It therefore stands to reason that the restriction of immigration is a moral crime.</p>
   <p>The foremost counterattack on the Immigration Bill comes from those who believe that every restriction on immigration procrastinates the economic development of the country. Compared with other countries, America is young and fallow. The agricultural status of this country is especially at a low ebb and, therefore, requires energetic and capable agriculturists.</p>
   <p>The most proficient farmers of the country, far from being Yankees, are of immigrant stock. We know that the best farmers of the country, under whose hands the Wild West has been transformed into a blooming grandeur, are immigrants. Now that the farmers' children are flocking to cities, it is imperative that the immigrants come to this country in order to develop the land and replace those who abandon their farms.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0080.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is also an established fact that immigrants are working in coal, ore, and copper mines, and that only through the constant flow of immigration are the large industries able to carry on.</p>
   <p>The larger the population of the country, the broader its domestic market, for the greater the number of people, the larger becomes the number of products that are required. As a matter of course, let us say fifty years from now, the United States will have twice as many people as it has today and its domestic market will also be doubled. The general practice in every country is to develop the home market, the development of foreign trade being only secondary. Above everything, competition with other countries is too keen for foreign markets.</p>
   <p>The consensus of opinion is that the Literacy Test falls short of being what it is intended to be, and, if anything, it reveals that the Immigration Bill is not so much aimed at undesired immigrants as it is at immigration in general, for it is a fact that those who unfortunately had no opportunity to learn how to read and write in the countries from whence they came, can, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0081.jpg" n="5"/>however, become the best citizens in the United States. As it is known to all, in many European countries the system of education is so inadequate as to make it impossible for a great number of people to obtain an elementary education.</p>
   <p>It is a great mistake to think that a person who can read and write will make a better citizen than one who can't.</p>
   <p>Many criminologists have proved that the most vicious criminals are men possessing education.</p>
   <p>This is why all agree that the Literacy Test should not be adopted under any circumstances. Notwithstanding the fact that some of the senators are working zealously to win the support of a two-thirds majority to pass the bill, nearly everybody is of the opinion that they will not succeed, because such a measure would simply prove a boomerang to the Democratic Administration, which by no means would invite its own destruction, since <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0082.jpg" n="6"/>the immigrants' votes play such an important role as to make any party think twice. And there is no doubt that were the Democrats to adopt this bill, their party will become an enemy of the immigrants.</p>
   <p>The present immigration bill is also superfluous because, as it is, we have already enough restrictions on immigration. Be it sufficient to mention that twenty thousand unfortunate immigrants were deported last year. The curious thing is that while all intellectuals attack the immigration bill only from the literacy angle, other odious clauses remain ignored. What is the reason for this? Do they concur with remaining clauses? Another article dealing with this shall follow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
