<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-04">Apr. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Theodore B. Sachs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1153</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1153.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-04">Apr. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THEODORE B. SACHS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The medical profession has lost an important member. Chicago citizens mourn a devoted neighbor. Dead is Chicago's true Jewish son--the fighter against the white plague. The poor, sick Jews grieve as though for a father or mother.</p>
   <p>THEODORE B. SACHS IS DEAD</p>
   <p>The medical profession should not feel discouraged. Other members can continue where Dr. Sachs left off. The citizens of Chicago will forget. New devoted neighbors will take the place of Dr. Sachs. The Jewish community of Chicago will give this faithful son a great funeral, and will then look forward to many other faithful sons. The West Side will gain new fighters against the white plague. The poor, sick Jews--who can wipe your tears which flow for that great man who lies now in the coffin? Who can give an orphan a father? Who can comfort a baby [whose mother had been taken]?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1154.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What hope remains for one stricken with the sweat of the white plague when there are no parents to remove that sweat?</p>
   <p>Theodore B. Sachs is dead and with him died the hopes of many poor Jews [whose homes have been attacked by the dread scourge of tuberculosis].</p>
   <p>They say that Dr. Theodore B. Sachs took his own life.</p>
   <p>Nonsense.</p>
   <p>Dr. Sachs did not possess a life. It was for others that his heart throbbed. When like a David, he resisted the Goliath of tuberculosis, he did not seek to protect his life, nor to enrich it, nor even to make it more comfortable. He fought for lives sentenced to death by society. He snatched the sword from the executioner who had legally murdered tens of thousands of innocent people annually. Not having life, he had none to take.</p>
   <p>They say that Dr. Theodore Sachs committed suicide.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1155.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This is still more foolish.</p>
   <p>It is evident that Dr. Sachs will now begin to live--[now that his soul has left his body--now that his entire life's work has ended--now that his goal has been destroyed]. More than anyone, Dr. Sachs realized this; [he knew] the result was [to be expected] after he had sacrificed his life for many years for those whom he loved; after he had, for a quarter of a century, given his spirit for his patients; after he had sacrificed his honor and reputation for his ideas; after he had used up his energy in his great struggle; after he was left with nothing but his body, he brought that also as a sacrifice for that which was sacred and dear to him--for the lives of the sufferers.</p>
   <p>Theodore B. Sachs is not dead. He will live an eternal life. Dr. Sachs is however dead to the indigent, sick Jews--the greatest victims of the white plague who are forgotten by everyone in this tragic moment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
