<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-06">Feb. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">We Don't Want War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-06">Feb. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WE DON'T WANT WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The amendment to the Barnett Bill, intended to limit the immigration of the Japanese and other Asiatic peoples, fell through. In sharp and heated debates, our representatives in Congress said that they don't want war.</p>
   <p>We boast of civilization, of a highly cultured and morally developed mankind; yet, we act like wild barbarians. The primitive savage does not see on a foreigner anything but how good he is for devouring or enslaving; yet he fears him.</p>
   <p>The thing is that congressmen are afraid of war. Those who frustrated the amendment, recognize that the Asiatics should not have been admitted because they are powerful and united.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0084.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is still another fact. Why fear the Asiatic and not the European? Are the European nations weaker than the Asiatic? Certainly not! The sad truth is that European powers care little for the masses or the sufferings of the poor. They do not care whether one of their emigrants is permitted to enter or not.</p>
   <p>The Asiatic powers are, on the contrary, still bound to their people. They are ready to defend with arms the honor of the poorest citizen; and even the reactionaries of our Republic fear war.</p>
   <p>However, the most important feature in this bill is that the President understands better than all congressmen that it is not practical at all, because the more illiterate a worker is, the better it is for the capitalists of the country. With this point in view, Wilson will probably veto it. The immigration limitations will reflect on the victims of foreign powers, i.e., the political offender and the religious persecuted Jew, against whom the Russian government can furnish as much evidence as is needed. For them, evidently, the portals <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0085.jpg" n="3"/>of the country will be closed, because even America hasn't any great sympathy for this element. It is possible that the present immigration limitations are intended for this element as a result of the discontent that since recently has been brewing in this country, where, owing to the high cost of living, strikes are breaking out everywhere. The foes of the immigrant blame him because he dares demand humane conditions for himself and his fellow-citizens. To bar this undesirable element they drew up the immigration bill, and every clause tending to eliminate immigrants was recognized as right by all congressmen.</p>
   <p>It stands to reason that the nations from where these immigrants come will not intercede for them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
