<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-24">May 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Moses Barnett Is Dead</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1093</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1093.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-24">May 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MOSES BARNETT IS DEAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Moses Barnett, cousin of the well-known Chicago civic leader H. M. Barnett, died yesterday afternoon at the age of 62 after a short illness at Washington Boulevard Hospital.</p>
   <p>The deceased came to Chicago fifty years ago. His father, Aaron Barnett, was the first Jew to open a kosher butcher shop, on Clark Street half a century ago. The Barnett family later founded the Beth Hamedrash Hagodol (synagogue) and Moses Barnett served there till the last days, first as president and later as superintendent. He also assisted in the founding of the Talmud Torah, was president of Somech Noflem (Support of the Downtrodden), and participated in the work of various other benevolent institutions.</p>
   <p>The deceased leaves a widow, Becky Barnett, who resides at 1207 Ashland Avenue; three brothers, Ben, Joe, and George; and a sister, Flora Lugoff of Duluth, Minnesota.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1094.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The funeral service will take place today at 10 A.M. at the chapel of Weinstein and Neierman, undertakers, 3652 West 12th Street, and also in the Beth Hamedrash Hagodol, corner Douglas and St. Louis, where the Rabbis Ephraim Epstein, Ezriel Epstein, and Nisan Budzinsky will deliver the eulogy. Cantor Solovaychuk will chant the memorial prayer. The deceased will be laid to rest near his parents in the Oakwoods Cemetery.</p>
   <p>All members of the congregation Beth Hamedrash Hagodol; Dr. Sultan Lodge, Independent Order Bnai Abraham; Malbin Lodge, Progressive Order of the West, and other lodges of which the deceased was a member; and also his countrymen from Maryampol are expected to be present to pay their last respects to the deceased.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
