<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-29">Apr. 29, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Rabbi Hirsch Makes a Zionist Speech</title><title level="a" type="sub">Promises to Help Movement if Zionists Will Stop Throwing Stones at Reformed Judaism</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0556</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0556.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-29">Apr. 29, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">RABBI HIRSCH MAKES A ZIONIST SPEECH</title><title level="a" type="sub">Promises To Help Movement If Zionists Will Stop Throwing Stones At Reformed Judaism</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The famous Rabbi of Sinai Temple, Dr. Emil G. Hirsch can soon be counted upon as a Zionist. For during the last three weeks, he has begun to acquaint himself more and more with Zionism and the reality of its program. His first step on the road to Zionism was to invite Dr. Ben-Zion Mosenson to speak yesterday at Sinai Temple. Because of bad weather the audience was not as large as was expected and Rabbi Hirsch therefore immediately invited the well-known Zionist leader to again address the members of his temple on the 12th of May.</p>
   <p>Dr. Mosenson's speech greatly impressed the audience; also good results are expected from his second address to be given at Sinai Temple on the 12th of May.</p>
   <p>The following excerpts from Dr. Hirsch's address make the Zionists believe <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0557.jpg" n="2"/>that the Rabbi of Sinai Temple has come closer to the ideas of Zionism, if not officially, then surely unofficially:</p>
   <p>"If the Zionists will stop criticizing and throwing stones at Reformed Judaism, then I am ready with all the power at my command to help them, and I can assure them, that they won't have a better friend, or a more active worker than I.</p>
   <p>"I am far from agreeing with those who become Zionists only for selfish purposes, for the sake of politics or other things, but those who sincerely believe in the ideals do much for the future of Judaism and humanity."</p>
   <p>Thursday evening, a dinner will be given at the Standard Club in honor of Dr. Mosenson. To this club belong the wealthiest and the most influential Jews of Chicago. On the invitations to this dinner appear the names of Judge Julian W. Mack, Albert H. Loeb and Dr. Emil G. Hirsch.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
