<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-11">May 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Galician Farbond Sends a Commission to Galicia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0538</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0538.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-11">May 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GALICIAN FARBOND SENDS A COMMISSION TO GALICIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Known Jewish civic workers and prosperous men in the National Committee under the auspices of the Joint Distribution Committee, will accept contributions from Galician societies and individuals for the purpose of distribution in Galicia.</p>
   <p>The Farbond of Galicia and Bukovina Jews in America will send shortly a special commission to Galicia with the purpose of bringing material aid to the Jewish population, and to establish direct communication between Galician and American Jews and their relatives across the sea. The commission, though sent directly from the Galician Farbond, will remain under the auspices of the Joint Distribution Committee.</p>
   <p>The harbingers of the Farbond will be outstanding in their mission, inasmuch as they will deviate from the functions of former commissions. The purpose of the committee is to take the funds collected by nearly a hundred Galician and Bukovinian Vereins and bring them to the Galician-Bukovinian states and villages for which they were designated. A detailed report shows <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0539.jpg" n="2"/>that in New York alone there are three hundred Galician Vereins named after the various cities and villages from which their members have come. Each of these vereins, without exception, possesses a relief fund which in the last few years was gathered specifically for the benefit of their individual villages. Not a cent of these funds, ranging from five hundred to five thousand dollars or more, the total combined sum being in the neighborhood of hundreds of thousands of dollars, has till now been used for this expressed purpose, simply because up to the present time there was no trustworthy committee that promised to transport these moneys and distribute them in the desired villages specified by these "Countrymen" Vereins. This work is now the responsibility of the commission sent from the Galician-Bukovinian Farbond.</p>
   <p>To facilitate pecuniary matters, and to see that all function properly, the Farbond elected a special committee called "The Committee for the Rebuilding of Galicia." This committee, composed of the most prominent, rich, and active workers, will directly supervise and be personally responsible for all moneys given to the commission that sails for Galicia. In the Committee for Rebuilding Galicia are found the well-known rich social workers W. William Fishman, Bernard Zemel, Isadore Bloiner, Jacob Shparbar, Lewis Bargenicht, I. M.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0540.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Wachman, Max Schwartz, S. Kronenberg, Yisker Thoe, F. Baron, and many others.</p>
   <p>The committee opened an office at 66 Second Avenue, where money will be received and receipts issued will be signed by William Fishman, Isadore Bloiner, and Bernard Zemel.</p>
   <p>The committee is also ready to accept money from individuals who wish to send it to their relatives in Galicia. The commission sailing for Galicia will formulate a system whereby they can get in touch with every Jew in Galicia and in Bukovina who have relatives in America. In this way, it will be possible for every Galician Jew in America to send money to his relatives in Galicia proper, with the assurance that the commission will do everything possible to find the indicated relative in these lands.</p>
   <p>The Farbond's Committee for Rebuilding Galicia will stand all expenses connected with sending the commission to Galicia and the installation of machinery for locating relatives in the Old Home. The committee guarantees that every cent entrusted to it for Galicia, both from organizations and from individuals, will <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0541.jpg" n="4"/>reach the destination for which it was meant.</p>
   <p>The Commission that sails for Galicia will consist of the most prominent and responsible persons of Galician circles. Arrangements have already been made, that in this mission should be Bernard Zemel, William Fishman, Isadore Bloiner, and Dr. S. Margoshes, the president of the Galician and Bukoviner Farbond.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
