<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-03-08">March 8, 1930</date>. Volume 79; p. 124.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0832</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0832.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-03-08">March 8, 1930</date>. Volume 79; p. 124.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the many people who entertained the same hopes were two brothers, who were in daily attendance at the Jewish Congress. These two men had not yet attained the prominence which to day makes their names known to all Chicago Jews. Bernard and Harris Horwich were still unknown at the time of which I write, but since I shall have occasion to refer to one or the other often in the course of this chronicle, I shall sketch here a brief outline of their lives.</p>
   <p>Bernard Horwich left his native town in Russia in the middle of the seventies and went to Germany where he remained for five years. From there he came to the United States and settled in Chicago. Here he engaged in business and made fair progress. Several years later he married the daughter of Rabbi Eliezar Anxter. Family responsiblities and business interests filled all of his time and left him no leisure moments to devote to other things.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0833.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The arrival in Chicago of his brother, Harris, in 1891, brought a great change in the lives of both brothers. The practical Bernard with his keen sense of humor was a sharp contrast to the serious minded Harris. The latter, the older of the two, a young man of the town of Poniemon, was a devoted student of the Talmud, until alas! he was ensnared by the "evil spirit" of the Haskalah and began to delve into the Neo-Hebraic literature and to study mathematics, history and geography.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
