<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-01-08">Jan. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Prominent Rabbi Dr. Emil G. Hirsch Dies</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1027</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1027.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-01-08">Jan. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">PROMINENT RABBI DR. EMIL G. HIRSCH DIES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Emil Gustov Hirsch, aged seventy-one, who occupied the pulpit for many years at the Sinai Congregation, died yesterday morning at his residence, 4608 Drexel Blvd.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch was one of the best orators in the country. His word was listened to with much respect. He, especially, raised his voice prior to the war. He denounced war and the war patriots, who force the country into the wholesale slaughter.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch was also Professor of Rabbinical Literature in the University of Chicago, and was known as one of the most prominent Jewish personalities in America. He was born in Luxemburg, May 27, 1852. He acquired his elementary education in the public schools of Luxemburg. He also attended the University of Pennsylvania. He went to Philadelphia with his father in 1886, when the latter was Rabbi of Congregation Knesis Israel. He continued his studies in Philadelphia at the Episcopal Academy. He graduated from the University of Pennsylvania in 1872. In that year he went to Germany and continued his studies in the Berlin University and then in Leipzig University, where he <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1028.jpg" n="2"/>received his degree, Doctor of Philosophy and Theology.</p>
   <p>Upon his return to America, Dr. Hirsch became Rabbi of the Mt. Sinai Congregation in Baltimore. In 1878 he became the spiritual leader of a congregation in Louisville, Kentucky, and in 1880 he came to Chicago, where he immediately became Rabbi of the Sinai Congregation, where he retained his Rabbinical position until death.</p>
   <p>Dr. Emil Hirsch had also published several newspapers. He published the Spiritual Times, in Milwaukee, in 1883, in 1886 he published the Reformer in New York and in 1888 he published the Reform Advocate. In the same year, he was appointed a member (later president) on the board of the Chicago Public Library. He had, also for some time. lectured on Jewish Poetry in the John Hopkins University, in Baltimore. Dr. Hirsch wrote many important treatises about the Bible, theology and sociology. He was one of the founders of the Jewish Manual Training Schools in Chicago and organized the Associated Jewish Charities. He was, for some time, president of the Board of Examiners of the Civil Service Commission in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
