<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-04-04">Apr. 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">In Our Days</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0543</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0543.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-04-04">Apr. 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">IN OUR DAYS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Gothard Deutsch, rector of history at the Union Theological College, proposed a very worthwhile plan at a conference held in Cincinnati by the reformed rabbis of the United States.</p>
   <p>This plan has very high aims and ideals. It proposes that since Jerusalem is freed from Turkey, it would be well to establish there a publishing house, equipped with the best and most modern printing machinery, which, in addition to publishing books, religious as well as academical, needed by the Jewish public, such as Bibles, prayer books, etc., will be able to give employment to Jewish workers and scholars.</p>
   <p>The Jerusalem Publishing House will publish new editions of the works of the Middle Ages, with greater neatness and accuracy than hitherto possible. This great task was delayed and neglected because of the 1914 census in Russia. The Jerusalem Publishing House will give proper attention to various old unpublished manuscripts, and will help develop the art of printing in Jerusalem, thus serving two purposes: one economic and the <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0544.jpg" n="2"/>other educational.</p>
   <p>This project not only provides work for printers, pressmen, compositors, stereotypists, proof-readers, bookbinders, and other workers, but will also give employment to many scholars living in Palestine, who will be able to do proof-reading, translating, transcribing, and other tasks. This project will elevate Jewish learning and wisdom to the zenith of perfection.</p>
   <p>Dr. Deutsh, as head of the committee, proposed that a certain number of shares, which the new executive committee would determine, be signed at the conference. Circulars are to be mailed to all members, inviting them to exert their influence for, and contribute to, this worthwhile undertaking. Many prominent people, now dead, were mentioned during the session. High tribute was paid to the late Dr. Rubin, organizer of the International Society of Agriculture, in Rome, Italy, who died the first of the year. Dr. Deutsch also mentioned the late Dr. John B. Foster, professor of Divinity at the University of Chicago, who died several months ago.</p>
   <p>Dr. Foster, one of the most brillant teachers of the liberal conception of religion, taught many of the young rabbis who attended the University of <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0545.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago.</p>
   <p>Dr. Deutsch recommended the adoption of a resolution expressing sentiments of respect to this great, liberal minded master, a copy of which is to be sent to the University of Chicago. Also mentioned in the report were the late Rabbi Moritz Niederman, of Vienna, and the Brisker genius, Chaim Solveitzick, who contrasted the conception of true Judaism with the conception of the reformed rabbis. The personality of Chaim Brisker was so enlightened, pure, and earnest that the rabbis at the conference felt that an expression of deep respect was due to this great and noble scholar.</p>
   <p>Going from one topic into another, Dr. Deutsch said that Dr. Max Nordau will soon celebrate his seventieth anniversary; that on April third of next year will be the two hundredth anniversary of the Vilno Genius; and that the three hundredthe anniversary of Mr. Chaim Wital falls on May 26, 1920. Dr. Deutsch also said that the reprint of the Vilno Shas (Six orders of the Talmud) should contain photographs taken in America, urging conference, to aid in this unique undertaking.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
