<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-27">Oct. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Our Language Problem</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-27">Oct. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">OUR LANGUAGE PROBLEM</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are asked to give our opinion regarding the language problem in Palestine.</p>
   <p>The Jews of America have done much to maintain the existence of Jewish Palestine and feel that they have a right to voice their opinions regarding the use of the Hebrew or the German languages.</p>
   <p>The Jewish youth, those born and reared in Palestine, want Hebrew to be the language of the people, in the homes as well as in the schools. The German Jews who founded and rule the Jewish colonies do not believe this will be possible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0675.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>First, because there are no well trained professors in the Hebrew, second, because youths who have completed their studies in the Hebrew and are ready to enter the industrial world, will find European ownership and influence for which their Hebrew does not prepare them.</p>
   <p>We, on the other hand, seem to be more strongly connected with the Hebrew than the German, yet we shall try to be non-partisan. Let us think of the friendly spirited feelings of the Hebrew speaking youths of Palestine, and of the cold logic of our rich "uncles" in Germany.</p>
   <p>It is true, that we do not have enough professors competent in the Hebrew language, or even text books for the purpose. But, this is no reason for adopting the German language. Let the language be Hebrew, and let those professors, not possessing the knowledge thereof, be given a definite length of time to learn it. The outstanding fact is that, in time, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0676.jpg" n="3"/>they should be able to teach the language of Israel. Thus each professor should be given to understand that his strange tongue will be permitted only until a properly trained man can be secured to teach the various subjects in Hebrew.</p>
   <p>The fact that one should know a European language well is absolutely correct. But, it may be taught as a separate subject and need not be used as the basis of all studies. In speaking of European languages, we find the same importance, in the Orient, to speak French, and those who do not choose to be in the Orient may find English even more important in those places where Jews gather most frequently in their wanderings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0677.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Hebrew should be the language taught in Jewish schools in Palestine, especially in Haffa which is the center of the pro-Jewish Germans. Here the Hebrew language will have a hard struggle to establish itself and the Yiddish should not be used as a weapon to defeat its purpose.</p>
   <p>We hope the German Jewish leaders will think of these facts and consider them carefully at their conference today in Berlin; and that they may espouse the cause of the rebirth of our dear old land, thereby helping to strengthen the bonds of our people, our language, and our land.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
