<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-12-15">December 15, 1910</date><title level="a">Zion Chronicle</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <!--                    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G.Zionism"/>
    -->
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G (Zionism)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-12-15">December 15, 1910</date><title level="a">ZION CHRONICLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jews of Chicago are called upon by the Zionists organization of the world to help the Jewish National Fund. The statement they make in this appeal is as follows:</p>
   <p>We come to you Jews of Chicago, in the name of our Jewish nation from which we have inherited the best and finest that we possess. Our wish is to reclaim our most treasured land by which we will insure honor and respect for our Jewish nation; the land of Israel, where our nation was born and grew to be great; the land of our Prophets and our Maccabees; ( warriors); our beautiful Holy Land. It comes to us Jews in Chicago and to Jews in other cities, to help redeem and deliver this Holy Land back in the hands of the Jewish nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0138.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now is the opportune time for our Jews to show their national pride, religiously, and historical understanding makes our aim, persistent, to have our Holy Land back in our hands. Should we fail at this opportune time, it will most certainly make an eternal stain on the Jewish nation's name. So the plan is this: to buy land in the Holy Land, as much as possible, and settle as many jews as possible on the land. That is the main object in view of the Jewish National Fund.</p>
   <p>The fund at present is worth over a half million dollars, that was collected in different countries. A large portion of this fund has already been invested in Palestine land. The National Jewish Fund can never resell this land, it has to remain Jewish land for the Jewish nation, forever.</p>
   <p>This land buying undertaking of Palestine is so enormous and important, that every Jew in Chicago must take an interest in this Holy cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0139.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Buy a "Dunas," a one-fourth of an acre of land for the sum of $10 or you may buy one-eighth of an acre for $5. As a deed for this land you get a certificate and your name is registered in the National Jewish Fund Book.</p>
   <p>The semi-annual report of the National Jewish Fund shows a total collection of $9,246.39 from May 24 to November 24, 1910.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
