<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-10">Oct. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A Letter to a Roman Catholic Bishop</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-10">Oct. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A LETTER TO A ROMAN CATHOLIC BISHOP</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Most Reverend and Dear Sir: The Roman Catholic church, ordering its believers to pray once a year for the Jews and for their salvation, is still taking an interest in the stiff-necked people, and, though it does not try to convert them by the missionary methods of the Protestant church, it does everything in its power to bring about their conversion to your Christianity. It does it by bringing a terrible pressure to bear on the Jews in those countries where your church is supreme, and in political power. In Hungary, your church is affiliated with all the enemies of our people, and is the motive power in the policy of terror of the Hungarian government against the Jews. In Poland, the Roman Catholic church is actually the guide of the pogrom policies of an immoral government, and of a demoralized people. In Austria all the anti-Semitic energies radiate from the church and from its representatives, the clergymen. In short, in all <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0373.jpg" n="2"/>the countries where the church is supreme, there is a deliberate attempt made to force the Jews into its arms, not by trying to convince them of the superiority of your religion, and of the truth contained in it, but by methods befitting, not the twentieth century, but the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries. The representatives of the Roman Catholic church are also interested in the spiritual welfare of our people; they, too, are trying to save our souls by spending millions of dollars a year on missionary work. Their methods of conquering us are at least pacific and civilized. Their missionaries try to argue with our children and our adults, and they appeal to our intellect and to our emotions, or to our human superstition. But your church, still nourishing and cultivating the traditions of the Holy Inquisition, acts differently. The Inquisition, as an institution, is, as you know, not yet abolished. The office of the Grand Inquisitor still exists, and though it is not permitted to bury human beings alive, because state and society would not stand for it, your church, in its attempts to bring the Jews under its wings, is still using many methods of the Inquisition. One of the most notorious methods of the Inquisition of old was economic pressure against <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0374.jpg" n="3"/>the Jews. Our ancestors in Spain or Portugal were often offered by your church the one alternative: either adopt Roman Catholicism or we confiscate your property. The Roman Catholic church has confiscated property of the Jews in Spain and Portugal amounting to tens of millions of dollars. Today confiscation pure and simple is no longer possible. Even the most Catholic and most clerical government cannot permit it. Instead of confiscating Jewish property, in case of the unwillingness of the Jew to adopt Roman Catholicism, your church uses today another trick as bad and as mean a trick as that of confiscation: an economic boycott against the Jews.</p>
   <p>In the lands where your church is politically supreme, or where it is highly influential, like in Poland, Hungary, Austria, and in many parts of Germany, there is an economic boycott against the Jews. In Poland the economic boycott against our people is already thirteen years in existence, and it assumes from day to day more terrible forms. In Hungary the Jews are actually excluded from business, and in Austria, where millions of people are still <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0375.jpg" n="4"/>under the spell of the Roman Catholic church, the economic boycott against the Jews is also felt very strongly.</p>
   <p>I am sorry to state that the results of this policy of economic pressure in the form of [an] economic boycott against our people in Catholic lands has not been less disastrous than the policy of confiscation during the time of the black terror of the Holy Inquisition in Spain and Portugal. Millions of Jews have been reduced to actual beggary, and thousands of them have been forced by sheer hunger to join the Church; that is to say, to desert our own race and our own religion. In spite of the revival of Judaism as the result of the war, the list of Jewish converts to your church in Austria, Hungary, and Poland, and in many parts of Germany is increasing weekly. Especially those intellectual, or semi-intellectual Jews, whose intellectuality has been developed at the expense of their will power, fall victims to the economic pressure brought to bear on them by your church. The Jewish communities in Berlin, Vienna, and Budapest are still issuing week by week lists of Jewish converts to the <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0376.jpg" n="5"/>Roman Catholic church, and most of these converts come from the middle class, because it is the middle class that suffers most from the economic boycott against the Jews.</p>
   <p>Another feature of the anti-Jewish activities of your church is the combining of clericalism with nationalism in all the lands where your church is in power. This combination has proven to be the most powerful weapon against the Jews, both politically and economically. In Austria, Hungary, and Poland, clericalism, nationalism and anti-Semitism are identical. In many cases, the clergymen in high position are active leaders in the anti-Semitic movement. Like in the dark Middle Ages, the Jews, badly harrassed and cruelly persecuted by the Roman Catholic mobs, have appealed to the clergy of your church for help, but their appeals were in vain. Is it not strange that no Roman Catholic dignitary has deemed it advisable or necessary to come out in the open against the anti-Semitic movement? Like in the Middle Ages, when the Roman Catholic church coerced the Jews into Roman Catholicism, while the Jews have displayed so much stiff-neckedness and have exhibited so much stubborness <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0377.jpg" n="6"/>during the last two thousand years, suffering pain and martyrdom at the hands of your church, [so] will [the Jews] finally be coerced into Roman Catholicism if the church succeeds in breaking the Jew economically and politically. The combination of clericalism and nationalism, the most unholy alliance that was ever formed, is the weapon with which your church hopes to crush the Jew. By intensifying the nationalistic sentiment everywhere, by turning it into criminal chauvinism, the church hopes to annihilate the Jew politically. Only when chauvinism is at its height, can the Jew be deprived of [his] civic and political rights, only then can he be made an alien instead of a more patriotic citizen. Once deprived of his political rights by anti-Semitic legislation, and once shattered economically by economic boycotts, the Jew in Catholic lands will be placed before the alternative, either to emigrate or adopt Roman Catholicism and be free.</p>
   <p>The same policy was pursued by your church in the Middle Ages. At the time, however, the representatives of your church did not find it even necessary to go to the trouble of organizing boycotts against the Jews, but they <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0378.jpg" n="7"/>would simply confiscate Jewish properties, and if that would not help, would dictate expulsion orders. For more than one hundred years the Roman Catholic church has tried to bring Spanish Jewry to its knees, by constantly confiscating Jewish properties, and when this policy of confiscation and open robbery proved to be unsuccessful, the representatives of your church proceeded to expel the Jews from the country altogether, by causing a despotic and bigoted monarch to sign an expulsion decree. To break the Spanish Jews altogether, and to prevent their economic recuperation, your church forbade the exiles to carry money with them or other valuables like silver and gold; they had to leave the country like beggars after having worked for its prosperity [for] nearly one thousand years. The church is now pursuing toward Jews in Catholic lands a similar policy, but different in its methods. Instead of confiscation, it is economic boycott, and instead of plain expulsion, it is depriving the Jew of his political and civic rights to such an extent and of pogroming [sic] him so much, that he [will] be compelled to leave the country. The Jews in Roman Catholic lands find themselves today in the same position as their ancestors in Spain and in <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0379.jpg" n="8"/>Portugal prior to the expulsion. The very basis of their economic life is shattered, the odium against them supreme, and there is no possibility for them whatsoever to remain in those countries, because it is the will of your church that they either adopt your faith or be ruined. I admit, most Reverend Sir, that the Catholic church will now succeed in breaking the Jew economically and politically, in all those lands where your church is supreme, and it will be successful in bringing about the exodus of the Jews from those lands, as it was successful in bringing about the expulsion of the Jews from Spain and Portugal. But whether or not the interest of your church will be better served by this disastrous result of its anti-Jewish policies, is a different question altogether.</p>
   <p>The result of the exodus of the Jews from Spain was that a highly developed country, at the height of civilization, and the most powerful empire of its time, sank into barbarity and was later on crushed politically and economically. Spain of today, poverty-stricken, ignorant, fanatic, and a bigot, is still suffering from the results of the Jewish expulsion in 1492. The same <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0380.jpg" n="9"/>holds good of Portugal. But meanwhile, the Roman Catholic church can hold its grip on the poor and pauperized country and rule it despotically. In the case of the Spanish Jews, your church was successful in every respect. It attained all its aims and objects, viz: to keep the Spanish people poor and ignorant, in order to be able to rule them and to control all their movements; but I doubt very much whether your church will bring about similar results in the case of Poland, Hungary, and Austria. After all, we are not living any more in the fifteenth but in the twentieth century. The wheel of history is moving now a million times faster than four hundred years ago. The Polish, Hungarian, and Austrian people will soon come to recognize the disastrous results of your policies with respect to the Jews, and will turn against you. The pauperized Poles or Hungarians or Austrians will not fail to ask the question, how is it that those countries with large Jewish populations are prosperous and wealthy, while their countries without the Jews are poverty-stricken and its population ignorant? Somebody will rise and tell them why it is so. He will tell them that the Jew is a great factor in the civilization of a people, that the Jew is industrious, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0381.jpg" n="10"/>inventive, resourceful, and a great help to every people and to every nation; and that all the Jewless countries of the white men are lacking in industry and commerce. And when the people will find this out, one day, you can expect only one result, viz: a reaction against your church. It seems to me, most Reverend Sir, that from the point of view of your [own] interest, it is poor statesmanship to continue the anti-Jewish traditions of the Inquisition, because you cannot possibly expect that the Inquisition applied to the Jews today in a different form will bring the same results to the church as it brought four hundred years ago. Poland, Austria, and Hungary are not Spain; they are centrally located countries, subject to currents and countercurrents, and various influences from all sides, and it will not take the peoples of these countries very long to find out who was the cause of their economic and political downfall. Then your church will be the sufferer. And if these countries turn against your church, then good-bye Roman Catholicism for all time, because it is dead in France, it is buried in England, it is crushed in Portugal, it is shattered in Germany, and the only refuge for Roman <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0382.jpg" n="11"/>Catholicism in Europe, say, [are] Poland, Austria, and Hungary. If Central Europe turns against your church too, then you may hope to build up another center for your church in China or in black Africa, but in Europe the Catholic church will be a thing of the past, and Roman Catholicism will be on par with any other religious sect instead of being the leading Christian church in the world. We Jews, by virtue of our own history, and because of our many experiences in the past, possess a highly developed historic instinct, and it is this historic instinct of ours that tells us that your church is now playing with fire. If we are going to be wiped out in Eastern Europe, the church, in consequence, will also be wiped out.</p>
   <p>Now it is true that we Jews are not very much concerned with the perpetuation of your church. If it leaves us alone, we are neither its friends nor its enemies, and it is immaterial to us whether it is the Roman Catholic church that is supreme or the Protestant church. And I am frank enough to state that if I speak of the possible disastrous result for your own church, as a consequence of its continuing the anti-Jewish policies of the Inquisition, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0383.jpg" n="12"/>it is not because I take an interest in the welfare of your church and its continuation, but because I know that the Roman Catholic bishops are realistically inclined and can be talked business to. I am sure that if the representatives of your church will come to realize that your anti-Jewish policies will do you more harm than good, you will give up these policies, because no matter how great your ambition may be to crush the Jewish people, and to crush Judaism, your will to live and to exist is still stronger.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, I want to call your attention, most Reverend Sir, to a fact probably well known to you, too, and this fact is, that each and every guilt finds its revenge on this earth. It is a superficial conception of history to imagine that one group of people can commit crimes against another group of people, and get out without punishment. By repeating the misdeeds of the Holy Inquisition, only in different forms, you invite the perpetual odium and hatred of our people, and we have our own ways and methods of how to get even with our enemies. We have crushed ancient <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0384.jpg" n="13"/>Rome by imposing Christianity on it, we have crushed czarist Russia by imposing a Trotsky on it, who is meting out to Russia all that is coming to her, and another Trotsky will arise to avenge the crimes your church is committing against us. You should not misunderstand me, and you should not misinterpret this statement in the sense that the Jews consciously and deliberately sent Trotsky to Russia to avenge Russia's crimes against the Jews. The Jews have no such power to do it, and the Jews are all against Trotsky, but history sent Trotsky to Russia to do what he is doing just now, and history will find another Trotsky to avenge the misdeeds of your church against us. You may crush us, but we will crush you, too. We do not invite your prayers for us, we do not even care for your sympathy with us. We only wish to be left alone, and not to be imposed upon by the Roman Catholic church, and not to suffer from its Inquisitorial policies. We have been poor neighbors in history for the last fifteen hundred years, and to be more correct, your church has been a bad neighbor of Judaism, and unless your church gives up its attempts to force us into its arms by using inquisitorial methods against us, a catastrophe for both of us must be the <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0385.jpg" n="14"/>result. If you take this to heart, and convey the message of a lonely Jew to your brothers in faith, you will render a great service to your church, to our people and to humanity at large.</p>
   <p>I beg to remain,</p>
   <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
   <p>Dr. S. M. Melamed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
