<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-01">Feb. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Three Problems of the Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Leon Zolotkoff</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0409</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0409.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-01">Feb. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THREE PROBLEMS OF THE DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Leon Zolotkoff</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The world tragedy which began in August, 1914, the last act of which we have not yet seen, has created for the Jewish people a mass of problems which they themselves must solve in order to live. Three of these stand out as the most important problems:</p>
   <p>The first is the emancipation of Jews in all the countries where they now live. The work has already been properly taken care of by the leading statesmen of Europe. The Peace Conference included "equal rights for the Jews" in its treaties with the newly created countries, as well as with those countries that were enlarged through the efforts of representatives of the great powers. But so far the recognition given the Jews is only a formal recognition. It is only a paper recognition. Poland, for instance, resorts to various methods in order to prevent the Jews of Poland from <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0410.jpg" n="2"/>gaining equal rights, despite the fact that she has signed such a treaty with the rest of the nations.</p>
   <p>We are not speaking here of the hellish anti-Semitism which rages in Poland. We are not demanding any love from the Poles, only ordinary human rights. Yet, as we see it, the Poles are doing their utmost to make Jewish life in Poland as miserable as possible. Take, for instance, the resolution of the Polish Parliament forbidding Jews to engage in business on Sunday. Within this prohibition are embodied the insincerity and hypocrisy of the Poles. The treaty signed by the Poles specifically states that Jews are not to be compelled to desecrate their Sabbath. Now the Polish anti-Semitic leaders, with simulated innocence, say: We are not compelling Jews to do any work on their Sabbath; we merely stand guard that they shall not work on Sunday. The Poles know very well that two days a week without work means economic ruin for the Jews who observe the Sabbath; and the latter are the greatest majority in Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0411.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The League of Nations is now closed. Probably the United States will soon join the League of Nations. In order to solve the difficult problem in Poland, it is necessary to continue to remind the world that those nations which the League of Nations has created, do not respect the treaties which they signed, that is, with reference to the Jews. We must not neglect this reminder, as we did in the case of the Berlin Tractate with Rumania.</p>
   <p>The second difficult problem is to recreate the normal conditions of Jewish life in those regions where the pogroms have ruined it. We are speaking here of the hundreds of thousands of Jews who were ruined and who find themselves in great distress. We must provide food for the hungry, clothes for the naked and a roof for the homeless. And yet this sort of assistance is inadequate. The unfortunate must be helped to pick up again the torn threads of their economic life, as far as it is possible. They must be provided with the necessary tools and materials with which to start anew.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0412.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The third--perhaps the all-important problem from the standpoint of preserving the Jewish people as a whole--is the reclamation, the rebirth of Palestine, and the settling of Jews there.</p>
   <p>Neither the emancipation of Jews in the Eastern European countries, nor the stupendous sums which will be expended for their rehabilitation, can do as much for the general improvement of the Jewish situation in the world, as the immigration and settlement of great numbers of Jews in Palestine.</p>
   <p>For proof, it isn't necessary to examine too deeply the social, political, moral or national reasons for this unique situation. The fact is that Jews will have to emigrate again from the Eastern European countries, as they have for the last forty or fifty years, and they will have to go toward Palestine because North America and the other countries to which they were previously attracted, are closed to them now.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0413.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It stands to reason that Palestine is not prepared as yet to receive great numbers of Jews in the way that America received them. But with the proper arrangements, with a strong organization, and particularly, with the use of sensible methods, it should be possible to settle in Palestine, each year, between seventy and one hundred thousand persons for the first few years, and each year thereafter, the capacity of Palestine would grow so that more Jews could go there.</p>
   <p>No one doubts any longer the possibility of developing Palestine, nor its capacity to receive ten million Jews in the future. When Palestine becomes a commercial and economic center, as we hope it will, then the most difficult problem--the problem of Jewish survival--will be solved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
