<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1886-04-16">April 16, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">Polish and Russian Jews in Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0232</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0232.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1886-04-16">April 16, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH AND RUSSIAN JEWS IN CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The number of Israelites hailing from Russia, has since a few years, largely increased in our city. Not by dozens and not by hundreds do they now come. It is said that there are now several thousands of them living in Chicago. Though their majority may be poor, yet there are a considerable number among who by their thrifty habits, their industry and economy, have become quite wealthy and who occupy a very honorable and respected position in society and in the city.</p>
   <p>Of the majority, it may be said that they are illiterate; illiterate in the sense in which this word is commonly understood. In Hebrew lore, there are very many of them who have the Talmud, the Midrash, the Paskim, and other parts of the Hebrew literature, throughly studied and mastered in their own peculiar ways and methods, and have them, so to say, at their fingers end.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0233.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Of the masses, it must be said, that the education they received in their native country was at least a very onesided one. Excluded from general society, suffering under anti-Jewish prejudices, living under oppressive tyrannical laws, made for them exclusively, they had to struggle on in a mental ghetto as well as in a real ghetto.</p>
   <p>They grew up among themselves; they lived among themselves mostly in bitter poverty; they had to maintain their own Jewish schools, in which only Hebrew was taught.....der Talmud und der Talmud, sie wussten anders nicht so reads a line in one of Chamisso's ballads....and thus they came over to this country, into the sharp atmosphere of life in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0234.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is now to be wondered at that it takes some years until these poor people who deserve the sincere sympathy of every humane Israelite, are more or less Americanized? We mean "Americanized" in the better sense of word.</p>
   <p>We have just said that the masses, aside from their Hebrew learning, are to be termed as illiterate. Yet there are several among the Polish Jews of Chicago, who visited higher schools and universities in Europe and who posess general culture and scientific training in a high degree. There are physicians among them of deserved reputation, (Dr. Kadison, Dr. Findelstein, and others); there are among them jurists, engineers, mathematicians, and so forth. And so it can be demonstrated by facts that not every Jew coming from Eastern Europe is an "ignorant Polak."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0235.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Of Polish-Hebrew congregations, there are quite a number here. The four principle ones are:-</p>
   <p>1. The Beth Hammidrash Haggadol, whose Rabbi is the learned and pious Rev. Dr. Jacob Gerson Lesser.</p>
   <p>2. The Beth Hammidrash Hechadash; the erudite Rev. Dr. Eliezer Anixter is the Rabbis of this flourishing congregation.</p>
   <p>3. The Ohabey Sholom (Mariampoler) congregation; their spiritual adviser and leader is the ever active Rev. Dr. Olperstein.</p>
   <p>4. The Anshe Russia; we do not know who are at the head of this congregation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0236.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>A number of smaller congregations exist who also have their own Rabbanim (Rabbis and Cantors) and Hazzanim. There is more than one Hazzan here who truly excells in chanting the prayers, in singing and musical training. Rev. Dr. Kleinovitz, Rev. Dr. Cantor, and so forth, are greatly admired precentors among our Polish co-religionists.</p>
   <p>Some months ago a Hebrew Literary Association was established under the name Hebrath Dorashe Safruth Ha-ibrith, which promises to do effective beneficial work for and among their countrymen and co-religionists.</p>
   <p>This association has already commenced to collect a library (not merely of Jewish books, general literature has also found a place in it), it has also established regular evening classes for instruction in various branches, and it will no doubt, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0237.jpg" n="6"/>promote a spirit of self-emancipation in some regards, and such self-emancipation, as all other kinds of self-help, is far more productive of good and lasting results than work coming from without, even if the same is as well meant as possible.</p>
   <p>We must not forget to mention that our Polish Jews deserve appreciation and credit for what they do for the schooling of poor children.</p>
   <p>There are Hebrew free schools in this city, if we are not mistaken, two... almost exclusively supported by the Polanders themselves, and these schools are visited by a large number of children. Of one of these schools, of the Montefaire Schools, we have recently heard that it is financially, in great distress, and that it needs aid and support if it shall continue in its noble work. Come forward, bretheren, ye who are blessed with wealth, come forward and support this school by your assistance. It deserves it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
