<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-16">Apr. 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Weizmann Greeted by Thunderous Ovation at Gigantic Massmeeting in Auditorium</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0303</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0303.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-16">Apr. 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">WEIZMANN GREETED BY THUNDEROUS OVATION AT GIGANTIC MASSMEETING IN AUDITORIUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Over five thousand Jewish men and women from various sections of the city assembled in the Auditorium yesterday to honor and hear Dr. Chaim Weizmann, president of the World Zionist Organization. The distinguished guest was accorded a grand reception when he appeared on the stage. He was tremendously applauded, and cheers for him and Palestine resounded throughout the hall. His speech was listened to with much enthusiasm and as a result the Keren Hayesod became richer by seventeen thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the evening was Max Shulman. He spoke of Dr. Weizmann's great mission in America, of the Zionist work the latter has undertaken, and expressed the hope that Weizmann's sojourn in America would yield favorable results for the upbuilding of Palestine. Mr. Shulman called upon Mr. Leonard Grossman [to speak] who greeted Dr. Weizmann in behalf of the local Zionist organization. The next speaker was Rabbi Judah L. Gordon, of Congregation <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0304.jpg" n="2"/>Tifereth Zion. As a symbol of respect, everybody arose when Rabbi Gordon took the speaker's stand.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Gordon began thus:</p>
   <p>"In the name of the Orthodox Jews in general and of the rabbis in particular, I welcome the great and beloved guest." The rabbi continued, "One learns the character of a person by his name. Dr. Weizmann's name is Chaim [Hebrew word for life] and it is an act from heaven that he has undertaken to lead us Jews into the Land of Life. Jews have vowed that they will not forget Zion and they cannot and will not forget it. An opportunity is now given to a large portion of our people to return there. These are the refugees and other Jews who have nowhere to go but Palestine. Let us therefore help them. Let us strengthen their hands by contributing to the fund, which will enable them to work and live there.</p>
   <p>"Dr. Weizmann urges us to do our duty. Let us heed him. We are doing it for <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0305.jpg" n="3"/>ourselves, for Palestine--our ancient home. May money shower upon the Keren Hayesod."</p>
   <p>Mr. Shulman then read a telegram from Senator McCormick, who excused himself for being unable to attend the meeting and extended good wishes to the Jewish people and to their ideals. Mr. Shulman then read the following letter from Mayor Dever to the publisher of the Jewish Courier:</p>
   <p>"My Dear Mr. Ginsburg:</p>
   <p>I regret very much that it will be impossible for me to attend the meeting Sunday evening in the Auditorium. A death in my family makes my presence there impossible.</p>
   <p>"It was my sincere wish to be with you at this affair, but the unexpected death of my niece in New York shattered all my plans so that it will be impossible for me to add my voice to the well-earned welcomes which, I know, will be given <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0306.jpg" n="4"/>to the noted guest, Dr. Chaim Weizmann.</p>
   <p>"I have deep sympathy for the idealism and the indomitable spirit which finds expression in the glorious work that Dr. Weizmann is doing. I admire his ingenuity and erudition and at this moment when I am so concerned about the future and the welfare of the Chicago people, it also gives me pleasure to greet one who has so honestly and sincerely proven his devotion to a lofty principle. My hope is that he and his friends shall eventually attain their objective and establish, on a sound basis in Palestine, a permanent national home for the Jewish people, and that Dr. Weizmann's mission in Chicago shall be crowned with great success.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>William E. Dever."</p>
   <p>The chairman then made an appeal for contributions to the Keren Hayesod. The 
    <pb n="5"/> aforementioned sum in cash was raised.</p>
    <p>Dr. Weizmann received a thunderous ovation when he was introduced. Among other things, Dr. Weizmann said: "The moment has come when all Jewish forces should be concentrated in the upbuilding of the Jewish National Home in Palestine. We have begun our work in a great and tragic hour. At a time when our possibilities of upbuilding Palestine are so great and so encouraging, two thirds of the Jewish people in Eastern Europe are living under unbearable conditions. On the eve of its resuscitation, the Jewish people is bleeding and lay wounded. It [the Jewish people] has only one hand with which to carry on the constructive work. With the other hand, it is desperately struggling against aggression, which threaten it with annihilation. The Jews of America are the remnants of oppression appointed by the Highest Authority to liberate the greatest portion of our people.</p>
    <p>"Huge sums of money are required for the success of rebuilding Palestine. The Keren Hayesod was organized for this purpose. The objective of the Keren Hayesod <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0307.jpg" n="6"/>is to make possible a regulated settlement of Palestine, and to provide for its economic development. We have already accomplished a great deal.</p>
   <p>"Land must be bought and prepared for the settlement thereon. Highways and railroads, sea ports and bridges are being built. Mountainous regions are being transformed, and swamps drained. Fruitful land must be irrigated and waterpower harnessed. Houses must be built and cities designed. Trades and industries must be developed. The social well-being of the population,public health, education, and the erection of universities must be properly provided for.</p>
   <p>"The Key to the gates of Palestine lies in Jewish hands. We can open these gates widely and establish a home for a large portion of our people. We must have money. We must build and prove that we mean well by wanting to become a Nation on a par with other nations.</p>
   <p>"The Zionist movement started as a sentimental project to assure the Jewish people with a National home, whence Jewish culture should spread throughout the whole world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0308.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"Since then, however, conditions have changed considerably and we must now provide a home for the millions of refugees and unemployed who flee from the persecution and pogroms of Central Europe. Most of the immigrants who now come to Palestine are from Russia, Poland, and other Central European countries. To many people it would be news to hear that more than a thousand immigrants enter Palestine each month and that 84 per cent of them are capable of doing the most difficult work required to build up the country.</p>
   <p>"In the course of the last two years, 30,000 Jews entered Palestine, or on the average of 1,000 a month.</p>
   <p>"The work in Palestine is now being carried on with great success, and it would be deplorable if the Chicago Jews should not contribute their portion to this great and noble work.</p>
   <p>"We are in need of money--money to build Palestine, to build a land that should not be put to shame by other civilized countries--a Jewish land, with a Jewish <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0309.jpg" n="8"/>language and with everything that is Jewish and Hebrew."</p>
   <p>His last words were sympathetically applauded and the beautiful meeting came to a close with the playing of Hatikvoh (Anthem).</p>
   <p>Among those present were Julius Rosenwald, Charles Shafner, Rabbi Joseph Stolz, Congreesman [Adolph] Sabath, and other prominent Jews of Chicago.</p>
   <p>A banquet will be given in honor of Dr. Weizmann this evening at the La Salle Hotel. About six hundred reservations have already been made.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
