<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-29">May 29, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">For the Theological Seminaries in Lithuania and Poland</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-29">May 29, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE THEOLOGICAL SEMINARIES IN LITHUANIA AND POLAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today we publish two documents which cast a bright light on the condition in which the large theological seminaries in Eastern Europe are found. One document is a brief but meaningful telegram from the head of the Slobodka Theological Seminary in Lithuania and the other document is a proclamation issued by the head of the Lomza Theological College in Poland. The other large seminaries are also in great straits, but they are less heard of, because they have no influential representatives to speak in their behalf.</p>
   <p>It is obvious that the Eastern European Jews themselves cannot maintain the large seminaries, and that the American Jews must partake of the work of raising the requisite means for their maintenance. Actually, the American Jews give large sums of money annually to the Eastern European Jews, but they <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0262.jpg" n="2"/>give neither methodically nor economically. If they would give methodically and economically, the seminaries would not be today in so critical condition as to be on the verge of folding up.</p>
   <p>The American Jews give at least one hundred thousand dollars a year to Eastern European seminaries. If ninety thousand dollars out of these one hundred thousand would reach the seminaries, the latter would be able to continue their work uninterruptedly. But not more than thirty or forty thousand dollars reach the seminaries, and probably not even that much, and the result is that they are constantly in a critical condition. In order to help the seminaries in Eastern Europe, the American Jews need not give more than they are now giving, but they should organize and centralize the work for the seminaries.</p>
   <p>The work for the seminaries must be centralized and the whole problem must be solved in connection with the Ezrath Torah (an organization in America which helps European seminaries). There must not and cannot exist a number of funds for Torah--only one fund, but this fund must be large and methodically <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0263.jpg" n="3"/>managed.</p>
   <p>Let the leaders of the Ezrath Torah fix a budget for Talmud Torahs (Hebrew schools) and seminaries, as well as for individuals who are entitled to support, and let the Ezrath Torah organize its work on the basis of this budget. We are convinced that if the work is carried on systematically no money will be lost, and in case an additional fifty thousand dollars a year is needed, it will also be raised. Our previous experience is that when a legitimate and truly organized Jewish body in America appeals to the American Jews for a certain amount of money, it gets it. A drive or a membership campaign is organized and the money is raised. We believe that the Ezrath Torah will obtain the requisite sums for its budget, if it will conduct its work in a systematic manner. The Ezrath Torah must establish a real office; it must hold a national conference which shall be represented by Orthodox rabbis and laymen, and it must elevate itself to the loftiness of its task. In every large city in America, a branch of the Ezrath Torah shall and can exist, and the Orthodox rabbis throughout America must deem it their task to <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0264.jpg" n="4"/>work for the Ezrath Torah and see to it that the committee shall function effectively. As long as this is not done, we do not perceive how the Eastern European seminaries can continue their work, because they cannot exist on the merits of the work of the Mishulochim (collectors for the seminaries). It is also impossible for every city in America to have an independent committee for seminaries, because not every city will work for the cause, and great injustices would arise over the distribution of the money.</p>
   <p>As long as there aren't any national organizations in America to come to the aid of the Eastern European seminaries, every city must, naturally, do as much as it can to help the seminaries in their present plight, and, also, we in Chicago must do something about this matter, which must not be neglected, because the closing of a large seminary, due to lack of funds, might mean a national catastrophe for the whole Eastern European Jewry.</p>
   <p>Whatever concerns the present crisis in which seminaries of Slobodka and <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0265.jpg" n="5"/>Lomza are found, we must say that if something is done, the initiative must come from the United Rabbinate. Let the United Rabbinate call a meeting of its members, as well as of fifty prominent laymen, and thus means and ways of raising a few thousand dollars will be found. The main thing is to establish a permanent organization in America to help the seminaries and we also believe that the initiative thereof should spring from Chicago.</p>
   <p>To us this seems to be the only way that we can and must help the Eastern European seminaries, because isolated actions in this or that city, or the work of Mishulochim, will accomplish very little.</p>
   <p>This is the only comment that we can make on the proclamation issued by the head of the Lomza Seminary, and this is the only answer we can give Rabbi Ephraim Epstein on the sad telegram he received from the Slobodka Seminary. If the rabbis will take the initiative, they will have the support of the entire Jewish press in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0266.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Rabbis, begin the work!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
