<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-11-15">November 15, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Rumanian Jews Pay Great Respect to the Queen of Rumania. but Remain Silent on the Persecution of Jews in Rumania</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-11-15">November 15, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">RUMANIAN JEWS PAY GREAT RESPECT TO THE QUEEN OF RUMANIA. BUT REMAIN SILENT ON THE PERSECUTION OF JEWS IN RUMANIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Rumanian Jews of Chicago showed great respect for Queen Marie of Rumania, yesterday by tendering her a reception in the Rumanian Shaarey Shomanim Synagogue, Douglas Boulevard and Millard Avenue. The synagogue was packed with curiosity-seekers who wanted to witness the appearance of a queen. People were more attired in full dress in her honor. She was seated, together with her children, Prince Nicholas and Princess Eliena, at the altar near the Holy Ark. A Cantor sang "Blessed be He Who Comes," as a welcome to her.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0257.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not one word was mentioned to Her Majesty, Queen of Rumania, that Jews are being persecuted in her country, and that their entire existence is a struggle against the ugliest of false accusations, brought against them; and against the cruelties they survive under the Anti-Semitic Rumanian Government.</p>
   <p>The reception in the Rumanian synagogue, with the exception of exposing submissiveness to the queen, did not distinguish itself in any way. It was sprinkled through out with ceremony that climaxed in comedy. The audience conducted itself in a disorderly manner. One person yelled out "Quiet," and the whole crowd followed by repeating the same. A number quite regularly lit cigarettes and the chairman of the affair, Mr. Bronstein, frequently called attention by "stop your smoking business."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0258.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The important scene commenced when the Queen was led to the Altar, accompanied by a wedding march played by the orchestra. Several in the audience, hummed, "Here Comes The Bride," and it seemed as though a wedding actually was taking place.</p>
   <p>The greetings opened when Cantor Kutai, dressed in a prayer-shawl, got through singing "Welcome," (in Hebrew), and the choir, under the direction of David Hirsch, responded with "Amen."</p>
   <p>Mr. Bronstein turned to Her Majesty and spoke in Rumanian enumerating all the elegant things of the Rumanian royal palace and the wonderful deeds that are being done for the oppressed masses.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0259.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>After that, the chairman introduced Mayor Dever, (William E.), who praised the Rumanian nation and said that it was a great race, a brave race, a race descending from the ancient Romans. He also praised the Rumanian Jews of Chicago saying that they are good citizens.</p>
   <p>The second speaker was Judge Harry Fisher, who apparently was substituted for Judge B. David. He thanked the Queen for taking such great interest in the welfare of her former Jewish subjects, who are now in America, receiving all the liberty.</p>
   <p>The third speaker was Henry Friend, who was invited to the royal palace in Romania and received medals there for his good relief work. He had given Her Majesty a testimonial from the Rumanian Jews of Illinois and wished her a pleasant trip back to Rumania.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0260.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Queen was then introduced. She expressed her gratitude, in English, for the great honor that had been rendered her. She said that she would relate this to the King, who consider "you"(Jews), as a great part of his nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
