<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-04-26">Apr. 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Immigration after the War</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-04-26">Apr. 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH IMMIGRATION AFTER THE WAR</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The important question of the day after the war, will positively be "Emigration to America."</p>
   <p>The number of immigrants, can be expected to be enormously large, especially Jewish immigration. It is therefore the proper time now to consider this problem, before the rush from devastated Europe gets into full swing and catches us unprepared.</p>
   <p>Many of the Jewish welfare workers and philanthropists are already voicing their ideas in that respect. It would be no more than right for all the Jews in this country to take an interest in this work. Generally, the <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0059.jpg" n="2"/>regulating of Jewish immigration is necessary so that we don't crowd one another. There will be sad results if we do not organize and direct the systematic distribution of the unfortunate Jews coming here to find new peaceful homes. The minute we leave immigration to its own fate, the immigrants will concentrate in one large city like New York, Philadelphia, Chicago, etc. They will compete with the old settled Jews, and neither group will benefit by that.</p>
   <p>Jacob Schiff, the old Jewish philanthropist who is interested in the fate of his people more than other Jewish millionaires, has expressed the same opinion in an interview, and suggests a remedy. He wants all Jewish community organizations and societies to organize and help carry out his plan.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0060.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>His suggestion is as follows: Since the Eastern states of our country are overfilled with Jews, we should arrange that new-comers land in the state of Texas, where there is room for 15,000 Jews. We must arrange with the steamship companies to take the immigrants direct to Galveston - whence the Jews will be dispersed throughout the state of Texas. From Galveston the steamships will continue with some of the immigrants through the Panama Canal to Los Angeles, San Francisco, Seattle, and Portland, where they can be dispersed throughout the states in the West. For this purpose, committees shall be organized by the Jews of these states, to care for these immigrants and to see that they are dispersed in the various cities and states accordingly. Subcommittees in the localities will arrange for the transfer of some of the immigrants to farms. The subcommittees shall see that this is carried out in such manner as to make it possible for the Jew to remain the possessor of the farm.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0061.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Schiff further states in his interview, that the Jews of the West have, to this day, done nothing for immigration but have left it all to the Jews in the East, who shouldered all the responsibility for the immigrants. This was unjust and it will now be possible for the Jews in the West to make right their wrong against the unfortunate brothers of Europe.</p>
   <p>In this noble work the Jews in the West may expect our heartfelt support. It is not too early to start this work immediately.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
