<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-03-07">Mar. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Banquet for Dr. Melamed at the Grenshaw Street Talmud Torah</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1025</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1025.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-03-07">Mar. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE BANQUET FOR DR. MELAMED AT THE GRENSHAW STREET TALMUD TORAH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large crowd of prominent citizens, rabbis, Zionist leaders, and community workers gathered Saturday night at the banquet given in honor of Dr. and Mrs. [S. M.] Melamed at the Grenshaw Street Talmud Torah.</p>
   <p>Mr. H. M. Barnett, chairman of the evening, explained in a short speech the purpose of the banquet. He then introduced the toastmaster, Mr. B. Horwich, who delivered an excellent and humorous speech about the guest of honor for the evening. At the end of his speech, Mr. Horwich said that a group of friends had collected a thousand dollars to present to Dr. Melamed as a wedding gift.</p>
   <p>Mr. H. Steinberg, as a representative of the local Zionists, then presented Dr. Melamed with an oil painting of himself, painted by a young Jewish artist who has just arrived from Palestine.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1026.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Other speakers of the evening were: the members of the Zionist delegation for the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization], Peter Schweitzer, Morris Ratenber, Dr. Goldstein, Judge Harry M. Fisher, Max Shulman, Rabbi Kaplan, Paul Rothenberg, and Mr. Slonim.</p>
   <p>Dr. Melamed was the last speaker of the evening. In an appropriate speech, he thanked everybody for the honor accorded him, for the pleasure the evening had given him, and for the presents that he had received.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
