<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1906-05-04">May 4, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Jews from San Francisco</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1906-05-04">May 4, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Jews from San Francisco</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago is now becoming a haven for a number of Jewish families who barely escaped with their lives in the disastrous San Francisco earthquake. These unfortunate people are now being cared for by the Chicago Jewish Shelter Home.</p>
   <p>San Francisco will eventually rise from the ashes in which it is embedded but until then, its inhabitants are sorely in need of help. Wholesale emigration is taking place. Every day brings new families to Chicago. These people have no destination, but travel as far as their money will take them. Trains are now carrying refugees free of charge to all points east. The west coast cannot absorb them anymore.</p>
   <p>Many refugees have relatives in Chicago to whom they can appeal for immediate aid. Many others have nowhere to turn. These wend their way to the Jewish Shelter Home. Many are without a cent in their pockets in a strange city. These people differ from new immigrants entering the United States from Europe in that they had hoped that their era of migration had ceased. They had already settled down to a happy settled life. Suddenly this catastrophe overtook them.</p>
   <p>The Shelter Home is doing all within its power to aid these people. This unexpected <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0183.jpg" n="2"/>drain on its treasury makes it imperative that they secure fresh funds from our local community to carry on their fine work. Jews here are asked to contribute whatever they can at this time to the Shelter Home. Help give a home to the homeless.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
