<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Dunne, Edward F., <title>Illinois - Heart of the Nation</title>, Lewis Publishing Company, Chicago &amp; New York,
<date when="1933">1933</date>, IV, 1.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0735</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0735.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Dunne, Edward F., <title>Illinois - The Heart of the Nation</title>, Lewis Publishing Company, Chicago &amp; New York,
<date when="1933">1933</date>, IV, 1.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Honorable Samuel Alschuler, United States circuit judge for the Seventh Judicial Circuit, was born in Chicago, November 20, 1859, of Jewish-German parent, Jacob &amp; Caroline (Stufil) Alschuler. Judge Alschuler's home city is Aurora, Illinois, where he lived since 1861, and attended the high school. In 1881 he was admitted to the Illinois bar, and practiced in and about Aurora for twenty years. In 1901 he joined the Chicago law firm of Kraus, Alschuler &amp; Holden, of which he remained a member until August 16, 1915, when President Wilson appointed him a federal circuit judge, in which capacity he has served ever since.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0736.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1917, when labor troubles threatened to tie up the basic war industry of the meat packing houses, Judge Alschuler was named as federal administrator for that industry, for fixing wages and working conditions and adjusting labor grievances therein during the period of the World War; and as the war did not officially terminate for a long period, the heavy burdens of this task devolved on him for nearly four years. In 1923, he was named by President Harding as a member of the President's Fact Finding Commission for the coal industry, wherein serious labor disturbances seemed imminent.</p>
   <p>He was a member of the State Commission of Claims from 1893 to 1897, and of the State Legislature from 1897 to 1901. In 1900 he was the nominee of the Democratic Party for governor, but failed of election.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0737.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He was a delegate at large from Illinois to the Democratic National Conventions at St. Louis, Denver, and Baltimore.</p>
   <p>March 5, 1923, he married Cela F. Kahn, of Chicago, in which city, by reason of his official duties there they maintain a home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
