<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-11-19">Nov. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Max Shulman Appeals to the Jews of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Max Shulman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0552</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0552.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-11-19">Nov. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MAX SHULMAN APPEALS TO THE JEWS OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Max Shulman</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jews throughout the country feel that the great hour for American Jewry has now arrived. Just as America must help in the rebuilding of Europe, so must the American Jews help in the rebuilding of Palestine--assist in building a Jewish home for the Jewish nation.</p>
   <p>The American Jews will be able to accomplish this great, honorable, and historical task only when they join the Zionist organization, whose only purpose is to establish a national home for our people in Palestine. The Zionist organization is now recognized by all the great powers as the legal and moral representative of the Jewish people, and if the Zionist organization is not sufficiently strong to carry out the great plan, we will lose the <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0553.jpg" n="2"/>greatest chance that we ever had.</p>
   <p>The American Zionist Organization is now doing the major work in Palestine; it carries the main burden and creates the conditions for a great immigration into our ancient country. The European Jews became poverty stricken during the War, and must depend upon the American Jews to undertake the great task.</p>
   <p>I, therefore, appeal to all the Jews of Chicago to fulfill their sacred duty, to register for Zion, and thereby becoming Zion builders in the real sense of the word.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
