<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-20">Apr. 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Idiotic Work</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0051</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0051.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-20">Apr. 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">IDIOTIC WORK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After being vetoed by two Presidents, Barnetts Anti-Immigration Bill, including the literacy test has again passed Congress for the fourth time. It will shortly be laid before President Wilson for approval. It is quite possible that the President may again veto it, and most likely the bill this time will receive the two-thirds vote in Congress required to overrule the President.</p>
   <p>This is not an honest and praiseworthy piece of legislation. It is an idiotic piece of work. It is unscrupulous because reading and writing--as every sensible person knows--is not an honest requirement for the serviceability and fitness of an immigrant. The inept and the dishonest immigrant often can read and write. It is evident that the intention is not to exclude only those who are unable to read and write, but to establish a method of excluding a large number of immigrants, and, if <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0052.jpg" n="2"/>possible, to do away with immigration altogether. This is not an open and aboveboard piece of legislation. If there is a hidden meaning in this bill, the American public should know about it.</p>
   <p>In the present period of war, we are beginning to feel the effects of stagnant immigration. We need only look into the daily newspapers, and examine the numerous columns replete with "help wanted" ads to convince ourselves that there exists a shortage of labor. These "help wanted" columns, occupying two, three or more pages, printed in the finest type, appear every day in all the newspapers of the country. The shortage of labor will be felt more each day until the climax of the war is reached. And here the Barnett Bill comes along, and seeks to make this condition permanent through a practical prohibition of immigration.</p>
   <p>This is the idiotic aspect of this bill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
