<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-10">Nov. 10, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Darkness Conquers</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0666</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0666.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-10">Nov. 10, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">DARKNESS CONQUERS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is said of the Italian Capital, that the Mayor of Rome, Ernest Nathan, has resigned. This resignation is a new indication of the political reaction prevailing at present throughout the European nations.</p>
   <p>Ernest Nathan is a Jew, but not because of that is he resigning from his position, nor has this hindered his political activities, as he was thoroughly Italianized, one of those who raised the flag of freedom and progress of that Italy that attained her unity and broke the rule of the Pope.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0667.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Perhaps, in him, although unknown even to himself, was hidden the old Jewish inheritance of Jerusalem that leads her historic battle against Rome dating back to ancient days. Perhaps this inheritance placed him in the ranks of the Italian fighters for liberty and progress, but he fought as an Italian for the welfare of the Italian nation without thought or idea of his own people. His resignation is due to the present circumstances in Italy.</p>
   <p>Italy is swept by a reactionary political tide and the Vatican of the Pope has raised its head. In the last surge, Ernest Nathan and his political comrades were defeated, giving victory to the Pope's candidates and the rest of the dark forces.</p>
   <p>The political reaction was brought about with the aid of the Triple Entente. In the problems of internal questions the reactionaries were unable to cope with the forces of progress, so the Triple Entente was created.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0668.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They played on the patriotic sentiments of the people, showing how they would reconquer old Lubia that was once part of the great Roman Empire.</p>
   <p>This patriotic swindle gained its goal. The people forgot all about poor living conditions and lack of necessities, quenching their thirst with imperialistic intoxicants.</p>
   <p>Everyone was netted in the tide of this bloody stream. The Pope gave his blessings for this holy conquest. Even the radical exponents were caught in the meshes without a warning that they were playing into the hands of the forces of darkness.</p>
   <p>The present tide of events has disclosed the results. The dark powers have reared their heads and are victorious.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0669.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Jewish Prime Minister, Lutzotto, has resigned. He did not favor the fight. Ernest Nathan resigned now because of its results. Now have the dark forces conquered. But this does not end the differences between Rome and Jerusalem.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
