<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-10-13">October 13, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Zion News for Chicago Jews</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-10-13">October 13, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">ZION NEWS FOR CHICAGO JEWS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Levin, is not a strange name in this country, for this is his third time in Chicago in the interest of Zionism. We owe many thanks to him for it is due to his energetic hard work, that the rich Jews of America have contributed a large sum of money for Jewish technical work in Haifa, Palestine.</p>
   <p>Dr. Levin was interviewed by the Jewish press, and this is what the Jewish Courier relates through its news columns: The question was asked Dr. Levin, "What is your honest opinion of the Zionist activities in Palestine?" His reply was as follows - "The Turkish government has not enacted any new laws, which will hinder or retard Jewish activity in rebuilding the Holy Land, by the Jews of the world. Palestine today, is the only country in the world where the Jew can study the art of self-sustainment. Every Jew there lives his own life, he is not looking for foreign matter. He is happy with his Jewish atmosphere, with his Jewish life. All this is due to the Hebrew schools, which furnish the Jewish atmosphere. Autonomy can not be bought. It must be developed and grow out in a natural manner of life. There is a great deal to accomplish in Palestine, and it is up to us Jews to be the cultural power of the country."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0143.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now, in reference to Zionism in and around Chicago - The last Grand Gate meeting was held October 6, and from the report submitted to us, we can see that good results were derived from the energetic activities. The Western Star, according to the latest report of the last convention, sent in $50 as a contribution to the National Fund. A committee was appointed by the Grand Gate to purchase National Fund stamps to be used in the correspondence of the secretary of the Western Star.</p>
   <p>Mr. Antonov reports that all the synagogues which were called upon by the National Fund committee, have purchased National Fund stamps. In other words, they responded very liberally, so we are very much in hope that this year, the sale of National Fund stamps will be much larger than in any previous year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
