<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-30">Mar. 30, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">When the Truth Hurts</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1196</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1196.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-30">Mar. 30, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WHEN THE TRUTH HURTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our old friend the Chicago Tribune, in commenting editorially about the explanation made by Mr. Harry A. Lipsky, member of the Board of Education, when he appeared as a witness before the States Investigating Committee, ended its comment with the statement that the Jews are not proud of Mr. Harry A. Lipsky.</p>
   <p>There is a vast number of Jews in Chicago, and it is hard to say which Jews the Tribune means. As far as we know, the Tribune represents a group of Jews who are above reproach because they happen not to be proud of a certain person.</p>
   <p>Recently the Tribune contacted Jews who stated through its columns that the Jews construct thin homes without fire-proof precautions for the purpose of setting fire to them so as to collect insurance; that Jewish physicians and pharmacists are fakes and blood-suckers; that Jews in the Jewish district carry guns and <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1197.jpg" n="2"/>shoot at most anything in order to impress their non-Jewish neighbors; and that the Jewish neighborhood is replete with gamblers and houses of ill repute. The Tribune took the word of a Jew whom an impartial jury declined to believe because they suspected that it was not probable that the prevaricator would tell the truth at that particular time. Since recently the Tribune has become the organ of Jewish trouble-makers and conspirators against the Jewish community of the West Side. If these Jews are not proud of Mr. Harry A. Lipsky, it is a great honor for the Jewish member of the Board of Education.</p>
   <p>It is hard for an impartial person to explain why the Tribune,--the self-styled "World's Greatest Newspaper,"--suddenly changed its colors and became reactionary in matters concerning the Jews and the Jewish West Side. It is incredible that such a newspaper, which wants to give the impression that it is progressive and impartial, should suddenly side with people who are excommunicated from all Jewish social activities, and who seek to attack the Jewish West Side in general <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1198.jpg" n="3"/>and particularly every activity of the Jews. It is rather difficult to suspect such a wealthy and independent newspaper of doing this from selfish motives. It is only natural that if these attacks upon the West Side Jews continue to enter the Tribune periodically and without any reason, the Jewish masses can find no explanation of this riddle, other than this newspaper perhaps is indulging in the everlasting hatred that some feel for the eternal people. So long as the Tribune does not offer a true explanation for its strange attitude toward the Jewish inhabitants of the West Side, this impression cannot but be uppermost in our minds.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harry A. Lipsky clarified this in his testimony before the State's Investigation Committee, and if the Tribune says that this is trivial, then Mr. Lipsky is certainly not guilty of this triviality. He spoke the truth and when the truth is spoken it hurts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
