<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-30">Aug. 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Jacob H. Marx, the Second Jewish Candidate *</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. A. Lebenson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-30">Aug. 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">JACOB H. MARX, THE SECOND JEWISH CANDIDATE *</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. A. Lebenson</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whereas Philip P. Bregstone, candidate for [judge of the] Municipal Court [Translator's note: on the Democratic ticket] was compelled to fight poverty and need until he attained the position in political and social life to which he is justly entitled, his colleague, the second Jewish candidate on the Democratic ticket for judge of the Municipal Court, Jacob H. Marx, was forced to combat a more powerful enemy. He had a more difficult course to tread. He had to overcome worse circumstances. He had to fight opulence and luxury.</p>
   <p>We know that most people would like to be born among riches, and they would say that if the Lord wished to punish them let Him plague them with a few thousand dollars. But all that glitters is not gold. The child who is born of <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1137.jpg" n="2"/>wealthy parents is really fortunate, but to be happy as a rich child one must possess a soul that is satisfied with the glitter of gold. Only then can one be happy, and only then can one enjoy everything in the world that gold can buy.</p>
   <p>However, there are people who cannot feel satisfied with the fact that they alone have three meals a day. They would also like to see that others have enough bread and herring. There are people whose hearts are bigger than their stomachs; whose souls transcend their pockets. These people do not rejoice in their luxury when they see so much poverty and destitution in their midst. Their anguished souls hover as in a void amid the glittering gold. They feel that they are alone in the wide, luxuriant world.</p>
   <p>There is a Moses who was reared in a royal palace, spent his childhood among slave drivers, and when he grew older and went out among his brethren and saw how hard they were driven, his pleasures faded. He attempted to help the enslaved and the despised, and because he was a lad, young and inexperienced, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1138.jpg" n="3"/>he forsook his home and friends, his fortune and pleasure, and chose to abide in a wilderness where there were no slaves and no slave drivers; there he studied the problem, the eternal problem; Why has one too much and the other nothing?</p>
   <p>When this Moses reached maturity, both mental and physical, he returned to the royal palace where he was raised and to which he was entitled, by law, to his portion. He did not come, however, to claim his portion and to live like a sybarite as all princes do. He came to demand an accounting for those at whose expense the slave drivers thrive. He came to demand justice for those who were denied the right to exist, he came to demand freedom for slaves, equality for the humiliated, brotherhood for stepbrothers.</p>
   <p>Naturally this Moses is called a renegade, because he abandoned his class. They [the slave drivers] do not understand that this Moses is their brother only in body but not in mind; they do not understand that in this Moses there is a soul descended directly from the celestial throne, imbued with justice and honesty, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1139.jpg" n="4"/>with love and tolerance for mankind. They can hardly conceive that this Moses is a spiritual brother to the slaves on whose blood the princes fatten, on whose marrow they grow corpulent and on whose strength they become powerful.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jacob H. Marx, the Jewish candidate for judge of the Municipal Court, has been endowed, fortunately or unfortunately, with the soul of a Moses. Jacob H. Marx is the son of Mr. Marx, one of the propietors of the large clothing concern, Hart, Schaffner and Marx, which employs more Jewish workers than any other firm in the world, and which, with other factories, installed the system of "not supplying straw, but demanding a larger production of bricks". [Translator's note: Taken from biblical text: "Ye shall no more give the people straw to make brick."]</p>
   <p>Like a prince, the young Jacob [Marx] was brought up in riches and luxury and was attracted to his father's factories. And there he felt as though he were among his brothers; there he saw for the first time how much sweat and tears, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1140.jpg" n="5"/>how much blood and marrow was pressed out of his brothers, that he might be provided with luxury and pleasure; there the eternal question first dawned upon him: Why is it that they who create everything have nothing, and they who create nothing have everything?</p>
   <p>But he was quite young [at that time], still a child. And when he posed this question, they who should have answered it looked upon him as if he were insane. So the young Marx went off into the "wilderness of science" in order to find an answer to this difficult question. He studied political economy, sociology and law. He became mature in body and mind, and returned home not to demand an answer to this question, but rather to dictate a correct answer.</p>
   <p>And he returned at the proper time. The enslaved tailors were beginning to revolt and the slave drivers had powerfully organized themselves to defend their position. The historic needle-trades strike was then going on in Chicago. The struggle grew worse each day. But what chance did the weak, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1141.jpg" n="6"/>hungry and wretched tailors have against the rich, satisfied manufacturers? But here Jacob H. Marx stepped in and, as one of the princes of the slave drivers, he raised the revolutionary banner and inscribed on that banner, justice to those deprived of their rights; liberty for slaves, brotherhood between employer and employee.</p>
   <p>He was ridiculed. The Pharoahs could not understand this. But in his Egypt, Jacob H. Marx was crown prince; there he was able to dictate and he did dictate. And for the first time, we saw the wolf and the sheep, Jacob H. Marx and Sidney Hillman, coming together, and the result is well known to everybody. In all other tailoring shops, strikes are periodic phenomena, but in the factories of Hart, Schaffner and Marx they are unknown.</p>
   <p>This is Jacob H. Marx whose name is little known among the Jews, but whose work and activity have been felt by the families who live by the needle trade.</p>
   <p>Now there is an opportunity for Mr. Jacob H. Marx to broaden his activity on <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1142.jpg" n="7"/>a much greater and broader scope. As judge of the Municipal Court, with his views on problems of capital and labor, he will be a godsend on the bench. With the help of the Jewish Democrats and with the assistance of the strong Sullivanite faction in the Democratic party, he will undoubtedly be nominated. His name is the sixth on the list of candidates for judge of the Municipal Court on the Democratic ticket. The Jewish public will surely vote for him two weeks hence, on September 13.</p>
   <p>* [Translator's note: By the "second Jewish candidate, the writer means that there are two Jewish candidates running for judge of the Municipal Court, and Jacob H. Marx is the second on the list.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
