<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-16">Nov. 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Isaac Greensfelder Dead at 86 Years</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1217</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1217.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-16">Nov. 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ISAAC GREENSFELDER DEAD AT 86 YEARS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Death has this Friday robbed us of one of the first Jewish pioneers in Chicago, the old, well-known merchant and public worker, Isaac Greensfelder, at the age of 86 years.</p>
   <p>Mr. Greensfelder was well-known in all Jewish circles through his indefatigable work for society. He was the first liberal donor for the first Jewish hospital in Chicago, the Michael Reese Hospital, of which he was president for 20 years. He was a life-time director of the United Hebrew Charities, a director of the orphanage on the South Side, and of the Home for Jewish Boys, and was connected with many other charitable societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1218.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the time Mr. Greensfelder became a leader upon coming to Chicago in 1853, of the Jewish Community, it was as yet a very small one. With his love for charity and his devotion to all that is Jewish he worked unremittingly to the day of his death. He died like a true Jewish social worker, at the helm of the boat.</p>
   <p>Every Friday, as was his habit, he visited the Michael Reese Hospital to comfort the sick, say a cheerful word, give them hope. It was in such a moment that the threads of life were severed for this Jewish pioneer of charitable work.</p>
   <p>Until about 15 years ago, he was noted as a great merchant. His life-long career was not entirely dedicated to commerce. He retired 15 years ago to devote his entire time to charities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1219.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He leaves a wife and six children: Tacklow, Rosa, Bella, Jacob, Adolf, and Dr. Louis A. Greensfelder.</p>
   <p>His funeral will take place 9 A. M. from Sinai Temple, where Dr. Hirsch will officiate. He will be laid at rest in Rosehill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
