<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-17">Aug. 17, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Responding Hearts</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0597</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0597.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-17">Aug. 17, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">RESPONDING HEARTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sea shells have a characteristic inner hum. There exists a whimsical idea that sea shells echo the murmurs of the sea from which they came. They may be thousands of miles away from the sea bed they originally occupied, yet, when a gale whips up the waters of their former home, the sea shells respond sympathetically with a buzzing sound. Whether there is any truth to the legend about sea shells we don't know. But if we were speaking of human beings, we would be strongly inclined to accept such a theory.</p>
   <p>Why do our spiritual leaders become so excited upon hearing troublesome voices from afar? Voices of past generations, from distant countries, resound in our hearts, expressing sympathy for the past and for those "from afar". We need not exert any painstaking efforts in search of evidence to confirm this fact. We can feel it; we can see it with our eyes. What is, for example, <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0598.jpg" n="2"/>the Zionist movement, if not the reverberation of distant voices?</p>
   <p>Last Wednesday evening several hundred Jews assembled in the Anshe Knesis Israel Congregation of Chicago to send, through special emissaries, an encouraging message to millions of their unfortunate brothers abroad. The large audience listened to the description of their brethren's trials and tribulations, but their attention was not concentrated upon these horrors. They have become so accustomed to listening to trouble that it no longer arouses them. However, undivided attention was given to those who described how courageously these millions of unfortunate Jews are fighting to preserve their spiritual values of the past--the heritage of their people. The audience was then quiet and serious, paying strict attention. Hearts were beating here in response to the millions of distant hearts. It was an interesting, a beautiful, and a poignant sight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
