<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-01-28">January 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Immigration Is a Gold Mine for America</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0122</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0122.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-01-28">January 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">IMMIGRATION IS A GOLD MINE FOR AMERICA</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The foes of immigration, inasmuch as they are sincere and patriotic in thinking that America can not provide adequate space for foreigners and that the foreigners are depriving the native Americans of employment - these foes will find it indispensable to refer to the fourth annual report of the Hebrew Sheltering and Aid Society.</p>
   <p>Facts speak better than profound conjectures, cold facts are neutral, and can not be interpreted otherwise than as a correct interpretation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0123.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The sixty-five thousand Jewish immigrants, who came to America last year for a future home of freedom, equality and economic opportunity, have contributed more than $5,000,000 to the government's income and profits of private corporations, and they were in possession of a purchasing power of close to $2,000,000 the first couple of weeks after their arrival.</p>
   <p>The seven million dollars were used by the 65,000 Jews to cover the portion of profits, which America receives from the migration expenses paid out by the immigrants when they left the old home for the free republic of the New World.</p>
   <p>It is apparent, therefore, that the immigrants not only bring muscles and energy with them, which is worth more than dollars and cents, but money also. If we should show that other immigrants bring in as much money, in proportion as do the Jews, we would have the colossal sum of $100,000,000, which annually flows into America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0124.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These are facts and there is evidence which tends to prove the money itself, apart from the labor-power, brought in annually by the immigrants is one of the most important factors which make the United States of America wealthy and powerful.</p>
   <p>All controversies against immigration are childish in comparison with the flow of gold, which again is dispersed throughout the entire land......</p>
   <p>The foes of immigration claim that the immigrants send out millions from this country. However, that which they send out is only a part of the profits which they create for this country, while the money, which they bring into this country is a gift, for which America does nothing to earn.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
