<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-29">May 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Congressman Sabath Cables the President to Stop Pogroms</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-29">May 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CONGRESSMAN SABATH CABLES THE PRESIDENT TO STOP POGROMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Wash. May 28. Today, acting Secretary of State,Frank Polk sent another cable to Hughes Gibson, Ambassador in Warsaw, asking that he send immediately by cable, a statement of the report of pogroms on Jews in Poland, such as he previously sent by post, in order that the American Government know what further steps to take in this regard.</p>
   <p>Congressman Adolph J. Sabath of Chicago sent the following cable to President Wilson:</p>
   <p>"Reports are being constantly received in the United States regarding horrible slaughters of Jews in Poland, Galicia, and Rumania. I beg <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0500.jpg" n="2"/>that you order an impartial investigation and demand that these deeds be ended."</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabath said he would attend to calling a meeting of the diplomatic officials and representatives of those lands where the slaughters took place, so that they may notify their governments of the opinion prevailing in the United States against such horrid barbarisms.</p>
   <p>The Polish Bureau here made public this statement by a Polish official, Walski of Warsaw: "The World will soon know of Poland's attitude toward Jews in the next six months, when a large stream of Jewish emigrants from Russia come to Poland and find there a"secure Haven." It is not certain what the Polish official meant by this statement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0501.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The House Committee on Foreign Affairs will hold a meeting next Monday to decide which of the various anti-pogrom resolutions should be recommended for adoption by the House. This evening notices to attend the meeting were sent to the members of the committee. It is believed that the committee will decide to favor the resolution of Congressman Sigel, from New York, which is similar to that of Senator Kolder. No doubt, the House will unanimously accept what the committee recommends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
