<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Dunne, Edward F., <title>Illinois - Heart of the Nation</title>, Lewis Publishing Company, Chicago &amp; New York,
<date when="1933">1933</date>, IV, 175.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Dunne, Edward F., <title>Illinois - Heart of the Nation</title>, Lewis Publishing Company, Chicago &amp; New York,
<date when="1933">1933</date>, IV, 175.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Barney Cohen, a recognized power in Illinois labor circles for many years, was the first man selected by Governor Lowden, when the state government was reorganized on a departmental basis, to fill the office of director of labor.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cohen has a colorful career. He was born in Prussia. He came to Chicago when a child, in 1870, had very limited opportunities to attend school, and his successful career of work and service has been the result of his natural intelligence, his gifts as a leader, and his tremendously energetic way of doing whatever he undertakes to do. When he was nine years of age he was put to work in a cigar factory. On reaching the age of fourteen he qualified as a journeyman cigar maker, and has held a card in the Cigar Makers International for forty-two years. When he was twenty-one years of age he was elected president of the Cigar Makers Union. From that time forward he has been one of the soundest counsellors and leaders in labor circles in Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0729.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Cohen served as president of the Illinois Federation of Labor for three consecutive years, 1904-06. In 1903 he was appointed deputy factory inspector by Governor Deneen and was reappointed to that office in 1912. Mr. Cohen from 1906 to 1910 conducted a cigar factory.</p>
   <p>In 1916 he was chosen the first director of the Department of Labor by Governor Lowden and served until the Small administration. He was then appointed by President Harding director of labor of the Third District, comprising five states, Illinois, Michigan, Indiana, Wisconsin and Ohio. From this position he resigned to accept the appointment from Governor Emmerson, as director of labor and again became head of that department in August 1929.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0730.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Department of Labor has for its general functions the improvement of labor conditions in Illinois. Mr. Cohen has a large personnel under his direction and these are engaged in the enforcement of inspection laws regulating factories, workshops, stores, and other industries where labor is employed, supervising and regulating state free employment agencies, and also the department collects and disseminates data and information relative to labor.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cohen married in 1892 Miss Sarah Strauss. She was born in London and was reared and educated in New York. They have three children.</p>
   <p>Mr. Barney Cohen is a Scottish Rite Mason and a Shriner, belonging to a lodge in Chicago and the Consistory and Shrine at Springfield. He is also affiliated with Lodge No. 4, B. B. O. Elks, in Chicago and is a member of several clubs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
