<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-12-29">December 29, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Departing for Europe in the Interests of the Jews</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0695</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0695.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-12-29">December 29, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">DEPARTING FOR EUROPE IN THE INTERESTS OF THE JEWS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Adolph Kraus, the prominent Jew, who is the president of the Order of B'nai B'rith, will leave Chicago, Tuesday, January 5, for New York, and thence to Europe in order to inspect all lodges of the Order of B'nai B'rith. Madame Kraus is accompanying Mr. Kraus. In order to demonstrate the appreciation of the wonderful work in the interests of world Jewry, the United B'nai B'rith Lodges of Chicago, have arranged in his honor a banquet tonight, 7 p. m., at the Standard Club. The banquet will be under the auspicies of the Central B'nai B'rith Council, which has sent out invitations to all members of the Order in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kraus has a new plan as to how the Order of B'nai B'rith should junction from now on. How to strengthen its influence and power for the benefit of all Jews, whose lot it is to live in countries where they are persecuted.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0696.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Besides the inspection which Mr. Kraus is aiming to make, he has a great mission concerning Jews the world over. Tonight he will present this problem to those present at the banquet.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zelenfreind, secretary of the Order informed a Courier reporter yesterday, that Mr. Kraus and wife will at first visit Berlin, where they have a son, who is studying medicine, then they will begin touring all through Germany, Austria, Roumania, Hungary, Russia, Turkey, Palestine, Egypt and everywhere, where the Order has lodges.</p>
   <p>While Mr. Kraus is making preparations for his departure to Europe, his friends in Chicago have begun to work energetically for the "Kraus 5,000 Club."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
