<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-08">Jan. 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Emil G. Hirsch</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0974</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0974.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-08">Jan. 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">DR. EMIL G. HIRSCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Emil G. Hirsch, rabbi of Chicago Sinai Congregation, died yesterday after a brief illness, at the age of seventy-one. Emil G. Hirsch was, without a doubt, the most popular, or more correctly, the best-known representative of the Reform movement in America. The Christian world of America accepted him as an authority on Jewish problems. He was a remarkable personality, at least he certainly was not a mediocre personality, that is, as a man, a Jew, and a rabbi. His father was a profound Jewish thinker and the creator of a system of Jewish religious philosophy. The great Stendhal was a fervent believer in the religio-philosophical theories of Emil G. Hirsch's father.</p>
   <p>As the son of a great thinker, the deceased grew up amid the Jewish intellectual traditions of Western Judaism. Emil G. Hirsch was an intellectual. He was a good linguist and had at his command a half-dozen European languages. He also had a wide knowledge of Yiddish. In addition to all this, he possessed a certain <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0975.jpg" n="2"/>degree of pungency and shrewdness and it is certainly regrettable that these characteristics were not used for constructive work.</p>
   <p>Along with his secular and Jewish knowledge, if Emil G. Hirsch had possessed strong Jewish sentiments, a love for the Jewish past, sympathy for the Jewish present, and the correct perspective toward the Jewish future, he would, undoubtedly, have accomplished great things for the Jewish people. He was very influential in many circles. Many educated Christian circles held a high opinion of him as a rabbi. He could have become the incontestable leader of the American youth--but he was not. His views on Jews and Judaism appealed only to those Jews who grew up without a Jewish education and who knew nothing about Judaism. To the Jews who had a Jewish education, Jewish sentiments, and Jewish hopes, he had nothing to say. And because he was an outspoken and aggressive personality, he aroused much opposition, and, not infrequently, strong protests from Jews, who are and will remain Jews.</p>
   <p>Emil G. Hirsch had an ideal--Reform, the Reform temple. But he was unable to realize this ideal. The Reform temple did not attract the Jewish youth, because <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0976.jpg" n="3"/>it did not appeal to them.</p>
   <p>Dr. Emil G. Hirsch accomplished many things for the local Jewish community. He helped build many benevolent institutions, he participated in relief work, and he participated in general Jewish philanthropic work.</p>
   <p>Should Hirsch's successor be a man with positive opinions on Jews and Judaism, then the mistakes made by Hirsch can still be rectified.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
