<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-06-09">June 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Chicago Delegation Accompanied by a Courier Correspondent Leaves for Mexico</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-06-09">June 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A CHICAGO DELEGATION ACCOMPANIED BY A COURIER CORRESPONDENT LEAVES FOR MEXICO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Attorney Paul Rothenberg, Judge Joseph W. Schulman, James Winer, and Assistant States Attorney H. B. Ritman will leave next Tuesday evening for Mexico as a delegation from Chicago to investigate the land which the Mexican government has offered to the Jews of Eastern Europe for colonization. Mr. J. Loebner accompanies the delegation as a correspondent from the Courier. Senator Gurma Vilabalas of Senora, Mexico, is expected to arrive in Chicago today from Washington. He will accompany the delegation to Mexico.</p>
   <p>The negotiations between the Mexican government and Mr. Rothenberg have been going on for over a year. An organization called "Jewish-Mexican Colonization Association" was founded here, upon the initiative of Mr. Rothenberg. This Association is sending the above-mentioned delegation to Mexico.</p>
   <p>The land, which President Obregon of Mexico has offered to Mr. Rothenberg for <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0338.jpg" n="2"/>Jewish colonization, is in Lower California, near the American-Mexican border. The land covers an area of sixty-four thousand square miles. They say that the territory is very favorable, the soil is good, the climate is healthy, and that there are many natural resources. The present population numbers twenty-five thousand people, while the territory is larger than Belgium.</p>
   <p>The territory, which Mexico is ready to give for Jewish colonization, is remote from the area usually affected by the revolutions that occur so often in Mexico.</p>
   <p>There are rumors that the American government has nothing against this plan; that, on the contrary, it is very much in favor of it, and that Secretary Hughes will soon issue an official statement about the favorable attitude of the American government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
