<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-08-21">Aug. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Pope Pius X</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-08-21">Aug. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">POPE PIUS X</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At one time the world thought that Jerusalem could only be reconstructed after the downfall of Rome, and that the Jews would never rise again as long as the Roman rule prevailed.</p>
   <p>However, conditions have slowly changed so that Spain - the land of the inquisition - invited a Jewish educator to lecture on Jewish literature, and urges the great-grandchildren of the Jews, it so brutally persecuted, to return and enjoy full citizen's rights. Portugal is willing to grant the Jews territory to establish an autonomous Jewish government.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0646.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Italy and France no longer discriminate against the Jew and Catholic, and even in Austria, where anti-Semites turned Catholicism into an anti-Jewish weapon, the Jews have a vast number of privileges, which they could not easily obtain in Greece, Russia, or Rumania.</p>
   <p>Here, in America, where religion is a private matter, Jews and Catholics often unite in order to defend the principle of religious freedom. Jews and Catholics also work hand in hand in the political parties and trade unions, and where enmity prevailed in the Middle Ages, sympathy and solidarity prevail today.</p>
   <p>Pope Pius X was personally a friend to the Jews. Being a child of common people, he was far from the anti-Semitism of the aristocratic classes. Not only did he number Jews among his personal friends, but he was sympathetic to all Jews. No other Pope has welcomed to the Vatican, as many Jews as Pope Pius X.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0647.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As late as last year, he greeted warmly the Jewish educator of Palestine, Mr. Ben Yahudah, and his wife who left him highly pleased.</p>
   <p>However, what renders his memory so dear to the Jewish people, and makes his name an honored one in the annals of Jewish history, is the fact that he was the first Pope who ever welcomed the Jews visiting the Vatican as official representatives of the Jewish people. He sought and won the sympathy of the 200,000,000 Catholics - whose eyes are centered on their spiritual King in Rome....</p>
   <p>Ten years ago during the month of March when Dr. Herzl, four months prior to his death, was greeted at the Vatican, he proposed to the late Pope the Zionistic ideology of redeeming Palestine. Pope Pius X at that time gave Dr. Herzl many promises which revealed him as a friend of the Jewish people. We honor his memory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
