<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>, <date when="1919-05-19">May 19, 1919</date>.<title level="a">One Heart, One Spirit</title>
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0525</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>, <date when="1919-05-19">May 19, 1919</date>.<title level="a">One Heart, One Spirit</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
  <p>The great Victor Hugo said, somewhere in his work, that the history of civilization  presented no more beautiful, no more inspiring concept than the realization of an ideal. We Jews are now passing through an epoch where we can verify by our own experience the great truth uttered by the great French writer. It is the good fortune of the present Jewish generation to witness the realization of an ideal--the re-establishment of Palestine.</p>
  <p>For thousands of years, Jews have dreamed of returning to Palestine. This has been the shining hope of every Jew in the Diaspora lands; now, in 1919, it is becoming historically possible, as a result of the Balfour Declaration.</p>
  <p>Because that ideal today seems to be on the threshold of fruition, we feel a sense of elation, of instinctive pleasure; we feel the presence of the great Jewish masses. The masses of a nation always feel instinctively the potential changes that are about to occur, even if they possess no knowledge
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0525.jpg" n="2"/> of them.</p>
   <p>It is significant that Jews, even in America, listen attentively to the message of the Balfour Declaration. How eagerly they absorb every bit of news pertaining to Palestine, and how pleased they are to respond to the demands of the Zionist organization!</p>
   <p>Year in and year out, appeals have been made to Jews in America for funds for various benevolent purposes. Aid was asked for victims of pogroms, the Kishinev pogrom of thirty (sic) years ago, and the [World] War victims of the last three years. Jews have given millions. Now money is being requested for the re-establishment of Palestine, and they are giving again.</p>
   <p>My, what a difference there is between just giving and giving. To secure the money for pogrom and [World] War victims, it was necessary to picture the dreadful misery of the victims, the murdered, the starving, the desperate mothers with their dying infants, and all the other horrible scenes of <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0526.jpg" n="3"/>Jewish despair. It was necessary to touch the heart through descriptions of the suffering [of innocent victims].</p>
   <p>Not so does Zion appeal to her children. She doesn't cry, she asks for no alms, she sheds no tears. With a smile of recovery, as one convalescing from a long illness, she calls out and says: "My children, your mother lives! Come to me, shield me from my long desolation, and you shall see what a mother you have! All my youthful energies are dormant. All the sweet motherly desires are still weak in me. I can hold you tenderly, I can feed and protect you; I can give you a home to which you may come whenever you please."</p>
   <p>There is no pity to be seen on any face--no anxiety for another's suffering, but a sweet delight, a quiet, instinctive happiness.</p>
   <p>It is a pleasure to bring these good tidings to the Jews and to watch the expressions on their faces, the glow of enthusiasm shining in their eyes <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0527.jpg" n="4"/>when the message is given. It is almost unnecessary to ask for the money. It may sometimes be difficult for them to realize the meaning of this message because many have long dismissed the possibility [of Palestine as a homeland]. The good news comes, therefore, so unexpectedly. But, as the message becomes clear and sinks into their hearts, their features assume a new glow. They give their money for Zion with an attitude that calls to mind the devoted father presenting his only son with a wedding gift. Jews are really happy when they can give their money for Palestine.</p>
   <p>This is an actual description of the attitude that prevails at the Jewish gatherings where this message is brought.</p>
   <p>It is a truly inspiring, and wonderful outlook, when an historical ideal is ripe, and begins to emerge as a reality.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
