<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1902-11-01">November 1, 1902</date>. p.235.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1394</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1394.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1902-11-01">November 1, 1902</date>. p.235.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Henry G. Foreman was born in Chicago in 1857. He is the eldest son of the late Gerhard Foreman, who settled in Chicago in its early days. Mr. Foreman received his education in the Chicago public schools, and began his business life in 1873, in the service of the First National Bank of Chicago.</p>
   <p>In 1874, when he was seventeen years of age, he entered the bank of his father, and three years later, he undertook the management of his father's large business.</p>
   <p>He retired from the banking business several years ago, to devote his entire attention to his real estate interests. He is one of the large real estate owners and operators in Chicago, and has handled successfully many important transactions both in downtown and suburban properties. He is one of the organizers of the Chicago Real Estate Board, of which he was elected vice-president in 1899, and he is still an active member.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1395.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Foreman never held any public office until appointed South Park Commissioner last March, and, his honest record as a Commissioner has proved that the public welfare is his whole thought and ambition.</p>
   <p>If elected, he will bring to the office of the President of the County Board, ability, intelligence and integrity, the three necessary qualifications. He is sponsored by the Republican Party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
