<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1893-12-08">December 8, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Charles Kozminski Gone to Rest</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_1586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1893-12-08">December 8, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">CHARLES KOZMINSKI GONE TO REST</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The sudden demise of Charles Kozminski has left a void in our community which may not be easily filled. The sad event occurred on Saturday, December 2, at 2 P. M., while Mr. Kozminski, as chairman of the fourth ward German Republican Club, had just finished an address to the Republican Convention and had been appointed one of the committee to apprise Mr. Geo. B. Swift of his unanimous nomination for Mayor of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kozminski was the founder of the firm of Kozminski and Co., bankers. He was born near Breslau, Silesia, in 1837. He was educated in his native district and at the age of sixteen entered the employ of a grain company as cashier. After following this vocation for two years, he came to America and settled in Corning, N. Y., engaging in the clothing business. He remained there until 1856 and in the Fall of that year started for the West and located in Chicago. His first venture in this city was a grocery store at Wells and Monroe streets. In 1864 he transferred his capital to the dry goods trade, but abandoned mercantile pursuits five years later to <pb facs="5423972_10_1_1587.jpg" n="2"/>organize the banking firm of Felsenthal and Kozminski. This firm continued in existence until January 1884, when it was dissolved. Mr. Kozminski then organized the present business, under the name of Charles Kozminski and Co.</p>
   <p>He occupied &amp; high social position and well and conscientiously filled numerous offices of honor and trust. Mr. Kozminski was elected president of District No. 6, I. O. B. B. and for many years was a trustee of Chicago Lodge, No. 437, A. F. and A. M. He was the Chicago trustee of the Cleveland Orphan Society and was, besides, president of the Relief Assembly. During the great fire, Mr. Kozminski worked in connection with Mr. Trusdale, superintendent of the Chicago Relief and Aid Society. His appointment by Mayor DeWitt C. Cregier as a Director of our Public School was one of his most solicitous ones.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
