<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1914-12">December, 1914</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0063</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0063.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1914-12">December, 1914</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lecture by Abraham Goldberg.</p>
   <p>On Sunday afternoon, May 9, an enthusiastic audience of Zionists and sympathizers gathered in the Assembly Hall to hear Mr. Abe Goldberg, Yiddish writer and lecturer. The meeting was arranged by the Order B'nai Zion, whose expectation in inviting Mr. Goldberg were more tham fulfilled. He is as able with his tongue as he is with his pen.</p>
   <p>It is seldom that one hears so stirring and impassioned a speech, one that thrills the inner chords of the heart. Sincere and deep-seated feeling for the cause he has at heart is the secret of Mr. Goldberg's success. His were words that really flowed forth from the fullness of his heart, which pains and bleeds for the abnormal pathetic life of the Jew today. The present war in Europe, Mr. Goldberg holds, has fully brought to light the <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0064.jpg" n="2"/>pathos of the Jewish abnormality, a nation without a land. The small European nations are actually the lovers of present politics, they pull the strings of the war, and their favor is curried by the powers. Alone the Jewish nation, which in numbers overlap the small nation limit, is completely neglected and ignored by all. With his true Jewish humor, that typical humor which jests with a tearful voice and breaking heart, Mr. Goldberg would that we were at least made some bluff promises - promises even if sure to be broken would at least hoax us into believing that we and our support were of some consequence. Our best sons are heroically shedding their blood on the battlefields. But their sacrifice is mostly without an object and meaningless: which enhances the tragedy. The last words of the address were an ardent appeal for immediate radical action towards a return to Palestine. If sacrifice we must, why not offer the sacrifice on our own altar, the altar of the new Jewish nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
