<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-08-05">Aug. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Bachmietoff Inspired by the Greetings of Chicago Jews</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-08-05">Aug. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BACHMIETOFF INSPIRED BY THE GREETINGS OF CHICAGO JEWS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only yesterday Chicago Jews were convinced that Russia is free, that Czarism is dead and that the Russian democratic government, born in the revolution, which brought full freedom to the Jews, has come to stay. This was realized by tens of thousands of Jews that assembled at four o'clock yesterday afternoon around the Douglas Park pavilion.</p>
   <p>Enthusiasm was great. The Jews of Chicago over 20,000 in number, in greeting the envoys of free Russia, gave them a hearty welcome and sent a message of greeting to the provisory government in Petrograd, which is now carrying on a doubtful fight against the foreign enemy that is trying to exterminate the freedom recently won.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0576.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"I will forever remember!" the first ambassador of free Russia said to a representative of the Courier. "This was a real welcome for free Russia, and we are convinced that the friendship of Jews is a true and upright one and we are proud of it."</p>
   <p>Free Russia will read with pleasure of how the Chicago Jews welcomed their representatives and listened to their message of brotherly love and equality.</p>
   <p>Ambassador Bachmietoff was very highly impressed with the Jewish greeting in Douglas Park. It was the greatest that the commission has received in Chicago. Above all Baron Ginsburg, the only Jewish member of the commission, expressed his pleasure over the greeting, to a Courier representative.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0577.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was an inspiring spectacle. The Jews, who ran away from Czarism, having suffered from the persecutions of the bloody Romanoff gentlemen, who, until recently trembled at the very mention of Russia, these Jews yesterday gave to the representative of free Russia a storm of applause and a hearty welcome.</p>
   <p>Ambassador Bachmietoff and Professor Lomonosoff assured the Chicago Jews that their six million brothers in Russia are now for the first time in the history of Russia full pledged citizens and enjoy the same political, religious and social rights as do all nationalities in the mighty empire.</p>
   <p>The Ambassador was so pleased with the greeting of the Jews, that he felt, he must say something to them aside from his official message, and he said: "I will ever be proud that I was fortunate enough to be one of those who immediately after the revolution, helped abolish all Czaristic laws against Jews."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0578.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the evening, a banquet was given for the Russian commission by the Jewish reception committee, in the Congress Hotel. Over 200 men and women were present, including a delegation of Milwaukee Jews. Adolph Krause was the toastmaster, and Judge Henry Horner and Ambassador Bachmietoff were the guest speakers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
