<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-30">Nov. 30, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Huge Protest Will Kill Immigration Bill</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-30">Nov. 30, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">HUGE PROTEST WILL KILL IMMIGRATION BILL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Congressman Adolph J. Sabath addressed a meeting of distributors and editors of foreign language papers in America yesterday at the La Salle Hotel.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harry A. Lipski, chairman, opened the meeting and introduced the speaker. In a very clear manner the speech of Congressman Sabath elucidated all questions pertaining to the planned Immigration Bill that enemies of free entrance plan to pass in Congress.</p>
   <p>The Bill at present is in the hands of the committee on immigration, which will present it to Congress for a hearing the coming Monday or Tuesday.</p>
   <p>"The Bill stands in great danger of being passed in Congress by a large majority," said the Jewish Congressman. "We must now concentrate our efforts on one point, to bring pressure on all congressman in districts of large foreign elements to take a stand against the Bill.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0102.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"We must withhold as many votes as possible," Mr. Sabath said further. "If this is accomplished, it is possible that President Wilson will veto it. But if the immigration bill is passed by a large majority, there remains for the president no other choice but to sign.</p>
   <p>"A large campaign must be made," the Congressman said. "Protests must be sent to every congressman by the citizens of his district. We must appeal to the foreign elements in their own language. They must be awakened to a gigantic protest that will reach every Congressman in the House. This is the only method that can be used to fight the bill that aims to close the doors of America. If we could withdraw many votes so that the bill may not pass with a large majority, then the president may veto it."</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabath closed his speech with good advice regarding procedures. "All foreign language newspapers should unite to bring about a gigantic battle against the bill by instructing their readers to send petitions to the congressmen of their districts."</p>
   <p>When Congressman Sabath ended his speech, he was strongly applauded.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0103.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A committee of seven was selected to formulate a statement for all the newspapers. Mr. Harry A. Lipsky was appointed chairman and will commence by Monday to press the fight against this bill.</p>
   <p>Among those present were Dr. Graham Taylor, Honorable Henry N. Hattman, vice-president of the Board of Education, and representatives of all language newspapers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
