<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-22">Apr. 22, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Successful Drive</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0296</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0296.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-22">Apr. 22, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESSFUL DRIVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Keren Hayesod [exchequer of World Zionist Organization] drive for a quarter of a million dollars, inagurated a few weeks ago by the local Keren Hayesod Committee, is now in full swing and promises to be a greater success than expected. There will actually be a quarter of a million dollars in cash before very long, and there can be no doubt about the possibility of raising this sum within a reasonable time. Last year the Keren Hayesod drive was only partly a success because only the greater part of the quota was raised; this year however the drive promises to be a full success, for the entire sum will be raised.</p>
   <p>The following figures and facts illustrate best the progress of the Keren Hayesod in Chicago. The first two functions in connection with the Keren Hayesod drive last year have been instrumental in raising thirteen thousand <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0297.jpg" n="2"/>dollars last year, but the two first functions in connection with the drive have produced more than forty thousand dollars this year. A year ago the goal was one hundred and fifty thousand dollars; this year the goal is a quarter of a million dollars. Last year the total number of subscribers to the Keren Hayesod in Chicago was not more than twenty-seven hundred; this year it is six thousand, and before not very long it will reach the eight thousand mark because hundreds of Jews in Chicago who have not even heard of the Keren Hayesod last year are giving liberally this year. We know of one synagogue the members of which contributed the last year to the Keren Hayesod three thousand dollars, to have raised their quota this year to thirteen thousand dollars. A number of leading Chicago Jews, who contributed very little last year toward the Keren Hayesod, are giving more liberally this year. All this would go to indicate that the Keren Hayesod is making rapid progress in Chicago, and there is reason to hope that before another year or two the Keren Hayesod will be the most popular Jewish movement in Chicago as well as in the entire Middle West. We dare say that before this year will close its eyes the number of Keren Hayesod subscribers in this city will reach <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0298.jpg" n="3"/>the ten thousand mark, and the Keren Hayesod will thus become the largest and the numerically strongest Jewish organization in Chicago.</p>
   <p>This in itself is one of the greatest assets in our public life. The larger the number of subscribers to the Keren Hayesod, the stronger our backbone and the richer our life. A Jew who contributes to the Keren Hayesod is more or less conscious of his Jewish duties, and being in touch with new Palestine keeps him in touch with everything that is Jewish, and therefore the success of the Keren Hayesod drive in Chicago should not be considered only from the point of view of how much it will help Palestine but also from the point of view of how much it helps us here to continue our Jewish traditions and to carry the burden of Judaism. It is our sincere belief that by investing money in Palestine through the Keren Hayesod we not only come to the aid of a Jewish Palestine but we also strengthen our hands in the countries of Diaspora.</p>
   <p>The growing success of the Keren Hayesod justifies the attitude of our optimists, who claim that in spite of all the destructive forces from within and <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0299.jpg" n="4"/>from without, Judaism in America will survive, for a Jewish group that takes such a strong interest in a cause like that of the Keren Hayesod must be strongly entrenched in Judaism and must draw its energies from very solid sources. It is true that the Keren Hayesod may never enroll all the Jews in America as subscribers and may never have such a large membership list as the Relief Organization has had, but the very fact that the Keren Hayesod could within a short time enroll hundreds of thousands of Jews as regular contributors and is growing in leaps and bounds, proves best that American Jewry is morally strong and is aware of the problem before it. The Keren Hayesod is not only the financial agency of the Jewish people with the help of which it is going to build Palestine, but it is also the test of the moral strength of American Jewry, and it is gratifying to learn the American Jewry has passed the test splendidly.</p>
   <p>Therein lies the significance of the success of the Keren Hayesod drive in Chicago and all the other Jewish communities [all over] the Union. The success of the drive does away with our doubts as to the future of American Judaism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0300.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Now we know that American Judaism has a future, and that it is destined to retain the leadership it acquired during the war. Now we know the American Judaism is strong and solid like a rock, and cannot be destroyed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
