<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-01-08">Jan. 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Emil G. Hirsch Dies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0981</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0981.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-01-08">Jan. 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">DR. EMIL G. HIRSCH DIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Great loss, as spiritual head of Sinai Congregation, as a speaker, a scientist, and editor of several publications, he acquired a reputation of national importance.</p>
   <p>Dr. Emil G. Hirsch, the spiritual head of Sinai Congregation died, yesterday, at his home, 4608 Drexel Boulevard, from abscess of the lungs combined with pneumonia. With his going one of the most prominent scientists, educators, orators, and editors has passed away and his congregation suffered an irreparable loss.</p>
   <p>On January 3, his condition was declared to be critical by the attending physicians, Drs. Isaac A. Abt, Otto Schmidt and Solomon Shauss. Saturday evening they gave up all hope, and accordingly notified his family. At the death bed were present his wife, his daughter, Mrs. Gerson B. Levi and her husband, Dr. Levi, who had nursed him with touching care. Owing to his <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0982.jpg" n="2"/>demise the meetings of the Chicago Council of Jewish Women, which should have taken place, today, and the one of the Mothers' Aid, called for Wednesday, have been countermanded. The funeral service will be held tomorrow morning, at 10:30 o'clock in Sinai Temple, and the interment will be in Rosehill Cemetery.</p>
   <p>As active pall bears the following are going to serve: Dr. Elkan W. Fishell, Walter E. Bauer, Milton E. Falker, Harold G. Cuthman, Merrill L. Israel, Abe J. Korr, Jay L. Kraus, I. L. Marienthal. The music will be furnished during the services, by the organist, Arthur Dunham, and the Sinai Choir. The ritual will be read by William Willhartz and the sermon given by Dr. Levi.</p>
   <p>His Development</p>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch was born May 22, 1853 in Luxemburg, the son of Rabbi Dr. Samuel Hirsch. Fourteen Years later, he settled with his parents in America and finished the course at the University of Pennsylvania. After having completed <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0983.jpg" n="3"/>his education at the Universities of Leipzig and Berlin, he was elected a Rabbi of the Sinai Congregation, in Baltimore, and one year later became the spiritual head of the Avath Israel Congregation in Louisville, where he remained till 1880, when he received a call to the Chicago Sinai Congregation. Although he received many flattering offers from other congregations, he remained true to the Sinai Congregation until his death.</p>
   <p>In 1878 he married the daughter of a well known New York Rabbi, Miss Mathilda Einhorn with whom he lived very happily.</p>
   <p>He Took An Active Part In Manifold Affairs</p>
   <p>In Chicago he developed great and useful activities. In the same year he became Professor of Hebraic literature at the University of Chicago. Besides this he lectured at John Hopkins University in 1902. Furthermore he was an editor of the Zeitgeist, the Reformer and the Reform Advocate. Not satisfied, he was a member for ten years of the Chicago Public Library's administration <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0984.jpg" n="4"/>and also a member of the Moral's Commission, established by Mayor Carter H. Harrison. As an orator he had few equals. In the pulpit he gave expression to his opinion with great frankness and did not spare with his criticism even the most influential members of his Congregation when necessary. Only a man of his importance and genius, could venture to break with the traditional custom of holding services on Saturday, and change to Sunday services.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch belonged to the Chicago Lincoln Club, the Chicago Singing Society, besides, he was an honorary member of the Turngemeinde. He always took an active part in all German-American efforts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
