<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-06-18">June 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Louis D. Brandeis - Regarding the Jewish Problem</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0610</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0610.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-06-18">June 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LOUIS D. BRANDEIS - REGARDING THE JEWISH PROBLEM</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The speech held by Mr. Louis Brandeis, not long ago, for the Eastern Council of Reform Rabbis, analyzed the Jewish problem and presented the actual situation of the Jews in its true colors...</p>
   <p>Let no American be under the impression that Zionism does not agree with patriotism. Every Jew who promotes the Jewish colonization in Palestine, although he knows that neither he nor his children will ever live there, will be a better person and a better American by doing so.</p>
   <p>Note what Seton Watson said. America is full of people who are proud of their American citizenship, yet who direct their thoughts to their homelands for a source of inspiration of their national culture and traditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0611.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This example describes best the feeling of the American Jew for Palestine.</p>
   <p>There is no conflict between loyalty to America and loyalty to Judaism. The Jewish spirit, the product of our religion and experience, is in reality modern and American.</p>
   <p>The basic laws of America aim to make the brotherhood of man a reality. This brotherhood was the Jewish basic law over 2,500 years ago. America's greatest need in the 20th century is social justice. This has been the Jewish ambition for many years. His tribulations as well as his religion have prepared the Jew for active democracy....</p>
   <p>We also have an important duty which only Zionism can help us fulfill. We must help America fight against the demoralization, which has to a certain degree taken hold of many American Jews. The reason for <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0612.jpg" n="3"/>this demoralization is clear. This is brought about largely because in our land of freedom everything by which the Jew was protected has been dispensed with, and a new generation grew up without the moral and spiritual protection of the ghetto. And it is not quite clear which would be the best remedy. Perhaps the Jew would regain self-respect,through the study of the past history of his race. This would also give him confidence in the future....This spirit can best be developed through active participation in the revival of Judaism. And this can only be done by the support of the Zionist movement.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
