<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-24">Feb. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Palestine Jews Certain about Jewish State, Says A. S. Roe</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_10_1_0399</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0399.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-24">Feb. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">PALESTINE JEWS CERTAIN ABOUT JEWISH STATE, SAYS A. S. ROE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. A. S. Roe, the well-known Jewish businessman, member of the firm of Grossfield and Roe, and Jewish civic leader, who made a trip to Europe and the Orient, yesterday returned to Chicago. Mr. Roe was abroad for six months. He visited England, Belgium, France, Egypt and Palestine where he spent most of his time. He appears to be in good health, refreshed and gay, which he attributed to the climate of the Holy Land. In London and Paris, Mr. Roe met Dr. Shmarya Levin and other Zionist leaders, who expressed to him their profound hope that Palestine would soon become a Jewish homeland.</p>
   <p>"In Palestine," Mr. Roe explained, "the Jews are very optimistic; they are anxiously awaiting the establishment of the League of Nations so that England can take over the mandate on Palestine, and then they can expect better times. Meanwhile, the Jews there are suffering. The cost of living is high and there is no money to buy the necessities of life. Transportation is bad, and it is impossible to export the usual Palestinian products. The Herzl colony was <pb facs="5423972_10_1_0400.jpg" n="2"/>completely destroyed during the war, and the members of the other colonies have suffered terribly.</p>
   <p>"But," he added, "life in Europe is becoming stable, and the same applies to Palestine. There are brilliant opportunities for all kinds of enterprises which will make Palestine a flourishing state."</p>
   <p>Mr. Roe said that Jews are buying a great deal of land from the Arabs in Palestine; that the deeds will become effective as soon as the country is set free. In this way, he and other Jews have bought large tracts of land not far from Jaffa, for industrial purposes.</p>
   <p>In his travels in Europe, Mr. Roe made connections which will enable his firm to send parcels of food to Poland and Rumania.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
