<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title><bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>, <date when="1936-11-13">Nov. 13, 1936</date></bibl></title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.L"/>
    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group"><list><item>DANISH</item></list></div>
   <div type="codes"><list><item>I C</item><item>III G</item><item>III A</item><item>I L</item></list></div>
  <div type="citation"><bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>, <date when="1936-11-13">Nov. 13, 1936</date></bibl></div>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0133.jpg" n="2"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>younger generation (after 1880) also has included many citizens who have won distinction as bankers, physicians, teachers, manufacturers, and men of affairs. Three became famous as musicians and composers. At least two were members of the State legislature. Several served in the city and village governments.</p>
   <p>The Danes brought to our State an innate honesty and integrity, coupled with a will to work hard for their homes, in accordance with principles which had stood the test of centuries. This tradition showed itself in the fondness of the Danish immigrant for his native ways, foods, speech, and diversions. Some notable choirs, active for a half-century or longer, still cultivate old home songs. For many years, each Danish settlement celebrated June 5, the anniversary of the Danish constitution, as a day of celebration, but in later times the tendency has been to transfer these festivals to July 4.</p>
   <p>Like other groups of foreign origin, the Danes in Illinois--as early as the sixties--began developing a literature of their own, founded on American <pb facs="5420780_1_0134.jpg" n="3"/>impressions of life and nature, or embodying old memories. Poetry flourished in the earlier Danish-American press and in a number of books. Hymns and their attendant sacred music continued to cheer and animate many men and women. From about 1880 there also developed considerable dramatic activity. The Danes still show an interest in sports dependent on personal initiative.</p>
   <p>The Dane is fond of arts and crafts, gymnastics, athletics, folk dances, and other constructive diversion. Danish artisans were much in demand until the advent of the machine age. Much artistic decoration of our older mansions in and about Chicago was done by Danish skill. Danish servants always were, and still are, at a premium.</p>
   <p>But the greatest contribution of the Danish immigrants, in Illinois and elsewhere, lies in their genius for homebuilding and the development of sound units of farming. Acting under the time-honored demand that every farm should be left in a better state of cultivation than when it was received, the Danish farmer has set a praiseworthy example for all time. Wherever a large and commodious <pb facs="5420780_1_0135.jpg" n="4"/>barn is found in conjunction with a modest dwelling, it is a safe guess that a Dane was responsible.</p>
   <p>A grandson of one of the early Danish pastors in Illinois was chosen for the distinguished task of editing the great history of the United States by Henry Adams.</p>
   <p>An immigrant of the first generation is largely responsible for the initial development of our park system and many private estates.</p>
   <p>Another American of Danish birth, who came to Illinois fifty years ago, founded the only American national park in a foreign country--in Denmark--dedicated to our hospitable country of adoption.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
