<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1919-05-17">May 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Danish Protest</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0858</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0858.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1919-05-17">May 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DANISH PROTEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>While most European nations seem to be on the alert to get all they can out of the peace treaty in the form of territory, people, or other advantages, little Denmark respectfully declines to get any more than is hers by right and national sympathies.</p>
   <p>The Danes of North Slesvig, in conjunction with the Danish government and parliament decided on a certain line north of which there are Danes in sufficient number to justify reunion with Denmark. The commission representing Denmark before the peace tribunal expounded this line and the reasons why.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0859.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But the peacemakers, according to the official summary of the preliminary plans, seem to be in favor of placing the Danish border line far more to the south than proposed by the Danes themselves, and have been providing for plebiscites in territories largely populated by Germans, or people with German sympathies.</p>
   <p>Many of these may, under the circumstances, vote for casting their lot with Denmark, at least temporarily. But Denmark does not want any such additions. She wants national unity, not any additional territory or people that may be a source of unrest and danger from within and without.</p>
   <p>The Danes, therefore, are protesting, as will be seen from the following <pb facs="5420780_1_0860.jpg" n="3"/>cabled information from Copenhagen, dated May 13:</p>
   <p>"Both chambers of Danish Parliament yesterday, in joint confidential sitting, discussed a situation created by peace conditions in and around Slesvig. The following resolution was adopted by a majority, consisting of Left party, radical party, socialists, and the conservative, Professor Birck:</p>
   <p>"While the Danish Parliament expresses its satisfaction at the prospect that the coming peace will bring the fulfillment of the national hopes of the Danish people, it insists on its resolution of October 23, 1918, and on the wishes expressed towards the allied and associated powers in Paris with regard to the voting zone in Slesvig by the parliamentary delegation <pb facs="5420780_1_0861.jpg" n="4"/>representing all parties, and by the representatives of the Danish Electors Association in Slesvig. Parliament still sticks to the opinion that a plebiscite on the basis of these wishes will afford best guarantee for the national future of the Danish people.</p>
   <p>The resolution of October 23, 1918, declared that no change in the present position of Slesvig, other than an arrangement in accordance with the principle of nationalities is consistent with the Danish peoples' wishes, feelings, and interests."</p>
   <p>Dissatisfaction on account of the plebescite provisions for southern Slesvig is also reflected in the Danish press, according to cables sent to American papers.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0862.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The political committee of the Rigsdag has telegraphed the Danish minister at Paris that the government and the Rigsdag insist in this connection on the enforcement of the principle of nationality.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
