<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-02-16">Feb. 16, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Nobel Prize</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0584</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0584.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-02-16">Feb. 16, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE NOBEL PRIZE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a letter to the Norwegian Minister of Foreign Affairs, Mr. Lovland, "Terrible Teddy" Roosevelt has expressed his thanks and appreciation for the Nobel Prize received by him as well as explaining how he intends to use the money. He declares:</p>
   <p>"In our days peace among the various classes of which the population of a country is made up is just as important as peace among nations."</p>
   <p>Surely lasting peace among the classes would be of tremendous importance and advantage for the class which Mr. Roosevelt represents, the upper class that feeds and preys on the lower ones. How wonderful it would be for the parasitical upper class to have "peace," so that there would be no trouble having the lower classes obey and hand over the fruits of their labor and be satisfied with the little they would be allowed to keep.</p>
   <p>Fortunately, this does not occur without protest and a steadily growing unrest which is better identified with an everlasting war during which great <pb facs="5420780_1_0585.jpg" n="2"/>social values are being destroyed; but it is a necessary war for the cause of saving the lower classes from being suppressed into virtual slavery. Furthermore, there is a movement going on all over the civilized world sponsoring demands for decency and justice in social affairs. This demand for a re-organization of Society is supported by so great an army of workers that these of the parasite class who still possess the ability to reason feel uncomfortably alarmed. Peace among the classes is neither possible nor desirable. The tendency in social development points towards the abolition of both the parasite classes and the classes supporting the parasites. When this goal has been reached we can safely hope for international peace, not before.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
