<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-07-26">July 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Marines Run Wild</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0343</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0343.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-07-26">July 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE MARINES RUN WILD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A detachment of U. S. Marines recently went on a rampage in Seattle, Washington, when they, assisted by a mob of "patriotic" bullies and hoodlums, raided the offices of the Socialist Party and the Industrial Workers of the World, burning and destroying furniture and records.</p>
   <p>This outrage is not so surprising when we consider the quality of the majority of enlisted men that make up our Army and Navy, and furthermore it should be remembered that they were being encouraged by a fanatically anti-Socialistic press.</p>
   <p>The most serious aspect of the whole affair is the fact that our Secretary of the Navy himself, Mr. Josephus Daniels, in a way gave the signal for this lawless outbreak, when he in a speech in a local club, just previously, violently attacked the "red flag," stating that "it has no place in this <pb facs="5420780_1_0344.jpg" n="2"/>country, and its believers have no place in this country."</p>
   <p>A more hateful and vicious attack on the Socialists in the United States, who now number hundreds of thousands, has never been made by a man in such a prominent public office, and if the Socialist Party had only one single representative in Congress, the Secretary's action would undoubtedly have been taken up before that body. As it is, we can only hope that the incident, through other channels, will come to the Presidents' attention, and that he immediately will send the tactless, dangerous Secretary of the Navy on his way to the peace and quiet of private life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
