<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-02-17">Feb. 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The United States of Europe</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0384</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0384.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-02-17">Feb. 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNITED STATES OF EUROPE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From and including today, we will run in this paper the story by Anatole France, "The United States of Europe." Anatole France is France's unsurpassed writer. "The United States of Europe" is part of a book titled On the White Stone, with the scene of action laid in the old Forum in Rome where the past and the present meet and where the reader is easily lost in meditation on both.</p>
   <p>After considering past incidents, the author gradually enters into a discussion of the present and the future. Are we, on the basis of <pb facs="5420780_1_0385.jpg" n="2"/>present social conditions, able to conclude or predict what we are heading for? We have reasons to think we are, because we are familiar with the conditions responsible for previous developments.</p>
   <p>For instance, if we consider the change in conditions for the working man, from slavery through serfdom to wage earner, we may conclude that present methods of production are not here to stay either.</p>
   <p>Be it a fact that industrialism and mass production have practically rendered the old crafts and small scale farming useless. Now we must <pb facs="5420780_1_0386.jpg" n="3"/>begin to think, about what is going to replace the capitalistic system. When making a study of how the feudal system was upheld by collecting rent and assessments, how and why it collapsed and was abolished, we may be able to imagine how the state of the future is going to take over the productive machinery of the country now privately owned.</p>
   <p>When we study institutions already operated by the state, we may conceive how Socialistic methods are going to be applied universally in the future. When thus having investigated the past and present of human enterprise, we may be able to judge whether or not collective action and a publicly <pb facs="5420780_1_0387.jpg" n="4"/>owned productive machinery can become a reality. It is futile to believe that justice is going to be a determining fact in future developments. Developments will be brought about through sheer necessity and as an unavoidable consequence of capitalistic falsehood.</p>
   <p>To illustrate his point, the author permits one of his characters tell a story describing the stages of development modern society will have to go through before it can be called a true democracy. As in "Looking Backward" by Bellamy, the author's intercessor is a young man who awakens in the midst of a new society and is almost overwhelmed by the change. The story by Anatole France is somewhat shorter, and does not go so much into detail as does Bellamy's; but as a modern supposition, it is <pb facs="5420780_1_0388.jpg" n="5"/>as brisk and liberal in its aspects.</p>
   <p>Anatole France has written books finer and purer and more sparkling than this one as far as the language is concerned. It is interesting to note, however, how a genius as critical and keen as Anatole France takes the revolutionary problem into consideration and declares himself openly in favor of the labor movement and its goal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
