<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1918-06-15">June 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Loyalty Demonstration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0163</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0163.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1918-06-15">June 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LOYALTY DEMONSTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday the "Danish American Loyalty Parade" started with sunshine and a good spirit. About noon, from Dania Hall, Kedzie and Wabansia Avenues, with the official car in the lead, the parade started down Kedzie to Armitage, and west on Armitage, while the motorcycle police rushed back and forth to keep everything in order.</p>
   <p>It was one of the largest and best auto parades Chicago has ever seen. There were over one hundred automobiles, all beautifully decorated with American flags.</p>
   <p>Dania's private cars were also decorated with pennants of all colors.</p>
   <p>The prize for the best decorated car was given to the "S. S. S.," an 1895 Ford which <pb facs="5420780_1_0164.jpg" n="2"/>portrayed a schooner under full sail, with the S.S.S. executive on board, and Mr. M. Edwards as mate. The official floats were a good imitation of a small fortress, with a cannon and a cannoneer on top; also a large truck with forty flower girls, dressed in white, where Holger Petersen, in the garb of Uncle Sam, sat on a throne. When the parade passed Humboldt Park on North Avenue, Hearst's Film Company was on the job to take moving-pictures. Because of a silly Sunday Blue Law, the promised Jackie's Band was not present, so the parade had to get along without this added attraction.</p>
   <p>The following telegram was received and read at Riverview Park when the parade arrived.</p>
   <p>"To the President of the United States: Washington, D.C.</p>
   <p>"Ten thousand American citizens of Danish birth, assembled in Riverview Park, have <pb facs="5420780_1_0165.jpg" n="3"/>this afternoon dedicated their Service Flag, and wish to convey to you their most sacred allegiance to the noble principles you have proclaimed to the world.</p>
   <p>"It is our privilege to be citizens of the United States, as we love our country, support its Constitution, obey its laws, respect its Flag and at all times stand ready to defend it against all enemies.</p>
   <p>"The Stars and Stripes forever.</p>
   <p>Wald A. Bauer, president of the Committee</p>
   <p>Chas. L. Wilde, chairman."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
