<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-04-20">Apr. 20, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[Roosevelt Condemns Men Not Proven Guilty]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-04-20">Apr. 20, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[ROOSEVELT CONDEMNS MEN NOT PROVEN GUILTY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is excusable indeed for President Roosevelt to have a quarrel with one of the capitalist cliques to whom he owes his election, and the incident is of little concern to anybody inasmuch as the capitalist class is fairly satisfied with his administration. (It ought to be.)</p>
   <p>However, President Roosevelt accidently revealed once more to which camp he actually belongs. Infuriated by his opponent's accusations and embarrassing evidence, Roosevelt compares him with the three suspected criminals Debs, Mayer and Haywood, classifying them all as "undesirable citizens." In his last "message," he used the selfsame expression about the socialists.</p>
   <p>Now as before, the socialists will, under ordinary circumstances, find the President's attitude amusing, or they may even feel pleased on account of the particular attention he devotes to them. Mr. Debs is not particularly worried because the capitalists' foremost representative wishes he were at <pb facs="5420780_1_0569.jpg" n="2"/>Jericho, or in a place still hotter, but the President's attacks on Mayer and Haywood are extremely unfair and mean and have been a source of regret and condemnation in wide circles, even in the more liberal capitalistic press.</p>
   <p>As we all know, Mayer and Haywood are two of the three mine-workers' trusted agents who were virtually kidnaped from their homes and families in Colorado and transported to Idaho, where they have been held as prisoners now for over a year, all on account of a bum's "confession" to the effect that he had been hired by the two men to slay Governor Stennenberg of Idaho. Any real foundation for the charge has not been found, which probably accounts for the fact that they have been held prisoners for so long before being tried and thus be able to prove their innocence. Their arrest, which was unconstitutional, has been argued before the Supreme Court, which as expected, decided against the three men. There was however one of the Supreme Court Justices who had the courage to describe the case against the three men as grossly unfair and against the law, a result of a conspiracy between the authorities of the two states, who in turn are backed by the mine-owners and the powerful interests of the standard Oil Company.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0570.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When even criminals whose guilt is unquestionable are considered innocent until proved guilty, it is the more inappropriate for the President of the country to condemn these men in advance when the charge against them is very doubtful; because he thereby endangers their lives, guilty or not guilty, that is, presuming the President speaks with authority. If it is true that once Roosevelt, as a Roughrider, shot a Spanish soldier in the back, the incident would be more forgivable than his attacks on the imprisoned labor leaders, which have caused much indignation not only among the hundreds of thousands who stubbornly believe the three men are innocent, but also on the part of every man whose sense of justice is not completely missing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
