<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-09-03">Sept. 3, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A Change of Front</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0410</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0410.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-09-03">Sept. 3, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A CHANGE OF FRONT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2..............The most important and remarkable statement so far uttered in connection with the "investigation" of the Steel Trust is not the one by Theodore Roosevelt, assuring us that he saved the country from a panic, by obeying the orders of J. P. Morgan. That particular incident now belongs to history, and serves only as an indication of Teddy's dwindling ferocity, in his role of the thundering lion.</p>
   <p>Far more significant, painting as it does, towards far reaching social-economical and political changes is the statement by the president of the Steel Trust himself, Judge Gary, before the investigating committee, that, in his opinion, the old era of destructive competition has come to an end, and that the price of all products in interstate commerce, should be fixed by a federal commission, and subject to revision <pb facs="5420780_1_0411.jpg" n="2"/>by the Federal courts. A similar opinion was expressed by Attorney General Wickersham before the Minnesota State Bar Association, when he stated as his belief that free competition no longer existed. He went on to say that supply and demand are no longer the price-determining factors, having been superseded by an agreement among the big trusts. Official court action against the latter was always based on the earlier condition, and is, therefore, now ineffective. Not even the tariff can be used to change this situation. The Attorney General stated flatly that competition is dying if it is not already dead, and recommended Federal control and regulation of prices, as already advocated by Judge Gary.</p>
   <p>Later, persons close to such business grants as Rockfeller, Morgan and Carnegie, have been talking in the same vein; it is, therefore, evident that this realization of the desirability of Federal control is not simply the idea of a few individual, isolated theorists, but that a complete change of front has taken place by America's business and industrial leaders.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0412.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>CAPITALISM AND SOCIALISM</p>
   <p>What is filling the hearts of the rulers with fear and rage is the firm hold which we have on the man in the street; the united change of front on the part of the great mass of voters; the reliazation that this is not simply a passing, unplanned dissatisfaction over injustices suffered, but a well planned, permanent movement towards a definite goal, namely the destruction of the prevailing wage - and profit system.</p>
   <p>In ever increasing numbers of people are reading our newspapers and periodicals; "Appeal to Reason" for instance, now has more than one half million subscribers. The power and influence thus wielded by our organizations are beginning to be felt. The workers are daily becoming more inimical to capitalism, its press, its courts and the hypnotic pharisocial doctrines of its churches. The grip on the masses is beginning to loosen, and this makes them furious.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0413.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>They are beginning to see the end of their corrupt sustem. Destruction is staring them in the face, and they realize that there is no salvation, because we are in perfect accord with the natural trend of social evolution.</p>
   <p>The future is ours' Hitch your waggon to a star!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
