<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-02-01">Feb. 1, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Danes in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-02-01">Feb. 1, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Danes began immigrating to the United States at an early date. At the present time there are about fifteen thousand Danish families in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Danish consul E. Dreier, arrived in Chicago in 1854, at the age of twenty-one, and consequently can give some very interesting information about the good old times. At the time that he came to Chicago there were only twenty Danes here. One of them was P. Hansen, who later became a United States consul in Elsinore. At one time he was the Health Commissioner of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Another Dane, H. A. Miller, made the first soda beverages in Chicago, and later established a syrup factory. Mr. Dreier was one of his employees. Later, Mr. Dreier started a drugstore. He retired from this business only recently. He expressed the viewpoint of all Danes. He said they have improved their conditions materially, compared with their old fatherland, and that therefore <pb facs="5420780_1_0191.jpg" n="2"/>immigration has been steadily increasing during recent years.</p>
   <p>Mr. Dreier was also a member of the Chicago School Board, and of the Park Board of the West Side.....One can hardly speak of Danish colonies or settlements, because the Danes mingle with Swedes and Norwegians. We find Danes in the vicinity of Wicker Park, Humboldt Park, between Division Street and North Avenue, and elsewhere.</p>
   <p>The majority of the Danes are Lutherans. They have many beautiful churches and large congregations.</p>
   <p>The club Dania is their largest social organization, and has four hundred members. The members not only are interested in music and social activities, but also carry out a mutual benefit plan.....</p>
   <p>Scandia Hall, 96 West Ohio Street, is likewise a meeting place for Danes, Swedes, and Norwegians. This excellent building was finished a year ago, and dedicated <pb facs="5420780_1_0192.jpg" n="3"/>to this purpose. Besides general entertainment, theater performances in Danish and Swedish are rendered here. The Danes take a lively interest in drama.....</p>
   <p>Danish women living in the neighborhood of Wicker Park have recently organized a new charity association, which has succeeded brilliantly and deserves general recognition of its merits.</p>
   <p>Two Danish newspapers are published in Chicago, the Norden, a weekly, and Scandinavia, a daily.</p>
   <p>The Danes are active in politics. In former years most of the voters were Republicans, but of late they have turned toward the Democratic camp.</p>
   <p>One of the oldest buildings in Chicago, the Hotel Dannevirko, was built by a Dane and is the property of C. Hansen.....The members of the Peterson &amp; Rax Bank are likewise Danes, and J. Skallerup, the County Commissioner, and O. Hansen, West Town Collector, belong to the same nationality.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0193.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>John P. Hansen is one of the richest of the Danish businessmen. He manages a large tobacco business on Milwaukee Avenue, and is also one of the directors of the Milwaukee Avenue State Bank. W. Hansen is a large real-estate operator and specializes in the sale of large farms.....</p>
   <p>Dr. Max Henius, partner of the firm Wahl &amp; Henius, has founded a chemical factory and a brewing academy which are outstanding from a scientific standpoint.</p>
   <p>Famous among the members of the Danish Community is the great pianist, A. Hyllested. He is perhaps the most skilled pianist in this city.</p>
   <p>The musician, J. R. Hald, who is also a musical critic for a number of English newspapers, has achieved considerable fame as a composer.....</p>
   <p>The land of Thorwaldsen's birth has given us two eminent sculptors, J. Selbert and C. Rohl-Smith. The Danish artist C. Paulsen is also well known among the lovers of art.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
