<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1931-02-06">Feb. 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Middle Road</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1931-02-06">Feb. 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE MIDDLE ROAD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Middle Road, there is none! As soon as a man wavers and does not know with which wind to be blown, he becomes neither fish nor foul. No matter how much credit his associates may give him, in reality he is just another nondescript bit of flotsam on the sea of life.</p>
   <p>On the whole, society today preaches that the happy medium is the right route to follow. This doubtless holds good regarding the indulgence of food, pleasure, and the satisfaction of physical needs. But here we must draw the line, for the spirit of man has no happy medium. As soon as he applies the brakes or puts the damper on his spiritual self, he ceases to be an individual. In thus following the line of least resistance, he loses his identity in the great mass of humanity.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0305.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have among us, all sorts of cowards. Yet the most despicable of all, perhaps, is the moral coward who does not have the courage of his own convictions, or having them lacks the temerity to acknowledge or fight for them openly. By doing this, his existence is a living lie, and he betrays his better self. In fact, far more respect is due the man who goes for gold and frankly admits it to be his one god, than to the individual of lofty ideals who inwardly despises the money-monger, yet fails to raise his voice in protest.</p>
   <p>Why? Because as yet the spirit of man has not triumphed over his body. He is afraid to suffer the possible deprivations of physical things as a penalty for having dared to pursue his ideals. If, by some miracle, overnight these spiritual pigmies were to rise up and claim their own, a great change for the better of all mankind would ensue. But alas, for the most part, man who was born to soar with wings, through lack of courage remains but a crawling worm. This, and this alone is the primary cause for the utter failure of present-day civilization. The cosmos knows no compromise, for there is no Middle Road.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
