<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-03-01">Mar. 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">New Socialistic Bills</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0352</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0352.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-03-01">Mar. 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">NEW SOCIALISTIC BILLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Legislative Assembly in Springfield, Ill. is finally ready to have members of the lower house introduce law proposals. The Senate has been working on new bills for over a month. A total of 115 bills have been introduced in the lower house and referred to various committees appointed for the purpose of studying them. The four socialist members have introduced more bills in the interest of the working class than all the other representatives combined, and the so-called labor laws proposed by the members are of little or no benefit to the workers.</p>
   <p>According to the rules, each member has the privilege of introducing <pb facs="5420780_1_0353.jpg" n="2"/>three bills for each roll call. Thus, the socialist had the opportunity to introduce a dozen. Among the proposals is a bill prohibiting the importing of strikebreakers unless they are properly informed as to their duties.</p>
   <p>Another bill calls for the worker's right to persuade comrades not to work as strikebreakers.</p>
   <p>A third bill is contemplated to prohibit employers from interfering with the organization of workers.</p>
   <p>Black-listing workers is proposed to be ranked as a crime subject to <pb facs="5420780_1_0354.jpg" n="3"/>fine and imprisonment.</p>
   <p>That imprisonment for violation of an injunction during a strike should be abolished, was also proposed.</p>
   <p>According to another bill, employers should be forced to pay salaries at least twice a month.</p>
   <p>The motion that workers should be guaranteed at least one day of rest every week was proposed. This is particularly aimed at hotel and restaurant owners whose employees are still working seven days a week.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0355.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A bill proposing compulsory state accident and health insurance was introduced.</p>
   <p>Of course, we realize that these and other bills introduced by the socialists will not all become laws, but the rights and demands of labor will at least be made the subject of discussion by the various committees and by the legislative body itself. If the increase in socialistic votes continues at the present rate, the other parties will no doubt realize the necessity of giving labor at least a part of what it demands.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
