<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-01-06">Jan. 6, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0789</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0789.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-01-06">Jan. 6, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2. In its new year issue Inter Ocean presents a number of articles, supplemented by pictures, about men prominent in the public life of Chicago, among whom we also find our countryman, Senator Niels Juul. In spite of the fact that we are his political opponents, we have the highest regard for Mr. Juul, due to his outstanding ability, absolute honesty and genuine Danish spirit and sentiment. To quote the Inter Ocean:</p>
   <p>Being author of the famous Juul bill, which so deeply concerns Chicago property owners, would alone be enough to distinguish one legislator from hundreds of others, but Niels Juul State Senator from the 23rd district, and assistant attorney for the Sanitary Board, has added other accomplishments to sustain his claim to distinction. Probably no man has made himself a more prominent figure in Illinois legislation in the last decade than this Chicago attorney. Along with the anti-children's crime law and the woman's guardianship law the Juul measure has done much to place Illinois on a favorable basis as compared <pb facs="5420780_1_0790.jpg" n="2"/>with other progressive states.</p>
   <p>Mr. Juul came to Chicago thirty-one years ago, while not in his teens, from Denmark,where he was born. He at once took up the study of law, and was admitted to the bar in 1898. The caliber of his legal mind was soon shown, and he was made assistant attorney for the Sanitary Board, which position he still holds. In 1899 he went in for politics, and was elected to the State Senate on the Republican ticket. He was reelected in 1902, 1904 and again in 1910.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
