<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1903-08-01">Aug. 1, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">[City Government Faithful to Capitalistic Masters]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0606</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0606.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1903-08-01">Aug. 1, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">[CITY GOVERNMENT FAITHFUL TO CAPITALISTIC MASTERS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(EDITORIAL)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2......In 1893 the Chicago City Council adopted an ordinance, making it compulsory for the railroads to elevate all crossings in the city, the ordinance becoming effective on January 1, 1899. After this date each crossing which had not been elevated, was subject to a fine.</p>
   <p>The socialistic Alderman Wm. Johnson has called attention to this ordinance, and pointed out that there are still 1200 railroad crossings which have not been elevated, and that the fines now would amount to $394,080,000. Mr. Johnson introduced a resolution to the effect that the city start proceedings to collect this amount from the roads. The resolution was buried in one of the many committees, the newspapers maintained silence, and the railroads continue killing people, and flaunting the law without the slightest interference.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0607.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A similar fate overtook a resolution introduced by Mr. Johnson at the last meeting of the City Council to the effect that the police remain neutral during strikes and lockouts as long as no violence takes place; furthermore, that the police refrain from interfering with strikers peaceful attempt to make non-striking workers join them in their fight for better working conditions. The partisan police, and the brutal employment of clubs and revolvers to break strikes, caused Mr. Johnson to present this resolution. But not one of the democratic or republican "friends of labor" in the city council supported this demand for simple justice, in spite of the fact that the present administration owes its existence to the labor vote.</p>
   <p>The resolution was buried in a committee; Mayor Harrison and his police, and the daily newspapers continue to serve the interests of their masters and thus everything is shipshape.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
