<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1932-02-05">Feb. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Mock Heroes</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0198</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0198.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1932-02-05">Feb. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">MOCK HEROES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All that glitters is not gold. True indeed; and so, too, all that win fame are not heroes. The world today is too full of hero worshippers. It is high time to smash a few pedestals and recognize that many haloes are but tinsel. Most of our "heroes" are stuffed with sawdust sprinkled with the blood of their brothers.</p>
   <p>For instance, a great man dies. Great in the sense that he is a public figure of renown and esteem, a veritable paragon of success, a captain of industry,--in short, a millionaire. Unlimited eloquence is squandered by the press who laud him for his prowess in amassing a fortune. Editorials from coast to coast expatiate on the results of his ambition, his superb initiative, his rise from a lowly position.</p>
   <p>Does he deserve this homage and praise? Is this wealth he has accumulated really his? Is any man, for that matter, worth a million? Is he a success <pb facs="5420780_1_0199.jpg" n="2"/>in any respect other than having attained a position in the financial realm? No, it doesn't require higher mathematics to figure out that a fortune running into seven, eight, or nine figures has been obtained by other than predatory business methods, too clever and subtle to be called fraudulent. Such fortunes have been amassed by exploitation of underpaid employees.</p>
   <p>Ambition is an asset; initiative is praise-worthy; one should always strive to forge ahead, to progress and to better his status. We grant that. But the right kind of ambition and success is not for individual gain; a truly famous man obliterates ego and endeavors to better the entire human family and raise its standard to a higher level. Our "heroes," however, have only served to impede rather than to ameliorate the current of the stream flowing toward real civilization.</p>
   <p>When a man, who has become a Croesus through the hard labor of thousands of men under his control, leaves a sum to charity, or endows a hospital, or establishes a public park, or sponsors a library, has he settled his debt to society? No, a thousand times, no! He is only returning a small pittance of what rightly belong to the exploited, in such a way that he will be applauded.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0200.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He is not a benefactor as long as he leaves a large estate, earned by multitudes who remain the miserable robot of industry, not to those who earned it, but to private interests.</p>
   <p>Fools that we are, we lose sight of these factors and follow the herd in hallowing the name of a mere mortal who puts himself above the masses. Meanwhile, ethics and brotherly-love remain only words, not deeds, and become covered with dust from lack of usage. Will we ever wake up? Will we always be blinded by high-sounding phrases and the desire to cheer, and the human penchant to worship a hero?</p>
   <p>Our financiers may be powerful, intelligent, "successful" (from a monetary point of view), but they are not heroes. "Go down to the dust from whence they sprung, unwept, unhonored and unsung."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
