<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-12-21">Dec. 21, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Stock Jugglers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-12-21">Dec. 21, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE STOCK JUGGLERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The U. S. Congress is again conducting one of its many and, as a rule, useless investigations of questionable practices in public affairs.</p>
   <p>This time the investigation deals with the "money trust," and the swindling in stocks which is going on in our financial centers, and which is particularly prevalent on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
   <p>The most surprising facts are brought to light. As an example, it may be mentioned that all the shares in one of the country's biggest railroad companies are being "turned over" are changing hands, at least once a month. This is, of course, only a paper transaction, just as when a speculator buys or sells a million bushels of wheat in the pit. A large profit goes to the brokers, who collect their commission whether the <pb facs="5420780_1_0369.jpg" n="2"/>prices go up or down. But the real profiteers are the big operators, who control enough capital to manipulate the market, buying when prices are low, and selling when they are high, while the "small fry" loses his shirt.</p>
   <p>Speculation and financial gambling have always flourished, and will keep on flourishing under our capitalistic system, but could not exist in a socialistic state.</p>
   <p>There is no stock in the U.S. Post Office or in municipally owned water-works, street railways, etc., and bonds issued by municipalities for the financing of various public works are not subject to great fluctuations, and are therefore of small interest to the speculator.</p>
   <p>In a socialistic society, the much acclaimed "private initiative" will not be permitted to exploit humanity, but there will be ample opportunity to work for the common good and to practice the golden rule.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
