<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1932-06-17">June 17, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">America's Need for Co-Operation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1932-06-17">June 17, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICA'S NEED FOR CO-OPERATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The present crisis is the worst in many years. Those who think that prosperity will soon return and that everything will be normal again within a few months, fool themselves. This depression may pass; but another and a far worse one is sure to appear before very long.</p>
   <p>The present social order, or disorder, cannot function without these terrible upheavals, so detrimental to the welfare of the American people.</p>
   <p>Many are beginning to think that unless our present capitalistic system undergoes some drastic changes, we shall in a few years be faced with anarchy and complete demoralization in the economic world. One thing is certain, our capitalistic system does not even function nowadays. If it did, there could not be eight million people out of work, and <pb facs="5420780_1_0298.jpg" n="2"/>some thirty-two million people in dire need in this the richest country in the world, as far as material wealth is concerned.</p>
   <p>It is time for the Government to consider the welfare and simple civil rights of those millions of long neglected human beings we call the American people. If no constructive measures are carried out in Washington soon, this nation will face civil war. The depression eats deeper and deeper into the marrow of the people, and nothing is done about it. American citizens of Danish descent have a peculiar task in these times, in demonstrating that co-operation is a better principle than competition, that confidence goes farther than fear, and that the principle of co-operation which saved Denmark from economic annihilation can bring results to America just as it did in Denmark.</p>
   <p>America must try new ways in the future, and there is much to learn from Denmark's co-operative institutions. American citizens of Danish descent should never fail to demonstrate the inherent value of adopting principles <pb facs="5420780_1_0299.jpg" n="3"/>of co-operation, where other measures have proven futile and disastrous. The American people must learn to co-operate. The "rugged individualism" principle has proved a failure.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
