<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende</title><date when="1925-06-12">June 12,1925</date>.
<title level="a">Presidential Election in Carpenter's Union.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0238</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0238.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title><date when="1925-06-12">June 12,1925</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION IN CARPENTER'S UNION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Saturday, June 13, between 1 and 6 P.M. Chicago Carpenter's Union, consisting of seventy locals, with a total membership of 28,500, will hold its annual election of officers.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harry Jensen has been president of the union for the past four years, and judging from his record, he should be entitled to all Scandinavian votes from Cook and Lake Counties.</p>
   <p>His countrymen, in particular, want him re-elected because Harry is a good Dane and a skilled organizer. Nobody ever asked Harry Jensen for assistance without getting, it insofar as circumstances permitted.</p>
   <p>During the years of Harry Jensen's presidency, the membership of the union has increased from 18,000 to 25,500, and all the locals are in good financial standing.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0239.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Working conditions have been favorable, so everybody was working despite the fact that the union has quarrelled continuously with a committee of citizens who sponsored the notorious "Landis Award."</p>
   <p>Harry Jensen has fought that movement with all the forces at his command. The Carpenter's Union has a good reputation and its officers words have been as good as their signatures.</p>
   <p>Charles H. Sand, (Swedish) secretary and treasurer, is also up for reelection. Mr. Sand has worked hand in hand with Harry Jensen in efforts to make Chicago Carpenter's Union the best organization of its kind in the United States. Mr. Sand, too, deserves the vote of every Scandinavian member.</p>
   <p>The office of the union has recently moved to 12 East Erie Street. The building has cost around $300,000, every dollar paid by voluntary contributions. It is said to be the finest union building in the United States, and the pride of every member.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
