<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-06-25">June 25, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Thornum for Commissioner</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0715</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0715.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Swedish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-06-25">June 25, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">THORNUM FOR COMMISSIONER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is generally believed that a change in the personnel of the civil service commission will take place upon the expiration of the terms of the present commissioners. Robert Lindblom [Swede] has stated repeatedly that he does not desire a re-appointment, and rumors of other changes have been current. Assuming that the mayor will be called upon to fill at least one vacancy by the appointment of a Democrat, the name of Peter J. Thornum [Dane] has been suggested as a fitting choice. Mr. Thornum is a West Sider, which certainly under the circumstances ought to be a strong point in his favor. He is a sturdy Democrat who has ever been ready to fight the battles of his party, never yielding or compromising, always striking straight from the shoulder. He is fearless and aggressively honest at all times, a man of sturdy backbone of the very kind that a civil service commissioner needs. He is the unanimous choice of the Scandinavian Democratic Central Club of Chicago for the position, <pb facs="5420780_1_0716.jpg" n="2"/>and it may be added that the Scandinavians in general, without regard to party affiliations, would approve of his appointment as a civil service commissioner.</p>
   <p>The management of Democratic politics in this bailiwick is not the concern of this paper. But the Skandinaven takes pleasure in testifying to the worth of a fellow citizen than whom no better Democrat is to be found in these parts, and whose character and honesty are valued most highly by those who know him best. Mayor Harrison would make no mistake by appointing Peter Thornum as Robert Lindblom's successor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
