<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1903-02-07">Feb. 7, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">[Hearst Wants a Big Navy]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0615</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0615.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1903-02-07">Feb. 7, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">[HEARST WANTS A BIG NAVY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(EDITORIAL)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2......Build a mighty navy, is the slogan of the Hearst papers, who are crazily patriotic as soon as there is the slightest possibility of an "international dog fight," as a result of the opposing capitalistic interests of the old and the new world, as is the case in Venezuela at the present time.</p>
   <p>Build a navy, powerful enough to whip the rest of the world, and we shall have peace, says the Examiner. The same argument is offered as an alibi for the great standing armies in Europe. A war ship is as much an instrument of murder as a cannon. Both are remnants from a barbaric period, and exist now only for the use of the capitalists in their projects of exploitation outwards as well as inwards, of the proletariat. What if the German Kaiser, for a while, is acting up in Venezuela; we do not have to see red and arm to the teeth. As to Germany, the German social democracy will probably in the near <pb facs="5420780_1_0616.jpg" n="2"/>future take care of both the Kaiser and his war craze, and as far as our own country is concerned, we should certainly serve its interests, and further the well being of our people better, by spending millions of dollars, not on Men-of-War, but on useful public improvements, or for the betterment of living conditions of our old people, for our sick and poor, and the children of the poor. We might even spend them for the dessimanation of the ideas of the brotherhood of socialism, by means of which, what remains of the animal nature in humanity, shall eventually be banished from the earth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
