<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende</title>,
<date when="1925-07-17">July 17, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Our Interest in History</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-07-17">July 17, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">OUR INTEREST IN HISTORY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In recent years Denmark has attracted the attention of a great number of people interested in social development. From all over the world students and representative groups come to study the social system in Denmark.</p>
   <p>There is nothing unusual, however, in the fact that a small country thus points the way for greater countries. In ancient Greece, of which the culture reached its peak more than two thousand years ago, art and architecture developed to a degree of beauty and perfection which has remained unsurpassed up to this very day. The works of the old Greek philosophers are still standard subjects of study in all our higher educational institutions, not on account of their antiquity but on account of their actual value for people nowadays who try to understand life's problems.</p>
   <p>Tiny Palestine, squeezed in between two mighty empires which alternately threatened her very existence, produced philosophers whose recorded spiritual <pb facs="5420780_1_0262.jpg" n="2"/>experiences are significant to humanity even at present; and with regard to religion the world of today cannot safely ignore the importance of the incidents which occurred in that little country nineteen hundred years ago.</p>
   <p>Thus small countries have taken the lead of larger ones and have been examples for them. They are capable of doing so today also, despite the popular idea that only that which is secularly great is of any importance.</p>
   <p>However, Denmark is not leading in the fields of art and architecture, nor is she famous for her spiritual contributions to civilization, although she has produced things of great value in these domains.</p>
   <p>It is the co-operative movement for which she has become so famous that statesmen and highly educated people from other countries find their way to her shores. It is the ability to co-operate and the unfailing knack of making a success of co-operation that make strangers wonder what the secret really is. The secret, if there is one, would be valuable because it has proved a necessity for people <pb facs="5420780_1_0263.jpg" n="3"/>of modern civilization to work in unity if they are to avoid class hatred and serious struggles between classes.</p>
   <p>Some time ago an American newspaperman came to me seeking some information about the co-operative movement in Denmark. He had an idea that there was some sort of connection between the Folk High Schools and the co-operative system, but just how it worked he did not know. Naturally he thought that co-operation was taught as a subject in the schools, and he wanted to describe the procedure of such instruction, which supposedly was for the purpose of starting the younger generation on the road to co-operative success.</p>
   <p>He was greatly surprised to learn that Danish Folk High Schools do not teach co-operation as a subject at all. They do not do so because the technical part of co-operative organization is comparatively easy to manage. There are always experts who are capable of handling that. The main obstacle to the success of co-operative enterprise is a spiritual obstacle. Co-operation is possible only for these people who feel that they have something in common which they <pb facs="5420780_1_0264.jpg" n="4"/>love and want to protect. That feeling of the existence of a common object and of mutual responsibility has been fostered by the Folk High Schools by means of appealing to the pupils' interest in history.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
