<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende</title>,
<date when="1925-09-18">Sept. 18, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Graft</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0821</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0821.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-09-18">Sept. 18, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">GRAFT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>King of the underworld, booze and beer runner Terry Druggan is supposed to be serving a sentence in a Chicago prison at the present time; but the "punishment" has taken on the appearance of a picnic.</p>
   <p>Of course Terry paid for the privileges he enjoyed, and the newspapers have been busy discovering who has received the graft. It did not take long to arrive at a conclusion.</p>
   <p>$60,000 was the price Druggan paid for the privilege of walking in and out to visit his "dentist," in whose office he conducted his sinister business.</p>
   <p>There has been some tension at police headquarters. One of the boys could not stand the heat and squealed so that a whole gang of high officials and prominent politicans had their summer vacation in Northern Wisconsin and elsewhere ruined, because they had to come home and try to check the scandal before too many incriminating facts had been revealed.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0822.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And of course they succeeded. Already the next day all talk about federal investigation committees had vanished completely, and so had rumors about the State's Attorney's promise to indict all the public officials implicated.</p>
   <p>The six or seven scoundrels who took the $60,000.00 in payment for breaking the laws they have been paid for guarding and enforcing went unharmed; presumably now plotting a new and better "case."</p>
   <p>By now they ought to have been on their way to the penitentiary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
