<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-09-07">Sept. 7, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Bryan's Candidacy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0527</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0527.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-09-07">Sept. 7, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">BRYAN'S CANDIDACY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>William Jennings Bryan, of Nebraska, is interested in the presidential candidacy for the coming election and has made a statement to the effect that government ownership of railroads is not an "immediate issue." After his return from Europe last year, at a meeting in New York he declared himself wholeheartedly in favor of government ownership, and said that he thought there was a growing belief in all parties that such ownership would be justified. However, his statements caused such a shower of protests from members of his own party that he was on the verge of losing his candidacy, so he is now trying to modify his utterances.</p>
   <p>Bryan is a genuine opportunist. Instead of using his valuable gifts to fight for what he thinks is right, he is concentrating his efforts on catching votes and on increasing the value of his own personal political stock. Not finding sufficient "growing belief" inside his own party, he dropped it at once, anticipating something else for an issue.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0528.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A more Sutstanding politician than Bryan would have met the protests by sticking to his statements and letting the party split up if it wanted to. But Bryan is not one of that type. A good many common people, who never aspired to become President or in any other way were interested in political honors, are acting exactly like Bryan by accepting whatever is available, regardless of principles.</p>
   <p>In fact, only the Socialists maintain a political ideal for which they stand firmly, belief or no belief, regardless of whether Socialism is the main issue today or tomorrow or ten or twenty years in the future. If the issue is amended it is not done for the purpose of gaining votes, but because such a change is in harmony with certain principles, and the present situation. The policy of the party may occasionally be opportunist, but not to the extent of modifying either its goal or its basic principles.</p>
   <p>Socialists do not specialize in taking advantage of a "growing belief" or a temporary fad; they are therefore, an absolute contrast to W. J. Bryan and the lesser Bryanites.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
