<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-01-13">Jan. 13, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Political Balancing Act</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0393</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0393.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-01-13">Jan. 13, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLITICAL BALANCING ACT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With particular reference to ex-President Roosevelt and his latest attack on the courts, the Daily Socialist in a recent issue commented as follows:</p>
   <p>"The politician seeks to get or hold office. To that end he endeavors to do two things: First, to secure the approval of those business interests that today dominate the political machinery of the Republican and Democratic parties. Without that approval he can not win recognition within those parties.</p>
   <p>"Second, to champion enough proposed laws of a supposedly progressive or radical character to secure the votes of a sufficient number of people to elect him, without going so far that he will lose the support of the afore-said <pb facs="5420780_1_0394.jpg" n="2"/>business interests, that are able to control the political machinery to which he is subservient.</p>
   <p>"To maintain the proper balance between these two extremes, is the chief concern of the politician."</p>
   <p>This very illustrative word-picture of a politician implies that while the public is being duped by radical politicians, the latter, as a rule, are in close touch with the big business interests, winking their eye in that direction, as was the case with Roosevelt, who during one of his campaigns against "wealthy wrongdoers," confered secretly with Harriman, assuring him that "you and I are practical men."</p>
   <p>It thus becomes evident that the balance between the two sides is not quite <pb facs="5420780_1_0395.jpg" n="3"/>stable, and one of the important tasks of politicians of the Roosevelt type is to prevent the people from getting wise to the trickery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
