<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-12-28">Dec. 28, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[Roosevelt's Humbug Reforms]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0489</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0489.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-12-28">Dec. 28, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[ROOSEVELT'S HUMBUG REFORMS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The capitalists have made President Roosevelt the object of a series of severe attacks, but we fear these attacks have been prearranged in the effort to bluff an unsuspecting public and an imbecile mob. Despite much noise and confusion, Roosevelt has not bothered the capitalists to any extent or interfered in the least with their system. Of course it is possible for the most faithful servant to get in wrong with his masters and be blamed instead of rewarded. Once in a while criticisms such as the following are obviously made in earnest:</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0490.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A Justice of the U. S. Supreme Court blamed Roosevelt for "playing the game of hide-and-seek with the American people." Chancellor Day of the University of Syracuse, N. Y., said that "one of the most serious aspects of the present administration's position, in relation to prevailing economic disturbances, is the fact that Mr. Roosevelt has not instituted any actual reforms. He has not sent any of the violators to prison. He has done nothing to improve the conditions which he himself has so severely criticised. All he has done is to incite the public and instigate a state of fear and unrest.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0491.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In fact, public attention has been further diverted from the real source of economic evils."</p>
   <p>The above statements coincide remarkably with the point of view maintained by the socialists that Roosevelt's reforms are plain humbug.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
