<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-01-28">Jan. 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Government Ownership of Railroads]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-01-28">Jan. 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[GOVERNMENT OWNERSHIP OF RAILROADS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.col.1........."Let the nation own the railroads and the postal clerks will have a chance to live and to get decent treatment and full pay"says the "Daily Socialist."</p>
   <p>We heartely agree with the foregoing statement - but - what would then become of the poor aristocrats who are living on the fat of the land spending railroad dividends that in 1909 amounted to $450,000,000. Imagine if you can, what a catastrophy it would be if these "blood suckers" should suddenly be deprived of their unworked-for luxuries and insult were added to injury by making them step out and do something useful and constructive in order to obtain the necessities of life. Unthinkably Cruel!</p>
   <p>Or imagine that these 450 millions were distributed justly among those who do the actual work on the railroads, trainmen, maintenance men, office workers and supervisors. Or a part of this amount could be used for general relief and welfare work thereby making life a little brighter for many now underpriveleged.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0428.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is terrifying to contemplate what ruin and devastation such a diversion of million would create in our family and religious life; what a demoralizing effect this one act of Socialism would have. If other monopolies were handled in the same manner life (in the opinions of the Capitalistic tyrants) would be unbearable.</p>
   <p>We, of the Socialistic faith, are an ungrateful conglomeration of selfishness, jealousy, independence and narrow-mindedness that find it impossible to be content and accept the dictates of the Capitalistic lackeys and defenders, editors, teachers, Roosevelts and preachers who want us to be humble servants even looking forward to the ultimate reward in the life hereafter.</p>
   <p>Even a worm will turn and eventually our working class will be so fed up on tyrany, wage-slavery and want that they will awaken and make the present minority party (Socialist) the vast majority party whose principles calls for honest dealing and a decent standard of living for every man.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
