<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1925-05-08">May 8, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavian Meeting</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0056</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <!--                        <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1.b"/> -->
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <!--                        <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1.b"/> -->
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0056.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II A 1 b (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>III B 4 (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>II A 1 b (Swedish)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d (Swedish)</item>
     <item>III B 4 (Swedish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1925-05-08">May 8, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIAN MEETING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4........The Society for Promotion of Scandinavian held its 15th Annual Meeting Friday and Saturday, May 1, and 2, at the University of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The "Society" with members throughout the nation, published a periodical containing articles dealing largely with the older and newer Scandinavian literature.</p>
   <p>At many of our universities, particularly in the Middle-West, the study of Scandinavian languages and literature is carried on and quite a number of well-known men of learning are engaged in this work.</p>
   <p>During the war the time was rather inopportune for the study of foreign languages as a whole, and a lack of interest was noted at all universities. However, the work was not abandoned, and a greatly increased interest in the study of the Scandinavian languages and literature is expected in the near future.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0057.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Several articles on literary and linguistic questions was read at the meeting.</p>
   <p>Professor Sturtevant of the University of Kansas, had written an article on Bjonrson's: The Hands of Mother," Professor Henning Larsen from Iowa University presented his work on an old Icelandic Document, which contained the oldest Nordic book on medicine. He proved that it dated back to the year 1450.</p>
   <p>Professor Rolvaag gave a resume of the Norwegian Author Hamsun's work "The Great Hunger," the conclusion of which from a critics point of view, he found unsatisfactory.</p>
   <p>Professor Mauritzon from Augustana College spoke on the poems in Victor Rydberg's: The Weapon Smith," and Professor Flom from Illinois University spoke on "Forbidden Words."</p>
   <p>Two interesting and enjoyable days were spent. Particularly enjoyable was the Public Dinner Friday evening, spiced with songs and speeches.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0058.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One of the "Societie's" traditions is a Song Evening, and under the direction of Pastor Dorf, many Danish, Norwegian and Swedish songs were sung from the High School Song Book.</p>
   <p>Professor Eivar Joranson from the University of Chicago and Pastor Dorf sang a few of the well-known "Gluntar," and Miss Karen Bruce played several of Grieg's compositions.</p>
   <p>It was a genuine Scandinavian evening, and the American Professor sang with enough zest and enthusiasm to put a Scandinavian gathering in the back ground.</p>
   <p>If any one wishes to support the Scandinavian studies in our universities, they should join our Society. Annual dues are one Dollar and should be sent to Professor J.J. Alexis at the University of Nebraska, who will forward membership cards as well as our "Paper."</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0059.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>At Chicago University, Professor J. N. Gould has charge of the study of Scandinavian Languages and Literature. He has traveled extensively through the Scandinavian country and knows Old Norse as well as modern Scandinavian literature as few others do.</p>
   <p>The University has under consideration several plans for the extension of this work. In order to do this a fund must be established, from which a Professor can be paid as well as the aquisition of a library.</p>
   <p>A committee representing the different people with this language group, has been appointed, and whose object it is to try to arouse interest for this cause.</p>
   <p>Here is a golden opportunity for some of our wealthy countrymen to lend a helping hand.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
