<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-01-27">Jan. 27, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Wilson and Harper's Weekly]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-01-27">Jan. 27, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[WILSON AND HARPER'S WEEKLY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is rather a peculiar incident that Governor Woodrow Wilson of New Jersey, who has been picked to succeed William J. Bryan as progressive democratic presidential candidate, found it necessary to break with Harper's Weekly.</p>
   <p>It was this Weekly which originally "discovered" Wilson, and so far has supported him strongly. In prompt response to the charges, the paper does not at all attempt to hide the fact that it belongs to J. P. Morgan and Company and Wall Street, "soul and body."</p>
   <p>This admission may prove to be dangerous to Wilson's candidacy. Both the old political parties are controlled by powerful financial interests, but this fact was conspicuously guarded as a secret. "The people" were not supposed to be aware of this. Now, Harper's Weekly has put the cards on the table, thereby breaking the rules of the game.</p>
   <p>It is not unlikely that the whole thing is a political show, arranged behind the scenes, in perfect understanding between the apparently disagreeing parties.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0390.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Harper's Weekly, in order to help Wilson, may have been forced to make an attack on him. Theodore Roosevelt was a master in the art of subjecting himself to severe public attacks and at the same time, he was friendly with his attackers. It has been maintained that Roosevelt is another favorite of Morgan as a presidential candidate, therefore, he has instructed several of his papers to attack him. Everything is possible for the capitalists and the politicians, who have been able to fool the people a great deal longer than Lincoln ever thought probable.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
