<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-07-22">July 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Capitalism and Socialism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-07-22">July 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">CAPITALISM AND SOCIALISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2...Our present ruling despots are inclined to use the same methods as their predecessors. They are trying to stop progress by force, by legislation, law breaking, police clubs and rifles, as they have always done. They have forgotten nothing, learned nothing. They fail to appreciate the import of one essential fact, that we have now reached the bottom of society. It is no longer the middle class, but the lower class that is fighting for its life; it is the united working class of all countries that is fighting for existence. It comprises nine-tenth of humanity, which, as wage earners, have common interests. The urge of self-preservation, with all its powers, together with a clear scientific understanding of the economic demands of our time fuse them into one powerful international organization. Agitation and education are being promoted on a larger scale. We have kindergartens and schools for children, and schools and high schools for adults, such as the Rand School of Social Science. We have street meetings, and lectures in our <pb facs="5420780_1_0418.jpg" n="2"/>auditoriums. The work is progressing, steadily and systematically. We have the most gifted and zealous lecturers in the country, men like Russel, Irvine, Debs and Spargo. The ablest journalists, the most famous authors, and the greatest scientists belong to us. And above all, we have the workers themselves. They are the ones that carry the movement, personifying its strength and vitality. The fact that we have succeeded in electing a mayor and several aldermen in a great city like Milwaukee, and that we have been victorious in a score of smaller cities all over the country is not the real reason for the capitalistic wrath.</p>
   <p>The sure hold we have on the man in the street, and the united change of front of the voting masses - this is what is filling their hearts with fear and rage. The realization that this is not a planless, passing resentment over injustices suffered, but a planned, permanent monument, toward a definite goal, the destruction of the wage and profit system, has been scared to death.</p>
   <p>Our newspapers and periodicals are enjoying an ever increasing distribution. Appeal to Reason now has more than half a million subscribers. The power <pb facs="5420780_1_0419.jpg" n="3"/>and influence wielded through these media are beginning to be felt. Workers, in increasing numbers, are deserting capitalism and its press, its courts and its churches with their hypnotic and pharisaical preachings, and their satisfaction with conditions as they are. The stranglehold which these institutions have had on the masses for ages is beginning to slip, and this makes them furious.</p>
   <p>They are looking at the beginning of the end and it is dawning on them that this means the destruction of their grafting system.</p>
   <p>Final destruction, "Ragnarok" (Norse Mythology), is staring them in the face, and they know there is no salvation for them, because we are in step with the logical trend of social evolution. The future is ours: Hitch your wagon to a star!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
