<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1914-06-27">June 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Poor Business</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1914-06-27">June 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">POOR BUSINESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to The Party Builder, the total receipts of the national office of the Socialist Party were $10,671.56 for the month of May, while expenditures were $12,002.40, and the total liabilities were $16,546.73.</p>
   <p>In trying to find the cause for such a deficit and such liabilities (many of which have been carried for years), some comrades might look at the account of the "foreign department," $970 having been paid to ten translator-secretaries most of them getting $19 a week or $95 a month.</p>
   <p>According to another Party Builder, dated May 23, 1914, only five of the foreign federations had more than one thousand members each, and the rest <pb facs="5420780_1_0335.jpg" n="2"/>had been causing the national office a loss of $2,833 since January 1, 1913.</p>
   <p>If it were not for the Finnish federation, with more than fourteen thousand members, there would be an actual loss of wages, not counting the rent and other incidentals.</p>
   <p>Is this worthwhile? Are the foreign federations showing results that warrant such large monthly and yearly subsidies from the party?</p>
   <p>To take an example, our own federation, composed of the Swedish, Norwegian, and Danish nationalities has now a total membership of 921 against 834 a year ago. The increase is 77 members. To get this the national <pb facs="5420780_1_0336.jpg" n="3"/>office pays each year about one thousand dollars in wages to a secretary-translator and gets less than half paid in dues! This is after the federation has been in existence about four years and it certainly should be in good working order if it ever will be!</p>
   <p>Without doubt most of the 921 members mentioned above have been, or would have been, members of Scandinavian or English-speaking branches of the party even if the federation or its salaried official had not existed, and consequently the net result of good for the party is even less than indicated by the small total membership of 921 and the net increase in one whole year of 77.</p>
   <p>The same can be said of the other small foreign federations which are not, <pb facs="5420780_1_0337.jpg" n="4"/>and never will become, even self-supporting.</p>
   <p>The conclusion is that most of this whole foreign federation system has been a mistake, a handicap to the party, and should be remedied - the sooner, the better.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
