<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-12-16">Dec. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A Rotten Affair</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0396</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0396.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-12-16">Dec. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A ROTTEN AFFAIR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the darkest chapters in the history of the American labor movement has been written through the unexpected confession by the McNamara brothers of the crimes of which they have been accused. When they were arrested about half a year ago, for having, among other things, occasioned the explosion in the Los Angeles Times building in which half a dozen people were killed, organized labor and the Socialists took their side without hesitation, not only because they were considered entirely innocent, but especially because they were kidnapped illegally by the authorities in one state, and put in jail in another state. The chief attorney of the accused ones, Clarence Darrow, now reveals that from the very first he knew that the brothers were guilty, and that his goal has only been to save them <pb facs="5420780_1_0397.jpg" n="2"/>from the gallows. During all this, the labor unions and the socialists have collected a defence fund of about $200,000, the greater part of which has passed through Mr. Darrow's hands or into his pockets. Without scruples he has accepted and used this money although he knew it was obtained under false pretences, and that no considerable part of the amount would have been contributed for the defence of two plain criminals.</p>
   <p>Clarence Darrow has, in time past done good service for the labor class without, however, closing his eyes to the amount in it for Mr. Darrow. In the present case, his expensive labor has been of doubtful value because through open confessions at the time of their arrest the accused ones would no doubt have obtained as mild a degree of punishment as under the deal now arranged to the trumpets of capitalism.</p>
   <p>The fact that the confessions came just at the present moment is no doubt <pb facs="5420780_1_0398.jpg" n="3"/>due to the calculations by the authorities and the capitalists as to the immediate influence thereof on the election in Los Angeles where the Socialists might be considered as practically having the victory in their hands. On this point the calculations proved well considered. But the Socialists do not need to worry over this. The McNamara scandal, of course, did not keep a single Socialist from voting for the party's candidates. If the scandal had not been there and the Socialists had won, it would have been by the aid of non-Socialist votes, and a victory obtained in such manner is of doubtful value. We can afford to wait, and after all, 40,000 Socialists votes is a worth while basis on which to build.</p>
   <p>For that matter, the Socialists may well wash their hands of this whole matter. Aside from a handful of revolutionists or anarchists, calling for direct action, the task of the Socialists is to improve the conditions of the workers through political activity and gradual parliamentary reconstruction of the present system. The pure and simple labor union movement <pb facs="5420780_1_0399.jpg" n="4"/>on the other hand has no such ideal, or on the whole any other means to use except strikes and boycotts. When these fail, when the capitalists, by means of servile law makers, police officers and other means of action, oppress the workers more and more, while at the same time the leaders of these workers fraternize with the employers, prattling about harmony between labor and capital, then, of course, there may always be found such within the ranks, as will be tempted to use the tactics of despair which so often find expression here in America, and which was employed by the McNamara brothers. There is every reason to believe that the capitalist class prefers these tactics, even coupled with destruction and murder, which at times the class undoubtedly helps to organize, rather than a fully class conscious and Socialist labor movement. The capitalists well know that such a movement is the only one which they need really to fear. This explains why it is that while all honest and sensible workers, and especially the Socialists, have taken a decided stand against the McNamaras, <pb facs="5420780_1_0400.jpg" n="5"/>some of the capitalist papers are about to make them heroes acting from noble motives; and it may be taken for granted that while they now will be living at the expense of the state, the state will see to it that they are taken well care of.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
