<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1933-10-20">Oct. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Brain Trust Folly</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1933-10-20">Oct. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">BRAIN TRUST FOLLY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Can wealth be created by destroying wealth? That, today, is the uppermost question confronting any thinking person caught in the clutches of our economic structure. Those who have been guided by false propaganda, whose brains, from lack of usage have become atrophied, might easily accept the gesture of the great Washington brain-trust as a panacea for our national ills. But those who have not entirely surrendered the individual right to think for themselves, take the food destroying program proposed by the dignitaries at the Capitol, as both contradictory and criminal.</p>
   <p>That it should be necessary to destroy two billion pounds of cotton, millions <pb facs="5420780_1_0291.jpg" n="2"/>of bushels of corn, as well as similar cuantities of wheat, and other commodities, to create wealth seems incredible as well as inhuman to any person. In fact, if such logic is the result of a highly trained academic mind, then those of us who have not been so exposed should thank our lucky stars for having escaped a college education.</p>
   <p>Until now, such destructive measures were interpreted as criminal, and those who perpetrated them were sent to jail or a madhouse. Today, such brilliant actions are rewarded by making the performers the counselors of the nation. As an illustration let us consider a glazier, who, in order to stimulate trade, takes these steps. One day he has suddenly found business dull, and has too much glass on hand. Accordingly, he hires thugs to destroy as many windows as possible. Then orders will begin to roll in, and be can get rid <pb facs="5420780_1_0292.jpg" n="3"/>of surplus stock at a profit. In the eyes of the world, not excluding our own government, his destructive tactics are criminal and punishable by law. If caught, he is put behind bars. Now Washington itself wants to fall into the category of racketeers and hoodlums. At least, the guilty glazier has paid his hirelings out of his own pocket, but the government pays for the destruction of crops with the taxpayers' money, the very taxpayer who is sadly in need of the food laid waste.</p>
   <p>It has been said that the spirit of today may become the reality of tomorrow. If that be true, then God help us! If it is right to waste and destroy perfectly good food by the billions of pounds today, at a time when it is needed by our own people, to say nothing of wretched people of other countries, then it might be equally right tomorrow, it we start to destroy bridges, <pb facs="5420780_1_0293.jpg" n="4"/>buildings, and other property, with a similar purpose. Maybe after we have succeeded in destroying everything, we will finish by destroying even ourselves.</p>
   <p>Certainly it would be more humane and reasonable--yet no more expensive, if our government would ship this surplus food to the starving countries of China and India for the cost of transportation. But why go elsewhere when we can do missionary work right at home. While thousands of children and good souls are starving, how can we sit back and firmly destroy food--for any theory whatsoever?</p>
   <p>If it be true that wealth can be created by destroying wealth, then how come that the war-ridden nations of Europe, whose structures were demolished, <pb facs="5420780_1_0294.jpg" n="5"/>crops destroyed and fields made sterile, and national resources diminished are not flourishing? This historical example, is all the more convincing because it is contemporary, and should suffice to show even a brain-trust the folly of such a course.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
