<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-11-13">Nov. 13, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Peace</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0846</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0846.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-11-13">Nov. 13, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">PEACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The noise of bells and factory whistles and the colorful decorations commemorating Armistice Day last Wednesday reminded us forcefully of the cold day in November seven years ago when the world resounded with the mighty and relieving word: Peace!</p>
   <p>That was the end of the great battle to save the world for democracy. Hundreds of thousands of young lives had been sacrificed, homes had been destroyed by the thousands, and billions of dollars worth of property had been ruined. With a blood-stained laurel wreath Uncle Sam retired from the earsplitting roar of Europe's battlefields.</p>
   <p>For those whose participation in the venture was limited to investment in <pb facs="5420780_1_0847.jpg" n="2"/>Liberty bonds, or to sharing the discomforts prevalent at home during the war, the memories are quickly vanishing. They celebrate Armistice Day and think no more about it.</p>
   <p>But in millions of homes in Europe and America sorrowing mothers fondle the pictures of their slain sons while their eyes are blinded with tears. No battle was ever won which mothers did not have to pay for--with the highest price that any one could demand.</p>
   <p>The whole world will have to suffer for this madness, maybe for a hundred years or more. And what was accomplished? Nothing! Oh, yes; maybe we shall have peace as long as the losing countries remain crushed, checked in their progress, and industrially paralyzed. Their resistance was broken in the nick of time because many of the so-called victors are on the verge of bankruptcy.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0848.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The great powers dictate the negotiations, sign treaties, and impose rules and regulations on the rest. We shall have peace for a couple of years, all right; but wait and see what will happen when the wounds inflicted on the defeated nations are healed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
