<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1918-08-24">Aug. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Why Replace a Loyal Congressman?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0737</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0737.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1918-08-24">Aug. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHY REPLACE A LOYAL CONGRESSMAN?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In less than ten days from now Congress will reconvene with business on hand of more importance than any since the Civil War. Every loyal member of experience will be of valuable service to his countrymen. The heart of America is one today. Party differences have been submerged in the national crisis as they have never been in our history--the Civil War and the American Revolution not excepted. "Well done, good and faithful servant," is more the prevailing sentiment than the question, Is he Democrat or Republican? The candidate for high office today stands not only, if at all, on party loyalty; he stands on American loyalty.</p>
   <p>That Niels Juul has performed his duty on every question appertaining to the affairs of the nation is not to be denied. He has not completed his first term [in office], but he has made his splendid individuality and devotion felt on every occasion when conscientious and fearless expression was required. Not only has he had the interests of his constituents at heart, but he <pb facs="5420780_1_0738.jpg" n="2"/>has been inspired in his speech and in his voting in the lower house of Congress by [his zeal for] the welfare of the people of the United States as a whole.</p>
   <p>Mr. Juul goes back to these councils with the single conscientious desire and purpose of fearlessly doing his best, unhampered by what is happening here at home in the Seventh Congressional District, where he has announced his candidacy for re-election. He has done his duty; he will continue to do it despite anything that may happen to his political career and his fortune.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
