<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende</title>,
<date when="1930-09-26">Sept. 26, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Rock Bottom-Where?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0201</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0201.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1930-09-26">Sept. 26, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">ROCK BOTTOM-WHERE?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every day our newspapers print glowing articles to reassure the public that the depression, which at the present is holding the entire nation in its grip, is on the wane. The public as a whole, being very optimistic, swallows these editorials hook, line, and sinker!</p>
   <p>But, in spite of these encouraging newspaper accounts, the truth is that prosperity is on the wane, and that we have not as yet reached rock bottom.</p>
   <p>All sorts of excuses are manufactured in order to justify existing conditions. The favorite reasons given are racketeering within the unions, the high cost of raw material, and the sudden reluctance on the part of the public to part with their hard-earned dollars.</p>
   <p>A few weeks ago, former President Coolidge, in one of his inspiring (?) articles, suggested, as a panacea, that people buy more freely in order to stimulate <pb facs="5420780_1_0202.jpg" n="2"/>big business and thus swing the pendulum back to prosperity. This remedy might be effective in places where money is plentiful, but only a very few individuals have the good fortune to be pushed into an editorial chair and to be presented with a yearly salary running into six figures. But even a former president should know that, with winter staring them in the face, the wage earners cannot afford to part with their last cent merely to help big business prosper even more.</p>
   <p>Another suggestion for saving the sinking ship is to refrain from cutting wages. Has this been done? Just ask the employees of our large department stores that are owned by big business about their pay envelopes. Their answers will convince even the most optimistic that "high" wages are nothing but editorial hokum.</p>
   <p>At the present time, the only people who are considered to receive a decent wage are those engaged in the building trade, and whenever the builders sign a contract they never fail to stress that point. But the contractor always forgets to mention the fact that, as a rule, part of the mechanic's Saturday check finds <pb facs="5420780_1_0203.jpg" n="3"/>its way back to the contractor's pocket the following Monday. If not, the worker will find himself minus a job.</p>
   <p>An example of the insincerity of this pretense of paying high wages is shown most clearly by the policy of the Southern Power Company, which is typical of many other large industries. "Come and get our cheap labor" is their sales cry. Nor do they fail to mention that "the labor laws of the State of Georgia are very liberal, since they permit sixty hours' work per week and contain no regulations as to the number of hours per day".</p>
   <p>As a result, this region has become a mecca for the captains of industry, and for the past five years, in North Carolina alone, factories have sprung up at the rate of one every few days. This sudden migration of our Northern industrial lords to the South, where labor is cheap and submissive, refutes the lies "dished out" to the unsuspecting public by all our "optimistic" editorial scribes, including Mr. Coolidge. But surely he, at least, should know the truth, since he resides in a state that was hit hardest by the sudden migration of numerous <pb facs="5420780_1_0204.jpg" n="4"/>textile factories to the South.</p>
   <p>This latest maneuver of our manufacturers proves conclusively that our so-called leaders of the nation do not have the welfare of the masses at heart. On the contrary, these industrial vampires, instead of trying to establish a fairly decent standard of living for the American worker, are interested only in the personal profit--and more profit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
