<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1933-11-03">Nov. 3, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Twilight of Civilization</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0838</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0838.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1933-11-03">Nov. 3, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">TWILIGHT OF CIVILIZATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today's civilization is on the verge of ruin. Unless a radical change of heart comes over the entire world, it will sink to a depth from which it may never recover. The Pollyannas,of course, refuse to take this statement seriously, but laugh it off with a pshaw, and a negative look into things. Consider, only a short while ago, when millions of young men, the very flower of the world's manhood, were dumped into the bosom of Mother Earth years before their time, while other millions, cheated of a premature grave, returned from the war maimed and disillusioned, cursing the day they were born. Did the War teach us anything? No indeed, a thousand time no! With our hands still stained with blood from the last struggle, we are again being shaped for further combat.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0839.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>About two thousand years ago, man started on the right path when the Occident adopted Christianity, and for a while, it actually looked as though man would turn his entire energies towards the road leading to brotherly love and kindness. But man's lofty aspirations were soon defeated by his stupidity in failing to wisely use his powers, and correctly harness his strength. For instance, we find that our inventive genius, today far more occupied with life destroying than lifesaving devices. We have perfected marvelous achievements in architecture, but on the other hand, make devices to destroy them, not unlike a foolish child who inflates a balloon to a glorious size and is not content till he bursts it.</p>
   <p>For instance, think of Robert Fulton, and his idea of a boat to be driven by steam power. This idea doubtless facilitated commerce, but the innocent looking sidewheeler of his dreams, thanks to man's ingenuity, has since developed into a floating fort whose cannons spatter and spray death inflicting <pb facs="5420780_1_0840.jpg" n="3"/>bullets whenever the occasion arises. If no occasion arises, we create an imaginary foe, usually a nation too weak to defend itself. Even worse than the battleship is the dreaded submarine.</p>
   <p>That man is still high-minded, is evidenced by the fleets of airships and bombing planes. Being piloted by good Christians, one would naturally think that their mission in the clouds would be a communication with loftier spirits supposed to inhabit those realms and from them receive inspiration to cease butchering of those on earth. This is not the case, but instead, a few well-directed bombs soon dispel such illusions, and we realize that the plane is used mainly for destruction. Man is indeed smart, so much so that he eventually outwits himself. Not content with building, we destroy, and naturally civilization suffers, and is going on the downgrade. In fact the "Zeitgeist," seems to indicate that our appetite for destruction will cease only after God himself has been dethroned by the ingenuity of man.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
