<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-03-02">Mar. 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Harrison Ignores Socialistis in Unemployment Investigation]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-03-02">Mar. 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[HARRISON IGNORES SOCIALISTIS IN UNEMPLOYMENT INVESTIGATION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Unemployment is a great problem at the present. According to information published by one of the city's public employment offices, there are 125,000 unemployed in Chicago alone, most of them able and willing to work. In New York, this number is said to be twice that figure.</p>
   <p>Conditions seems to be almost as desperate as they were during the Roosevelt panic or more so under the Cleveland administration.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0278.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To investigate the situation, Mayor Harrison has appointed a committee consisting of prominent business-men, university professors, and scientists, but not a single socialist is admitted as a member. The mayor seems not to be aware of the fact that the Socialist Party is the only political party whose aim it is to do away with unemployment and the causes responsible for that social evil, and that it becomes more and more evident that the defenders of capitalism are neither able nor willing to adjust conditions so that every man willing and able to work may have a job.</p>
   <p>But, of course, Mayor Harrison has his reasons for ignoring the socialists. As long as the majority of workers, whether idle or active, tolerate these abnormal conditions, and continue to vote for the persons responsible for <pb facs="5420780_1_0279.jpg" n="3"/>these deplorable conditions, then it would be useless to expect any different state of affairs.</p>
   <p>The situation will remain the same until the educational work sponsored by the Socialist Party has done away with stupidity and prejudices which in particular, are dominating American political life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
