<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-05-04">May 4, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[Roosevelt Changes Front on Moyer-Haywood Kidnapping]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0563</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0563.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-05-04">May 4, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[ROOSEVELT CHANGES FRONT ON MOYER-HAYWOOD KIDNAPPING]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Roosevelt's uncalled for condemnation of the two labor leaders held in Idaho on a criminal charge (but not convicted) has caused so much indignation that the President himself found it appropriate to come forward with an explanation which, by the way, did anything but justify his statement. On the contrary, it shows that the President is not only apt to commit a terrible blunder in a moment of anger but that he also is too stubborn, cowardly and dishonest to admit his mistakes, and therefore attempts to worm away from the incident by means of eccentric arguments and false statements, all in order to save his face.</p>
   <p>By arguing that the workers all over the country have taken sides with the accused men, he tries to hide his own mistake of joining their accusers. We would think that the workers of America, who sincerely believe in the innocence of their unfortunate trusted agents, should be free to make use of all legitimate means in order to save their comrades from the gallows <pb facs="5420780_1_0564.jpg" n="2"/>on which they most likely <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> irrespective of built or evidence, had act public opinion and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> be their rescue.</p>
   <p>The President did not mean to accuse the two men and declare them guilty of the crime, say he, but <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, "undesirable citizens," just the same. Why these <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> the rest of an the President does <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, and for good reasons, because Moyer and Haywood law pet be <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> of any ill gitimate action. But the fact that the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> authorities in Colorado have committed crimes and a still <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, that would but even the tyr any of the Russian <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, has <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> in court and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> by the President's own commisioner, Carroll, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> is assigned to the case. The kidnapping of Moyer and Haywood was but the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> of a tyranny long in existence about which even a Justice of the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> spoke in words not to be mistaken.</p>
   <p>But Mr. Roosevelt  does not find anything "undesirable" about the capitalistic tyrants roaming the hills and plains of Idaho and Colorado and terrorizing the <pb facs="5420780_1_0565.jpg" n="3"/>working class. They are of his kind and by is their faithful servant, which he has proved by his attitude in this case better than ever. But this very attitude on the part of the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>ent did also serve to open the eyes of the workers. The case, originally scheduled for the purpose of crushing the Western Federation of Miners, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> served to raise and strengthen the brotherly feeling among the workers of the nation in a most excellent way, and might turn out to be a bad boomerang for the capitalistic bosses and their hirelings throughout the country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
