<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-06-29">June 29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0546</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0546.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-06-29">June 29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our well-known countryman, druggist Ried. Knudsen of Brooklyn, wrote to Rasmussen's Ugebladet recently commenting on the subject of Socialism and addressing himself particularly to Mr. G. S. Strandvold, who toured the country giving poor lectures and complained of poor attendances. In the following issue appeared an "open letter," addressed to Mr. Knudsen by Mr. G. S. Strandvold who excelled in stupid remarks, etc. Mr. Knudsen sent the letter quoted below; but it was not printed because the Rasmussen papers are not organized for fair play and ought to be let alone by men of broad views on life:</p>
   <p>Dear Editor;</p>
   <p>"Common sense is what we need," says Mr. Strandvold. Yes, surely it is, my dear Mr. Strandvold, and that is exactly what we socialists want. By organizing a system of collective ownership we will create opportunities for better social conditions, intellectually and materially, so that people will not be tempted to "envy" their fellow-men and be "unreasonable" and "pretentious" in their demands about which you complain so much and blame Socialism.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0547.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is the aim of socialism to prevent such abuses and misconceptions and it has in it the means to do it. But do not confuse the means with the aim. Forget your old ideas and humdrum that resulted in nothing but empty High Schools and sleepy audiences. I advised you to study socialism for stimulation purposes, and you reject it without considering it.</p>
   <p>I asked you for something better if you had it, and you do not answer me.</p>
   <p>Surely I agree with you that common sense and intelligence is what we need.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours</p>
   <p>Rudolph Knudsen,</p>
   <p>Brooklyn, N. Y.,</p>
   <p>June 17, 1907.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
