<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-10-19">Oct. 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Roosevelt's Mission</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0778</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0778.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-10-19">Oct. 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">ROOSEVELT'S MISSION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whether Roosevelt's radical agitation since he was turned down by his own party, will have an accelerating or a retarding effect on the Socialistic movement, is anybody's guess. Some observers are of the opinion that he is unwittingly preparing the political soil for the Socialistic seed, while others see in him a false prophet whose mission it is to draw the people farther and deeper into the capitalistic quicksand and away from the promised land of Socialism.</p>
   <p>Regardless of the ultimate effect which his propaganda will have on our party's future, we consider it certain that Roosevelt's performance as a "radical" will deceive a great number of "liberals" who are disgusted with <pb facs="5420780_1_0779.jpg" n="2"/>the record of the old parties, and divert their votes from the Social-Democratic ticket.</p>
   <p>In reality, being deprived of such votes is no calamity for the party, which at its present stage of development is better off by receiving only those votes that reflect real Socialistic opinion and tradition.</p>
   <p>The immediate and more important result of the third party movement and Roosevelts candidacy will probably be the election of Wilson as the next president of the United States, thus giving the Democratic party, which lately has been considered doomed to a slow but sure death, a new lease on life for a shorter or longer time. No matter what happens to the Republicans and the "Bull-Moosers" at the coming election, for some time to come there will be two, possibly three, parties, frantically trying to keep the capitalistic mill going and to stem the Socialistic tide, which has steadily gained momentum during the last decade, when a feeble <pb facs="5420780_1_0780.jpg" n="3"/>and demoralized Democratic party has fought a losing battle against the reactionary Republicans in national politics.</p>
   <p>If Roosevelt now can revive the Democratic corpse and thus save a situation which is becoming increasingly dangerous for the capitalistic moguls, the large sums of money that are now being spent on him may truly be said to be a good investment from their point of view. Perkins and Company undoubtedly know what they are doing when they engage the greatest attraction of the political circus, the roaring lion, to perform for the voters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
