<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1918-08-24">Aug. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Niels Juul</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0739</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0739.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1918-08-24">Aug. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NIELS JUUL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What is the duty of his fellow citizens?</p>
   <p>Is it their duty to stand by the present efficient incumbent of the seat in Congress now so ably filled and to see that his nomination next month be made a certainty? Or is it their duty to listen to every self-seeking politician who, for one personal ambition or another, feels impelled to cry "Change!" and to try to secure the nomination that by every rule of right, equity, and justice should be Niels Juul's?</p>
   <p>It ought to be clear that the duty of every fair-minded citizen is to come out in the open and not only declare himself but put forth every effort to assure the nomination of Niels Juul on September 11, the day of the primaries.</p>
   <p>It is only fair that Mr. Juul should receive the opportunity of going back to his labors--and oh, how few but the initiated know how arduous are the labors of <pb facs="5420780_1_0740.jpg" n="2"/>every member of Congress today!--relieved of all care as to his political future.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, while this Congressman is preoccupied with momentous questions of state, is it fair that every politician who lusts for office should be permitted, unhampered by the presence of the man at Washington, to conduct his specious campaign against the candidate whose duties require him to renounce the presentation of his claims for a second term--a term which with his experience gained in the first will necessarily be far better and more efficient?</p>
   <p>American patriotism demands the re-election of men of the caliber of Niels Juul. Will the patriotism of the electorate of the Seventh Congressional District of the State of Illinois rise to the demand?</p>
   <p>It was the greatest Illinoisan who said, "Don't swap horses when crossing a stream". This homely truism still stands, more important and impressive now than when it was uttered, more than half a century ago.</p>
   <p>No great business establishment but heeds the warning uttered by Lincoln. No <pb facs="5420780_1_0741.jpg" n="3"/>commercial institution in a period of stress would think of losing the services of a tried and efficient employee for the simple reason that some other fellow felt impelled to seek the job. Why, at this time, in an era surcharged with questions of the highest importance to our national existence, when experience and capability, more than at any other period, are needed in our councils, should any voter with the good of his country at heart even dream of making a needless, foolish, and dangerous change, or of substituting ward politics for the highest statesmanship?</p>
   <p>To quote again the immortal Lincoln, from a speech made before his first election:</p>
   <p>"Let us have faith that right makes might, and in that faith let us dare to do our duty as we understand it."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
