<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1919-03-08">Mar. 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Dania Victory Tablet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_1_0863</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0863.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1919-03-08">Mar. 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DANIA VICTORY TABLET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dania Home Guards have decided to commemorate the services given by our boys during the War by presenting a Victory Tablet to each one who saw service in this country or overseas.</p>
   <p>It is a permanent, substantial, refined and elegant memento of his part and activity in the world war. It is made of bronze on a rich, dull finished mahogany base, the service star and allied flags enameled in colors, the inscription is etched throughout and the name plate is engraved. It contains nothing whatever suggesting the cheap or spectacular, and is designed and issued to the ideal it commemorates.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_1_0864.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The service flag has beautifully served its purpose, and we wish the victory tablet to take its place in every home of the boys whose parents are members of the Home Guards, or of Society Dania, or the Ladies' Society.</p>
   <p>The American people for generations to come will remember and point proudly to the part our boys played in winning the World War just as surely as gratitude and love of our country are engraved in their hearts.</p>
   <p>The Dania Home Guards are taking pride in presenting this memento, and we think we have reason to believe the boys will feel proud and honored by being remembered by the societies of their fathers and mothers.</p>
   <p>This memento will be ready for distribution on the evening when our Home <pb facs="5420780_1_0865.jpg" n="3"/>Reception will take place in Dania Hall, which will be announced at the proper time.</p>
   <p>Yours very truly,</p>
   <p>The Committee</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
