<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-05">Apr. 5, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to Polish Women in America on Behalf of the Lwow Exposition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1265</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1265.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-05">Apr. 5, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO POLISH WOMEN IN AMERICA ON BEHALF OF THE LWOW EXPOSITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are requested to publish the following communication: "On March 14, 1894, Section XIX (Women's Work Section) of the Lwow Exposition appointed me delegate for North America. I am instructed to furnish Section XIX with the following material:</p>
   <p>"1. Copies of diplomas and educational essays penned by Polish women.</p>
   <p>"2. Statistical records: a) a list of [the names] of Polish women attending American universities; b) a list of [the names of] Polish women who have received academic degrees from American universities; c) a list of [the names of] Polish professional women, such as physicians, lawyers, professors, etc.</p>
   <p>"3. Products of women's industries and craft work, such as: a) needle work,</p>
   <p>b) women's farm products, c) women's city home products, d) products raised at home, e) list of charitable deeds.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1266.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"As my appointment has arrived just now, after our local committee of the Lwow Exposition has already begun to collect the exhibits of the products produced by women's craft work, there remains only the first two items for me to fulfill, which up till now were not taken under consideration by the Polish-American committee specially organized for this purpose. Therefore, I ask all Polish women in America to send us as soon as Possible the following:</p>
   <p>"a) Copies of diplomas issued by higher institutions of learning or schools of art.</p>
   <p>"b) Printed copies of educational, Journalistic or literary works, such as fiction, poetry, etc.</p>
   <p>"c) Copies of constitutions of women's organizations and societies, social and religious, number of members, and short histories of the organizations or societies.</p>
   <p>"d) Information concerning professional women, their occupation, location <pb facs="5423968_4_1267.jpg" n="3"/>[of their offices],hours of practice, and official title of the public office.</p>
   <p>"e) Information concerning women's commercial firms, bookkeepers, post-office and railroad clerks, telegraph and telephone operators, etc.</p>
   <p>"f) Information concerning women's benevolent institutions and convents.</p>
   <p>"g) Information concerning Polish women who are attending American universities.</p>
   <p>"Since all material must reach the exposition in the middle of May, all women are requested to send the material as soon as possible. Please send parcels and other material to J. Kodis, 3247 Laurel Street, Chicago.</p>
   <p>"The administration of the Lwow Exposition is of the opinion that our ardent patriotism, which unites us all in the far-flung corners of the world, will stimulate us to this civic duty of participating in the exposition. Let us remember that this is not a question of showing our pride, but of demonstrating the vitality and moral strength of the Polish nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1268.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"All Polish-American newspapers are asked to reprint this appeal.</p>
   <p>"Josephine Kodis, Ph. D."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
