<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-17">Apr. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Few Words about the Present Liberty Loan</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial on Women's Page)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-17">Apr. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A FEW WORDS ABOUT THE PRESENT LIBERTY LOAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial on Women's Page)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The third Liberty Loan bonds which are now on sale, have a special significance to the Poles, and we ought to support this loan even more strongly than the previous loans.</p>
   <p>We would like to explain to our women readers the reasons why the present Liberty Loan bonds should be purchased by us especially. In the first place, although the Poles invested a great deal of money in the first two loans, it brought us no credit as a nation, for there was no indication on bond applications that the bond was purchased by a Pole; it was all credited to the people of America, while later, the question was asked, "Did the Poles support the Liberty Loans and can they prove it by any results?"</p>
   <p>At present, however, the Poles have arranged it so that we will be credited <pb facs="5423968_4_0303.jpg" n="2"/>with the bonds which we purchase.</p>
   <p>Credit will be given us in that on each application that we fill out will be stamped the words "Polish Branch"; every single one of us must ask for such an application and no other. If the locality in which a Pole who is purchasing a Liberty bond has no applications stamped in this way, he himself can write in the words "Polish Branch," and that will be entirely satisfactory. To prove how necessary it is that we specify our nationality, we will cite, as an example, the fact that at the end of the last Liberty Loan campaign, certain American newspapers which have always been unfavorable to the Poles, mentioned practically every other nationality that purchased Liberty bonds, but failed to mention us, while we had nothing by which to prove the amount of money invested by the Poles in that loan--and we know well that it was a large amount.</p>
   <p>Let us think, then, how great the benefit to the Polish cause will be if we buy bonds and indicate that it is Poles who are buying them! Let us go to work <pb facs="5423968_4_0304.jpg" n="3"/>energetically and prove that we are one of the most loyal national groups in America, despite the fact that we do not forsake our Polish nationality, but rather place emphasis on it everywhere and always.</p>
   <p>The time has passed, thank God, when certain unenlightened Poles were ashamed to admit that they were Polish. Today, every one of us is proud of his or her Polish descent, and our nation is winning ever greater sympathy and recognition among people of other nations.</p>
   <p>Let us hold high our national standard by supporting the aims of democratic America and its president, for only by working hand in hand for them can we realize our own aims--a united and independent Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
