<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-24">July 24, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">New Polish Doctor in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1446</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1446.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-24">July 24, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">NEW POLISH DOCTOR IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>News has reached our office that a new Polish doctor has come to Chicago to establish himself permanently in his profession. His name is Doctor T. F. Lawczynski.</p>
   <p>According to Wiarus (Veteran), the doctor has suffered a number of reverses time and again. A summary of the article is given below.</p>
   <p>Dr. T. Lawczynski is 32 years of age. After completing his college education in Warsaw he entered the military medical academy in Saint Petersburg, where he spent three years, later receiving an appointment as military doctor. During his travels he had an opportunity to hear lectures by the famous German pathologists, Dr. Rudolph Virchow, in Berlin, and Louis Pasteur, in Paris. During 1892 and 1893, Dr. Lawczynski was a member of the medical staff of the Stanley Expedition, with which he spent some time in the African Congo. He is familiar with the French, Polish, Russian, German, and Spanish languages. His travels have taken him half across the globe.....</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1447.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He came to the United States from Cuba. After practicing three months in Philadelphia, he was appointed instructor of anatomy at the University of Pennsylvania, under Dr. Porter. When Dr. Porter left for Milwaukee, Dr. Iawczynski lost his position. He then tried his luck in Milwauke and Stevens Point, Misconsin, but neither place was to his material benefit, for his patients did not pay him. Because of his generous heart, he became impoverished, despite the fact that his patients owed him several hundred dollars. In the and he found shelter at the Sisters of Elizabeth Convent in Manitowoc. After saving a few dollars, he decided to try his fortune in Chicago.</p>
   <p>At present Dr. Lawoczynski is looking for a suitable location to open an office. The local Polish doctors will undoubtedly give their compatriot a helping hand and ease the burden of the first few trying months.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
