<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-05">May 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Gerard's Remarks about Poland</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0548</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0548.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-05">May 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">GERARD'S REMARKS ABOUT POLAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The delegation of Chicago Poles did well to call on James W. Gerard, United States Ambassador to Berlin, in order to hear from the lips of this official representative of the United States in Germany, words which were a very grave accusation against the Germans now occupying Polish territory.</p>
   <p>Gerard clearly and unequivocally stated that the Germans are guilty of not allowing food to come into the country out of which they have taken all the food reserves and crops which they found there. Mr. Gerard has proof of this in the form of German newspapers and photographs which appear in them. They are, therefore, directly responsible for the fact that hundreds of thousands of Polish people are suffering famine. Nevertheless the Germans did not want to admit this. For example, the semi-official Norddeutscher Allgemeine Zeitung <pb facs="5423968_4_0549.jpg" n="2"/>some time ago tried to explain that the taking away of Polish wheat and bringing it to Germany was due to the "poorly developed Polish railroad system" and to "conditions prevalent in the Polish milling industry." This paper asserted at the time that "Polish mills are not equipped to grind damp seed," and therefore, the Germans took the entire harvest of 1915 and 1916, promising to supply the people with flour in exchange.</p>
   <p>Mr. Gerard's testimony suffices. The Poles will remember the words condemning the Germans for their nefarious economic actions on our soil, and will later know how to evaluate properly other "cultural benefits" of our sincere [sic] friends.</p>
   <p>The American ex-ambassador pointed out another fact; namely, the reasons behind the German idea of issuing, on November 5, documents establishing the "Kingdom of Poland". It is true that the facts mentioned by Ambassador Gerard are not news to us, and although the clear description of these reasons does not come <pb facs="5423968_4_0550.jpg" n="3"/>to us as a surprise, because all of us knew about it, nevertheless the confirmation of Polish conjectures by the official representative of the United States in Berlin has tremendous meaning for us and our cause.</p>
   <p>The Germans so greatly desired "the so-called restoration of the Kingdom of Poland by them, because they wanted to raise an army of Poles". This Ambassador Gerard asserts, adding at the same time that "the raising of this army was a complete failure". Is this not the greatest recognition and honor for the Poles of the Kingdom [district of Poland] for their political wisdom and intelligence? Mr. Gerard did not need to add that "the Poles are too intelligent and too clever a nation to allow themselves to be caught in this sort of trap, and allow themselves to be led to death for the Central Powers; the more so since we have never heard of a willingness on the part of Germany or Austria to agree to the return of any part of the former country of Poland, which is now about to be restored".</p>
   <p>Further, Ambassador Gerard mentioned the fact that the Germans were most provoked at President Wilson, because in his proclamation he asserted that every nation <pb facs="5423968_4_0551.jpg" n="4"/>should have access to the sea; that therefore the Germans must return Danzig and the mouth of the Vistula to the Poles, which Germany does not want to do for anything in the world.</p>
   <p>Whether they want to or not they will have to, because it will not be they who will dictate the peace terms, but it is sufficient to mention that they well understand the meaning of President Wilson's proclamation, since Mr. Gerard made a point of mentioning it. Therefore, they are thinking about this in the government circles of the United States, and are taking it into consideration, which for the present is sufficient for us.</p>
   <p>One must thoroughly understand the importance of former Ambassador Gerard's remarks made to the Poles. We must remember that former Ambassador Gerard--as we know from other sources--has not yet ended his career, and that he will still play a very important role when the peace negotiations take place.</p>
   <p>The important matter is not the kind of information given us about Poland, <pb facs="5423968_4_0552.jpg" n="5"/>but the person and the official status occupied by the person at the time he received this information at first hand.</p>
   <p>Gerard's words--as those of the Ambassador of the United States--are very important because they reflect the opinions of the official circles in Washington, which play the first violin in this war. This is not the war correspondent of some newspaper who speaks, but the official representative of the United States, which one day will be the highest judge and court of appeal of all oppressed nations.</p>
   <p>Looking upon our interview with former Ambassador Gerard in this light, we will first be able to recognize its importance, because all Poland will be able to recall the words uttered by him on May 3 at the Blackstone Hotel, Chicago, to the Polish delegation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
