<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-23">Sept. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting to Promote Sale of Liberty Bonds</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-23">Sept. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING TO PROMOTE SALE OF LIBERTY BONDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A mass meeting in support of the issuance and sale of bonds of the Fourth Liberty Loan was held on Sunday, September 23, at St. Adalbert's Parish hall. Representatives of nearly all societies existing in or about St. Adalbert's Parish were present at this meeting.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by the Reverend Father Casimir Gronkowski, pastor of the local parish. He first explained the aim and purpose of the meeting and then called upon Mr. Anthony Gorecki to act as chairman, while Mr. Ignace Frasz was selected as recording secretary. It was decided to have a big demonstration and parade in the vicinity of the St. Adalbert's Parish, on October 12, 1918. Following this parade a large mass meeting is to be held at Pulaski Hall in behalf of the Liberty loan. In that way the Polish element will aid this country to defeat our common enemy--the German aggressor. Both the Polish and English languages will be spoken at this forthcoming mass meeting. The following were selected as members of a committee to <pb facs="5423968_4_0139.jpg" n="2"/>arrange the proposed mass meeting: I. Frasz, Reverend Father Casimir Gronkowski, O. Grochowski, John Taul, Ignace Tyrakowski, Francis Kaminski, and Anthony Gorecki. Mr. Joseph Kaminski was selected as grand marshal of the parade, while Messrs. Stephen Nowakowski and S. Wozniak are to act as his aides. A more detailed program will be presented in a future publication.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
