<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-24">Apr. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Receiver Appointed for Bankrupt Fidelity State Bank</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1634</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1634.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-24">Apr. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">RECEIVER APPOINTED FOR BANKRUPT FIDELITY STATE BANK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The bankruptcy case of the Fidelity State Bank, located at 2954 Milwaukee Avenue, closed last February by the state authorities because of insolvency, has taken a new turn. W. Szrojda, well-known Pole and former county commissioner, was recently appointed receiver for the bankrupt institution. Szrojda was appointed by Superior Court Judge Foell on the recommendation of State Auditor Andrew Russell when the case was brought before him by State's Attorney E. J. Brundage.</p>
   <p>The new receiver was placed under a $150,000 bond, the same amount as was required of his predecessor, Ralph Fairbairn, who resigned because of other duties. Szrojda was appointed chiefly for the reason that the depositors of the Fidelity State Bank were principally Poles who did not speak English. Szrojda's attorney, M. J. Moriarty, says that at the present time, nothing can be said as to the closed bank's financial condition.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1635.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the time of its failure, the bank's liabilities totalled $225,007.64. What percentage of this sum the depositors will receive is as yet uncertain, but there are rumors that not more than fifty per cent will be paid.</p>
   <p>Since we have repeatedly been asked as to what is to become of the first and second Liberty Loan bonds that were being paid up in this bank, we applied for information to W. Szrojda, the new receiver. According to him, those who were paying up on Liberty bonds at this bank should be patient, for this question will soon be clarified and information as to where further payments are to be made will appear in the press. "Purchasers of the first two Liberty bond issues have nothing to worry about," said Mr. Szrojda; "their money is safe. Whoever can do so ought to purchase Liberty bonds of the third issue and thus help the United States win the war with Germany." Depositors who had savings in the Fidelity Bank ought to be patient also, for now that a Pole has been appointed receiver, everything will be done to make satisfactory arrangements as soon as possible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1636.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Those concerned can get all information by applying to W. Szrojda at the bank, where he can be found daily from eight o'clock in the morning until five in the afternoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
