<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-06-14">June 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A New Amendment to the Constitution of the United States</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-06-14">June 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW AMENDMENT TO THE CONSTITUTION OF THE UNITED STATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of all the constitutions adopted by large countries the Constitution of the United States of North America is the only one that has existed 120 years without undergoing major changes, showing thereby the greatness of the minds of the men who framed it, and also the intelligence of the people who have used it and are using it now. During that period of time, France had fifteen different constitutions. Practical England did not wish to trouble herself with framing a constitution and governs her subjects by a great number of laws made from time to time. The constitutions of Austria, Italy, and Germany, though formed in modern times, are already obsolete.</p>
   <p>The Constitution of the United States was created by men, and for this reason it is not without weak points. These points, however, are of <pb facs="5423968_4_1127.jpg" n="2"/>such character that the nation can change or improve them, if necessary, without damaging any part of the structure. Fifteen small changes, called amendments and repeals, have been made in the Constitution during its whole existence. At present the nation is adopting the 16th and a very important constitutional amendment, because, if it is passed, the United States senators will be elected by the people and not by the legislatures of the states.</p>
   <p>This gradual coalescence is a great step towards the unification of all states into one great country. In the beginning there were only a few independent colonies; later these formed a loosely connected Union of thirteen independent republics with a weak federal government; and after the Civil War there arose a great and powerful country, the United States. The process of coalescence continues uninterruptedly.</p>
   <p>Until now the senators have been elected by the state legislatures and the Senate only represented the independent republics constituting the Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1128.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The senators acted as ambassadors from their states to the Congress and to the President, and as guardians of the independence and laws of the states. The Senate, however, is changing from an ambassadorial into a legislative body. During the period of years that elapsed between Presidents Jefferson and Lincoln the most important debates on legislation were conducted in the Senate, where the best statesmen of the nation were assembled. During that time, and especially after President Jackson's term, the Senate ruled the country. At that period there were no great presidents or prominent men in the Lower House of the Congress; instead of them, Senators Clay, Webster, Calhoun, Sumner and a small number of others fought in the Senate and ruled the country. This change in the character of the Senate has justified the necessity of changing the system of electing the senators. Ambassadors are appointed by the heads of their respective governments or legislatures, but the legislators should be elected by the people if the people wish to have their will expressed through them. A senator elected by a legislature may try to express the will of all members of the legislature, but basically he cannot express the will of the people who have not empowered him to do so.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1129.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Nation, however, had such a great respect for its Constitution that, though noticing the change in the character of the Senate, it did not express a desire for any new amendment. Nevertheless, the nation was compelled to this action by internal disintegration in the body of the Senate itself. This disintegration in the Senate had progressed to such a degree that it began to irritate even the most common and unassuming citizens.</p>
   <p>What has caused this deterioration, this corruption? This corruption was caused by a delayed reform. It could be said that the original Senate had died a natural death, therefore, a reform was necessary forty years ago, when the supposed death occurred. The Nation did not recognize the necessity of reform, delayed it and the decomposition of the dead organism began.</p>
   <p>This decomposition was manifested by a very simple symptom - the bribery. Instead of poor Clays and Websters, there appeared in the Senate common men, but rich, who either personally bought their seats or were financed by <pb facs="5423968_4_1130.jpg" n="5"/>selfish individuals or groups. Finally, the Senate became a scene of continuous accusations, investigations, scandals and debates on the question whether a certain senator is guilty of some crime or not. The nation laughed at first, was angry and malignant later on, and finally it became frightened. In many States the legislatures have passed resolutions, demanding reforms of the system by which the senators are elected; in other words, they demand a 16th constitutional amendment. This reform bill is on the way to become a law, for it was accepted in principle by the Lower House, and by the Senate, by a vote of 64 to 24, though the formulation of the bill was slightly changed. On account of the slight change this bill, in a new form, must return to the Lower House of the Congress, and, if it is accepted and signed by the President, it must be passed in the state legislatures by three quarters (3/4) of the votes.</p>
   <p>This is a long and tedious process, and there will be many difficulties, but the beginning has already been made and the public is of the opinion that good will be accomplished. When the people are determined, they must and will accomplish their purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
