<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-10">Oct. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">One More Argument</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-10">Oct. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ONE MORE ARGUMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is with real pain that we must communicate to the Polish public a fact which, bitter as it may be to the Poles in America, is one more reason why we should exert all our efforts to form a Polish national army.</p>
   <p>Everyone knows with what enthusiasm American Poles gathered beneath the Stars and Stripes and that, in order to encourage our countrymen to enlist in the army, we did our utmost to convince the authorities to create strictly Polish units within the American army. After considerable effort and many difficulties, we were successful, and the American army permitted the formation of purely Polish companies within its ranks, as, for example, the widely-known "Kosciusko Guard" and the company commanded by Captain Blenski, censor of the Polish National Alliance, in Milwaukee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0493.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As a result of the fact that the army was placed upon a war basis, an internal reorganization was necessary to meet the new requirements. The Polish companies were completely disbanded and their men used to fill out other companies--although the "Kosciusko Guard" remained, it was expanded by the addition of non-Poles to its ranks. Of the two hundred and fifty soldiers now in the "Kosciusko Guard," only a hundred and fifty are Poles, while the remaining hundred are men of other national background. In other words, it has ceased to be a Polish company.</p>
   <p>Although we really cannot criticize the changes, evidently essential, which have been made and which are probably useful from the point of view of the authorities, we can also see in them another glaring proof that whoever wants to fight in this war as a Polish soldier ought to hasten to enlist in the Polish army, under the White Eagle. Scattered throughout the regiments in the American army, Poles will be fighting only as American soldiers, and, of course, this is as it should be. The United States is forced to create a homogeneous national army in which it cannot give special consideration to any particular element.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0494.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the American army, the Pole will be fighting only for the United States. At the coming peace conference, no one will ask how many Poles fought under the Stars and Stripes. Uncle Sam, and not Poland, will get the credit for even the most heroic deeds of individual Poles in the American army.</p>
   <p>We have given many proofs, as many as we could, of our gratitude to this country and our love for this adopted homeland of ours which accepted us so hospitably. Poles led during the time in which Uncle Sam was recruiting volunteers and later, when the draft came into effect, the American army took from localities such as South Bend, for example, ninety per cent of its quota from among Poles. And in the future, we shall continue to do our duty to the United States with the same willingness and sacrifice, without hesitation.</p>
   <p>But since the American Secretary of War himself announced, in behalf of the American government, that that government would be faithful to its declaration for a free and united Poland and is entirely in accord with the plan to recruit <pb facs="5423968_4_0495.jpg" n="4"/>Poles to form a Polish national army and desires the fullest success of our recruiting campaign, it must be clear, beyond any shadow of doubt, that every good Pole who is not yet obliged to serve in the American army, has only one duty before him--to enlist without delay in our own Polish army, which the United States, together with all of the Allied Powers, has recognized.</p>
   <p>Only as Polish soldiers in a Polish army, fighting beside the armies of great and friendly nations, can we serve our country at first hand, lifting away the rocks that entomb it with our own hands while, at the same time, we are in no way diminishing the military power of the United States, which has plenty of men and really desires to see us within the ranks of our own national army. Poland, too, calls us, as do the authorized representatives of the entire Polish element in exile.</p>
   <p>There can be no more hesitation and uncertainty; we must show quick and spirited action. To arms!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
