<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-26">Dec. 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Young Polish Lawyer Admitted to Bar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1425</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1425.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-26">Dec. 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG POLISH LAWYER ADMITTED TO BAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Edmund T. Wleklinski, organizer and president of Group 1823, Polish National Alliance, has joined the ranks of Chicago's young Polish lawyers. After passing the bar examinations in Springfield successfully, he received his license to practice law.</p>
   <p>Young Wleklinski was born in Chicago on November 23, 1892. He received his early education in the public schools, after which he attended Tuley High School. He attended law classes at the Chicago Kent College of Law. Wleklinski is the son of Francis X. Wleklinski, former director on the Central Board of the Polish National Alliance and one of the organization's oldest members. The young lawyer lives with his parents at 1017 North Hoyne Avenue.</p>
   <p>In spite of the fact that the last examination was especially difficult, Wleklinski, passed it creditably, receiving one of the highest grades. He will start practicing immediately.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1426.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The young lawyer is well known among our best class of youth. He takes active part in nationalistic and organizational work, and enjoys the high esteem of his Colleagues in Commune III, Polish National Alliance, to which he is a delegate from Group 1823. He has been employed for some time by the law firm of Kraus, Alschuler, and Holden. Three months ago he returned from Texas, where he was employed by the Federal Government as a clerk in the quartermaster's office.</p>
   <p>It is to be hoped that the young lawyer will enjoy a large clientele among the Chicago Poles, as he well deserves it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
