<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XII, No. 15,
<date when="1917-04-12">April 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Loyalty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0603</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0603.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XII, No. 15,
<date when="1917-04-12">April 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH LOYALTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Poles, when not engaged in battle for their own freedom, have shed blood for the principle of freedom in every other part of the globe, but, be it to their honor, they have never battled for a cause which was not just.</p>
   <p>Distinguished were their services rendered to America in every conflict from the day of the Revolution to the present time. Whole regiments fought in the Civil War, and today four and a half million citizens of our race by birth or extraction, resident in America, are well represented in the army and navy.</p>
   <p>The average American does not well understand Poland's position. We are neither Austrians, Russians, nor Germans. We are Poles striving as a nation for complete freedom.</p>
   <p>Poles have every reason to be grateful to America for the asylum she <pb facs="5423968_4_0604.jpg" n="2"/>has furnished them from foreign oppression and now even more grateful for the sympathetic reference to Poland by its great President in his address to the Senate.</p>
   <p>Poles will be ever loyal to America, and especially at this time can America depend upon them. True to their tradition, they will rally to her flag. They are born soldiers, great numbers have had military training in the old country and will now offer their services to their adopted country.</p>
   <p>We notice anxiety on the part of manufacturers employing foreign labor in their plants. We say to them, If you employ Polish labor that is your best insurance. And to such Polish employees we might say, Bear in mind that there are other ways of being of service to your adopted country besides taking up arms in its defense.</p>
   <p>Tens of thousands of you are engaged in manufacturing of every description <pb facs="5423968_4_0605.jpg" n="3"/>Political fanatics with interests inimical to America will seek to cripple her industries by plot and conspiracy. It is your duty to be watchful, keep your eyes open and ears to the ground. Should you hear or have reason to suspect anything wrong, immediately, but carefully, inform your superior or the government authorities. Guard the plants as if they were your own, and this applies to every line of industry and endeavor. Thus will you show your loyalty and best serve your fatherland.</p>
   <p>Do not forget you are Poles, not Austrians, not Germans nor Russians, and above all properly register as such when applying for a position. Many Poles are still interned in Canada as Germans and Austrians because of improper registration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
