<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-09-08">Sept. 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1700</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1700.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-09-08">Sept. 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The need for a school in which our countrymen could learn the tailoring trade at a relatively low cost has long been felt among the Poles of Chicago. It is well known that Poles who decried to learn cutting, which, parenthetically speaking, is the most difficult part of tailoring <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, have had to go to tailoring schools operated by non-Poles and pay large sums of money for the course. Very often, they have not been given their money's worth.</p>
   <p>As the idea of returning to our homeland grows, the number of men desiring to learn the tailoring trade has increased considerably. Everyone who knows a little of tailoring, but who does not know how to cat, is hastening to learn cutting, for he knows that there will be plenty of work in Europe when the war is over. Thousands of tailors will find an extremely well-paying occupation in clothing Europe's denuded millions of people.</p>
   <p>The Poles who intend to return to Poland, there to earn their living, would do <pb facs="5423968_4_1701.jpg" n="2"/>best to learn the tailoring trade here in the United States.</p>
   <p>All those desiring to learn cutting should take advantage of the school opened by the Polish Tailors' Society, group 5, Polish National Alliance. Classes are held at the Falcons' Hall, 1063 Milwaukee Avenue. The few members who, as we learned recently, enrolled for the course were well pleased with themselves for doing so after attending a few classes.</p>
   <p>We shall not take time here to give a lengthy description of this school of cutting. We must, however, commend this step taken by the Polish Tailors' society, for it is a means of increasing the usefulness of many of our countrymen who plan to return to Poland after the war, to earn their living there and to help rebuild the land from its present ashes and ruins.</p>
   <p>The capable tailor, Sickucki, has been appointed instructor of cutting. The cost of the course to members of the society is thirty dollars, to non-members, sixty dollars. One way to save thirty dollars is to join the Polish Tailors' society.</p>
   <p>Further information will be cheerfully given by the secretary to all those who desire it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
