<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-01-05">Jan. 5, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Dangers of War between Mexico and United States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-01-05">Jan. 5, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">DANGERS OF WAR BETWEEN MEXICO AND UNITED STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republic of Mexico, with President Calles as its leader, is conducting a religious war in Mexico, as well as an economic war with its powerful neighbor, the United States. This is a typical economic war between two countries. The most important reason for this conflict is the exploitation of Mexico by American industry. At one time, President Diaz opened the door of Mexico to the United States for exploitation, hoping that better uniform economic conditions would ensue.</p>
   <p>In the year of 1901 it relieved foreign capital of taxes, the importation of machinery and the exporting of oil was also free from taxation. In the year of 1907, the United States settled, and assumed property ownership in Mexico. An English Association, Pearson Co., did likewise and Holland followed in 1923. This started a dispute among these nations. In the year of 1923, American co-operations offered president Huerta $200,000,000, for exclusive rights and options to their oil fields. However, a revolutionary outburst, in Carranza, made it impossible to reach an agreement. Because of financial pressure at end of 1913, Washington, broke diplomatic relations with Mexico, and in the month of April 1914, stationed an army at Vera Cruz. This action did not meet with the approval of European nations. An open warfare was started.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0105.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The United States had an entirely free hand. An Expedition under the command of General Pershing, was sent to Mexico to take disciplinary action, which resulted in attacks and invasions by Mexican bandits along the borders of United States. Mexico will reply that the constitution of Queretaro of 1917, included articles of defiance against foreign finance. The most important part is; "The land ownership rights are restricted and confined, only to the nations of Mexico, and concessions to mine, coal, and established water power projects. Mexico can also grant the rights to all foreigners, providing they do not seek the influence of their governments" thus: American may not acquire land or any territorial rights within the radius of 100 miles of the border.</p>
   <p>It is lastly stipulated, that foreign stock companies are not privileged to acquire tillable land. This enactment caused the United States to be angry, and created a panic in the stock market. It was understood that the investment of American capital is estimated at $2,000,000 dollars; some of the American productive co-operation branches controlling 90 percent of ownership. Any addition to the amendment of the constitution, would be a loss of great wealth. Under pressure, Washington, in 1919, brought to attention, the conditional paragraph of foreign ownership in Mexico; and president Obregon, was officially praised by the-administration in Washington. According to this agreement condition, the amendment will bind only those foreigners who in the future desire to exploit the wealth of Mexico.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0106.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, President Calles, in spite of the tradition set by his predecessor, and without regard, began applying rules to the constitution. After conducting a series of acceptances, he designated the first day of January as the date when all foreign interest will be under government jurisdiction. This resulted in a severe reprimand by the United States, in a note, in which they expressed their readiness to object, unless Mexico conforms to a decision handed down by the Supreme Court in Hague. The Calles administration will dissolve the oil industry, supporting the action of a revolution among their workers. It will effect the reducing of production, and the increasing unemployment.</p>
   <p>In this conflict, noble opinion would favor the nation in which they set up a dominion of foreign capital. In addition to this unwarranted conflict, the question of religious persecution was added. This, of course, is a conspiracy instigated by the enemies of the church; using unemployment as a tool for discontent and corruption, and creating thereby an artificial stimulus for religious conflict. They wish to place capital and religion on one battlefront, this manuever should not proceed. With a non-partisan view, one can readily determine the real enemy - American capital; and the imaginery one - religion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
