<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-03-11">March 11, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Freedom of Speech</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1139</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1139.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-03-11">March 11, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">FREEDOM OF SPEECH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Because of the murderous attack by an anarchist upon the life of the Chicago chief of police, much has been said and written in the last few days about the freedom of speech. Special attention was drawn to Emma Goldman, well known Anarchist agitator, who had an urgent desire to speak publicly in Chicago. This privilege, however was denied because of the public demand that police stop all public speaking on street corners. On the other hand, the people protested against policemen depriving them of their constitutional rights, and threats were made that they would acquaint themselves with policemen's clubs if necessary, to protect that right.</p>
   <p>Freedom of speech is a precious acquisition, won after centuries of hard struggle and many sacrifices, and should, therefore, be jealously guarded and protected against even a fractional curtailment.</p>
   <p>It is indeed unjust to lay crime to an innocent cause. Many outrages have been committed in the name of liberty, but its principles are undefiled. The same is true of religion, yet it remains beautiful as always.</p>
   <p>We should, therefore, maintain the proper attitude toward freedom of speech <pb facs="5423968_4_1140.jpg" n="2"/>and realize that it is not necessary to abolish or restrict its purpose because of the few individuals who are opposed to it.</p>
   <p>In our opinion, public speaking and gatherings on street corners, in halls and other places should not be barred merely because some one may say some-ting that does not meet with our individual approval. Such limitations of our expression would be unconstitutional. Instead, we should see that no abuses are committed against this freedom of speech, and that it is not used in defense of murder or treason.</p>
   <p>Every civilized country has a law which points out words that are prohibited. It is also unlawful to persuade the listeners to commit a crime. If there is no such law, one should be enacted and it should point out very clearly just what constitutes forbidden speech, then proper steps could be taken to prevent it. Because of the absence of such a law, freedom of speech is encouraged.</p>
   <p>Let us use common sense in all actions and remain within the boundaries of the law. We should, therefore, not limit the rights of citizens just because we think that some one might abuse us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
