<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-28">July 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Development of Polish Industry in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">Polish Casket Factory</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-28">July 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">DEVELOPMENT OF POLISH INDUSTRY IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">Polish Casket Factory</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The sole Polish casket factory in the United States is located in the three-story brick building at 1029 West Chicago Avenue. The large letters of the sign reading "Standard Coffin and Casket Company" can be seen at a distance of several blocks....</p>
   <p>With the desire of acquainting the readers of this paper with this sole Polish enterprise of its kind in America, Dziennik Zwiazkowy sent its reporter to visit the factory personally, to see how caskets are made and to obtain details of the firms beginnings, its capital, and its prospects for the future.</p>
   <p>In Existence Fourteen Years</p>
   <p>According to the manager, L. Wolczynski, the firm was organized in 1902 by <pb facs="5423968_4_1729.jpg" n="2"/>Stanislaus Ambrozewski, B. Raclawski, Nicholas Kordel, and Anthony Ablamowicz, all enterprising and energetic men. A year later, that is, in 1903, it was incorporated under the laws of the State of Illinois in the sum of $25,000. Since that time, the firm has progressed steadily, doing an ever increasing business among the Poles of Chicago and in outlying Polish communities.</p>
   <p>The present administration of the firm consists of: J. Magdziarz, president: L. Wojczynski, vice-president and manager; F.P. Kujawski, secretary; M. Wojczynski, assistant secretary, and J.N. Nowicki, treasurer. The board of directors consists of these officers and Stanislaus Ambrozewski. The firm's salesmen are Ambrozewski and Raclawski. The well-chosen administration works together harmoniously, and the company does its best to satisfy all customers by the swift and adequate filling of orders and by using the best possible materials at the lowest possible cost.</p>
   <p>Upon entering the building, the visitor first enters a large vestibule which opens upon the office and showroom. The showroom contains caskets of every description. Starting from the smallest size, they are larger by degrees <pb facs="5423968_4_1730.jpg" n="3"/>until finally one sees coffins that are wide enough and long enough to accommodate the bodies of the tallest and broadest people.</p>
   <p>The choice of caskets is varied. There are richly decorated oaken caskets, less pretentious caskets, and caskets covered with velvet and lined with silk. The manager of the firm opened a door to another room and said, "Here we have one stock of crosses of every kind, and also trimmings for caskets." He displayed several kinds. Everything is beautiful, made by the most modern methods, but has something repellent about it, something that reminds one of the grave, of death. The stock room, in which a great many coffins await their tenants, is located on the top floor. Every person who enters this room can surely find a casket that would suit him admirably after death.</p>
   <p>The third floor hums with activity. Some of the workmen cover caskets with velvet, others line them with silk. Girls working beside them cut the silk and sew the linings, using machines built for that purpose. Behind them is the stock of silks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1731.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"In these packages," says the manager, opening a few of them and displaying the contents, "we have several thousands of dollars worth of silk. It is expensive material. In case of fire, our insurance company would have to pay out a considerable sum."</p>
   <p>On the second floor--more coffins. They are not as decorative and attractive as the finished coffins, but wait until the workers finish them! They can make anything beautiful. They cover the wooden coffins with velvet and do it so skillfully that it is a pleasure to watch them. The wood is first covered with glue, and then the velvet is applied so fast that before a person has time to note the whole process, the already beautiful casket is set aside, ready to be sent upstairs.</p>
   <p>"Here again," says the manager, "is our stock of candles, covering materials, and caskets ready for delivery. Those that you see wrapped in paper are the same as those you saw downstairs in the showroom."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1732.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The greatest activity, however, is to be found on the first floor, among the cabinetmakers. The lumber passes from hand to hand, from machine to machine, is glued together and sanded until it becomes the last resting place for a man--a coffin. The wood-working machinery is worthy of notice. There are hand saws and planers, as well as machines for ornamental work. Still other machines are to be found in the basement, next to the stock of lumber. Each machine is run by electricity, the cost of which, according to the manager, runs into more than a hundred dollars per month.</p>
   <p>After visiting all parts of the factory, our reporter asked Manager Wojczynski whether his firm recieves the support of the Poles. Wojczynski answered: "We cannot complain of lack of support from the Poles and Lithuanians. Not only have we the support of Chicago's Polonia, but of Polonia all over the United States. We have orders from Polish undertakers in Jersey City, South Bend, Buffalo, Pittsburgh, and many other cities. Only the undertakers of South Chicago do not support us very well. They do business with other firms; despite that fact, they cannot get better merchandise than we offer. They <pb facs="5423968_4_1733.jpg" n="6"/>support Jews or Germans, seeming hardly to realize that a Polish firm exists."</p>
   <p>It is indeed unfortunate that such a condition exists. Polish undertakers of South Chicago and Town of Lake should not support other factories when a Polish factory can supply them with merchandise that is just as good, or better, at the same prices.</p>
   <p>Prejudice against everything that is Polish should--once and for all--be eradicated among the Poles. It should become a habit with us to support Polish enterprise.</p>
   <p>The motto "Patronize your own countrymen" (Swoj Do Swego) should point the way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
