<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-16">Nov. 16, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Separate Elections for Judges</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-16">Nov. 16, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">SEPARATE ELECTIONS FOR JUDGES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A certain American newspaper calls attention to the fact, and justifiably, that federal, municipal, circuit, police, probate, and other judges should be elected separately by the voters, instead of being elected with the candidates for different offices. This newspaper states with reason that judges should not take part in political campaigns. Moreover, their names should not be placed on the ballot with the names of other candidates because the judiciary branch of our government, be that federal, state, or municipal, should be free of political influence and atmosphere. This is a matter of importance to every man. An ordinary politician should not be a judge, because his only interest would be in money, and he would consider his office not a duty but an opportunity to become wealthy at the expense of taxpayers. A judge after all, is the personification of justice, truth, and sincerity--he is like a father who punishes misbehaving children. Consequently, he cannot be a politician--one who is accessible to bribery.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0059.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In electing judges the people should consider not the candidate's party but his character. A judge, therefore, must be free of all partisanship. Candidates aspiring to a judicial office should be presented not on a partisan but on a nonpartisan basis. All voters would then be able to vote for judges, not under political mottoes, but according to their convictions as to which of the candidates would be a better and more just judge, which of them is more capable as an attorney, and which is a man of unblemished character.</p>
   <p>The elction campaign of 1910 illustrates our point. Wise, just, and honest judges lost and, in their stead, worse people were successful simply because their party was victorious. Many judges were defeated in the election, not because they were bad or incapable, but because they belonged to the Republican party, which suffered defeat. Such conditions should not prevail. Judges at least should be free from politics and should not aspire to win such distinguished office through the aid of dollars and propaganda. It looks so silly to see a candidate for judge, that office which protects justice and truth, run from one meeting to another, praise himself as good material, denounce his opponents, members of other parties, and conduct politics on a large scale--at <pb facs="5423968_4_0060.jpg" n="3"/>times with the aid of whiskey, beer, money, and promises. The election of judges should be conducted in a different manner--on a nonpartisan basis and one devoid of repulsive politics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
