<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-20">May 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Safeguarding of Citizens</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1006</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.9"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1006.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II D 9</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-20">May 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE SAFEGUARDING OF CITIZENS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although the United States probably spends more money than any country in the world for its police system, the average citizen does not benefit from this expenditure, for his life is endangered daily. Daily headlines bring to us the news of murders and robberies, many of which are committed in broad daylight, on public thoroughfares, busy streets of the city - virtually under the noses of the police; yet, there are only a few arrests and less convictions. Non one is safe from these criminals at large. The publicity of the crimes reaches many frontiers.</p>
   <p>Italy and Spain, known for their bandit tribes, do not have as many murders and robberies in a year as are committed in the United States in a week. The Mafia of Italy, which is the terror of our citizens, is not as bold in its own country as it is in the United States. A majority of the crimes here are perpetrated by this group. It is apparent that our police force <pb facs="5423968_4_1007.jpg" n="2"/>are helpless in their work, or plainly speaking, in order to safeguard their own life, they do not show any interference.</p>
   <p>The well-known detective Petrosini, who lost his life in Sicily through the bullets of the Black Hand, was the only person that waged a constant fight to eradicate the criminals and their crimes. His activity was second to none. The gangland world was in constant fear of him.</p>
   <p>The sluggish and idle sons of the Green Island, adorned with a club and a star, can be more easily found in the saloons than on their beats, where they ought to be on the lookout for any suspicious act.</p>
   <p>A certain band that has been throwing bombs over many parts of the city, causing damage to private property and disturbing the peace of the community, must be well-organized, for the well-paid police force cannot track it down.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1008.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Everyday the citizens are open prey for these bandits, becoming innocent victims, at times paying with their lives. When the criminal is caught and brought to justice, he is given a light sentence. Those that commit petty crimes are the ones that suffer the most. Organized crime virtually thrives and is becoming stronger in metropolitan areas.</p>
   <p>The activity of the criminal is branching out in many fields, crossing many borders. Organized bands hold up express trains, rob the mail, and the passengers. Their acts of crime go unmolested.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday, highway bandits held up the Great Northern Limited, near Moriss, Washington. Pouches containing about $20,000 in registered mail were taken. Country posses and farm vigilantes are taking a hand in the search for these bandits, filling the gap of the incompetent police, who do not know how to search out for the bandits who escaped with the loot. The railroad company <pb facs="5423968_4_1009.jpg" n="4"/>offers a $10,000 reward for any clue leading to the conviction of each of the culprits. There were six of them. The company is posting a $60,000 reward for their conviction. It feels that this is the only method that will bring the bandits before the courts of justice. This will also make the police department use better and more energetic methods for action.</p>
   <p>When an individual or a company offers a reward for the capture of thieves, the police seem to become more active. The rewards are alluring and lucrative, which makes them to be successful; otherwise they would not exert themselves to fulfill their duties.</p>
   <p>Everyday bands of bank robbers force their way into stores and banks, break fireproof vaults and carry out small and large sums of valuables. The pickpockets empty the pockets of innocent people, the mail boxes are emptied of their mail. In spite of these daily mass operations, the police is only <pb facs="5423968_4_1010.jpg" n="5"/>able to make twenty arrests per day. This perhaps is only as a gesture.</p>
   <p>Should these crimes increase and broaden out it won't be hard to predict the position in which this country will find itself. No one will be certain of his personal liberty, not even of his life. Since many of the holdups take place near where the police are stationed, and this happens in Chicago, the latter at times catch the felons but let them free. At times the person seeking help from the officers gets a taste of the club himself.</p>
   <p>The upkeep of the Chicago police is estimated at three million dollars, a cost which is borne by the citizens. In exchange for this, the citizen gets a feeling of insecurity, for he does now know whether he is safe at home or our in the streets. His personal freedom is constantly at stake, not to say anything of his personal property.</p>
   <p>Statistics show that out of every 1000 dollars stolen, 50 return to the <pb facs="5423968_4_1011.jpg" n="6"/>original owners. These crimes increase daily. During the first week of last year there were 656 robberies reported. This year, in Chicago, there were 963. The smaller petty larceny cases, or the number of persons injured are not included. Conditions are getting worse. Should the citizens not require from the police department a stronger enforcement of the laws, crime will be out of control. Why should the burden be shouldered by the citizenry? Why should millions be spent, if the expenditures do not bring any results? The safety of the citizen is jepardized to such an extent that he sometimes is not certain of his life. The bandit groups have grown and spread out more rapidly in the cities than the Italian bandits in the hills and forests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
