<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-12">Sept. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Voice of the Reader</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0797</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0797.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-12">Sept. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">VOICE OF THE READER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are between the anvil and the hammer. We are like a bar of iron in the hands of a blacksmith, who is going to hammer the iron into steel--steel which flashes, steel which no force can bend. The blacksmith is the present moment; we are the iron; our fighting units will be the steel.</p>
   <p>Our men ardently desire to gather all Polish sons under one flag, to inspire all with one thought, to inculcate in all one idea and one motto: "Fight," regardless of what happens. Fight, because only by fighting can we hope to save all of Poland!</p>
   <p>The time for deliberation has passed. The time for political ideologies has gone without leaving even an echo. High politics has fallen from its lofty perch and broken its neck, and only one idea remains: Fight! Fight in such a way that either they or we shall be annihilated. Fight our enemies for all of the wrongs, persecutions, and tortures they have inflicted on us. Fight <pb facs="5423968_4_0798.jpg" n="2"/>for the plight of past and future generations. Fight, fight, and keep on fighting.</p>
   <p>Galicia as one man has marched forward. Galicia will find thousands of people in the Kingdom who will follow her, snatch up their scythes, and cut down the ranks of the enemy. [Translator's note: During the Kosciusko Insurrection the peasants had no arms, so they sharpened their scythes and fought with them.] Let the nobility and the gentry supply the money, the peasants will do the fighting. When they thresh the enemy, instead of seeds, they will thresh out a free and independent Poland.</p>
   <p>It may be that in writing these words I am crazy and that buckets of cold water should be poured over my head, but I write them in the terrible excitement which great moments produce in us.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0799.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Poland is a great thing"--but even greater is the moment when we shall be given freedom and independence.</p>
   <p>Therefore I do not care about anything else, if only I can share a bit of my enthusiasm and desire with our brothers over there--if in writing these words I can offer at least half of my life for this battle, this beautiful battle.</p>
   <p>I respect the careful judgment of people who are cooler in politics than I. I value their carefulness and their tendency to look before they leap, but what am I to do when, in spite of this, my soul strains more toward those who are fighting than toward those who are waiting for something or someone!</p>
   <p>With such emotions I write these words to my unknown, but very dear, mass of readers. I write in the hope that at least one soul among them will feel my desire to bring help to the homeland at once.</p>
   <p>We cannot go there to fight. We cannot seize arms and, together with peasants.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0800.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>and laborers, offer our heads on the altar of the homeland. But at least we can hurry with material aid.</p>
   <p>Let us hurry now, because our dollar will lose half of its value and might lose all of its value, if it comes too late. We should then deserve the epithet " A Pole is wise after the harm is done."</p>
   <p>One hundred and nineteen years of serfdom should have taught us wisdom. So many times during that period we have been late. We have talked politics until we have talked Poland out of existence. This time let us not procrastinate. Let us not do things when it is too late, when everything is all over, but let us act now--right away.</p>
   <p>If this war should end without Poland's restoration, it would then be too late: we would not be allowed to seize arms then, but would be looked upon as ilotas accustomed to servitude.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0801.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Whatever may happen, it is our duty to fight our enemies at this time.</p>
   <p>As long as military preparations were insignificant and were made by one-party, it was not our duty to take sides in the political squabbles. But now the nation has seized arms, the idea of an armed reminder of Poland's rights has flashed across the Polish horizon, and we are to appear before the congress of diplomats not as begging servants, but as fighting soldiers. Then let us hurry to the aid of those who are fighting, who are covered with wounds, who are dying for the cause. Any Pole who does not want to be left out of things must co-operate now. He may not sit on the sidelines with his arms crossed, he may not postpone his aid ad calendas graecas. Now our decision must be as quick as lightening and as strong as a peasant's right hand.</p>
   <p>Then let us shower money. Let us not regret the dollars we give to the independence fund, because out of this money as out of seeds sown on blood-drenched soil, the free and independent homeland will blossom.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Grzesznik</p>
   <p>[The Sinner]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
