<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-09">Sept. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Report on the Meeting of the League of Polish Building and Loan Associations of Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-09">Sept. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT ON THE MEETING OF THE LEAGUE OF POLISH BUILDING AND LOAN ASSOCIATIONS OF ILLINOIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the League of Polish Building and Loan Associations of Illinois was held on Saturday, September 7, 1918, at Skarpinski Hall, 3059 West Twenty-second Street. More than thirty delegates were present, representing eighteen building and loan associations. The meeting was called to order by Mr. Albert Wachowski, president of the League, at 3:45 P. M. He directed Mr. Anthony Wlodarski to call the roll of officials and delegates. [Two] officials were absent, Messrs. John Sakwinski, vice-president, and Stanley Strzelecki, treasurer. The following associations were represented [by delegates] at this meeting: Albert Wacfcowski, Casimir Pulaski, John Sobieski, St. Hyacinth, White Eagle, Tenth Ward, St. Hedwig, Cracow, Skala Polska, King Casimir III., Chopin, King Walter Jagiello, St. John Cantius, Prince Joseph Poniatowski, St. Anne, Pioneer, St. James, Grunwald, and St. Casimir.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1603.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following new building and loan associations were admitted as members of the League: the Adam Mickiewicz Association of Hawthorne, Illinois, and the J. Kraszewski Association located in the vicinity of St. Adalbert's parish. Upon acceptance into the League the new associations paid their annual dues.</p>
   <p>The secretary, Mr. A. Wlodarski, then read the minutes of the last regular meeting. They were accepted as read. He then presented some proposals which had been introduced at a special meeting. These were left for discussion as unfinished business. The president, Mr. Wachowski, then gave a report on the convention of all the building and loan associations throughout the United States, held in Newark, New Jersey, last month. In conclusion the president presented his written report, entitled "The Present War and Its Influence upon Humanity". Mr. Wlodarski first read this report in English, and the author himself then read it in Polish. The delegates accepted the report enthusiastically. The followed a detailed report on the Polish convention recently held at <pb facs="5423968_4_1604.jpg" n="3"/>Detroit, Michigan. President Wachowski, who represented the League of Polish Building and Loan Associations of Illinois, and Mr. W. Grzegorzewski, who represented St. Casimir's parish, presented their views. The report was accepted with acclaim.</p>
   <p>The president, Mr. Wachowski, next informed the delegates that on September 28, 1918 the drive for the sale of the Fourth Liberty Loan bonds will begin. He declared that it is the duty and the obligation of every organization, corporation, association, and individual citizen of this country to give active support to this drive.</p>
   <p>The next to speak on this topic was the secretary, Mr. A. Wlodarski, who urged every one to buy as many Government bends as possible. He then made a motion that the League of Polish Building and Loan Associations of Illinois take an active part in the purchase of these Fourth Liberty Loan bonds, as it did when the third series was being sold. He urged that all individual <pb facs="5423968_4_1605.jpg" n="4"/>building and loan associations belonging to the League make such investments and thus aid this country to defeat its foe and at the same time demonstrate our loyalty to the nation by giving active and concrete support to our adopted country, the United States of America.</p>
   <p>A longer speech on the Fourth Liberty Loan bonds was delivered by Mr. Walter Grzegorzewski, a well-known leader in the Polish National Alliance groups and one of the most-prominent and diligent workers in behalf of Polish building and loan associations. On his motion it was decided to empower the secretary of the League to direct every individual building and loan association belonging to it to purchase the greatest amount possible of the Fourth Liberty Loan bonds through the League of Polish Building and Loan Associations of Illinois. A committee was then selected of which the business will be to obtain from the proper authorities the printed matter, permit, receipt books, and advertisments necessary in the sale of these bonds. The following delegates were placed on <pb facs="5423968_4_1606.jpg" n="5"/>this committee: Messrs. Albert Wachowski, president, Anthony Wlodarski, secretary, and Stanley Strzelecki, treasurer.</p>
   <p>Then followed an exhaustive discussion [to determine] whether or not the League should send delegates to the convention of the International League of Building and Loan Associations, to be held on September 11 and 12, 1918, at Streator, Illinois. Messrs. Grzegorzewski and Wachowski opposed sending delegates of the League to this convention. They based their arguments on the fact that the International League demands prohibitive membership dues. These fees have to be paid by the individual building and loan associations. The International League, moreover, is of no benefit to the Polish building and loan associations, since for the money obtained from Polish groups it advertises its building and loan associations in non-Polish newspapers. The Poles gain nothing by such advertisements, since such non-Polish newspapers never reach the hands of Polish readers. After a thorough consideration of this important matter it was unanimously decided to sever connections with <pb facs="5423968_4_1607.jpg" n="6"/>the International League and to cease making any future payments into its treasury. The money collected from individual building and loan associations affiliated with the League of Polish Building and Loan Associations of Illinois and intended for the International League was to be retained by the Polish League. The administration of the Polish League is to use the money so collected to purchase advertising space in the Polish newspapers in Chicago. This will be of more benefit to all the individual building and loan associations. The administration of the Polish League was ordered to communicate immediately with all Polish building and loan associations of which representatives were not present at this meeting, warning such associations against making any direct or indirect payments to the International League. It was established that the officials of the International League were Germans and Jews, whose sole interest was not the welfare of the Polish building and loan associations but rather their own financial profit. It was also recommended that this warning be printed in all the Polish newspapers. The Polish reporters present at this meeting promised to have the warning published in the Monday editions of <pb facs="5423968_4_1608.jpg" n="7"/>their respective newspapers.</p>
   <p>With respect to the question of refusing payment out of building and loan association funds to so-called alien enemies in accordance with the requirements of the law it was decided to comply with the demands of the federal authorities; with this reservation, however, that whenever a building and loan association fails to observe such regulations, it does so at its own risk. It was recommended that the secretaries of individual building and loan associations extend courteous treatment to members wishing to withdraw their savings. Such members should have the law against such withdrawals explained to them. This will prevent a feeling of ill will against the building and loan associations on the part of those to whom the law applies.</p>
   <p>The question of fire insurance was left in the hands of the special committee <pb facs="5423968_4_1609.jpg" n="8"/>selected for this purpose. It will give a report of its accomplishments at the next regular session of the Polish League.</p>
   <p>The final item in the order of the day was the Question of the date when the Polish League shall hold its next regular session. It was seen from past experience that Saturday is not a very convenient day on which to hold such meetings. Many delegates and representatives have been unable to attend meetings [on Saturday] because of matters requiring their presence elsewhere. After thorough discussion it was decided to leave the disposition of the matter to the forthcoming annual meeting. It was also decided that the next regular session of the Polish League shall be held three months from now, on a Sunday, at 3 P. M.. The place of the next meeting is to be designated by the administration of the Polish League after coming to an understanding with the administration of one of the associations belonging to the League. Having completed the business of the day, the meeting was adjourned at 6:30 P. M.. The administration of the Casimir Pulaski Building and Loan Association, in <pb facs="5423968_4_1610.jpg" n="9"/>the quarters of which this meeting of the League of Polish Building and Loan Associations had been held, invited the delegates present to participate in an informal luncheon as guests of the Pulaski Association. The luncheon had been prepared at the personal expense of the administration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
