<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-10">Feb. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">War and Runs on Banks</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0661</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0661.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-10">Feb. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WAR AND RUNS ON BANKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday we called your attention to the declaration of the Government of the United States that it would not touch any money deposited in the banks, or the personal assets of any foreigners, in the event of a war with Germany.</p>
   <p>This should calm all those who do not understand the situation, and, fearing we do not know what, hurry to the banks and postal savings banks to withdraw their deposits.</p>
   <p>New York's Nowiny Codzienne (Daily News) has published a rather severe reprimand against those who run to the banks for their money in order to hide it in their mattresses,to the great joy of all sorts of burglars and thieves. Among other things it writes:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0662.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"There will be a war! Indeed there will! A war which in the first place will take away all the money which the Poles have on deposit in banks. At least this is what one can deduce from the fact that many Poles are rushing to withdraw their money in order to hide it under the stove or in a mattress, so that thieves will have something to steal.</p>
   <p>"Listen, people! The Prussians will probably sprout wings and fly across the Atlantic, leaving their country for the Allies to plunder, in order to fly to America for the purpose of taking the money that the Poles have on deposit in the banks here.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, run to the banks and get your money!</p>
   <p>"Oh people, people! What are you afraid of? What is the sense of this? If war does break out in the worst contingency, America will manufacture guns <pb facs="5423968_4_0663.jpg" n="3"/>and ammunition as fast as she can to send to Europe, because on this will its chief support of the Allies be based. The result of this will be such that the production of factories will be even greater than it is now, that earnings will increase, because already many factories are working day and night.</p>
   <p>"Do you know that right now America has more than half of all the gold in the world? When war breaks out even more of it will be sent here, because the Allies will pay for their arms and ammunition. And is it not silly to suppose that this, the wealthiest country in the world, should reach for the money which you have on deposit in the banks?"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
