<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-12">June 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Too Many "Uniformed Slackers"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0227</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0227.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-12">June 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TOO MANY "UNIFORMED SLACKERS"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>American society already has too many so-called uniformed slackers. Any father who is fairly wealthy or who has a certain amount of political influence finds ways and means to get for his son, who is well fed and well built and would make a fine soldier, an officer's post with the American army or navy. And this strong, healthy, well-provided young man parades through the streets of American cities in the uniform of an officer, draws a salary, enjoys himself, and does nothing, since he is not qualified for any read army work. There are now thousands of such officer parasites connected with various commissions and departments who could go to France, since the work they do could be done by any teen-age girl. And they are so sure of themselves, so arrogant because of the influence backing the that they sneer quietly among themselves at those who have gone or will go to the battlefront in Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0228.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>American society tolerated these uniformed dandies for a long time. Finally, however, Congressman Martin B. Hadden of Chicago introduced a resolution that military offices be cleared of young officers capable of active service. Confusion arose among the parasites, since, as a result of this resolution, a checkup began of the officer strength in the offices of all army departments.</p>
   <p>The same thing which has happened in American army circles has happened, on a much smaller scale, in our own Polish army. Our army too has accumulated its "uniformed slackers", sarcastically referred to by some as "blue generals with canes." We do not refer here to officials or recruiting officers who really work unceasingly, who stay here only because they must, who, although they are more than anxious to go to France, are held here on orders of the Military Commision because they are effective agitators or good speakers. But, leaving these men aside, there are a great many real parasites who have not brought in a single recruit--or if they have, it was because somebody else, unknown and unrewarded, did it for them. And these officer parasites strut about, initiating profitless projects, subjecting the meager treasury of the Polish <pb facs="5423968_4_0229.jpg" n="3"/>Army to large and useless expenditures. Things came to a point where Major Kozlowski's attention was turned to this abnormal condition. Dziennik Narodowy writes:</p>
   <p>"One of the recruiting officials in New York decided to create a 'Corps of Polish Amazons'. He sent out press releases and went about organizing his 'Corps,' even working out a set of bylaws. When Major Kozlowski, Chief of the Polish Military Commission, learned of this, he abolished the 'Polish Amazons' with one stroke of his pen in the following statement:</p>
   <p>"'Order to all recruiting workers: I prohibit any recruiting workers under the jurisdiction of the Polish Military Commission from creating any new organizations, women's or otherwise, without my approval of such organizations; I prohibit also the announcement of unapproved projects in the press. Any recruiting officer who acts contrary to this order will be immediately suspended and discharged from the service.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0230.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"'The announcement in New York of the organization of an Amazon Corps was made during my absence and without my knowledge. Announcements which were published in the Bulletin and in other Polish newspapers should be disregarded as not approved by me and by the Polish Military Commission.</p>
   <p>"'Major J. Kozlowski, June 2, 1918.'"</p>
   <p>Dziennik Narodowy, in publishing the above statement, severely criticized the recruiting officers on its own account, claiming that they are only recruiting workers and not actual officers. The matter was also taken up by Dziennik Chicagoski, which wrote in Monday's issue:</p>
   <p>"Saturday's Dziennik Narodowy, in publishing Major Kozlowski's statement, added on its own account a short note expressing the hope that major Kozlowski will give his attention to clearing up conditions among recruiting workers. We too are of this opinion, and we agree with the opinion, more widely expressed, that the methods and the control of recruiting workers are <pb facs="5423968_4_0231.jpg" n="5"/>in need of regulation; recruiting officers should be selected only from among men with irreproachable records. After the energetic action of Major Kozlowski in one instance, we look forward to further action on his part, long awaited because it is necessary."</p>
   <p>Without going into Dziennik Chicagoski's demands, we mention merely that reorganization is the more necessary in that the Polish Army in France is suffering from a real lack of officers. In the meantime, there are a great many of them here in the United States actually doing nothing, since they are neither speakers, nor organizers, nor good office workers, while they could be of good use in the army. We feel that it is high time that the young, strong men, especially those with military experience, be sent to France, while the recruiting work here be carried on by those who do not qualify for active service either physically or perhaps for family reasons, for there have accumulated among us, as among the Americans, too many "uniformed slackers".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
