<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>, 
<date when="1916-02-10">Feb. 10, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Penalty of Weakness</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0692</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0692.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>, 
<date when="1916-02-10">Feb. 10, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE PENALTY OF WEAKNESS</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a nation we have the bad habit of referring every effect to a convenient cause, or a spectacular one. The remote results of national action and the consequences which flow from unadvertised deeds, we are prone to forget. Wherefore, it may be well to conduct a very short catechism on the sorrowful history of a nation which is now much in the public eye.</p>
   <p>The question is; "Why is Poland ruined and starving today?" The answer:</p>
   <p>Because she was too weak to resist the royal robbers led by Frederick the Great, in 1772. If Poland had been an independent nation, her sufferings during the war would have been comparatively mild.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0693.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>She is too big to be treated like Belgium; even Belgian woes have been less severe than those of the Poles. Poland would have been independent if she had been strong enough to resist that first invasion of her territory. She never has lacked patriotism. Her crime was weakness. She had not made ready to refend herself in a world full of wolfish kings; she had not taken the plain warning given by Frederick's earlier invasion of Silesia. All her woes today date back to that weakness 144 years ago.</p>
   <p>So much is certain: no thoughtful student of history would dream of denying it. What follows is speculation, but it has a strong basis of probability. If Poland had been strong enough to sustain herself, the chances are that the present war would never have occurred. Alone, among the peoples of central Europe, the Poles were passionately devoted to liberty. With a free Poland on one side and a free France on the other, <pb facs="5423968_4_0694.jpg" n="3"/>the reactionaries of Berlin and Vienna could never have dominated Germany and without such domination the great war would have been impossible.</p>
   <p>The moral seems to be, that if we want to insure the liberty of our great grandchildren and the peace of the world, we had better prepare to defend our country against any royal schemes for world power.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
