<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-06-29">June 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To the Women Readers of the Alliance Papers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-06-29">June 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE WOMEN READERS OF THE ALLIANCE PAPERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I envy those [women] who, not having behind them years of struggling with the pen, so willingly and boldly place their names upon the list of candidates for editorships of the Women's Section in the Alliance papers, while to me, who am accustomed to putting my thoughts on paper, that task seems today so difficult that I approach it only with a great many fears and doubts. I ask myself whether, after living so long in the quiet of home, I shall be able to grasp the wide horizons of thought in the present political situation which, like the most terrible of hurricanes, has enveloped the whole world, involving to an ever-increasing extent the immortal right of independent Poland to exist. It could almost be said that, today, Poland stands in the very center of international politics. But it stands there not as a power, regulating European affairs through the influence of its strength; it stands rather as a specter of past wrongs, the just righting of which will finally open a new era of progress for the nations of Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1183.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the face of Poland's position with reference to politics in general, the conduct of Poles ought always to have personal integrity in view, rather than small-souled arrogance in the analysis of Polish affairs, or small-souled bows to enemy nations, or untimely sneers at those which, according to the demands of war, turn to us with increasing sympathy or fear--that is, with an excess of promises or threats. Let us await the future with dignity and tranquillity, but let us not wait inactively, but with redoubled elasticity and wisdom in our deeds. As many of us as there are, let each man and woman take upon himself or herself duties in accordance with his own powers, the purpose of which should be either a preparation of political influence for the final moments of the present war (that is, the determination of peace terms) or increasing effort toward raising our national worth in education, art, science, commerce, and industry, in family, social, organizational, and community life. Our future depends upon our understanding and fulfillment of these duties.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, we must remember that we are living in times of a war that has reached even the United States, and that the tendencies of the United States <pb facs="5423968_4_1184.jpg" n="3"/>are united with the ideals of the Polish element in America more unqualifiedly than ever before. The politically deep and philosophically trained mind of the highest representative of North America, President Wilson, has taken the Polish question into its wise and just consideration in a way truly beneficial to us because it is based upon a real knowledge of facts, and regards us in respect to the American-European war, not as ordinary citizens, but as voluntary debtors and friends of everything connected with the welfare of the United States. This is another question that requires a great deal of tact and personal integrity on the part of both men and women. For let us consider that a mother must give up her mature, intellectually and physically fully developed offspring who, perhaps, may never be returned to her. To this self-denial for the good of one's real and adopted homelands, to this alert citizenship, she must be encouraged today, her path to this duty lighted, the weaknesses of her heart removed, her will and sense of honor strengthened. How great and, at the same time, how terrible and difficult this task appears to the writer. The difficulties mount as we turn to the third, and perhaps most important, women's duty at the present time--that is, awakening the sympathy of the Poles in America for <pb facs="5423968_4_1185.jpg" n="4"/>the poverty and misery of the Poles in Poland. For what, after all, is happening to our collections and offerings for those who, drenched with blood and exhausted by every sort of torture, are fighting with feverish enthusiasm for the future of the Polish nation? Have we changed our styles, perhaps, as was considered at the beginning of the war, in order to contribute the money thus saved to the benefit of the poor in Poland, or have we dispensed with any household superfluities, or have we reached into our funds in American banks in order to ease, at least partially, the misery in Poland? I shall not answer these questions, for I believe firmly that whoever has not done this until now will do so the moment he comprehends the whole greatness and terribleness of present-day events. At that, the fact that the Poles in the United States have thus far gathered only so small a sum for the Polish cause is perhaps not wholly their fault, but rather the fault of those who, in describing conditions, had not the eloquence of pen to bring forth, in all its naked truth, the terrible fate of our beloved homeland. Had there been more genuises like the late [Henryk] Sienkiewicz or Paderewski, who is now working with us, the offerings for Poland would have grown and mounted with each day and year, instead of weakening <pb facs="5423968_4_1186.jpg" n="5"/>and diminishing.</p>
   <p>That diminishment represents our psychological weakness and political immaturity. Let us observe the Americans, who need but one day to collect more for war purposes in only one city than we have collected for the Polish cause during the whole course of the war. Can it be that the Pole values his dollar, locked away in a bank, more than the honor of aiding his starving homeland?</p>
   <p>But I desire to interest the readers of Zgoda not only with a discussion of political questions. Of no less importance to us are tasks of a social, educational, or economic nature; presenting them in their proper light, raising the level of our culture will enable us, at the same time, to understand more deeply our present national duties. In discussing these questions, we shall observe the young women being educated in the high schools and universities, as well as those who are working in stores and factories--young women who in order best to fulfill their duties to themselves and the Polish element in general, are in need of someone to take an interest in them and their fate, so often sad. Nothing <pb facs="5423968_4_1187.jpg" n="6"/>so facilitates individual progress as an analysis of the shortcomings and working conditions which, in any case, determine the power and strength of every nation. To think means to progress, to judge, condemn , or praise means to change the conditions of existence from bad to good. It is in this power of judgment and wise criticism that all free nations have laid the foundation for their development, and it is in this power of judgment and just condemnation or praise that our Polish-American community must find the means of escaping the retrogression and financial selfishness that now bind it.</p>
   <p>In taking up the duties of editor of the Women's Section of the Alliance papers, I did so not for the purpose of adding to the journalistic material, of which there is no lack in Polish and American journalism, but to co-operate with you, my women readers for our national, social, organizational, and general cultural, good. A number of year's work and disappointments in Chicago have convinced me that that which a person carries in his heart and in his willingly expressed thoughts, is communicated to those around one, despite the greatest obstacles. For the sixteen years of my stay in Chicago, I have tried, for example, to the <pb facs="5423968_4_1188.jpg" n="7"/>best of my ability, to raise the intellectual level of the youth around me; however, in every enterprise of this nature, my work was often paralyzed or reduced to the minumum of its influence. In view of this, nothing remained to me, through this whole time, excepting the maintenance of a school of music. Today, however, I observe with the greatest satisfaction that a large percentage of the students of this school of mine, through perservance and wise mental effort, now are earning laurels in the high schools and universities of Chicago. I regard this highly desired (though unexpected) result as the highest pedagogical honor, if my influence has been of any value. In order to increase it, I should like, through the columns of the Women's Sections in the Alliance papers that have been entrusted to my care, to establish the most extensive possible relations with the mothers of the numerous Polish families who, despite willingness, do not know how to, or cannot, persevere in their duty of giving their children the advantage of higher education after they have gone through the preliminary public school. In the meantime, life becomes more difficult from day to day for individuals who have no specialized or professional training.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1189.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Let woman enter the struggle for life prepared with an intellectual skill of one kind or another, artistic, technical, or commercial; let her be educated systematically and thoroughly, not in a superficial manner. But in her pursuit of a career, let no Polish woman forget the Polish origin of her family; she must reaffirm it, always and everywhere, by work for the good of Poland. For this wide range of work that is being laid out before us by present-day events, we must join hands for the mutual uplifting of our spirits, for the cleansing of our hearts, and for the crushing of retrogression in all its forms.</p>
   <p>Let us not think that the rebirth of Poland will happen of itself, simply because it depends upon our regaining what was taken from us by force. Not at all. We must approach this event with a knowledge of our own intellectual and moral transformation, with a reform of our emotions, our processes of thought, and our actions. For, after all, it was a lack of intelligence that caused us to lose the heritage of our forefathers; on regaining it, we can hold it and use it toward better aims only when, curbing the impulsiveness of our emotions, we manage <pb facs="5423968_4_1190.jpg" n="9"/>to control them by the strength of our minds, wills, and spirit. Our collapse was caused by an exaggerated idea of freedom which should not be renewed now without including a wisely planned discipline on the one hand and a national solidarity on the other. Only then, when we invest reborn Poland with strength of mind and will, can we erase from history our weaknesses, our powerlessness, our disunion, disharmony and retrogressiveness, and bring to the fore that which will constitute our strength, our energy, and our creativeness, as well as the universal shaping of our relations for the individual and national good.</p>
   <p>Let us apply ourselves to this work with mutual confidence and, first of all, with faith in the fact that victory depends upon our own deeds and transformations.</p>
   <p>Dr. Anna Wyczolkowski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
