<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-15">Oct. 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Solemn High Mass Celebrated at Holy Trinity Church for Success of Polish Army</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0468</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0468.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-15">Oct. 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SOLEMN HIGH MASS CELEBRATED AT HOLY TRINITY CHURCH FOR SUCCESS OF POLISH ARMY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today at 10:15 in the morning, a solemn high mass was celebrated at Holy Trinity Church for the Polish Army that is now being recruited in the United States. At the head of the parade which started out from the Polish Women's Alliance Hall, to the strains of a Falcon band, at about ten o'clock, marched the Citizens' Committee in the persons of John F. Smulski, M. Perlowski, W. Szrojda, A. Grochowski, and T. M. Helinski, and recruiting officers W. N. Skarzyynski and J. Chrzanowski. They were followed by Mrs. M. Milewski, member of the board of directors of the Polish National Alliance, Mrs. Anna Neuman, president of the Polish Women's Alliance, Mrs. W. Wolowski, treasurer of the same organization, and Mrs. Jankiewicz, of the Women's Department of the Polish National Alliance. Behind them marched six uniformed Falcons, carrying the American flag, and more than two hundred volunteers to the Polish Army who will depart today for the training camp at Niagara-on-the-Lake in Ontario, Canada.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0469.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Behind the soldiers marched a great many private individuals and friends and relatives of the volunteers, among whom we noticed Joseph Kukulski, F. Bradel, secretary of Council 39, Polish National Alliance, and Joseph Tyrakowski, members of the Citizens' Committee for Town of Lake. Also present at the church ceremony were Ignace Paderewski and his wife, Madam Helen Paderewski.</p>
   <p>Mass was celebrated by the Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, pastor of Holy Trinity Church, who also delivered the farewell sermon to the departing soldiers. In his beautiful sermon, the Reverend Sztuczko touched upon the famous deeds of our forefathers, who always fought with clear hearts and consciences, and who never blemished their honor by any unworthy deed. The Reverend Sztuczko called upon the volunteers to fight for Poland in the same spirit, and said that the blessing of God will be upon them. At the conclusion of the services, Father Sztuczko pronounced his blessing upon the volunteers to the Polish Army. A photograph was taken in front of the church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
