<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XXX, No. 24,
<date when="1936-06-11">June 11, 1936</date><title level="a">The Largest Polish Brewery in the United States Only Poles May Be Stockholders; Million Barrels of Beer Have Been Brewed Since its Existence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1487</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1487.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XXX, No. 24,
<date when="1936-06-11">June 11, 1936</date><title level="a">THE LARGEST POLISH BREWERY IN THE UNITED STATES ONLY POLES MAY BE STOCKHOLDERS; MILLION BARRELS OF BEER HAVE BEEN BREWED SINCE ITS EXISTENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the leading Polish enterprises in the United States is the White Eagle Brewing Company, organized on the 21st of November, 1899, by the late John F. and Francis Czaja, Adam Czaja, son of John F., and Bernard and Anna Maciejewski. Originally, the brewery was located near St. Adalbert's church at 18th street and Ashland avenue, the present location of Pulaski Hall, which is still owned by the brewery.</p>
   <p>EXPANSION OF THE BREWERY</p>
   <p>In 1907 the White Eagle Brewing Company bought out the Illinois Brewing and Malting Company, located at 3735-35 S. Racine avenue. As soon as the transaction was completed, the White Eagle Brewing Company moved in. At the same time the company reorganized an incorporated, accepting only Poles as its shareholders.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1488.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following officers were elected to conduct the business of the newly incorporated company:</p>
   <p>Leonard Rutkowski, president; J. F. Balcer, vice-president; S. Wlek-linski, cashier; Jan A. Pelka, secretary.</p>
   <p>The following were made directors B. L. Maciejewski, Leonard Rutkowski, S. Belinski, S. Wleklinski, J. A. Cichocki, F. Gorzynski, H. Nowak, Piotr Niedzwieoki, J. Baller, Jan A. Relika</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
