<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 71,
<date when="1921-11-02">Nov. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">How Many of Us in Chicago Feel Being Children of Polish Extraction?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 71,
<date when="1921-11-02">Nov. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">HOW MANY OF US IN CHICAGO FEEL BEING CHILDREN OF POLISH EXTRACTION?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only once in the lives of Poles, men, women and children, of the city of Chicago, have we the possibility of witnessing and heartily greeting one of the greatest army leaders in the world, Marshal Foch, coming to America from France, and who this Sunday will be greeted by many groups and organizations, or, in other words, by every loyal Pole.</p>
   <p>Germans and other foes of the Poles in Chicago openly allege that the American Polish citizen, speaking in general about the massive Chicago Polonia, will not understand and will, therefore, be unable to benefit from the marshal's presence for the cause of Polish affairs.</p>
   <p>Those who offered their chests as targets during the war for Poland; those who fought and shed blood in order to protect the world from the German whip and boot, and who are experienced in knowing what is best for anything that is Polish, have already given an answer to their enemies with this public announcement. This Sunday, attired in the same uniforms that <pb facs="5423968_4_0114.jpg" n="2"/>we wore when we fought in France and Poland, we will be present to greet Marshal Foch. The Polish National Alliance, the Polish Roman Catholic Union, the Polish Alma Mater, the Women's Alliance, the Polish Falcons' Organization, the Polish World War Veterans Organization, the Polish Armies Alliance, the Catholic Foresters Society, and many other groups will take an active part in the coming parade and demonstration in honor of Marshal Foch. Every Polish pastor in Chicago was informed and invited to encourage every Polish member residing in the parish to participate in this great fete for a great man, Marshal Foch. From Polish pulpits came the request and the urge to be present at the parade, which will march beneath the colors of a Polish banner. He who is alive and believes in God and loves Poland, let him stand under the banners of free America, Poland, and friendly France, next Sunday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
