<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-30">Apr. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Draft</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0553</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0553.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-30">Apr. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE DRAFT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Congress of the United States, by an overwhelming majority--one can almost say unanimously--passed the conscription bill for the entire country, accepting in its entirety the war bill introduced by the government.</p>
   <p>Even the most enthusiastic supporters of this bill did not expect that the opposition in both houses of Congress would diminish to such an insignificant number, because in the Lower House 397 voted for the bill and only 24 against it, while in the Senate 81 Senators voted for the bill, and only 8 against, and these last few who voted against the bill were known from previous filibustering performances, headed by La Follette. Even Speaker Champ Clark, who delivered an ardent speech against conscription, changed his mind in the end and voted for the bill.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0554.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This vote in Congress is not only a tremendous victory for the government in Washington, but the best indication that the states are getting seriously to work to defeat the Germans, and that they will make every effort to help the Allies conquer the Teutons. A man who, today, can disregard all the traditions of the past in regard to war, who can in one day cast seven billion dollars on the side of the Allies, and on the next day introduce the military draft, will also know how to persevere to the end, even if he were forced to make even greater sacrifices.</p>
   <p>Now the people of the United States know that war is not a game and that, since the country has entered this war, it cannot be concluded without a satisfactory solution to the problems which brought it on. War demands innumerable sacrifices, but the whole country is ready to make them.</p>
   <p>At the same time that it passed the conscription bill, the Senate passed an amendment permitting volunteer corps to be raised in the United States which can be recruited from among those who do not meet the requirements of the <pb facs="5423968_4_0555.jpg" n="3"/>draft, either because of age, or because they do not come under this law. If the House of Representatives accepts this amendment, there is hope that former President Roosevelt will secure a commission to organize a volunteer division which is to go to the Western Front in France. On the same basis the government could sanction the raising of other volunteer divisions, and then the Falcons would have the opportunity of raising the Kosciusko Army, which, at their special convention at Pittsburgh, they offered to the President of the United States.</p>
   <p>It is true, however, that the conscription bill which was passed Saturday is not quite complete, because both houses have not as yet established the age limits within which every citizen may be called to serve. But this is a trifling detail which the joint Congressional committee will settle and present to both houses of Congress.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the popular wish of the entire nation has been realized. Since the volunteer system of recruiting men was a disappointment, the government <pb facs="5423968_4_0556.jpg" n="4"/>had no choice but to pass the conscription bill. The lesson which England taught the world, at a very high cost to herself and the cause of the Allies, was not ignored. The United States today cannot commit the same errors that others have committed. Now, at last, those in Berlin will understand that all their calculations on the disorganization and the weakness of America were wrong.</p>
   <p>When all calculations miscarry, when plans begin breaking down in all directions, then the fiction of power will no longer help, and they must finally realize that they cannot conquer the world, and that the longer the war lasts the greater the bills will be, and the greater the hatred and the desire for revenge. Some of the German newspapers already realize this full well, and the entire German nation will now, no doubt, realize that the passing of the conscription bill in the United States means the eventual destruction and complete annihilation of Germanic militarism and its desire to conquer the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
