<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-20">Sept. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Poles and the Fourth Liberty Bonds</title><title level="a" type="sub">Resolutions Adopted at Conference of Representatives of Chicago Poles at the Headquarters of the Central Committee, Thursday, September 19, 1918.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-20">Sept. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO POLES AND THE FOURTH LIBERTY BONDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Resolutions Adopted at Conference of Representatives of Chicago Poles at the Headquarters of the Central Committee, Thursday, September 19, 1918.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Representatives of every Polish district were present.</p>
   <p>Mr. Felix Strechmans, Federal Director of Liberty Loans, presided at the meeting.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vincent Jozwiakowski, vice-president of the Northwestern Trust and Savings Bank, was called upon to act as recording secretary.</p>
   <p>In accordance with the plan adopted by headquarters, the creation of a central executive committee of American Poles was in order. This committee is to be composed of representatives of every ward and every <pb facs="5423968_4_0141.jpg" n="2"/>suburb inhabited by Poles.</p>
   <p>Officials of the Polish Central Committee will be selected on Monday, September 23, 1918, at the headquarters of the main committee, 105 West Monroe Street.</p>
   <p>Individual wards and suburbs were grouped into districts. A district vice-president will be selected to conduct the campaign in his or her district.</p>
   <p>The following districts were formed:</p>
   <p>First District: Wards Four, Five, Twenty-nine and Thirty. In other words, the area in and around the following Polish Roman Catholic parishes: Our Lady of Perpetual Help, St. Barbara, SS. Peter and Paul, Five Holy Martyrs, St. Joseph, Sacred Heart of Jesus and St. John of God.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0142.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Second District: Wards Eight and Nine, or the following parishes: St. Michael Archangel, St. Magdalene, Immaculate Conception of the Blessed Virgin Mary, St. Florian (in Hegewisch), St. Florian (in Kensington), Ascension of Blessed Virgin Mary (in West Pullman), and the suburbs of West Hammond, Harvey, Blue Island, Posen, and Chicago Heights.</p>
   <p>Third District: Wards Eleven and Twelve and the Township of Cicero. It will take in the following parishes: St. Adalbert, St. Ann, St. Casimir, The Good Shepherd, Our Lady of Czenstochowa (in Hawthorne), and St. Valentine (in Grant Works).</p>
   <p>Fourth District: Wards Fifteen, Sixteen, Seventeen and Twenty-eight, comprising the following parishes: St. Helen, St. Stanislaus Kostka, Holy Trinity, St. John Cantius, St. Mary of Angels, Holy Innocents, St. Stephen, and St. Hegewisch.</p>
   <p>Fifth District: Wards Twenty-seven, Thirty-three and Thirty-five, <pb facs="5423968_4_0143.jpg" n="4"/>comprising the following parishes: St. Hyacinth, Immaculate Heart of Mary, St. Walter, St. Ladislaus, St. Stanislaus Bishop and Martyr, St. James the Apostle, St. Francis of Assisi, St. Constance, and the village of Niles.</p>
   <p>Sixth District: Wards Twenty-four and Twenty-six, taking in the following parishes: St. Josephat, Transfiguration and the village of Evanston.</p>
   <p>Seventh District: Townships of Lyons, Summit, Argo, and Lemont.</p>
   <p>The following gentlemen were elected ward and local vice-presidents: Fourth Ward--Joseph Mendrzycki, 1046 West Thirty-second Street; Fifth Ward--B. F. Zintak, 3663 South Paulina Street; Eighth Ward--Adam Bloch, 8723 Commercial Avenue; Ninth Ward--James Bzdak, 137 East 118 Street; Eleventh Ward--Joseph S. Zientek, 2001 West 18 Street; Twelfth Ward--Victor Pijanowski, 2242 Marshall Boulevard; Fifteenth Ward--Hon. Joseph S. LaBuy, 1001 North Oakley Blvd; Sixteenth Ward--Alderman V. S. Zwiefka, 1226 <pb facs="5423968_4_0144.jpg" n="5"/>Dickson Street, Seventeenth Ward--Jos. Ruszkiewicz, 1536 West Chicago Avenue; Twenty-fourth Ward--Leon Winiecki, 2726 Southport Avenue; Twenty-sixth Ward--Thos. Krowka, 4938 North Western Avenue; Twenty-seventh Ward--John Szwaba, 2801 North Central Park Avenue; Twenty-eighth Ward--Ignace Wroblewski, 2290 Frankfort St.; Twenty-ninth Ward--A. Mazurek, 1646 West Forty-seventh St.; Thirtieth Ward--B.F. Kowalewski, 1259 West Fifty-First Street; Thirty-third Ward--L.F. Zygmunt, 2300 Lorel Avenue; Thirty-fourth Ward--F. J. Majka, 2705 South Kolin Avenue; Thirty-fifth Ward--J.J. Blazejczyk, 4400 Augusta Street; Townships of: Cicero--S. M. Haremski; Blue Island--Peter Feliszak; Posen--Reverend John Robakowski; Harvey--Walter Borys; Chicago Heights--Henry Radajewski; Evanston--Reverend F. Feldheim; North Chicago--M. Przyborski; Lemont--Vincent Buszkiewicz; Summit--Reverend Thomas Bona; Niles--Paul Williams; West Hammond---Paul Kamradt.</p>
   <p>Each of the above-mentioned ward and district officials is to organize a local committee, taking into consideration all the parishes situated in <pb facs="5423968_4_0145.jpg" n="6"/>in a ward. The names of such committeemen are to be presented at the headquarters of the central organization at a meeting to be held on Monday, September 23, 1918.</p>
   <p>Committees on press and publicity, organization, and mass meetings are to be formed, and enough members selected to serve on them at the next meeting.</p>
   <p>The following were selected to form local committees to contact ward vice-presidents:</p>
   <p>Fourth Ward--F. J. Palt, 3205 South Morgan; Fifth Ward--Frank Derdzinski, 1658 W. 38th Street; Eighth Ward--Julian Sadowski, 8834 Commercial Avenue; Frank K. Rydzewski and Alderman M. J. Furman, 8745 Commercial Avenue; Ninth Ward--John Borkowski, Bruno Prystalski, S. Strzelecki, Janas J. Lewandowski, Joseph Spiker, John Demka, L. Kanoza, Francis Kozlowski, John Boza, F. Malak.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0146.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Eleventh Ward--Reverend S. Chylla, John S. Rybicki, Honorable [Judge] I.F. Dankowski, M.S. Bystrzynski, J. Dumanowski, John Dyszel, Ignace Franz.</p>
   <p>Twelfth Ward--Stanley J. Kuflewski, Leon A. Wachowski, John Paprocki, Albert Wachowski, Peter Jezierny.</p>
   <p>Fifteenth Ward--Reverend Peter N. Pyterek, V. Jozwiakowski, Peter Mindak, Leon C. Nyka, John Kempczynski, F. Janiszewski, John Ruszkiewicz, Paul Drymalski, John S. Konopa.</p>
   <p>Sixteenth Ward--Stanley kunz, John Czekala, W. Schrojda, Peter Rostenkowski, Bruno S. Mindak, John A. Piotrowski.</p>
   <p>Seventeenth Ward--T. Wejna, W.J. Suwalski, S. Adamkiewicz, S. Walkowiak, John Jankowski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0147.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Twenty-fourth Ward--Joseph Pionke.</p>
   <p>Twenty-sixth Ward--Reverend F.J. Wojciechowski, Anton Petelczyk, Joseph Hotys.</p>
   <p>Twenty-seventh Ward--Stephen Kolanowski, A.F. Soska, Felix Gorski, Joseph Glomski, Simon Sikorski, N.S, Budzban, Mrs. A. Baranowski.</p>
   <p>Twenty-eighth Ward--V. Slosarczyk, M.Adamowski, Albert Nowak, John M. Nowicki, Walter Armknecht.</p>
   <p>Twenty-ninth Ward--Roman Kowalewski, A. Wlodarski, Edward Trandel, S. Klechamer, Frank Perlowski.</p>
   <p>Thirtieth Ward--C. Tomkiewicz, W. F. Synowiec.</p>
   <p>Thirty-third Ward--J. Lisack, F. Pawlowski, J. Rathnow, Stephen Druzba, <pb facs="5423968_4_0148.jpg" n="9"/>Ignace Kubczak, J. Januszewski.</p>
   <p>Thirty-fourth Ward--John Sierocinski, Walter Pietras, Francis Dumanowski.</p>
   <p>Thirty-fifth Ward--P. Kusinski, Joseph Walienski, John Kulik.</p>
   <p>Townships: Cicero--V. Kasperski, F. Skrzydlewski, and Anthony Maciejewski.</p>
   <p>Blue Island--Stanley Swiercz, John Synakiewicz.</p>
   <p>Posen--John Mech, Bruno Grzondzinski.</p>
   <p>Chicago Heights--Joseph Ziemba.</p>
   <p>Lemont--Walter Chojnacki.</p>
   <p>Summit--Frank Brodnicki.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0149.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Niles--William Wawrzynkiewicz, Francis Fuhl.</p>
   <p>Evanston--A. Cieslak.</p>
   <p>West Kammond--Reverend W. Nowakowski, Adam Stachowicz.</p>
   <p>Harvey--Reverend Dominic Zinc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
