<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-02-11">Feb. 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Symphonic Prelude to Proserity</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0875</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0875.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-02-11">Feb. 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A SYMPHONIC PRELUDE TO PROSERITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American Press is continually heralding that good times are in the offing, while everything else seems to prove that the high cost of living and social burdens are steadily increasing with no sign or relief. The proclaiming of optimistic hopes, under such circumstances, is a sign of thoughtlessness and of perversion on the part of the hypocritical and two-faced American newspapers whose hidden purpose is to delude the workingman with the hope of prosperity, and to sustain in him a thoughtless disposition which will forestall any reflection by which he could feel the necessity to use his money sparingly and save it for the dark hours, instead of dissipating it for trifles and for luxury. Business would suffer financial losses if the workingman started to save; therefore, he is induced to spend even the last dollar for enjoyment in the expectation of prosperity.</p>
   <p>In the meanwhile Mr. Garrison, the Secretary of War, paints for us a different picture of the sad reality which sounds like a sharp dissonance in the midst of that prosperity symphony. It appears that the pacifying serenades of Mr. Bryan and of other world pacifists have rocked and stilled our Government to such an extent that, to-day, we can scarcely compete with other countries in natters of national defense and welfare.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0876.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the gloomy picture of our political and economic shortcomings dwells the futile hope for prosperity in the near future, and the strains of the misleading tune of the symphonic prelude, Prosperity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
