<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-26">Sept. 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Our Incompetent Police]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0074</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0074.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-26">Sept. 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[OUR INCOMPETENT POLICE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Killings "by mistake" are making our "zealous" Chicago police more notorious every day. Policeman Otto Klein, attached to the Maxwell Station, fatally wounded Mr. A. Rudnik, a victim of mistaken identity, when the latter did not heed his command to stop. The policeman, without any thought of the consequences, shot after the fleeing man, killing him. Upon investigation, it was definitely established that the victim was a law abiding-citizen, who, evidently mistaking the police officer for someone else, had decided to run away. Such unthoughtful shooting at people, as if they were hunted animals, brings shame upon our local police, which, under other circumstances, does not manifest such bravery, unless it is to murder the unarmed. Several months ago, some members of the Chicago Detective Bureau shot an innocent Pole, Mr. John Dubinski, under similar circumstances. Shortly thereafter, Mr. Axel Ludman, an innocent man, was also slain. Now a third innocent <pb facs="5423968_4_0075.jpg" n="2"/>victim has become a target for the bullets of the gunwielders. Indeed, killings such as these show an evident disregard of human life on the part of the police scoundrels. They overlook actual bandits and murderers and slaughter law-abiding and peaceful people. They cannot track down culprits who plant bombs destroying human life and property. Several murders have been committed in Chicago, but so far the Chicago police has not been able to apprehend the guilty persons. Gambling and vice are flourishing openly in this city, but our celebrated police pays no attention to this. Under the very noses of the police, to use the vernacular, in the immediate vicinity of the West Side Police Station, thieves robbed the Chotinier Brothers of ten thousand dollars and, in addition, beat their victims severely. But, even in this instance, the police is unable to find the culprits. One home on the North Side was robbed on four different occasions at close intervals. But here also the police is unable to track down the burglars. Out of every hundred cases of robbery, larceny, murder, and assault, only two or three are successfully handled by the police. It seems as though our publicly maintained keepers of public <pb facs="5423968_4_0076.jpg" n="3"/>safety are only capable of shooting at innocent people, drinking in taverns, sleeping in some corners or molesting young girls and peaceful passers-by. It seems that our city has the most incompetent police force. Because of this every citizen should prevail upon his alderman to remedy these shameful conditions in the police department. As if it were not enough that the innocent citizens are attacked and murdered by bandits, now we find that the police also aids them "by mistake" in their nefarious deeds. People of Chicago are uncertain of life or property in a city where several million dollars are spent annually on the police.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
