<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-15">Dec. 15, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">What Does the Constitution of the United States Give Us?</title><title level="a" type="sub">It Is Our Protection against Injustice</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1075</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1075.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-15">Dec. 15, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT DOES THE CONSTITUTION OF THE UNITED STATES GIVE US?</title><title level="a" type="sub">It Is Our Protection Against Injustice</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every person should read and study the Constitution of the United States in order to become familiar with his rights and duties. It is the highest and strongest statute of this country, which offers individual rights to the cities and states. Become familiar with some of the most important facts. Know that the Constitution of the United States provides for the following:</p>
   <p>1) It maintains a lasting government that is responsible for the protection and welfare of the people.</p>
   <p>2) It gives the right of citizenship and the privilege to vote to all nationality groups who have met the requirements of the naturalization laws.</p>
   <p>3) It gives the voters the right to take part in the government by electing their own representatives. It gives the right to anyone, who has the qualifications, to run for office in any branch of the government.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1076.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(The Presidential office is the only public office that is not open to any naturalized citizen).</p>
   <p>4) It guarantees the free exercise of religious beliefs, "the freedom of speech or of the press, and the right of the people peaceably to assemble and to petition the government for a redress of any grievances".</p>
   <p>5) It protects the right of the people "to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and effects against unreasonable searches and seizures shall not be violated, and no warrants shall issue but upon probable cause, supported by oath or affirmation, and particularly describing the place to be searched and the persons or things to be seized".</p>
   <p>6) All persons are equal according to its laws.</p>
   <p>7) Protection against any injustice is offered. In the event of arrest, no person shall be held to answer for a capital or otherwise infamous crime unless on a</p>
   <p>or indictment of a grand jury, in cases arising in the land or naval forces, or the militia, when in actual service in time of <pb facs="5423968_4_1077.jpg" n="3"/>war or public danger; nor shall any person be subject for the same offense to be twice put in jeopardy of life or limb; nor shall be compelled in any criminal case to be a witness against himself, nor be deprived of life, liberty, or property without due process of law; nor shall private property be taken for private use, without just compensation.</p>
   <p>"In all criminal prosecutions the accused shall enjoy the right to a speedy and public trial by an impartial jury of the state and district wherein the crime shall have been committed, which district shall have been previously ascertained by law; to be informed of the nature and cause of the accusation; to be confronted with the witnesses against him; to have compulsory process for obtaining witnesses in his favor; he shall have the assistance of counsel for his defense.</p>
   <p>"Excessive bail shall not be required, nor excessive fines imposed, nor cruel and unusual punishments inflicted.</p>
   <p>"A well regulated militia being necessary to the security of a free state. The right of the people to keep and bear arms, shall not be infringed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1078.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"In suits at common law, where the value in the controversy shall exceed twenty dollars, the right of a trial by jury shall be preserved, and no fact tried by a jury shall be otherwise re-examined in any court of the United States, than according to the rules of the common law.</p>
   <p>"The enumeration in the constitution of certain rights shall not be construed to deny or disparage others retained by the people.</p>
   <p>"The judicial power of the United States shall not be construed to extend to any suit in law or equity, commenced or prosecuted against one of the United States by citizens of another state or citizens or subjects of any foreign state".</p>
   <p>Become acquainted with the Constitution of the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
