<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-26"> Jan. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">One of Ours</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1546</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1546.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-26"> Jan. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ONE OF OURS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Joseph P. Michalski was born on March 1, 1877, in Sierpiec, Plock County Poland, then under Russian occupation. He received his elementary education in his native town and later some instruction in building and construction from his father, who was a builder. Discontinuing his studies, he emigrated to America, where he was forced to take up some practical trade. He chose bookbinding, in which occupation he became unusually proficient. He arrived in Chicago in 1896 and worked for various bookbinderies, among them the Canky Company of Hammond, Indiana, S. D. Childs, and Shea and Smith.</p>
   <p>Accumulating a little capital and gaining a reputation as a first-class artisan, he decided to work for himself. He opened his own bookbindery in St. John Cantius parish on Carpenter Street. That was in 1917. Soon afterwards he became a partner in the large bookbinding firm of Olszewski and Company, the founder of which had just died. Mr. Michalski became a pillar of the concern and an organizer. He bought and installed the latest and most improved <pb facs="5423968_4_1547.jpg" n="2"/>machinery, so that this firm attained the highest development in its history. In 1919 the name of the firm was changed to American Bookbindery Company, with Mr. Michalski as president; the second partner, Mr. E. G. Mares, became vice-president, and the third partner, Mr. W. J. Andrzejewski, was secretary and treasurer. The business has remained under the same management up to the present time. The American Bookbindery Company is growing splendidly, thanks to the above-mentioned men and especially to Mr. Joseph Michalski, who is a master craftsman and without doubt, the best in his field in the whole Chicago Polonia.</p>
   <p>Mr. Michalski is still a comparatively young man, energetic, a good worker, progressive, and enterprising. There is not the least doubt that the business which he is managing will achieve great success. Personally he enjoys great popularity and the friendship of many. He is a member of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, the Polish National Alliance, the Polish Falcons' Alliance, and the Alliance of Polish Military Societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1548.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We wish to mention that the American Bookbindery Company does most of the work connected with bookbinding for our publishing firm, the Polish Publishing Company. Most of the schoolbooks and novels published by us are bound to our complete satisfaction by the firm managed by Mr. Michalski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
