<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-10-25">Oct. 25, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">How Immigrant Children Are Employed in the United States</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0903</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0903.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-10-25">Oct. 25, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">HOW IMMIGRANT CHILDREN ARE EMPLOYED IN THE UNITED STATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Making artificial flowers, clothing for dolls, stringing pearls and putting safety pins on cards, are just a few of the fifty various jobs young children are given as regular employment, according to the latest report of the Federal Children's Bureau which conducted a special investigation of industrial work performed in the homes, in the state of New Jersey. This investigation was conducted in the following cities of the state of New Jersey: Newark, Patterson, North Bergen, South River, Sayreville, Hammonton, and Vineland.</p>
   <p>With home employment it is very easy to use children and it is one of the main characteristics of home industries, that parents are inclined to harness the young members of their families to work of such nature as was mentioned above. As an example I will cite a family which was visited by an investigator of the Children's Bureau. Three children at the ages of nine, four and three were found opening safety pins, and two others, ages ten and eleven, pinning them on cards; their grandmother and aunt were assisting them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0904.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This investigation was conducted for the benefit of children who had not yet reached their sixteenth birthday. It was discovered that eleven hundred and thirty-one were being used in home work; approximately one-fourth had not yet reached their tenth birthday, and one-fifth were past their fourteenth birthday; nineteen of these children were just six years old, and six of them were even younger.</p>
   <p>In this home work, boys as well a girls are employed, but the number of boys doing this work is usually smaller than that of the girls; the latter, however, are younger.</p>
   <p>Why does the state of New Jersey conduct home work on such a vast scale? This may be explained in the following manner: This state is located near New York and Philadelphia, where a great many industries employ home workers in large numbers.</p>
   <p>The state of New York and Pennsylvania have a special law which does not permit manufacturers, of these states to employ children for factory or home work, and those violating this law are liable to punishment. A similar <pb facs="5423968_4_0905.jpg" n="3"/>law in New Jersey does not prevent children from doing industrial work at home. Why do manufacturers of New York and Pennsylvania send their work to homes in New Jersey? Because very seldom are they held responsible by the state of New Jersey, and at the same time they are escaping the laws enforced by their own states.</p>
   <p>Many industrial branches, using home workers especially the tailoring industry, employ forty-four percent of the children, which usually go over, by certain periods of stagnation, falling in the summer months. The result is, as was proven by the investigation, that more children were employed in home work of this nature in the school period, than during vacation.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, the regular use of children in this work depends chiefly, on how often the manufacturers send work to their homes; however, even in the school period, a majority of he children work from two to three hours a day, and a certain number between three and four hours a day, if they have sufficient material. For many of them this meant the practice of night work. From a number of one thousand and thirty-three children, who were occupied in work of this nature during the school periods forty-six percent usually work after supper; the majority of them work two hours a day, <pb facs="5423968_4_0906.jpg" n="4"/>and the minority from three to five hours a day. The older children work longer than the younger.</p>
   <p>From a number of six hundred and twenty-eight families investigated, a majority explained, that it is necessary for them to do home work, because of financial need. From a numbers of four hundred and seventy-five families, over one half had proof other work beside the home work; their earnings were one thousand four hundred and fifty dollars annually. But this work does not increase the income of a family. From a number of three hundred and thirty-four families, who keep a regular account of income derived from this source of work, over one half had an income of one hundred dollars a year.</p>
   <p>Manufacturers using home work in the state of New Jersey recruits a majority of immigrant families.</p>
   <p>We read in the report of the Children's Bureau, "That an immigrant woman can easily secure home employment; what is more, in that way she does not have to come in contact with those who do not understand her language and habits. Naturally she welcomes the opportunity of securing such employment, <pb facs="5423968_4_0907.jpg" n="5"/>which enables her to increase her family income, even though it may not be by very much. And when she once takes up this work, without a doubt, sooner of later she will begin to demand help from the other members of the family."</p>
   <p>The opinion of the fathers differs in regard to this home employment; some are dissatisfied and complain; in many cases they curse because of such small earning derived from this work; also it keeps them from visiting friends, as they cannot leave the home that has been turned into a factory. Others,however, agree with the wives and encourage them to continue in this work, because they see and opportunity of deriving an income for the upkeep of the family.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
