<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-13">Aug. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to All the Divisions and Branches of the Alliance of Polish Military Societies in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0835</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0835.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-13">Aug. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO ALL THE DIVISIONS AND BRANCHES OF THE ALLIANCE OF POLISH MILITARY SOCIETIES IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Colleagues: A terrible moment has come upon all of Europe. Our entire unfortunate country is covered with the blood of the soldiers of our oppressors, and perhaps already thousands of our brothers have fallen--not only those who were called to the colors of our oppressors, but also innocent and defenseless children, old people and women.</p>
   <p>How much blood and destruction from the hail of enemy bullets has already fallen upon the soil of our poor and unfortunate homeland! Our entire country has now become the prey of our bloodthirsty oppressors, who burn and destroy the entire property of our fathers, brothers, kinsmen, and friends. How many widows and orphans are there already suffering poverty and hunger, perhaps without a roof over their heads, sent about from place to place, seeking shelter before the oncoming enemy in order to save their lives!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0836.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Brothers! This terrible period of poverty and hunger is echoed in our hearts and minds. The voices of the poor orphans and widows reach the ears of us living here in the free land of Washington. Brothers, you who have escaped this terrible period and breathe the air of freedom, come to the help of the poor unfortunate orphans and widows, come to help your poor unfortunate motherland, which is not going through the cruel moments of resurrection. Perhaps these terrible times from which we are now suffering will be the last struggle with our enemies.</p>
   <p>Brothers-in-arms! We appeal to you in the name of Poland, our crucified homeland, in the name of the poor unfortunate widows and orphans who are living through these terrible times. Let us help as brothers. Let us collect donations in order to save from a death of starvation those who are inundated with blood and destruction. Let us offer this widow's mite on the altar of our homeland. Knock at the hearts of our brothers who remain outside our organization, and ask them to answer the call, the voice of our homeland, together with us. Let us knock at the hearts of <pb facs="5423968_4_0837.jpg" n="3"/>the most hardhearted, those who have never taken a sincere interest in the national cause, but have concerned themselves only with international or party members. Let them learn that the general cause, the Polish cause, is a sacred one, for they, too, are the children of one mother--Poland.</p>
   <p>We have proved many times before that the Alliance of Polish Military Societies does not belong to any party, but is concerned only with military and purely patriotic matters relating to Poland, as well as to the country in which we live. For that reason, colleagues, it is our sacred duty, as soldiers, to be the first to answer the call, in order to demonstrate that we are not only good for parades and display but that we are capable of serving the sacred cause.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we are sure that we shall not find within our ranks a single man who would draw aside from a cause of such grave importance as the cause of the homeland. We need an army and we need money.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0838.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As we all know, a military fund for the cause of Poland's independence has been established by the Polish National Alliance. This fund will be under the control of trustworthy people, in whom the Polish community can have absolute confidence, knowing that the money it offers on the altar of the homeland will not be wasted or misappropriated for purposes of party politics. For this reason we ask you kindly to forward all contributions to the treasurer of the Polish National Alliance, who will forward them to the proper place and will acknowledge them through the papers.</p>
   <p>Colleagues! In view of the fact that the United States has announced its neutrality, we cannot think of leaving for Europe to defend our threatened  homeland. Besides, we must wait in order to strike our weakened enemies at the appropriate moment. We dare not meet them too soon, lest we bury the cause of the homeland for centuries. Brothers! Let us always be ready, because we do not know the day or the hour when the bugle will call us to battle. Let us collect a fund and an army before it is too late.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0839.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Colleagues, there are people over there who do not sleep but who watch and follow carefully all matters relating to the present situation. If we are not permitted to offer our lives for the freedom of the widows and orphans left by our brothers who fell on the battlefield from enemy bullets, and perhaps from the bullets of their own brothers fight in the opposite ranks.</p>
   <p>The Alliance of Polish Military Societies need not make any extensive preparations or devise methods to assemble divisions of men and put them through their paces each and every week; for in our ranks are men who are familiar with army tactics, and almost every one of us has served in some European army. Therefore, drill maneuvers once a year are sufficient for us.</p>
   <p>From what we hear, these long drills in the fields and parks, as well as the constant marches with arms along the street, have let the governments of several states to prohibit not only the carrying of guns on the streets <pb facs="5423968_4_0840.jpg" n="6"/>but also the holding of any sort of field drills with arms.</p>
   <p>Therefore, colleagues, we warn you to be always careful. No one should allow himself to be persuaded by some Pharaoh to participate in any kind of mobilization--the kind of mobilization, for instance, which was attempted by the notorious Rylski, whose stupidity might have harmed the entire cause had not sensible people called a halt by publicaly warning everyone. Let us keep cool and await the command of sensible people--the command of the Polish National Alliance to which we belong. Remember that the board of directors of the Polish National Alliance are not sleeping but are watching events carefully in order to know when to act without hurting the good cause.</p>
   <p>The board of directors of the Polish National Alliance have never exposed the branches of the Alliance to a loss. They have always been and always will be their faithful guardians in all matters of general interest. Colleagues, let us go ahead with a slow and even tread, and we shall get further.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0841.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Brothers, let us work shoulder to shoulder! Let us get to work with complete self-effacement. Let us contribute generously to the cause of liberating our homeland, Poland. Let us increase our ranks so that, if required, we may be ready to give the greatest service to the cause of the homeland. Right now we need not words, but action.</p>
   <p>Long live free and independent democratic Poland!</p>
   <p>F. Porzulzek, president.</p>
   <p>W. J. Andrzejewski, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
