<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-09-27">Sept. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Businessmen's Association Creates Huge Polish Food Products Corporation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1682</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1682.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-09-27">Sept. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH BUSINESSMEN'S ASSOCIATION CREATES HUGE POLISH FOOD PRODUCTS CORPORATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Organized three years ago on a wide program of activity in the field of business and industry, the Polish Businessmen's Association of Chicago has now begun to realize some of the projects.</p>
   <p>Having before it a well-defined aim--that of developing Polish business and industry in America, placing it upon the level it should occupy in view of the number of Polish people here, their state of enlightenment, and their economic means--the Association is moving boldly forward with full confidence that the Polish people of Chicago will support its efforts to the fullest extent.</p>
   <p>The first project of the Association the formation of a huge wholesale food products corporation. The necessary capital will be raised through the sale of stock among the Polish people exclusively.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1683.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The enterprise has already been incorporated in accordance with the laws of the state of Illinois, for one hundred thousand dollars under the name "The Associated Polish Businessmen's Corporation".</p>
   <p>Zenon Ulanowski, as president, is at the head of the new corporation. Ulanowski is the proprietor of the Progress Clothing Company at 1165 Milwaukee Avenue. The corporation's offices are located at 1155 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
