<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-12">Jan. 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">To the Citizens of Hawthorne and Vicinity</title><title level="a" type="sub">Businessmen's Association Protests against Dumping Refuse in Abandoned Quarries</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1316</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1316.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-12">Jan. 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE CITIZENS OF HAWTHORNE AND VICINITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Businessmen's Association Protests against Dumping Refuse in Abandoned Quarries</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Undoubtedly, everyone in the Hawthorne area is aware that the quarries in the South and Southwest Sides are being filled with refuse brought from various parts of Chicago. The dumped refuse lies there exposed to the elements until it rots or is set on fire. The stench emanating from it is beyond description, to say nothing of the fact that during the summer it constitutes a danger to health. But this is not all. Due to this unsanitary condition, the value of property in the district depreciates a great deal. For quite a time protests have been made, but so far no steps have been taken to remedy the situation. The local Businessmen's Association has tried to find a solution to the problem. The Association invited an official of the Hawthorne district to one of its meetings and asked him whether or not something could be done. The City Council was also asked. Although many promises have been made, nothing has been accomplished to alleviate this condition.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1317.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>With the coming of spring not so far off, the smell from the refuse dumps will envelop the neighborhood once again. Because of this the Hawthorne Businessmen's Association has resolved to put up a fight to the end.</p>
   <p>A committee has been named to find a solution to this problem. Its members are A. Maciejewski, S. Witkowski, K. Celmera, and S. Sikorski. The committee has engaged an attorney to investigate the matter and to prefer charges, which will be brought before the courts. An attempt will be made to prevent the owners of these stone quarries from permitting the city to dump its refuse on their property.</p>
   <p>To a certain extent, this problem should be solved by the city officials or the Board of Health. No one can understand why the city officials are so slow in taking action in this direction. Maybe it is because they can do nothing about it. That is why an appeal is being made now to all citizens to support this movement. This support, of course, is necessary because litigation costs will reach a considerable sum, too heavy for the <pb facs="5423968_4_1318.jpg" n="3"/>Businessmen's Association to carry alone. Help is needed from every citizen sharing these unpleasant conditions. With the support of all, we will be able to fight this battle to the end.</p>
   <p>This is not a political fight, but a fight to safeguard the health of every citizen living in Hawthorne and vicinity--a fight to protect the health of every family. There is no reason why this community should not be as pleasant to live in as other communites. This locality can be as clean as it was of old, when people from many parts of the city used to come to enjoy the freshness of the atmosphere. Today people keep away from here as if the place were a plague-spot.</p>
   <p>It is felt that the people of this locality are entitled to a good and clean neighborhood, something to be proud of, and that is why an appeal is made for support. In the near future a general mass meeting will be held in one of the larger halls of the community. Everyone is invited to attend. The opinions of others on this question will be of interest.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1319.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Committee of the Hawthorne Businessmen's Association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
