<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-03">Apr. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Entrance into the War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0617</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0617.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-03">Apr. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ENTRANCE INTO THE WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States is at last on the verge of entering the holy war against Germany, a war which it has been approaching by slow, heavy steps for quite some time. The minute the United States steps in, this war will enter a new phase, the end of which will be the rebirth and freedom of all nations.</p>
   <p>Long, too long, had the United States been patient to the point of exasperation before it finally came to the conclusion that Germany would never listen to reason unless she were completely defeated.</p>
   <p>The United States is accepting the challenge, not for selfish reasons, not in the defense of the American rights ignored and violated by Germany, but in the name of civilization, in defense of the freedom of all civilized countries.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0618.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>President Wilson's war proclamation constitutes a historical document of world-wide importance. There can be no doubt about this. For us Poles, this proclamation contains full assurance that America is entering this great world war for those very principles which President Wilson presented in his address of January 22, [1917], before the Senate. In speaking of the freedom of nations, Wilson emphasized the fact that Poland must be united, independent, and autonomous.</p>
   <p>These same great ideals and principles will be incorporated into the war aims of the United States. Therefore, it will be our duty to rally round The Star-Spangled Banner and go wherever our national honor and duty call.</p>
   <p>Only people of low and undeveloped minds could still talk about pacifism, especially when the President of the United States asserts that an honorable war is preferable to a dishonorable peace, and when he guarantees that this will be a war for the rights and freedom of nations, for the peace and security of the world. Only brainless gossipers, only "old grandmothers" of both sexes and all ages, only cowards or wretches cannot or do not want to <pb facs="5423968_4_0619.jpg" n="3"/>see that a great moment in our lives is approaching, a moment in which we will be able to express ourselves through armed action.</p>
   <p>The United States, together with all of Poland, will march by the side of the Allies to a final settlement with the enemy, in whose camp reaction, autocracy, military atrocities, oppression, slavery, and lawlessness are all gathered together.</p>
   <p>All sorts of prussophiles and Austriophiles have tried in vain to get the Polish immigrants to join the camp of these degenerate outcasts of humanity. Today they alone are the admirers of the miserable Prussian reaction and the enemies of their own nation.</p>
   <p>When it comes to proving with action the soundness of the ideals they have been preaching, they hang their socialism up on a nail and throw all their principles into some convenient corner. They take their rusty doctrine out of their pockets only when it can serve as a convenient means of covering up their baseness. And so today, in accordance with their socialist principles, <pb facs="5423968_4_0620.jpg" n="4"/>these same people who have tried to get the young Poles to join the war in the interest of the Kaiser, are now haranguing against the United States' entering the war against Germany.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
