<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-15">Mar. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Reorganize Polish Corporation, Ecciesiastical Goods Company</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1659</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1659.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-15">Mar. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">REORGANIZE POLISH CORPORATION, ECCIESIASTICAL GOODS COMPANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the annual meeting of the stockholders of the Polish corporation, held yesterday, Ecclesiastical Goods Company, the first steps toward reorganizing the Company were taken. It is the only Polish firm of its kind not only in Chicago, but in America.</p>
   <p>The following stockholders were present at yesterday's meeting: Mrs. H. Augustynowicz, A. Rush, County Commissioner A. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, Judge Edmund K. Jarecki, A. G. Urbanski, B. P. Pstrong, Miss <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. Augustynowicz, A. A. Kowalski, J. F. Szatkowski, and John S. Konopa. The new officers and directors are as follows: E. H. Jarecki, president; Miss <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. Augustynowicz, vice president; B. P. Pstrong, secretary, and John S. Konopa, treasurer and manager. The firm was organized fourteen years ago by the late F. Augustynowicz and N. L. Piotrowski. Since the death of Augustynowicz two and a half years ago, the business has been managed by his daughter Helen, who resigned at last night's meeting. The new manager, J. S. Konopa, former secretary <pb facs="5423968_4_1660.jpg" n="2"/>general of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, has many years experience in this line of business. He worked for several years with a similar firm downtown, and when the Ecclesiastical Goods Company was organized, he became its chief representative, remaining in this capacity for seven years.</p>
   <p>In order to expand the corporation's field of activity, the board of directors decided to increase its capital by several thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>The store is located at 1113 Noble Street, not far from Milwaukee Avenue, and directly opposite the Holy Trinity rectory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
