<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-16">Feb. 16, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Fidelity State Bank Will Be Reopened</title><title level="a" type="sub">Avondale and South Chicago Businessmen Come to the Polish Bank's Rescue</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1661</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1661.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-16">Feb. 16, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FIDELITY STATE BANK WILL BE REOPENED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Avondale and South Chicago Businessmen Come to the Polish Bank's Rescue</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Fidelity State Bank, which was closed on the first of February by the state auditor, will probably be reopened next week. This news will probably be greeted with great joy in Avondale, where everyone has waited with great impatience for the results of the work of the Citizens' Committee. The Committee was chosen by the depositors at several meetings held in Warszynski's hall.</p>
   <p>Originally, the Committee consisted of five men: J. S. Bartkowski, chairman, Anthony Hojka, secretary, Ludwig Paczynski of South Chicago, Simon Sikorski, and J. Kirschner. Later, Stephen Kolanowski and Attorney Peter Schwaba were added.</p>
   <p>After a week of arduous labor--labor from morning until late at night for <pb facs="5423968_4_1662.jpg" n="2"/>the last few days--the Committee can now assure the depositors that the bank will reopen and that no one will lose a penny. No one will receive all the money he has on deposit at one time. At the depositors' meeting, it was unanimously decided that half of all the savings deposits would remain in the bank for at least one year. Only on such conditions can the bank be reopened. The other half of the deposits are to remain in the bank for an indefinite period, until such a time as the new board of directors decides that the funds can be released. Those having checking accounts with the bank must leave half of their money on deposit for an indefinite period. The other half can be used for business purposes under certain conditions. In time, however, they will be able to draw out all of their money.</p>
   <p>Through the Committee's efforts, the president of the bank signed over all his property to the institution. The value of this property completely covers the shortage, if any exists. The president's real-estate holdings could not be sold at the present time because of the general stagnation in <pb facs="5423968_4_1663.jpg" n="3"/>the real-estate market caused by the war. The Committee decided, therefore, to collect a large enough fund to cover the shortages and later, by the sale of the real estate, to return the money. A trust fund was created to which the depositors and Avondale businessmen can transfer that half of their deposits which is to remain in the bank for an indefinite period. To date, almost all of the Avondale businessmen have thus transferred their deposits. This was done in part at a meeting held the day before yesterday at the offices of Kolanowski and Krzykowski, and yesterday the Committee solicited the signatures of those who were unable to be present at the meeting. [List of depositors omitted by translator].</p>
   <p>The rest of the businessmen and others who have checking accounts with the Fidelity State Bank will be contacted by the Committee tonight and at the meeting to be held Monday. This meeting will be held at Warszinski's hall at the corner of Central Park Avenue and Wolfram Street. Every depositor should be present and must show his bank book upon entrance into the hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1664.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Committee also collected from businessmen and others a considerable sum for shares in the reorganization of the bank and to further strengthen the trust fund.</p>
   <p>[List of contributors omitted by translator. Total sum collected was $22,150.]</p>
   <p>Further purchases of shares in the new institution will be published on Thursday.</p>
   <p>John M. Kleczewski, the wealthiest Pole in Avondale, pledged a thousand dollars. He is purchasing ten shares and will be a director of the new Fidelity State Bank.</p>
   <p>Depositors having savings accounts with the bank ought to sign as soon as possible the agreement prepared by the Committee. The agreement will bind them to keep half of their deposits in the bank for a period of twelve months.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1665.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Depositors may sign the agreement at the following places: [List omitted by translator.]</p>
   <p>In concluding this report, the depositors are hereby requested to attend the general meeting to be held on Monday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
