<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XXX, No. 24,
<date when="1936-06-11">June 11, 1936</date><title level="a">Polish Roofing Company in South Chicago and its Interesting History</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1484</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1484.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XXX, No. 24,
<date when="1936-06-11">June 11, 1936</date><title level="a">POLISH ROOFING COMPANY IN SOUTH CHICAGO AND ITS INTERESTING HISTORY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The firm Interstate Roofing Company was organized in 1921 by Mr. W. R. Bojanowski and Mr. E. A. Dutkiewicz, who having experience in that line, started their own business in South Chicago. In the beginning they were satisfied with a very small business, which was conducted at a private home, 8043 Coles Avenue. But later on when the business started to grow steadily and gained the confidence of the public, they decided to incorporate it, which was done in 1928.</p>
   <p>Mr. W. R. Bojanowski was the first president of the firm, and Mr. E. A. Dutkiewicz was the secretary and cashier. Mr. G. B. Guzowski was vice-president. In January, 1924, the company bought a warehouse from the Berghoff Brewing Company, which is located near the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad. This warehouse is still used by the company.</p>
   <p>Immediately after the incorporation of the firm the business started to grow and to such an extent that it was necessary to look for a new office location. This was found at 8700 Commercial avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1485.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1927 the company introduced into its business an asphalt department equipped with modern machinery. In a short time the asbestos roofing and siding came into existence.</p>
   <p>The Interstate Roofing Company was the first firm in South Chicago that introduced that kind of siding and accepted contracts.</p>
   <p>The firm, Interstate Roofing Company, covered about two thousand roofs and seven hundred buildings.</p>
   <p>The firm also had suffered during the depression but weathered the storm successfully. Mr. Bojanowski and Mr. Dutkiewicz certainly deserve a credit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
