<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 33,
<date when="1919-08-13">Aug. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Negro Question (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0917</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0917.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 33,<date when="1919-08-13">Aug. 13, 1919</date><title level="a">NEGRO QUESTION (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago we were witnesses to an unheard of tragedy in Chicago. On the South Side of the city, in a section inhabited by Poles, Lithuanians, Czechs and Slovaks, there were burnt 70 residential homes, as a result of which several hundred families were left without a roof over their heads. This happened not by some accidents but from the will of some hated individuals. Some say that the houses were set on fire by negroes; others attribute it to members of the I. W. W. An investigation is being conducted by local police. Whatever the outcome of this investigation may be, we know that this tragic encounter has a direct connection with race riots or the so-called negro pogroms.</p>
   <p>Within the last few years, a great number of negroes have come from the South into the larger cities, too many, considering the amount of the general population. Society was not prepared to accept and help acclimatize them. THe cities, plunged completely in war activities, could not digest the excessive Negro element. There was evinced, therefore, <pb facs="5423968_4_0918.jpg" n="2"/>a lack of understanding and patience on both sides. Who are we to blame for the breaking out of riots, fires and pogroms?</p>
   <p>The fault lies with both sides, and above all the fault lies in the fact that the owners of factories, seeking cheap and ignorant labor willing to work for the smallest kind of recompense, caused the excessive influx of Negroes. Then this negro, transported to the northern states, became a certain kind of misanthrope, exploited by ward politicians, unknown completely by the by the better classes of American society, and hated by the most ignorant individuals of the white race. The coming in contract of the ignorant individuals of the negro race with the lower element of the white race must bring about an outbreak, which is only a blemish on the honor of eve the smallest or the most ignorant community.</p>
   <p>An outbreak followed. The results are very sad. The Poles do not carry any blame in this because they did not take part in the pogroms. they became plainly the victims of Negro hatred or the Satanic work of instigators or bolshevistic agitators.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0919.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Negro question is one of the most difficult we have to solve in the United States. You cannot solve it with pogroms and riots, The first step towards is solution is a systematic school campaign among the Negroes in the south, simultaneously fighting against the hatred of negroes, which is being evinced among the disorders of the white race, grouped in all manufacturing centers</p>
   <p>The government must itself initiate this matter and tend systematically to its solution without any long delay.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
