<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-02">Sept. 2, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">President Theodore Roosevelt a Great Leader</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-02">Sept. 2, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT THEODORE ROOSEVELT A GREAT LEADER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Colonel Theodore Roosevelt, former President of the United States, was an ardent supporter of radical reforms and movements, intended for the improvement of conditions in all spheres of political and national life in this country. Himself a social worker, a statesman and a keen observer, he knew best the needs of his country. Highly educated, and righteous in home and social life, Theodore Roosevelt never stained his reputation with deeds that would bring disgrace to his nation either here or abroad. He is familiar with the intricacies of political machinery, because, in his position as Vice President, and later, upon the death of Pres. McKinley, when he became President of this country he had an excellent opportunity to observe and study the national needs, which can be adjusted by timely and necessary changes in procedure, and by reforms which are fair to each and every citizen of this free republic. A mind so alert and active as Roosevelt's, makes it a point to scrutinize even the minute social and political questions so thoroughly that he is able to arrive at an opinion and render quick decisions in even the most perplexed matters.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1137.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is a well-known fact that Roosevelt, while President, was always fighting congress and the senate, not because of any personal, capricious impulse or because of an innate quarrelsome inclination, but simply because he deemed it necessary, as a matter of civic duty, to contest with representatives all matters pertinent to the fundamentals of this nation. As an alert and keen statesman he was fully aware that existing conditions are not in the desired shape or order in this land of freedom and constitutional rights. He also knew that the spirit of the great Washington, Jefferson and Lincoln is vanishing in the oblivion of the past, and is being replaced by the evil spirit of lawlessness, avarice, and injustice. As an eminent statesman and a good citizen he fully realized that such a state of affairs will bring this country to the level of a moral abyss. Therefore he demanded that Congress and the Senate vote on far reaching reforms, thus assuring better, national development, security and justice to all residents of the country.</p>
   <p>He fought organized trusts, labeling them as the greatest evil afflicting this country; and it was here that he met with the consolidated and powerful opposition, surpassing his great energy and absolutism. Although these trusts, championed in the Senate and in the Congress by members of both, prove more <pb facs="5423968_4_1138.jpg" n="3"/>powerful than the President, the Constitution, and the courts of the land, Theodore Roosevelt persistently fought them as the greatest national evil of all time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
