<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-25">Sept. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Mexican Fighting Cocks</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0765</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0765.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-25">Sept. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICAN FIGHTING COCKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Polish-American papers and at all sorts of mass meetings and gatherings, one sees nothing and hears nothing but invectives and complaints against fellow countrymen.</p>
   <p>With the conceit of peacocks our would-be apostles of so-called progress spread their colored feathers before the eyes of peaceful, uncritical people, shouting that only they are authorized to work for Poland, that everything that others do is wrong, deserves condemnation, and is the work of provocators.</p>
   <p>Looking at this battle with cool objectivity one wonders what these people are fighting about. One knows only this for certain: during the entire history of our nation and especially in its epoch of martyrdom, we have had <pb facs="5423968_4_0766.jpg" n="2"/>three enemies, Germany, Russia, and Austria. It would seem that since these are against us, we would be for each other. The opposite is true. Although all of us hate our enemies, although all of us desire Poland's freedom and independence, nevertheless, to the great joy of these very enemies of ours, we cannot agree among ourselves. We seem not to recognize the necessity of consolidated united national work at a time of such tremendous importance to the future of our homeland.</p>
   <p>Any example taken at random from life shows the senselessness of the conduct of the Polish-American brawlers.</p>
   <p>For example, doctors are called to the bedside of a certain patient (and Poland certainly can be considered such a bedridden patient) to hold a consultation. The calling of a consultation indicates that a difference of opinion on the diagnosis of the disease and the method of treating it is anticipated. The doctors argue and discuss their points but finally come to an agreement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0767.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If these physicians followed the example of our "politicians," each of them would cry out, "Let the patient die, but I will not yield my point." The patient would die.</p>
   <p>Does not this example suffice to show the stupidity of the conduct of our political parties, these "doctors" of the homeland?</p>
   <p>Yes!--but not in the opinion of various fomenting editors and others of their ilk. Some shout that we should wish success to the Triple Alliance, that we should not want Germany defeated, for then Russia would rule the world and thus the civilization and culture of ages would be lost. Others, again, see our future in German victory, etc.</p>
   <p>Nonsense. Double nonsense! In the first place, the Western powers will not allow Russia to extend her influence unbridled. If necessary, they can simply refuse to grant Russia credit, and thus destroy her within a year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0768.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the second place, why mention civilization and culture in the present era, when the European war has already surpassed in barbarism the barbaric invasions of the Huns and Attila? How can one talk about culture and civilization when the civilized countries could find no other means of settling their disputes than murder and destruction? Is not the bombing of private homes and hospitals, whose protection in wartime was guaranteed at the International Conference of 1864 at Geneva, worse than the barbarity of the Tartar or Kalmuck hordes? This is not the time to talk of civilization because we shall not see it again until after the war.</p>
   <p>The mere victory of the civilized nations in this war is not enough; what these civilized countries do after the war and how they go about it are the important things. The victors of this war can show themselves magnificent reformers of the world; or they can show themselves to be worse scoundrels than they were on the bloodiest battlefields.</p>
   <p>Today we have no way of knowing what they will be like when the war ends.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0769.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>All we can do is to show England and France greater confidence than Prussia. Therefore, why all of the quarrels, foolish talk, dissention,and attacks against each other? Those who oppose any sort of united national work should view the present situation in the light of reason, not in the light of party egotism or personal dislike for individuals within our camp. Neither you nor we will accomplish anything as individuals. Only the people as a whole can achieve, and we individuals should serve as an example to others.</p>
   <p>Why then do you fly at us like Mexican fighting cocks? No one is taking anything away from you. No one is trying to impose his convictions on you. Each of us feels that he has the right to love the homeland and work for it with all of his strength. That is why we are Poles. To serve his country is the privilege of every Pole, and we will not allow even the reddest of our enemies to take it away from us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
