<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-15">Dec. 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Present-Day Agriculture</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-15">Dec. 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">PRESENT-DAY AGRICULTURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Official statistics on the development of agriculture in one of our states show the strange phenomenon, that we have large landowners and small farmers. Formerly in Europe, and especially in Poland, there were two classes of landowners, that is, masters of extensive estates on one hand, and small farmers possessing barely a few acres of land on the other. Here in America, the same state of affairs is becoming more and more evident. The capitalistic class purchases large areas of land and gains profit from them, while, on the other hand, the poorer farmer maintains himself with great difficulty on a small farm of only a few acres. The value of land increases with each year, and many of the smaller farmers are forced to sell their farms to manufacturing and railroad tycoons. The comparatively wealthy middle class of farmers is now gradually becoming extinct. Because of this, we find that only two classes of owners are left, owners of large areas of land on <pb facs="5423968_4_1279.jpg" n="2"/>one side, and small farmers managing on a few acres of land, and making a meager livelihood out of it, on the other.</p>
   <p>The old type of farmer is gradually becoming extinct here. Farmers of that type at one time cut down dense forests, cleared the land, tilled it, and lived from it. But all-powerful Capital is gradually encroaching even upon this category of profits, by buying out the land and changing the small landowners into vassals. Many become greedy for the high price offered them for their land by the capitalists. They, therefore, sell it without thinking of the time when they will become slaves of capitalism. The state of Maine is one example of such conditions, but it is not unique. Similar conditions are prevalent in other agricultural states, where small farms are becoming extinct and large ones are being created. Those who formerly worked for themselves are now tilling the same land but giving the profits to the capitalists. The outlook is none too bright for the future, because capitalism is growing more and more powerful by bringing agriculture under its control. As a result of this, there are more and more poor people who <pb facs="5423968_4_1280.jpg" n="3"/>will be in complete dependence upon the wealthy capitalist. And so we find that capital has control over trade and commerce and is now spreading its tentacles over agriculture. Such a state of affairs bodes ill for the unpropertied class. Something should be done to prevent this monster of capitalism from strengthening its grasp upon the agriculture of this nation, lest it have everyone and everything under its control.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
