<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-19">Feb. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Eugenic Laws for Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1328</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1328.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-19">Feb. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">EUGENIC LAWS FOR WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The state medical association is preparing a health bill to be submitted for consideration by the state legislature, which will create a law in the state of Illinois providing the necessity of a medical examination of all applicants for a marriage license.</p>
   <p>At the present time men only are subject to this requirement, women being exempt; this is not fair and such exemption should not be given to women. The bill reads as follows:</p>
   <p>All persons who are about to be married are required by law to submit to a physical examination fifteen days prior to the application for the license.</p>
   <p>This examination is to be performed by a duly authorized physician who possesses a license to practice medicine in the state of Illinois. To secure this certificate of health the applicants must be free of all contagious and venereal <pb facs="5423968_4_1329.jpg" n="2"/>diseases.</p>
   <p>The examining physician's fee shall not exceed five dollars per examination.</p>
   <p>This newly proposed bill gives the examining physician the right to refuse the issuance of this certificate in the event that his findings are unsatisfactory and do not meet the requirements of the medical association.</p>
   <p>In the event a physician refuses to issue the health bill, and should this meet disapproval or create a doubt in the mind of the applicant, the latter shall under the law be entitled to file a sworn statement of objection in the office of the county clerk, and thereupon submit to a thorough examination by a commission of physicians appointed by the Governor of the state of Illinois for this express purpose. The decision based on these findings shall be final.</p>
   <p>The bill likewise has a stipulation that any person found guilty of willfully evading this law and its provisions by establishing a temporary residence in <pb facs="5423968_4_1330.jpg" n="3"/>another state with matrimony as his objective, is subject to prosecution in the municipal branch of courts, and is liable to a fine not less than ten dollars and not exceeding one thousand dollars and imprisonment of not less than thirty days and not to exceed one year in the county jail or both. Should this bill be approved and passed by the state legislature, it is the desire of this newspaper to secure an appointment for at least two Polish physicians to the commission, as this would give the Poles of the state of Illinois, and particularly Chicago, a fair and very necessary representation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
