<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-23">Sept. 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Should We Follow Our Hearts or Our Minds?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0776</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0776.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-23">Sept. 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">SHOULD WE FOLLOW OUR HEARTS OR OUR MINDS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The general European tragedy which is now being enacted on the continent of the Old World has united practically all nations in their aims and demands. In us, remote spectators, it still fans the flames of fratricidal quarrel-someness and encourages disharmony between groups of brothers.</p>
   <p>False conceptions and opinions of the moment, which came from the heart and were not based on political judgment, have been smuggled over to us for years. Because of them, our society here has been unable to make the effort to accomplish a most important thing, namely, destruction of the last vestige of the spirit of 1912, a spirit which captivated us when political policies were shaping up quite differently and other clouds were taking form on the horizon.</p>
   <p>Then we felt, and to a certain extent we were justified in this feeling, that if a war broke out between Austria and Russia, if all of Europe kept out of it, <pb facs="5423968_4_0777.jpg" n="2"/>we, as a nation, could not join the side of the worse of these two enemies of ours, but should defend Austria, the one which had given us the greatest amount of freedom, liberty, and national development.</p>
   <p>This was an impulse of the heart, or rather a feeling of gratitude to one of our annexes; it was not the result of cool-headed political intelligence, by which society should govern itself at such times. Without taking into consideration the possibility of all sorts of nationalistic, governmental complications which would appear as soon as one of the powers reached for its sword, we, like children, toyed with the boldest day dreams and placed ourselves under the sceptre of him who gave us a certain amount of personal liberty and permitted us to have some sort of autonomous politico-national existence.</p>
   <p>Under such circumstances, our deductions were rather logical. The present European tragedy has presented an entirely different set of circumstances and we must change our deductions completely. We see that this enemy of ours, who granted us certain liberties, is loyally supporting our worst enemy, who for an entire century has exerted every effort to advance against our nation the traitorous policy of destroying <pb facs="5423968_4_0778.jpg" n="3"/>everything Polish, everything which was ours, and who at the same time, as Europe's detested "policeman of armed peace," has quarreled with everyone and has drawn the wrath of dozens of the most influential and most powerful nations, so that they have sworn to revenge themselves and annihilate him.</p>
   <p>Political wisdom and cool calculations demonstrate clearly that this enemy can never emerge as the victor of the war. As the old adage says, nec Hercules contra plures, even Hercules cannot conquer many opponents. Therefore in such times as these, the impulses of the heart should give way to the judgment of the mind, and in our present calculations we should not take into consideration what we agreed to do two years ago, but what sober political thinking tells us to do now.</p>
   <p>We see that on one side stand such powers as England, France, Russia, Japan, Italy, Belgium, Serbia, and Montenegro, with their sympathizers, while on the other side there is only Germany and Austria, the latter already condemned to annihilation. We can see at a glance, without any mathematical calculations, which side has the advantage and to which side victory will fall.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0779.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Cognizant of this, do we want to side with the conquered or with the victors, who for our loyalty alone, promise us, and already openly demand, that what one of the former succeeded in taking from us by force be returned to us?</p>
   <p>On the one hand we have political wisdom, on the other impulses of the heart. On the one side sober, cool political calculations, on the other a stubborn hanging on to a rickety old fence which will fall any day now and which offers no support for the future. We should govern ourselves now with our minds, not with our hearts, and follow the advice of those who have not allowed their intelligence to be obscured by impulses of good will and who calculate clearly what benefit can come to us as a result of helping the stronger. The greatest men of the nation, who can think clearly, urge us to follow the dictates of political wisdom. Today's cablegram from France to the emigrants here, probably the most important one which we have recently received, exhorts us to take this political step.</p>
   <p>For what, then, shall we declare ourselves, for the mind or for the heart? It seems to us that we should declare ourselves for that which assures us a better future, which tells us to weigh everything coolly--that is, for good political <pb facs="5423968_4_0780.jpg" n="5"/>judgment--in our efforts for Poland's independence, here in a foreign land. Therefore, let us follow our minds, and surely we shall not blunder, as our fellow countrymen in Galicia, who have followed the dictates of their hearts, have blundered, and who probably already realize only too well the consequences of their false move.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
