<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-04">Feb. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Business Enterprises</title><title level="a" type="sub">Polonia Soap Company, Largest Polish Soap Factory in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-04">Feb. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH BUSINESS ENTERPRISES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Polonia Soap Company, Largest Polish Soap Factory in Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Slowly but steadily, various branches of Polish business are developing in Chicago, thus taking away the opportunities of other national groups to profit by the labor of our countrymen, and proving that by forming companies and corporations we can accomplish something. The motto "Swoj do Swego" [Patronize your own merchants], ignored these many years, again stands before the eyes of our brethren, reminding them that the force that will place our nation in a high position among industrial nations depends upon the support we give to our own business interests.</p>
   <p>A few months ago we wrote about the various branches of Polish industry in Chicago which, despite mounting difficulties, have established themselves on firm foundations. Again today, we would like to write a few words about a Polish soap factory, the Polonia Soap Company, which was visited by a representative of Dziennik Zwiazkowy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1671.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Polonia Soap Company is located on the northwest side of the city, at 1420-22 Emma Street, in a large brick building of which it occupies two floors. The present owner of the factory is J. W. Koss, well-known member of the Polish Industrialists and Tradesmen's Society, Group 3, Polish National Alliance. Jews, Germans, Irishmen, and others have been doing good business among the Poles for many years. The factory was opened about two years ago by two Poles as the United States Soap Company, but because of a misunderstanding, the partners sold it to the present owner, who knew what initial difficulties had to be overcome, and what competition there would be with manufacturers belonging to other national groups. He was undaunted by the work, and at present the factory produces various types of soap and soap powder of a quality as high as or higher than those produced by other factories.</p>
   <p>The Polonia Soap Company is incorporated for $10,000, but, as the owner explained to us, that sum will soon be raised to $25,000. The present employees of the factory are all well-known alliance members--J. Skowronski, John Szymanski, Martin Ziolkowski, Martin Kotwica, and Sigmund Krasinski. In addition to these <pb facs="5423968_4_1672.jpg" n="3"/>men, five girls are also employed.</p>
   <p>Mr. Koss, the owner of the factory, conducted our representative through the building and showed him all of the machines and apparatus used in the manufacture of soap, and explained the use of each. First, we visited the lower floor where the great kettles in which the fats, brought in in large barrels, are melted. The fats, after being mixed with chemicals and then strained, are poured into an enormous iron vat and from here into specially constructed wagons, where the soap is left until it sets and hardens. The great pieces of soap, often weighing as much as two thousand pounds, are then taken by elevator to the second floor, where they are scraped. After a few days, the soap is cut into bars of the required size by a special machine, the knives of which are steel wires similar to the strings of a piano. The cut pieces of soap are again placed into wagons to dry for several days, after which they are cut into various shapes, such as oval, circular, square, octagonal, and so on. At the same time, the trade mark of the firm is stamped on each piece. As a final operation, the soap is wrapped, packaged, and packed into boxes for shipment. At the entrance to <pb facs="5423968_4_1673.jpg" n="4"/>the factory, we find a neatly arranged office; accounts are accurately kept according to the latest system of bookkeeping.</p>
   <p>The Polonia Soap Company manufactures the best grades of perfumed soaps, shaving soaps, tar soaps, and facial and washing soaps. It also manufactures a "cleanser", upon the containers of which appears a white eagle with a Polish inscription. In a word, this factory, although it is not as large as some of the old, established soap factories here, yields to none in the quality or price of its products.</p>
   <p>Polish Grocers Should Support Polish Manufacturers</p>
   <p>A Polish soap factory is not at all to the liking of Jewish and German manufacturers, who think that they alone have the right to do business among the Poles, that they ought to extract money from the pockets of our countrymen, so that when the need arises they will have funds to carry on the struggle against them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1674.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We have heard that agents of Jewish and German firms, like vultures circling over their prey, are circulating uncomplimentary statements concerning the Polish soap factory among the Poles. These tactics should be punishable; they should be condemned at every step.</p>
   <p>A Word to Our Polish Housekeepers</p>
   <p>To the Polish housekeepers in Chicago, we strongly recommend that when they are buying soap in a Polish grocery, they demand soap from the Polish factory, the Polonia Soap Company, and that they support only Polish industry.</p>
   <p>The strength of our nation lies in the development of Polish industry. If we support Polish business, if we support ourselves mutually and remove from our midst the foreign leeches, then in a short time we will find ourselves among the strong and influential nations with whom everyone must reckon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
