<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-24">Aug. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Polish National Alliance and the Slavs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0812</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0812.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-24">Aug. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE AND THE SLAVS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As is generally known to the members of the Alliance, a convention of the Advisory Board and the Board of Directors of the Polish National Alliance was held at the Alliance College at Cambridge Springs, Pennsylvania, last week. The bodies deliberated over many important matters, among them the stand which the P. N. A. should take in regard to the present war in Europe.</p>
   <p>The Advisory Board as the highest body of our organization, having the authority to pass all sorts of decrees and resolutions during the interim between conventions, usually settles all matters which the Convention did not foresee and which definitely demand decision. The last convention of the Advisory Board was necessary because there were internal matters to be settled, which demanded the opinion and approval of the Advisory Board. It was also necessary to decide what stand the Alliance should take at so important a time as the present, when the fate of our homeland is standing in the balance in Europe and the dawn of liberty begins to break for the Polish nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0813.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The subject of Poland's independence, therefore, was deliberated upon harmoniously and calmly. All of the details were considered and the consequences which the present turmoil in Europe might bring. After the most careful consideration of this matter, of such great importance to all of us, the Advisory Board, approving the action of the Board of Directors up to the present, finally decided that the Alliance should co-operate with the Czechs, Slovaks, Serbs, Montenegrens, and other Slavs. In other words, the Alliance is taking a definite stand against the Germans, who are being fought not only by the entire Slavic world but by other nations as well.</p>
   <p>This is a wise decision. It would not be fitting for us to take any other stand. The Muscovite is our enemy, though he calls himself a Slav, but the German is an even worse enemy. He should be crushed, no matter who does the deed. Then, the Muscovites are not alone in fighting the Germans, but are joined by almost all of the civilized nations, with the Slavs of all the various tribes in the first rank. The Poles cannot possibly side with their everlasting enemy, the Teutons, whose mailed fist has struck them more than once. They must side with <pb facs="5423968_4_0814.jpg" n="3"/>the Slavs, the Anglo-Saxons, the Franks, and other peoples, who, also, have begun to feel the weight of the German hand to such an extent, that they have finally decided to rise up and crush it.</p>
   <p>Everyone of us can already foresee that the Germans, despite violent attacks in the beginning and drives forward to the French border, in spite of winning one or more battles, nevertheless, cannot win the war, and must fall, crushed, because soon they will run out of men, ammunition and food. Too, they are threatened by a bloody revolution within the country itself.</p>
   <p>It is certain that, after the war and the crushing of Prussianism, the map of Europe will undergo a complete change. Surely Poland will appear on it, as a free, neutral country, patterned after gallant Belgium. This is the desire of both France and England, who will have the deciding voices. This will surely not be opposed by Czechs, Serbs, Bulgars, Slovaks, Croatians, or any other Slavs, when they see that we have gone with them, hand in hand, during the time of bloody necessity. To take the part of the Germans, our worst enemy, at a time <pb facs="5423968_4_0815.jpg" n="4"/>when they are threatened by a pogrom, which will make them powerless for many years to come, would be madness on our part and suicide for the nation, Under pressure from England, France, and the Slavs of various tribes, our other enemy, Russia, must yield, and agree to the creation of a free Polish country, which will separate Germany from Russia, and will know how to defend its neutrality, as Belgium is defending hers today. (Belgium has given the best example of how a free nation defends its liberty.)</p>
   <p>The Germans, defeated and crushed, will not be able to oppose the reconstruction of Poland. Moreover, fearing Russia's ownership of Galicia and Poznan, they themselves, in their own interest, will be for the re-creation of Poland, which would separate them from the Bear of the North.</p>
   <p>This is more or less how the present situation appears to us. Hope burns brightly in our breasts. We can gain only by siding with the Slavs and other peoples, who are fighting the Germans. This is the way those of our countrymen who are <pb facs="5423968_4_0816.jpg" n="5"/>flocking in large numbers to the English and French ranks, understand our situation. They are asking to be sent against the Prussian, whom they desire to fight, and to fight fiercely, for the century-old wrongs which he has dealt us.</p>
   <p>This is how the Polish National Alliance which, through its representatives, has declared itself on the side of the Slavs, understands our situation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
