<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 20,
<date when="1919-05-13">May 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Soldiers Return a Contrast</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0123</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0123.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 20,
<date when="1919-05-13">May 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOLDIERS RETURN A CONTRAST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The other day a group of about forty soldiers, members of the Polish army came into town. They left the train at the station, came to 92nd St. and Commercial avenue, looked around and then went on their way. There was no one to meet them; no welcome sign to greet them, and few who paid any attention to them.</p>
   <p>Perhaps they recalled in their minds the scene of their departure, bands playing, flags waving, people cheering and all that went with a typical soldiers farewell.</p>
   <p>They came back victors for the Allied armies of which they were a part and parcel, accomplished everything that the people desired. The war has been over for a year and a half now, however, and the enthusiasm of the people has subsided.</p>
   <p>People of today are no different than they were years ago and centuries ago. Public gratitude is just as fickle and as short-lived toay as centuries ago. We sent our soldiers away like heroes, but we are found wanting when they return.</p>
   <p>What happened in the case of these soldiers has happened with our own American boys, and what happened in our town is typical of the scenes that prevail all over the land.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0124.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are all the same and we are all deserving of the same censure. The other day the writer chanced to be downtown at one of the big railroad stations, and on trucks were flag-draped caskets of American heroes who have perished on the battlefields of Europe. A few soldiers stood on guard, some people looked at the flag-draped biers and asked questions; occasionally some one raised his hat, but one glance was enough for most of them, as they hurried on their way. To them the war is over, and with it has departed all their feeling of appreciation toward the men who made the great sacrifices for them and the world. It is sad, but nonetheless true.</p>
   <p>We have heard some of the boys who have been there complain, and we can imagine what others think, and one can't blame them either. But then the human race is made out of the same sort of clay today that it was centuries ago, and civilization has failed to make it any more appreciative than it was in the early or so-called dark ages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
