<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 7,
<date when="1916-02-16">Feb. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Women Section - in an Important Matter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0936</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0936.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 7,
<date when="1916-02-16">Feb. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH WOMEN SECTION - IN AN IMPORTANT MATTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the state of Illinois for several years a special commission is working to find out the reason young girls falling into white slavery and immorality.</p>
   <p>In the opinion of this commission the reason for prostitution and immorality of women is the darkness of the mind and poor wages.</p>
   <p>The most dangerous menace to a girl's virtue is work in a hotel.</p>
   <p>The bosses in the factories and offices are to blame for this too.</p>
   <p>As a remedy the above mentioned commission to decrease prostitution proposes that the legislature should adopt and regulate the average wages of the working girls, so they do not ruin themselves and fall in into white slavery.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0937.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They propose to build special homes for girls where they will learn a decent trade and occupation.</p>
   <p>The desire of the commission is to stop the news articles containing chronicles of the scandalous divorce cases and immorality. The opinion of this commission is not right in everything.</p>
   <p>One must admit that immorality exists among all classes of society without respect as to sex, but it is absurd to prove that the poor class of people is among the majority when the reverse is true.</p>
   <p>Every woman physically or mentally healthy in America will make a living if she is willing to. But lack of religious education leads the girls the wrong way. Next is the desire of worldly pleasures and beautiful clothes, not poverty.</p>
   <p>If somebody would compile an authentic record of Polish girls working in <pb facs="5423968_4_0938.jpg" n="3"/>the hotels as dishwashers, cleaners and maids, then we would see the few thousands of this army without any protection in the worst kind of immoral conditions.</p>
   <p>No hotel in America, starting from the low, foul smelling Jewish to a first class hotel is without a few of these Polish girls.</p>
   <p>Americans readily hire them and they know the Polish girls are clean and good kitchen workers and careful about their jobs.</p>
   <p>This recognition, as much as it rightfully is due to our Polish girls, does not react to the benefit of Polish girls, because they knowing about this, take to hotel service in large numbers.</p>
   <p>Facts prove that the hotels are very dangerous to the young Polish girls. They are to blame for the spoiling and demoralization of girls.</p>
   <p>Large masses of Polish girls lost in white slavery are also lost to the <pb facs="5423968_4_0939.jpg" n="4"/>Polish home and the church.</p>
   <p>In the hotels they come in contact with men of the worst type. If anyone objects to evil influence and corruption, then they use forceful means on her.</p>
   <p>In the last edition of Glos Polek are given to us two facts which should interest all Polish societies. In the Congress Hotel in Chicago, for which are working several hundred girls, about two hundred of these are Polish girls, various kinds of servants, and most of them living in the same hotel.</p>
   <p>From this hotel they called the orphanage of the Guardian Angel, asking if they would take care of a young Polish girl, an expectant mother, because she would not be able to work and had no parents or friends in the city.</p>
   <p>Next case: In a Greek lunch room in Chicago, a Polish girl was a servant <pb facs="5423968_4_0940.jpg" n="5"/>around the kitchen. Not so long ago she came from Europe. A cook's helper gave her a bad proposition; refusing she lost her job. But the girls was decent and did not accept the brutal proposition but rather quit work and went to the orphanage.</p>
   <p>A long series of such events is repeated almost every day. Someone told us that a Polish girl, after a year of service in a hotel, when she was satisfied, her desire was to go to work as servant in a home.</p>
   <p>She went to a family and was hired. But after a month's service she left. And why? For this very reason, a decent family does not permit her to indulge in nightly escapades. The girl will not get used to this, nature calls the wolf to the woods.</p>
   <p>In all probability before she went to the hotel service she was a decent girl.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0941.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We write this with the aim of calling attention to Polish women, especially those who show a preference to work for society.</p>
   <p>Here is an open field to work. So, Polish women, take care of them. Organize societies, show them the way to get out of this!</p>
   <p>It is our duty to save these unfortunate Polish girls from white slavery, and this duty belongs to the Polish woman.</p>
   <p>Only you women, even partially to prevent corruption, educate them about moral life and with mothers' care and protection have guardianship over them. Those girls working in the hotels and restaurants especially, almost have no parents and no protection.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
