<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-26">Feb. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Compulsory Military Service</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0648</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0648.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-26">Feb. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Government of the United States has introduced a bill in Congress proposing compulsory conscription and general military service. The proposal was worked out by the general staff of Uncle Sam's army and approved by the War Department and President Wilson.</p>
   <p>This proposed bill suggests that all young men, nineteen years of age, physically fit for military service, be drafted to serve in the regular army of the United States for eleven months, and then be called up for two-week training periods during the first and second years after serving in the ranks, that is, in the twentieth and twenty-first years of their lives.</p>
   <p>According to the calculations of the general staff, 500,000 boys of draft age will be able each year to join the regular army, and in three years the <pb facs="5423968_4_0649.jpg" n="2"/>[United] States will have an army of 1,500,000 trained soldiers ready for battle. The general staff wants to keep 3,000,000 men in armed military preparedness. This will constitute a reserve of the first order, to which every soldier will belong for four years after having served his term. After this he will automatically pass on to the second reserve, and finally on to general mobilization, in which category he will have to remain until he has reached the age of forty-five, after which he will be retired.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the regular army and the first reserve could be called at any moment, because it would have equipment and uniforms in reserve. The second reserve would require a little more time before it could be sent to the front, though even in this respect certain changes would be made later. At any rate, we could count on an army of 1,500,000 soldiers at once and on an additional 1,000,000 men of the second reserve.</p>
   <p>Besides this, the general staff plans to maintain a permanent, professional, <pb facs="5423968_4_0650.jpg" n="3"/>regular army numbering 300,000 men, consisting of 24,400 officers and 285,886 soldiers. Of this army, 97,000 would be in the colonial or overseas service, and the remainder would constitute the home defense, which at the same time would drill and train the recruits called up each year.</p>
   <p>The cost of keeping such an army has been estimated to be $472,258,746 yearly, on the basis that the equipment and upkeep of one soldier would cost $143.28 yearly. For the above sum, or say five hundred million dollars in round numbers, the [United] States could support an army of 3,296,029 men, including the regular army and the newly drafted recruits. The War Department has estimated that, under the present system of counting on the States' National Guards, the cost of supporting 1,137,200 men, together with the regular army, would reach $339,548,000, or that the average cost per man would be $298.58.</p>
   <p>We have extracted these most important statistics from the recently published <pb facs="5423968_4_0651.jpg" n="4"/>report of Secretary of War Baker, which serves as an introduction to the submitted bill in the matter of compulsory draft and general military service in the [United] States, in order to acquaint our readers with the main principles of this bill, which can cause a complete upheaval in conditions here, and following the example of the old world introduce a military system here, which really is necessary for the defense of the country, as long as aggression and the desire to grab other people's countries will not vanish from the world.</p>
   <p>This bill will first be deliberated over by the Committee on Military Affairs in the Senate. It is true that it would be difficult to suppose that Congress could debate this bill during its present session or come to a decision. Therefore, there will be plenty of time for its discussion, and we shall no doubt revert to it on many occasions in the future. Today we merely wish to say that humanity in general, instead of thinking about disarmament, is making further preparations for war, which can be prevented only by a peace based on the permanent and just principles of leaving to each nation the right of <pb facs="5423968_4_0652.jpg" n="5"/>independent existence and of deciding their own fate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
