<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-21">Aug. 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Creative Work of Poles in Trade and Commerce</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1622</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1622.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-21">Aug. 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CREATIVE WORK OF POLES IN TRADE AND COMMERCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Poles have finally applied themselves seriously to a rather important matter. They are combining and forming their own trade and commerce associations. They pool together their small savings and concentrate their ideas and their abilities, and in that way they create a new power--a power that thus far has been little known to exist among Poles.</p>
   <p>Our people have finally come to realize that in this modern age an individual relying solely upon his own resources cannot accomplish a great deal. Other nations now have powerful and well-financed organizations in every branch of trade and commerce. Consequently we Poles must also build up our trade and commerce on a new pattern and in a different way than that which has been followed thus far.</p>
   <p>Comments are heard from all parts of the world relative to the creative work <pb facs="5423968_4_1623.jpg" n="2"/>of Poles in that direction. And so in Cracow, Poland, a Polish steamship line has already been organized. The purpose of this corporation is to get into Polish hands Poland's waterway trade. It has another aim also, and that is to create a Polish merchant marine when Poland gains access to the sea. A Polish import and export corporation is now being formed in Copenhagen, Denmark. It is expected that with the termination of the World War trade on a vast scale will begin between Poland and other nations. As a result of this the Poles can see that they should endeavor in every possible manner to make certain that at least a part of that trade shall come into Polish hands.</p>
   <p>The Poles in Chicago are also making great strides forward. Several important associations and corporations have been formed in the last few years. In Chicago alone such corporations have been created as the Polish Wholesale Grocers' Corporation and the Polish Trade Corporation. This latter corporation conducts classes which are rendering hundreds of our people well versed in <pb facs="5423968_4_1624.jpg" n="3"/>matters of trade and commerce. The Polish Commercial and Industrial Circle is another example of our solidarity. Then, again, we have the Great Lakes Fire Insurance Company, the Providers' Life Insurance Company, and other corporations. This same organization movement in the field of trade and commerce is becoming more and more evident in other cities and towns in America with a large Polish population.</p>
   <p>All this progress, however, is merely the proverbial drop of water in the ocean in comparison to the enormity of the task ahead of our people. We need literally hundreds of similar corporations.</p>
   <p>If our people seriously contemplate accomplishing things in the world of trade and commerce, we must gradually embrace all the branches and spheres of the nation's business. The Polish convention held at Detroit has rendered our people an invaluable service in that respect by calling into being the Department of Polish Trade and Commerce. The task and the purpose <pb facs="5423968_4_1625.jpg" n="4"/>of this Department are to encourage Poles to work in the field of trade and commerce. It will give our people instructions on how to create and organize associations and corporations. It will also teach the Poles how to conduct enterprises of trade and commerce in order to achieve the highest possible growth and development.</p>
   <p>The Poles have already begun to work in that direction. Their endeavors are earnest and sincere. The only thing left for us to do is to make certain that this admirable work once started shall not die but on the contrary shall be allowed to grow and develop.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
