<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-16">Nov. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Social Reform</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0961</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0961.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-16">Nov. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIAL REFORM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The abuses and brutality of the employees in some of our county hospitals, poor houses, insane asylums, orphanages, and prisons are already well known from descriptions in the newspapers and from investigations conducted here and there. The energetic attitude of Commissioner Bartzen in Cook County, Illinois, who dismissed half of the employees of the insane asylum at Dunning, because he had established the fact that the unfortunate patients there were treated worse than beasts, is also well known. In many other institutions, the abuse and the maltreatment of human beings who, through unfortunate circumstances, were placed in these institutions, where even a dumb animal would not be treated the way the brutal wardens treat the inmates, have been brought to light. [Translator's note: Here follows a specific instance of brutality practiced on a Pole in Milwaukee by the name of Roczynial, who was released from prison after serving seven years of a twenty-five year sentence, only to die in his home of tuberculosis contracted in prison. This individual, before his death, disclosed the medieval tortures to which he had been subjected.]</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0962.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If Roczynial's deposition is true, the authorities should institute an investigation and should punish the people in charge. Similar events could only occur in Russia.</p>
   <p>But the authorities, somehow, are not too eager to institute investigations and to punish the brutal transgressors, who in this way prey upon people. Therefore, it is up to the citizens to take this matter in hand and to enter a vigorous protest against such barbarism.</p>
   <p>The Poles, although they constitute a very small percentage of criminals in this country, nevertheless are guilty of many lesser transgressions, and receive less severe sentences. Many are sentenced by the courts for drunkenness and fighting, and recently there have been many cases of desertion: wives leaving husbands, husbands leaving wives, and sometimes even degenerate parents leaving their own children to the generosity of fate, running away without one thought about the creatures to whom they have given life. An example of this comes to us from Philadelphia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0963.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: Here follows the story of the Polski family. Mrs. Polski deserted her husband, leaving three children. Mr. Polski, not able to manage alone, left $7.50 with a neighbor for food and left his children, to go in search of his wife. Neither parent returned. After the money was exhausted, the neighbor, unable to support the children herself, took them to the police who in turn sent them to an orphanage.]</p>
   <p>Where is the conscience, the heart, in parents such as these? Why even a dumb animal loves and protects its young, and often suffers hunger and dies of starvation. It is obvious, then, that some people are worse than animals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
