<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. 25, No. 70,
<date when="1921-10-31">October 31, 1921</date><title level="a">General Foch and Our Immigration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0115</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0115.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. 25, No. 70,
<date when="1921-10-31">October 31, 1921</date><title level="a">GENERAL FOCH AND OUR IMMIGRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Marshal Foch, the victorious chief commander of the entire anti-German coalition armies in the World War, will arrive in Chicago next Saturday.</p>
   <p>Chicago is the capital of our large Polish organizations in America, therefore our Chicago Polish settlement, represented by the managements of our organizations, may receive Marshal Foch in the name of the whole Polish American Immigration, expressing thereby its sentiment.</p>
   <p>The whole city is preparing very energetically for the reception of this greatest military leader, for we wish to give him a grand reception.</p>
   <p>We are positive that great throngs of people, such as never had been witnessed before in Chicago, will come out to greet this great conqueror of Germany and her Allies.</p>
   <p>Now, it is our great duty to see that our Polish immigration does its part, <pb facs="5423968_4_0116.jpg" n="2"/>that it should not be last, that it should come out in great numbers and demonstrate very strongly the sentiments of our Polish immigrants in America, towards that great son of France and great defender of the Polish cause at every opportunity.</p>
   <p>We should demonstrate very loudly, and prove - not only our numerical strength, but also the knowledge of political affairs and by that action show that we appreciate the friendly attitude of France and her greatest warrior towards us. A proper demonstration of our immigrants may have a very powerful influence upon Marshal Foch and his attitude toward Polish cause, including whole France.</p>
   <p>A proper demonstration on our side, in honor of the great commander-in-chief of the allied armies will not only be a great surprise to him, but will also increase his authority at a French conference which will be held in Washington, D. C. At the same time he may render a great service to Poland <pb facs="5423968_4_0117.jpg" n="3"/>We will appear as Americans of Polish descent. As citizens of the United States we will play a very important part.</p>
   <p>We should not neglect this great opportunity, of making the visit of this great man very pleasant for him. We should bear in our minds that Marshal Foch is now the idol of the people and very important person in the world.</p>
   <p>We have a great opportunity now to honor a great man and at the same time to help Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
