<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-17">Jan. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Affair of the Universal Machine and Tool Corporation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-17">Jan. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE AFFAIR OF THE UNIVERSAL MACHINE AND TOOL CORPORATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon, in the offices of Sidney Eastman, receiver, room 907, Monadnock Building, a second hearing was held in the case of the Universal Machine and Tool Corporation, which declared itself insolvent on October 7 of last year. The principal witnesses in yesterday's inquiry were Mr. Pontkowski, former president of the company, and Mr. Vincent Szalaj, former bookkeeper and office manager. Creditors and shareholders were represented by Attorney Leech of the law firm of Leech and Lutes, 5 North La Salle Street.</p>
   <p>The matter, according to the sworn statements of Messrs Pontkowski and Szalaj, is as follows:</p>
   <p>The Universal Machine and Tool Company was incorporated under the laws of <pb facs="5423968_4_1569.jpg" n="2"/>the State of Illinois on January 3, 1919, with a capital of $28,000. In September of the same year the capital was raised to $100,000, and in the following year to $500,000. The increase in capital was reported to the secretary of state in Springfield, Illinois, who made an audit of the assets of the company and placed it in class D. According to the Illinois blue-sky law the stock of such companies should be stamped distinctly as speculative stock. Officers of the corporation ignored completely this law, advertising the stock as absolutely guaranteed.</p>
   <p>In July, 1921, the Universal Company merged with the factory of Mr. Politowski. At that time the Universal submitted the audited report of its assets, whereas Mr. Politowski did not. It was then that the enlarged corporation found itself in financial difficulties and took steps contrary to law. It advertised in a Polish newspaper for workmen who were willing to put some money into the business, promising steady work and high wages. Many men <pb facs="5423968_4_1570.jpg" n="3"/>answered the ad, contributing from four hundred to two thousand dollars apiece. For their money they received notes. Shortly afterwards efforts were made to have them agree to exchange their notes for common stock, which many of them did. Some time later the factory closed, and the creditors and the shareholders found themselves without jobs. At the suggestion of Mr. Albert Nowak, one of the directors, it was decided to declare bankruptcy. The company's books showed liabilities of $124,600 and assets of $25,000, consisting of equipment and goods.</p>
   <p>Mr. Szalaj emphatically denied the accusations made by the creditors that Dr. Chrzan and Albert Nowak had carted away the moving picture machines that the corporation was manufacturing. It was further said that before receivers took over the factory, machines, instruments, and boxes of tools were taken out. Mr. Lemacki affirmed under oath that he had seen two men carrying a moving picture machine to Mr. Szalaj's office on Milwaukee Avenue. Mr. Szalaj denied it. Attorney Leech cross-examined Szalaj and Pontkowski <pb facs="5423968_4_1571.jpg" n="4"/>about the disappearance of the company's funds and condemned the irregularities in bookkeeping. At the next hearing, which will be held next Monday, Attorney Leech will endeavor to arrive at the truth and find but what really happened to the $23,000 which the corporation received when it merged with Politowski's factory, and further, what became of the $60,000 which at one time was in the company's possession. Finally, he expects to show what types of irregularity were being practiced by the company officials.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
