<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-03">May 3, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Smallpox Prevalent in Polish Communities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1379</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1379.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-03">May 3, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">SMALLPOX PREVALENT IN POLISH COMMUNITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. E. Garrot, chief inspector of the Board of Health, paid a visit to the offices of the Dziennik Chicagoski and informed our staff about the sad health conditions in our communities.</p>
   <p>In the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish and adjoining communities, smallpox has been prevalent for some time, especially among the Poles, and it is spreading. During the past few weeks over sixty cases of smallpox were reported in this region; a few cases of black smallpox were also listed.</p>
   <p>Cases arose in the following homes: 608 and 611 Holt Avenue, 468, 469, and 470 Elston Avenue, 704 and 748 Noble Street (4 cases), 28 Luke Street, 781 Milwaukee Avenue, 6 and 10 Sloan Street, and 134 North Avenue (8 cases). This, however, is only a partial list.</p>
   <p>The smallpox epidemic is spreading because a large number of the families and <pb facs="5423968_4_1380.jpg" n="2"/>even some of the doctors are keeping the sickness a secret; consequently their reports come late to the Board of Health. As a result, the stricken person cannot be removed to a hospital nor the home disinfected, which would check the spread of the disease to a minimum. As a result of this condition the spread of the disease has given cause for alarm.</p>
   <p>Because of this, Dr. Garrot warns all Poles to take precautions, and he appeals to them in their own interest to report all cases of smallpox, and not to keep them secret. All those who have not been vaccinated, or who were vaccinated a long time ago, are requested to see to it that they are vaccinated immediately.</p>
   <p>Vaccination services are rendered free by Dr. Edward Czerniewski, 699 Noble Street (corner of Noble and Blackhawk streets, above Burda's drugstore).</p>
   <p>All doctors who withhold any information about new smallpox cases will be prosecuted by law. Dr. Garrot has revealed their names to us; however, we will not reveal them, hoping that the doctors in question will remedy their policies in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
