<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-04-25">April 25, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">To Commemorate the Memory of Fallen Soldiers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0102</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0102.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-04-25">April 25, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">TO COMMEMORATE THE MEMORY OF FALLEN SOLDIERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A gold star was the insignia of a life sacrificed on the battle field. Such gold stars were in evidence in many Polish communities in Chicago. Statistics report that over 300 of the dead soldiers of Chicago were of Polish-American descent. In commemoration of these heroes, the Reverend Francis Kulinski, chaplain of the American army, organized the Fathers and Mothers Gold Star Society, for those whose sons gave their lives for the ideals of this country.</p>
   <p>This society is the pride of the Polish element in America. Americans and people of other foreign elements cannot accuse the people of Polish descent, of refusing to enlist and participate in the war because of national discord on the battlefield. The purpose of this organization is to honor the memory of the dead soldiers by celebrating a Holy Mass, and decorating their graves annually. The most important aim however, is to erect a monument at Saint Adalbert cemetery, for an estimated cost of $25,000. Very few of our people are aware of the fact that there are many soldiers of Polish descent buried in different sections of our cemetery; and that with the passing of time, the memory of these great men will erase itself and leave the future generation ignorant of the circumstances which caused the great sacrifice made by the Polish-American youth, during the World's war. Coming to the aid of this Gold Star Society, in pursuit of this honorable objective, was his Emminence, Cardinal Mundelein, offering a sizeable section of land on Saint Adalbert Cemetery, for the distinct purpose of assembling the remains of all Polish soldiers who lost their lives in this war, and bury them in one designated section.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0103.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the future, this section will be used as a gathering place for the Polish people of Chicago, where in the presence of God, they can express their gratitude to those who sacrificed their life and suffered the hardship of war; here also, youth shall accumulate that spirit necessary to face the daily battle of life. Future generations shall, with pride, read of the fact that the Pole is able and competent to defend any just and worthwhile cause; and they shall be happy to know, Polish spirit, lies there, buried far from its native land, but in this humble manner makes the Polish name honorable.</p>
   <p>In the coming year, the tenth anniversary of the Armistice, all America will observe this day, and with it, the Gold Star Society will introduce an important moment to the Polish element in Chicago, by unveiling a monument, the description of which follows: The cost of this monument is $25,000., it will be of Barre granite construction thirty three feet in height, the top of which will bear a group of three soldiers, one of which will be an American soldier, another an American marine, and the third, that of the Polish volunteer of General Haller's army. The height of these figures which are cast in bronze, is six and one half feet.</p>
   <p>We appeal to all Poles of Chicago to help make this honorable gesture a complete success. At this time we find that we are still in need of $10,000. Therefore, on the fifteenth day of May, 1927 we shall conduct a tag-day, which, we believe, will create this necessary balance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
