<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-06-06">June 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Best Answer</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-06-06">June 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE BEST ANSWER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance, as has already been published, has decided to buy $112,000 worth of United States Liberty Loan bonds, thus giving the most eloquent proof that we not only call upon others to purchase Liberty bonds, but ourselves practice what we preach. Of the $112,000 appropriated by the Polish National Alliance for the purchase of Liberty bonds, $50,000 belongs to the [Polish] national tax fund, collected among the Alliance members in those "five-cent pieces" that caused some people headaches, especially the followers of K. O. N. [Komitet Obrony Narodowe--National Defense Committee] who even tried to accuse the central administration of using that money for some sort of "czar-boosting agitation". Obviously, that money is in the bank, since today the central administration, upon authority of the National Tax Control Commission, is able to take up the funds and invest them in government bonds for a stated time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0541.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The second $50,000 for the purchase of Liberty bonds will be taken by the central administration from the present capital of the Alliance, to allocate it where it will not be in any danger, discharging, at the same time, a duty that our organization owes to this, our adopted homeland. We feel sure that none of our Alliance brothers will raise a word of protest against this decision of the central administration of the Polish National Alliance, but will heartily applaud it.</p>
   <p>Finally, $12,000 has been allotted for the same purpose by the Polish National Alliance publications, that is, the funds will come from the savings of Dziennik Zwiazkowy and Zgoda. As the official report confirms, the Alliance publications have a surplus capital of more than $24,000, and from this they will purchase $12,000 worth of Liberty bonds.</p>
   <p>This is the best answer to all accusations made by people of ill will that Dziennik Zwiazkowy does not pay for itself, and that the Alliance has to make up its deficit at the rate of $12,000 per month. It must be understood that <pb facs="5423968_4_0542.jpg" n="3"/>the finances of the publications are handled entirely apart from the finances of the Alliance itself; they are controlled, however, by the central administration, which approves or rejects all expenditures, and must give its approbation to all orders placed by the newspapers' administration; in short, it has complete control over the publications' finances.</p>
   <p>The fact that today the Alliance publications have purchased $12,000 worth of United States Liberty Loan bonds proves most eloquently the shallowness and baselessness of all accusations concerning the financial side of our publications, and gives the lie to all rumors that these publications do not show a profit and do not support themselves.</p>
   <p>Through the purchase of Liberty bonds, the publications have performed their duty. Let us hope that they continue to prosper so that, in a short time, they may double their bond purchase. Then, perhaps, part of the surplus can be used for the benefit of those who labor intensively over their development and expansion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
