<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-11">Apr. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Liberty Bond Campaign</title><title level="a" type="sub">St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish Holds Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0315</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0315.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-11">Apr. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LIBERTY BOND CAMPAIGN</title><title level="a" type="sub">St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish Holds Meeting</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday evening a meeting was held in the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish Hall, called by the parish division of the Polish Liberty Bond Committee at the request of Archbishop Mundelein, who is conducting the campaign among Roman Catholics. The meeting was held for the purpose of interesting Poles in the purchase of Third Liberty Loan bonds. It was explained that these bonds are safer than bank deposits, that they pay four and one-half per cent interest, and that it is the duty of every loyal citizen, especially if he is a Pole, to purchase Liberty bonds to the extent of his means.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened with a prayer by the Reverend [F.] Dembinski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, after which John Nering, chairman of the local division of the Liberty bond committee, spoke a few words on the sujbect of Liberty bonds. F. Blachowski acted as secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0316.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The next speaker was Mr. Conewen, sent by the Knights of Columbus, who showed by statistics the patriotism of the Poles, and who said that this time, too, the Poles will live up to the expectations of the United States. He explained the significance of the present war and its causes. He described our duties to the soldiers who are risking their lives fighting for us. He pointed out also that if we care for our freedom and if we wish to continue enjoying that freedom and not be slaves of the Kaiser, we must be ready to sacrifice everything.</p>
   <p>The speakers following Mr. Conewen were Judge E. Jarecki, president of the Polish [Liberty Bond] Committee; F. Barc, of the Polish National Council; Niedzialkowski, secretary of the Polish [Liberty Bond] Committee; and, finally, Vincent Zwiefka, president of the Sixteenth Ward Liberty Loan office. All of these speakers did their best to explain the conditions under which Liberty bonds may be purchased and the need for purchasing them. They emphasized the fact that it is the duty of every good Pole to purchase these bonds, for the <pb facs="5423968_4_0317.jpg" n="3"/>Poles have heretofore shown themselves to be good American patriots and must continue to be. We must give proof that we Poles understand our duty and the significance of the present moment. If America wins the war, we also win, for free America will call to life a free Poland, as President Wilson has already declared.</p>
   <p>Among other things, F. Barc said that at a meeting he had attended, he heard the statement: "When after his death, Frederick the Great went to hell, many of the devils refused to stay there. It can be gathered from this that when Kaiser Wilhelm goes to hell, all of the devils, and even Lucifer himself, will run away." He added on his own part that the principal aim of the present Liberty Loan is to send the Kaiser there as quickly as possible.</p>
   <p>As a result of yesterday's meeting, fifteen applications were filed for bonds, the total value of which is more than six thousand dollars. Of these, one application, filed by F. Blachowski in behalf of the Polish Alma Mater, was for the sum of five thousand dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
