<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. VI, No. 179,
<date when="1926-08-02">Aug. 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Opening of Polish Hotel Mr. Frank Demeter, Engineer Is Owner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. VI, No. 179,
<date when="1926-08-02">Aug. 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">OPENING OF POLISH HOTEL MR. FRANK DEMETER, ENGINEER IS OWNER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The opening of the very beautiful Ashland Manor Hotel, 404 S. Ashland Ave., whose owners are Frank and Sophia Demeter, took place last Saturday.</p>
   <p>Mr. Demeter made himself known to the Poles in Chicago as an outstanding engineer, who, in his time was entrusted with the building of the tunnel in the southern part of the city of Boston. He has conducted similar work in New York and other cities of the United States. He is a brother-in-law of Mr. Zygmunt Stefanowicz, chief editor of the publications of the Polish R. C. Union.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Sophia Demeter is the daughter of Mrs. W. Chodzinski, Director of the Polish Women's Alliance, and well known as a worker in the national and social plane.</p>
   <p>The hotel has 160 large and beautifully furnished rooms, also an extraordinarily equipped lobby which is enhanced by furniture acquired from the <pb facs="5423968_4_1521.jpg" n="2"/>Palmer House, as for example, a clock worth several thousand dollars; a set of furniture from a room which at one time was occupied by presidents of the United States, Grant and Cleveland, also the famous singers, Patti and Tetrazzini; and a mirror of artistic out, bought from a certain Protestant congregation. The lobby also has a fountain and numerous pictures, some of these brought over from Poland by Mrs. Chodzinski.</p>
   <p>The hotel was built at a cost of $65,000. The popularity of Mr. Demeter among Americans is so great, that all of the rooms in the hotel were rented the very first day it was opened.</p>
   <p>Mr. Demeter, as is becoming a good Pole, employs mostly Polish people.</p>
   <p>Last Saturday, which was the opening day, a banquet was held in the diningroom of the hotel, to which all of Mr. Demeter's relatives and numerous friends were invited.</p>
   <p>Mr. Demeter, as we are informed, intends to have two more similar hotels built in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
