<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-11">Sept. 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Time to End Our Quarrels</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0802</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0802.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-11">Sept. 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TIME TO END OUR QUARRELS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are printing below an article sent us by our regular correspondent, Mr. S.Z.S.</p>
   <p>This article could, from our point of view, be used to strike at our opposition here and there, but it has one great virtue: it presents an intelligent and well-founded appeal for contributions to the independence fund.</p>
   <p>Mr. S. obviously has different convictions from ours, but when he writes intelligently and honestly he can always count on a just evaluation of his opinions by people brought up on the idea of respect for the convictions of others.</p>
   <p>We recommend Mr. S.'s closing appeal and herewith attach the entire article without modifications:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0803.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Whom should we join, whom should we support, whom should we help, Prussia, Austria, or Russia? Or should we wait until our enemies have given each other a thorough thrashing and then concentrate our forces and strike against them? Should we give money? To whom should we give it? Through what channels should we send it? Which organization, which committee for aiding Poland, is the better one here in America? These are the questions which we ask not only others, but also ourselves, at the present time--a time that is terrible and yet so full of hope for us.</p>
   <p>"May I be permitted to voice my opinion on this matter, which will, perhaps, offer answers to some of these questions? Every one of us Poles knows that our worst enemies are the Russian and the Prussian. Nevertheless, let us be just in our judgment. Russia took away from us the largest part of our land. Russia persecuted us most in every respect. Russia caused us more bloodshed than any other country. But would Austria--under whose rule we brag that we were so well treated--would Austria have treated us any better, <pb facs="5423968_4_0804.jpg" n="3"/>if we had behaved as "disloyally" as we did in Russia, or rather in the Polish Kingdom? After all, all of the revolutions and insurrections took place in Russia. The only attempt made in Galicia was unsuccessful because the Austrian Government used the most repulsive means of putting it down: they stirred up the peasants against the gentry and the insurrectionists and paid in gold for the head of each insurrectionist. The Russian government has punished insurrectionists but has done it by the right of the conqueror, the right of the stronger. Moreover, it has punished not only Poles, but its own Russian people, as is customary for every country to do. When we compare our insurrections, our "rebellions," our stubborn opposition under Russian rule, and the punishments meted out to us by that government to the attempted insurrection in Galicia and the butchering of the gentry as punishment for it, we have a picture of the kind of treatment which would have been meted out to us in Austria, if we had been as rebellious there as we have been in Russia. Surely many more of us would have been put to death, many more would have hung at the citadel in Lwow, many more would have rotted in the dungeons <pb facs="5423968_4_0805.jpg" n="4"/>within the walls of Wisnicza. But because we were quiet, because we did not rebel, and, finally, because Austria was herself having difficulties and wanted to have peace in Galicia, she gave us autonomy and a congress. She gave us a State Board of Education too, but at the same time forbade the singing of "God Save Poland" and "Poland Is Not Lost" in the public schools. Every teacher had to pledge loyalty not to his work, not to the children for whose development he was responsible, but to the Austrian Government. (Perhaps there are a few of these teachers here in America. They will tell you about this, if you do not want to believe that it is so). Austria gave us greater freedom of movement, but she condemned us to death by starvation, because for the past few years she prohibited our emigrating to America in search of bread. All branches of industry were burdened with extraordinarily heavy taxes. Roads were left in disrepair, communications were of the worst sort. A peasant could not build himself a respectable house of two or three rooms without being burdened with taxes. Salt, which is produced in greatest quantities in the Polish mines of Wieliczka and Bochenka, is the property of the Government, and recently a project was submitted to Parliament for making matches a Government monopoly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0806.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Gentlemen statisticians and you who approve of an alliance with Austria, count the number of Poles from Galicia who are in America, and the number from the Kingdom. When you ask each one what made him leave the homeland, you will learn that all of those formerly under Austrian rule left because of hunger and poverty, while those formerly under the Russian Government are principally political refugees or socialists, who in a majority of cases had nothing in common with Poland.</p>
   <p>"Finally,let us give Austria credit for only those favors she has already granted to help raise our nation. Were we to defend her because "she was the first to give us liberty" and because she finally gave us Archduke Stephen of Zywiec as a Polish king, were we to form legions for Austria and help her fight the Russians, still she could not, despite her most sincere intentions, lift up our nation.</p>
   <p>"It is as clear as the hand before you, when you consider current events in <pb facs="5423968_4_0807.jpg" n="6"/>Europe--not merely enemy papers--that Austria must fall. If she is not actually divided between Russia, Prussia, Italy, and Serbia, she will at least disintegrate as a country and in her place there will be resurrected among other nations the kingdoms of Bohemia and Hungary. Half of Galicia is already in the hands of the Russians and if we wait a little while the other half will fall into their possession. Then, if we have behaved disloyally toward the Russians, we shall be persecuted again. Again we shall be populating Siberia; for the promises of the Czar and the various manifestoes will mean nothing.</p>
   <p>"The Prussians, if they are now helping Austria fight the Russians, do so to save their own hides. If at present they are fighting the French, Belgians, or English, that is not at all strange: militarism has been prevalent in Germany for the past forty years. Soldiers there form the best trained fighting machines and they believe in the power of the Hohenzollerns. But let us wait just a little while. When these mechanical German soldiers, who have no feeling of being individuals, once get whipped, the German ranks will disintegrate and the star of the Hohenzollerns will pale. There will be a <pb facs="5423968_4_0808.jpg" n="7"/>shortage of food and then there will be a revolution, as a result of which the German empire must fall and with it Austria. Today, it is true, the Germans are powerful, but good fortune already is turning away from them and toward the side of France and Russia.</p>
   <p>"Whom should we join? With whom should we side? It would be best if we could stir up our brothers--serving today in enemy armies and shooting at each other to revolt, to step out of the ranks of our enemies, and to stand on the side of Poland. With the Sharpshooters, the Falcons etc., they could push forward into the center of the territory of the old Republic, taking the Polish land and cutting down their enemies before them. This, however, is impossible. Before the Polish battalion could even plan a revolt, it would be wiped out to the last man as was the Czech infantry battalion in Prague. However, this is not what we are concerned about now. We know that the Russians are winning victories everywhere while the Austrians and Germans are being defeated. We also know that the majority of the people in Poland <pb facs="5423968_4_0809.jpg" n="8"/>sympathize with Russia, believing that Russia will keep her promise to reconstruct Poland. We know, as I have mentioned above, or rather we believe, that Austria will be defeated and will disintegrate and that we, by the same token, having followed Austria and helped her, will be oppressed again by victorious Russia. Then why should we go along with Austria and be slaughtered, when there is a possibility of emerging with more whole heads if we declare ourselves for and stand on the side of Russia. This is our only hope.</p>
   <p>"We here in Poland's Fourth District have not known on which side of the fence to jump since the outbreak of the European war. We have formed all sorts of orientations. Some of us have held to the ideas of the K. O. N. [Committee of National Defense], others to those of the P. R. N. [Polish National Council]. Finally we have created the Department of Independence, and all of us have been waiting for news from our brothers in the homeland, promising <pb facs="5423968_4_0810.jpg" n="9"/>ourselves that as soon as some news of a more definite nature reached us, we should all end our quarrels and make up. Today, this news has reached us, but it is sad news because it tells that during the first moments of conflict some Poles have declared themselves for Austria, others for Russia. Let us believe that only a small group of people have declared themselves for Austria. The last few papers bring us news that the Polish people are demanding a merger of factions. In some cities all of the parties and factions are uniting without exception and are calling upon all other factions to join them in taking a stand against Austria. It looks as though Russia were giving us real guarantees of Poland's reconstruction. This must be true because our statesmen in the homeland, who we must admit have better heads than ours, have declared themselves for Russia. Besides, the entire world expects Poland's restitution to be achieved with Russia's help. It is certain that all factions will unite and together will strike our common enemy. There is the hope that either the K. O. N. or the P. R. N. will yield or at least change its stand.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0811.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>"The news from the homeland for which we have been waiting has come. The call has come. The sound of the Golden Horn, for which we have been waiting, we hear. Then for what and for whom are we waiting? We know that our brothers in the homeland are fighting and dying. Therefore, let us collect money and send it at once to the homeland. Let us train young men and send them wherever our leaders in the homeland order us. Let us all believe in this: our lives and our money will not be given in vain. If we cannot unite all of our organizations, at least let us try not to interfere in each other's work. Let us tell ourselves that all of these organizations will send the money to the same place, that all are collecting funds for the same purpose, to bring help to our unfortunate mother country. It is time that we end our quarrels--time to understand that every good Pole makes his contribution not for some specific organization but for his homeland."</p>
   <p>"(Signed) S. Z. S."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
