<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. I, No. 11,
<date when="1907-03-28">March 28, 1907</date><title level="a">This Paper Is Devoted to the Working Class Interests</title><title level="a" type="sub">Womens' Struggle for the Right to Vote</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1250</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1250.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. I, No. 11,
<date when="1907-03-28">March 28, 1907</date><title level="a">This Paper Is Devoted To The Working Class Interests</title><title level="a" type="sub">WOMENS' STRUGGLE FOR THE RIGHT TO VOTE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Women suffragists assembled in Springfield, Illinois today with the aim of demanding from the State legislature, the right to vote. The affair has created a great bustle, even though the members of the State legislature endeavor to make a joke of this whole affair. It is evident that they are dismayed about giving a decision on this matter, brought about by the suffragettes.</p>
   <p>Aside from the right to vote the suffragists also demand a complete equalization, political and social, with the men. Their demands were formulated on a roll of paper to which was appended a vast amount of signatures. This lengthy roll of paper measures a hundred and fifty yards.</p>
   <p>The delegation consists of the following women:</p>
   <p>Ella Stewart, President of the Illinois Equal Voters Club: Minnie Watkins, President of the Illinois Womens' Alliance Club; Mary Kuhl, President of the W. C. T. U.; L. Ducanson, President of the Chiocago's Equal Rights Political <pb facs="5423968_4_1251.jpg" n="2"/>League; Ada Cracker, President of the Northern Voters' League; H. Sloate, President of the Evanston Political Equal Rights League; Dr. R. Wistine of the Womens' Czechs Club; and Catherine McCulloch.</p>
   <p>Their petition had already been presented to their representative, Sheldon, before the delegation arrived here, to be present and witness their own committees' discussions, selected specially for this meeting.</p>
   <p>In this way Chicago's women have been the first in America to form a serious organization to claim the rights and power which has been prohibited them.</p>
   <p>The "mighty" would desire and hope to see them as inanimated dolls and playthings, designed for pleasure</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
