<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-09">Feb. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to All Polish Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-09">Feb. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO ALL POLISH WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sister Poles!</p>
   <p>Loyal to and imbued with an ardent love for our unhappy country, Poland, we have at the same time obligations of gratitude toward the magnificent, free, and independent land of America. Some of us have come here exiled from our native land by the might of our enemies; others of us were born in America, but all of us have found liberty, protection, and bread here. The powerful United States is, therefore, as another homeland to us.</p>
   <p>The time is coming when America will demand of its citizens proof of their love and affection. In order that this moment may not find these citizens unprepared, American women are organizing committees in order to help the country.</p>
   <p>We Polish women who owe America a debt of gratitude must not withdraw from <pb facs="5423968_4_1223.jpg" n="2"/>serving the nation, but should stand ready to work together with the daughters of this country.</p>
   <p>Let us follow the shining examples of our Polish heroes, who generously shed their blood in defense of America's right to freedom.</p>
   <p>For this purpose, the Women's Auxiliary of the Polish National Alliance is hereby convoking a general mass meeting for Sunday, February 11, at 2 P. M., at the Polish National Alliance Building, 1406-08 West Division Street, to which it cordially invites all Polish women, regardless of what organizations they belong to, in order to discuss the problem together and to organize a service committee. In this way we will express honorably and fittingly the feelings we have for the people and the country, whose representative President Wilson announced before the whole world that Poland should be united, free, and autonomous.</p>
   <p>Every Polish woman who is a loyal American citizen is obliged to attend this <pb facs="5423968_4_1224.jpg" n="3"/>mass meeting.</p>
   <p>For the Women's Auxiliary of the Polish</p>
   <p>National Alliance:</p>
   <p>Mary Sakowski, president</p>
   <p>Magdalene Milewski, vice-president</p>
   <p>Jane Dunin, secretary</p>
   <p>Mary Majewski, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
