<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-07-16">July 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Neswpaper in Chicago Exposes Austro-Hungarian Activities in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0697</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0697.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H (Hungarian)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-07-16">July 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH NEWSPAPER IN CHICAGO EXPOSES AUSTRO-HUNGARIAN ACTIVITIES IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Continuing a series of articles exposing Austro-Hungarian activities against munition manufacturers and kindred propaganda, the Zgoda, (a Polish daily), and official organ of the Polish National Alliance, gives details of how the Austrian secret agents, Hausner and Mlynarski, installed and maintained a national polyglot press agency and subsidy. Detroit, Cleveland, Buffalo, Scranton, and Toledo were the centers of this pernicious propaganda in the middle West. New York, and Chicago were the fountainheads of it, and the Austrian embassy in Washington, through the secret agents Hausner and Mlynarski, its directing genius, says the Polish Daily Zgoda.</p>
   <p>The time of its birth was the arrival in the United States of the agents Hausner and Mlynarski. Its spread was marked in an unvarying course by an itinerary of these men about the country, and its effects are seen in controversies of both clerical and lay character in the section referred to by Dr. Dumba in his now famous strike proposal to Foreign Minister Burian in <pb facs="5423968_4_0698.jpg" n="2"/>Vienna.</p>
   <p>Among the newspapers which either have been subsidized outright or have been eager servants of the Austrian representatives and agents in this little known phase of Dr. Dumba's pernicious career, are the following:</p>
   <p>The daily Szabodsag (Liberty), in Cleveland. Its editor and later New York representative, Martin Dienes, alias William Warm, drafted the middle West strike plans seized on Captain Archibald.</p>
   <p>The daily Amerikai Magyar Nepsava (The American Hungarian Exponent), in New York. Its editor, G. D. Berko, formerly David Bercovitz, figures in investigations, now under way, having to do with passport matters.</p>
   <p>Kuryer Codzienny (Daily Courier), in Cleveland. Casimir Gluchowski, the editor, was supported by Dr. Bogacki and Dr. Ernest Ludwig, Austrian consul in Cleveland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0699.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Narodowiec (The Nationalist), a Cleveland weekly, of which Stanislaus Dangel is the editor and publisher.</p>
   <p>Dziennik Polski (Polish News), in Detroit, a daily. U. Karasiewicz, editor.</p>
   <p>Dziennik Ludowy (People's Daily), in Chicago, published by the Polish Socialist Party. This newspaper is the plaintiff in a libel suit against one of its contemporaries, in which the name of Count Bernstorff, Dr. Dumba and Consul Ludwig of Cleveland appear as part of the record.</p>
   <p>Bicz Bozy (Scourge of God), in Chicago, a weekly; Polish Publishing Company, Publishers. A harsh and inflamatory anticlerical and Socialist publication of a satirical character. Its columns have been marked lately by vicious attacks on Bishop Rhode of the Roman Catholic Diocese.</p>
   <p>Dziennik Dla Wszystkich (Everybodys Daily), in Buffalo, N. Y., a daily edited <pb facs="5423968_4_0700.jpg" n="4"/>by J. Kaminski.</p>
   <p>Telegram Codzienny (The Daily Telegram), in New York, a daily.</p>
   <p>Straz (Sentinel), in Scranton, Pa., a weekly organ of the so-called Polish National Church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
