<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIV, No. 34,
<date when="1920-08-25">Aug. 25, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">On Women's Suffrage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIV, No. 34,
<date when="1920-08-25">Aug. 25, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">ON WOMEN'S SUFFRAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Women can vote! After six years of continuous fighting, the women of the United States have been given the right of equality at the polls. We will describe in a few words how it happened.</p>
   <p>In 1878 the following amendment was presented before the United States Congress for adoption:</p>
   <p>ARTICLE XIX. The right of the citizens of the United States to vote shall not be abridged by the United States, or by any state, on account of i. Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate legislation. Declared in force August 26, 1920.</p>
   <p>This article was passed by the House of Representatives on the 21st day of May, 1919, and by the Senate on the 4th day of June of the same year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1165.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That is not all. Before the law becomes effective it must have the approval of three fourths of the states, or, in other words, it must first (pass) the legislatures of 36 states. Then the fight started in every state. Some states ratified the new law; others rejected it. The State of Illinois was the first state that ratified it, other states followed. On the 18th day of August, 1920, the 36th state passed this law. It was the state of Tennessee. This ended the fight for the remaining twelve states.</p>
   <p>From now on every woman in the United States, who is over 21 years of age, will have an equal right to vote with men. This fall women may vote for the President if they register at the proper time.</p>
   <p>According to the statistics computed by the head bureau of the suffragettes, there are 26,883,566 women eligible to vote in the United States of America. Out of these about 20 million will vote at the fall election. There will be about 29 million votes cast by men.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1166.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The American press is pleased on account of the women's victory, but the opponents of the suffrage predict a downfall of society. It matters not who is right, but we wish to emphasize that the Polish women of the United States should plunge into the hard work of enlightening themselves on politics. If we have the right to vote we should take advantage of it. If we do not do so, others will take the offices.</p>
   <p>In Poland women have the right to vote. In our Polish Roman-Catholic Union men and women have equal rights.</p>
   <p>Why should a woman not wish to have a voice in matters concerning the United States? Women of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, we congratulate you on your victory and we are inviting you to work in a larger field!</p>
   <p>Learn the laws of the United States, register in the proper time, vote on election day. Those who are not citizens should take out their <pb facs="5423968_4_1167.jpg" n="4"/>naturalization papers. If your husband is not a citizen, prevail upon him to take out his citizenship papers. The field is open. Act! Do not fall asleep on this matter! Whoever falls asleep over matters today will be stepped on. Therefore, let us go ahead!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
