<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-08">May 8, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to Mothers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1363</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1363.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-08">May 8, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO MOTHERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Within a short time, hot summer days are going to prevail. These hot days subject children and infants to summer disease or infant cholera Many an inexperienced mother has seen her child, and hundreds of others, succumb to this lurking summer sickness, bringing untold grief to the bereaved families. Many a mother whose child is stricken with the disease goes to seek aid from a family that has experienced this illness. As it happens, some cures are effected in this manner; however, a larger number are not, because the information received is not of the right kind, and hence many an innocent tot is carried off to the grave.</p>
   <p>It is conditions such as these that prompt me to write the following words to mothers, in order that they may bring up healthy children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1364.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Infant cholera is prevalent among children from two months to two and one-half years of age. The cause of this illness is poor nourishment. A child's stomach is very delicate and its digestive process is weak, consequently improper food will cause all kinds of complications and sicknesses, especially infant cholera. This sickness affects the stomach and intestines. It starts with a cold of the membranes of the stomach and intestines. The stomach ceases its digestive function, and this is followed by a nervous breakdown, which soon affects the brain--then death follows.</p>
   <p>A practical mother can avert these complications by one method or another. The best way is to protect the child's health by proper care and accurate feeding, along hygienic lines. (By hygiene it is meant that food and care is administered the child under the most sanitary, or clean, conditions possible, at home and outdoors. This is not much different than taking good care of an adult.) One of the first hygienic steps is proper feeding for the child. Such nutriment is milk from a mother's breast. In the event the child is too old to be breast-fed, the mother should give the child proper substitutes in measured <pb facs="5423968_4_1365.jpg" n="3"/>portions at scheduled hours. A certain amount of time is necessary for the food to be digested. If the food is given at a time when the child is ready to sleep, it is only natural that the food will not undergo a thorough digestive process when the child dozes off immediately after eating. Such improper digestion brings about a number of ailments and, in the summer time, courts infant cholera.</p>
   <p>A child, from birth until one year of age, should be fed every two hours.</p>
   <p>Dziennik Chicagoski, May 10, 1897.</p>
   <p>From one year to two years, the feeding should not be as frequent, for the child is not satisfied with the same kind of diet. A mother should not breastfeed a child longer than twenty minutes, and in the event the child cries after that, it is not because it is hungry but because it has cramps or other complications.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1366.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>For a child who is not breast-fed, the best substitute is cow's milk. Such milk should not come from several cows, but from one healthy cow. Pure milk is not given the child until it is diluted with boiled water.</p>
   <p>Infants are given one part milk and three parts water, and in the event the child is not sustained on this type of diet, half milk and half water should be given in larger quantities. This procedure applies to babies from three to six months old. Older children should get two parts milk and one part water. The amount of water is decreased (as the child grows older) until its stomach is able to digest pure milk. In preparing the boiled water, a little sugar is added-for example, one teaspoon of sugar to one glass of water.</p>
   <p>In the event the child has diarrhea, rolled oats or barley should be given instead of water, adding slightly less sugar than in the water. To prepare such a meal, one uses two tablespoons of rolled oats or barley and grinds it in a coffee grinder. Then two thirds of a quart of water is added to this and the mixture is boiled for thirty minutes in a covered pot. This is then strained <pb facs="5423968_4_1367.jpg" n="5"/>through a cloth or a fine sieve.</p>
   <p>This preparation is placed in a cool room, and only the required portion is taken out each time. This mixture cannot be stored long, because it spoils easily. In order to preserve this preparation, a small pinch of soda should be used. In the event the above measures do not give results, and the child continues to lose its appetite, becomes unruly, and begins to vomit, along with diarrhea, especially during the summer season, this should be considered as a sign that the child has a touch of summer sickness. In this event it is not advisable to seek aid from any neighbor or would-be diagnostician.</p>
   <p>Time should not be wasted, for every moment brings a more dangerous condition, A doctor should be consulted, by all means, because he is the one most fit to combat the disease.</p>
   <p>Dr. M. F. Bozyncz,</p>
   <p>291 N. Carpenter Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
