<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>,
<date when="1918-02-07">Feb. 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Poles! Make a Supreme Effort!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Our President Says That War Will Be Decided in 1918</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>,
<date when="1918-02-07">Feb. 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">POLES! MAKE A SUPREME EFFORT!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Our President Says That War Will Be Decided in 1918</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Washington, D. C.--President Wilson in a message sent to the farmers conference at Urbana, Illinois, said, "You will realize, as I think statesmen on both sides of the water realize, that the culminating crisis of the struggle has come, and that the achievements of this year on the one side or the other must determine the issue."</p>
   <p>"It has turned out that the forces that fight for freedom, the freedom of men all over the world as well as our own, depend upon us in an extraordinary and unexpected degree for sustenance, for the supply of the material by which men are to live and to fight, and it will be our glory, when the war is over, that we have supplied these materials and supplied them abundantly, and it will be the greater glory because in supplying them we have made our supreme effort and sacrifice."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0423.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>BROTHER POLES</p>
   <p>Our illustrious President has you in mind as much as anyone in America, his words are directed to you. Now it is up to you to make good. If you want to shorten the war produce more. If you want to shorten the suffering of the population in Poland, drive that extra nail, even when you hear the whistle blowing. If you want to save the life of that starving Polish mother with a babe in her arms, do more work, do it more effectively and influence your fellow worker to do the same. Remember! you owe a duty to your President, to America, and to your own dear Poland; and do not forget that the TEUTON whom you are now fighting was always your enemy. Remember the men in the trenches, consider yourself one of an industrial army and a part of its military equipment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
