<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-28">Mar. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Society for the Protection of Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1191</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1191.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-28">Mar. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SOCIETY FOR THE PROTECTION OF WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last meeting of a group of people of good will who met at the Polish Press Club, Mrs. Helen Setmajer read the following report regarding the newly formed Polish Society for the Protection of Women, a report which speaks for itself concerning the aims and purposes of this worthy society.</p>
   <p>"By sending out written invitations to today's gathering, invitations whose contents have already informed you in general of the aims and purposes of the Polish Society for the Protection of Women, we wanted in the first place to let Mr. Virden, representative of the State authorities, see with what earnest interest our people regard this problem, and how greatly they feel the need of such an organization.</p>
   <p>"Besides this, we would like to take advantage of today's gathering in order to ask you to help and support us by joining our group and to call it to the <pb facs="5423968_4_1192.jpg" n="2"/>attention of your friends, whom we do not know but who can be very helpful to us in our socio-national work.</p>
   <p>"Were we only to stop and consider the predicament of our Polish women and girls, we would all no doubt unanimously agree that it is our duty as Poles to give help and advice to those who need them.</p>
   <p>"If we would take the trouble to examine the court records, we would find innumerable cases which, by being dragged through the courts, bring shame and dishonor not only to the family in question but to our entire nationality as well.</p>
   <p>"Frequently this is not so much the fault of those who from their childhood spend their time working for a living and have no time to learn to differentiate between good and bad and what a woman should be ashamed of and should guard against, as it is the fault of society, which has not as yet made an effort to organize appropriate care and protection for these unfortunate beings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1193.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"We Polish women who sympathize with and understand the terrible lot of the victims of our social indifference, are called upon in the first place to make a united effort to remedy the evil.</p>
   <p>"The serious though sporadic voices which have occasionally been raised in the papers regarding this matter, as well as the increasing police and court reports which bring shame to Polish names by disclosing facts about the complete moral decay of Polish women and girls, have caused a group of Polish women to decide to take a definite step in the direction of remedying this evil. They have organized the Polish Society for the Protection of Women, the aims of which are as follows:</p>
   <p>"1. To give advice and protection to women and girls of Slavic ancestry, especially to Polish women.</p>
   <p>"2. To defend the reputation and honor of these women and girls, when the need arises (in a legal sense).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1194.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"3. To make free employment service available to them and to contact employers.</p>
   <p>"4. To gain admittance to hotels and restaurants, where a large majority of these girls work, for the purpose of extending moral control and protection over them, such control and protection to be in the form of appropriate lectures and evening school classes in English reading and writing.</p>
   <p>"5. To organize clubs for these women where they can spend a few hours each week in proper relaxation and listen to morally strengthening lectures, and where they can learn handicraft, either for their own use or for use of charitable institutions.</p>
   <p>"In order to make possible these aims, the Society will arrange all kinds of social events, bazaars, and collections, and will use the proceeds for the necessary expenditures and for erecting its own building. This building will be <pb facs="5423968_4_1195.jpg" n="5"/>called 'Protection of Women,' and will constitute a social and educational center for all women and girls who may want to take advantage of it.</p>
   <p>"Besides lecture rooms and recreation halls, the building will house the administrative offices of the society and rooms where women and girls can find temporary shelter in cases of emergency.</p>
   <p>"For the purpose of raising funds for the most immediate necessities, the members of the Society have voluntarily taxed themselves one dollar each as an initiation fee, and will pay twenty-five cents monthly dues. They are also establishing a book of donors, in which even the smallest contributions will be recorded.</p>
   <p>"A list of these contributions will also be published in the local papers.</p>
   <p>"In conclusion, it should be added that this Society is wholly nonpartisan and <pb facs="5423968_4_1196.jpg" n="6"/>desires to give help and advice to all Polish women, regardless of their viewpoints, beliefs, or principles.</p>
   <p>"It will gratefully accept the co-operation and help, no matter how small, of every woman, regardless of her social or organizational affiliations.</p>
   <p>"For this reason, in order not to give today's gathering a semblance of partisanship, we refrained from asking our Polish organizations for a place where we could gather. Instead we invited you, ladies and gentlemen, to the Polish Press Club, which represents all our press, since in this undertaking we wanted to unite everybody.</p>
   <p>"We express our sincere thanks to the Polish Press Club for its kind hospitality. In this kind and disinterested gesture we see proof of the fact that the press, which in every cultural community is the expression of public opinion, approves of our undertaking and will not fail to support it with the entire force of its powerful influence."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
