<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-18">Feb. 18, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">The Egg Will Teach the Chicken</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-18">Feb. 18, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THE EGG WILL TEACH THE CHICKEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There will soon be a shortage of clients in our Polish-American communities, according to the number of lawyers opening offices throughout the city. [Translator's note: This rather obscure reference pertains to the fact that the Church was in existence long before the current crop of lawyers, who were offending many persons by attempting to modernize the social order established and sanctioned by the Church]</p>
   <p>The Catholic Church, through nineteen centuries, has carefully watched over youth, but Sztandar (Standard), the organ of the Polish Young Men's Alliance, is making new discoveries in the field of caring for young people. They do this under the pretext of enlightenment.</p>
   <p>This paper is quoted as follows: "The only salutary method is to influence <pb facs="5423968_4_1256.jpg" n="2"/>our maidens to join the young people's organizations, together with the young men. Let us throw aside the wrong conviction that such societies are the cause of the spread of immorality among young people. Be certain, mother and father, that their first aim is to teach the gospel of morality."</p>
   <p>The above paragraph (slightly abbreviated) can be read in the February 15th issue of the Sztandar, on the first page, sixth column.</p>
   <p>It pleased God, our Creator, to divide vegetation and animals into genders, male and female, as well as the human race. But, God endowed the human being with a brain and free will, whereas other creatures are governed by instinct only. Therefore, social contacts between male and female human beings depend on the laws of correct understanding, enlightened by God's graces: Faith, Hope, and Love.</p>
   <p>The Catholic church has always condemned the seeming indifference toward maidenly modesty and simplicity, which will suffer from mutual social contacts <pb facs="5423968_4_1257.jpg" n="3"/>of both sexes without strict parental supervision.</p>
   <p>This is not the way, Sztandar!</p>
   <p>Not that! To send our daughters to watch the turners drill, to send our daughters to young men's meetings, so that they may sit on the same bench and discuss matters together, to snatch our daughters in the evening and late at night from under the watchful eye of the mother, is to commit an act of social suicide.</p>
   <p>No Catholic, in fact no respectable person, loving the flower of innocence in his child, could ever agree to such evil suggestions.</p>
   <p>The modernized girl turners and their lawyers forget the simplest supreme truth--that what God has made, no human is able to change.</p>
   <p>Our reformers of Polish maidens forget the old-time Polish saying, which told <pb facs="5423968_4_1258.jpg" n="4"/>Mr. Krupa, who wished to fight the crusaders, that "Krupa is worrying needlessly, because he cannot be made over into a lamb"--and no woman can be made over into a man.</p>
   <p>To what did the pagan spirit of the maidens bring them during the times of the Roman emperors?</p>
   <p>They began with dancing, then passed on to gymnastics, and acquired a love for heavyweight drilling. But these exercises were too innocent to please them, according to the article of Reverend Niedzialkowski in the Warsaw paper Rola. Their souls were soaring to greater heights. They began to drill as the gladiators did. They dressed up in breast plates and helmets, wore soldiers' footwear and knee protectors, put on the gloves of contestants, and began exercising, first with a wooden pole, then an iron one. If the neighbor's dog's barking disturbed the slumber of a maiden before noontime, the terrible amazon would appear, with lightning in her eyes, on the neighbor's lawn, and unsparingly would mete out what she considered justice to the wrongdoers, <pb facs="5423968_4_1259.jpg" n="5"/>both dog and master. In her pursuit for publicity and emancipation, she played with tame lions and tigers. Truly, there was no diversion to which the animal nature of the human being did not resort, and with which the emancipated maidens did not become enamored, just to fill that spiritual void emptied of faith and graces.</p>
   <p>The Sztandar evidently wishes a return of those pagan practices.</p>
   <p>The demoralization is to spread to the schoolchidren at an age when they need the most careful attention and Christian education. As many an old woman thinks that face powder will bring back her maidenly blush, so do our progressives believe that they can substitute, for the Christian graces, sugar-coated secret meetings between the youth of both sexes.</p>
   <p>This is not the way!</p>
   <p>This should be sufficient to settle the matter. The writers lie, and lie, until <pb facs="5423968_4_1260.jpg" n="6"/>they eventually convince somebody. The smarties!</p>
   <p>F.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
