<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-27">Jan. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Golden Jubilee of Mrs. Slominska's Badge and Banner Shop</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1541</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1541.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-27">Jan. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">GOLDEN JUBILEE OF MRS. SLOMINSKA'S BADGE AND BANNER SHOP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thanks to an enterprising Polish woman who would not give up, a new enterprise was launched a year after the great Chicago fire of 1871, which nearly destroyed the whole city. This business not only is still in existence but is well known all over America and even in Poland, where at the world's fair in the city of Lwow (Lemberg) Mrs. Slominska's establishment received two medals for its artistic embroideries.</p>
   <p>It was in 1872, after the great fire. Our respected and patriotic, country-woman had lost nearly all of her possessions in the conflagration. On top of that a protracted illness had incapacitated her husband Stanislas. However, this brave woman did not become discouraged but went to work and by efforts that would have exhausted even the strongest she finally succeeded in opening a little store at Halsted and Bunker Streets, in the so-called Bohemian <pb facs="5423968_4_1542.jpg" n="2"/>St. Venceslas parish. In this shop she received her first order for scarfs from one of the societies of St. Stanislas Kostka's Church. St. Stanislas was then the only Polish church in Chicago, and Mr. and Mrs. Slominski were members of this parish. From this small beginning, the little store in which for several years Mrs. Slomlnska also sold women's hats, grew the badge and banner shop of W. Slominska, one of the largest of its kind in America because of the honest and artistic work done by this purely Polish establishment.</p>
   <p>With the increase of Polish immigration to America and the concomitant growth of Polish societies, the sideline of women's hats was discontinued, and all efforts were directed solely to the manufacture and distribution of banners, flages, badges, scarfs, and similar requisites of Polish societies, liturgical vestments of all kinds necessary for church ceremonials, and canopies for church processions.</p>
   <p>In this business the late Stanislas Slominski was of great help to his wife <pb facs="5423968_4_1543.jpg" n="3"/>Waleria up to the date of his death in 1910. After her husband's demise Mrs. Slominska did not resign herself to despair but continued to work devotedly at her business. He asked her son-in-law, the well-known Adalbert J. Danisch, to come to work with her, which he did, managing the business up to July, 1917, when he bought it from his mother-in-law, who lived only fourteen months longer in retirement with her daughter Angeline Danisch in St. Venceslas' parish in the Avondale section of our city.</p>
   <p>In the Badge and Banner Shop of W. Slominska were made most of the banners and Polish flags for Polish societies in America. Even the tiniest Polish community in the United States has some Polish organization which uses the products made by this well-known firm. But the larger Polish organizations also had their banners made in this establishment; for instance the very beautiful banner of the Polish National Alliance and those of the Polish Union in Buffalo, the Polish Union in Wilkes Barre, Pennsylvania, the Alliance of Poles in the State of Ohio, the Polish Women's Alliance in America, and many other important organizations, leagues, and alliances, some of which <pb facs="5423968_4_1544.jpg" n="4"/>no longer exist.</p>
   <p>In the fifty years of the existence of the Slominska Badge and Banner Shop more than three thousand Polish organizations, more than a hundred Lithuanian societies, and about two hundred societies of other nationalities, such as Bohemian, Italian, Hungarian, Rumanian, Irish, and German, have come to this shop with their needs. This firm has gained a reputation of "good as gold" among business houses operated by other nationalities and especially among wholesale houses because its word is as good as gold, in that the goods contracted for are delivered without fail at the time promised. This reputation has been maintained by the firm up to the present day. From this short history we can see that Poles also can conduct a business successfully if only they strive to satisfy their customers and to execute orders to their complete satisfaction.</p>
   <p>We are confident that the Badge and Banner Shop of W. Slominska, under the management of so energetic and enterprising a countryman of ours as <pb facs="5423968_4_1545.jpg" n="5"/>Mr. Adalbert J. Danisch, will celebrate not only its diamond jubilee but also its centennial.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
