<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-20">Sept. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Committee to Promote Sale of American Liberty Bonds</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-20">Sept. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH COMMITTEE TO PROMOTE SALE OF AMERICAN LIBERTY BONDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Polish division to promote sale of Fourth Liberty bonds was held on Thursday, September 19, 1918, at 105 West Monroe Street. The most prominent municipal and civic leaders were present. The main topic of discussion was how to organize the Polish people in the individual wards and vicinities outside of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. P. Streychmans, the chairman of the meeting, informed those present that, in his effort to satisfy the wishes of the Polish element, he succeeded in having a clause inserted in the subscription blanks instructing that the nationality of the purchaser be shown. In that way the credit which large business institutions receive for financing the loans will be given to people of the various nationalities who purchase these bonds. He explained, for example, that in the stock yards, steel mills, and other similar business concerns, the credit was given to the firms, whereas in reality Polish laborers <pb facs="5423968_4_0151.jpg" n="2"/>employed by these companies bought the greatest amount of bonds. But now such will not be the case; the bonds which will be purchased out of the earnings of Poles will be credited to them.</p>
   <p>Mr. Steychmans stated that the distinguished president of the Polish committee, the Honorable Judge Edmund Jarecki, had resigned on account of business pressure and that it was in order to select a new president for the Polish group.</p>
   <p>It was decided to organize individual wards and districts first, and then at the next meeting, which is to be held on Monday, September 23, 1918, at the same location, the election of a new chairman, secretary, and other officials will take place.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vincent Jozwiakowski, the present secretary, was ordered to communicate with various prominent Polish leaders who were recommended at this meeting <pb facs="5423968_4_0152.jpg" n="3"/>for the individual Polish wards and districts, and will give a detailed report at the next meeting. Due credit for his untiring work must be given to Mr. Jozwiakowski, who, despite his numerous business activities, has never failed to co-operate in any activity which would help the good name of the Polish people. Upon a motion made by Mr. John Rybicki, it was decided to divide the neighboring Polish wards into districts, each one under the charge of a vice-president who would control the activities in the district. The motion was passed and such a distribution was made.</p>
   <p>The Honorable Judge Joseph LaBuy, the incumbent candidate for the same office, has, despite the strenuous campaign that awaits him, promised to exert all his efforts in this drive to sell Liberty bonds. Thus, as in the past, the Polish element has always come to the fore whenever and wherever the defense of true democracy was necessary or its safety threatened.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
