<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-03">Mar. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">On the Eve of the Inauguration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0630</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0630.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-03">Mar. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE EVE OF THE INAUGURATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The eventful though not very impressive inauguration of President Wilson will take place on March 4 in Washington. Last November the majority of the people of the United States chose Wilson to steer the ship of state for the next four years.</p>
   <p>No one supposed or could suppose on March 4, 1913, when President Wilson accepted for the first time the office of highest authority in the [United] States, that an event of such great magnitude [as the present war in Europe] would be enacted on the historical stage of the world or that this event would elevate him to the rank of one of the greatest Presidents of the United States, one whom future historians will probably place beside Washington and Lincoln.</p>
   <p>He took over the pilot's wheel at a most critical time. A storm was raging in <pb facs="5423968_4_0631.jpg" n="2"/>Mexico which wiped away the rosy sleep from the eyes of the capitalists who had imprisoned their golden calves in the Mexican mines and oil refineries. The President was urged to pacify Mexico, which he did not want to do, knowing that this would lead to a long war and might even get the United States into worse entanglements, as subsequent events have proved. Both the President and his Mixican policy have been the objects of much severe criticism, but finally it has become clear that the President was right in not wanting to engage us too deeply in the difficulties of our neighboring republic.</p>
   <p>At the time of the outbreak of the European war and the launching of relentless and brutal methods of warfare by Germany, President Wilson was able for two and a half years to preserve the neutrality of the United States, as he promised to do in August of 1914. This he has done in spite of the fact that the kind of events which are taking place demands the greatest patience and coolheaded forebearance in order not to permit oneself to lose one's equilibrium and follow either the path of the pacifists, which leads to dishonor and loss of respect and importance for the United States, or the path of jingoism which possibly <pb facs="5423968_4_0632.jpg" n="3"/>leads to premature war measures, paths which would help neither the Allies nor the [United] States.</p>
   <p>Although President Wilson was able to gain in the last election the majority of the electoral votes by the peace plank in his platform, and although in accordance with this platform he wanted to be a peace mediator and sent peace proposals to the world, nevertheless today, on the eve of his second inauguration, he faces an open war with Germany, with which four weeks ago he had to break off diplomatic relations.</p>
   <p>No one in the United States any longer has any doubt that such a war will come. Such grave events have taken place, and matters have taken such a turn, that it is impossible to wade through them by leaning on the weak stick of the pacifist.</p>
   <p>We must now depend upon a strong sword.</p>
   <p>War between the [United] States and Germany is imminent. The question, therefore, <pb facs="5423968_4_0633.jpg" n="4"/>is: What can we, or rather the Polish cause, gain by it? In our opinion our cause will benefit a great deal, because we would gain in the United States, or rather in President Wilson, a powerful backer and defender on whom we can always count. The people of the United States have expressed themselves clearly and openly on the Polish question through the mouth of President Wilson on January 22, [1917].</p>
   <p>Up to the present, the President's voice was rather that of an adviser on the side lines, that of an unprejudiced judge who wanted to bring about an agreement between two contesting parties. In the event that the United States declares war on Germany and openly sides with the Allies, we will gain in the United States an official spokesman which some day will have a voice in the peace conference and will join the nations already friendly toward us in order to fight for the postulate of freedom, independence, and autonomy for Poland.</p>
   <p>Therefore, if yesterday, as Polonia justly writes, we had every reason to rejoice at President Wilson's proclamation, today we owe him double gratitude.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0634.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This was well understood in the homeland. It was well understood by the young people in Warsaw who gathered in front of the American consulate in order to manifest their gratitude toward the President of the United States, despite the fact that the German censorship toned down the real subject of President Wilson's proclamation, leaving out the well-known phrase--the expression dealing with the uniting of all Polish territories.</p>
   <p>Therefore, if our people in the homeland have understood the importance of President Wilson's words, how much better must our immigrants, who instinctively recognized in the President a defender of their rights, and almost unanimously gave him their votes in the last election, have understood and appreciated them.</p>
   <p>On the eve of the inaugural ceremony in Washington, these Polish immigrants, scattered over the broad expanse of this land, join in the sincere wishes of the entire American nation which flow toward the White House, that our President may carry through the magnificent undertaking which he has begun for civilization and in defense of the rights of smaller nations and humanity to a successful conclusion, and that Providence may grant that the country emerge with honor and respect <pb facs="5423968_4_0635.jpg" n="6"/>out of the difficult situation in which it now finds itself.</p>
   <p>Feeling behind him the will and justification of the entire nation, and the justness of the cause which he is defending, having at his disposal all the means and resources which the power and wealth of this country grant him, he can be assured that at the critical moment not a single citizen or foreigner in this country will be found who will not answer his call and go forth to defend the principles of this freedom of which he is the greatest advocate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
