<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-24">Sept. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution Passed at Tenth Convention of Polish Women's Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0770</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0770.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-24">Sept. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION PASSED AT TENTH CONVENTION OF POLISH WOMEN'S ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We the delegates to the Tenth Convention of the Alliance of Polish Women in America, meeting at Chicago, Illinois, in view of the latest news from across the sea, bringing us emigrants an appeal from Poland's best sons to take up action for freeing the homeland from the chains of subjection; cognizant of the fact that now every minute is precious and that even the smallest delay can bring great harm to the sacred cause; without waiting until the end of our convention deliberations, do resolve and decree the following on this twenty-third day of September, 1914:</p>
   <p>1. In the name of the most sacred cause of Poland's independence, dear to every Polish heart, we appeal to all Polish organizations in America and to all of our emigrants in general, to forget at once, all differences of opinion, organizational rivalry, and partisanship; to offer each other a fraternal <pb facs="5423968_4_0771.jpg" n="2"/>handclasp; and to unite to form a central national government and treasury among the emigrants for the purpose of beginning immediate, energetic action for the cause of Poland's independence.</p>
   <p>2. Since the present polemical war, being conducted with relentless brutality in our newspapers, greatly hinders the development of a final understanding between us and prevents us from consolidating our strength to further our sacred cause; since this repulsive fratricidal war only widens differences of conviction and encourages personal antagonism, so that we call our opponents traitors to the national cause; we condemn it with all severity. We declare that there are no traitors in the Polish nation now and that the entire nation, all sons and daughters of Poland, are fired by the same spirit, the desire to regain the independence of the homeland. Since men may have different opinion and yet seek the same goal, no one has the right to hurl invectives and aspersions at a countryman whose method of approach is not the same. He who is guilty of such unseemly action at a time like this, <pb facs="5423968_4_0772.jpg" n="3"/>perpetrates a grave crime against the mother country.</p>
   <p>3. Immediately after the Poles in America have succeeded in organizing a central national government and treasury, we appeal to them to carry out the will of this government with unquestioned obedience and willingly to place all of their material wealth at its disposal.</p>
   <p>Countrymen, we have not a moment to lose! Poland is awakening from her century-old lethargy and calls to us for help! Our young men are eager for action! They await the command of their leaders with impatience! We must not delay and put off, we must strike with steel! Long live Poland, free and independent, delivered from her bondage by the united efforts of all of her children.</p>
   <p>Press Committee:</p>
   <p>Helen Setmajer</p>
   <p>Frances Garbarek</p>
   <p>Michalina Swietlik</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
