<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-06">Oct. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Recruiting for Polish Army Begun Here</title><title level="a" type="sub">Recruiting Office Opened in Polish Women's Alliance Building</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0500</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0500.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-06">Oct. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">RECRUITING FOR POLISH ARMY BEGUN HERE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Recruiting Office Opened in Polish Women's Alliance Building</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we mentioned in yesterday's issue of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, the Chicago recruiting headquarters of the Polish Army have been opened in the Polish Women's Alliance Building at 1309 North Ashland Avenue.</p>
   <p>The long-awaited action, then, has finally begun, and now it is up to us and to the Polish youth to see that the Polish Army numbers thousands upon thousands of men, so that we can show the world that a Pole knows who his enemies are, and that he knows when the time for action has come.</p>
   <p>To action--we do not need words!</p>
   <p>The Polish Army is now arising in America to join later with the Polish <pb facs="5423968_4_0501.jpg" n="2"/>Army in France, where it will march to battle--to fight for a free, independent, and united Poland. Enlistments in this army are accepted at the Polish Women's Alliance Building between 9 and 12 o'clock in the morning, 2 and 5 o'clock in the afternoon, and 7 and 9 o'clock in the evening. Lieutenant Skarzynski, who was sent to Chicago by the Military Commission expressly for this purpose, is in charge of recruiting.</p>
   <p>The recruiting office was furnished by the Union Liberty Furniture Company (owned by the Perlowski brothers) for which the company deserves sincere acknowledgement.</p>
   <p>At the present time, Michael Perlowski, president of the Citizen's Committee, is engaged in touring all the Polish communities in Chicago with Lieutenant Skarzynski, for the purpose of making preparations for agitation among Chicago's Polish youth for enlistment in the Polish Army.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0502.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Since those who enlist now cannot as yet be sent to the training camp in Canada (Ontario), quarters have been found where they can stay a few days before leaving. Through the efforts of the Citizen's Committee, a whole building on Noble Street, one of the Holy Trinity parish buildings, has been allotted for this purpose.</p>
   <p>As we can see then, work is going actively forward, and it is to be expected that, within a short time, thousands of our young men will fill the ranks of the Polish Army, ready to fight the Germans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
