<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>,
<date when="1921-11-24">Nov. 24, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The First Thanksgiving</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1088</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1088.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>,
<date when="1921-11-24">Nov. 24, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST THANKSGIVING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The founders of this great Republic of the United States came here from England when all this land was one terrible wilderness inhabited by Indians. To make a home here in the shores of America was, indeed, a heroic task. What brought the first immigrants to our shores? What was it that made them leave the well cultivated lands of England? The cozy homes they have loved so much, and all that was dear to them and come here and suffer indescribable hardships of pioneer life? The answer to this question is, indeed, a wonderful story of devotion to truth, to freedom of conscience; of untold courage.</p>
   <p>There, in the English homes, they were happy until king James began to persecute all who broke away from the state church: the Church of England. The persecution was very severe; men and women were jailed, flogged, pilloried, and otherwise tormented for their faith. They were not allowed to worship in their own way. Rather than submit to the king's will, the men and women of deep convictions decided to leave <pb facs="5423968_4_1089.jpg" n="2"/>England. First they sailed to Holland (1607-1608) to the cities of Amsterdam and Leyden, but they found it was hard to make a living there and especially that their children were forgetting the English language: their mother tongue. For these reasons they decided to go to America, where they hoped to lay the foundation of a country all their own, where they might enjoy both religious and national freedom. Because of this going from place to place, those who started for America were called the "Pilgrims." That is why we sing, "Land of the Pilgrims' pride." These pilgrims started from Holland in the summer of 1620. They were delayed in England until September 6. The name of the ship in which they sailed was the "Mayflower," a comparatively small sail boat. For nine terrible weeks the pilgrims were tossed about on the waves of the Atlantic, until they finally landed near Cape Cod and decided to settle there. It was on the 21st of December, 1620. It was a bitterly cold day. All that there was to welcome the heroic little band were woods laden with thick snow and the cold north wind howling through the branches. Only the bravest could stand the hardship of the first days. Fortunately, the <pb facs="5423968_4_1090.jpg" n="3"/>pilgrims were the bravest of the brave, fired with a passion for freedom. They were not discouraged by the difficulties, however great; but set to work to build their homes in which they were determined to stay for the rest of their lives. Their first year in America was full of hard work, sickness, famine, and danger. What heroes must they have been to suffer all this so that they might be froe. What a precious jewel must freedom be to be worth such great sacrifices. Do we value it enough? What are we doing to keep to preserve the priceless treasure left us by the Pilgrim fathers? Their labor and sacrifices were not in vain. Time came when the terrible winter, during which many of their number died, passed. At last in the fall they were able to gather in their crops and celebrate their first victory over the wilderness. The cornerstone of their new country had been laid. They knew now that they would have a home of their own where they could enjoy freedom of conscience and remain true to their national ideals.</p>
   <p>No wonder that they decided to celebrate this event, and that they set <pb facs="5423968_4_1091.jpg" n="4"/>apart a few days during which they were to feast, to rejoice and to give thanks. The first thanksgiving day was a great event; even the Indians were invited. They had helped the settlers during the hard winter by selling them furs and corn; they had shown them how to plant corn and were great friends of the white men. They had brought five deer for the feast and entertained the settlers with wild Indian games. The white men in turn gave the Indian exhibitions of military tactics and maneuvering. In 1623 another day of feasting and thanksgiving was held, and after that every year a day was set apart as a Thanksgiving Day, until in our day the last Thursday of November is a national legal holiday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
