<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-24">Sept. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Polish Committee for the Fourth Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0135</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0135.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-24">Sept. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE POLISH COMMITTEE FOR THE FOURTH LIBERTY LOAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the organizing committee for the Fourth Liberty Loan was held on Monday September 23, 1918, at 105 West Monroe Street. Mr. Streychmans was the presiding officer.</p>
   <p>The Hon. Judge Edmund Jarecki was selected as permanent chairman of the Polish committee, and, after a popular request, reconsidered his formerly planned resignation. Judge Jarecki appealed to all those present to assist him in the fulfillment of his new duties, so that he might perform the task adequately. "No one questions the loyalty of our people." Judge Jarecki said. The important thing is to maintain and uphold our reputation, and endeavor to show others how we Poles are inspired with this zeal for victory that unites all good-thinking citizens. People describe you as you seem to be. Let us Poles therefore make certain that other nationalities see our efforts and write <pb facs="5423968_4_0136.jpg" n="2"/>about us. That will greatly assist our Polish cause. In view of the fact that now at the time of subscribing for Liberty bonds every nationality will be individualized, we remind you to mark your nationality in the square on the application where it reads Polish. In that way the Polish element will easily obtain first place among all other nationalities making such purchases.</p>
   <p>The list of ward vice-chairmen and other officials in charge of the sale of Liberty bonds will be given in the official report. It might be timely to mention here that the bonds can be obtained either through a national organization authorized to make such sales or through trade organizations. A committee to plan sales promotion was chosen at this meeting.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Mary Sakowski, who was chosen general vice-chairman of the auxiliary committee, and Mr. A. Baranowski invite all women who wish to take an active <pb facs="5423968_4_0137.jpg" n="3"/>part in the sale of bonds to meet on Wednesday, September 25, 1918, at 3 P. M., at the Polish National Alliance building. Matters of utmost importance will be discussed at this meeting and all good thinking women should try to attend.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
