<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-15">Feb. 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The League of Polish Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1210</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1210.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-15">Feb. 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE LEAGUE OF POLISH WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We send this appeal to all the Polish women in Chicago with the thought that our voice will not pass on without an echo, that all our sister Poles in whom a sense of duty is awakened will join us in our civic work and show that we Polish women are ready to answer the call of our homeland with action, and to stand by for a call from America should the need arise. Therefore, sisters, let us get to work, without flowery speeches, without empty, meaningless phrases, but with sincere and genuine loyalty for those who do good to us. Let us slowly but surely prepare ourselves for the work which we must face inevitably and which must not find us unprepared.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday, February 11, a meeting of Polish women was held at the Polish National Alliance Building. Representatives of all our organizations were present as well as other Polish women who take an active interest in social work. A society called the Legion of Polish Women was organized, and the <pb facs="5423968_4_1211.jpg" n="2"/>undersigned officers were elected. The officers were granted authority to send out this appeal and to invite all Polish women affiliated with organizations or remaining outside of our organizations to come to our mass meeting, which will be held today, February 15, at 8 P.M., at the Polish Women's Alliance Building. All those who want to join may do so and take a course in hospital training given by our physicians and surgeons. Therefore if we want to demonstrate our loyalty to the United States, let us also be prepared in the event that our help should be needed.</p>
   <p>League of Polish Women:</p>
   <p>A. Emily Napieralski, president</p>
   <p>Magdalene Milewski, vice-president</p>
   <p>Mary Osuch, vice-president</p>
   <p>Antoinette Baranowski, vice-president</p>
   <p>Casimira Obarski, recording secretary</p>
   <p>Mary Sakowski, financial secretary</p>
   <p>Anna Neuman, treasurer</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
