<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-21">Mar. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a"/><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0624</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0624.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-21">Mar. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/><pb facs="5423968_4_0625.jpg" n="2"/>and application of basic moral laws, principles of civilization, and elementary human standards will also aid in forcing America to enter the war. The most provocative German crimes and assaults, the most shameless murdering of defenseless American citizens, acts which challenge the [United] States day after day to enter this war, are only the external manifestations of a hostile attitude which in the end will lead to war.</p>
   <p>This tremendous difference of outlook was given its most classic expression by the official proclamations of the President of the United States and the Chancellor of the German Reich.</p>
   <p>Accepting the heritage of the most noble American statesman, President Wilson announced:</p>
   <p>"My thoughts reach out to these great principles of sympathy and protection whereby humanity tries to secure the life of man, the lives of nonbellingerents, the lives of people who preserve the efficient and vital commercial relations <pb facs="5423968_4_0626.jpg" n="3"/>of the world, the lives of women and children, and the lives of those who toil for their support."</p>
   <p>At the same time Chancellor Bethmann-Hollweg, speaking in the name of the Teutonic race, said in the Reichstag:</p>
   <p>"We are determined to conquer not only on land but also on the seas, and today we can announce with pride that in the underseas battle we are now much stronger than we were a year ago."</p>
   <p>Between the one viewpoint and the other there is not only the ocean that covers the victims of German crimes but the entire depth of the abyss that separates the highest morality of civilization from the most abject barbarism.</p>
   <p>When Wilson says: "I have in mind those human rights without which there can be no civilization," Bethmann-Hollweg replies: "By this war I want to gain a peace which will give us compensation for what we have endured, a peace which <pb facs="5423968_4_0627.jpg" n="4"/>will assure Germany of a powerful existence in the future."</p>
   <p>What miracle could possibly bring about an agreement between these two statesmen? How could these two nations understand each other?</p>
   <p>They do not speak the same language. One thinks with his brain, the other is motivated by the greediness of his stomach. On the one hand, we have humanitarian civilization in the best sense of the word, in its most noble manifestations; on the other, German "Kultur."</p>
   <p>Today there can be no thought either of an understanding or of harmonious cohabitation of civilized peoples with the Germans, cultured in their barbarism, since the Teutonic Knights of the Cross does not recognize any law but his own need, any right but that of his own brutal strength, or any national existence except his own.</p>
   <p>Since 1914 practically all humanity has been at war with Germany. Thus the <pb facs="5423968_4_0628.jpg" n="5"/>great American Republic, if she does not want to turn over her own affairs and her own civilization to the rapacious Teutonic vultures, will finally have to admit that for her also the hour of armed action is at hand.</p>
   <p>This hour has already come. It is another matter entirely that President Wilson is approaching this war with a reluctance which is as great as the haste with which the Germans are provoking the war is wild.</p>
   <p>Arming American ships to fight submarines was scarcely an introductory step. It is now time for Wilson to take more definite steps. If the United States does not want this war to spread across the ocean and penetrate to America, it will doubtlessly have to give the Allies its absolute co-operation. This cooperation in war will no doubt be adapted to the geographical position, as well as to the economic, military, and naval conditions, of the great and powerful American Republic. But this co-operation should be unconditional and without any reservations, as befits the dignity of a great nation without blemish or fear.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0629.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>And when the final battle of the great war, in which the Star-Spangled Banner of the United States proudly flies beside the flags of all civilized nations, is fought, we believe that Wilson's ideal of justice and independence for all nations will emerge triumphant from this bloody conflict which was forced upon humanity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
