<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-19">Jan. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">One of Ours</title><title level="a" type="sub">John Ruszkiewicz</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-19">Jan. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ONE OF OURS</title><title level="a" type="sub">John Ruszkiewicz</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. John Ruszkiewicz was born in Western Poland, in the province of Posen, in 1869. As a nine-year-old boy he came with his parents to America; they settled in Milwaukee, Wisconsin. He received his elementary schooling in a Polish parochial school. When he was twenty years old, he came to Chicago. Working during the day and attending night school, he also found the opportunity to become acquainted with many outstanding Poles. In due course of time he entered the real-estate field, which business he has followed ever since.</p>
   <p>In the lifetime of Messrs. [Peter] Kiolbassa and Brodowski, who were the first Polish real-estate men in Chicago, he was superintendent of Humboldt Park and gave employment to many Poles; later he was employed as clerk in the tax collector's office in the County Building. His next appointment was that of State inspector of factories. In this capacity he helped to regulate the working <pb facs="5423968_4_1566.jpg" n="2"/>hours in industry. It is well known that many Polish girls had to work fourteen hours or more a day for unscrupulous employers. For this humanitarian work John Ruszkiewicz earned the gratitude and the support of the Polish workers.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ruszkiewicz married Mary Kowalska, daughter of a man well known for his various activities, a settler in Holy Trinity parish. There are three children, of whom the eldest boy goes to Lane Technical High School.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ruszkiewicz is one of the founders of St. Helen's parish; he is also an organizer and the present secretary of the St. Helen Building and Loan Association. only recently he was elected director of the Division Street State Bank, 2601 West Division Street; he manages the real-estate department of the bank, at the same time conducting his own real-estate business. He is a member of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, the Polish National Alliance, the Polish Brokers' Association, and many other organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1567.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the time of the last war he was very active in government loan campaigns, both American and Polish. He was even decorated by the Polish government for his efficient and effective work during the Polish Loan campaign.</p>
   <p>At present Mr. Ruszkiewicz lives in St. Helen's Parish at 1038 North Hoyne Avenue. Kind, pleasant, obliging, courteous, a good Pole, and an honest businessman, Mr. Ruszkiewicz is widely known and successful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
