<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-10-24">Oct. 24, 1913</date>.
<title level="a"/><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0877</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0877.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-10-24">Oct. 24, 1913</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the life of men and nations there are moments which are very difficult to fathom. One of those historical moments is being experienced by one of the great American Republics. Mexico, the great and rich country in the nearest neighborhood to the United States, was destined by its very nature for the exploitation of its natural wealth. It could be an excellent market for our products. But Mexico has been changed lately into a nest of hornets and has become an unlimited source of trouble for the Washington Government. For several years the revolution is ruining and tearing that country and retarding all progress.</p>
   <p>If this revolution had some definite program or any social problem to solve, we could hope that some time in the near future this turmoil will come to an end. Alas, as this struggle is conducted without any plan and is carried on by ambitious individuals in quest for leadership, it only causes a general chaos. If today Huerta could seize and shoot Caranza, or vice versa, tomorrow Zapata would do the same thing to the victor. This would not help <pb facs="5423968_4_0878.jpg" n="2"/>to pacify Mexico, because someone else would try to dispose of Zapata and to become a new ruler. Mexican constitutionalism is very problematic. Huerta, without paying any attention to the constitution, was able to put into jail all progressive members of the Mexican congress. Such an act is unthinkable in any constitutional country, as it would have provoked a violent reaction on the part of the people. Huerta's action puts an end to all talk about constitutionalism having been accepted by Mexico. Evidently the Mexican people do not value their constitution and freedom very much. Under such conditions we cannot expect a legal and constitutional government to be organized, and diplomatic relation between the United States and Mexico to be established. Waiting for legal presidential elections in Mexico is just a waste of time.</p>
   <p>But in connection with this affair another vital factor came into daylight, a factor more important than we thought. We know very well in what difficulty would be a nation which would try to enlarge its possessions. Every attempt to increase its possessions would arouse strong protests, and possibly would cause a war with another nation, expecially with England, which is in fear of losing Canada.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0879.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Even if the United States' government were to guarantee that only pacification, not annexation of Mexico is its goal, England would not believe that, and would probably, together with another interested country, land some armed forces in Mexico; and because of this fear, our government's policy in Mexico is so doubtful and vacillating that Huerta, knowing this, laughs and ignores us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
