<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XXX, No. 24,
<date when="1936-06-11">June 11, 1936</date><title level="a">A Polish Lumber Company the Manhattan Lumber Company Is the Largest Lumber and Material Firm in S. Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XXX, No. 24,
<date when="1936-06-11">June 11, 1936</date><title level="a">A POLISH LUMBER COMPANY THE MANHATTAN LUMBER COMPANY IS THE LARGEST LUMBER AND MATERIAL FIRM IN S. CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the important enterprises in South Chicago is a Polish firm, the Manhattan Lumber Company, which occupies a large tract of land at 83rd street and Commercial avenue.</p>
   <p>The company was organized in 1905 by a group of Polish businessmen, and was incorporated with a capital of $250,000. During its existence it always stood at the top because its directors and managers understood their business very well. Another contributing factor to its rapid development is the fact that they sold a first-class material.</p>
   <p>There were many changes in its management during its long existence, but always for the better. The present management is in the hands of a very competent man. They are: C. A. Hanson, president; Viotor J. Wyszynski, vice-president; William J. Pieczynski, auditor; Walenty Mularski, yard foreman; Andrew Wozniak, shop foreman; Kaz. Golkowski and John Stagenber, directors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1479.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Polish contractors patronize the firm. Almost all Polish contractors of So. Chicago patronize the Manhattan Lumber Company. The Polish lumber company is a success.</p>
   <p>A POLISH PLUMBING CONTRACTOR IN SO. CHICAGO</p>
   <p>The first professional plumber in South Chicago was and still is a Pole by the name of W. A.Swiderski, who conducts a plumbing business for the last thirty-seven years. Mr. W. A. Swiderski was born in Chicago on the 13th day of June, 1886. This Saturday he will celebrate his fiftieth anniversary in Bess emer Park, where the Poles will also celebrate Polish Day.</p>
   <p>During the twenty-seven years of his business career he performed his duties very conscientiously and on that account he was patronized by all during the building boom in Chicago.</p>
   <p>He filled many large contracts in Chicago, many of them for the Board of Education, hotels and banks. In South Chicago most of the plumbing work <pb facs="5423968_4_1480.jpg" n="3"/>has been done by Mr. Swiderski, who used to employ about twenty-five men at a time.</p>
   <p>Mr. Swiderski is the only licensed plumber in South Chicago,and is a member of the Master Plumbers' Union of Illinois.</p>
   <p>Besides his regular work he also devotes his time to national and patriotic affairs. He is a good citizen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
