<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-08">Nov. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Election of Judges in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0045</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0045.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-08">Nov. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ELECTION OF JUDGES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The citizens of Chicago showed yesterday that they are capable of deciding things for themselves and will no longer allow themselves to be led by the nose by politicians, for the price of a glass of beer, a pleasant word, or even a few dollars. No attention was paid to parties, but only to the candidates themselves, and only those were elected whom the voters in general considered the best and most reliable for their respective posts. Six Republicans and five Democrats were elected; it is clear, therefore, that the voters were not voting for parties, and were independent of any political machine.</p>
   <p>Victors For the Superior Court</p>
   <p>Marcus A. Kavanagh, Republican, 110,398 votes</p>
   <p>William A. McSurely, Republican, 101,963 votes</p>
   <p>Joseph H. Fitch, Democrat, 94,412 votes</p>
   <p>Henry V. Freeman, Republican, 90,948 votes</p>
   <p>Albert C. Barnes, Republican, 90,545 votes</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0046.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Hugo Pam, Republican, 89,879 votes</p>
   <p>M. L. McKinley, Democrat, 88,021 votes</p>
   <p>Clarence N. Goodwin, Democrat, 80,723 votes</p>
   <p>Charles M. Foell, Republican, 79,941 votes</p>
   <p>Dennis E. Sullivan, Democrat, 79,031 votes</p>
   <p>Victor for the Circuit Court (to fill vacancy)</p>
   <p>John P. McGoorty, Democrat, 72,314 votes</p>
   <p>With two exceptions, all of the candidates who had been recommended by the Bar Association, and whose names had been published in Dziennik Zwiazkowy, were elected. Candidates of the infamous Sullivan, Lorimer, Busse, "Hinky Dink," and other politicians, were shamefully beaten.</p>
   <p>One must admit that yesterday's election was very quiet and clean. Politicians did not cheat in the matter of votes, and no bribery was noticed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0047.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That yesterday the citizens did not vote blindly, or in accordance with the instructions of ward bosses, is illustrated by the fact that two small ballots--one of which, having as its purpose the increase of salaries of various officials, would have cost the city an additional hundred thousand dollars per year, and the other of which, demanding some changes in the judiciary, would have been of no benefit to the people in general, but to the advantage of certain individuals in office--were cast aside. On the other band, three proposals were accepted by vote, namely: to issue bonds in the amount of $4,655,000 for the building of new bridges; to issue bonds in the amount of $750,000 to cover various individual suits entered against the city; and to spend $1,000,000 in purchasing land for parks in the district of Austin.</p>
   <p>Yesterday the Socialists obtained, 16,819 votes, more than even they had expected. Encouraged by this showing, they hope to elect at least two aldermen next spring.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
