<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-19">May 19, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Annexation Politics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0891</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0891.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-19">May 19, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">ANNEXATION POLITICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is quite a number of would-be politicians and patriots in whose eyes the appeal of the President for $50,000 toward the relief of the poor American citizens in Cuba is an extremely important move. They are of the opinion that the relief agreed upon by representatives and senators will greatly elevate the position of the Stars and Stripes of the United States in the eyes of the Cubans, and will well prepare them for the proposed plans of President McKinley--that is, the annexation of Cuba and Hawaii.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, there is also no lack of pessimists in Washington who do not paint as rosy a picture as the former. They consider the allotment of $50,000 for the poor Americans in Cuba as nothing but humbug, and believe the annexation idea disastrous to American interests, and especially annexation by the methods proposed in the Republican platform.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0892.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They are of the opinion that if the National Treasury has enough money to render relief to Americans in Cuba, it would be more advantageous to give assistance to our unemployed workers. The so-called American poor in Cuba are such in name only, for they have become citizens of the United States by pretext. They are nothing more than cowardly revolutionists who fled to Key West, Florida, prior to the rising, took out citizenship papers and returned to Cuba, only to agitate anew. Now that they are being pressed against the wall by the Spanish Government they are making pleas to Uncle Sam for help. Such people are nothing more than foreigners hiding under the cloak of American citizenship.</p>
   <p>If the purpose of the relief is to create enthusiasm among the Cubans and simplify the annexation for President McKinley, then it is even worse. Such a policy would betray a lack of logic on the part of President McKinley.</p>
   <p>His efforts to establish protective tariffs has as its objective the betterment of our industry, especially that of sugar which is manufactured from beets <pb facs="5423968_4_0893.jpg" n="3"/>raised by our farmers. The protective policy does not agree with the policy of annexation of Cuba and Hawaii. These islands produce so much cheap sugar from sugar cane that they can supply the needs of this country. The millions of dollars invested by American capital in the sugar beet industry, which produces sugar at a higher cost, would be jeopardized, for these factories would have to close.</p>
   <p>Under such circumstances it is simple to understand that the annexation policies of President McKinley, relative to Cuba and Hawaii, cannot be considered. He can afford to be liberal with the people's money for the purpose of gaining popularity, but we do not agree that he should step into international politics merely because a group of would-be politicians and patriots, who do not see farther than the tip of their nose, favor this plan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
