<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-13">June 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Casimir E. Midcwicz Given Law Degree</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1408</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1408.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-13">June 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CASIMIR E. MIDCWICZ GIVEN LAW DEGREE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Commencement exercises were held yesterday at Northwestern University's Patten Gymnasium at which degree were awarded. Among those to receive his Bachelor of Law degree was young Casimir Midowicz, son of the late Dr. Casimir Midowicz, well-known physician and nationalistic worker who will long be remembered by the Poles and by Chicago, and Theodisia Hoffman Widowicz, who, since the death of her husband has been living only for her son and has awaited yesterday's occasion for many long years.</p>
   <p>Our young lawyer was born in Calumet, [S]hasta County, California. He attended St. Stanislaus Kostka Parochial School and Carl Schurz High School. After graduation from high school, he attended the Chicago and Northwestern universities, at the latter of which he completed his three years of law with high honors. In addition to the degree, he was awarded the Charles Koepke Prize.</p>
   <p>In the last year of his tudies, the University faculty appointed young Midowicz <pb facs="5423968_4_1409.jpg" n="2"/>to an associate editorship of the Illinois Law Review, the first Pole to receive this honor. He was sent at the university's expense to the Appellate Court in Mount Vernon in order to review and report on the proceedings of its last session.</p>
   <p>Midowicz was employed for some time at the Northwestern Trust and Savings Bank and is at present employed by the law firm of Zimmerman, Garrett and Rundell, National Life Building.</p>
   <p>We extend our congratulations to the young lawyer and we hope that he will travel in the footstep of his illustrious father, remembering that, although he was born in this country, he is of Polish blood. We also extend our congratulations to his mother, who, after many years of waiting, can now be proud of her son.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
