<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-25">June 25, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Campaign against Smallpox</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1361</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1361.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-25">June 25, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL CAMPAIGN AGAINST SMALLPOX</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual campaign against smallpox by the Board of Health has again begun. The best method of avoiding an epidemic is the inoculation of school children, and adults as well, against this disease. For this purpose groups of doctors have been appointed in various parts of Chicago to supervise the work of vaccination. Every parishioner, every mother should bear in mind that this is one of her obligations to her children.</p>
   <p>Dr. Szwajkart has been appointed to take charge of [vaccination] in St. Stanislaus Kostka's and St. John Cantius' parishes. For the convenience of those who are unable to see Dr. Szwajkart [at his office] special hours have been arranged by him. He is to be at St. Stanislaus Kostka's parish school each Wednesday and Thursday from 10 A. M. to 12 noon. At St. John Cantius' parish hall he will have the same hours on Friday and Saturday.</p>
   <p>Inoculation is free. If the vaccination takes, the doctor issues a certificate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1362.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Children who come to the designated places should be thoroughly bathed and have clean underwear. A handkerchief should be brought to cover the vaccination. Children from twelve to sixteen who have not as yet been vaccinated should come.</p>
   <p>Remember, mothers and fathers, to bring your children to the places above designated. If this [order] is not complied with you will have serious trouble with the Board of Health inspectors. Investigators will go from house to house, demanding evidence that the children have been vaccinated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
