<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-30">May 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[The McKinley Tariff Legislation]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1045</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1045.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-30">May 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[THE McKINLEY TARIFF LEGISLATION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The deductions of the newspaper New Life, defending the predatory statutes of McKinley, are comical; [they are] supposed to be proof that a high tariff assures a better remuneration for the laboring man than free trade could accomplish. It compiles the payrolls and expenses of the working people in the United States in localities where the enactment of McKinley prevails, and the pay and expenses of the workers in England where free trade governs.</p>
   <p>That is no way to do. It is truly a blindfolding of the people. We readily agree that the worker in America finds far better conditions than exist in Europe, however not because of the high tariff, but rather despite the existence of this nefarious tariff. The causes of this [prosperity] are entirely different. If the New Life or other Republican papers wish to make such <pb facs="5423968_4_1046.jpg" n="2"/>comparison, then let them also compare our existing conditions with those prevailing for example in Russia, where an enormously high tariff is instituted. Let them compare the conditions existing in England with its free trade with those of Russia and its high tariff, and then it will become evident, if the assertion is true, whether a high tariff improves the welfare of the worker. It is no art to befuddle the people in this manner. Europe is different from America. Here, even if the highest tariff were imposed--despite that, the conditions of the workers' existence would be better than anywhere in Europe where the people work for the maintenance of large armies, and the estates of the rulers, the true wastrels.</p>
   <p>If, however, the conditions of existence of the working man in America are better today than even in England, still it does not follow that we should maintain the high tariff, as if we were satisfied with these better conditions. In Europe the conditions are unbearable, and there even free trade could not help until other reforms were instituted; here, in the United <pb facs="5423968_4_1047.jpg" n="3"/>States, conditions are tolerable to some extent, but are not as they should be, and the abolition of the high tariff will lead to the bettering of conditions. Even the better republicans feel this. The greatest man of state of the Republican party, Blaine, is also conscious of this because he has forcibly brought a fragment of free trade into McKinley's enactment--agreements of mutual tariff exchange.</p>
   <p>We are not commenting further on this subject in this column because in addition to our statement, we submit an excellent quotation from Henry George on this question. We again urge upon our readers a careful consideration of this interesting matter, since after study, the reader will possess such strong arguments that repudiation will be difficult.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
