<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-22">Feb. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">One Hundred and Forty Years Ago and Now</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-22">Feb. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ONE HUNDRED AND FORTY YEARS AGO AND NOW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are moments which, though centuries apart, are almost identical, if it happens that they result from similar conditions. A hundred and forty years ago, just as today, America was at war, with this difference, however, that it fought for independence with the last strength of its best sons and meager resources; today, as a giant, it fights not only for the freedom and independence of various countries but for the democracy of the whole world. A hundred and forty years ago, as today, America was facing a crisis created by the shortage of food supplies for the soldiers in the field and for those who supported them. On January 23, 1778, the commander in chief of the American armed forces, later to become the first President of the United States--George Washington--addressed the following words to a committee from Congress:</p>
   <p>"If during this winter and in the coming spring we do not receive adequate food <pb facs="5423968_4_0417.jpg" n="2"/>supplies, we cannot expect any success in the coming campaign. Our army, weakened by the irregular and inadequate arrival of food supplies, can expect little else than ill fame and disillusionment."</p>
   <p>In his well-known letter addressed to the American farmers at their convention this year, President Wilson wrote the following words:</p>
   <p>"The course of events has taken such a turn that the forces fighting for freedom, the freedom of the people of the whole world as well as our own, depend upon us to an extraordinary and unexpected extent, namely, for the maintenance of life so that they can live and fight. We are fighting just as much for the freedom and independence of the United States today as if we were fighting our Revolutionary War over again."</p>
   <p>In principle then, nothing has changed. Today, just as a century and a half ago, not so important a part is played by arms and the number of men as by adequate food supplies. Today, if the Allies were deprived of adequate food supplies, <pb facs="5423968_4_0418.jpg" n="3"/>they would not be conquered by German gas of superiority of Teutonic armed forces, or by the perfidious diplomacy of the enemy, but by hunger, which would lay them at the Germans' feet. And so, just as a hundred and forty years ago Congress heeded Washington's words and supplied food, so today President Wilson's words ought be heeded not only by the farmers but by the whole American public; for outside of the army itself, this public is the greatest and most important factor in making possible the life, movements, and final victory of the Allies.</p>
   <p>Today is the 186th anniversary of the birth of George Washington, who was not only the founder of American democracy, but the rock upon which America has developed into the defender and herald of the rights of individual nations and of man. Had it not been for the wisdom, deep insight, capability, and perseverance of Washington, the United States might not have become what it is today; perhaps, during the present war, it would be fighting on the opposite side, or, divided into small countries, would be conducting within itself a war similar to the one now raging in Europe. That it is united and faithful to the postulates <pb facs="5423968_4_0419.jpg" n="4"/>of democracy, that it has taken up arms and tipped the scales of victory to the side of the Allies, is due only to the immortal spirit of George Washington. It was a great moment for the world when this incorruptible man first saw the light of day, and this 186th anniversary of his birth is a great day for humanity.</p>
   <p>America, however, remained faithful not only to Washington's principles but to such virtues of his as perseverance. Washington was not one of these leader for whom the star of victory shone continually. He was more often defeated than victorious. At the very beginning of his military career, Washington had to surrender Fort Necessity to the French. As commander in chief of the Revolutionary Army, he was defeated by the English at Long Island on August 27, 1776, and later at White Plains on October 28, 1776. Defeated, he had to retreat through New Jersey, and after temporary success at Princeton in January, 1777, he was again defeated, first at Brandywine and then at German-town in the same year. After the indecisive battle of Monmouth, he withdrew the remnants of his army with difficulty. But in spite of all this ill fortune <pb facs="5423968_4_0420.jpg" n="5"/>he never lost heart, he never wavered nor surrendered, he never lost faith in himself and in the American cause, and in the end he was victorious.</p>
   <p>That great virtue, perseverance, remained a characteristic of the American people, and it is this virtue that the Allies can thank for the fact that they will win. They can face more than one disaster, more than one disappointment, but with the help of the Americans, they must win in the end. Just as Washington did not give in until he had reached his goal, so America will not give in until democracy triumphs and brings with it the freedom of nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
