<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-23">Jan. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Late Theophil Gordon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1556</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1556.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-23">Jan. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE LATE THEOPHIL GORDON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We were just going to write about him in our section "One of Ours"; in fact we had his short biographical sketch ready, when suddenly--as it frequently happens with human plans that turn to dust--we are compelled today to write his obituary.</p>
   <p>For the last several days a sincere and deep sorrow has been felt in the building of the Dziennik Chicagoski. For Theophil Gordon is dead: He died after several weeks' illness. For many years he was general manager of our firm and chief bookkeeper. He was liked by everybody for his warm and sympathetic heart and his pleasant, friendly, generous nature.</p>
   <p>Truly, one cannot think, one cannot believe that our administration has lost such a representative figure, with his characteristic Polish features. For a long, long time will he be missed at his usual window by his fellow workers, who are deeply grieved by his death, and by all who have known him and held <pb facs="5423968_4_1557.jpg" n="2"/>him in high esteem. His loss will be felt by his many friends, and how many friends, and how many friends he had could be seen by the multitude which thronged and filled to capacity the gigantic Church of St. Mary of the Angels to pay him the last tribute yesterday. Deep sorrow for his passing is felt everywhere.</p>
   <p>The late Theophil Gordon, the fourth child of Thomas and Anne Gordon, was born April 19, 1865, in Truszczyn, in the Prussian-occupied part of Poland. He received his elementary and secondary education in his native land. Having learned the leatherworkers' trade, he emigrated to Germany, where he became noted for his excellent work in his trade, being honored with orders for the German Kaiser's household in Berlin. After spending several years in Berlin he left for America with his brother Edmund and landed at Baltimore. Shortly afterwards he arrived in Chicago and settled here for good. Two years later he married Miss Stanislava Stabrowska. The marriage ceremony, was performed in St. Stanislas Kostka's Church by his brother, the Reverend Francis Gordon, the present pastor of St. Mary of the Angels' Church and the delegate general of the Ressurectionist Congregation. This marriage has been blessed with <pb facs="5423968_4_1558.jpg" n="3"/>eight children, of whom six are alive, one daughter, Helen, and five sons, of whom the eldest, Thomas, is also an administrative officer of the Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <p>His beloved wife died on May 27, 1914, and in less than eight years he has followed her himself, passing away on January 19 of this year at 11:30 P. M. in the Polish hospital, where, very seriously ill, he was taken by order of his physicians. In the Christmas holidays he became seriously ill with ptomaine poisoning, which weakened his system to such an extent that complications which developed in recent days have cut the thread of this good and honorable man's life.</p>
   <p>The late Theophil Gordon was the best of husbands and fathers; he was, one may say, an example of the good citizen and the good worker in the community. His greatest care was his home and his family; he was thrifty and economical.</p>
   <p>At first he worked for various concerns and even conducted his own business; <pb facs="5423968_4_1559.jpg" n="4"/>finally he associated himself with the Dziennik Chicagoski, where for more than twenty years he was one of the most useful and most dependable workers. He gave his children the best possible education; his daughter graduated from the Holy Family Academy, and his sons graduated from the St. Stanislas College. One son works in the offices of the Dziennik Chicagoski, another is studying dentistry, and the third is an electrotechnician.</p>
   <p>His whole active and busy life was devoted to industrious and diligent work, to his nearest and dearest, and to his community. He belonged to a great many societies and organizations. At one time he was a vice-president of the Executive Board of the Polish Alma Mater, a member of which he had been from its foundation, belonging to the St. Aloysius Section Number Seven. He was also a member of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, of the Society of St. Vincent de Paul, of the St. Casimir Society, of the Order of Catholic Foresters, of the Mickiewicz Citizens' Club in St. Mary of the Angels' parish, in which he held the office of president, and of the church choir of St. Mary of the Angels'. Everywhere he was one of the most active and most highly esteemed of men; his <pb facs="5423968_4_1560.jpg" n="5"/>opinions were always respected and appreciated. More than ten years ago he was one of the group of men who organized the Father Gordon Building and Loan Association, and he was president of its board of directors from its very beginning and one of those who contributed most to its present splendid development.</p>
   <p>But his activities included also purely patriotic services rendered to this country. In the World War he was called to take part in the recruiting work, to help in creating our army of millions of men; he was even elected president of the Thirty-sixth Draft District, and his services were so distinguished and valuable that later he received a letter of thanks and appreciation from the Government of the United States.</p>
   <p>This is a short summary of the active and industrious life of a well-deserving and noble citizen and countryman of ours.</p>
   <p>Today, writing this biographical sketch, we are bidding him good-bye in deep <pb facs="5423968_4_1561.jpg" n="6"/>sorrow, sorrow even greater because of his so sudden and completely unexpected departure. We firmly believed that his strong constitution would overcome this deadly illness, the more so because everything was done to save him. Alas, the complication of ills together with the exhaustion of his constitution frustrated all efforts.</p>
   <p>Theophil Gordon has not left much of wordly goods; it will not be much for the little flock of children which he is leaving behind him. But he did leave them a priceless heritage in this world--a good name, the example of a noble and useful life, and the respect of his community and his countrymen. This treasure is more precious than temporal riches; it cannot be squandered over the earth but will remain the lasting possession of the family to which, because of the death of one of its oldest members, we hasten to offer our sincere and deep sympathy in its hour of sorrow.</p>
   <p>Eternal peace to our beloved friend after a life of honest labor and great accomplishment!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
