<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-08">May 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Save!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0270</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0270.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-08">May 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LET US SAVE!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In American papers,one sees quite frequently the complaint that the American public lacks a certain very valuable virtue namely, thriftiness, and this is contrasted with the millions saved annually by European immigrants. We can say with pride that thrift is one of the characteristics of the Polish people in America, and no agitation or cajolery is necessary to encourage thrift in Polish homes; that is, the saving of small sums.</p>
   <p>Rather can we find certain faults with the way in which these savings are invested. In view of the fact that banks often pay little or no interest, institutions that give very little guarantee of stability lure depositors with promises of high interest rates; very often bankruptcy or abuses of trust of institutions of this kind cause distrust [among our people]. All inconveniences <pb facs="5423968_4_0271.jpg" n="2"/>concerning the interest rates as well as the security of the principal are automatically eliminated by the purchase of war-savings stamps.</p>
   <p>The conveniences of saving this way are as follows;</p>
   <p>1. Even the smallest sums can be saved, for the value of a single stamp is twenty-five cents.</p>
   <p>2. The rate of interest is higher than that offered by any other investment, since interest is compound. After five years, $10 will be paid for every $8.32.</p>
   <p>3. The security of the money scarcely needs to be mentioned; such guarantee as the government gives is not given by any other financial institution in the world.</p>
   <p>4. Proof of the privileges derived from placing savings in war-savings <pb facs="5423968_4_0272.jpg" n="3"/>stamps is the fact that the Treasury Department will not accept sums in excess of a thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>All those who are saving for a "rainy day" or for other reasons ought to place their money in these stamps, which may be purchased at any post office or in the offices of the Polish National Alliance, where war-savings stamps are always available.</p>
   <p>During the present critical time for all of us, when the fate of the world and the fate of our dearest homeland are at stake, it is our duty to this adopted American homeland of ours, struggling for the same ideals as we are, and using the same means to reach them--namely, by engaging in a life or death struggle with a mortal enemy--to aid the treasury of this country, with our savings, to buy arms with which to fight the enemy.</p>
   <p>During next week, people of good will, giving their time and labor gratuitously <pb facs="5423968_4_0273.jpg" n="4"/>to the service of a great ideal, will gather pledges from the people to save a certain portion of their weekly earnings according to their means, so that by the end of the year, December 31, 1918, each person will have a minimum of twenty dollars saved. Naturally, this is not a limitation; whoever can, may save as much as a thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>It is our opinion that no one will refuse outright to make such a pledge, for saving a few cents a week in order to make up twenty dollars by the end of the year is within the means of everyone. Even if it were necessary to do without a few cigarettes or a few glasses of beer, or perhaps a few packages of gum or candy, it would not be so great a sacrifice. At the same time, the opportunity of personal benefit, coupled with the fulfillment of our duty to both our adopted and natural homelands, is such a rare one that everyone ought to avail himself of it willingly.</p>
   <p>To many it might seem that a few cents a week, that is, twenty dollars by the <pb facs="5423968_4_0274.jpg" n="5"/>end of the year, will not be a very great loss to the treasury. If we take into consideration, however, that of the one hundred and twenty million people in the United States, approximately eighty million are self-supporting, and that if everyone of these saves at least twenty dollars, it will amount to more than a billion and a half dollars, we come to the conclusion that every little bit is one brick for the fortress this country is building for the defense of the rights and liberties of all humanity.</p>
   <p>Let no one neglect to supply his little brick; let this small saving that can give such great service be a part of anyone's saving for a "rainy day". We all expect and we are all awaiting better times in a free, independent, and united Poland that will reach to the sea; let that small saving serve to pay the cost of returning home to our own people--and when that moment arrives, we will have long forgotten that that saving ever meant any sacrifice or that we ever deprived ourselves of a few personal pleasures.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0275.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>There should not be a single individual among the Poles who would refuse this small, voluntary obligation, for such a refusal could not be founded upon any reasonable grounds that could justify it; we are certain, moreover, that there will be no such persons.</p>
   <p>In the hope that these few words of explanation and advice will find acceptance in the widest possible circles of our community, we submit to the public the information that pledges will be taken during the week of May 11-18.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
