<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-20">July 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Medical Lectures for Polish Mothers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1324</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1324.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-20">July 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">MEDICAL LECTURES FOR POLISH MOTHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish physicians of our city have just made a decision of great importance, we learn. Since the state of health in Chicago is unsatisfactory, and on the northwest side of the city residents are not adhering as they should to rules of sanitation, often with the result that unpleasant incidents occur with the health department, to say nothing of the detrimental effect upon the general health of the Polish people, the Polish physicians have decided to give a series of lectures on health and hygiene for Polish women, who ought to know how to conduct their households under healthful and hygienic conditions, how to rear their children and feed them properly, and so on. The lectures will be held daily except Saturday and Sunday at two o'clock in the afternoon at Eckhart Park, Noble Street and Chicago Avenue, beginning next Monday [July 23].</p>
   <p>The Polish physicians who have decided to give these free lectures, appeal, through the columns of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, to all Polish mothers who are concerned with the health of their families to attend the first lecture on Monday. Mothers may bring their children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1325.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Polish physicians submitted the following appeal with a request for publication:</p>
   <p>To Polish Mothers!</p>
   <p>A great many children and infants die in the surmer months, mostly from stomach and intestinal ailments. In Polish communities, densely populated and none too clean, the death rate among children is appallingly high and the chief cause is the ignorance of Polish mothers. The majority do not know how to care for their children, how to feed them properly, how, and how often to bathe them , or what sort of clothes they should wear. Diarrhea, with which so many children suffer in the summer months, is usually the result of improper feeding, either in respect sickness, expense, sorrow, and often death--ignorance, but sometimes neglect also.</p>
   <p>In order to change this state of affairs and thus to lower the death rate among <pb facs="5423968_4_1326.jpg" n="3"/>children, the Association of Polish Physicians of Chicago is arranging a series of popular lectures for mothers during the week of July 23 to 28 inclusive. The lectures will be held at Eckhart Park, Noble Street and Chicago Avenue, daily from two to four o'clock in the afternoon. The program of lectures is as follows:</p>
   <p>Monday: two to three o'clock, Dr. A. Balcerzak, "General Hygiene"; three to four o'clock, Dr. W. Statkiewicz, "Feeding of Infants and Hygiene".</p>
   <p>Tuesday: two to three o'clock, Dr. J. M. Kostrzewski, "General Prevention of Disease"; three to four o'clock, Dr. F. Cienciara, "Prevention of Diarrhea".</p>
   <p>Wednesday: two to three o'clock, Dr. A. Pietrzykowski, "First Aid in Sickness"; three to four o'clock, Dr. F. Lenart, "When to Call the Doctor".</p>
   <p>Thursday: two to three o'clock, Dr. S. Boguslawski, "Smallpox, Whooping Cough, Rickets, Consumption, and Paralysis"; three to four o'clock, Dr. A. Szumkowski, <pb facs="5423968_4_1327.jpg" n="4"/>"Infectious Diseases, Scarlet Fever, Diphtheria, and Measles".</p>
   <p>Friday: two to three o'clock, Dr. F. Kalacinski, "Nutrition, Feeding"; three to four o'clock, Dr. K. Gieraltowski, "Nutrition, Breast Feeding".</p>
   <p>We invite all Polish mothers and wives to the first course. The lectures will be concise, interesting, and practical, and what is most important, they will be given in Polish. Those who listen to them with attention and understanding will learn much in the way of preventing children's illnesses and may save a good deal of expense, sorrow, and misfortune. Every woman who has children should attend these lectures and encourage her friends and acquaintances to do likewise.</p>
   <p>We have hopes that the clergy will support our efforts from the pulpit, and that the press will do so by publishing our appeal in its columns. If the first course at Eckhart Park is well attended, similar lectures will be given in other Polish communities throughout the city.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>The Association of Polish Physicians of</p>
   <p>Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
