<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-06-05">June 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to Polish Voters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0079</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0079.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-06-05">June 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO POLISH VOTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not many voters are aware of the importance of the coming judicial election in Cook County; all should stop, therfore, and think before they cast their vote. It is impossible to know all of the candidates personally, therefore, I as an attorney knowing personally practically all of the candidates as well as their record and as an active citizen taking part in the affairs of city government, am in a position to render information and advice to my clients and voters of my ward. The important issue at hand is to elect judges who are guided by integrity, and honesty, without selfishness. I, as a true Democrat, regret to say that the members of the bench in all of the courts of Cook County, with rare exceptions are members of the Republican Party, and since there are but nine Democrats judges in all of the branches, it is to these 9 men that credit for their splendid record must be given; the balance of the bench which is 47 judges are Republican, therefore, there seems to be irregularity as to the just division of high positions where justice should prevail supreme.</p>
   <p>The Democratic party has assembled a number of presiding judges, and also some leading attorneys to become candidates to the bench, for election or re-election. Some of the names we find on the Democratic ticket are men well-known for integrity and honesty such as has been displayed by the judges: Baker, Clifford, Mack, Adams, Brown, Honore, Kersten, Walker, Windes and other prominent, private citizens such as Brown, Arthur, Burke, McGoorty, Morrill and Murray.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0080.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After looking over this list we can rest assured that we are giving the right men our support. We have, therefore, nothing to be ashamed of. Citizens, do not forget, that on Monday, June 7th, the election for judges is to be held, and it is your duty to vote. Be sure to vote the Democratic ticket and assure yourselves of honest judicial administration in Cook County.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
