<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Poles Are Not Enemies of the United States</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Delegation of Twenty-five Poles Calls on Attorney Clyne</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0592</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0592.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLES ARE NOT ENEMIES OF THE UNITED STATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Delegation of Twenty-five Poles Calls on Attorney Clyne</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A delegation of twenty-five influential Poles, representing the Poles who have come to the United States from Pozen and Galicia and headed by Julius F. Smietanka and Francis X. Rydzewski, called on County Prosecuting Attorney Clyne yesterday in a very important matter. Since the declaration of a state of war by President Wilson, the Poles from Pozen have been considered as enemy aliens by the American government. According to the Federal authorities, they are to be treated like Germans. Since President Wilson's declaration, the Poles from Pozen have been unable to receive either their first or second citizenship papers.</p>
   <p>This is a great blow and a grave injustice to us Poles. Are we to suffer in the United States, too, because in the past our enemy, through dastardly means and by criminal actions behind our backs, succeeded in subjecting us?</p>
   <p>The delegation explained the matter in detail to Prosecuting Attorney Clyne, <pb facs="5423968_4_0593.jpg" n="2"/>requesting that the unjust appellation of enemy aliens be removed from the Poles, and that no obstacles be placed in the path of their receiving their citizenship papers.</p>
   <p>Clyne would not give the delegation any definite answer. He admitted, however, that the demands of the Poles were just, and asked them to come back to him Monday.</p>
   <p>This matter ought to be given every consideration by the Federal authorities.</p>
   <p>We believe that the government of the United States, which has always championed liberty, will not treat us as enemies simply because we have lost our freedom against our will as the result of the lawlessness of our invaders.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
