<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-06">Jan. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">One of Ours</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mieczvslas J. Pereczkouski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1399</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1399.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-06">Jan. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ONE OF OURS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mieczvslas J. Pereczkouski</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Widely known and generally liked in the social life of our Chicago Polonia, Mr. Bereczkowski was born in 1880 in Tarnow, Poland where he attended grammar school and the classical gymnasium. We completed only two years of the gymnasium because in 1893, as a thirteen-year-old boy, he came to Chicago to live with his uncle in St. Stanislas parish. were he was at first a pupil of the St. Staniglas parochial school and then of the public grammar school. Shortly afterwards he moved with his uncle to California. After his return to Chicago he enrolled at Northwestern University as a student in the pharmaceutical department, and in 1902, after passing the final examination, the received the certificate of registered pharmacist when only twenty-one years old. During the first years of his career as a pharmacist he was manager of the Burdow drugstore at Noble and Blackhawk Streets. In the following year, however, he went into the real estate business, entering the firm of Stylinski, Szwajkart and Company, whose offices were located at Milwaukee Avenue and Tell Street and later were removed to Millmaukee Avenue not far from Division Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1400.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At present Mr. Bereczkowski is conducting his own real estate business.</p>
   <p>Married in 1912 to Miss Alexandra Stachowska, has one son, Robert. Besides being a member of a great many American organizations, including the good County Real Estate Board and the Iroquois Club, Mr. Bereczkowski belongs to many Polish societies, among others the Polish National Alliance. He is also one of the founders of the Polish Real Estate Association and at present is its president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
