<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-24">Apr. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">From the Polish Recruiting Station</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-24">Apr. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE POLISH RECRUITING STATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish recruiting station at the Polish Roman Catholic Union Building has aroused a great deal of interest among Chicago Poles.</p>
   <p>Since Saturday about one hundred men have enlisted in Uncle Sam's army. Mr. J. S. Konopa and T. Kotlowski drive the enlisting men over to the main recruiting office. They are aided by Mr. L. Nyka.</p>
   <p>Saturday there was unusual activity at the Polish Roman Catholic Union Building. In the evening veterans of the Spanish War marched in, headed by Captain Lanson and Sigismund Wisniewski. The sound of bugles and drums awakened war enthusiasm among the people, who yelled hurrah until the walls of the Polish Roman Catholic Union actually shook.</p>
   <p>Captain Lanson, in a conversation with a reporter of an American newspaper, stated he had never seen so much enthusiasm and zeal at any other station. He announced that those not accepted at the main recruiting office at 526 <pb facs="5423968_4_0568.jpg" n="2"/>South State Street, should come to him at Room 510, Grand Pacific Hotel, Clark Street and Jackson Boulevard. Men are needed as mechanics, cooks, etc. for the Quartermaster Reserve Corps and the intendancy.</p>
   <p>Attorney Leon C. Nyka has been busy right along making out first citizenship papers. Those willing to enlist in the army will receive their papers without any difficulty.</p>
   <p>Captain Kenney was well pleased with the turn of events. He said that the Poles can and should raise their own regiment.</p>
   <p>Tuesday, at 1 P. M., all those who enlisted at the Polish recruiting station are to meet there and then go in a body to the main recruiting office downtown, thence to the Jefferson barracks in St. Louis, Missouri.</p>
   <p>Countrymen, time presses! At any moment now Congress will pass the Draft Bill and then everyone will be pressed into service.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0569.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Do not wait until you are grabbed by the collar. Join now, voluntarily! Do your duty!</p>
   <p>Captain Kenney said that with such enthusiasm we can raise a regiment. So far only 901 boys have enlisted; this is not enough.</p>
   <p>Do you know how many men form an infantry regiment during war time? To form an infantry regiment 21,642 officers and soldiers are required. We are very far from this number!</p>
   <p>When are you going to join? The bureau is open daily from 9 A. M. to 9 P. M., and on Sundays from 1 to 6 P. M.</p>
   <p>Our compatriots are given every help and consideration at the bureau. Those who have no citizenship papers will receive them without any red tape. Application blanks can be filled out right at the station.</p>
   <p>More men with automobiles are needed to drive our boys at 3 P. M. to the main <pb facs="5423968_4_0570.jpg" n="4"/>recruiting station at 526 South State Street. It seems that everyone, with the exception of Mr. J. S. Konopa and Mr. Kotlowski, is somehow sleeping on the job. Who will volunteer?</p>
   <p>Anyone wanting to join the army for the duration of the war should be under forty years of age, should know how to sign his name, and should be able to understand English after a fashion.</p>
   <p>Those under eighteen must have the consent of their parents or guardians.</p>
   <p>Older men who have wives in Europe should register as unmarried.</p>
   <p>To join the infantry, coast artillery, and engineers, the applicant must be at least 5 feet 4 inches tall, and weigh not more than 190 pounds.</p>
   <p>To join the cavalry the applicant must be twenty-one or over, not less than 5 feet 4 inches or more than six feet tall, and his weight may not exceed 190 pounds. To join the Mountain Batteries the applicant may not be less than <pb facs="5423968_4_0571.jpg" n="5"/>5 feet 8 inches tall.</p>
   <p>The minimum weight of an applicant of twenty-one or over for general service is 128 pounds; applicants under this weight will not be accepted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
