<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-21">Nov. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Much Depends Upon Polish Women</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-21">Nov. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">MUCH DEPENDS UPON POLISH WOMEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The priestess of the home fires, the guiding angel, the guardian of the purest virtues which every Pole should possess, the inculcator of the true national ideal, the defender of the Polish language, traditions, and customs, and of clean Polish habits--such is every good wife and mother to her family. Many examples in the history of our homeland prove that the burden of keeping bright the torch of love for the homeland, so that it would always burn in our hearts, has rested mainly on our Polish women.</p>
   <p>The fathers girded the great Polish knights and heroes for war with the enemy, taught them to ride, to fight with sword, ax, or lance, and hardened their bodies with camp life; but the mothers taught their sons a sense of duty, self-respect, and love for their native land, poured courage and all other noble <pb facs="5423968_4_1242.jpg" n="2"/>attributes into them, and rooted out sternly all wicked or ignoble impulses. The fathers had neither the time nor the ability to bring up their children from the cradle to the teens, and so the duty of educating them to be good citizens, of making them good Poles, fell upon these priestesses of the home fires.</p>
   <p>The young people were brought up in a model fashion. They were examples of the virtues of manliness, justice, and love of truth. When the husbands, with their grown sons, all in full armor and bearing their weapons, left for the battlefields to run the invaders out of the borders of the country, and when the invaders sacked the towns and villages, the Polish matrons, lacking the help of strong arms and manly breasts, seized the helm of the entire society in their weak hands. Besides bringing up the children in an exemplary way, they fostered the agriculture, industry and commerce of the country, and in addition cared for the wounded knights, sewed the clothing for the soldiers at the battle front, made bandages and medicines for the wounded, cared for the poor widows and <pb facs="5423968_4_1243.jpg" n="3"/>orphans, and performed a thousand other tasks.</p>
   <p>Such were our great-grandmothers--such should be our present mothers, wives, and sisters. One does not demand of the present Polish woman the labors that the Polish woman performed ages ago in feudal Poland. These heavy duties no longer exist for her. But one does demand that she bring up her children in the true Polish spirit. Today's Polish mother should inculcate, in the creatures to whom she has given life, a love for the mother tongue, respect for our past, and a belief in the future of the Polish nation.</p>
   <p>It is even more necessary that the Polish women perform this duty here in a strange land, where we are surrounded on all sides by foreign influences that take away from us thousands of our young people, absorbing them completely. In Poland, under three different governments, brave Polish women fight valiantly against the oppressors and bring up their children in the Polish spirit, but <pb facs="5423968_4_1244.jpg" n="4"/>here many neglect their sacred duty, and allow the younger generation to become irrevocably lost to national causes.</p>
   <p>Here it is not enough to bring up a son to be a "sport", to chew tobacco, to pour down liquor, and, often, to become a bully; it is not enough to bring up a daughter to be a painted and powdered "doll", who chatters only in English, and who seeks amusements in inappropriate places. One must bring up these young sprigs in accordance with the example set by our great-grandmothers, that is, imbue them with virtue, respect for the mother tongue, and love of their homeland back in Europe, instill modesty in the girls, and noble manliness in the boys.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, in trying to uphold the Polish spirit here in our young people, we ourselves must set a good example--we must join Polish organizations and bring our children into them. You, Polish fathers and mothers, should be members of the Polish National Alliance; you should support the Polish Falcons; you should spread Polish song here through organizing and developing choirs, and should <pb facs="5423968_4_1245.jpg" n="5"/>bring your daughters and sons to choir meetings. Surely your little ones will not then lose their national identity, but will love it sincerely, because they will recognize the beauty of Polish ideals; they will be filled with noble impulses and true patriotism.</p>
   <p>A great deal depends on the Polish women, not only in bringing up their children in an exemplary and patriotic fashion, but also in influencing their husbands and brothers into a more zealous support of the national cause, into joining organizations of such noble aims as the Polish National Alliance, the Polish Falcons, singers alliances, Polish army alliances, etc. Even ten intimate friends could not persuade a man to join a Polish organization half so well as a wife can persuade her husband; a mother, her son; a sister, her brother; a maid, her fiance; a cousin, her cousin.</p>
   <p>Then let our gracious Polish women recognize the fact that they possess this power with which they can do much for the Polish cause. A tired husband and <pb facs="5423968_4_1246.jpg" n="6"/>father forgets many things, and neglects many others, but our Polish women should remember and care; they should awaken the indolent, set the lazy and negligent to work for the national cause, warm and encourage the doubters. When the Polish women undertake this work, we shall be able to accomplish miracles.</p>
   <p>To work, then, Polish women! Let the spirits of your brave and patriotic great-grandmothers rejoice, for you will be following in the footsteps of these great Polish women, of whom history writes in letters of gold.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
