<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-01-18">Jan. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">In the Name of Justice</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1001</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1001.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy, Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-01-18">Jan. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE NAME OF JUSTICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The last act of the tragedy which plunged hundreds of miners into eternity at Cherry, Illinois, is being played at the present time in the State capital at Springfield.</p>
   <p>In a few weeks the mines will be reopened. The dead miners will be in their graves. The widows and orphans will scatter to all parts of the country. And the press will be silent. The capitalistic monster will resume its traffic in human lives, disregarding the safety of thousands of men for the sake of greedy profit.</p>
   <p>These conditions will prevail until another catastrophe occurs, which will again remind the public of the gross negligence of the greedy capitalists. At present our representatives at Springfield, who are responsible for the safety and the welfare of the public, are pondering over the fate of the miners' families.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1002.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Their welfare and rehabilitation is most important. There are 442 children, averaging about five years of age, and their mothers must be taken care of.</p>
   <p>The enactment of legislation to prevent the recurrence of similar tragedies is a grave problem. Laws protecting the life and the health of the workingman are necessary and will have to be enacted. Laws protecting the workers in all industries are in force throughout Europe.</p>
   <p>The public conscience will find peace and satisfaction in such legislation because it will end this wanton waste of life by unscrupulous employers.</p>
   <p>There are about 70,000 people employed in hazardous occupations in the State of Illinois, and about 700,000 are similarly employed throughout the United States. These people are compelled to work at these hazardous occupations or to starve. They have no alternative. They are exposed daily to certain death or horrible mutilation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1003.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>So in the name of justice the public should demand reasonable protection and safety for the worker who supports his family with the meager earnings of his hard labor.</p>
   <p>In the name of justice and decency, the worker is entitled to some measure of safety. We should prevent by law the recurrence of such tragedies, severely punishing the violators, who are responsible for the lives and the safety of the people whom they employ.</p>
   <p>A commission of three miners, three owners, and three persons representing the public was appointed to investigate the mines in the State of Illinois.</p>
   <p>They thoroughly investigated all mine shafts, fire-fighting apparatus, and alarm systems, and the result of this investigation is embodied in a bill which is now before the senate.</p>
   <p>Not only the mining industry should be subject to regular inspections; a <pb facs="5423968_4_1004.jpg" n="4"/>complete study and survey of safety measures should be made. These safety measures should be enforced. The miner must familiarize himself with all safety rules, and he must know how to fight fires caused by the presence of poisonous and explosive gases, which cause most of the mine disasters.</p>
   <p>The European mines are equipped with gas-detecting devices which sound an alarm in all parts of the mine, warning the men to run for the exits. After all the miners have been taken to the surface, a crew of men with special equipment, protected against deadly fumes, descends into the mine and forces out all the deadly gases.</p>
   <p>Many of the safety devices used in European mines could not be used in our American mines for obvious reasons, and that is why we experience so many disasters.</p>
   <p>We must admit that not all accidents are avoidable, but emergency measures and apparatus with which to combat fire, smoke, and gas should be on hand in order <pb facs="5423968_4_1005.jpg" n="5"/>to reduce the casualties to a minimum.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that the bills now before the legislature will be passed. And in the name of justice and of the thousands of widows and orphans we hope that these laws will be enforced.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
