<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-02-06">Feb. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">One of Ours</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1536</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1536.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-02-06">Feb. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ONE OF OURS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Francis Pawlowski was born on January 6, 1872, in Poland, in the province of Pomerania and in the village of Koniojady. When he was only seven years old, he had to work after school to help his widowed mother. Unwilling to submit to Prussian oppression, he emigrated to America when he was only fifteen. He came directly to Chicago where he worked for several years in various factories and shops. In the evenings he attended night school, since he had decided to learn the English language and secure a better place for himself in society.</p>
   <p>A lover of music, he practiced this art in his spare time, and when a vacancy occurred in the post of organist in St. Stanislas Bishop and Martyr's Church, the pastor of the church, the Reverend John Obyrtacz, offered him the place, which he held for twelve years. When his salary in this position became insufficient to support his rather larger family, he opened, as a sideline, a <pb facs="5423968_4_1537.jpg" n="2"/>real-estate office which proved to be so profitable a business venture that Mr. Pawlowski was forced to resign as organist; he was succeeded by his oldest son, Francis.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile the Cragin district was growing rapidly, and the need for a Polish bank became more pressing. Our People had to do their banking business with bankers of other nationalities or were compelled to go downtown for this purpose. So Mr. Pawlowski formed a partnership with Attorney Zygmunt and opened in 1917 a mortgage bank, Pawlowski and Zygmunt. This financial institution does banking business in all branches. It enjoys the enthusiastic support and patronage not only of Poles but also of people of other nationalities. At present the bank is building ten three-story apartment buildings on Leamington Street, in the most beautiful location in the whole parish.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pawlowski has always been very active in patriotic and civic affairs. His services were especially valuable during the campaign to raise a $10,000,000 fund, to which his parish contributed $22,000. As a delegate of the local <pb facs="5423968_4_1538.jpg" n="3"/>citizens' committee he has attended every convention held by the Polish people in America.</p>
   <p>In 1893 Mr. Pawlowski married Miss Catherine Michalska. The marriage ceremony was performed in St. Adalbert's church. In the same year he moved to the Cragin district, where he has lived ever since.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pawlowski has reared quite a large family, always retaining his race-consciousness as a Pole and remembering his obligations toward the land of his forefathers. His oldest son, Francis, until recently the organist of the parish church, is at present working in his father's bank. The second son, Dr. Bernard Pawlowski, is a dentist, and the third son, Stanislas, is a student at the University of Illinois. Three daughters, Anne, Valerie, and Elizabeth, are home girls, and Rosalie goes to the parish school. The youngest son, Joseph, is a student at St. Stanislas Kostka College.</p>
   <p>Since he was homesick for his native land, Mr. Pawlowski visited Pomerania <pb facs="5423968_4_1539.jpg" n="4"/>in 1920, extending his visit to other parts of Poland.</p>
   <p>For the last twenty-five years he has been a member of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. He is also a member of the Citizens' Club in the parish</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
