<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-18">Jan. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">One of Ours</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1395</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1395.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-18">Jan. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ONE OF OURS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Ladislas A. Kuflewski was born in Posen province, Poland, in 1870. There he received his elementary and secondary schooling. In 1886 young Kuflewski arrived in Chicago. Here he enrolled for medical studies in the University of Illinois, and in 1894 he received his final diploma as a physician and surgeon. He began his professional career in the Polish hospital, St. Mary's of Nazareth, where in the course of time he earned a reputation and became a famous surgeon. At present he is a senior surgeon on the staff of the Polish hospital and is one of its best and most devoted friends and workers.</p>
   <p>Dr. Kuflewski is very active in social and patriotic affairs. He is a founder, a life member, and at this moment the president of the Polish Physicians' Association, a member of the Chicago Medical Society, the Illinois Medical Society, the Illinois Surgical Society, the Chicago Surgical Academy, and the American Medical Association, and an associate member of the American College of Surgeons. Dr. Kuflewski is also an active member of the Chicago Athletic Club and of the <pb facs="5423968_4_1396.jpg" n="2"/>Polish National Alliance, of which he has been a chief medical examiner. He has also been a professor of surgery in the Chicago Medical College, vice-president of the Chicago Board of Education, President of the Chicago Public Library Board, and president of the Polish National Library Board. The Poles in American elected him chief marshal for the unveiling ceremonies of the monuments of the American Revolutionary war leaders, General Kosciusko and General Pulaski, in Washington, D. C., in 1910. In the same year he was sent by the Chicago Poles as a delegate to the Polish Congress held in Washington, D. C., during which he was chairman of the finance committee. At the present time he is again the chief medical examiner for the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>In 1906 Dr. Kuflewski married Miss Rose Cwiklinska of Buffalo. They have one daughter, Alice, now two years old. They live on the Northwest Side of the city, but in the near future they will remove to their new residence at 1725 South Ashland Avenue.</p>
   <p>Widely known as a great physician, a good Pole, and a man of noble virtues, Dr. Kuflewski is one of the shining lights of our Polonia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
