<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-04-26">Apr. 26, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">The Doctor and the Patient</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-04-26">Apr. 26, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">THE DOCTOR AND THE PATIENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A question has been raised as to how a doctor should conduct himself among the sick and their relatives in the event the patients are threatened with a permanent disfigurement or death. Should he tell them of the imminent danger or not?</p>
   <p>This is how one doctor considers this question:</p>
   <p>"The position of a physician who has several patients under his care who are dangerously ill or incurable is very difficult and unpleasant. If the doctor tells the patient and his family the true circumstances of the case he may complicate matters for the ailing person and disturb the entire family, In the event the physician does not tell of the inevitable result, he may <pb facs="5423968_4_1369.jpg" n="2"/>lose the confidence that people have in him as a capable doctor. Not only is his good name as a doctor threatened but the opinion may be voiced that he exploits his patients.</p>
   <p>"I judge, however, that a doctor who has great feeling and understanding of his calling can easily extricate himself from such difficulties. In this respect he will not treat his patients mechanically nor handle them as if they have no feelings once he has made his diagnosis, but will become their friend and to their families he will express sincere sympathy. Through psychological observances the doctor can see the good points as well as the shortcomings of his patients' characters. After these observations are made the doctor can them tell his patients of their condition, tempering his statement according to his idea of their mental status.</p>
   <p>"When the question arises about telling a patient that he will either be permanently incapacitated or that his disease is incurable, it is best not to tell the true circumstances. Why sadden the patient, since there is not <pb facs="5423968_4_1370.jpg" n="3"/>much more hope left for him in this world? In the event that the patient's days are numbered the doctor should approach the sick person delicately and tell him that he is about to face a crisis and that it would be advisable to get religious solace. Once the patient is joined with God he at least can have moral ease." This can do no harm to a life that has its days numbered, according to the doctor's observations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
