<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 40,
<date when="1916-10-04">Oct. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Women in Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1225</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1225.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 40,
<date when="1916-10-04">Oct. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH WOMEN IN POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The result from general calculations is that in the entire Cook County there are not more than 15,000 Polish women who vote, and over 25,000 have the right to vote. Polish women from principle do not care to mix in politics, because they consider this matter as belonging to men. This is a wrong argumentation and through this we suffer very much in politics and more than once some Polish candidate loses because of the lack of women's votes.</p>
   <p>The American women understand this matter, altogether differently, because they interest themselves very often much more in political life, than men and in many instances decide in the election of a given candidate. Such an instance occurred during the last primaries in the 25th ward, where over 10,000 women took part in the voting. This is an extraordinary considerable figure, when 10,000 votes decides the difference between victory and defeat of a given candidate in Cook County. That 10,000 women's votes fell in considerable majority on candidates running for the office of sanitary trustees and just on <pb facs="5423968_4_1226.jpg" n="2"/>account of that our candidate for sanitary trustee, Mr. Joseph Ruszkiewicz, is third on the Democratic ballot relative to the number of votes received, and he should have been second if the Polish women had taken part in the primaries. As you yourself surmise, women of other nationalities do not look with kindly eyes upon the Polish candidates and give their votes to their own candidates.</p>
   <p>In the coming November election we must combine our strength, if we should elect our Polish candidates. Every Polish vote will be needed for victory and before all we must strive that as many Polish women as possible should cast their vote, so that even partly we could equalize the votes of women of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Remember that Saturday October 7 will be a registration day. Let then the husbands invite their wives, the mothers their daughters, the relatives their friends to register on October 7.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1227.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This will not take up much of your time, and you will contribute greatly toward the Polish cause, because you will help with your votes to elect Mr. Joseph Ruszkiewicz sanitary trustee, Mr. Is. T. Dankowski municipal judge and other Polish candidates. Let on the 7th day of October be repeated again the watchword: "Let us all register!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
