<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-12">Jan. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Do Your Duty Buy Thrift Stamps and Help Defeat the Kaiser</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0440</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0440.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-12">Jan. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">DO YOUR DUTY BUY THRIFT STAMPS AND HELP DEFEAT THE KAISER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Above, we present a facsimile of a "Thrift Card". It is a mark of patriotism to possess such a card.</p>
   <p>Whenever you buy a "Thrift Stamp", you are contributing to the purchase of one more bullet, which may perhaps save the life of one more American, and bring death to one more enemy of civilization. The stamp that you buy may help to purchase one more pair of shoes, or a blanket for one of our warriors. Whenever you buy a "Thrift Stamp," remember that you are helping to bring about the defeat of the Kaiser and his enormous army.</p>
   <p>If, from time to time, you do without some necessity, or some article that you want and are accustomed to having, and in its stead, you buy a few "Thrift Stamps", attaching them to a card as pictured above, you prove yourself a patriot. When your "Thrift Card" has been filled with stamps, you can take <pb facs="5423968_4_0441.jpg" n="2"/>it to the nearest post office and there receive in exchange a government certificate[War Savings Certificate Stamp].</p>
   <p>The card pictured above has space for twenty "Thrift Stamps". Every stamp affixed to the card is a Liberty Bond in miniature. A card of this kind can be exchanged for cash on January 1, 1923. The government will pay annual interest of four per cent, [computed] every three months, on money saved in this way. If, however, you should need the money before then, you can withdraw it at any time and the government will pay three per-cent[annual]interest on it from the time of deposit to its withdrawal.</p>
   <p>However, there will not be many who will want to cash in their cards before the expiration date. Rather will everyone want to buy as many "Thrift Stamps" as possible.</p>
   <p>When a card with "War Savings Stamps" has been filled, it will be worth <pb facs="5423968_4_0442.jpg" n="3"/>one hundred dollars (twenty stamps at five dollars each), redeemable on January 1, 1923.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
