<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-22">Sept. 22, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[The Problem of Child Labor]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0982</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0982.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-22">Sept. 22, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[THE PROBLEM OF CHILD LABOR]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The statistics presented by certain ladies' organizations in this country are sad. They have reported that over two million children under sixteen years of age are gainfully employed throughout the United States. These young people, who should still be in school, often support their unemployed father and younger members of the family. While thousands of healthy, strong men are desperately in search of work--their young and weak children perform hazardous and difficult work in factories, work which is often beyond their physical endurance. There, where an older person should work, the unscrupulous employers place a small boy to whom they pay niggardly wages. Quite frequently, these manufacturers employ young girls who have not yet fully completed grammar school. Two million minors do physical labor for their bread. This is a hideous exploitation which incurs <pb facs="5423968_4_0983.jpg" n="2"/>the wrath and scorn of the civilized world directed against the nation which allows such conditions to exist. The manufacturers and the merchants here built empires of wealth, and live in luxury while frail and wan human beings perish at their mills--children suffer for no fault of their own. Law.... is blind here. Even in such states where there is legislation directed against employing minors in factories and stores--most children work there "under the watchful eyes" of factory inspectors. These officials are mindful of everything, but neglect the enforcement of rules and regulations.</p>
   <p>After the horrible coal mine accident at Cherry, Illinois, where three hundred miners met violent death, it was shown that eleven boys, who were less than fourteen years of age, were also killed. The law states that it is illegal for anyone to employ boys under sixteen years of age in mines. But, unfortunately, our legislators enact laws which the exploiting class of our society fails to observe. The parents who send their immature children to work, falsifying their age to factory and mine officials, are also to blame. But why do we have inspectors, <pb facs="5423968_4_0984.jpg" n="3"/>supported by public taxes, when they either do not care or do not know how to make certain whether the children employed in the various factories and mines really are of the legally prescribed age. Certainly the public does not maintain inspectors just for superficial purposes, but in order that they shall tend to the duties given them.</p>
   <p>Equally exploited here are the women workers who do a man's work and receive half his pay. Various women's organizations are demanding a change of these shameful conditions. Labor unions make vigorous protest against such exploitation. Despite all this, nothing seems to avail because the law here seems to exist to benefit the capitalists and the miserable profiteers--not the working people. How long will the public allow such unlawfulness and such exploitation of the dispossessed class....?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
