<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-07-15">July 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Newspaper Correspondent from Chicago Granted an Interview with Russian Prime Minister</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0701</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0701.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-07-15">July 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH NEWSPAPER CORRESPONDENT FROM CHICAGO GRANTED AN INTERVIEW WITH RUSSIAN PRIME MINISTER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I had the honor to be granted an interview with His Excellency, Mr. Goremykin, Prime Minister of Russia, the man who, next to the Emperor, is the greatest in the Empire in power and influence. It was not an interview, he said, but a visit during which the Premier expressed his ideas.</p>
   <p>He did not receive me as a newspaper correspondent seeking an interview, but he did consent to his utterances being published in the Chicago Herald. You will note that on each page of this letter the word "correct" occurs with the signature of S. Yourief, the Premier's secretary, without which <pb facs="5423968_4_0702.jpg" n="2"/>it would be impossible for the document to leave Russia and which proves its authenticity.</p>
   <p>The interviews or audiences with the other ministers which I have had are similarly authenticated. I considered those utterances and the sources from which they came of such great importance that I did not want to leave the least doubt about their authenticity.</p>
   <p>I was received by the Premier in his summer residence at the appointed time, which was three o'clock Saturday afternoon.</p>
   <p>The residence, which is a frame building and situated next to that of the Empress Dowager, is severely plain, and it typifies the unassuming simplicity and modesty of the great man who occupies it.</p>
   <p>The Premier, I am told, is seventy-five years of age, but looks vigorous <pb facs="5423968_4_0703.jpg" n="3"/>and healthy. He is rather small of stature for a Russian. Russians, as a rule, are quite tall, but the Premier has a fine, big head and penetrating eyes. He received me very kindly and by his simple, unaffected manner made me feel at home.</p>
   <p>I was most agreeably surprised and delighted when I heard that the Premier spoke English. While it is true that all educated Russians now speak English as well as French almost as fluently as their own language, yet during the generation to which the Premier belongs the English language was not given the same recognition as that of the French. Our conversation was, therefore, carried on in English.</p>
   <p>By way of introduction, I told the Premier briefly the purpose of my coming to Petrograd. I told him that I was an American citizen of Polish nationality; that the people of America are deeply interested in the fate of <pb facs="5423968_4_0704.jpg" n="4"/>Poland, and are sympathizing with the Poles because of their frightful suffering in this terrible war, and are contributing money to alleviate their suffering. I also told him that they read with great interest, the proclamation issued by the Commander in Chief of the Russian Army, Grand Duke Nicholas, promising freedom to Poland, and that they would like to see that promise realized.</p>
   <p>I then asked the Premier whether the proclamation of the Commander in Chief was made with the knowledge and sanction of the Emperor and his ministers. He replied:</p>
   <p>"The proclamation was made by the Grand Duke with the knowledge and sanction of the Emperor and of the ministry".</p>
   <p>Next, I asked the following question:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0705.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"What has been done to put that promise into effect, and make it a reality?"</p>
   <p>In answer the Premier told me that a commission has been appointed, composed of six Poles and of six Russians, which commission is at the present time engaged in preparing a plan to put the promise contained in the Grand Duke's proclamation into a concrete form, in so far as that will be possible under existing conditions and circumstances.</p>
   <p>I next called the premier's attention to the fact that the German army is at the present time occupying most of Poland. In view of that, I asked him how the promise to make Poland free could be accomplished. I received the following answer:</p>
   <p>"The occupation of Poland by the German army is only temporary; Russia <pb facs="5423968_4_0706.jpg" n="6"/>is determined to carry on this war not only until the Germans are driven out of Poland, but until Germany is completely crushed.</p>
   <p>"This is the sentiment of the Emperor, of the whole government, and of the Russian nation. We are all as one on that point. After that is accomplished, then all the three parts of Poland will be united and made free in accordance with the Grand Duke's proclamation."</p>
   <p>I asked him two other questions, not relating to the Polish situation, which he did not answer, but he did advise me to see the ministers who have charge of these affairs. I was deeply impressed with the frankness of the Premier's answers to my questions. I may add that the Premier began his political career in Poland, having held his first important office, that of a commissioner, in that country. He is, therefore, well acquainted with the Poles and the Polish question.</p>
   <p>(signed)</p>
   <p>N. L. Piotrowski,</p>
   <p>War Correspondent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
