<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-07-16">July 16, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Town of Lake Gives Polish Army Volunteers Send-Off</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-07-16">July 16, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TOWN OF LAKE GIVES POLISH ARMY VOLUNTEERS SEND-OFF</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The City of Chicago bade farewell yesterday to almost two hundred volunteers to the Polish Army, who left for the training camp in Canada so that, after proper training, they might go to France to avenge the wrongs committed by the Germans against not only the Poles but the whole world.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's farewell banquet for volunteers to the Polish Army was held in the oldest parish in Town of Lake, St. Joseph's, the pastor of which is the Reverend Stanislaus Cholewinski. The dinner for the volunteers, recruiting officers, nurses, the citizens' committee, and guests was held, entirely at Father Cholewinski's expense, in the beautifully decorated Sherman Park hall at 59th and Throop Streets.</p>
   <p>Before nine o'clock in the morning, some thirty-six local volunteers had gathered in front of the Town of Lake recruiting office, together with the local citizens' committee, W. Lagocki's band, and hundreds of other people, including friends and <pb facs="5423968_4_0183.jpg" n="2"/>families of the recruits, and awaited the arrival of the recruiting officers and volunteers from Center II. The music of the band, which played throughout the time of waiting, attracted hundreds of additional people, from among whom five more men enlisted in the Polish Army; of these, four left yesterday for the training camp.</p>
   <p>Shortly after ten o'clock, two chartered street cars arrived with the volunteers from Center II and other neighborhoods, with their recruiting sergeants. The local volunteers, under recruiting sergeant S. Deplewski, joined them and, forming ranks, moved down 47th Street to Wood, to 47th Street, and to St. Joseph's Church, located at South Hermitage and 48th Streets.</p>
   <p>Upon arrival at the church and after the volunteers, recruiting sergeants, and the citizens' committee were seated, S. Bolewski, the local organist, played a welcoming march, and the large St. Joseph's Church was filled to capacity with families, friends, and relatives of the volunteers. Solemn high mass was <pb facs="5423968_4_0184.jpg" n="3"/>celebrated by the Reverend Julian Grzesinski, assisted by the Reverend Anthony A. Klowo of Sacred Heart Parish as deacon, and the Reverend Stephen Szczepanski as subdeacon. The local St. Cecelia choir, under the direction of the organist, Bolewski, sang beautifully throughout the ceremony. The ceremony ended with the presentation of the Holy Sacrament and the singing of "Boga Rodzica" ("Mother of God").</p>
   <p>A beautiful and patriotic sermon was delivered by the Reverend F. Kachnowski, assistant of St. Joseph's Parish. This able priest-patriot showed, in his long and inspiring sermon, how we should love our homeland, Poland, which has given us everything; we, in return, as faithful sons of that mother Poland, should hasten now to her aid.</p>
   <p>He ended his sermon by bidding the volunteers farewell and giving them his blessing. The entire congregation then sang the Polish national hymn, "Boze Cos Polske" ("God Save Poland"). Outside the church, ranks were again formed and the parade marched to the Sherman Park Hall at 52nd and Throop Streets, where an <pb facs="5423968_4_0185.jpg" n="4"/>ample dinner awaited.</p>
   <p>Upon arrival at the hall, the volunteers, recruiting sergeants, the clergy, nurses, and the citizens' committee took their places, and the dinner, which had been prepared by the women of the local Helen Paderewski White Cross Society, headed by Mrs. A. Milasiewicz, president, and Mrs. A. Wlodarski, secretary, was served. Throughout the course of the dinner, W. Lagocki's band occupied the platform and entertained the gathering with its music, beginning with the American national anthem, "The Star-Spangled Banner," at which everyone arose.</p>
   <p>At the main table we noticed the Reverends L. Grudzinski, J. Grzesinski, Felix Kachnowski, A. Klowo, and Stephen Szczepanski, and members of the local citizens' committee: B. Kowalewski, W. Wrzesinski, R. Kowalewski, E. Bradel, S. Jankowski, J. Kukulski, J. Kwiatkowski, J. Krolewczyk, K. Czapka, and W. Olszewski, and others from other parts of the city.</p>
   <p>Amongst the other guests, we noticed the secretaries from Recruiting Center II, <pb facs="5423968_4_0186.jpg" n="5"/>Miss Z. Jaworowski, and Miss H. Wolff, J. Przyprawa, S. Rozkosz, Miss A. Wisla, W. Lubicz, vice-president of Circuit II, Polish Falcons' Alliance,and the well-known Northwest Side citizens, Preiss and Wisniewski. The press was represented as follows: Dziennik Chicagoski by W. Gorzynski, Dziennik Narodowy by E. Kolakowski, and Dziennik Zwiazkowy by W. Skwarczynski. Near them sat the Polish Army nurses...., the volunteers, and their recruiting sergeants.</p>
   <p>The first speaker to address the gathering after dinner was B. Kowalewski, well-known banker of Town of Lake and president of the local citizens' committee. He greeted the volunteers in behalf of St. Joseph's Parish and Town of Lake and called up the Reverend Julian Grzesinski to act as toastmaster. He in his turn greeted the volunteers in behalf of the absent pastor of St. Joseph's Church, S. Cholewinski, and the whole parish, wishing them a speedy victory over the base Prussians and a glorious homecoming.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was the well-known priest-patriot, the Reverend L. Grudzinski, diocesan counsel. In his long and beautiful address, the reverend speaker <pb facs="5423968_4_0187.jpg" n="6"/>pointed out how difficult it is to orient oneself and believe what is happening, that it is not a mirage; for, after so many years of slavery, we did not even dream that we would be permitted to organize our own army, under our own flag. Yet it is no mirage, it is a reality today. We already have tens of thousands of volunteer soldiers, a good part of whom are now on the battle front in France, fighting not only for our homeland's freedom, but for the freedom of all the oppressed nations of the world.</p>
   <p>He went on to say that it is his belief that the United States is paying its debt to us, that this country is grateful to us for our heroes, Kosciusko and Pulaski, who, as lovers of freedom, hastened to this country to help it win its independence. The worthy priest-patriot urged enlistment in the Polish Army, which is already fairly large. "You are going to fight," he said, "not as hired or conscripted soldiers, but as free citizens, as Poles to whom pay or rewards or privileges are not of primary importance. On enlistment, you were not promised 'golden mountains', you knew that you were going to fight as good sons of Poland, and I believe that you will restore Poland to liberty, that you will tear off the <pb facs="5423968_4_0188.jpg" n="7"/>chains with which our enemies have kept her bound for more than a century."</p>
   <p>In conclusion, the speaker bade farewell to the volunteers, and begged them to give to our brave boys who are already at the front the assurance that the clergy and the people have not forgotten, nor will ever forget, about them. For so heartfelt an address, the gathering rewarded Father Grudzinski with three cheers.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was W. Lubicz, vice-president of Circuit II, Polish Falcons' Alliance, who greeted the volunteers in behalf of the Falcons, expressing his hope that they will be victorious and plant the standards of the White Eagle on the walls of our old cities, Krakow, Poznan, and Warsaw.</p>
   <p>Following this address, S. Krzywonos, organizer for the Polish Army, spoke with his usual ease. He urged enlistment in the Polish Army, while for those who oppose the organization of this army, he had nothing but words of contempt. Krzywonos then introduced two volunteers who ought to serve as examples to those who have not enlisted as yet. These were S. Bujakiewicz, former editor of <pb facs="5423968_4_0189.jpg" n="8"/>Dziennik Narodowy, an elderly man with gray hair, and a sixteen-year-old youngster, Theodore Freling, of St. Joseph, Missouri. Neither of these volunteers were drawn into the service by any hope of personal gain, but by love of Poland. In conclusion, Krzywonds presented the young man with an army watch, for which the youthful volunteer thanked him.</p>
   <p>The well-known priest-patriot, A. Klowo, then spoke in behalf of Sacred Heart Parish, wishing the volunteers as speedy as possible a victory and a safe return. After this splendid address, volunteer S. Bujakiewicz spoke, thanking the community of Town of Lake in behalf of the volunteers for so splendid a reception. A very nice speech was also made by Miss Frances Koza, in which she bade farewell to the volunteers and gave them best wishes for a quick victory; she spoke in behalf of the Polish Army nurses and the Polish women.</p>
   <p>The last speaker was the toastmaster himself, Father Grzesinski, who bade the volunteers farewell in behalf of Town of Lake and Polonia in general. The gathering then sang "Boze Cos Polske" ("God Save Poland") to the accompaniment <pb facs="5423968_4_0190.jpg" n="9"/>of the orchestra, and the dinner was at an end. When the program was ended, the women of the local citizens' committee passed out parcels of food amongst the recruits, while the men gave cigarettes and cigars.</p>
   <p>After certain necessary formalities were taken care of by the recruiting officers, the volunteers were photographed by the two well-known Rozanski brothers in front of the park pavilion. The photographers have assured us that, despite the rain, the photographs have turned out very well.</p>
   <p>The local citizens' committee then invited the officers, committee, and volunteers into automobiles that waited to take them to Grant Park. The procession of automobiles, decorated with Polish and American flags, was a very beautiful one. It was led by an open car bearing eight standard-bearers with the flags of the allied nations, following which came a motor truck, lent for the purpose by the Perlowski Brothers Furniture Company, carrying W. Lagocki's band, which played beautiful marches throughout the whole trip. Then followed the cars bearing the citizens' committee, the clergy, recruiting officers, representatives <pb facs="5423968_4_0191.jpg" n="10"/>of the press, volunteers, and guests. Altogether, the procession included fifty-nine automobiles and two trucks, one with the musicians and the other, bringing up the rear, with the volunteers' baggage. The second truck was lent without charge by E. Pawelkiewicz, well-known furniture dealer. The procession, stretching for several blocks, moved down Garfield Boulevard to Michigan Boulevard, and thence to Grant Park, where ranks were formed for a parade downtown to the railroad station at Dearborn and Polk Streets.</p>
   <p>Parade Downtown</p>
   <p>At the head of the parade marched the recruiting officers Rozkosz and Przyprawa, followed by the citizens' committee and the allied flags. Then came the band, followed by the Polish Army nurses. The volunteers were led by Recruiting Officer G. Kostecki and sergeants from the various stations. The parade was extremely attractive as it moved down Jackson Boulevard to Dearborn Street and to the Grand Trunk station. Because of the lateness of the hour, the parade was shorter than originally planned, but nevertheless it was enthusiastically <pb facs="5423968_4_0192.jpg" n="11"/>applauded and cheered by the bystanders.</p>
   <p>Immediately after arrival at the station, the volunteers took their places in three special cars, where they said their final farewells to families and friends, while the band played to keep up cheerful spirit. In the meantime, cigarettes, soap, books, and postcards were distributed amongst the volunteers. Finally, as the band played Polish national hymns, the train started, carrying away those faithful sons of Poland who have gone forth to restore Poland to freedom, to strike off the chains that binds her, and to avenge the crimes committed by the Germans, the modern Huns, and to return as heroes, covered with glory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
