<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-07-30">July 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Present War and its Influence Upon Humanity</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Address by Albert Wachowski, President of the Polish League of Building and Loan Associations, delivered at the Universal Convention of Building and Loan Associations Last Week in Newark, New Jersey)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0166</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0166.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-07-30">July 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRESENT WAR AND ITS INFLUENCE UPON HUMANITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Address by Albert Wachowski, President of the Polish League of Building and Loan Associations, delivered at the Universal Convention of Building and Loan Associations Last Week in Newark, New Jersey)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are gathered here today, not so much to examine what we have done or what we have neglected to do in our association during the past year, as to give ourselves completely to a great enterprise which we have begun in opposition to everything that has been said during the past year, at a time when we are at war with the Central Powers of Europe,--supporting and aiding our hardpressed Allies. However, it seems to me that the average citizen does not yet understand how fundamental is the cause for which the world is fighting, and how great a benefit it is that we were able to enter this struggle on the right side, how important and what a turning point in history the result of this war may be, and how fortunate it is that we have a president who was <pb facs="5423968_4_0167.jpg" n="2"/>able to convince the people that the object of the war is progress in human liberty and not, as it seemed to narrow-minded observers, a struggle for conquest and economic gains.</p>
   <p>At first, this war gave the impression of being a great struggle between powerful nations for more land, more subjects, more wealth. It was natural that, judging from previous human experience, small nations standing in the path of this terrific struggle for national supremacy should be swept away, that such will be the result of the struggle between great powers, and despite sympathy for these small nations, it will be said of them, "Well, such is life--such is the fate of the small man and the small nation". And then, despite the shameful procedure of the Central Powers, certain citizens tried to restrain this country from any action, forgetful of our moral obligations to the nations of this world. With one noble move, President Wilson swept aside these doubts concerning the division of the world and its organization; but he made the issue clear that this war is a war to safeguard human liberty for all the peoples of the world, and not for us alone, so that the weak and <pb facs="5423968_4_0168.jpg" n="3"/>the strong alike can decide the course of their own lives as free people. This is a program to which every one of us can subscribe, for which every one of us can work, suffer, even die, for we believe that human liberty is the cornerstone of human progress.</p>
   <p>The best part of it, however, is the fact that President Wilson seeks to make this the program of the Allies, of all the world. Never before in history have so many nations united in the conscious aim of making the world a place where everyone has a right to live, and this we owe to the President of the United States, Woodrow Wilson. Let us stand with him until his goal is achieved. And on the other hand, we must express our hope that this war will not only have its salutary effect upon the Poles, Czechs, Slovaks, and Serbs, but also, to no less a degree, upon subject peoples who are fighting, not on the side of the Central Powers, but on the Allied side, our side.</p>
   <p>Despite the fact that we have been a peace-loving people, we have instituted a recruiting system for our army that is far better than that used by anyone <pb facs="5423968_4_0169.jpg" n="4"/>else. It was instituted without any difficulties, without any trouble whatsoever, and with the complete agreement and enthusiastic support of the entire American nation. It is the most democratic system ever adopted and, with a few changes, it can be regarded as an example of how a free nation recruits and maintains an army. We were in a position to meet all our bills and in addition, to lend great sums to our Allies to help them in their troubles. Above all, however, it must be emphasized that the most important thing is the fact that we have begun to send soldiers to the battle front in France, not by the hundreds but by the thousands and millions.</p>
   <p>Victory for the Allies means freedom for Poland. Poland, like America, has always been the friend of the weak and the oppressed. For centuries it withstood the attacks of barbarians from the east, and richly deserves the title it has been given, "Bulwark of Christianity".</p>
   <p>Even after the partitions we find sons of Poland in France, Italy, America, Hungary, and other countries, fighting wherever the cry for freedom could be <pb facs="5423968_4_0170.jpg" n="5"/>heard. And, like America, Poland has never drawn its sword for purposes of conquest, or to extend its boundaries at the expense of its neighbors.</p>
   <p>Prussia and Russia both enjoyed complete freedom and autonomy under Polish rule. More than once Austria was saved by Poland, always without territorial gain to Poland. Poland was the oldest republican country in Europe, and is now being aided by the oldest existing Republic. Despite the fact that Poland is drenched with blood, overrun by Prussian hordes, its people dying of hunger, it has men not only in the army of that Republic, but it has an army in Russia and in France, consisting mainly of volunteers from America, fighting not only for their own freedom but for the freedom of all oppressed peoples.</p>
   <p>Our victory will be the triumph of justice and progress, for small nations and people, for women and children. There shall be liberty and freedom for all.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
