<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-06-05">June 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Buy Liberty Bonds</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0543</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0543.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-06-05">June 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BUY LIBERTY BONDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, Chicago Polonia experienced an extremely pleasant and solemn moment.</p>
   <p>In a great gathering, we showed that we can--and want to--show our loyalty to this powerful republic, and that we shall hold the name of our great President in everlasting gratitude, for whenever a speaker mentioned the name of the highest executive of the land, a veritable storm of cheers and applause arose.</p>
   <p>However, our duty did not end with listening to the speeches and experiencing the impressions of this great day. Great watchwords were thrown to us from the platform; we were urged to fulfill duties to this, our adopted homeland, and urged to the most honest fulfillment of those duties for, as one of the <pb facs="5423968_4_0544.jpg" n="2"/>speakers justly said, whoever does not fulfill those duties is aiding the worst enemy of the United States.</p>
   <p>Not all of us can seize a rifle in order to fight for the rights of man, and for sacred ideals. As a matter of fact, no one expects this of us. All of us can, however, fulfill a great and important duty, and that is to aid the United States financially toward a final victory over the arrogant Prussian.</p>
   <p>The United States must have two billion dollars in its treasury in order to prepare adequately and to conduct the war effectively. This money is needed now. The people of America have understood this and, as one man, have hastened with the greatest enthusiasm and with unheard-of determination to the aid of the government, purchasing Liberty bonds with their savings.</p>
   <p>Since, however, the sum of two billion dollars (two thousand millions) is a large one to raise, the whole bond issue has not yet been purchased, and <pb facs="5423968_4_0545.jpg" n="3"/>it is necessary that the patriotic citizens of America continue with the purchase of Liberty bonds. Everyone ought to hasten to swell the loan for patriotic, humanitarian, and economic reasons.</p>
   <p>We know that the United States did not go into this war for purposes of territorial gain; it entered the war in order to fight for the rights of all mankind, and for the small nations that are being oppressed today. We know that, in this case, even the greatest efforts of single individuals cannot help, for only by united and well-organized action of the whole nation can this cause be adequately served. Thus, private individuals and whole associations, societies, groups, and clubs ought immediately to take up the matter of purchasing Liberty bonds, and to appropriate from funds lying idle in the bank, so much for the purchase of such bonds.</p>
   <p>Three things are necessary to carry on a war, as Napoleon said--namely, money, money, and more money. Since the government does not have enough money in the banks, it must borrow from its citizens. Surely every one <pb facs="5423968_4_0546.jpg" n="4"/>of us understands that a loan given to the United States Government is the safest in the world. Not one cent can ever be lost by anyone. Money is safer in the hands of the government than in a hundred banks. The government will pay three and one-half percent interest, that is, $3.50 on every hundred dollars, annually.</p>
   <p>For money paid to the government, each person will receive a note, that is, a government bond, which will have the same value as paper money. Bonds may be purchased in State and Federal banks in denominations of fifty dollars and higher. Bonds may be purchased on easy payments, which can be made for any length of time until the bond subscribed for has been paid. Wealthier people can purchase bonds at $100, $500, $1,000, $10,000, and even at hundreds of thousands of dollars.</p>
   <p>Information on this matter will be given free at any bank. The chief concern is good will on our part. Since the guarantees of all money invested in government bonds are of the best, and since, at the same time, one can <pb facs="5423968_4_0547.jpg" n="5"/>have the happy knowledge that adequate weapons are being made (for use against our enemies and the enemies of all mankind) with this money, we can flatter ourselves that here, too, the Poles will be of great help to the government, and that great masses of them will purchase United States Liberty bonds.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
