<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 69,
<date when="1922-03-23">March 23, 1922</date><title level="a">Self-Dependence of Women - Mrs. Edith Rockefeller McCormick</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 69,
<date when="1922-03-23">March 23, 1922</date><title level="a">SELF-DEPENDENCE OF WOMEN - MRS. EDITH ROCKEFELLER McCORMICK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. Edith Rockefeller McCormick spoke the day before yesterday at the Chicago College Club, on the theme of the superiority of women over men. She said that a woman who enters the bonds of marriage with a man not belonging to her sphere becomes a slave. With this claim we can agree with her completely, because often we have many examples among our Polish people.</p>
   <p>For example, Polish women who marry men of other nationalities with different views and customs than ours, are not happy, and very quickly a break in the family occurs which ends with divorce. Mixed marriages are not successful. Another example may be cited - education. If the man is intelligent and educated then he should find a wife who is equally educated and sensible, and vice-versa. When one party in a marriage is wise and the other stupid, there will always be a misunderstanding.</p>
   <p>MOTHER LOVE MEANS NOTHING</p>
   <p>In the further course of her talk Mrs. Rockefeller-McCormick said, that women today have done more than to acquire a place for themselves. "All modern women <pb facs="5423968_4_1162.jpg" n="2"/>want to be self-dependent".</p>
   <p>Mrs. McCormick evidently is disseminating propaganda to destroy the family, because she expresses herself as follows: "Love is an important factor, but is not everything. A woman's general love is a thing considerably greater"...</p>
   <p>It is difficult to agree with Mrs. Rockefeller-McCormick on this point. A great dissolution is taking place today in society, and logically-thinking people are struggling to remedy these conditions. The Catholic clergy are struggling to remedy this. It places as the foundation of all humanity, faith, love of thy neighbor and a happy family circle. Mrs. McCormick, by her declaration, draws a woman away from these fundamental factors for success and encourages them toward unexplained demonstrations and their independent development. No one can deny a woman's efforts and rights toward her independent development, but there must be in this instance a clearer explanation of how this self-dependent woman should develop.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1163.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>THE WOMAN PUSHED ON A PATHLESS TRACK</p>
   <p>If, according to the opinion of a wealthy woman, self-defense means the ignoring of the family hearth, the neglect of the teachings of Christ, then our Polish women will not "register for this new study". In the spheres of wealthy people in America, the women are so self-dependent, that the papers are filled with their scandalous news. If the disciple of this unexplained self-dependence, who places maternal love on a secondary plane, found among the listeners some slight-thinking women, then before long the chronicles will record the scandalous deed of some American dame from the financial world. If they can implant in the minds of some women such comprehensions of wealthy women who lead idle lives, then they will "self-dependently face into a precipice".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
