<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-14">July 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">New Polish Physician</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-14">July 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">NEW POLISH PHYSICIAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The science of healing human ills has a magnetic attraction that does not confine itself to drawing men into its ranks, for occasionally it attracts women. Such a woman is Dr. Helen Gorecki, born in Chicago, daughter of Mr. and Mrs. W. Gorecki.</p>
   <p>Dr. Helen Gorecki received her first education at the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parochial School. Later, when her family moved to Arlington Heights, she attended public school there. She also attended the public high school in Arlington Heights, after her graduation from which she began to consider her future career. Her thoughts naturally turned in the direction of art, and with this idea in mind she entered Loyola University, receiving her diploma upon completion of the course of study. But here her natural woman's curiosity and her desire to aid suffering humanity turned her attention to medicine, and she entered the Medical School at Loyola, where she earned the respect of every one by her untiring work and completed her studies with honors. She <pb facs="5423968_4_1418.jpg" n="2"/>received her degree of Doctor of Medicine on June 19, receiving on the same day the certificate giving her the right to practice in the State of Illinois from the State Examination Board.</p>
   <p>During the first years of her studies at the University, Dr. Gorecki earned the confidence of her class, which in recognition of her unusual abilities elected her class treasurer. On June 18, Dr. Gorecki had an opportunity to display her abilities as a speaker at the alumni banquet held at the Hotel La Salle in honor of the graduates. It must be admitted that her eloquence aroused the admiration of all present.</p>
   <p>The young doctor's aim is to acquire the greatest possible knowledge in the field of medicine. She plans to spend the next few years gaining practical knowledge to support the theoretical knowledge which she has already gained. In order to achieve her aims, she has entered the Michael Meagher Memorial Hospital in Arkansas and will later serve at the Mary Thompson Hospital. After completing her hospital work Dr. Gorecki plans to become an assistant <pb facs="5423968_4_1419.jpg" n="3"/>to a well-known surgeon.</p>
   <p>During the entire period of her apprenticeship Dr. Gorecki's aim will be to secure more and more knowledge, so that later, when she begins her independent practice, she will be adequately trained to relieve human suffering.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
