<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-02-16">Feb. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Poland's Gethsemane</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0689</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0689.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-02-16">Feb. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">POLAND'S GETHSEMANE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is Poland's midnight in the Garden of Gethsemane. The agony of the dark hour cannot be uttered. Never before in hundreds of years has a whole people been sacrificed so ruthlessly.</p>
   <p>Behind curtains of iron the frightful tragedy is being enacted. We are fortunate, perhaps, that we cannot see the tortures in their nude horror, the tortures to which twenty million people are subjected. The wail of innocent babes, sick, starving, and dying, would be intolerable. The outcry of the myriads of mothers, helpless before their dying children, would be heart-rending. The lamentations of millions of men and women struck down in the glory of maturity, some by hunger, others by the swift violence of war, would be overwhelming.</p>
   <p>Poland, caught between titanic hostile forces, is paying the extreme penalty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0690.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Her sons are divided. By a cynical decree of destiny Poles must fight against their blood-brothers in a war not of their choosing. And while brothers are so arrayed against each other an economic struggle impalpable as the breath of an infernal god lays waste the land of their birth. This, in truth, is Poland's midnight hour in the Garden of Gethsemane. A day of promise will shine in Poland if the awfulness of the present can be survived. The wrongs committed a century and a half ago have played their part in causing this madness of self-destruction now devastating Europe. Germany and Russia and Austria are draining to the dregs the cup of bitterness which was foreordained when Poland was dismembered.</p>
   <p>The tragedy is that not only are the international sins of the fathers visited upon the children unto the third and fourth generation. More terrible is the visitation upon the children of them who were violated. For so inextricably are we bound together as members of the same human race that evil avenges itself upon the just and the unjust, upon the slayers and the slain.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0691.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Poland will rise again because men are recognizing the inexorable consequences of their acts. So far as Europe is able, the ancient kingdom will be restored. The very existence of all races demands it. Poland resurgent in a peaceful Europe! God speed the day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
