<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-09">Jan. 9, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A New Polish Financial Institution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1503</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1503.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-09">Jan. 9, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW POLISH FINANCIAL INSTITUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Half-tone, one column-eighth of a page, profile of Attorney Max A. Drezmal, president.]</p>
   <p>[Half-tone, one column-eighth of a page, profile of August Klimek, vice-president.]</p>
   <p>[Half-tone, one column-eighth of a page, profile of Dr. Leon P. Kozakiewicz, vice-president.]</p>
   <p>[Half-tone, one column-eighth of a page, profile of E. J. Odalski, secretary and cashier.]</p>
   <p>Of recent days, on the northwest side of Chicago, a new Polish financial institution has been established. The founders are persons who daily come across problems that require immediate assistance, but these honest people have no other form of security than their good character.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1504.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This new financial institution is called the "Chicago Industrial Finance Corporation." The offices of this company will be found in the Milwaukee Avenue neighborhood, Division and Ashland Avenue. As soon as the offices are opened then the Polish people will be able to make loans and pay them back in installments to suit their purse.</p>
   <p>The officers of this organization are as follows: Max A. Drezmal, president; Dr. L. P. Kozakiewicz, first vice-president; August Klimek, second vice-president; E. J. Odalski, secretary and cashier.</p>
   <p>The directors are: Attorney M. A. Drezmal, Dr. F. A. Dulak, Dr. W. E. Gogolinski, August Klimek, August J. Kowalski, Dr. L. P. Kozakiewicz, Joseph Makarski, Ed. J. Odalski, and A. S. Wengierski.</p>
   <p>From the above, it is self-evident that this new company is made up of well-known Polish individuals, who are prominent in the business world. Their names are a guarantee of success.</p>
   <p>The capital of this financial institution has been based on the laws of <pb facs="5423968_4_1505.jpg" n="3"/>the State of Illinois, and amounts to $200,000. This sum will be deposited in the Northwestern Bank. This bank has also been asked to act as trustee.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Industrial Finance Corporation is the twelfth of its kind in Chicago and vicinity. It is organized under the system known as the Security System, Inc. A. C. Schauer, vice-president of the Security System, Inc., took an active interest in getting this twelfth organization in order.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
