<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-12">Jan. 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Meeting of the Stockholders of the Alliance National Bank Brings about Changes in the Administration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-12">Jan. 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF THE STOCKHOLDERS OF THE ALLIANCE NATIONAL BANK BRINGS ABOUT CHANGES IN THE ADMINISTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At an annual meeting of stockholders of the Alliance National Bank, most of whom were from Holy Innocents', St. Stephen's, St. Helen's and St. John Cantius' parishes, held at the bank headquarters yesterday afternoon, changes were decided upon in the administration. Besides this, plans and problems for the good of the organization were discussed.</p>
   <p>After the presentation of the directors who were on the board during 1927, reports were introduced. In the absence of Clayton F. Smith, chairman of the board of directors, who is in Washington on an important mission, Leon S. Mallek, president of the bank, gave a comprehensive report on the bank's business, administrators, and personnel. A table or index was given to every stockholder present, which showed the qualification of the directors.</p>
   <p>The results of yesterday's elections showed that the following were chosen as directors:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1499.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Leon S. Mallek, attorney; Peter Rostenkowski, former president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union and present cashier of the bank, who always takes an active part in Polish affairs; Clayton F. Smith, a financier who is well known to all the important banking institutions; John A. Biggio, realtor and owner of a subdivision in "Uptown"; Gustave D. Moldenhauer, physician; Francis J. Burns, proprietor of a wholesale lumber company; Edward Oplatka, co-owner of the Leader Stores; Mrs. Sophia Ruszkiewicz, wife of the late Joseph Ruszkiewicz, who organized the bank; and Nicholas A. Cummings, manager of the ice firm Reter Rusetos.</p>
   <p>The following were chosen officers of the bank: Leon S. Mallek, president; Clayton F. Smith, vice-president; Francis J. Burns, vice-president; Robert F. Crowley, cashier; Anthony M. Adams and Valentine P. Kaszuba, assistant cashiers.</p>
   <p>In the course of this annual report, Mr. Mallek pointed out that the assets of the bank have passed the five-million-dollar mark; the capital, accrued <pb facs="5423968_4_1500.jpg" n="3"/>interest, and undivided income totaled $424,247.36, and the stockholders received a twelve per cent dividend in 1927.</p>
   <p>"Credit for the growth of this institution," said Mr. Mallek, "must be given to the undivided co-operation of our clients, who are well aware of the financial strength of the Alliance National Bank and therefore consider it a sound place to deposit their savings."</p>
   <p>The Alliance National Bank is on a par with the largest banking institutions of America. It is a member of the Federal Reserve Board and of Chicago's strongest financial institution, the Chicago Clearing House.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
