<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-14">Dec. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Washington Pact</title><title level="a" type="sub">Peace for Ten Years Assured (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1079</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1079.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-14">Dec. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE WASHINGTON PACT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Peace for Ten Years Assured (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Washington Conference can adjourn for the Christmas holidays, and the members can go home with a peaceful mind. Although everything was not accomplished, for there was not sufficient time, what has been completed however, is worthy of mention. Peace negotiations between the four great powers. England, France, the United States, and Japan have been completed. Peace has been assured for at least ten years.</p>
   <p>This pact, which paves the way for a "modus vivendi" among the mentioned powers, has been attacked by the same professional bugbears, who have been active before the recent World War. Although this assurance of peace for a decade is not a very long one, there remains the important fact that <pb facs="5423968_4_1080.jpg" n="2"/>this move will make the United States an historical pioneer in the initiation of peace treaties between world powers. It brings about an understanding between a power on the far western side of the Pacific and the dominant powers in European affairs. This move will introduce a mutual relationship in politics and [promote] the interests of these nations.</p>
   <p>This treaty may be recorded in history; the document consists of only four articles. To say the least, it is short, explicit, and to the point. A reservation has been included, stipulating that in the event of misunderstanding in regards to vital issues during the course of ten years and in the event these issues cannot be remedied through regular diplomatic channels, each power has the right to call a conference of the representatives of the four countries who will negotiate peace terms; in the event the interests of the smaller powers are threatened by an agressor nation, or one of the four powers, the representatives can convene and decide what action to follow. Since the understanding is agreed to last <pb facs="5423968_4_1081.jpg" n="3"/>ten years, any nation can withdraw only after giving a twelve-month notice.</p>
   <p>Indeed,the contents of this pact are an important step towards world peace.</p>
   <p>The importance of this arrangement becomes more significant when we consider the many political circumstances in which they can participate. We must take into consideration that before this accord was reached, before the greatly interested nations came to this understanding, many barriers had to be overcome and many problems that confronted the world had to be rectified.</p>
   <p>The more significant questions will be pointed out:</p>
   <p>The problem of the Far East, or the aggressive attitude of the Japanese in regards to the affairs of China, which is gradually placing the latter <pb facs="5423968_4_1082.jpg" n="4"/>under the control of Japan; the questions of Kiau Chau, Manchuria and the concessions of Japan along the shores and waters of the Chinese coast line, especially along eastern China; the Siberian question; and the question of the Pacific Isles, coal stations, cable lines, and so forth.</p>
   <p>A number of important complications had to be disentangled.</p>
   <p>The former Anglo-Japanese alliance, for instance, as well as the alliance between the United States and Japan.</p>
   <p>This conglomeration of problems had to be settled before the present peace pact could be agreed upon by the four great powers. But this was not all. Some steps towards effecting a conciliation relative to the problems of Japanese-American colonization, immigration, and so forth had to be worked out; and an agreement had to be reached in regards to naval parity. All this had to be thoroughly discussed, concessions had <pb facs="5423968_4_1083.jpg" n="5"/>to be granted and, above all, a document had to be formulated in such a fashion that it would not be invalidated soon after its completion. What was wanted, was a treaty that would be a forerunner of others. Because of this principle factor, the twelve month notice period for withdrawing from this treaty was inserted.</p>
   <p>The importance of this move can be easily seen and understood. This one year notice gives ample time for reflection and reconsideration and enough time to seek other roads, but above all, enough time to abide by the original agreement. In this respect, the pact can continue for the full duration of the ten-year period and perhaps indefinitely.</p>
   <p>The following important questions which are of immediate concern to the four powers have been agreed upon:</p>
   <p>China, presenting one of the most critical problems in the East, especially in regards to the relations between Japan and the United States, will <pb facs="5423968_4_1084.jpg" n="6"/>receive a guarantee of its integrity according to the treaty. Thus, by removing the United States a considerable distance from the spectre of war, which has been lurking in the offing, this war scare has been dealt another blow by the Anglo-Japanese Alliance. Prior to this agreement both powers were cautious of such conciliations. As a result of this, the United States has arrived at a road of mutual understanding with Japan relative to the question of the Pacific.</p>
   <p>By participating in this conference, Japan has again gained a new evaluation and recognition of her strength and prestige, which she highly cherishes. Thus, Japan rids herself of the fear of war and its colossal cost of preparedness. Besides all this, she attains her desires for expansion in Asia, and in sections where no harm will be done to anyone. Is it in Siberia perhaps?</p>
   <p>France, in this respect, has gained the continuation of the coalition effected during the World War. She has also gained other protective <pb facs="5423968_4_1085.jpg" n="7"/>measures which place her in a position of high rank in European affairs. Her military power has been strengthened by her ties with England. In the event France is attacked by Germany, England will be at her side.</p>
   <p>For many centuries England has been able to gain the greatest advantages in negotiating international, political and diplomatic affairs. Again she has managed to do herself a great good. She will still reign as "Queen of the Seas." Closer relationship with the United States has been assured, for she looks upon the United States to make friends with Japan. A guarantee of peace in the Pacific and along the southern part of Asia, which is not far from India, has been reached. This is a place where England may need a free hand in the near future.</p>
   <p>What more does one want? Satisfaction has been rendered all. Besides this, there is the ten-year period of peace to look forward to. In the event of a misunderstanding, arrangements have been made to reach an accord by negotiation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1086.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>This is indeed an optimistic outlook and, above all, the pact has been completed. The press today is enthusiastically publicizing this event throughout the world, and is emphasizing the many advantages it offers. It asserts that a desirable precedent has been set by the fulfillment of the Washington pact. The fears of war have been melted by it and rumors of an impending struggle between Japan and the United States have been dispelled. Within a short time the benefits of this arrangement will be felt by all.</p>
   <p>The Washington pact is also important in respect to another phase of international affairs, for it is an excellent conclusion of negotiations with America and Asia. This can be compared with the League of Nations which is instrumental in [managing] European affairs. Although the United States does not belong to the League, the powers that have joined the Washington pact do. In this respect, it is believed that these nations may influence America in being favorably inclined towards the League of Nations. But it is apparent that the United States have no desire for <pb facs="5423968_4_1087.jpg" n="9"/>this--let her insist on this. Nevertheless, the Washington pact will handle the affairs of Asia and America just as the League handles the peace status in Europe.</p>
   <p>As a result, both ends of the world will be united by alliances. The sole purpose of these treaties will be the maintenance of peace and the prevention of unnecessary bloodshed. It is sincerely believed that such international bartering for peace will bring about a release of war tension. One must admit that nothing drastically wrong will occur which may precipitate another world war.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
