<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-13">Aug. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to All the Divisions and Branches of the Alliance of Polish Military Societies in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0835</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0835.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-13">Aug. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO ALL THE DIVISIONS AND BRANCHES OF THE ALLIANCE OF POLISH MILITARY SOCIETIES IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Colleagues: A terrible moment has come upon all of Europe. Our entire unfortunate country is covered with the blood of the soldiers of our oppressors, and perhaps already thousands of our brothers have fallen--not only those who were called to the colors of our oppressors, but also innocent and defenseless children, old people and women.</p>
   <p>How much blood and destruction from the hail of enemy bullets has already fallen upon the soil of our poor and unfortunate homeland! Our entire country has now become the prey of our bloodthirsty oppressors, who burn and destroy the entire property of our fathers, brothers, kinsmen, and friends. How many widows and orphans are there already suffering poverty and hunger, perhaps without a roof over their heads, sent about from place to place, seeking shelter before the oncoming enemy in order to save their lives!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0836.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/><pb facs="5423968_4_0837.jpg" n="3"/>the most <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> sincere interest in the national cause, but have concerned themselves only with international or party <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Let them learn that the general cause, the Polish cause, is a sacred one, for they, too, are the children of one mother--Poland.</p>
   <p>We have proved many times before that the Alliance of Polish Military Societies does not belong to any party, but is concerned only with military and purely patriotic matters relating to Poland, as well as to the country in which we live. For that reason, colleagues, it is our sacred duty, as soldiers, to be the first to answer the call, in order to demonstrate that we are not only good for parades and display but that we are capable of serving the sacred cause.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we are sure that we shall not find within our ranks a single man who would draw aside from a cause of such grave importance as the cause of the homeland. We need an army and we need money.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0838.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0839.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0840.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0841.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
