<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-03-29">Mar. 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1026</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1026.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-03-29">Mar. 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two weeks ago, mention was <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> made in the Illinosis Legislature, at Springfield, to distribute <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> free of charge in the public schools. The disadvantages of this proposal were stated, and we urged a stern protest against this project, not only for the protection of our taxpayers, but also of our parochial schools.</p>
   <p>Arrangements were made with the officers of the Polish societies of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, and a mass meeting was hold last night at the Polish Hall, Bradley and Noble Streets. A capacity crowd attended to express their right of protest against a move that would jeopordize the parochial schools, including the Polish Roman Catholic schools.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Vincent Marzynski, paster of St. Stanislaus Mostka Church, presided as chairman and called upon Frank Puhl to act as recording secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1027.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Besides the chairman's address, Peter Kiolbassh and Attorney L. N. Piotrowski made explanations and interpretations of the proposal, which was introduced to the Legislature through the influence of the American Protective Association and others.</p>
   <p>The following resolution was unanimously approved by the entire assemblage:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, a bill has been introduce in the Illinois Legislature which would permit the free distribution of school books in the public schools, we are compelled to voice a unified and emphatic protest in this matter. We have no intention of opposing the present system of public schools; however, we protest against the further increase of taxation which will further burden those individuals who not only support the public schools through taxation but support their own private and parochial schools. We therefore condemn the above-mentioned bill as unnecessary, unjust, insidious, and un-American.</p>
   <p>"I. This unnecessary and unreasonable bill is being opposed because it claims to <pb facs="5423968_4_1028.jpg" n="3"/>have, as one of its aims, the lessening of the burdens of the poor, but the fact is that the children of the poor have been receiving books free of charge. There fore such a bill is not needed.</p>
   <p>"II. We consider this bill unjustifiable because it brings along with it an in equitable taxation of citizens who possess the same rights as others, and who will be in no position to enjoy its advantages. The unfairness of this bill is most evident, when one considers the fact that these citizens build and support their own parish and private schools at great cost, and that they neither demand nor receive assistance from the state, which would lessen the financial load; them, too, one must consider the fact that, through this support, they help the state save large sums of money and are now to be even more heavily taxed.</p>
   <p>"III. That this proposal is insidious is evidenced by the fact that the parents of the children who are to get the free schoolbooks will have to pay, in the long run through higher taxation, even more than they pay for the books at present.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1029.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"IV. This bill should be stamped as un-American because it directly interferes with the principles of the Republic, in that it interferes with a privilege which rightfully belongs to the parents, and which will be taken over by the state. Therefore, we solemnly pretest against prepositions of this nature, and deem them unpatriotic and dangerous to the good of the nation."</p>
   <p>After the reading of the bill to the audience, the presidents of all Polish societies represented at the meeting signed their names by popular demand, designating how many members they represented.</p>
   <p>A committee was chosen from the combined societies, and delegated to go to Springfield and give a copy of the protest to the legislators and other influencial persons.</p>
   <p>News has reached the editorial rooms that other Polish parishes throughout Chicago and vicinity are going to take the same action.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
