<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-15">Oct. 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">25,000 Poles Honor Polish Army</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dexter Pavilion Filled to Capacity Collection for Polish Army Nets Thousands of Dollars</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-15">Oct. 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">25,000 POLES HONOR POLISH ARMY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dexter Pavilion Filled to Capacity Collection for Polish Army Nets Thousands of Dollars</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago's Polonia celebrated two occasions yesterday--it observed the one hundredth anniversary of the death of Thaddeus Kosciusko, the hero of two hemispheres, and it presented the battle flags to the Polish National Army which, side by side with the armies of the Allied powers will fight for freedom and liberty, for the rights and equality of all nations.</p>
   <p>And, as could be foreseen, the Poles of Chicago fully understood the significance of this great Polish occasion and that the greatest possible number of people should attend in order to honor properly the memory of the great Kosciusko and to witness the presentation of the first Polish standards, under which the brave Polish-American soldiers will fight the Prussians.</p>
   <p>It is no wonder, then, that early in the morning there was unusual activity <pb facs="5423968_4_0471.jpg" n="2"/>in Town of Lake. At one o'clock in the afternoon, when the first societies that were to participate in the parade began to gather, the streets around St. Joseph's Church at 48th Street and Hermitage Avenue were filled with members of Polish societies, organizations, and groups.</p>
   <p>Julius Slowacki Hall, which had been designated as the starting point for the parade to the church, was soon filled to overflowing. The volunteers who enlisted in the Polish Army within the last few days, as well as the recruiting officer, Lieutenant Skarzynski, and the administrations of the Polish National Alliance, the Polish Roman Catholic Union, the Polish Women's Alliance, the Polish Alma Mater, the Polish Falcons' Alliance, the Alliance of Polish Military Societies, and others gathered there.</p>
   <p>At one o'clock, the parade, which was to carry the standards from St. Joseph's Church to the Dexter Pavilion at Halsted and 43rd Streets where the principal exercises were to be held, began to form. At two o'clock, the parade began <pb facs="5423968_4_0472.jpg" n="3"/>to move toward the church. At its head flew the splendid Polish banner, hand-made by Polish-American women, carried by the aged Mrs. Lipczynski, wife of one of the organizers of the Polish National Alliance and former member of that organization's board of directors, accompanied by John J. Chrzanowski. There was a second banner also, donated to the Polish Army by the National Department of the Polish Central Relief Committee of America. This banner was carried by Vincent Sroka, member of Falcons' Nest #37. The long and beautiful streamers that were attached to the flagstaffs were held by the representatives of all of our Polish organizations.</p>
   <p>Following the banners marched the newly enlisted volunteers to the Polish army, followed by representatives of Polish societies and of various Polish groups. It should be added here that alongside the banners marched the representatives of the Polish Army in France, Lieutenants Gasiorowski, Poniatowski, Szaniawski, and Zekiecki. St. Joseph's Church was soon filled to capacity. The air was one of great dignity and solemnity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0473.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Reverend Stanislaus Cholewinski, pastor of St. Joseph's Church, officiated at vespers, after which he consecrated the banners which were held by the sponsors. During this ceremony, Reverend L. Grudzinski was deacon, Reverend F. Karabasz, pastor of Sacred Heart Church, subdeacon. In addition to these, the following priests participated in the ceremony: Reverend F. Wojtalewicz, pastor of St. Mary's Church in South Chicago, Reverend [F.] Kulinski of Kensington, Reverend P. Pyterek, Reverend A. Klowo, Reverend [J.] Appelt, pastor of Immaculate Heart Church in Irving Park, Reverend J. Gawrych, Reverend Stoinski, and the Reverends F. Kachnowski, S. Grzesinski, and A. Raczynski, the last three being assistants at St. Joseph's Church.</p>
   <p>Sermon Delivered by Reverend Kowalewski</p>
   <p>"Under this banner you shall win"--these are the words with which Reverend E. Kowalewski opened his sermon. "A hundred and twenty-two years have passed <pb facs="5423968_4_0474.jpg" n="5"/>since the three enemies of Poland dismembered our homeland and Poland lost its independence. The famous deeds of our country, "he continued," remain as a permanent reminder of the injustice perpetrated upon it, and the words of President Wilson, the first head of a great nation to raise the issue of a free and independent Poland, are the best evidence that Poland still lives, that it shall continue to live as long as Polish hearts beat, as long as there are just and great people in this world.</p>
   <p>"The banner is the symbol of our uniting together in a holy cause. Let us have faith that God will grant his blessing upon it and upon the Polish Army that will enter into mortal combat for Poland under its colors. For it is through union that an unbounded strength exists even in the weakest individuals."</p>
   <p>The speaker then traced Polish history from the battle of Raclawice and <pb facs="5423968_4_0475.jpg" n="6"/>Bartosz Glowacki to modern times." I call upon you, brethren, to gather beneath these Polish colors as heroes in these sad but momentous times.</p>
   <p>"We, the 'fourth partition' of Poland, pledge ourselves to give you all possible aid within our means and, as today, so later, we shall encourage the Polish clergy to pray God that you may carry these Polish colors to victory."</p>
   <p>A collection for the benefit of the Polish Army was then taken up by the Reverends Kulinski, Kachnowski, and Stoinski.</p>
   <p>Parade to Dexter Pavilion</p>
   <p>It was 3:30 in the afternoon when the people poured out of the church and began to form the great parade which was to take the Polish banners to <pb facs="5423968_4_0476.jpg" n="7"/>Dexter Pavilion. The parade was headed by a platoon of mounted and foot police followed by the band and by the members of the committee in charge of the day's proceedings. Then came the 11th Regiment of the Illinois National Guard and the living American flag [formed by Polish women and girls] followed by the volunteers to the Polish Army, and the newly consecrated flags, alongside which marched the representatives of the Polish Army in France and the delegate from the French army, Commander L. C. Eckenfelder, sent here by the French government to participate in this manifestation. The sponsors of the flags followed immediately behind and, after them, the Polish Falcons. The Falcons were followed by various Polish organizations and societies, among which were: Council 2 [Polish National Alliance] and societies of St. Adalbert's Parish, Council 3, P. N. A. and societies of Holy Trinity and St. Stanislaus Kostka Parishes, Council 23, P. N. A. and the societies of South Chicago, Kensington, Pullman, and West Pullman parishes, Councils 40 and 41, P. N. A., and societies of St. Helen's and St. Hedwig's Parishes, Council 75, P. N. A., <pb facs="5423968_4_0477.jpg" n="8"/>and societies of Holy Innocents, St. John Cantius, and St. Mary of Angels Parishes, Council 79, P. N. A., and societies of St. Casimir's Parish, Council 30 and societies of St. Barbara, St. Mary of Perpetual Help, St. Peter and Paul, and Five Holy Martyrs' Parishes, and Council 39, P. N. A., and societies of Sacred Heart St. John of God, and St. Joseph's Parishes. The rear of the parade was brought up by throngs of people, after whom followed automobiles decorated with Polish, American, English, and French flags.</p>
   <p>The parade proceeded from 48th Street to Lincoln Avenue, then turned north to 47th Street, then to Ashland Avenue, to 48th Street to Throop Street, to 51st Street, to Halsted Street, back to 47th Street, to Union Avenue, down Union Avenue to 43rd Street and down 43rd Street to Dexter Pavilion. It should be mentioned here that the grand marshal of the parade was J. Kukulski, member of Nest 37, Polish Falcons' Alliance, assisted ably by Zygmunt Szmidt, president of Nest 105 and Victor Orciuch, a member of Nest 37.</p>
   <p>Exercises at Dexter Pavilion</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0478.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>At about five o'clock, the procession arrived at the Dexter Pavilion, where throngs of people were awaiting the beginning of the exercises. The representatives of the Allied powers, the American government, Ignace Paderewski and his wife, other invited guests, representatives of Polish organizations and the clergy soon arrived. The main platform was occupied by Paderewski and his wife, Commander Eckenfelder, Captain Stanton, representing the general staff of the American army, Captain Murray, representative of the British government, O'Connell, representative of Ireland, John F. Smulski, and T. M. Helinski. At the press tables sat representatives of the following newspapers: the Chicago Hearld, the Chicago Tribune, the Chicago American, and the Chicago Journal. The Polish newspapers were represented as follows: For Dziennik Zwiazkowy, editors [S.] Orpiszewski, [S.] Lewental, Skwarczynski, and Miss Seyoler, stenographer; Dziennik Chicagoski--W. Papara; Dziennik Narodowy--[H.] Lokanski and [L.] Kolakowski; and Kuryer Polski of Milwaukee--[Karol] Piatkiewicz.</p>
   <p>After everyone had taken his place and every seat in the hall was occupied <pb facs="5423968_4_0479.jpg" n="10"/>and even all the standing room had been utilized, M. Perlowski, president of the citizens' committee opened the exercises with the following address:</p>
   <p>"Distinguished guests, reverend guests, ladies and gentlemen, countrymen: It is with great pleasure and with deep emotion that I greet you here today. Great must be the cause that unites so many thousands of hearts and powerful must be the spirit that creates such enthusiasm. Before our guests, before the delegates from France and from the Polish Army in France our entire Polish group has gathered here, represented by men's and women's organizations, the clergy, the intelligentsia, the professional men, and the workers, while at the head of this great gathering stands our unequalled leader, Ignace Paderewski with his distinguished wife, guardian of Polish orphans, Madame Helen Paderewski. From the many thousands of hearts united today in this gathering here, there emanates an ardent, flaming spirit of patriotism to <pb facs="5423968_4_0480.jpg" n="11"/>Poland. We are gathered here today for an act of the greatest sacrifice--to offer solemnly our best strength for the defense of our homeland's freedom. We do this on the one hundredth anniversary of the death of Thaddeus Kosciusko, fulfilling his tow that the Polish nation shall not lay down its arms until it has regained its freedom. And just as our forefathers who went into battle devoutly singing "Bogu Rodzica" [Mother of God, a XIV century chant], so shall we humble ourselves before Christ the Saviour before entering the struggle.</p>
   <p>"I ask Reverend [W.] Zapala to read the invocation and to pronounce the blessing upon this gathering. The committee places the chairmanship into the experienced hands of John F. Smulski, unequalled in his civic work and always an ardent servant of the Polish cause."</p>
   <p>Following Perlowski's address, Smulski took over the chairmanship and called upon T. M. Helinski to act as secretary. The invocation by Reverend Zapala <pb facs="5423968_4_0481.jpg" n="12"/>followed:</p>
   <p>"Countrymen: On this hundredth anniversary of the death of Kosciusko and on this day of consecration of the first standards for the Polish Army, praise be to the Almighty Lord and honor to our homeland.</p>
   <p>"All honor to you, Poland, for your past is a volume filled with brilliant and worthy deeds, for your path was that of sacrifice and of love for higher ideals, your struggles were struggles in defense of truth and justice. Praise to you, O Poland, for you have ever been God's thunderbolt, the very bulwark of Christianity in Europe against its enemies, because you brought Christianity to Lithuania and crushed the Teutonic knights, whose bloody depredations defamed the holy sign of the Cross under which they fought. Praise to you, O Poland, for you were the heart that was filled with love, for you were the angel that led the Piasts [first dynasty of kings in Poland] that they might lay the foundations for the triumph of the Jagellons, for, <pb facs="5423968_4_0482.jpg" n="13"/>like a mother, you took Lithuania and Ruthenia beneath your protective arms and gave them peace and prosperity and a share of your glory.</p>
   <p>"Honor to you, O Poland, for your unshaken faith, for Plowce, Grunwald [battlefields on which the Teutonic knights were defeated], for Lokietek and the Jagellons, for Sobieski, for Kosciusko, for your many geniuses, for your valiant knights, and for this day, that you have called us together in such great numbers. Honor to you, O Poland, for the graves in which lie your fallen defenders, for the crucifixes that mark your crossroads, for the hymn "Bogu Rodzica that even now reaches us in triumphal echo.</p>
   <p>"Thanks to you, O Poland, for this day that is to us, prisoner bound by three sets of chains, a day of glory and triumph. Praise to you, O Poland, for you are one of those worthy lands that are not stained with the blood of injustice, but rather with your own blood, spilled by the injustice of <pb facs="5423968_4_0483.jpg" n="14"/>others.</p>
   <p>"Before Thee, Almighty God, we stand as poor wanderers, oppressed, imprisoned, dispropriated, persecuted, poisoned by doubt; we arise, awakened from a lethargic sleep because Thou, O Lord, hast spoken to us, because Poland calls. Today we can hear no other voice, we have no other watchwords; today only one thought prevails in our minds--that we are children of Poland.</p>
   <p>"Poland is the watchword that has gathered these thousands together. We are all here. Here are our many standards and banners, here our music resounds, our songs ring out. We have gathered here to show that we are children of Poland.</p>
   <p>"Today our homeland accepts these standards we have consecrated, it accepts the volunteers who have enlisted in the ranks of its national army. Today, before the whole United States, we show that at the call of Poland our <pb facs="5423968_4_0484.jpg" n="15"/>soldiers move, that we are a nation alive; we show this before the whole civilized world. Our knights of old shall rub shoulders with our soldiers of today and knight them with the words, 'Serve your homeland and give every ounce of your strength for its welfare!'</p>
   <p>"Go forward into battle in the name of God, O Polish soldiers, and bring glory and victory to our beloved Poland. May the blessing of God be upon you, and of Her who defended Czestochowo and Ostra Brama, the Holy Mother of God."</p>
   <p>Paderewski's Hymn</p>
   <p>In a short address, Smulski then thanked the audience for gathering in such large numbers, and introduced each of the distinguished guests upon the platform. The secretary then read congratulatory telegrams from Jusserand, <pb facs="5423968_4_0485.jpg" n="16"/>Cecil Spring Rice, Bachmetiew [Russian ambassador], Captain Blenski, censor of the Polish National Alliance, and Werwinski, vice-censor of the same organization.</p>
   <p>The next number was the rendition of the Polish hymn composed especially for this occasion by Ignace Paderewski, by the Philaret choir under the direction of the well-known operatic star from Boston, T. Wronski, accompanied by the orchestra, conducted by Przybylski. It would be difficult to describe the immense effect this splendid composition had upon the audience. The thunderous applause seemed without end, and the rendition had to be repeated. And so, once again the tones of the splendid melody resounded, filling the audience with patriotic fervor. At its conclusion, Paderewski was thanked for, and congratulated upon, his composition by the chairman, who then called upon the great artist to address the gathering. [Paderewski's address appears upon another page of the same issue of Dziennik Zwiazkowy.]</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0486.jpg" n="17"/>
   <p>Presentation of Flags</p>
   <p>Upon concluding his address, Paderewski presented the flag donated by the National Department of the Polish Central Relief Committee to Lieutenant Gasiorowski of the Polish Army, who, after kissing it reverently, turned it over to Szaniawski. The other flag, handmade by Polish women of Chicago, was presented by Mrs. Lipczynski, while Miss Emily Napieralski, secretary-general of the Polish Women's Alliance of America addressed the gathering in English and presented the Polish Army delegation with a check for one thousand dollars from the Polish Women's Alliance. Lieutenant Gasiorowski then spoke, expressing the Polish Army's gratitude, and promised that the soldiers themselves will best offer their thanks--on the battle front. He then called upon the volunteers to rise and to take the oath of the Polish Army as follows:</p>
   <p>"I solemnly swear to my homeland, united and independent Poland, that on <pb facs="5423968_4_0487.jpg" n="18"/>land or sea, or anywhere in the world, I will serve it honestly and faithfully to the fullest extent of my strength and ability, and that I will in no way detract from the unblemished honor and traditions of the Polish Army; I will faithfully obey my superior officers, execute all commands, and abide by all regulations. In the present war, I will fight for a united and independent Poland to the last drop of my blood, and will regard the soldiers of the other Allied nations as my brothers. In general, I will conduct myself in such a way that I may live as a true and brave Polish soldier, So help me, God!"</p>
   <p>After the volunteers had taken the oath, during which tears glistened in many eyes as well as hope for a brighter future for Poland, a great cheer for the Polish Army was given. The orchestra then played the hymns "Jeszcze Polska Nie Zginela" [Poland is not yet lost] and "The Star-Spangled Banner," following which Captain Stanton, personal representative of Secretary of War Baker, spoke. His address was rewarded with enthusiastic applause from the <pb facs="5423968_4_0488.jpg" n="19"/>audience.</p>
   <p>After the orchestra had played the "Marseillaise," the representatives of England, France, Scotland, and Ireland spoke.</p>
   <p>Collection For the Polish Army</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of these addresses, the chairman called upon those present to pledge themselves for contributions for the Polish Army, while a collection was taken up in the hall. Casimir Zychlinski pledged $5,000 in behalf of the P. N. A. and Reverend Zapala pledged $5,000 in behalf of the association of Polish Priests. In all, $13,560, not counting a large number of small pledges which were later recorded, was pledged. Details of these will be published in a later issue.</p>
   <p>It was 8:30 in the evening when the chairman called the meeting to a close <pb facs="5423968_4_0489.jpg" n="20"/>with the singing of "Boze Cos Polske" [God Save Poland].</p>
   <p>It should be added here that a very fine painting of Kosciusko was donated to the Polish Army by Bernard Markiewicz, well-known Polish artist.</p>
   <p>Today (Monday, Oct. 15) the Polish Army delegation will proceed to Milwaukee, where a great patriotic demonstration is to be held at Kosciusko Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
