<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-01">Sept. 1, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Question of the High Cost of Living.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0985</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0985.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-01">Sept. 1, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE QUESTION OF THE HIGH COST OF LIVING.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The high cost of living is occupying the minds of all people, especially those most affected, the working class. The wealthier people, who are practical economists, are likewise pondering the cause of high prices. Some blame the tariff, others attribute the high cost of living to the farmer and the trusts who, as stockholders, control our commodities and hoard big supplies of provisions in warehouses and refrigerators, accumulated over a period of months, and in many cases, years. Limitation causes scarcity, and thus the increase in price. Therefore, those speculators whose objective is only profit and who cast aside all thought of sentiment, justice or charity in their quest for gold, are responsible for the present conditions.</p>
   <p>It is true that similar conditions exist in other countries, but only as a result of wars and internal strife whereby the cultivation of land was sadly neglected. Other countries are faced with the serious problem of over-population. In the United States, however, that condition does not exist, therefore we have great ranges of virgin land available which can be cultivated by <pb facs="5423968_4_0986.jpg" n="2"/>our farmers; neither are we troubled with warfare or internal conflicts. Our rich soil produces a large variety of grains to fatten our poultry and cattle. We can raise abundant vegetables and fruits. The great plains, our prairie ranges, provide sufficient grazing territory for many herds.</p>
   <p>In addition, our shipping facilities are so well developed, that we can deliver our produce and finished products to any desired locality. There is no physical reason why the cost of living should continue to soar upward, unchecked. With prices of food, clothing, fuel, and housing so unreasonably high, the average workingman, earning $1.50 per day, finds it hardly possible to support his family. No wonder, then, that in the years of so-called prosperity there is great want among the poorer classes.</p>
   <p>These pressing matters should be investigated thoroughly to determine the real cause of the high cost of living. In this manner we can cut away this social canker which causes so much misery, dissatisfaction, class hatred and extensive disorder. We can prevent the theatening eruption of a volcano whose lava of justified anger might overflow and exterminate a group of ruthless exploiters-madmen, blinded by the lustre of gold.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
