<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-23">Apr. 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Recruiting Station at the Polish Roman Catholic Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0589</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0589.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-23">Apr. 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">RECRUITING STATION AT THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Saturday at 9 A. M. the first Polish recruiting station was opened at the Polish Roman Catholic Union, Milwaukee Avenue and Augusta Street, for volunteers to the regular army of the United States.</p>
   <p>J. S. Konopa, secretary of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, W. Goralski, T. Kozlowski, former corporal in the American army, and J. Skibinski, editor of the biweekly Free Poland, were authorized by Officer Franklin R. Kenney, chief recruiting officer, to accept volunteers to the ranks of Uncle Sam's army. They were informed in detail of conditions in the army and will thus be able to give those interested all the necessary information.</p>
   <p>The new recruiting bureau was open Saturday from 9 A.M. to 9 P.M. and yesterday <pb facs="5423968_4_0590.jpg" n="2"/>[Sunday] from 1 to 6 P. M. Ninety volunteers have already enlisted. Many have received the necessary information, and many are still applying.</p>
   <p>The bureau will be open every day for the convenience of those interested. Therefore, anyone who is young and healthy, who realizes that we owe much to the United States for taking us in and giving us freedom and protection, who is not a coward but a manly descendant of Chrobry [Boleslaw Chrobry, a Polish king] and Kosciusko, should hasten to help the United States in its fight against humanity's greatest enemy--the Germans.</p>
   <p>The Poles--as Captain Kenney says--are good material for the American army, not only in the ranks but as officers as well.</p>
   <p>"I have always been of the opinion," said Captain Kenney, "that the Poles are loyal citizens of this country. Poles are brave. A Pole, and I say this from <pb facs="5423968_4_0591.jpg" n="3"/>personal experience, placed among other men is more skillful and therefore deserves promotion faster than men of other nationalities."</p>
   <p>This is an American captain's opinion of us Poles.</p>
   <p>We are happy about this good opinion, and we should strive to keep it by enlisting under the Stars and Stripes of Uncle Sam.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
