<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-01">Dec. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Illinois Cylinder Grinding Machine Company - a Polish Corporation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1588</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1588.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-01">Dec. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE ILLINOIS CYLINDER GRINDING MACHINE COMPANY - A POLISH CORPORATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From time to time we have given space to the spread of Polish corporations in Chicago. Hot only do we give them publicity, but also support. One of these firms is the Illinois Cylinder Grinding Machine Company, located at 1005-09 W. Division Street. This firm possesses patents on two grinding machines that are being manufactured for grinding and polishing automobile cylinders. Flans are being made to enter the automotive field.</p>
   <p>The patented "Ace" grinder has proved to be a useful product. The "Triumph" gasoline motor, also patented, silted, has great possibilities in the automotive field. Recently this motor proved that it surpasses all others.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1589.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It has been reported that at the present time it functions one hundred per cent better than any other motor on the market; parts can easily be replaced without the need of an expert mechanic or high cost.</p>
   <p>At present all of the Polish industrial enterprises are suffering because of lack of lack of capital. Because of this they cannot expand to any large extents. Besides this the appearance of low-priced machines and tools from Europe have also been important factors in retarding the growth of industry in this country.</p>
   <p>The Illinois Cylinder Grinding Machine Company, with its patented equipment, can become an important producer of this type of Machinery and <pb facs="5423968_4_1590.jpg" n="3"/>compete on a large scale with similar companies, Information has been received that this Polish concern will soon increase its capital by issuing a block of stock. This added money will be used to build a foundry. From a general point of view this company has a good opportunity to make good.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
