<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-18">Mar. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Protest against the American-Russian Extradition Tranty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1037</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1037.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-18">Mar. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST AGAINST THE AMERICAN-RUSSIAN EXTRADITION TRANTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The last Republican administration of the United States approved a new extradition treaty with Russia. This treaty contains a clause that provides the return to Russia even of political offenders if their offense is a criminal one. Obviously, such a treaty would serve as a powerful weapon to the perversity and baseness of Russian justice toward those who have sought shelter from its persecution in the United States. A loud protest against this treaty has begun to develop even in American circles. Tens of thousands of signatures have figured on protests against this destructive treaty; for such a treaty could make a land of oppression and persecution of a free country, such as the United States has been heretofore. Among those condemning the treaty is to be found even so respected a Republican as Chauncey M. Depew.</p>
   <p>Fortunately the treaty has not as yet been ratified. The new Democratic <pb facs="5423968_4_1038.jpg" n="2"/>administration, at whose head is Cleveland, may reject it. In any case, it can be referred to the legislative body, which is now largely Democratic, for re-examination. This matter will be concluded one way or the other toward the end of next week.</p>
   <p>With affairs at their present stage, it is not too late for American citizens to protest against this evil and subversive treaty. Protests originating now can still reach authoritative quarters before decisive steps have been taken. Protests should be made sooner by Poles than by anyone else. It is the Poles who are best acquainted with the Czar's touch, and who eventually would feel the results of such a treaty most heavily.</p>
   <p>The idea of a protest against the Czar's despotism has existed among the Poles for a long time, and it may be that had it not been for interference on the part of ill-willed people, it would already have attained considerable results.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1039.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On New Year's Day, 1892, the Reverend Vincent Barzynski effected a gathering of 2,500 Poles with the purpose of instituting a protest against the horrible persecution of thousands of Poles by the Russian tyrant and his henchmen--persecution for no other reason than that these Poles refused to renounce the faith of their forefather. At that time, jealousy, awakened by the intrigues of a certain clique with the aid of a paper erroneously called Zgoda, caused a violent reaction to the idea, Certainly these thoughtless people had not realized how soon the bitter fruits of their miserable politics would ripen. Today, the United States desires a treaty with Russia. Would this desire ever have arisen had last year's protest against Russian despotism, authenticated by hundreds of thousands of American Poles, been allowed to ring in the ears of American citizens? The idea of a protest returns today, at the last minute. Today everybody understands its importance. Thus, strong-willed people, unmindful of obstacles, have decided to call a great mass meeting <pb facs="5423968_4_1040.jpg" n="4"/>to register a protest against a treaty which would make the United States subservient to Moscow. The mass meeting will be held tomorrow (Sunday) in the St. Stanislaus parish school hall at eight o'clock in the evening.</p>
   <p>Let everyone attend! Let us appeal to this nation and its statesmen. Let us protest with all our strength against an alliance of this free nation with a tyrant. Our mass meeting, at which every Pole should be present, will not be ineffectual. Having made the necessary decisions, we can appeal to the President of the United States, asking that he withhold ratification of the treaty with Russia, and further, that he accept a more detailed representation of the matter. Doubtless, the result will be that this treaty, approved by only the worst of the Republicans, will be confuted.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1041.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>And so--all Poles to the mass meeting at the school hall at Bradley Street!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
