<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-10">Mar. 10, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Labors Dangers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1383</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1383.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-10">Mar. 10, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">LABORS DANGERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Labor, under present conditions, is a source of constant danger to the workers. The special exertion to which certain parts of the body are subjected, is the source of Many diseases that afflict the worker--the initial source of his weakening and degeneration. Many books have been written by learned physicians on the dangers to which the health of a worker is exposed by poor labor conditions.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly, the greatest danger is the fatal effect of various kinds of shop dust on the lungs and other organs of the body. In Places where metal, glass, shell, and horn products are manufactured, minute particles of these materials form a dust that settles in the lungs and pores and kills the worker slowly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1384.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A famous French physician has made a very careful study over the past few years of the effects of dust on the health of workers. He has reached the following conclusions, based on a detailed examination of a great number of individual cases: For every hundred metal workers, 54 die of consumption; in minerals, 51; compositors, 27. Among glass is workers, 27 out of 500 die of consumption. The highest mortality rate is among cabinetmakers--56 out of one hundred.</p>
   <p>The above are authoritative statistics. It is unnecessary to add that such occupations as, for instance, sorting of old rugs, work in factories which manufacture fertilizers and other chemical products, work that brings one in contact with phosphorus, mercury, and similar substances, are all dangerous to health. We need not mention damp, unsanitary, poorly ventilated places in which many people work.</p>
   <p>A laborer, then, is beset with a great variety of dangers and no safeguards.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1385.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Measures for safeguarding the lives and health of workers have long been demanded. Methods and apparatuses have been even developed to this end, as for example, ventilators to remove the dust from the air in shops and factories. Thus far these demands have brought but meager results. These fatal working conditions exist not only in the factories of Europe, but in those of America as well. Aside from ventilation, practically nothing has been done to protect the lives and health of the workers.</p>
   <p>This is the greatest fault of the capitalists. The sight of their egoism in the face of the workers' sufferings gives rise only to constantly embittered relations between capital and labor--relations which may lead to the worst consequences.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
