<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-28">Jan. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">In the Congressional Record</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0716</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0716.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-28">Jan. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE CONGRESSIONAL RECORD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During these days we trace carefully and assiduously every opinion expressed by prominent people here in America on the Polish matter. We do so because we expect that the opinions of the representatives of the states in Congress will have great significance during the peace treaties after the war. The sympathy with which America views our cause must necessarily be reflected in the settlement of this very involved Polish question.</p>
   <p>It is therefore the duty of all the more prominent Poles in American to constantly inform opinion in America on matters pertinent to Poland. We should all endeavor to awaken widespread sympathy for our homeland, so that some day we may refer to American public opinion and the way this country treated our cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0717.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One of the very important facts upon which we might some day rely is a discussion on the Polish question found in the Congressional Record of January 11, 1915, on page 1376. This discussion took place in the Senate of the United States after the secretary of the Senate read a letter written by Mr. N. L. Piotrowski, the City Counsellor of Chicago, addressed to the Honorable W. J. Stone, Senator of the United States. The discussion pertained to the congressional amendment excluding Belgians from the intelligence-test clause in the immigration statute now being drawn up. Senator Stone arose and requested the president of the Senate--the Honorable Thomas R. Marshall, Vice President of the United States--to permit him to read the letter he had received on the matter that was under consideration. When none of those present objected to the reading of this document, the secretary of the Senate read the letter of Mr. N. L. Piotrowski. It then was recorded in the Congressional Record. This letter is a follows:</p>
   <p>"I have read in the reports from Washington that the Senate has passed an immigration bill Which also contains an intelligence-test clause, which <pb facs="5423968_4_0718.jpg" n="3"/>states that Belgians need not be subject to the test. That is a very sane and humane bill, and I am certain that every freedom-loving American citizen will be pleased that the portals of this country are wide open to the unfortunate Belgians.</p>
   <p>"On this occasion I should like to call your attention to another country, whose fate is perhaps even more tragic than that of Belgium. I refer to Poland. The Poles were deprived of their country about one hundred and fifty years ago. This bloody tragedy, which brought to light knavery unparalleled in the history of modern Europe, and as a result of which Poland was divided and plundered and twenty-five million of her children were deprived of their freedom, has not, I believe, been forgotten. Nor do I believe that freedom-loving Americans will be indifferent to Poland's fate. The Poles have no country which they are free to call their own. Those who have an opportunity to avoid severe persecutions by their tyrants migrate to every country and to all corners of the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0719.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Allow me to call your attention to the terrible experiences of the Polish people in this horrible war. Nearly all of Galicia, the part of Poland now under Austrian rule, possessing a population of seven million, was first invaded by Russians, then by the Austrian and German armies, and again by Russian soldiers. Today it is one mass of ruin. Its residents who were not killed flee from place to place like wild animals without food and shelter, and hide in holes to avoid cannon shells.</p>
   <p>"This same tragic fate has also befallen the area known as the Kingdom of Poland, numbering twelve million people. The Germans devastated this country up to the localities six miles from Warsaw. The Russians did the rest when they chased the Germans back the same way they came. At present the Germans are making a third attempt to conquer Warsaw. Rumors have it that west of the Vistula river, in the Kingdom of Poland, more than five hundred cities, occupied predominantly by Poles, were ruined completely. Everyone has heard of the fate that befell Louvain, but hardly anyone has heard of the fate of Kalisz, a city of about forty thousand people, in the Polish <pb facs="5423968_4_0720.jpg" n="5"/>Kingdom. The people of Kalisz met the same fate as those of Louvain. The Poles in East Prussia have endured the same hardships, and a similar fate yet awaits the Poles in Posen annexed by Prussia.</p>
   <p>"The Belgians have at least the satisfaction left that they are fighting for their country. They have a hope that when the Allied forces are victorious, the wrongs done them will be righted. Judging by the past, there is little hope left for the Poles, despite the promises made them by the three powers--Russia, Austria, and Germany. The Poles are not only compelled to fight against their will, but in a dition they are forced to fight for a cause that is not their own but that of their oppressors. In addition to that--and what is even worse--they are compelled to fight against themselves, to shed the blood of their brethren; a brother must attack his brother and a son his father. To them it is a fratricidal war. It is therefore, perhaps the most horrible tragedy of this war.</p>
   <p>"About three hundred and fifty thousand Poles are in the German army and <pb facs="5423968_4_0721.jpg" n="6"/>about that many in the Austrian. There are approximately seven hundred thousand Poles in the Russian forces. This means that about one and a half million Poles are fighting in this war on one side or another. And why are they fighting? Certainly not for Poland's cause. In the opinion of all who read, and are closely interested in, the matters of the present war, the Poles are more deserving of pity than are the Belgians."</p>
   <p>After presenting this bloody picture of our present position in Europe, the City Counsellor of Chicago appealed to the Senate to protect the Polish people by excluding them from the intelligence-test clause in the future immigration statute of the United States.</p>
   <p>After reading this letter, Senator Stone proposed that it be sent to the committee on immigration matters and also that it be read to the Conference Committee, if that is possible and permissible.</p>
   <p>Because the bill was before the Senate and the clause on the free admission <pb facs="5423968_4_0722.jpg" n="7"/>of Belgians had been defeated in the House of Representatives, Mr. Piotrowski's letter did not bring about the proper result. The fact, however, remains that this letter was presented in its entirety and reprinted in the Congressional Record, so that official America can become acquainted with the contents of this document on the fate of unfortunate Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
