<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 28,
<date when="1889-07-10">July 10, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">News in America Forty-Two States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 28,
<date when="1889-07-10">July 10, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS IN AMERICA FORTY-TWO STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>July 14, 1889, there were four new stars added to our American flag, because on this day four new states were composed and admitted to the American Union. We have today forty-two stars hovering in the sky of our Republic, the United States of America.</p>
   <p>This same day in the year of 1790 there were only thirteen stars shining on their area of 325,065 square miles; today the expansion of this same Republic covers the area of 2,405,070 square miles.</p>
   <p>From the time of the daring and heroic associates of Washington, consisting of bold and brave generals, among whom we find Kosciuszko and Pulaski, who fought gallantly for the freedom of our Republic, our country grew consistently in area and that is why today it is so large it could easily, without any damage or injury to itself, take in the population of Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1159.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the years of 1791, 1792, 1796, three new stars were added to the original: Vermont, Kentucky and Tennessee. In the year 1802, Ohio; 1812, Louisiana; 1816, Indiana; 1817, Mississippi; 1818, Illinois; 1819, Alabama; 1820, Maine; 1821, Missouri; 1836, Arkansas; 1837, Michigan; 1845, Florida and Iowa; 1846, Texas; 1847, Wisconsin; 1850, California; 1858, Minnesota; 1859, Oregon; 1861, Kansas; 1862, West Virginia; 1864, Nevada; 1867, Nebraska; 1875, Colorado. Washington, Montana and both of the Dakotas were just admitted into the Union, July 4, 1889.</p>
   <p>The area of the United States is large, and frequently there is a creation of a new settlement. The people always migrate forward. This, then, creates material for future stars in the form of budding states.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
