<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-27">Sept. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">News from North Chicago Organization Meeting of the Polish Division of the Fourth Liberty Loan Drive</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-27">Sept. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM NORTH CHICAGO ORGANIZATION MEETING OF THE POLISH DIVISION OF THE FOURTH LIBERTY LOAN DRIVE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Division of the Fourth Liberty Loan Drive Committee held an organization meeting on Tuesday, September 24, 1918, at Our Lady of Rosary parish hall.</p>
   <p>Mr. Max Przyborski was unanimously selected chairman of the meeting, and Mr. F. Mazewski was made secretary. The chairman expressed his gratitude for the honor bestowed upon him. He then appealed to every one present to fulfill his obligations faithfully so that the Poles in America may demonstrate to the world at large that our people always occupy first place in matters in which the welfare of America and of Poland are concerned.</p>
   <p>"We appeal, therefore, to you, fellow Poles," said the chairman," to demonstrate your loyalty to the United States by purchasing American Liberty Bonds. If the Poles wish to show how much they are inspired, and how anxious our people are to <pb facs="5423968_4_0131.jpg" n="2"/>attain victory over our common foe, the best way to manifest it is to buy Liberty Bonds through the Polish Committee. Every purchaser who does so will be recorded as a Pole and a good citizen of this country."</p>
   <p>The Polish Committee on Liberty Bonds will issue subscription blanks every evening at 7 o'clock, beginning on September 30, 1918, at Our Lady of Rosary parish hall.</p>
   <p>"And so every right minded Pole should make application to this Polish Committee at the designated place. We shall thus be certain that we, as Poles, will receive due credit, and that our people will gain first place for their purchases of bonds. This will prevent other nationalities from obtaining undue recognition.</p>
   <p>"Permit us to remind you that we Poles are of the Allies. Every [member of an Allied Nation] has his individual duty to perform and has an individual obligation to fulfill. Those of us who cannot fight in the front lines should not feel that they are unable to contribute to make the victory of our cause a reality. It is the duty of every good citizen not in actual combat to lend money to this Government and to endeavor to persuade others to do likewise. The purchase of these Liberty Bonds should not be delayed but should be made as soon as they appear.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0132.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If every soldier, for example, were to pause and consider whether or not to fight the enemy as many of us stop and consider whether or not to lend money to the Government, final victory would be uncertain. A coward is he who can but will not fight, but equally a coward is he who in a time when a soldier does not pause to consider whether or not to fight considers whether or not he shall lend money to the Government or delays in making his loan. Such a person is a financial coward.</p>
   <p>"What right have we Poles [to delay], who will benefit by the freedom won by our soldiers? The blood of that soldier fighting in France calls to us to give and to give now and until the end of the war, until our final victory is attained. He who does not understand this call can have no place among our people, nor will there ever be a place for him. If we wish to see the dawn of a better and brighter future, we must give either our money or our blood. We must give one or the other, or even both, because it is in behalf of democracy."</p>
   <p>Promotion Committee:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0133.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Max Przyborski</p>
   <p>F. Mazewski</p>
   <p>W. Zdanowicz</p>
   <p>F. Kusiewski</p>
   <p>J. Janas</p>
   <p>B. Kaczmarek</p>
   <p>M. Szeluga</p>
   <p>F. Walczak</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
