<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 30.
<date when="1917-07-25">July 25, 1917</date>. 
<title level="a">Medical Lectures for Polish Mothers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1320</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1320.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 30.
<date when="1917-07-25">July 25, 1917</date>. 
<title level="a">MEDICAL LECTURES FOR POLISH MOTHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are informed that the Polish physicians in Chicago put forward an important resolution recently. Whereas it appears that the state of health in our city is unsatisfactory and on the northwest side of the city the citizens do not observe sanitary rules as they should, which often is the cause of unpleasant encounters with the Board of Health, not to speak of the harm inflicted on the health of the Poles, the Polish physicians resolved to give a series of lectures on health and hygiene for the Polish women, who first ought to know how to rear children, how to nourish them in a healthy manner, etc. The lectures will be conducted systematically every day (except Saturdays and Sundays) at 2 P. M. in the Field House of Eckhardt Park, at Noble and Chicago Avenues, beginning Monday.</p>
   <p>The Polish physicians who unselfishly resolved to give these lectures, appeal to all Polish mothers who have the cause of health and hygiene at heart, to come to the lectures at Eckhardt Park. The Polish mothers can come with their children to these lectures.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1321.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Below we insert the address pertaining to this matter, sent to us by the Polish physicians:</p>
   <p>To Polish mothers:-Many children and infants die during the summer months, mainly due to diseases of the stomach and intestines. In Polish sections thickly populated and not a bit too clean, this mortality is directly frightful. The main reason for this is the lack of knowledge on the part of Polish mothers. The majority of them do not know how to take care of children, what to give them to eat, how and when to bathe them, how to dress them, summer complaint, with which so many children suffer during the hot weather, is usually the result of improper feeding, whether in regard to the amount or the kind of nourishment. The ignorance of the mothers beings about sickness, expense, sorrow and often death. Ignorance and sometimes also negligence.</p>
   <p>In order to change this state of things, in order to lower the high <pb facs="5423968_4_1322.jpg" n="3"/>mortality rate among children, the Polish Physicians Association in Chicago is giving a series of popular lectures for mothers during the week from the 23rd to the 28th of July. The lectures will be given in park number 1 at Chicago and Noble St., from 2 to 4 P. M. daily, starting next Monday, July 23rd.</p>
   <p>We invite all Polish mothers and wives to this first course. The lectures will be concise, interesting and practical, and what is more important, in the Polish language. Listening to them attentively and understanding them will teach one to avoid many maladies of the infant stage and can save you many expenses, sorrow and misfortune.</p>
   <p>Every woman, bringing up children, ought to attend these lectures and encourage her acquaintances and friends.</p>
   <p>We entertain a full hope that the reverend clergy and the respected press will support our efforts through a gracious announcement of our summons from the pulpit and in the daily newspapers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1323.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If the course is successful in park number 1, similar lectures will be given later in other Polish sections.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Polish Physicians Association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
