<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-08">June 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The May Campaign</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0238</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0238.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-08">June 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAY CAMPAIGN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The May Campaign now being conducted throughout all Polish communities in America, is to the Polish Army what the Liberty Loan campaigns were to the American. It is an indispensable factor in the formation and existence of that army. Every recruiting officer knows how recruiting is affected by the argument that the Polish soldier has no insurance in case of injury. Our able boys who are joining the Polish Army do not ask for pay or insurance. They are ready to make the greatest sacrifices in order to help restore Poland, and they would enlist in the Army even if they knew that in case of crippling injury they would be reduced to beggars without aid or care. But it is up to society to give this sacrifice the proper appreciation and to contribute, even to its last penny, toward establishing an insurance fund. By such an action, society will be co-operating more closely with the Polish Army--a co-operation which has not been in evidence hitherto, owing to the fact that the Polish Army has been supported by <pb facs="5423968_4_0239.jpg" n="2"/>France. Our soldiers would certainly be wronged if, after receiving pay, arms, and ammunition from France, their own community could not assure them that, in case of disablement, they will not be forced to beg bread after the war.</p>
   <p>The very announcement of the campaign served to raise our soldiers' spirits and to increase the number of volunteers. But the campaign should be conducted to a successful conclusion if good intentions are to be turned into deeds.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, it is the duty of every recruiting officer to support the campaign to the fullest possible extent. It is a fact that because of many misunderstandings and much harmful propaganda, the collection of funds for the May Campaign has not been conducted with the same enthusiasm and intensity in every Polish community. The seed of ill will, sown long before the campaign began, is bearing fruit today, even though <pb facs="5423968_4_0240.jpg" n="3"/>misunderstandings as to the control and allocation of these funds have been cleared up. Recruiting officers ought not remain indifferent in such instances. They cannot say that this is a civic or political matter and thus maintain a sort of false neutrality, for it is a vital concern of the Polish Army. Where the campaign is in the hands of capable citizens and is being conducted energetically, it is not necessary for recruiting officers to give all of their time to this cause. But wherever the campaign has not developed properly because of indolence or political misunderstanding, recruiting officers should take action energetically and organize the citizens to collect funds for the May Campaign. If fake rumors are being circulated, they should be corrected by use of the official statements of the Military Commission and the National Department. It should also be explained to the people that politics has no place in such an important matter, that everyone of us ought to do his national duty as a soldier and put politics aside, as something to be settled by organizations and conventions. Once the movement is under way, recruiting <pb facs="5423968_4_0241.jpg" n="4"/>officers can return to their regular duties, leaving the campaign to be conducted by the proper committees.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
