<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-16">Oct. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">First Polish Volunteers Depart for Training Camp</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-16">Oct. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST POLISH VOLUNTEERS DEPART FOR TRAINING CAMP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the solemn high mass held yesterday in Holy Trinity Church for the Polish Army, described in yesterday's issue of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, the volunteers were conducted back to the Polish Women's Alliance Hall, where the Citizens' Committee had prepared a farewell reception. Our young men sat down to well-laden tables and partook of God's abundance while representatives of Polish organizations and prominent Polish citizens spoke to the gathering. Among those present, we noted T. M. Helinski, president of the Polish Central Relief Committee, W. Szrojda, M. Perlowski, president of the Citizens' Committee, Mrs. M. Sakowski and Mrs. M. Milewski, members of the board of directors of the Polish National Alliance, Miss E. Napieralski, secretary-general of the Polish Women's Alliance, Lieutenant Skarzynski, Attorney Rybicki, H. Setmajer, secretary of the Polish Central Relief Committee, Mrs. A. Neuman, president of the Polish Women's Alliance, Mrs. Laudyn-Chrzanowski, editor of Glos Polek [Women's Voice], Mrs. Lipczynski of Grand Rapids, Michigan....the Reverend W. Zapala, John F. Smulski, and a great many <pb facs="5423968_4_0464.jpg" n="2"/>others. Almost everyone of the above-named individuals addressed the departing volunteers, and each speaker was rewarded with ovational applause.</p>
   <p>At this point it should be mentioned that the following contributions were made to make the trip to the training camp a pleasanter one for the recruits: The Women's Department of the Polish National Alliance offered twenty-five dollars for minor expenses, Teophil Stan donated two hundred cigars, and Kaczorowski supplied each of the men with cigarettes.</p>
   <p>Polish Clergy in Polish Army</p>
   <p>There was great enthusiasm among the volunteers when the Reverend Zapala announced in his address that Polish clergymen are also preparing to leave for the battle fronts together with the Polish soldiers. "There will be one Polish Chaplain for every eight hundred soldiers," he said. "Already there are twelve Polish-American priests ready to enter the service. We are only waiting <pb facs="5423968_4_0465.jpg" n="3"/>for the final approval of the Papal Delegate, with whom Bishop Rhode has been conferring upon this subject."</p>
   <p>It was about two o'clock when the banquet was brought to a conclusion and the gathering began to form ranks for a parade through the city to the railroad station. At two-thirty, the procession started, moving from the Polish Women's Alliance Building down Ashland Avenue to Washington Boulevard, then to La Salle Street, Monroe, and Dearborn, to the Dearborn Street Station.</p>
   <p>At the head of the parade rode four mounted policemen, followed by Perlowski, president of the Citizens' Committee, and Recruiting Officer Lieutenant Skarzynski. The American flag was carried by Kornaszewski. Then, in ranks of four, came the following: Casimir Zychlinski, [president of the Polish National Alliance], J. Chrzanowski, W. Szrojda, J. Magdziarz, [treasurer of the Polish National Alliance]....and others. These were followed by the administration of Circuit II, Polish Falcons' Alliance and fifty women members. Then came <pb facs="5423968_4_0466.jpg" n="4"/>Przybylski's orchestra and finally, the volunteers, under the command of Sergeants Schubert and Pieprzny. The rear was brought up by a great number of friends and relatives of the departing volunteers.</p>
   <p>The procession was given a tremendous ovation in the Loop. Throngs of people lined the streets, watching with interest the Polish volunteers who are leaving to train for the struggle with Germany. The placards carried by the volunteers were inscribed "Volunteers to the Polish Army," and these were enthusiastically cheered.</p>
   <p>When the parade arrived at the railroad station, the gathered throngs gave our brave volunteers an unusual ovation. They were leaving as befitted future heroes--light-hearted and with a strong determination to beat the Prussian and fight their way through to Polish soil.</p>
   <p>These first brave volunteers from Chicago departed on the one hundredth <pb facs="5423968_4_0467.jpg" n="5"/>anniversary of the death of Kosciusko. May the spirit of this great Pole lead them on to victory. May it give them strength to break the iron ring which the Germans have locked around Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
