<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-10">Aug. 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Manifestation at Pulaski Park</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0842</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0842.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-10">Aug. 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MANIFESTATION AT PULASKI PARK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although the weather man did not seem to favor yesterday's picnic, arranged for the benefit of the Library of the Polish National Alliance, nevertheless more than a thousand people gathered to participate in this annual social gathering, which this year reached the proportions of a national demonstration.</p>
   <p>At the entrance to the park notices were posted with the inscription, "No dancing in this park today". These notices, signed by the Arrangement Committee, were received with surprise, the more so since there was dancing at Kosciusko Park across the way. Here and there the people, gave audible expression to this surprise, until at last the speakers explained the reason for this stand on the part of the Committee.</p>
   <p>At five o'clock, Michael Kmieciak, chairman of the Library Department and director of the Alliance, addressed a few words to the people thanking them for attending the picnic and for contributing to the fund of the Library of the Polish National <pb facs="5423968_4_0843.jpg" n="2"/>Alliance. His speech over, Mr. Kmieciak introduced John F. Smulski as the next speaker. Mr. Smulski spoke tersely and, as always, well. At the outset he emphasided the fact that the present situation in Europe is too important, so far as Poland is concerned, for the Poles not to be interested in it. "Polish Emigration," said Mr. Smulski, "may not now stand about with folded arms. He who would not at this time do everything in his power to help his native land, would not only be a disloyal but also a degenerate son of his mother country."</p>
   <p>While Mr. Smulski delivered his address, several women took up a collection that yielded forty-eight dollars. After Smulski got through speaking, a medley of Polish songs was sung, followed by an intermission.</p>
   <p>The culminating point of the gathering was the address of Mr. C. Zychlinski, president of the Polish National Alliance, who spoke to the point but probably better than ever before. "Zychlinski," said those who have known him for many years, "was quite eloquent at the time and spoke with greater enthusiasm and conviction than ever before."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0844.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Dear Compatriots! Sisters and Brothers in the Alliance!" began the honorable speaker. "Many of you are no doubt surprised that there is no dancing today in this park for the duration of the picnic for the Library of the Polish National Alliance, because you have been attending these picnics for many years and know that there was always dancing. Nevertheless, today we are not going to dance, because while our brothers in Poland are dying from the sword and from starvation, when their cannons are playing funeral music for women and children, it is not fitting for us to dance. What is more, it is not fitting for us to be present where there is dancing. One Mother gave us birth. We are the children of one Polish Mother oppressed by chains, and we cannot, while those over there offer their blood and their lives to the moloch of war, enjoy ourselves as though we were indifferent to this. Because we are deeply cognizant of this important unusual moment, to which we have looked forward for centuries, in which Poland's invaders, rapacious vultures which, having torn our Mother Poland apart, and having divided her soil among themselves, have entered battle and have begun to murder each other. This is the moment foretold by Poland's poet-prophets. This is the moment about which Wispianski, in his "Wedding," said, 'Grab your horses, grab your guns, the <pb facs="5423968_4_0845.jpg" n="4"/>court of Wawel awaits you.' It is coming, and for this reason, we who have not been granted the privilege there across the sea to sacrifice our lives and goods on the greatest and most sacred altar, because it is the altar of the Homeland, should bring moral and financial aid to our fighting brothers."</p>
   <p>The speaker, having summarized the events which took place in Europe, beginning with the murder of the heir to the throne, answered then the question he himself had posed: With whom should we cast our lot? "With the Muscovites? With the Muscovite," repeated our honorable president, "whose throne is spattered with the blood of innocent brothers, with the Tsar, whose conscience is weighted down by the crime of the murdered Polish martyrs? Should we join him to whom the groaning of the murdered heroes of Poland and of those dying in prison dungeons was the sweetest music? "Or perhaps we should join the brutal and audacious Prussian, who tried to deprive Polish children of their native language, with him who erected a memorial like that of Wrzesnia [Translators note: Wrzesnia was the city in which between 600 and 700 Polish school children were executed en masse for singing the Polish anthem.] and Moabite to the eternal shame of the <pb facs="5423968_4_0846.jpg" n="5"/>nineteenth and twentieth centuries? (Applause.) Can we go along with the Prussian, who piece by piece, span by span, takes away Polish soil from its rightful owners?</p>
   <p>"Or perhaps we should join Austria, which, as they say, permitted the singing of Polish songs when it was convenient for her to do so? Would we forget that the Austrian government, headed then by the same ruler, stirred up brother against brother? Would we be supposed to forget the Galician matter? Was not this the Austrian governmen's affair?</p>
   <p>"We have not forgotten, because we may not forget. We must not join at this moment any one of our three annexers. We can only wait until the three robbers who have divided Poland among themselves wear out each other's strength. And then we can repay them for the imprisonment of centuries, for the shackles of our brothers, for the blood of the martyrs which fell upon the soil like dew, for the defamation of our mothers, wives, and sisters. Historical Nemesis is pursuing our annexers! Soon the hour of retribution will strike on history's clock. The mad game of Poland's annexers is drawing to its close. Everything <pb facs="5423968_4_0847.jpg" n="6"/>they have is falling apart, and the invisible hand of history writes in bloody letters: "Woe to you annexers-executioners woe! (Applause.) It was not granted to me, or to you, Sisters and Brothers, to be there, where, at any moment, the furious battle for the freedom of Poland will break out. It was not granted us to wash away the many sins which we have committed, often forgetting our Mother, with our blood, but we have the duty of bringing help when it is needed. Our brothers across the sea, if they are not already covering the battlefields with their bodies, pressed into service by the governments of the annexers, suffer hunger. Destitution knocks upon the doors of their cottages, this inseparable companion of the poorest in the nation. Let us help them! Let us ease their suffering! Let everyone give what he can, and let us not stop giving as long as there is need. We can afford it. None of us suffers hunger--none of us is homeless. In the name of oppressed Poland, in the name of our suffering brothers, I ask you, please, to contribute to the fund of the Department of Independence [of the P.N.A], which fund will not be used for party matters, but for truly national purposes. Let us all contribute, because Poland is the Mother of all of us and will gather all of us to herself, and give all of us the feeling of home. Let us forget anger, quarrels, parties, political camps and <pb facs="5423968_4_0848.jpg" n="7"/>platforms, and let us work in harmony as befits the loyal sons of the Homeland. Poland is a great thing, and in the face of a great thing it is unseemly to quarrel. So let us work harmoniously and influence others toward harmony in the name of resurrecting Independent Democratic Poland." (Applause.)</p>
   <p>While the president was delivering his address, another collection was taken up which yielded fifty-nine dollars and eighteen cents. Editor John Przyprawa spoke next summarizing events as they took place since the murder of the heir to the Austrian throne. "Historical necessities, "concluded Mr. Przyprawa, "cannot be changed by the knouts of the Tsar or the sentences of his sycophants. Neither the rape nor the audacity of the Prussian soldier, nor the false politics of the Austrian government in regard to the Polish nation can alter them. Neither Tsar Nicholas, proud William, nor Francis Joseph can still the loud voice of historical necessity, because the voice of historical necessity demands a free democratic Poland."</p>
   <p>On the motion of director Kmieciak, it was voted to send greetings to the Minister of War in Belgium for the brave stand of the Belgians and the victories gained.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0849.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"We, Poles of the city of Chicago, gathered at this mass meeting of the Library Department of the Polish National Alliance on August 9, 1914, resolve:</p>
   <p>"To send a cablegram to the Belgian nation, congratulating it on its victories over the Prussians, the eternal enemy of the Republic of Poland, sending it expressions of sincere friendship and encouragement to persevere in the defense of its Native land, Belgium. Long live free Belgium and France!"</p>
   <p>The public accepted this resolution with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>With the singing of "Poland is not lost!" and "God save Poland!" the meeting was brought to a close.6</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
