<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-12">Jan. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Our Co-Operative Movement</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Guaranty Mortgage and Security Corporation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1576</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1576.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-12">Jan. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CO-OPERATIVE MOVEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Guaranty Mortgage and Security Corporation</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago the annual meeting of shareholders in the Polish company, the Guaranty Mortgage and Security Corporation, well known in American circles as well as among Poles, took place in the Knights of Columbus hall downtown at 10 A.M. This corporation was organized many years ago by Mr. Peter Niemira and is located at 155 North Clark Street. The meeting was attended by a great number of shareholders and by the officers of the corporation. The chairman of the meeting was Mr. M. Szymczak, former president of the corporation, and the duties of the secretary were performed by Mr. Mielcarek. Officers of the corporation submitted detailed reports of the business, which were listened to with great interest and satisfaction. After expressive sentiments of appreciation to the retiring officers the shareholders elected Mr. Peter Niemira president, Mr. J. Martynowicz vice-president, Mr. T. Mielcarek secretary, Mr. Grzeszczyk assistant <pb facs="5423968_4_1577.jpg" n="2"/>secretary, and Mr. M. Szymczak treasurer.</p>
   <p>The meeting lasted until three o'clock in the afternoon. It was learned that the business is growing very satisfactorily in spite of the last depression, the effects of which were felt in the whole country; while other firms went bankrupt, this Polish corporation is doing good business, and future prospects are even brighter. The shareholders are justified in expecting larger profits from the prospective improvement in the economic condition of the country.</p>
   <p>In all fairness we must add that this firm also has suffered in the general business depression and by unfair competition. But because of efficient management and the unselfish devotion of its officers the company has successfully weathered the storm and is even able to show considerable profit. We should also mention that the legal matters are handled very successfully by the law firm of Gorman and Brundage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
