<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-07-01">July 1, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Poles at Jesuits College</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1462</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1462.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-07-01">July 1, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">POLES AT JESUITS COLLEGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We received the official report of Jesuits College for the year of 1890-91, from, which we are quoting the following, and correcting the last particulars, which appeared in our journal concerning Polish students attending that institution.</p>
   <p>The following fraternities established at that college and supervised by its professors have Poles among its offices:</p>
   <p>The Chrysostamian Debating Society</p>
   <p>The purpose of this association is to study literature and elocution. In that fraternity, the second censor of the second year is John G. Bednarek.</p>
   <p>The Students' library Association</p>
   <p>This library was founded to promote good literature. Already, it has two <pb facs="5423968_4_1463.jpg" n="2"/>thousand volumes. One of the censors of that association is John G. Bednarek.</p>
   <p>The Athletic and Game Room Association has John G. Bednarek'as its censor also.</p>
   <p>Last year, the college gave a few theatrical plays, and some of the actors were Polish students. On February 5, 1890, a play depicting a historical tragedy entitled "The Black Knight" was given by that institution which was staged at the Grand Opera House. In that production, John G. Bednarek played a very important role.</p>
   <p>On November 24, 1890, "the first Academic" of that school staged a production entitled "A Trip to Greece with Nepos as Our Guide." The invitation was recited by John Jendrzejak.</p>
   <p>On November 28, 1890, a production "The Greeks Visit the Romans, A.D. 170," at which J. S. Schultz played a piano solo and piano duet with another pianist.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1464.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following Poles attended this college:</p>
   <p>Bednarek, John G. Subject Poetry</p>
   <p>Cholewinski, Stan. P. Preparatory</p>
   <p>Jendrzejewski, John G. First Academic</p>
   <p>Klosowski, Edward A. Third Academic</p>
   <p>Kowalewski, Edward A. Third Academic</p>
   <p>Nawrocki, Anthony S. Third Academic</p>
   <p>Politowski, August A. Third Academic</p>
   <p>Schultz, Stephen J. Second Academic</p>
   <p>Szulerski, Albert G. Third Academic</p>
   <p>Zalewski, Ambrose M. Third Academic</p>
   <p>The following awards were presented to the Polish students at the end of the school year: John G. Bednarek received a gold watch as the first award for the best Latin composition. John G. Jendrzejek, was especially distinguished for the best marks in Latin (in all courses) as the first after the one who was awarded with a gold watch. The same John G. Jendrzejek was also distinguished for the best marks in mathematics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1465.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The following Polish students received book awards: John G. Bednarek, second award for Latin, Greek, and mathematics; he also received honorable mention for history and chemistry.</p>
   <p>Stephen J. Schultz, honorable mention for Greek, and a first award for penmanship.</p>
   <p>August A. Politowski received honorable mention for religion and Latin, second award for English, history, geography, and orthography, and first award for arithmetic and penmanship.</p>
   <p>Anthony S. Nawrocki, first award for Latin, and honorable mention for penmanship.</p>
   <p>Edward A. Kowalewski, honorable mention for religion.</p>
   <p>Ambrose M. Zalewski, honorable mention for penmanship.</p>
   <p>Besides these, honorable mention was given to Anthony Nawrocki and Aug. Politowski, for the German language as extra curricular.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1466.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The following Polish students received honorable mention for extra good behavior: John G. Bednarek, St. P. Cholewinski, John G. Jendrzejek, Ed. A. Kowalewski, Anthony S. Nawrocki, Aug. A. Politowski, Stephen I. Schultz, and Albert G. Szulerski.</p>
   <p>Polish students also distinguished themselves by high marks. It is understood that one hundred is the highest mark, but no one has ever received it at that college.</p>
   <p>John G. Bednarek--91</p>
   <p>Stan. P. Cholewinski--93</p>
   <p>John G. Jendrzejek--99</p>
   <p>Edw. A. Kowalewski--88</p>
   <p>Anthony S. Nawrocki--80</p>
   <p>Aug. A. Politowski--99</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
