<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><date when="1910-01-28">Jan. 28, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial.)</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Use of Tobacco by Children Becomes Health Problem]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><date when="1910-01-28">Jan. 28, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial.)</title><title level="a" type="sub">[USE OF TOBACCO BY CHILDREN BECOMES HEALTH PROBLEM]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Juvenile Protective Association distributed a letter to all newspapers, and to all leading citizens, in which they plead for support in the fight against the use of tobacco by children. They point out that, to smoke a pipe, cigar or cigarette is a crazy and useless habit. Tobacco injures one's health, and its continued use is similar to suicide. Tobacco makes one a useless creature, and a burden to society instead of an industrious wide - awake, and upright citizen. The nicotine in tobacco destroys clean thought, ambition and energy. It blurrs one's intelligence, and wrecks the nerves.</p>
   <p>Even a strong person, after continued use of tobacco, becomes an idiot, unable to feel or think. An appeal to parents to discourage and influence their children against the use of tobacco has also been broadcast. A warning against the sale of tobacco in any from, to minors, has been sent to all dealers and stores.</p>
   <p>A young boy smoking a cigar or cigarette is a pathetic sight; and he is unaware of the harmful results. The nicotine poisons his system, and he is doomed to an early death. It is our belief, that this movement is a just one, and should receive the support of all good citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
