<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-21">Apr. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Peter Kiolbassa Retires from Office</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-21">Apr. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">MR. PETER KIOLBASSA RETIRES FROM OFFICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday Mr. Peter Kiolbassa formally retired from office as city treasurer and made a final accounting of the funds under his care to his successor. These amounted to $1,884,680 in cash, aside from special funds. Besides this, Mr. Kiolbassa returned $43,991 to the treasury as the remainder from accumulated interest on city funds. The return of this money aroused considerable comment. As is generally known, the interest that accrues on the city's funds deposited in various banks, amounting sometimes to over a hundred thousand dollars, heretofore belonged to the city treasurer. In the campaign before his election, Mr. Kiolbassa promised that he would turn the interest back to the treasury. In spite of the sarcasm of an unfriendly press, he proved himself honest and honorable and kept his promise.</p>
   <p>In the course of his two years in office, the accumulated interest amounted <pb facs="5423968_4_0085.jpg" n="2"/>to $106,991.52. Of this sum, Mr. Kiolbassa spent, for his own salary and the upkeep of his office, $63,000, in this way saving the city that amount of money. The remaining $43,991.52 was received yesterday by the new treasurer. Thus, Mr. Kiolbassa has presented to the citizens of Chicago the sum of $106.991.52. It is an exceptional action and the first of its kind in the history of Chicago. Mr. Kiolbassa has earned the respect of all honest people and is a source of pride to all the Poles in America. In truth, Mr. Kiolbassa promised the voters that he would do this. It is well known, however, that political promises are rarely made to be kept. Of course, there were many people, even honest people, who doubted that Mr. Kiolbassa would keep his promise. Only God knows how many of these people would have acted as he did were they in his place. His promise was the cause of constant attacks against him by the unfriendly press during his two years in office. Today--of his own free will, for nothing compelled him to do so--Mr. Kiolbassa made good his word because of his own inherent honesty. By returning to the city treasury money which was legally his own, he silenced his enemies and brought new glory to the Polish name.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0086.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>All the American newspapers are paying homage to our Mr. Kiolbassa. Where other city treasurers have left office rich, Mr. Kiolbassa left without material gain, but with his head high--an honest man.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
