<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-02">Mar. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a"/><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_0636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-02">Mar. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite the pacifistic orgy now <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the country, despite the Teutonic propaganda pushed to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of heights of audacity, despite the silly intrigues of the childish and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the United States will have to come to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> conflict with the Germans on both land and sea. And the sooner this <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the better it will be for the [United] States.</p>
   <p>It is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> understandable that Congress--at present the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for the performances of individuals who do not understand the position of this country in world politics, or are absolutely <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> capable of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> American interests of today and the future, or yield to pernicious influence calculated to undermine the [United] States--should hesitate to grant the President the power and authority to declare war. In the face of this hesitation and cowardly tying of the administration's hands, the entering into armed conflict with the Germans <pb facs="5423968_4_0637.jpg" n="2"/>will be accomplished step by step. From <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> we have passed on first to a neutrality which favored the Allies, then to a neutrality which actually disapproved of the Teutons, and now to a phase of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> neutrality which in the present circumstances <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> other than preparation for war with Germany.</p>
   <p>The transition from a state of peace to a state of war is a hard, tedious, and to a certain extent painful process for such a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> mass of people as compose the United States. Before the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of declaring war on the German Kaiser can be reached, and especially before America can transport to the European continent new, suddenly formed, but nevertheless powerful American armies, a certain evolution <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> take place in the mind of the average American, who up to the present has been <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> tradesman par excellence and who in addition has befogged the horizon of his political thinking with the fallacy of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>onroe's little formula.</p>
   <p>At the present time we are in the full swing of this evolution, embollished, <pb facs="5423968_4_0638.jpg" n="3"/>for the purpose of variety in the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, by the mad antics of all sorts of Bryans, simple-minded little women of the type of the very worthy Jane Addams, and the sallies of all sorts of "peoples' spokesmen" a la Kennedy of Hearst, spokesmen who misuse their "ideas" or money to exploit human ignorance, and who serve a foreign cause which is inimical to this country by playing on the low instincts of the ignorant and disorganized mob.</p>
   <p>Gradually this greatly desired change in the thinking processes of the American people is taking place. Gradually the people <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> opening their <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in order to look into the face of reality. Gradually illusions and prejudices on the necessity, advantages, and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of a "friendship" between Germany and the United States are beginning to vanish. And the Germans themselves, who no longer have anything to lose and who are throwing away their masks and no longer conceal their hatred of the United States, and the American people, are helping this evolution along.</p>
   <p>The last speech of the German Chancellor and the hostile outbursts of the <pb facs="5423968_4_0639.jpg" n="4"/>party leaders in the Reichstag should convince even the blindest of the peace advocates that the Germans are not pleased with the attitude of the United States and feel hatred toward it, since the Germans believe that in this war America is placing obstacles in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> path. Peaceful and neutral America has become an irreconcilable foe to the Germans, and the Teutons will never forgive these offenses. The <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> political figures in Germany are already saying that barring England, the United States is Germany's worst enemy. This is how all Germans feel today, and they voice this feeling as loudly as possible. And on the morrow following the war, remembering this, all Germans will want <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <p>And so, from now on, German politics will have to treat America as an enemy, unless the outcome of the war completely changes the political situation in the world. From now on the country of the German Kaiser also becomes the decided enemy of the United States, and its complete annihilation must constitute an indispensable condition of America's future safety.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0641.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Should the Germans come out of the present war victorious, the United States would have to face a very greet danger on the part of this Teutonic enemy, who after defeating the Allies would become the greatest military, political, and economic power in the world. But even a Germany not wholly victorious, not completely weakened and made forever harmless, would threaten the safety and vital interests of the [United] States by entering into alliances with neutral competitors of Uncle Sam, such as Japan and Mexico.</p>
   <p>The destruction of England's sea power would give absolute control of the Atlantic to Germany and control of the Pacific to Japan. The United States would be isolated from the rest of the world, threatened at any moment by an attack from Germany on the and Japan on the west. Therefore, the destruction or even the neutralization of the sea power so successfully extended all over the world by Great Britain, the natural ally and guardian of America, would destroy the sovereign position of the United States, burying for centuries the prosperity, development, and future security of this country.</p>
   <!-- 5423968_4_0640 omitted, duplicate of 5423968_4_0641 -->
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0642.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>In circumstances such as these, the United States has no alternative but to arm as quickly as possible, in order to be able to throw all its power and splendid resources openly and mightily into the Allied camp, to defend England's power on the seas with all its strength and in general not to neglect anything that might help to destroy military Germany today or in the future.</p>
   <p>During the World War or after it the United States can proceed only at the Allies' side and always against the Germans.</p>
   <p>In all calmness and with due consideration, in the belief in the justice of the cause they are defending, the American people must prepare themselves energetically for the inevitable war, casting aside as manifestations of cowardice, ineptitude, weakness, or even treason all efforts to maintain peace and to keep us out of the war. Congress cannot hesitate much longer and must not paralyze the President's wise initiative, thus exposing the whole future and honor of this republic to danger. And when finally the United States does enter the war, it will have to be a victorious war, a war conducted at the side of the Allies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_0643.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The great majority of the American people already understand this, and the local Daily News asserts that one cannot conduct a war with an external enemy on paper or in some spirit world, and warns against the statements now being made in Washington that the United States would best defend its interests and honor by keeping out of the war which the Central Powers are now waging against the Allies. This paper justly concludes that:</p>
   <p>"Such a political policy would be ruinous for the United States, because it would lead to a scandalous shedding of blood and wasteof money, and a piling up of misfortunes for the future. Therefore, in complete alliance with those countries which are now fighting Germany, the American people must insist that every effort be made to put an end to Germany's submarine madness. With such an alliance the United States can proceed with full confidence and power toward a just and lasting peace."</p>
   <p>Therefore, even for the United States, the only road toward peace leads through war. And a peace without victory would be madness--merely an unfortunate parody <pb facs="5423968_4_0644.jpg" n="8"/><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
