<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-07">Nov. 7, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Health and Sanitation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_4_1350</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1350.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I M (Lithuanian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-07">Nov. 7, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">HEALTH and SANITATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The English Medical Association began a series of lectures on Saturday, November 4. Dr Hultgen; who practices in the stockyards, lectured on tuberculosis. This is the gist of his lecture:</p>
   <p>Tuberculosis has been known since ancient times. The Greeks and Romans were familiar with this disease though they called it by another name. It was not discovered until the nineteenth century that tuberculosis was contagious and was caused by little organisms called baccili. Many doctors sacrificed their lives in the study of the causes and methods of curing this white plague.</p>
   <p>Sanitariums, which are scattered throughout the country, render a truly great service; nevertheless, they alone are not sufficient in combating this disease. We have to turn entire cities into sanitaria. We should have, first of all, <pb facs="5423968_4_1351.jpg" n="2"/>fresh air, wholesome food, and clean and comfortable houses. Science, prescriptions, medicines, even the very best, will not help, if the victim is forced to live in a neighborhood full of smoke, to eat unwholesome food, to live in a damp, small and badly constructed house.</p>
   <p>The neighborhood of the stockyards is principally inhabited by Poles and Lithuanians. There one finds the areas where garbage from the entire city is dumped. These give forth terrible odors; day and night this district is covered with smoke. And, what is worse, in these areas where the garbage is dumped, our Polish mothers roam with their children, searching for bits of fuel, food or clothing. The homes there are poor beyond description. Saloons, one next to the other, are always crowded. They absorb the larger portion of the weekly pay.</p>
   <p>How can one talk of sanitary conditions here when the state of affairs at the stock yards is so horrible. The work at the stockyards is exhausting, and <pb facs="5423968_4_1352.jpg" n="3"/>the pay is meager, barely $10 per week. After ten hours or repulsive work, the laborers go to the saloons, wasting there, their money and health. Not only are they under singing their own health, but also that of their wives and children. Here we see a great source of the white plague, and we must combat it with all our strength. We will conquer it only when we have remedied these deplorable living conditions.</p>
   <p>For us Poles this lecture is important because it depicts us on slides and photographs in actual life, emphasizing the fact that these are Poles who are dirty, exhausted, and drunk. The cause for all this, all this, according to Dr. Kultgen, is the environment. Because the river is full of disease germs, and garbage is dumped near human habitations; and because the pay is eagre and these people are not steadily employed, he sees only one remedy--to change the environment. In order to avoid this horrible disease of tuberculosis, one must first make the surroundings healthful, and give people the chance to work and live hygienically.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_4_1353.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Dr. Hultgen declared at the outset that he was not a socialist, but that he earnestly desires this [change to take place] in the name of humanity and Christianity.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Felicya H. Cienciara.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
