<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-03-05">Mar. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Meeting of the Spolek Starych Ceskych Osadniku</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-03-05">Mar. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF THE SPOLEK STARYCH CESKYCH OSADNIKU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Spolek Starych Ceskych Osadniku (Bohemian Old Settlers' Society) held its fifteenth annual meeting last night. The meeting hall, U Libuse, was filled with members and their friends. Practically all those men and women who were influential in directing the general development of the great Bohemian colony in Chicago belong to the Spolek. For these old pioneers we have a feeling of profound gratitude. It was they who struggled so successfully through the initial hardships; who cleared the way for the material advancement of the Bohemian element; and who laid the foundation for our cultural and social life in this city. The large attendance at last night's meeting was new evidence of their great popularity.</p>
   <p>The meeting was presided over by Mr. Ant. T. Pergler who opened with a brief but fervent address. The secretary, Mr. Frank Stejskal, read the minutes of the last meeting, whereupon the election of directors took place. Elected were: Mr. V. Pospisil, W. Stuchlik, Mr. J. Cizkovsky, <pb facs="5418478_6_1445.jpg" n="2"/>Mrs. A. Kostka, Mrs. B. Matasek, and Mrs. M. Pavlik; all of them were chosen by acclamation. The president cordially thanked the outgoing directors: Messrs Fr. Fucik, J. M. Kralovec, and V. Topinka, who also received a stormy ovation from those assembled.</p>
   <p>Thereafter a report was presented showing the way in which the Spolek conducts its charitable work, special reference being made to the support of the Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage). During the fifteen years of the Spolek's existence, the Ceska Utulna received donations of $2,650. The Spolek's contributions to the Catholic Orphanage in Lisle amounted to $850. May this splendid example of our pioneers find ample emulation not only among our lodges and societies, but also among individuals who have reached such a degree of financial independence that they are well able to make occasional contributions to these important charitable institutions. President Pergler closed the meeting by urging the incoming directors to perform their duties conscientiously so that in the future the Spolek may be able to take good care of all the <pb facs="5418478_6_1446.jpg" n="3"/>obligations which it has so gladly taken upon itself.</p>
   <p>The successful evening was concluded with an entertaining program of comical scenes by our well-known couple, Rudolf and Kamila Suva, who are visiting here among friends.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
