<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-26">Sept. 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Transfers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0784</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0784.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-26">Sept. 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE TRANSFERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Vaclav and Katerina Lala sold the building on the southeast corner of 50th Street and Indiana Avenue to Elizabeth Hackel for $75,000. As down payment, they accepted the residence at 938 Ridge Avenue in Evanston and $16,000 cash. There is a mortgage of $43,000 on the Indiana Avenue building.</p>
   <p>William T. Sullins sold the property on Carmen Avenue, 250 feet east of Leclaire Avenue, north front, 25 by 125 1/2 feet, to Michal Steffek for $1,500.</p>
   <p>James S. Ashby sold the property on 46th Place, 274 feet west of Western Avenue, south front, 26 by 125 feet, to Peter Bezemek for $350.</p>
   <p>Frank Kral sold the property on 47th Street, northeast corner of 47th Court, south front, 32 by 125 feet, to James Vasumpaur for $400.</p>
   <p>Mary Swanson sold the property on Honore Street, northeast corner of 53rd <pb facs="5418478_6_0785.jpg" n="2"/>Street, west front, 24 by 125 feet, to Karel Svec for $1,000.</p>
   <p>The McAvoy Brewing Company sold the property on Robey Street, 200 feet south of 53rd Street, west front, 25 by 116 feet, to Charles Proskovec for $10.</p>
   <p>Thos. P. Evans sold the property on Sacramento Avenue, 46 feet north of 53rd Street, 24 by 125 feet, to Thomas Tuma for $235.</p>
   <p>Vaclav Svejda sold the property on Winchester Avenue, 145 feet south of 50th Street, west front, 24 by 124 1/2 feet, to John Cvrk for $3,700.</p>
   <p>Pat. Gillehooley sold the property on Winchester Avenue, 100 feet south of 53rd Street, east front, 25 by 116 feet, to Karel Konicek for $575.</p>
   <p>Ida W. Hoffman sold the property on Hastings Street, 246 feet west of Laflin <pb facs="5418478_6_0786.jpg" n="3"/>Street, south front, 24 by 124 feet, to Kam. Novacek for $3,000.</p>
   <p>Jos. Karvan sold the property on Kedzie Avenue, 180 feet north of 27th Street, east front, 25 by 125 feet, to Bohumil Siegl for $3,350.</p>
   <p>Julia Fiala sold the property on Spaulding Avenue, 150 feet south of 27th Street, east front, 25 by 125 feet, to Jos. Marousek for $2,800.</p>
   <p>Vaclav Kirian sold the property on Turner Avenue, 225 feet north of 24th Street, east front, 25 by 125 feet, to John Kazda for $2,310.</p>
   <p>Josef Lala sold the property on Turner Avenue, 300 feet south of 30th Street, east front, 25 by 125 feet, to Albert Kratochvil for $2,600.</p>
   <p>Josef J. Madej sold the property on 20th Street, 146 feet east of Rockwell Street, north front, 24 by 89 feet, to Jan Cep for $1,830.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0787.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Antonie Kolar sold the property on 21st Street, 350 feet west of Oakley Avenue, north front, 25 by 126 feet, to James J. Kolar for $1.</p>
   <p>Susan R. Weare sold the property in Morton Park, Land and Improvement Company's Addition, block 10, lots 4, 5, and 6, to Vaclav Kobzina for $10.</p>
   <p>Anton Havlik sold the property in Cicero, 22nd Street Boulevard Subdivision, lots 45 and 46, to Frank Nemecek for $1,200.</p>
   <p>William A. Barlow sold the property in Morton Park, Land and Improvement Company's Addition, block 7, lots 8 and 9, to Thom. Hrodet for $1.</p>
   <p>Emil B. Camsky sold the property in Cicero, Chicago Title and Trust Company's Subdivision, part of lot 14, lots 15, and 16, etc., to Vaclav Spachman for $1,900.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0788.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Marie Riha sold the property on 51st Street, southwest corner of Hoyne Avenue, north front, 25 by 126 feet, to Bedrich Happ for $2,100.</p>
   <p>Felix B. Janovsky sold the property on Rockwell Street, 174 feet north of 52nd Street, west front, 37 1/2 by 175 1/2 feet, to Frank Svoboda for $10.</p>
   <p>Vac. Marek sold the property on Cornelia Street, 309 feet west of Western Avenue, north front, 24 by 124 1/2 feet, to Fred. Mrak for $10.</p>
   <p>Nelson Weaver sold the property on 40th Court, 56 feet south of 18th Street, east front, 25 by 120 feet, to Annie Hauser for $2,300.</p>
   <p>E. A. Cummings sold the property on 50th Court, 212 feet north of Augusta Street, east front, 30 by 124 feet, to Charles E. Vodicka for $920.</p>
   <p>Edward Nelson sold the property on Kammerling Avenue, 67 feet east of 42nd Avenue, south front, 29 by 123 1/2 feet, to Frank Pesek for $6,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0789.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Christina Dermody sold the property in Cicero, M. and H.'s Subdivision, block 8, lot 8, etc., to Josef Novotny for $350.</p>
   <p>Thos. J. Hruby sold the property in Morton Park, B. and B.'s Addition, block 6, lot 26, etc., to Frank Losos for $600.</p>
   <p>Carl A. Carlson sold the property in Cicero, Baker's Subdivision, block 9, lot 9, to Vaclav Bicek for $1.</p>
   <p>Simon Radmitzer sold the property in Morton Park, B. and B.'s Addition, block 11, lots 13 and 14, to John Karlovsky for $10.</p>
   <p>Morris L. Greeley sold the property in Berwyn, Greeley's Addition, block 5, lot 26, etc., to Joe L. Novak for $350.</p>
   <p>Frank G. Hajicek sold the property in the Morton Park Land Association's Subdivision, <pb facs="5418478_6_0790.jpg" n="7"/>block 13, lot 48, to Vincent Doubek for $265.</p>
   <p>Wm. Kabat sold the property in Cicero, Rose's Subdivision, part of lot 50, etc., to Chares Divis for $400.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
