<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-09">Jan. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A New Year's Gift to the Bohemian Nation</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Successful Agitation for the Ceske Narodni Zdruzeni in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1280</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1280.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-09">Jan. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW YEAR'S GIFT TO THE BOHEMIAN NATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Successful Agitation for the Ceske Narodni Zdruzeni in America</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The movement for the independence of the Bohemian nation is forging ahead irresistibly. The proof of this statement is evidenced by the activity seen in the Ceske Narodni Zdruzeni (Bohemian National Union of America) whose members (of the local union) arranged a collection among friends with whom they came in contact, personally or by letter.</p>
   <p>Today many new members of our national organization both men and women owe their membership to the serious work of our union members, who can look upon their work with the greatest satisfaction, because without this activity and propaganda the organization could not go on.</p>
   <p>We cannot at this time acknowledge all contributions received. For the present we will print the first list, received by mail, of the names of contributors and the amounts donated; new lists are piling up every day.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1281.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It has also been impossible for us to include a list of those contributors who had sent one-dollar bills for Czech national stamps.</p>
   <p>Among the long list of names of contributors we miss many of our prominent countrymen; but let us hope that, before the close of this campaign, we will hear from them.</p>
   <p>We have not listed the records of mass contributions, as for instance the collection of the Bohemian Tailors' Union, which is an example for others to follow; especially, this refers to our more well-to-do countrymen who up to the moment have not responded.</p>
   <p>The contributions and donations are not listed according to our contribution lists, but in order of the amounts donated, because printing the lists in this form lessens the labors of the editorial staff in the newspaper offices, and also the work of the compositors.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1282.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Surely every countryman will be satisfied to see in print the amount he has donated, with his name directly below.</p>
   <p>The Ceske Narodni Zdruzeni most heartily extends its gratitude to all donors and all collectors of contributions, and especially does it wish to thank the very modest workers who, for many long days, prepared letters for mailing with subscription lists and national stamps enclosed, and who still are busily so doing, which of course deserves the highest commendation.</p>
   <p>More work is still in the making; many more countrymen need to be awakened to perform the many tasks to which they have obligated themselves.</p>
   <p>The following collectors deserve especial mention: Antonin Wagner, J.J. Nosek (a departed worker), J. Florian, Karel Smrha, Vaclav Vermuch, Frantisek Masek, Josef Kaspar, Frantisek vojta, and Josef Hejl.</p>
   <p>Three of our countrymen donated $50 each.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1283.jpg" n="4"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Five have donated</cell>
     <cell>$25</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Thirteen have donated</cell>
     <cell>$10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>One has donated</cell>
     <cell>$ 7</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Twenty-six have donated</cell>
     <cell>$ 5</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Ten have donated</cell>
     <cell>$ 4</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>One has donated</cell>
     <cell>$ 2.40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>One has donated</cell>
     <cell>$ 2.30</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Eleven have donated</cell>
     <cell>$ 2</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>One hundred and ten have donated</cell>
     <cell>$.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>One has donated</cell>
     <cell>$.40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Two have donated</cell>
     <cell>$.35</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Eight have donated</cell>
     <cell>.30</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>One hundred and eleven have donated</cell>
     <cell>.25</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Forty have donated</cell>
     <cell>.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>One has donated</cell>
     <cell>.15</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Forty have donated</cell>
     <cell>.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Five have donated</cell>
     <cell>.05</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Donations to date</cell>
     <cell>$707.35</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>To all of the donors and collectors we extend our most hearty thanks.</p>
   <p>All who have donated more than one dollar become members of the Ceske Narodni Zdruzeni, and may attend the meetings of our local, held every second and fourth Monday of each month, in the Vojta Maprstek school.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1284.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Membership cards will be issued to all members who have sent in their addresses. All others are requested to apply for their cards at the office of the Ceske Narodni Zdruzeni, on the third floor, 3639 West 26th Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
