<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-08">Aug. 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Death Finds an Overabundant Crop on "Eastland"</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, four column-third of a page, showing a high tombstone, with the inscription "Nasi Cesi", (Our Bohemians) and the date of July 24, 1915; on the stone a weeping angel leans. a huge cemetery is in the background; dark skies, and setting sun. Over the picture the word "Eastland" is written.]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-08">Aug. 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">DEATH FINDS AN OVERABUNDANT CROP ON "EASTLAND"</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, four column-third of a page, showing a high tombstone, with the inscription "Nasi Cesi", (Our Bohemians) and the date of July 24, 1915; on the stone a weeping angel leans. A huge cemetery is in the background; dark skies, and setting sun. Over the picture the word "Eastland" is written.]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first fairly complete list of identified victims of the terrible catastrophe, the greatest ever to occur in Bohemian-America follows:</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Two hundred and thirty-six names, ages, and addresses in alphabetical order, are omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>It was two weeks ago yesterday when the whole of Chicago was horrified by the terrible news that the Steamship "Eastland" sank, or rather keeled, on Chicago River, at the North Clark Street bridge. The vessel carried over twenty-five <pb facs="5418478_6_0274.jpg" n="2"/>hundred passengers, participants in an excursion arranged by the Hawthorne Club to Michigan City, Indiana. This news was particularly shocking in districts adjacent to the shops of the Western Electric Company, because it was in these districts that there lived a large number of the members of that Club, composed of employees of that firm, who joined the excursion with their families, relatives, and friends. The news was a terrible blow not only to hundreds of Bohemian families in Cicero, Illinois, but also in New Tabor, Lawndale, Bohemian California, Pilsen, Town of Lake, and other Bohemian residential districts from where so many of our people, mostly young and in excellent health, justifying the rosiest hopes for the future, joined the excursion.</p>
   <p>The catastrophe cost the lives of almost one thousand people, who are now identified, of whom two hundred and fifty are our people; people living in the Bohemian districts of Chicago. Our colony will never fully recover from this disaster. It spent a full week in our cemeteries where caskets were laid alongside each other in fresh graves. In more than one instance, whole families were thus interred.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
