<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-08-23">Aug. 23, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Demonstration of the United Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-08-23">Aug. 23, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">DEMONSTRATION OF THE UNITED SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United Societies for Personal Freedom have done much good work up to the present in the field of personal freedom and citizens' rights. They have often barred the road to fanatics who seek to oppress the masses; they are working for equitable taxation of large corporations, and lower taxes of the less fortunate citizens. The United Societies are arranging a great demonstration for next Sunday at Forest Park. This demonstration is to be turned into a camp for all friends of personal freedom.</p>
   <p>The Bohemians are well represented in the United Societies for Personal Freedom, and are the most active workers in the organization. The Bohemian representatives take special interest in all discussions and decisions of these societies. The Attendance of the Bohemians at next Sunday's demonstration is awaited with great interest and will form a criterion for all like demonstrations held in the future. Our countrymen will be even more anxious to attend the demonstration because a fine program of entertainment has been <pb facs="5418478_6_1479.jpg" n="2"/>arranged for the day. The program will include speeches by prominent citizens and many other entertaining events.</p>
   <p>Speeches will be made by Mayor Carter H. Harrison, former Congressman H. S. Boutell, Jiri Landa, chairman of the United Societies for Personal Freedom, and the secretary of the same societies, our own Alderman Anton J. Cermak. The admission of twenty-five cents entitles the guest to all the activities and entertainments during the day. The park opens at one o'clock in the afternoon. As is well known the United Societies collect no dues from its members, and the officers function without pay; nevertheless the expense is quite considerable for rent must be paid and office upkeep must be considered. The proceeds of next Sunday's demonstration will be applied for those purposes. Whether the profit be large or small depends upon the interest shown in us next Sunday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
