<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-10">July 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Meritorious Work</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-10">July 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MERITORIOUS WORK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are pointing out specifically that the name should read Ceskoslovansky Pomocny Vybor (Czechoslav Aid Committee), and not Ceskoslovensky (Czechoslovak). This mistake occurs frequently.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslav Aid Committee held a meeting last night. Since the United States has entered the war, the agenda of the Committee has naturally expanded considerably. The Committee was created immediately after the great demonstration meeting in Pilsen Brewery Park on the occasion of the declaration of war on Serbia by Austria-Hungary. The Czech National Alliance was founded later.</p>
   <p>The Committee is quietly and steadily performing the various tasks which it has taken upon its shoulders: Support and relief for the suffering, the wounded, and the sick; for the widows and orphans; and for maimed soldiers. Czechs and Slovaks comprise the majority of those receiving aid.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0095.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Special attention was given to Slavs who had been forced into the armies of the Central Powers and then taken prisoners by the Allies. These men were released, and joined either the Allied armies or the Czechoslovak Army in France or Russia. Books, newspapers, and many other useful articles, were sent to the prison camps; the value of these gifts amounted to thousands of dollars. This work is being continued. The Committee of the Czech National Alliance contributed several thousand dollars, from which clothing and, especially, smokers' supplies were bought for our boys--mostly for those in Serbia and Russia. Our soldiers in France also receive our support whenever the demand arises.</p>
   <p>Five hundred dollars was sent recently to Paris for widows, orphans, and maimed soldiers. Many members of the Committee contributed out of their own pockets.</p>
   <p>The American Red Cross is to be fitted out with heavy ambulances, each costing $2,400. The Bohemian National Cemetery contributed $300, and $1,500 has <pb facs="5418478_6_0096.jpg" n="3"/>already been pledged among us, so that the entire cost of one ambulance will soon be handed over to the Red Cross. The ambulance donated by the Czechs will not bear any sign showing the name of the donor. The element of satisfaction for the Czechs will rest in the fact that they have fulfilled what they consider a beautiful duty.</p>
   <p>It was stated in the meeting that all official formalities involving the state laws and the license for collecting contributions have been complied with. The organization received its charter in August, 1914, as the "Czechoslav Aid Committee". It is composed of various associations which are members just like any individual member. Every person of our nationality can become a member by paying two dollars. Associations, clubs, etc., pay a minimum "gift" of five dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
