<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-30">Jan. 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">From Our Public Institutions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0725</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0725.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-30">Jan. 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR PUBLIC INSTITUTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Illinois certainly is not among the last in the number of state institutions which are, in the true sense of the word, benevolent.</p>
   <p>We call attention to the great number of houses of correction, state institutions for the feeble-minded, and the many charitable institutions, that have undertaken the task of lessening the misery of the less fortunate among us.</p>
   <p>There are institutions which take care of the orphans, and many others which do work along different lines.</p>
   <p>We very seldom hear about the activities of these institutions. They should be publicized much more than they are because of the work they are doing for the benefit of mankind.</p>
   <p>The public may obtain all the information it desires by getting in touch with <pb facs="5418478_6_0726.jpg" n="2"/>the State Charitable Commission and the State psycopathic institution, which jointly publish a monthly magazine, under the direction of Mr. A. L. Bowen, managing secretary of the State Charitable Commission at Springfield, Illinois, or they may write Mr. Fred J. Kern, President of the State Commission, in Springfield, or to Dr. Singer, Superintendent of the Psycopathic Institute at Kankakee, Illinois. In this publication are outlined the activities of our institutions; there are many interesting statistical records, and reports on rare individual cases.</p>
   <p>We have been able to get a copy of the above-named publication dated December 31, 1915, and our attention was attracted to pages 20 and 21 where may be seen the tabulated records of inmates of our many institutions, the number of people representing the different nationalities in Cook County, with the number of boys held as prisoners in these corrective institutions.</p>
   <p>These tabulated records show that, according to the last census, taken three years ago by the coroner's office, there are two hundred and fifty <pb facs="5418478_6_0727.jpg" n="3"/>thousand Czechs living in Cook County, and that to the end of the year just four Czech boys were classed as inmates of a penal institution.</p>
   <p>Czechs, are one of eleven nationalities living in Cook County. The Czechs have the smallest showing of youthful delinquents of these nationalities. The Irish, of whom there are a little over sixty thousand in Cook County, are third from the top in delinquency, showing forty-nine youthful inmates in our corrective homes; so that it is evident from the perusal of these tables that the Czech people living in America need not be classed with the undesirables, but, on the contrary, the Czechs living in Cook County are people of whom the United States, and especially the State of Illinois, may well be proud.</p>
   <p>Dr. George A. Zeller , ex-superintendent of the institution for the feeble-minded in Peoria, Illinois, reports an outstanding incident relative to the behavior of one of the inmates, a countryman, Petr Dudena.</p>
   <p>Visitors at the institution's cemetery reported a number of graves partly <pb facs="5418478_6_0728.jpg" n="4"/>opened, and the superintendent ordered a watch to be placed there to guard the premises. The watchman surprised the inmate, Petr Dudena, in the act of opening another grave.</p>
   <p>Dr. Zeller ordered an investigation, and it was found that Petr Dudena's wife whom he dearly loved, had died, and he had tried to find her remains among the cemetery lots. Thus the so-called mystery was explained.</p>
   <p>.....Dr. Zeller was so impressed with the plight of poor Petr Dudena that when Dudena died he had a cross erected and placed on Petr Dudena's grave reading: "To the Memory of Petr Dudena and His Wife."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
