<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-17">Mar. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Who Will Head Czech Chicago?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-17">Mar. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHO WILL HEAD CZECH CHICAGO?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If Czech Chicago, the third city in the world with relation to Czecha population, should decide upon a mayor of its own--who would receive that distinction?</p>
   <p>This question will be answered at the bazaar sponsored by the Czech National Alliance of Czech Catholics, which will be held the second and third weeks of next May. This contest will surpass anything ever attempted by our group. It will even surpass the glamour of the election of a queen for last year's bazaar.</p>
   <p>The next bazaar promises to become the most lavish national event in our history, for all propitious elements are combining to help us obtain that purpose. The most sublime among these is the struggle for the liberation of the old homeland, for it has united all parties and strata of our Czech Chicago. By the same token, the contest at the bazaar is to be regarded as the climax of the spirit of <pb facs="5418478_6_1186.jpg" n="2"/>sacrifice and patriotic enthusiasm in behalf of our motherland and our suffering brothers.</p>
   <p>Who is going to become "mayor"--and we hasten to onlarge--or "mayoress" of the capital of Czech America? It would not have been possible to put this question to our people sometime ago, for there were two camps. A "mayor" elected by one would not have been recognized by the other. Things are different today. Our people have followed the example of heroic France, democratic Great Britain, and all other nations that are menaced by German lust for expansion and barbaric ruthlessness. All of these present only one united front to face the enemy. They have buried their internal dissentions while there is an external foe and their liberty is not assured.</p>
   <p>Today we may justly ask ourselves: Which one of our Czech-American men or women is so well known, so meritorious, and so beloved by his fellow countrymen that he will be elected to head this Czech metropolis? With a people as democratic as the Czechs, it is, of course, as possible for a woman as it is for a man to <pb facs="5418478_6_1187.jpg" n="3"/>attain this high office.....</p>
   <p>There will be a primary election in which each Czech organization will vote for one candidate. From these candidates the mayor or mayoress will be elected on the last day of the bazaar.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
