<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-10">Feb. 10, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">An Evening for New Citizens</title><title level="a" type="sub">Patriotic Celebration in Farragut School at 24th Street and Spaulding Avenue</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-10">Feb. 10, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">AN EVENING FOR NEW CITIZENS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Patriotic Celebration in Farragut School at 24th Street and Spaulding Avenue</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Professor Bohumil Kral, who has charge of teaching citizenship to those who wish to become citizens, has made arrangements for a dignified celebration at the Farragut school on February 11, which will be full of significance to those who are preparing for their citizenship examination.</p>
   <p>In the first place, respects will be paid to two great builders of our country, who believed in the rights of men: Washington, the father of our country, and Lincoln, who saved our Union.</p>
   <p>It is appropriate that those who are now becoming citizens and enjoying the fruits of freedom and protection the seeds of which Washington and Lincoln had sown should try to visualize the high ideals of citizenship that the fathers of our <pb facs="5418478_6_1274.jpg" n="2"/>republic strove to attain will be the topic no doubt of the well-known writer and traveler, Mr. E. St. Vraz, who will deliver the lecture in Czech.</p>
   <p>The next speaker of the evening will be the Chief Naturalization Examiner of the district of Chicago, who will speak about the educational activities of the Naturalization Bureau, the well-known Mr. M. A. Sturges.</p>
   <p>Those who expect to take the examination for citizenship should gratefully appreciate the chance of hearing, meeting, and getting acquainted with a gentleman so well versed in his subject, and who can give them a helping hand to attain that goal which they wish to attain.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vincent Sedlak, a student of citizenship will recite the well-known Lincoln oration on the battlefield of Gettysburg.</p>
   <p>The musical part of the program will be filled by the school orchestra, and the singing societies of the Social Center, who will sing well-known American songs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1275.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Josef A. Cerny, chairman of the graduating class of the Farragut school will preside at this celebration.</p>
   <p>The Farragut school graduates invite all of us to this, our all-American evening. The celebration begins at eight o'clock.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
