<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-09-18">Sept. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Festive Meeting of the United Karel Havlicek and M. Tyrs Sokol Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-09-18">Sept. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">FESTIVE MEETING OF THE UNITED KAREL HAVLICEK AND M. TYRS SOKOL SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night the United Karel Havlicek and M. Tyrs Sokol Societies held their meeting in the Sokol Tyrs Hall, Sawyer Avenue and 25th Street. The meeting was called to order by the president of Sokol Havlicek, after which the following agreement made between the two societies was read:</p>
   <p>"In accordance with the agreement previously made, Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Karel Havlicek (Gymnastic Society Sokol Karel Havlicek) and Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Miroslav Tyrs (Gymnastic Society Sokol Miroslav Tyrs) unite into one society.</p>
   <p>"From this day forward, the activities of these societies will be carried on under the name 'Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs'.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1517.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The construction of the gymnasium begun by Sokol Karel Havlicek will be completed under the charter as issued to that organization; however, the cornerstone and the inscription upon the building will carry the name of the newly created organization.</p>
   <p>"The [title to the] building will be transferred to the new organization and a new charter will be applied for after the joint meeting in December by which time construction work should be completed.</p>
   <p>"Meetings of the new society will be held as follows: on the first Wednesday of the month in Soukup's Hall, on Sawyer Avenue and 25th Street; on the third Thursday of the month in Matousek's Place, at 30th Street and Trumbull Avenue. Gymnastic training will be continued in both halls under the supervision of the present instructors.</p>
   <p>"Officers: From the former Sokol Karel Havlicek Society, the president, <pb facs="5418478_6_1518.jpg" n="3"/>the secretary, and the financial secretary will remain in office in the new organization; the following officers will resign: vice-president, treasurer, and instructor. The places of the officers who resign will be taken by members elected from the ranks of the former Sokol Miroslav Tyrs Society.</p>
   <p>"The present building committee will be augmented by five members selected from the membership of the former Sokol Miroslav Tyrs.</p>
   <p>"Gymnastic meetings: Meetings will be joint meetings of both organizations.</p>
   <p>"The color sergeants will both remain.....</p>
   <p>"A new set of books will be started for the new organization.</p>
   <p>"The property of both of the former organizations will be sold to the <pb facs="5418478_6_1519.jpg" n="4"/>officials of the new organization and the cash assets of the former Sokol Miroslav Tyrs Society will be turned over to the building committee to add to the building funds.</p>
   <p>"Entertainment Committee: The committees of both former organizations will unite into one.</p>
   <p>"The drum and bugle corps of both societies will be combined into one. The order of meetings, the drills, the officers of the society, and the business management will remain in force until the society moves into its new quarters.</p>
   <p>"Women's Division: If they have not already united, the women members are given one month's time in which to do so.</p>
   <p>"Signed in Chicago, this seventeenth day of September, 1911.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1520.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"For Tel. Jed. Sokol Karel Havlicek:</p>
   <p>Frantisek Vlach, president,</p>
   <p>Fr. Martinek, secretary.</p>
   <p>"For Tel. Jed. Sokol Miroslav Tyrs:</p>
   <p>Vaclav Mejda, president,</p>
   <p>Frank Kratochvil, secretary."</p>
   <p>Following the reading of this agreement, the president of Sokol Miroslav Tyrs spoke. Mr. Dolezal spoke for the Fugner-Tyrs Group; Mr. Popelka spoke for Sokol Slavoj; followed by the presiding officer, Mr. Vlach.</p>
   <p>The next order of business was the reports of officers and the tendering of resignations which were accepted. Then followed the election of officers which resulted as follows: Frank Vlach, president; Vaclav Mejda, vicepresident; <pb facs="5418478_6_1521.jpg" n="6"/>Frank Martinek, secretary; Frank Danec, treasurer; R. Zacek, physical director; Messrs. Joseph Culek, Joseph Koza, F. Drnec, F. Cibulka, members of the board of directors. The business of the meeting having been finished, an informal entertainment then followed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
