<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-05">Aug. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Immediate Help Is Needed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0275</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0275.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-05">Aug. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">IMMEDIATE HELP IS NEEDED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has been reported that the Mayor's Fund for the victims of the "Eastland" disaster has reached the amount of approximately $400,000. No doubt a great deal of good could be done with so much money, many tears would dry and much misery would be averted if it was used in the right place and at the right time. It seems now that we are facing a repetition of the experience we had after the great disaster in the Stock Yards a few years ago when the so-called "trustees" got hold of the large amount of money which had been collected for the families of the firemen who had perished there. The "trustees" proposed to administer that fund in such a way that they would have to grant only an occasional donation from it. It was necessary to undertake most energetic steps in order to get the money for those families when they needed it most.</p>
   <p>Now, although the Mayor himself is in favor of an immediate distribution of those funds, there are a number of gentlemen who would like to play the role of "guardians" to the relatives of the victims of the "Eastland" disaster and <pb facs="5418478_6_0276.jpg" n="2"/>dole out the help in the form of "alms". The money that has been collected, if really divided right away among those who need it, could safeguard their future and heal the wounds caused by the terrible catastrophe. Occasional "alms" will only reopen those wounds and do very little good.</p>
   <p>Since there are about twenty-five per cent of Bohemians among the victims of the catastrophe, and about the same proportion among them who need help, it is the duty of our public to follow closely how the "Mayor's Fund" is disbursed and see that the greatest possible amount of good is done with it for all concerned. This thought was in the mind of Alderman John Toman when he asked City Clerk Siman and Jos. A. Holpuch, a member of the school board, to accompany him to see Mayor Thompson and ask him to include as members of the board which will administer the fund some representatives of the Bohemian people, who have so greatly suffered from the disaster. Both men were glad to comply with Mr. Toman's request, and a deputation composed of those three men called on Mayor Thompson yesterday and explained to him the reasons for their urgent request.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0277.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Mayor, although in full agreement with their arguments, advised them that the whole matter had been put in the hands of a certain Mr. Timpson. The three men immediately called on Mr. Timpson and learned from him that the collection had been closed and the whole Fund given to the American Red Cross for distribution in accordance with their findings of where it will do the most good.</p>
   <p>A certain Mr. Bickwell is administering this Fund on behalf of the Red Cross, and our men called on him next. Mr. Bickwell advised them that the plan is to administer the Fund for four years and pay out contributions to the families of the victims when and as needed. Seeing this was the case, the Bohemian deputation demanded that our people be represented on the board, or committee, in charge of the distribution of the Fund. After long bickering and argumentation Mr. Bickwell agreed to give the Bohemians one seat on the board.</p>
   <p>Since it was Mr. Anton J. Cermak who worked so hard in the interests of the <pb facs="5418478_6_0278.jpg" n="4"/>families of the catastrophe victims, Messrs. Toman, Siman, and Holpuch decided that he should be given an opportunity to continue in such activities as a member of the board. Mr. Bickwell agreed, and so Mr. Cermak will have a voice in the administration of the $400,000. In view of his character and experience it is needless to say that he will see that the Fund does as much good as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
