<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-21">Sept. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Sokoldom</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-21">Sept. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOKOLDOM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Sokols received from their founders a clearly defined program which even here in America is not entirely unknown, even here has its value, and should, therefore, be followed. This program is a very simple one and therefore can be understood by all our people who have at least some faculty of judgment and are sincere in their patriotism. It is "to cultivate, for the benefit of our nation and the Bohemian ways of life, a healthy mind in a healthy body". That is, in principle, all that there is to it, and all our lives may be governed by this principle. We are living, however, in a nervous age, in an age in which new ideas are born with the rapidity characteristic of worthless and vague conceptions. Like the sensational news in our journals, they are being thrown at our people, but happily many a well-meant but sterile idea, to the everlasting benefit of its originator and our public, is soon forgotten.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1335.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now, all of a sudden, the idea is being considered of putting our Sokols on a Military basis of militarizing them in order to send out, in case the United States should become actively involved in the war, ready-made formations of Bohemian volunteers, Bohemian legionnaires.</p>
   <p>We have not the least doubt that such an idea will be well received in certain quarters, although the nation of Podebrad [Jiri Z Podebrad, Bohemian king, fifteenth century], Huss, and Komensky (Comenius) has always been antimilitaristic. But that is just the way we are. Our character requires, as was proved by Masaryk and before him by Chalupny [professor of philosophy, University of Prague] in their numerous essays, a continual succession of new ideas, plans, and schemes on which to get intoxicated. These schemes, born of the times, do not necessarily have to be original or beneficial to our national character, After all, there never has been any dearth of ideas among us. We trust, however, that the Sokols will know what to do with such wild schemes, which in their consequences would certainly disrupt the whole Sokol organization; we trust that the Sokols will be satisfied with fulfilling their mission, the mission <pb facs="5418478_6_1336.jpg" n="3"/>given to them by the founders of their society. We also trust that our central, national political body, which has in it well-known men of the best reputation for sagacity and excellent common sense, will find ways and means to make such wild schemes, in the interest of the seriousness of our work for the old country, disappear as rapidly as they are born in these nervous times.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
