<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-20">June 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Timely Enthusiasm</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-20">June 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TIMELY ENTHUSIASM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many times in life one becomes unduly excited for one reason or another, only to regret when the passion subsides. The enthusiasm shown in yesterday's meeting of the patronage of the Bohemian Orhpanage and Old People's Home will not be regretted by any one of those present. On the contrary, it will bring about reward in its results....</p>
   <p>An action was started for the amortization of debts amounting to $23,000. The money will have to be provided by gifts..... The idea originated several months ago, but action was postponed until yesterday, when the right moment came to give it effective impulse. This was done by Mr. Spinar, one of the delegates, who proposed appeals to our public for the benefit of the institution which, as a result of new developments and changed general <pb facs="5418478_6_0098.jpg" n="2"/>conditions, has, so to speak, been left in the background of public generosity, in favor of national, patriotic obligations which had to be given preference. Mr. Spinar addressed himself first to our well-to-do fellow citizens, asking them to remember the Orphanage when drawing up their last will, no matter how small the contribution, for it is only by charitable beneficence that the debts can be erased.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. L. Novak, another delegate, seized upon the idea. He sounded the right note by declaring that the value of an idea depends on its realization. To give his contention substance, he declared himself ready to contribute $500 the moment the action is started. A promise such as this fell on fertile soil, and resulted in the unanimous resolve to join hands and begin to work among the Czech-American public. Mr. Spinar, grasping instantly that this was the moment for high pressure persuasion, declared that he also is ready with a contribution, "not quite as large as Mr. Novak's," of $100.</p>
   <p>The lady delegates would not stay behind. Mrs. Vyhnanek rose and proclaimed <pb facs="5418478_6_0099.jpg" n="3"/>nonchalantly that she too will know how to find "a dusty hundred-spot" somewhere. She was swiftly joined by Mrs. Zahrobsky who refused to leave Mrs. Vyhnanek to be the lone donor among women. She promised to produce $50. Others followed example, and the first thousand dollars for the payment of debts were on the spot in the wink of an eye.</p>
   <p>We sincerely hope that our Czech public will extend its helping hand and provide the remaining thousands for a purpose which is sure to honor our nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
