<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-26">July 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Catholics Active</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-26">July 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH CATHOLICS ACTIVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Leading members of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics have become aware of the need for an organization for the transaction of local business pertaining to the nation-wide movement for the liberation of the Czech people now under the rule of Austria. It became obvious that the Executive Committee was overburdened with detail work which could be assigned to a special organization. The duties performed by the Executive Committee, although dealing mostly with local issues, are nevertheless of broad significance for the entire patriotic Czech-American people. This committee, acting through the diverse branches of the Alliance, directs the latter's movements all over the United States.</p>
   <p>A meeting of representatives of all the branches of the Alliance was <pb facs="5418478_6_1205.jpg" n="2"/>called for the creation of a committee. This body, similar to the County Committee of the Czech National Alliance, is to take charge of agenda within the State of Illinois.</p>
   <p>The Executive Committee, and the committee of the Union of the Czech Catholics of the Archdiocese of Chicago, took part in the meeting. A body was created whose official name will be Statni Obdor Narodniho Svazu Ceskych Katoliku v Illinoisu (State Division of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in Illinois). Reverend F. W. Jodlicka presided. The following officers were elected: Joseph Krakora, president; Joseph R. Vojtech, vice-president; Vaclav Jedlicka, secretary; and Vaclav Paveza, treasurer.</p>
   <p>It was resolved that the newly created body should take part in the preparations for the "Ceske Posviceni," a festival to be held on September 3, in the Pilsen Brewery Park, in co-operation with the County Committee of <pb facs="5418478_6_1206.jpg" n="3"/>the Czech National Alliance. The proceeds from this joint enterprise will be sent to the offices of the Narodni Rada (National Council) in Paris, France, as a"gift from the Czechs of Chicago," to be used for politico-national activities.</p>
   <p>The Union of the Czech Catholics of the Archdiocese of Chicago, the Club Rieger, and other associations, will be requested to support the State Division of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in its work. The proposed "Posviceni" festival is expected to be an affair of such magnitude as Chicago has not yet seen. This is the first time since the World's Fair, in the year of 1893, that Chicago Czechs will unite, regardless of creed or political conviction, for a common enterprise. The next meeting of the State Division will be held July 31, in the office of the Alliance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
