<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-18">Sept. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">[Decline of the Bohemian Language]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial Comment)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0893</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0893.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-18">Sept. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">[DECLINE OF THE BOHEMIAN LANGUAGE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial Comment)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It seems that we do not know what we want. Our old wounds remain open, and we do not seem at all to feel the sharpness of the pain which they are causing.</p>
   <p>As far back as 1909, when Dr. Josef Scheiner [the head of all Sokol organizations and leader of the whole movement in the old country] visited this country, he regretted our small esteem of our native language even among the Sokols, and he expressed his regret in his Pamatnik [book or booklet descriptive of the history or memories of a certain person or organization, usually published in an impressive form and on the occasion of memorable events] by saying:</p>
   <p>"What a heartache it caused us to hear our boys from somewhere around Caslav or Pisek address one another, call to each other, in the English language! And we could hardly believe the evidence of our ears. We felt ashamed and <pb facs="5418478_6_0894.jpg" n="2"/>angry to see how easily our brothers forget their mother tongue, and how gladly, with a kind of pride, they are using a foreign language, even [using it in their] drills in their Sokol gymnasiums. That, brothers, is not our idea of a Sokol. In our conception of Sokoldom, the defense and promotion of everything Bohemian has a very prominent place; the love of everything Bohemian is apparent in every facial expression, every vibration of the voice, every mental conception of a Sokol!"</p>
   <p>Has anything changed among us since those days? Evidently not a great deal; otherwise the Borec [official organ of the Sokols] could not have written:</p>
   <p>"In this free American land, where nobody interferes with our use of the Bohemian language, at least in Bohemian halls, Bohemian parties, and Bohemian social gatherings, we seem to be avoiding our mother tongue, so that it might seem that we are ashamed of it!"</p>
   <p>Unfortunately there is more truth in these words than many of us would like <pb facs="5418478_6_0895.jpg" n="3"/>to admit, a state of affairs in which there is not the least to be proud of.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
