<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-15">Feb. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Gift to Czechoslovakian Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0076</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0076.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-15">Feb. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">GIFT TO CZECHOSLOVAKIAN CHILDREN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The sum of four hundred and fifty thousand Czechoslovak Kronen was sent during the last few days to Doctor Alice Masaryk, president of the Czechoslovak Red Cross to be used to save the suffering children in Czechoslovakia. Recognizing the necessity of aid to these innocent sufferers, the generous members of Bohemian rationalist societies in Chicago and vicinity collected among our countrymen and men of other nations the sum of $4,229.49, which sum being exchanged for American money, is equivalent to the above-mentioned amount of Kronen which was sent to Czechoslovakia for the cause of our children.</p>
   <p>It is also necessary to mention that the members of Frantisek Ludvik theatrical group and children of rationalist schools and clubs also assisted in this collection. This collection is one of the many noble deeds, performed by the people of good will toward the protection of our young Czechoslovak republic.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0077.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Following are the individual items of this collection: Receipts:</p>
   <p>Members of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Women's Unity) lodges $1,719.98, members of the Sesterske Podporujici Jednoty (Mutual Benevolent Sisterhood) lodges $672.17, the Vcelky (Bees) $910.40, the Divadelni Spolecnost Ludvikova (Frantisek Ludvik's Dramatic Association) $287.45, The Klub Svoboda Ceskych Zen a divek (Liberty Club of Bohemian Women and Girls) $252.50, the Americke Damy (American Ladies Association) $130.00, volunteer workers of the Loze Vlast (Country Lodge) No. 165, of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows $237.10, The Sokolice (Women's Gymnastic Association) $89.90, the Ceske Svobodomyslne Skoly (Bohemian Rationalist Schools) $93.85, the Ceske Dorostove Kluby (Bohemian Youth Clubs) $61.80, members of the Rebecca Lodge of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows $47.45, the Ustredni Jednota Cesko-Americkych Zen (Central Bohemian-American Women's Association) $133.00, and a gift from Mrs. Bachman [first name not given] $15.00.</p>
   <p>Interest $2.74, Total $4,653.34.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0078.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Expense:</p>
   <p>For the emblems $375.00, for the collection books $48.00, postage 85c. Total $423.85. The clear profit amounts to $4,229.49.</p>
   <p>Besides this, other things were sent to the Bohemian Red Cross. A package containing a pair of shoes, one pair of oxfords, two pairs of underwear and two caps as donations from Bohemian businessmen. Thanks to all who have contributed to this noble cause.</p>
   <p>For the collection committee:</p>
   <p>Fanny Piper, president,</p>
   <p>Frantiska Hulka, accountant.</p>
   <p>Auditing committee: Marie Smrcek, Alzbeta Lisy, Anna J. Novak.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
