<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-10-10">Oct. 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Social Evil</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0700</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0700.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-10-10">Oct. 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIAL EVIL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>State's Attorney Wayman has stirred up the quiet flow of Chicago waters in an interesting way. He has issued an ordinance closing all resorts in the red-light district.....Why now, just at the end of his term?....</p>
   <p>Prostitution in as large a city as Chicago is an evil which should be regarded as a necessary one. Very little can be done about it with force. The thing to do is to go to its roots--to its causes--remove them, and it will disappear by itself. Prohibition is opposed to cafes and to the sale of all intoxicating beverages. Is that just? Certainly not. Is it sincere? Still less. It is hypocrisy, and that is all. If our prohibitionists were sincere and determined to eradicate an "evil," they would go deeper, right to the root of the "evil," and this root is the manufacture of intoxicating beverages. The <pb facs="5418478_6_0701.jpg" n="2"/>prohibition movement would have to go directly against that and stop right there.</p>
   <p>As long as intoxicants are manufactured, they will be sold. And for just as long the fight against cafes, saloons, beer, liquor, and other drinks will remain ridiculous, petty, and extremely comical.</p>
   <p>To fight prostitution according to the method selected by Mr. Wayman is just as ridiculous, petty, and comical. But most of all, it is unsound, because it is hypocritical. He has annihilated the red-light district. Very well. He has annihilated a district which was closed and which, therefore, could easily be controlled by the police or other proper authorities. Mr. Wayman has closed the disorderly houses and resorts in the district and has chased out their inmates, giving no thought to where they will go or where they will settle. He does not care--in that he is not interested. All he wanted was to padlock the district. And what did he achieve by that? Nothing but to open a small, well-limited, and closed district of the vice trust, and to spread it all over <pb facs="5418478_6_0702.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago. The prostitutes have settled in hotels, in residential districts.....Will that do Chicago any good? .. Was his step sensible?....</p>
   <p>Mr. Wayman is a man of sufficient intelligence to know that that is no way to combat prostitution. As long as social conditions remain as they are, prostitution will be a necessary evil. It roots are deep in our social conditions. It cannot be suprooted without uprooting these social conditions. And for that, Mr. Wayman is far from strong enough. This is a job for our legislative bodies. They should see to it that economic conditions cause a decrease, rather than increase in the number of prostitutes. Why does their number increase? Because the wages paid to young girls in most lines of employment are too small to live on. If the girl's parents or friends do not help, the girl falls. She is sure to fall.</p>
   <p>But parents are also at fault. They should not give their daughters, particularly in their early youth, so much freedom or liberty as they do now. Freedom, liberty, and especially bad company lead to places where prostitutes are <pb facs="5418478_6_0703.jpg" n="4"/>recruited and made. First they ply their business on the sly, later on openly and publicly, and they are protected by the law itself. If prostitution is to be combated, it must be combated by laws--strong and healthy laws. But such laws, dear Mr. Wayman, do not yet exist. They will have to be made. They will have to be made in the future, in the future of a new, healthy, and better society.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wayman has closed the district and has spread the menace throughout Chicago....But it is not Mr. Wayman who is to blame. There is no doubt that he was forced to yield to the pressure of our "virtuous and saintly reformers". They fight open evil; they publicly and hypocritically lift their eyes to heaven when they talk about it; but secretly, at home, unseen by anybody, perhaps in their beautiful residences, they indulge in much worse, much more immoral, much more debasing and shameful evils. And it is they who will be responsible for what results from the closing of the red-light district!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
