<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-08-22">Aug. 22, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Representatives of Bohemian National Cemetery Association Made Annual Inspection of Cemetery Yesterday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0681</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0681.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-08-22">Aug. 22, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">REPRESENTATIVES OF BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION MADE ANNUAL INSPECTION OF CEMETERY YESTERDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian National Cemetery -- the pride of Chicago Bohemians, and of American-Bohemians as well -- was subjected to a thorough inspection yesterday by representatives of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association. Through these yearly inspections, the association's representatives get first-hand information of conditions, which enables them to form an idea of how things are run in the cemetery, and whether their orders, as embodied in their resolutions, are carried out to the letter. They see with their own eyes, whether or not the cemetery is improving. We will say in advance that the findings proved very satisfactory. The management, as well as the staff, is worthy of commendation, for our cemetery looks like a beautiful park, and everything in it is so pleasant and agreeable as to make the visitor regret the time when he has to depart from this place of perpetual quiet and peace. Every detail shows that great care is devoted to the cemetery and that the best is being done to reach the perfection we seek for our national undertaking.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0682.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Look about the cemetery and you will find everything so beautifully arranged as to arouse your admiration. The graves of our dead are covered with multi-colored flowers; bushy trees cast their shadows over them, and an almost intoxicating fragrance of rich flowers fills the air. The roads among the graves are carefully arranged and -- thanks to the National Cemetery's perfect drainage system -- always dry, Here you find everything in order at all times, which shows that the cemetery is conducted by a firm and experienced hand. The same can be said of the interior arrangements of the greenhouses. Here you will be surprised at the great multitude of carefully gardened flowers. Even the barns for the wagons, the stables for the horses--in short, everything that belongs to the cemetery--give us ample proof that it it managed with a firm hand and that the people in charge perform their duties whole-heartedly. It would be easy to ascertain who deserves credit for the success of the cemetery. To begin with, the Association's representatives are in for general acknowledgement. There is hardly a society in Chicago whose meetings are so well attended as are those of the National Cemetery Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0683.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The inspection began at 10 o'clock in the morning. The sun was so hot that many of the representatives were perspiring profusely. Mr. Filip, our chubby secretary, perspired so much that he had the appearance of one having just emerged from a pond. The office was inspected and everything was found in order. The inspection of the greenhouses proved equally satisfactory. The representatives' admiration was aroused by an artistic floral pillow which Mr. Ine, the gardener, had made all by himself. The entire cemetery was looked over, including the new section recently subdivided into lots. After the inspection was over, the delegation went to Mr. Seiner's place, where a delightful luncheon was served. As customary on such occasions, several of the representatives gave short talks to express their satisfaction for,and their undisguised pleasure at, the success of the cemetery. The cemetery was founded twenty-seven years ago on a very modest basis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
