<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-03-20">Mar. 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Charitable Association</title><title level="a" type="sub">Thirty Bohemian families are being provided for by the Bohemian Charitable Association.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0661</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0661.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-03-20">Mar. 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Thirty Bohemian families are being provided for by the Bohemian Charitable Association.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1--If we consider, that the Bohemian Charitable Association has been in existence for not quite five weeks, and in that time, not only has the association helped to obtain work for its countrymen and aid them in some form or other, but at present is continuously supporting thirty families, we must admit, that a record of this kind, is remarkable. Therefore, it should be the duty of every Bohemian, to become a member of this association, mainly, to prevent our people from suffering in poverty. A director's meeting of the Bohemian Charitable Association, was held last Friday evening, in the office of Mr. F. G. Hajicek's bank on West 26th Street. At this meeting, Judge J. Z. Uhlir, presided and the majority of the directors were present. Much beneficial work was accomplished. After the reading of the minutes and communications, the investigating committee gave their reports. Composing the committee were, Anton J. Cermak, J. A. Cervenka, Joseph Turek, Frank J. Petru and Sinagl, who investigated the group <pb facs="5418478_6_0662.jpg" n="2"/>who applied for assistance at the previous meeting. The committee granted aid to most of them, but refused some of their requests. The Bohemian Charitable Association, at the time of its organization, made a ruling, not to divulge the names of those, who being in dire need, ask for aid. The names would be held strictly confidential, and thus humiliation of their countrymen would be avoided. After the completion of the old business, the names of the new applicants were read to the directors. At present the meetings last from 8 to 12 P. M. Next meeting will take place next Friday evening, at the usual time and place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
