<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-11-21">Nov. 21, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Women's Share in Benevolent Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1624</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1624.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-11-21">Nov. 21, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN'S SHARE IN BENEVOLENT ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the Czech Guard undertook the distribution of Christmas gifts to the poor Czech children and destitute fellow countrymen last year, the excellent work done by the ladies in the organization found sincere appreciation even among those who at the outset had eyed the enterprise with suspicion. These skeptics had wondered whether there really were needy children and grownups in our community, but before the evening was over they became so thoroughly convinced of the necessity for charitable action that many of them left with tears in their eyes and pity in their hearts. They had come in touch with stark reality.</p>
   <p>As a consequence, the ladies of the Czech Guard took up the noble work with renewed ardor and vigor by sending out appeals to the more fortunate Czech-Americans. Collections solicited in this manner were slow, however, and the ladies were prompted to devise a more efficient method of attaining their humanitarian goal.</p>
   <p>A theatrical performance was arranged, and held in the hall of the Bohemian-American <pb facs="5418478_6_1625.jpg" n="2"/>Free Thought School last night. The performance was successful, and the ladies were proved to be correct in the assumption that everybody feels inclined to be good to others when a good entertainment for himself is in store. "The Ironmaster," by George Ohnet, was performed by a group of amateurs and a few professional actors, among whom Vladimir Samberk deserves special mention. The house was completely sold out, a few vacant seats having been paid for in advance by those who would not brave the inclement weather. It was, therefore, a financial as well as an artistic success. Considering the humanitarian character of the performance, the acting could, on the whole, be pronounced good. Messrs. Samberk, Hladky, and Kovarik, as well as Mrs. Benes and Mrs. Cervenka, portrayed their roles excellently....</p>
   <p>The evening yielded about $200, and the distribution of gifts will take place about New Year's Day. The ladies of the Czech Guard intend to make general appeals for the purpose of increasing the fund created by the theatrical performance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
