<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-13">Oct. 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">More about Hyphens</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0885</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0885.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-13">Oct. 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">MORE ABOUT HYPHENS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Hyphenated" Americans are again a thorn in the flesh of many a politician, and of many newspapers, big and small, from that one which calls itself "the world's greatest newspaper" down to those that are nothing more than an excuse for journalistic efforts. However, it is an old story, which pops up every once in a while with new and more or less timely variations. Immigrants have made America what it is today. Without them there would be no riches here. It is particularly our agriculture, of which Americans are so proud, that owes its development and progress to immigrants. But in spite of all that, the American-born citizens consider the immigrants as inferior people who need a guardian who would be constantly reminding them of their duties and keeping them to the fulfilling of accepted obligations. Well, let us tell you one thing. The much abused hyphen is not a sign of cleavage, but a sign of unity. It is an indication that those who are using it, while not unmindful of their origin, cling firmly to this country, the country they have chosen as their <pb facs="5418478_6_0886.jpg" n="2"/>new home.</p>
   <p>Therefore, Mr. Wilson has no reason to be afraid of "hyphenated" Americans. People who have come here in order to develop their abilities and powers under more favorable circumstances than those prevailing in their native countries, in order to live a life of greater freedom and liberty than they could have lived in their oppressed homelands, know how to appreciate America and American institutions, and will remain loyal to her under all circumstances. Moreover, Mr. Wilson has no reason whatever to be afraid that the immigrants will oppose him when he becomes a candidate for re-election. The position he has taken toward the belligerent nations and his methods of defending that position find a greater understanding and more thorough appreciation among the immigrants than among native-born Americans. With the exception of some half-crazy Germans and Irish, the millions of naturalized citizens are not only the staunchest followers of the slogan "America First," but also the most sincere admirers of Mr. Wilson and his policies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
