<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-01-16">Jan. 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Plenary Meeting of the Bohemian Arts Club of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-01-16">Jan. 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL PLENARY MEETING OF THE BOHEMIAN ARTS CLUB OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday afternoon, the Bohemian Arts Club of Chicago held its first annual plenary meeting which was well attended by the membership. The violin virtuoso Jaroslav Kocian, and Professor Karel Veleminsky, who came toward the end of the meeting, were especially welcome guests.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by the president, Dr. Jaroslav E. Salaba Vojan, who presented a resume of the Club's work during its first year. All objectives as set up in the bylaws were being pursued: Fellowship among the members was being promoted by meetings like the Smetana evening in Korbel's Studio, the musicale in the auditorium of the Art Institute, and Ales party in Sterba's Studio. For the general public, the Vrchlicky evening was arranged in cooperation with the [Cesko-Americka] Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) and the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press <pb facs="5418478_6_1451.jpg" n="2"/>Bureau). The members were active in the banquet in honor of Count Frankish Luzon, at the meeting of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada, etc. Newspaper articles, such as the president's recent article on Ales [Translator's note: Vaclav Ales, famous Bohemian painter] in the Daily News, will be continued. The resume was unanimously approved and [the Club's] appreciation expressed to the president.</p>
   <p>The president then asked the meeting to rise in memory of Mr. Bartos Bitner and Mr. J. Patek. There followed then the unanimous re-election of Dr. Vojan (for the committee on Literature) as president; Mr.A. Sterba (for the committee on Creative Arts) as vice-president; and Mr. J. Mrazek (for the committee on Architecture) as organizer and recorder. A motion to amend the bylaws by an article concerning contributing members was adopted. The Club will now admit as members friends of the arts who will have the right to attend all concerts, social evenings, and all other undertakings of the Club. The dues will amount to five dollars a year, and admission to membership will <pb facs="5418478_6_1452.jpg" n="3"/>be decided by a committee of five members composed of Mr. V. Machek for the Committee on Music, Mr. R. J. Psenka for Committee on Literature, Mr. Frantisek Randak for Committee on Architecture, Mr. Antonin Petrtyl for Committee on Creative Arts, and President Vojan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
