<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-12">Nov. 12, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">New Members of the Bohemian-American Press Bureau</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1507</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1507.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-12">Nov. 12, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">NEW MEMBERS OF THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN PRESS BUREAU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau), through its executive committee secretary, recently sent letters inviting individuals of various Bohemian-American communities to become members of the Bureau. The dues of an active member are twenty-five dollars a year.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian-American Press Bureau, in the course of its two years existence, has proven the irrepressibility of that institution, because achievements such as the census action, the million-cent collection for the scholastic association in the old homeland, which brought so much honor to Bohemian-America, the action against Count Apponyi, which called the attention of the American press to the American Czechs, and the coming lecture tour of American universities by Dr. Frantisek [Frank] Luetzow, are of the kind which it is simply impossible to carry through without some special permanent institution. Every newspaper, every society has its own field of activity, and they are absolutely <pb facs="5418478_6_1508.jpg" n="2"/>unable to undertake such tasks. All those who did not receive letters, and who are willing to contribute to the maintenance of the Bureau, should remit their dues to the treasurer, Mr. F. J. Skala, 966 West 18th Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Other new members whose applications were received this week are: Messrs. Bohus Hak, John Karel, who is president of the American State Bank; Cyril Fiala, proprietor of Little Bohemia; and John Pech, chairman of the National Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies). All of these applications are from Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
