<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-11-29">Nov. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">November Activities of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-11-29">Nov. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">NOVEMBER ACTIVITIES OF THE CESKO-AMERICKA TISKOVA KANCELAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau) corrected the printing and publishing firm of Rand McNally on the subject of the erroneous marking of the area and location of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery), on Chicago maps, and the omission of Bohemian banks, clubs, the Havlicek monument in Douglas Park, and Bohemian charitable societies and institutions in the Chicago guide published by the firm.</p>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar also started an action in the Chicago Public Library which aims toward better care of, and a more adequate representation of, Bohemian literature in the Library's branches and reading rooms in Bohemian districts. The action will be continued. The Society took issue with the periodical Inter-Ocean in regard to that publication's erroneous designation of Mr. Rudolf Friml as a German composer. Its editor, Mr. Charles W. Collins, sent a letter expressing appreciation for the information supplied by the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar, and used this correct information in his article of <pb facs="5418478_6_1425.jpg" n="2"/>November 23. All newspapers have been furnished the correct information concerning the Bohemian singer, Mr. Otokar Marak, who is expected in Chicago shortly. The Society is co-operating with Dr. Barnes of New Orleans in the work on an illustrated article on Bohemia written for the National Geographic Magazine, and published by the National Geographic Society. In addition, the Society has sent a collection of local newspapers and periodicals to the Jednota Soukromych Uredniku (Union of private office employees)in Pelhrimov (Bohemia) to be used in an exhibition of newspapers from all over the world. No doubt the organizers of this exhibition would be pleased to receive specimens from other communities. The work on translations from Bohemian literature was started with the co-operation of local Bohemian university students.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
