<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-01-25">Jan. 25, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Donations of the Czecho-Slavonic Aid Committee</title><title level="a" type="sub">One Hundred Thousand K. C. (Czechoslovak Kronen) Sent to President Masaryk and Same Amount to Komensky School in Vienna, Austria for the Benefit of Poor Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0085</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0085.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-01-25">Jan. 25, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">DONATIONS OF THE CZECHO-SLAVONIC AID COMMITTEE</title><title level="a" type="sub">One Hundred Thousand K. C. (Czechoslovak Kronen) Sent to President Masaryk and Same Amount to Komensky School in Vienna, Austria for the Benefit of Poor Children</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many a time we had an opportunity to write about the Czecho-Slavonic Aid Committee as doing the most needed work among our National organizations. Although not often advertised, it is very effective in places where it is needed most. It does not have expensive offices and high salaried officials; to conduct its office does not cost a penny, but all is being done for the love of nation and republic, without claim for rewards whatsoever. We have already written about the Czecho-Slavonic Aid Committee's achievements for our legionnaires in Siberia, and not a long time ago we announced its gift of one hundred thousand Czechoslovak Kronen to Thomas G. Masaryk, President of the Czechoslovak republic, with instructions to use this sum anywhere he <pb facs="5418478_6_0086.jpg" n="2"/>sees fit, according to the best of his knowledge and opinion.</p>
   <p>Today, shortly afterward, we bring another joyful report about the Czecho-Slavonic Aid Committee. In its last meeting, it was resolved to remember all those who are suffering in our old country with another large sum. In consequence of this decision, another large sum of one hundred thousand K. C. was sent to President Thomas G. Masaryk by Mr. Otto Vasak, treasurer of the Czecho-Slavonic Aid Committee, requesting him to use this money anywhere, according to his conviction, it is most needed. Furthermore, the sum of one hundred thousand K. C. (Czechoslovak Kronen) was also sent to the Jan Amos Komensky school in Vienna, Austria, with the request that the administration of this school divide this money among the Czech families in Vienna with the greatest number of suffering and needy children.</p>
   <p>This deed speaks for itself. In consideration of this charity, rendered twice in succession in a comparatively short time, there is no need to <pb facs="5418478_6_0087.jpg" n="3"/>recommend the Czecho-Slavonic Committee to our public. It is surely recognized. The public is able to judge where unselfish and benevolent work is being done, and for that reason surely as in its organizations, societies, and clubs, so in the ranks of individuals, these sincere patriots and philanthropists will remember more and more the Czecho-Slavonic Aid Committee, which brings honor and credit to us, and which deserves all our help and support.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
