<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-03">May 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Question of Czech Independence before the United States Congress</title><title level="a" type="sub">Congressman Sabath of Chicago Presents Resolution to Congress Today</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1009</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1009.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-03">May 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE QUESTION OF CZECH INDEPENDENCE BEFORE THE UNITED STATES CONGRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Congressman Sabath of Chicago Presents Resolution to Congress Today</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The presence of delegates from France and England will give signal importance to the appearance of Congressman A. J. Sabath in behalf of the liberation of the Czech nation; the following resolution will be laid before the legislative body by him today:</p>
   <p>"Whereas the Czech National Alliance, representing 540,000 Americans of Czech birth or descent, believes that at the termination of the war the fate of the small nations should be given just consideration in the peace treaty and</p>
   <p>"Whereas large numbers of Americans of Czech extraction have been helpful in the preservation of American liberty and unity, and today have contributed more volunteers than other nationalities and <pb facs="5418478_6_1010.jpg" n="2"/>"Whereas the Czechs' struggle for independence and the preservation of their language has been going on for centuries, notwithstanding all Austrian terrorism and the vicious influences of tyrannical Austrian bureaucracy and</p>
   <p>"Whereas the President proclaimed before Congress, in his great appeal to the honor of America, that right is more precious than peace; that we must battle for those ideals ever dear to our hearts; that we must fight to achieve democracy for those who submit to authority in order to win a voice in their own government; that we must fight for the rights and the liberty of small nations, for a world of universal right, and an agreement among free nations to insure peace and safety for all; that for an aim such as this we should sacrifice <pb facs="5418478_6_1011.jpg" n="3"/>our lives and our possessions; that we should do this with the conviction that the day has arrived when American can donate its blood and power for those principles which have given it peace and happiness, so help us God.</p>
   <p>"Be it therefore resolved by the Senate and the House that one of the conditions of peace shall be the liberation of the Czechs and a place among the nations of the world for them, in harmony with the principles promulgated by the President in his call for a League of Nations--those principles which assert that all governments derive their just powers from the people by whom they are set up; and</p>
   <p>"For the realization of this purpose, be it further resolved that Congress, as a participant in the peace negotiations, shall insist upon freedom and independence for the Czechs."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1012.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The resolution was sent to the congressman by the Pilsen Sokol, Chicago.</p>
   <p>[Translator's Note: See article of May 4, 1917, captioned Congressman Sabath to the Pilsen Sokol.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
