<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-24">Dec. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost Distributes Christmas Baskets</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0592</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0592.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-24">Dec. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST DISTRIBUTES CHRISTMAS BASKETS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) performed a meritorious piece of work yesterday afternoon. This act [distributing Christmas baskets to the needy] will surely be remembered by all who sympathize with our indigent countrymen, especially during this Christmas season. The Christmas distribution, for the success of which the Association has worked a long time, became a reality yesterday. Hundreds of our poor, distressed Czech families will have a happier and merrier Christmas, thanks to the efforts of our Charitable Association.</p>
   <p>The distribution of gifts began yesterday at 2 P.M. Four hundred families received baskets. About six hundred applications were investigated by the committee, composed of Messrs. Vanek, Krasny and Klenha. They were very careful to see that no really needy family was omitted. Four hundred and fifty of the six hundred applications were accepted. The Ceska Dobrocinna <pb facs="5418478_6_0593.jpg" n="2"/>Spolecnost took care of four-hundred families, while the management of the Czech Settlement took care of the remaining fifty families.</p>
   <p>The Association conducted the distribution in the following manner: A basket filled with an assortment of the most necessary foodstuffs was given to each accepted family. Each basket contained one or more chickens, groceries, sugar, coffee, flour, and other things. The children were not forgotten, since each basket also contained sweets and toys proportionate to the number of children in each family. The portions of the large families were increased to a quantity sufficient to meet the needs of all the members. Each basket cost up to three dollars. The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost had apportioned one thousand dollars for the distribution. This, however, did not take care of the total cost of the distribution. The committee, composed of Messrs. J. Z. Uhlir, John A. Cervenka, Anton J. Cermak, R. Sedlacek, and Turek, made a collection among Bohemian businessmen. The latter responded to the request of the committee with genuine "countryman generosity". Our ladies, the Mmes. Uhlir, Cervenka, Sedlacek and Serhant, had their hands full <pb facs="5418478_6_0594.jpg" n="3"/>with this Christmas distribution, and their work deserves full recognition.</p>
   <p>The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost yesterday did a very worthy piece of work toward the alleviation of the want and suffering of our needy countrymen. Our well-to-do public ought to help the Association in its welfare work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
