<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-05-31">May 31, 1902</date> p. 4
<title level="a">The Opinion of Some Americans about Immigrants</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0939</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0939.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-05-31">May 31, 1902</date> p. 4
<title level="a">THE OPINION OF SOME AMERICANS ABOUT IMMIGRANTS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The reading of English language newspapers, especially the Tribune, is very interesting. From them we learn what sort of opinions prevail among the various circles of American society, especially about immigrants and particularly about Bohemians. Thus, the Tribune informs us about what the committee which was to investigate localities where small parks could most conveniently be established, told the West Park Commissioners in regard to our "Pilsen." In their report, these gentlemen criticise our Pilsen as follows:</p>
   <p>"The people living in this section are dangerously crowded into tenement buildings. Every inch of land is covered with buildings of this type. The rear tenements are the worst in Chicago. In one block without an alley, there are several three-story buildings, extending from street to street. The population of the 10th ward is increasing rapidly, and tenement conditions are fast becoming worse, overpopulation is more perceptible, and the landlords are more avaricious, endeavoring to <pb facs="5418478_6_0940.jpg" n="2"/>cover every inch of their land with high tenement buildings. Land here continually rises in value. "</p>
   <p>In this light is seen our Pilsen and especially our landlords by the gentlemen of the West Park Commissioners' Committee. The Tribune also informs us on how some American ladies look upon immigrants and their wives, in its report of the meeting of the Chicago Political Equality League, where a lady named Vida Goldstein of Melbourne, Australia, lectured on the subject, "Women's suffrage in Australia." A certain Miss Cordelia Kirkland declared that the women of the United States cannot follow the example of Australian women in seeking voting rights. This lady, evidently a spinster, clinging to her own prejudices, gave the following reasons for her assertions:</p>
   <p>"This country has been flooded with immigrants, who, for the most part, are brutes, and they brought with them wives who are only a little removed from animals. Those men are governed by the lowest instincts, and their wives do whatever the men order them to do."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0941.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This lady received from several of the more moderate ladies a deserved rebuke, but her words, nevertheless, clearly indicate how immigrants are looked upon in some American circles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
