<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-08">Sept. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Notice to the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-08">Sept. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A NOTICE TO THE CZECHOSLOVAK LEGIONNAIRES OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Brothers! When we were on the fields of France we made a solemn promise never to surrender to the enemy, and never to abandon one another. Faithful to that promise we have returned victoriously from the battlefields of France, Tesinsko [Translator's note: Region between Moravia, Silesia and Poland], and Slovakia. It seemed then that our brotherhood, united by blood and sanctified by high ideals, would endure even in our later civilian life. We are sorry to say that the dropping out of the Chicago Druzina (Legion Post) from the legion organization reached disruptively into our brotherly unity. We are not going to analyze here the reasons and causes which made it possible for a few individuals to succeed in creating a situation which led to that [disruptive] step; we must, however, emphasize the fact that it was an unwholesome phenomenon when the whole organization was blamed for the errors committed by a few.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1036.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today, when the invalid veteran question is not yet satisfactorily settled, when the widows and orphans of our fallen brothers are not yet provided for, the Chicago Druzina is leaving our ranks, thus excluding itself from our common work and our duties to the central body, the Svaz Ceskoslovenskych Legionaru (Federation of Czechoslovak Legionnaires).</p>
   <p>This lack of comprehension of the basic moral principles of the legion has luckily not found its echo everywhere; fortunately there still remains a strong group of brothers who have already started to work for the common cause, and who, being loyal to the traditions of the legion, will continue to work for it. These men will not abandon their brothers who are invalids and in whose interest there is still much work to be done. Yes, "we shall remain such as we were".</p>
   <p>Brothers! We call you to work and to your duty. Only in unity lies the <pb facs="5418478_6_1037.jpg" n="3"/>significance of the legion; only by unity may the tasks of the legion be speedily and more successfully accomplished. Legionnaires! You who understand the importance of organic unity, become members of the Svazova Druzina Ceskoslovenskych Legionaru v Chicagu (Czechoslovak Legion Post of Chicago). See the secretary about application forms. Na Zdar! (To success!)</p>
   <p>For the Svazova Druzina of Chicago:</p>
   <p>Jaroslav Bukovsky, president,</p>
   <p>J. J. Fekl, secretary,</p>
   <p>2641 South Turner Avenue,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
