<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-10-06">Oct. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Regular Meeting of the Bohemian Charitable Association Was Held Yesterday Evening with a Numerous Attendance of Directors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0644</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0644.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-10-06">Oct. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">REGULAR MEETING OF THE BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION WAS HELD YESTERDAY EVENING WITH A NUMEROUS ATTENDANCE OF DIRECTORS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1, Col.6--In it's quarters in the rear of Mr. Foucek's drug store, a directors meeting was held yesterday evening. The meeting was called to order by Chairman, Judge J. Z. Uhlir, shortly after 8 o'clock after which the minutes of the previous meeting were read and approved, with the exception of one small change as was read.</p>
   <p>Secretary, Mr. Foucek, then read the minutes of the special meeting in which the directors decided to arrange a dance for the purpose of raising funds for the association which would be sufficient to take care of the requests, placed upon it during the course of the winter.</p>
   <p>Likewise these minutes were approved as read.</p>
   <p>Former requests were referred to the proper committee for investigation, <pb facs="5418478_6_0645.jpg" n="2"/>whereupon the chairman presented a communication from St. Ptacek, manager of the Branch of the Central School Union (Matice Skolska) in which it requested the association for assistance. In this communication, the chairman stated that the Branch of the Central School Union (Matice Skolska) without any other aid is taking care of schools and because contributions from the poor district are voluntary, is compelled to seek help elsewhere. Because the activity of the association is limited to Chicago, a motion was accepted in this manner, that the secretary answer the communication and eventually recommend to the Branch of the Central School Union (Matice Skolska) to seek aid of the public openly, and especially in Moeavia.</p>
   <p>The secretary of the association gave various reports and reported that Mr. Mendel, a florist is willing to decorate the hall of the pavilion at the Pilsen Brewing Park, for the occasion of a charity ball which will be held on the 26th day of this month, and render his services free of charge, which was gratefully accepted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Petru, announced, that he would petition Judge Newcomer, to discharge a bailee by the name of L. Guzek, who recently was sentenced to a term in <pb facs="5418478_6_0646.jpg" n="3"/>the Bridewell to serve out a fine of $50 and who now is expecting his wife and children from the old country.</p>
   <p>It was Guzek's brother who caused the incarceration. This matter was turned over to Mr. Foucek.</p>
   <p>The meeting was well attended, though some of the directors were absent. A motion was made by Mr. Stastny, to have the secretary notify those who were absent. Then the committee made it's report concerning work, for the forthcoming ball. A motion was made by Mr. Sedlacek, that the women should be assigned to do the kitchen work for the ball and after a brief discussion it was agreed to give preference to those women who have previously served.</p>
   <p>The entertainment committee was instructed to send notice to these women.</p>
   <p>Judge J. Z. Uhlir, brought to the attention of the directors present, that quite a large number of prominent Americans are expected to attend this charity ball, and emphasized, that not only will the Bohemian Charitable Association be represented, but all Bohemians, in particular.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0647.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>According to the reports given thus far a large attendance is expected. The best kind of entertainment will be presented.</p>
   <p>It was also agreed at this meeting that hereafter in all future meetings, a roll call will be called of directors, present and absent.</p>
   <p>An important matter was discussed when Mr. Foucek, had announced that he was visited by a committee from Sokol Slavsky, which is arranging a theatrical performance for the benefit of the association and was asked if he would accept tickets for sale. This matter was left in care of the former. A discussion ensued to be taken up in future with cases of similar nature. The next meeting will be held, Wednesday, October 12th, 1910, at promptly, 8 o'clock in the evening. Yesterday's evening meeting adjourned at 11 o'clock.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
