<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-08">Sept. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czechoslovak National Holiday to Be Celebrated in Chicago on September 14, 1918</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1767</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1767.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2 (Slovak)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-08">Sept. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHOSLOVAK NATIONAL HOLIDAY TO BE CELEBRATED IN CHICAGO ON SEPTEMBER 14, 1918</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Government has recognized our independence. We have been striving fully four years for this day: a day of splendid success for the Czechoslovak cause. It is our right to rejoice over this success, in the achievement of which Czechoslovak America has helped. We must also be grateful to the Government of the United States for the recognition of our independence and of our own national government.</p>
   <p>For this reason a meeting was held last Friday in which our Czechoslovak associations and organizations in Chicago took part. Preparations for a great manifestation of gratitude to the President and to the United States, which is to be held on September 14, 1918, were discussed. It was decided to use the War <pb facs="5418478_6_1768.jpg" n="2"/>Exposition grounds adjacent to Michigan Boulevard.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak people have proclaimed that occasion to be a national holiday for the entire Czechoslovak populace of Chicago. The beginning of the celbration was set for 12 noon.</p>
   <p>We implore you, citizens of Chicago, to submit to the arrangements for this manifestation, gladly and in a spirit of sacrifice, to demonstrate your loyalty and gratitude to the United States. Close your stores, offices, shops, and other places of business at the midday hour on Saturday, September 14. We request you to allow your employees to leave at noon, so that they may take part in this memorable celebration which signifies that a new member will be introduced into the family of Allied nations--that people which Theodore Roosevelt called the heroic Czech nation.</p>
   <p>We have bought 5,000 tickets, which are being sold for twenty-five cents to participants in the parade, and entitle one to admission to the War Exposition <pb facs="5418478_6_1769.jpg" n="3"/>grounds.....</p>
   <p>Our brothers, the Slovaks, will appear in their native costumes. They will be led by Mr. O. Schustek, and will execute their own "Ride of the Kings".</p>
   <p>The various groups are to march, each with their own standard, and each participant will be supplied with a small flag of the Czechoslovak state. These will be issued by a committee of girls which is led by Mr. F. Vencl. This committee is intrusted with the sale of souvenir coins, propaganda literature in the English language, emblems, tags, etc.....</p>
   <p>Czechoslovaks are requested to decorate their houses one day in advance, using American, Czech, and Slovak colors to show their joy over the great act of the American Government. Let the Czech and Slovak districts be flooded with decorations to give them the aspect of a sea of flags!</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1770.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A people's banquet will be held in the La Salle Hotel on September 18, at which Professor T. G. Masaryk is going to address the American public.....</p>
   <p>The cost will be within reason, so that the less prosperous may also attend. The ticket will cost around two dollars.</p>
   <p>For the Czech National Alliance:</p>
   <p>Vojta Benes, F. R. Kubec.</p>
   <p>For the National Alliance of Czech Catholics:</p>
   <p>The Reverend Father I. Kestl, Fr. Sindelar.</p>
   <p>For the Slovak League:</p>
   <p>O. Schustek, The Reverend Father Vaniscak.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
