<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-11-19">Nov. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Splendid Results of the Contest</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0169</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0169.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-11-19">Nov. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SPLENDID RESULTS OF THE CONTEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The contest arranged by the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) proved a veritable boon for our poor, because it brought $3,700 into the coffers of the charitable organization. The amount may, after final accounting is completed, even exceed this figure. The Association is thus enabled to face the coming winter, confident that it can continue its humanitarian activity to the same extent as it has done in former years.</p>
   <p>We deem it fitting to mention in this space those who have contributed so generously to the success of the enterprise. We mean, in the first place, the donors of all the beautiful and useful articles, the gifts that were raffled and won by the holders of the lucky coupons. (The coupons were bought from the Association by businessmen, who gave each customer one, or even two, with every ten-cent purchase.)</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0170.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last but not least, the members of the Association have won praise for the large amount of work they performed to bring about a satisfactory result. Mr. Stanislav L. Loula, president of the Association, and Mr. Louis Solar, president of the contest committee, have outdone everything that might have fairly been expected of them. Though both are heads of business concerns that demand their constant presence, they devoted almost every day of the last few weeks exclusively to the contest.</p>
   <p>The intense and wide-spread interest shown in the event was evident yesterday when the drawing took place in the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewery Park. Conservative estimates placed the number of visitors at 2,500. A preliminary survey gave the number of coupons distributed as three million. Since there were still more coupons stocked up, they were offered for sale at the wheel. Mr. Anton Cermak was in charge of this game and worked so hard at it that within a short time his voice was almost cracked. He did not give in, however, but worked up to the very moment of the drawing, with the result that many hundreds of dollars were taken in for the remaining coupons. This <pb facs="5418478_6_0171.jpg" n="3"/>exhilarating activity was embellished with a festive background by the merry tunes played by Mr. Rudolph Rubringer's band.</p>
   <p>The drawing began at 5 P. M., and the pavilion was filled to capacity. Before this business was tended to, Mr. S. J. Loula, president of the Bohemian Charitable Association, expressed his thanks to all the businessmen who helped financially, and also to the press that handled the publicity end of the affair. Joseph Uhlir, judge of the municipal court, spoke on the efforts made by the Association. He was followed by Mr. Cermak, who explained the method used in the drawing of the coupon numbers.</p>
   <p>The officers of the Spolecnost and representatives of the press took the stage, acting as watchers. The drawing was done by eight little girls, six of whom were wards of the Czech orphanage.....Mr. Cermak and Judge Uhlir alternated in calling the winning numbers, which were then placed upon an open table. [Translator's note: The list of the winning numbers is printed in this article.]</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0172.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>So far as we have been informed, not one of the lucky winners has put in a claim for his prize as yet. This may be done at a later date, however, the last day being December 16.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
