<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-03">Mar. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">An Explanation Addressed to the Friends and Families of Our Soldiers from the Twelfth Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-03">Mar. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AN EXPLANATION ADDRESSED TO THE FRIENDS AND FAMILIES OF OUR SOLDIERS FROM THE TWELFTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have received numerous inquiries from friends and relatives of our soldiers regarding support [for the latter's dependents to be granted]either by the United States Government or by our committee on military affairs. We are an aid society supporting our soldiers in the camps. We are willing to extend help where it is needed and as our duty demands. Through the good offices of our committee, soldiers in camps have been supplied with pianos, victrolas and records, gymnastic apparatus, and other articles. Considerable amounts of money representing voluntary contributions by members of our organization were also sent to the soldiers. We have recently published our dailies, just how every dollar of the money collected has been utilized.</p>
   <p>Whoever wishes to contribute may do so by leaving his donation with Mr. F. G. Hajicek, president of the Lawndale National Bank. Our organization intends to remain active until the end of the war.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0131.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We wish to learn the addresses of all of our soldiers in various camps other than those in Rockford and in Texas and California, so that these soldiers, too, will receive our support. We also wish to learn the addresses of families entitled to support by the United States Government, so that we may assist them. We would also like to know about those who are dependent upon the soldiers for support.</p>
   <p>We wish, however, to emphasize that we, as an organization or as individuals, have no control over Government funds. We can, however, intercede so that claims may be duly disposed of by the authorities. The claims may be filed at any time in the office of our chairman, Mr. Anton J. Cermak, chief bailiff of the Municipal Court, City Hall, eighth floor, or in his office of notary public, 26th Street and Homan Avenue. As for the Czech National Alliance, we know that this organization has restricted its auxiliary activities to families of soldiers of the Czechoslovak Army only. The Alliance maintains an information service in its main offices.</p>
   <p>We hope this information will suffice to clarify the situation for our fellow <pb facs="5418478_6_0132.jpg" n="3"/>countrymen from the Twelfth Ward, and that they will be guided by it.</p>
   <p>For the Soldiers' Relief Association:</p>
   <p>Anton J. Cermak, chairman</p>
   <p>Abram Adelman and J. A. Hospodsky, secretaries</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
