<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-14">Sept. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Ladies' Auxiliary of the Czechoslovak National Alliance to Give a Soiree</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1033</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1033.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-14">Sept. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE LADIES' AUXILIARY OF THE CZECHOSLOVAK NATIONAL ALLIANCE TO GIVE A SOIREE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Vcelky (Ladies' Auxiliary) of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni (Czechoslovak National Alliance) held a soiree last night in Pilsen Park pavilion, West 26th Street and South Albany Avenue, to welcome the well-known globe-trotter, Mr. Venceslav Kotal, who is also the founder of the Argentine branch of the Sdruzeni. Mr. Kotal arrived here last Sunday after a gruelling and dangerous journey from Saeng Pena, Argentia. The attendance at the pavilion on this occasion was such as was never witnessed before. The program of the evening included a speech by the editor, Mr. R. J. Psenka, after which the president of the Vcelky, Mrs. A. J. Novak, handed Mr. Kotal a wreath of flowers. The guest of honor then took the floor, and in a simple and unpretentious manner described his journey from Brazil to Chicago.....His account was listened to intently and was rewarded by a thunder of applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1034.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This address was followed by a supper, and it need not be emphasized that the products of the Bohemian culinary art were truly excellent. All were greatly pleased with the cooking, and especially Mr. Kotal, who, after journeying through such distant lands in which he often had to be satisfied with any kind of food, really appreciated the hospitality of the Vcelky. After the end of the official program the members and their friends engaged in a free entertainment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
