<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-14">Feb. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Parole Law</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary of Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0742</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0742.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-14">Feb. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PAROLE LAW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary of Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the parole law was enacted some years ago, it was considered a boon and perfectly in accord with modern views on how to reform criminals. Criminologists look upon a criminal as a person with abnormal tendencies who has to be taught instead of punished in order to be guided toward the straight and narrow path.</p>
   <p>Various systems have been in use to accomplish this aim, one of them being the honor system, which allows one prisoner more freedom than others. He is sent to an "honor farm" and his "word of honor" is taken as a guarantee that he will not violate the parole. He is left, so to speak, to himself.....The criminal law prescribes that no delinquent may be sentenced to prison for a shorter term than one year. This is really the entire punishment meted out in our state in the majority of cases. After such time, the prisoner may apply for parole.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0743.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Under these circumstances it is only a matter of course that a large number of allegedly reformed criminals roam at large. The parole board, it seems, sets them free at the same rate at which they are sentenced and interned. If the parole law worked out in practice as it appears in theory, there would be no objections to it.....</p>
   <p>As a result of the manner in which the parole law is being put into practice now, Chicago is overrun with paroled criminals of all sorts, and the police and the State's attorney's office are making vain efforts to lessen the crime wave in our city. If the parole law cannot be employed for the best protection of the public, it would be better if it were abolished.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
