<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-12-10">Dec. 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Christmas Preparations of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0248</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0248.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-12-10">Dec. 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CHRISTMAS PREPARATIONS OF THE CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) needs five hundred Christmas hampers this year for the needy families it is supporting. In order to secure them, the ladies' auxiliary of the Spolecnost has decided to approach our dailies for help. The hampers are to be distributed in the Pilsen Park pavilion, December 23.</p>
   <p>Our countrymen, both individuals and their families, are urgently requested to co-operate with the ladies in their endeavor. Hampers for smaller families can be bought for three dollars, and larger ones cost four dollars....</p>
   <p>The meeting of the ladies' auxiliary was attended by about twenty ladies, all of whom pledged at least one Christmas hamper each....</p>
   <p>Our newspapers will be helping by reporting, every Sunday, the progress the ladies have made in their action during the week. The reports will start <pb facs="5418478_6_0249.jpg" n="2"/>next Sunday, and the names of those who agree to supply a hamper will be published in the reports.....</p>
   <p>Pledges should be sent either to any one of our dailies or to the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost at 2603 South Kedzie Avenue, or else to the officers of the ladies' auxiliary, to the president, Dr. Sylvia Napper at 2759 West 22nd Street, the secretary, Mrs. Sophie Kreml, at 2123 West 19th Street, or the treasurer, Mrs. Theresa Hajicek, 2406 South Ridgeway Avenue. Who will be the first to send in their names?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
