<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-04">Oct. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Second Monthly Report of the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-04">Oct. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE SECOND MONTHLY REPORT OF THE CESKO-SLOVANSKY POMOCNY VYBOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the great St. Wenceslaus concert held in the Pilsen Park pavilion on the night of September 28, we have concluded the second month of activities which started July 25, the day of Austria's declaration of war against Serbia.</p>
   <p>We are looking back with satisfaction at the work that has been done, but at the same time, we feel that there is much, much more to be done. Our letters, sent to all our large national organizations, to all conventions to be held in the near future, and to many smaller national bodies, have without exception been most favorably received. The leaders and representatives of these bodies are starting to co-operate with us in our work, which now will be progressing more rapidly with their help and counsel.</p>
   <p>Of the bodies now directly represented in the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor <pb facs="5418478_6_0444.jpg" n="2"/>(Bohemian-Slavonic Auxiliary Committee), we want to mention first the Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Association), the Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs (Sokol unit called Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs), the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Women's Unity), and the Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Associations).</p>
   <p>Their representatives and the representatives of other bodies that will become our members will soon find that we have made an auspicious start. We have sent nine hundred collection sheets to all parts of the United States and Canada. Cash collections now amount to $3,896, of which $2,748 was received in the month of September. Of the collection sheets, eighty have been returned with names and amounts contributed by our friends.</p>
   <p>Letters have been sent to two hundred of our well-known national workers requesting them to help us in our action. All material necessary for collections is ready and available: There are collection sheets, handbills, posters, signs <pb facs="5418478_6_0445.jpg" n="3"/>for collection posts,and other printed materials. These things are available for anybody and everybody who desires to take up collections and will ask for them in our offices, either personally or by mail addressed to the undersigned secretary.</p>
   <p>We hope that amounts appropriated by various organizations will be collected soon, and that all these organizations will send their representatives to us in Chicago. They will be needed here for active work and conferences. Prompt action is necessary, because the amounts collected or pledged so far are far less than could be expected in view of the number of Bohemians in America. In addition to the cash we have on hand, there are pledges barely amounting to nine thousand dollars. We know that the Bohemians are a good people, and all that is necessary is to knock on their generous hearts, and they will help the nation in this time of dire need. We keep on knocking, keep on asking, but so far the results are far below what they should be in John Huss' nation. It seems that there are many sceptics among us who want to wait until they hear directly from the old country that the people there are starving to death, <pb facs="5418478_6_0446.jpg" n="4"/>freezing, and have nothing to eat but tree bark--as has happened on several occasions in the past--before they will come up with their contributions! How beautiful in times like these is the deed of Mr. J. Tichy of Kedzie Avenue, Chicago, who writes us somewhat like this: "We talk about collecting one million dollars. Well, that is very simple indeed. There are about seven hundred thousand of us here in the United States, of whom at least half a million are good, patriotic Bohemians. Let every one of them assess himself with a national tax of two dollars a year, and the money is here! I am starting the move. I am a man of very modest means, and there are six of us in our family. Hence, I am enclosing twelve dollars. We shall manage somehow".....It seems to us that Neruda [prominent writer] had such men in mind when he talked about the Bohemian people as a "nation of granite". If we had as many such men as we have critics and pussyfoots who are afraid to give a dime for fear it may be confiscated by the Austrian government, we could do wonders.</p>
   <p>So I repeat here again that the money will be sent to the old country only <pb facs="5418478_6_0447.jpg" n="5"/>under conditions which will assure its proper delivery. We are already in touch with the Ceska Obec Sokolska (Bohemian Sokol Community) and the Jednota Ceskych Ucitelu (Association of Bohemian Teachers) [both bodies in the old country], discussing the way they could help us in distributing the funds so that the American money would be given only to the best and most needy Bohemian people.</p>
   <p>At first we were hoping that in these tragic days, in this time of great catastrophe which is affecting our entire nation, we would be able to unite all Bohemians toward one huge humane action, and that all of us would,at least for the time being, forget all views and ideas which separate us one from the other. We thought that our hope was that much more justified when we saw how the German Kaiser succeeded in unifying the whole German nation in his business of murder. It was easy to hope for the unification of our nation in the cause of humaneness. But we were wrong. The Bohemian nation is not unified today. Perhaps it is because we have no Kaiser, and a Bohemian king has not yet been <pb facs="5418478_6_0448.jpg" n="6"/>elected. Thus, in Chicago the Socialists are making collections for their own people, and the Catholics have started their own fund. Outside of Chicago, there are several collection centers soliciting money for similar purposes and in ways similar to our own. But we hope to make an agreement with them, because in marching toward one and the same goal, we would be in one another's way if we did not march together.</p>
   <p>Our St. Wenceslaus concert was a success, particularly in its artistic and moral aspects. Little wonder, then, that there are many voices suggesting that such concerts be arranged more frequently. To this we have just one thing to say: If we were to pay for all expenses and all services, there would be, instead of a one-hundred-dollar profit--the exact financial report will be published later--a three-hundred-dollar deficit. With all this beautiful music, let us not forget that the musicians want to live, too! Of course, for the St. Wenceslaus concert they donated their services to the country. They not only played free of charge, but also procured the largest advance sale of <pb facs="5418478_6_0449.jpg" n="7"/>tickets and thus assured a good attendance at the concert. Many thanks to them!</p>
   <p>We would suggest that our out-of-town communities try to stir up an interest in our collections by organizing similar concerts or lectures or other entertainments. Our headquarters will be glad to help in any such undertaking. Let us get down to work! Let us perform some sacrifice! Let us wake up and shake off our lethargy! Let us accumulate some merits for helping the old country! Let us repay at least a part of our debt to her! Let us show some pure, healthy, human feelings and prove that we are not indifferent toward the suffering of thousands of Bohemian families who have lost their providers and supporters on the battlefields and now are facing misery and need. Let us alleviate the sorrow of the orphans, widows, and mothers, if in no other way than by an expression of sympathy in the form of a dollar.</p>
   <p>For the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor, J. V. Nigrin, Secretary, 1825 Blue Island Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
