<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-10-16">Oct. 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada's Party for Mr. Vopicka</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-10-16">Oct. 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKO-AMERICKA NARODNI RADA'S PARTY FOR MR. VOPICKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council), called into being as the American branch of the Narodni Rada Ceska (Bohemian National Council [in Bohemia]) by our famous traveler and writer, Mr. E. St. Vraz, immediately after his return from the old country a few years ago, is a body that may be called the cultural center of the Bohemian colony of Chicago without any shadow of exaggeration. It was founded for the purpose of promoting contacts with cultural trends in Bohemia and of dealing with everything that concerns the cultural development of the American branch of the Bohemian nation, not only in Chicago, but throughout the entire United States.</p>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada has included in its program the fostering of everything that may help Bohemians in America prosper as a national group and <pb facs="5418478_6_1428.jpg" n="2"/>maintain their national character. In this respect it must be stated frankly that the Rada's quiet and industrious work has done a great deal of good and has accomplished many things whose value will be more fully appreciated in the future than it is now. Just as an example, let us mention its indefatigable plodding toward the introduction by the Chicago Board of Education of the Bohemian language into public schools, the preparation and publication of adequate textbooks to be used in this connection, the organizing of whole series of lectures for pupils of public schools on Bohemia, its steps toward the establishment of an immigration station in Chicago and, last but not least, its energetic protest against the unfortunate Root-Dillingham immigration bill. These are only a few of the accomplishments to which the Rada can point as successful efforts in its variegated program of activities.</p>
   <p>The Narodni Rada, with Vraz and a few other unselfish leaders at its head, has taken a hand in all matters concerning the well-being of the Bohemian <pb facs="5418478_6_1429.jpg" n="3"/>people, and we feel certain that in the future it will always adhere faithfully to its lefty program. The meritorious work of the Rada must be that much more appreciated when we realize that the body had to work without public understanding and with meager financial means, its only capital being the enthusiasm of a few self-sacrificing individuals whose only reward was the satisfaction of knowing that they were doing their duty and doing it well. This fact should always be borne in mind when one judges the work of the Narodni Rada.</p>
   <p>Yesterday the Narodni Rada came before the public eye with its annual dinner party held in the Pilsen auditorium, a party which each year initiates a new period of work, and which was particularly significant this year, because at it the Narodni Rada bade farewell to one of its most prominent members, Mr. Charles J. Vopicka, who will shortly be on his way to Europe to take the office of United States Ambassador to the Balkan States. Mr. Vopicka has been a member of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada ever since its foundation. He <pb facs="5418478_6_1430.jpg" n="4"/>has held the office of vice-president of the group; he took an active part in all its undertakings; he always put his best into these efforts and gladly used his social position whenever and wherever it was necessary to further the interests of the Rada.</p>
   <p>Little wonder, then, that the Narodni Rada hates to part with him, and it is still more natural that, in recognition of his great merits, it gave a fare-well party for him which neither he nor anybody else of those present will soon forget. And there were many guests,for the ball room of the auditiroum was almost completely filled. There was a formal dinner with excellent food, and a program of classical music presented by our foremost artists. The exquisite taste, good form, and high social standing of those responsible for the party were clearly evident. However, there was not even a trace of stiffness. If any of those participating ever wear an armor of cool formality, they left it at home this night. Sincere and warm fellowship, that will for many years linger in the memories of all who took part, prevailed.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1431.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: A long paragraph is devoted to the description of the dinner and the several selections on the program, the artists, etc.]</p>
   <p>After the last vocal selection, the impressive ceremony of bidding farewell to Mr. Vopicka took place. It was performed by Mr. E. St. Vraz who, in his inimitable way, spoke in behalf of the Narodni Rada and all those present. The occasion gave him an opportunity to deliver one of his remarkable, poetic but sincere, perfectly formed but straight-from-the-heart speeches for which he is so justly famous.....He spoke as a great Bohemian, a great Slav, but principally as a great man whose heart is filled with a love of everything good, everything great, noble, and beautiful.....</p>
   <p>Another vocal solo followed, after which Mr. Vraz added a brief explanation of the aims, objectives,and purposes of the Narodni Rada. He spoke about the <pb facs="5418478_6_1432.jpg" n="6"/>lack of proper understanding of this body among the general public, about the many and great obstacles it had and still has to overcome.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Vopicka, in a voice filled with emotion, thanked one and all for the signal honor. His speech in its essence was his autobiography and would be a lesson to any young Bohemian-American on possibilities which this country offers to a man who builds on honesty, energetic self-application, and, principally, on a determination to work hard.....[Translator's note: Dots are the author's]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
