<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-13">Jan. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From the Czech Charitable Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-13">Jan. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE CZECH CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The ladies' section of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Czech Charitable Association) held its regular meeting on January 8. The officers' reports were received with great satisfaction.</p>
   <p>In reviewing the activities for the year 1917, the Charitable Association may certainly feel gratified by the work accomplished by its executives for the relief of the destitute. They sponsored a "strawberry feast," and also a musical in Harrison High School. These affairs yielded $1,200 for the treasury of the Association. A very neat pile for the poor! Our investigating committee knows best how many tears can be spared with that amount. He who never learned what misery means cannot understand the emotions of the mother of a sick child who can provide neither medication nor food nor heat for it. To look at all this distress is enough to make any one's heart bleed.</p>
   <p>The Association is making every effort to remedy these conditions. It succeeded <pb facs="5418478_6_0141.jpg" n="2"/>in its endeavor, thanks to the generous support from the Czech public. Anyone who contributes will dry many tears.</p>
   <p>The ladies' section, which helped materially by the distribution of Christmas baskets, observed misery in many places. You should have witnessed the surprise and happiness in the eyes of an aged woman when she was presented with a basket filled with food, and even delicacies, which she had never even dreamed of possessing. The poor old soul was so filled with joy that she hastened from house to house of her acquaintances proudly exhibiting the precious goods.....Had you seen this, you would be even more satisfied with having done your bit.</p>
   <p>The meeting acknowledged the annual reports, following which the new officers were introduced by Mmes. Selacek and Hahn: Marie Sokol, president; Josephine Beranek, vice-president; Sophie Kerml, secretary; Frances Stejskal, bookkeeper; Marie Rezabek, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
