<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-04-20">Apr. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Let's Be Sensible!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-04-20">Apr. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S BE SENSIBLE!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is clearly apparent that interest in the great events in Europe is ebbing. The contributions to our fund are diminishing, and our people are dropping thoughts about the future of our country from their minds. The fact that times are bad and that there is a great deal of misery among the people has nothing to do with that matter. There are many well-to-do individuals among us who hardly notice any difference between these times and the times of prosperity.</p>
   <p>The reason is quite different. Our people do not mind giving when they know where the money goes. We have auxiliary committees, we have unselfish individuals who work hard, but our people are used to seeing what is being done and thus having a share, even if a passive one, in the work; in other words, they like to have a "run" for their money. When they do not know what is going on they lose all interest.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0349.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But our people should realize that these are abnormal circumstances. The work cannot be done before our eyes. We are in a position to assure our readers that a great deal of work is being done, but it must not be broadcast. In times like these, when scaffolds are being built in Austria, when courts-martial are busy day and night, and when people are being sent to jail for years for nothing more than a careless utterance, "absolutely no publicity" must be the watchword. Anything else would be "duck soup" for the Austrian consul, who is a most keen reader not only of the Denni Hlasatel but of all other Bohemian papers in Chicago, whose news he diligently forwards to Vienna. Therefore it is impossible to tell everybody what is going on, and truly patriotic people should be content to do their duty and let our responsible leaders do the work.</p>
   <p>What, really, is our duty? Our opinion about that has not changed since the very start. Bohemian America can do nothing else but furnish the money. We can neither create the republic, nor elect its president, as some dreamers in Chicago and New York like to imagine. The destiny of our country will be decided in Europe, and we Bohemians in America will have nothing to say about it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0350.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But money will be necessary, a great deal of money, and everybody who can, and who has a bit of love for his old country, should contribute.</p>
   <p>This war is not being waged for territorial gains. France will take back its old provinces, that is, its own land, and nothing more. Neither Russia nor England desires a bit of Austrian or German territory. This war is being waged for the recognition of small nations. But there should be no mistake: Let us not believe that anybody will give us anything for love, for our own sake. In creating small states, the big powers will be safeguarding themselves. But even so, now when world-ruling England has plunged into the war for the sake of little Belgium, when Russia has declared itself for an independent Polish state, when so much has been sacrificed for little Serbia's sake, anybody can see that the dawn of liberty is coming for small nations, and that our turn will come also. But we repeat: It is not because the great powers love us so much, but because Germany will be weakened by creating small independent countries. The Bohemian lands have always been a thorn in Germany's side. An independent Bohemian state will prevent Germany from swallowing Austria and <pb facs="5418478_6_0351.jpg" n="4"/>becoming that much stronger.</p>
   <p>But one thing is imperative, to make the world aware of the importance of the Bohemian nation in the future European order. That is being done. There are honest and responsible men working for us, and the time is coming when we shall receive a detailed report on their activities. Everyone of us may be sure that he will never have an opportunity to render his country more valuable services than just now, in these historic times. All he has to do is to make his contribution of money, not a great deal of it, even a little will help. The saying goes, "He gives twice, who gives quickly," but in these circumstances it is now or never.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
