<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-13">July 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czechs in the United Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-13">July 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHS IN THE UNITED SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two Chicago Czechs, John A. Cervenka, and Jan [John] Svehla were among the vice-presidents elected in a meeting of the executive committee of the United Societies in the Briggs House last night. Among the several subcommittees formed in the meeting one has to take care of the political activities of this anti-Prohibitionists organization. The following are Czech members on it: Anton J. Cermak, John A. Cervenka, Joseph Cermak, R. C. Jandus, Joseph Smejkal, John Toman, and Mrs. Anna Velik. On the organization committee is Mrs. Anna Zenisek, who is of Czech descent. On the committee for legal affairs there were named: C. R. Jandus, J. Z. Uhlir, Anton Pecival, and Joseph Smejkal. Two Czechs, Joseph Stastny, and J. A. Hospodsky are among the members of the press committee. Joseph Bolek is a member of the finance committee. John Toman is chairman, and Ferdinand Svoboda and Mrs. Antonia Hofreiter, are the other members on the committee on taxation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1213.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Beautiful diplomas were awarded to the following members of more than ten years standing: Anton J. Cermak, John A. Cervenka, C. R. Jandus, Ferdinand Svoboda, Joseph Z. Uhlir, associate Judge of the Municipal Court, were among those thus honored.</p>
   <p>It was emphatically declared in the meeting that although the United Societies stand for a liberal interpretation of the liquor laws, they will relentlessly prosecute saloons whose behavior is liable to damage the cause of the organization. The organization will, therefore, stand up for those places only that conduct business in a decent, lawful manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
