<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-13">May 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Lawndale Taxpayers' Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0874</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0874.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-13">May 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LAWNDALE TAXPAYERS' CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following the routine business, members of the Lawndale Taxpayers' Club heard a very interesting lecture at their recent regular meeting. Alderman Otto Kerner spoke on the activities of the Chicago City Council.</p>
   <p>He compared the way the city council's agenda was handled not so long ago, when the "Gray Wolves" were the rulers of our city's legislative body, with the manner in which the business is transacted today. The alderman then announced that the protest against the annual observance of St. Patrick's Day by the City Hall had been effective. He assured the audience that the City Hall would not observe that holiday any more.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of Mr. Kerner's address the chairman commented on the scant <pb facs="5418478_6_0875.jpg" n="2"/>attendance at club meetings. He felt that this was a result both of the migration of the Czechs into communities farther west, such as Cicero and Berwyn, and of the continual sale of property by the Czechs in the Lawndale district.</p>
   <p>"Behind the Czechs who are abandoning their old established grounds a foreign element encroaches. Against this influx vigorous resistance must be made by a strong organization of old settlers, who will not move, those who have developed the neighborhood, and who are loath to see their beautiful Lawndale district lost to them!" The chairman continued:</p>
   <p>"Only in unity is there strength; therefore it is necessary that every Czech taxpayer join our club for the protection of our interests and the amelioration of these conditions."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0876.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Lawndale Taxpayers' Club is politically independent; it not only works for the interests of all, but it offers its members special personal advantages. To make membership more accessible for those of moderate means, no fee will be asked from those who file their application at the next meeting which will be held in the Vojta Naprstek school, 26th Street and Homan Avenue, on May 19.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
