<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-06-06">June 6, 1890</date><title level="a">Participation in Public Affairs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0960</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0960.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-06-06">June 6, 1890</date><title level="a">PARTICIPATION IN PUBLIC AFFAIRS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Svornost has been urging our countryman for over a long period of time, to be present and take part in all public ceremonies and celebrations, which the American people are holding--whether it is a celebration in memorial of some famous American, or some other national celebration. Participation of our people can only have beneficial results. It is not long since the English papers, unable to find any other faults, complained and with reason, that we Bohemians are extremely clannish, that we remain within our own narrow circle, tending to create a separate Bohemian Community.</p>
   <p>We undertook it as an obligation upon ourselves at that time, to work toward that end, so that public opinion of us Bohemians should change; therefore we urged our Lodges to take a brotherly interest in all public celebrations, which are participated in by other nationalities such as German, Scandinavians, etc., at the same time, however, we urged our countrymen to take care that their public appearances were dignified, made a good impression and encouraged respect.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0961.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is true, that some kind of street parade, will not serve to redeem our nationality regardless of how many of our people might participate, but every sincere Bohemian would much rather read about the good impression made by the Bohemians participating, than the continual repetition of the charge that we are trying to establish a sort of special nationality, avoiding all contact with public life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
