<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-09-19">Sept. 19, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">A Friend of the Czech-Americans Passes Away.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-09-19">Sept. 19, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">A FRIEND OF THE CZECH-AMERICANS PASSES AWAY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the Chicago Czechs learned through the papers of the decease of Josephine Naprstek there was perhaps not one race-conscious fellow countryman whose eyes were not filled with tears of grief. And there is no Czech who mourns the death of this humanitarian, patriotic Czech woman more than the Bohemian-Americans, in whose memories she has found a lasting place. The Vojta Naprstek School in "Bohemian California," the large Czech district of Chicago, testified in a solemn manifestation to its love for their dead friend; the school bears the name of Josephine Naprstek's late husband.</p>
   <p>On both buildings the flag was at half mast. The teachers told the pupils of the life of the good-hearted patriotic woman; a gratifying way of teaching our children to be loyal, devoted Czechs. We sincerely wish that the teachers' words would forever take root in the little hearts: "Never forget that you are the children of Czech parents; that you are the children of our dear Czech fatherland.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1627.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And though a foreign sea surround and toss its waves towards you, do not recoil, but remain loyal Czechs. Thus you will command the respect of those foreigners also, who know the value of pure patriotism. May you live and work in the spirit of Josephine Naprstek who lived for her country."</p>
   <p>Beautiful words! The teachers of this best of our Czech schools certainly deserve to be rewarded. Not in substance, for they do not expect any renumeration in their most remote thought, but by convincing them that their words are indelibly written in the heart of every Czech-American.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
