<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-12">Aug. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">For the Bohemian Cause!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni [Bohemian National Alliance])</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1339</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1339.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-12">Aug. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE BOHEMIAN CAUSE!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni [Bohemian National Alliance])</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although the activities of societies always ebb in summer and collections suffer to a particularly marked degree, our countrymen do not forget the Bohemian cause and considerable amounts are being collected these days, even though many of our workers have been devoting their time more recently to efforts in connection with the "Eastland" catastrophe. The feeling that perhaps the Russian retreat would have a detrimental effect on our collections has proved, fortunately, unjustified. At least collections have not been affected to such an extent that the slackening would endanger the success of our future work. Now, when it is quite evident that in spite of the real or imaginary Russian set backs, the war will probably last for years, and when the probability of future exploits of the Allies can be appraised, we must not be losing courage <pb facs="5418478_6_1340.jpg" n="2"/>for continued work, On the contrary, all this should spur us on to greater efforts, should stimulate our energy. All in all, we should be guided by the fact that, as news just reaching us from Europe shows, due to our financial help, our leaders have been able to penetrate with our demands everywhere where it had appeared necessary. The Bohemian cause, due to the untiring efforts of a number of workers in Europe in recent times, has continued to advance steadily, and we are therefore justified in hoping that the future, in spite of the Bohemian pessimism, will decide in our favor.</p>
   <p>The confidence in the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni is growing not only in America but also in Europe. Thus the London Bohemians have decided to join hands with us, and so have our countrymen in Paris, and in Switzerland. In this way, the Narodni Sdruzeni is becoming the main headquarters, on both sides of the ocean, for the work toward Bohemian liberation, and the realization of the purpose of the greatest emigrant of the last century, Vojta Naprstek. The distance of thousands of miles is being spanned by common work and desires. A number of Bohemian centers in Canada have joined us, and Winnipeg is expected to be <pb facs="5418478_6_1341.jpg" n="3"/>added within a day or two. Local branches of the Narodni Sdruzeni have been newly established in Seattle, Washington; St. Louis, Missouri; New Britain and Hartford,Connecticut.</p>
   <p>As far as collections are concerned, the following merit especial mention: The pupils of the Ceska Svobodomyslna Skola (Bohemian Free Thought School) Vojta Naprstek have donated the creditable sum of $43. We have sent a special letter of thanks to these little donors. It would be a matter of great satisfaction if all other Free Thought schools would follow their example! The benefit performance of the Ludvikovo Divadlo (Frantisek Ludvik's Bohemian Dramatic Society of Chicago) brought $37.45; from our branches the following sums have been received recently: Milwaukee, $100; Baltimore, $300; and Detroit, $139.32.</p>
   <p>Associations and bodies delegating a representative to the Narodni Sdruzeni [Twelve Free Thought bodies contributing amounts ranging from five to two hundred dollars, a total of $485]. Other associations through newspapers <pb facs="5418478_6_1342.jpg" n="4"/>[Six donations, total $232.43].</p>
   <p>The amounts received from collection forms will be acknowledged in a few days. Our receipts during the month of July were $1,196.40, but much more was collected in associations, particularly women's organizations, and the money is not yet in our hands.</p>
   <p>Our Bohemian businessmen and shopkeepers will be given a supply of national one-cent stamps in the next few days for them to sell. All our organizations and individual countrymen are requested to use these stamps on all their correspondence and thus contribute to the success of this national tax. The stamp is of fine appearance, designed by the well-known Bohemian artist, Mr. Ruzicka of New York, and it is a splendid means of propaganda. In addition to these stamps, membership emblems will be put on sale, in the form of lapel buttons for men and pins for women. These were designed by Sculptor Kratina and sell for twenty-five cents apiece. All businessmen willing to put these items on sale, please contact our secretary, Mr. J. Tvrzicky, at 2613 South Avers Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1343.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In reply to many inquiries as to who may become a member of the Narodni Sdruzeni we are glad to advise that membership in the Sdruzeni is available to every Bohemian man or woman for the payment of the minimum yearly dues of one dollar. Applications should be addressed to our secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
