<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-11-25">Nov. 25, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Another Slavic Mass Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-11-25">Nov. 25, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">ANOTHER SLAVIC MASS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Added proof of the fact that the enthusiasm for the cause of the Balkan Slavs, who are engaged in a death struggle with their oppressors, is not diminishing among us was demonstrated at yesterday's spirited meeting held. Under the auspices of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) in the spacious pavilion of the Pilsen Brewing Company.</p>
   <p>Like the Pilsen Auditorium two weeks ago, the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewing Company attracted a huge throng of men who were led by a single idea: To offer their sympathy and their money to aid a cause which is common to all of us--the liberation of the Slavs.</p>
   <p>Those gathered in yesterday's assembly were mostly Bohemians; but just the same, we saw quite a number of Yugoslavs both in the audience and on the speakers' platform.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1464.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The chairman of yesterday's meeting was the Clerk of the Probate Court, Mr. John A. Cervenka....who introduced the first speaker of the day, Mr. Jar. K. Kosar.....</p>
   <p>His words provoked stormy applause when he said that Mr. Stepina has so far received $2,200 in contributions for the Slavic Red Cross. The money was sent to Professor Pupin in New York.....</p>
   <p>The envelope collection yielded $408.15......</p>
   <p>Contributions for the Slavic cause are being solicited everywhere.....As far as our Sokols are concerned, the Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Unity) is getting ready to inaugurate a fifty-cent head tax, which, computing its membership at about seven thousand, would mean a substantial increase in <pb facs="5418478_6_1465.jpg" n="3"/>the general fund. A similar step is contemplated by the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs (Fuegner-Tyrs Sokol Division).....Why could not each of our building and loan associations declare an extra installment?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
