<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-23">Feb. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Sokol Slavsky Presents an Evening of Entertainment</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1698</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1698.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-23">Feb. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">SOKOL SLAVSKY PRESENTS AN EVENING OF ENTERTAINMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To celebrate George Washington's birthday, the Sokol Slavsky gave an evening's entertainment which met with decided success both morally and financially. Despite the fact that a great majority of the members and friends of the Sokol had to work yesterday, the hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) was well filled. The program opened with a festive overture played by the musical section of the Sokol unit. This organization, under the leadership of Brother Ropp, has attained a sufficient degree of proficiency.....</p>
   <p>The president of the local unit, Brother Miller, greeted the audience, mentioning some of the significant features of the War of Independence, which was headed by Washington; he likewise recalled the fact that it was chiefly the trained Sokols--the legionnaires--who freed Czechoslovakia from the Hapsburg yoke. The nation should therefore feel indebted to those men and <pb facs="5418478_6_1699.jpg" n="2"/>should support the local units of the Sokol organization, particularly their gymnasiums.....</p>
   <p>The musical section then played Dvorak's "Humoresque" and Hervert's "Serenade".....This was followed by miscellaneous gymnastic exercises by the adolescent members of the Sokol, who performed well with musical accompaniment.....Next on the program was Sister Kostlan, who gave a recitation concerning a legend about Bohemia.....Parts of the recitation were dramatized by choreography and national dances. A gala number on the program was a song from the opera "Dve Vdovy" (Two Widows) by Smetana, sung by our well-known artist, Mrs. Havelka. For an encore, she sang a song by Celansky and an aria from Bizet's opera, "Carmen". The musical group of the Sokol Slavsky then played a piece by Lehar; this was followed by a violin solo played by Jaroslav Sindelar, who was accompanied at the piano by Karolina Sindelar.....The women members of the Sokol then gave a performance with Indian clubs.....The final number was a gymnastic performance symbolizing the fall of a <pb facs="5418478_6_1700.jpg" n="3"/>tyrant and was combined with the recitation of a poem of the same name written by Brother Pergl at the time of the persecution of our nation. It was recited by Brother Cerny....and contained several dramatic scenes; the symbolizations of these dramatic incidents were performed by twelve Sokols under the direction of Brother Konecny.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
