<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-07-04">July 4, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku V Americe</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1745</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1745.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-07-04">July 4, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION OF THE NARODNI SVAZ CESKYCH KATOLIKU V AMERICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We, the Bohemian Catholics who are organized in the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America), whose headquarters are located in Chicago, do recollect the July 4, 1776, when the founders of our great Union laid the foundations of the movements for the people's freedom, for right and justice toward all. We recollect, especially, the great leaders of the American nation--George Washington, Abraham Lincoln, and Thomas Jefferson--who by their work, by the blood and sacrifices of the best sons of the nation, instilled a new law into the heart of the nation: the great ideals of a real democracy.</p>
   <p>We enjoy the advantages resulting from this freedom, and, therefore we, <pb facs="5418478_6_1746.jpg" n="2"/>the Bohemian Catholics of America, who have made this country our new home, who enjoy the national and religious liberties, do solemnly proclaim before the entire American public and before the whole democratic world, on the anniversary of the most significant day in this country's history, Independence Day, that with all our might, our souls, our bodies, and our fortunes, we stand behind the United States and by our esteemed President, Woodrow Wilson.</p>
   <p>To prove the genuineness and sincerity of our patriotic sentiment, we, the Bohemian Catholics who are assembled under the Star-Spangled Manner in our Catholic churches, are renewing our pledge of loyalty and devotion to the United States and its president, and we do solemnly swear:</p>
   <p>We believe in the United States, in the government of the people, by the people, and for the people. We believe in the democracy of many free <pb facs="5418478_6_1747.jpg" n="3"/>states that are united into one great inseparable Union, founded upon the principles of freedom, equality, justice, and humanity--ideals to which the American patriots consecrated their lives and fortunes. We believe, therefore, that it is our duty to love our new country, to support its Constitution, to obey its laws, to honor its flag, and to defend it against all enemies.</p>
   <p>Behind this oath we stood, we stand, and we shall stand in the life's struggles, because the ideals of America are our ideals.</p>
   <p>For the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe:</p>
   <p>Jan Straka, President,</p>
   <p>Reverend Fr. Zozenek, Secrctary,</p>
   <p>Anton Vaclav Tesar, Manager of</p>
   <p>the headquarters. Chicago, July 4, 1920.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
