<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-06">Feb. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0228</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0228.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-06">Feb. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Benevolent Association) was held last Friday. In the chairman's absence, vice-chairman Mr. Stanislav J. Loula presided.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the previous meeting were accepted as read. Miss Marie Hutter presented her managerial report, which shows that during the last fourteen days twenty-four persons received free lodging for the night; three persons received free medical treatment; one person was sent to the County Hospital; five persons were referred to the county agent; fifteen families received coal; twenty-four letters were written; cases of five families were turned over to the juvenile court; one child was placed in an orphanage; nine persons applied for work, and work was secured for most of the applicants. In addition a large number of people were outfitted with underwear, shoes, and clothing.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0229.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At this meeting $264.92 was voted to pay rents of indigent families. The matter of trying to secure a position for a Czech in the county superintendent's office was taken under advisement. A suggestion was made that it might be very beneficial if a Czech should take the next civil service examination for the positon of assistant superintendent at the county office.</p>
   <p>Mr. Petr Drije is donating $7.10 which he paid as his share of the expense during the street carnival.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Vaclav Vanek, secretary of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, received a check for $100 for services and other expenses during the year. He returned a check for $50 to be applied to the credit of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, which amount was gratefully accepted by the trustees.</p>
   <p>Dr. Solomon Rosenblatt is offering free medical service to all Czech indigents recommended by the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0230.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A motion made by Anton J. Cermak that no checks be issued for rents due until every case is thoroughly investigated was recommended and passed.</p>
   <p>The trustees are making an appeal for donations of used clothing, shoes, and underwear. A large number of people are in need of these items and the Dobrocinna Spolecnost has no stock on hand.</p>
   <p>The Dobrocinna Spolecnost is asking Czech doctors who are willing to donate their services to register in the office of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost.</p>
   <p>A special meeting of the directors will be held on February 16. The yearly meeting will be held on January 18, at which time officers for the forthcoming year will be elected, and vacated seats on the directorate filled. The officials of the Pilsen Brewing Company are donating $25 to the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, which amount was sent to the Pilsen Brewing Company in payment of rent for the ballroom used for the charity ball <pb facs="5418478_6_0231.jpg" n="4"/>of the Dobrocinna.</p>
   <p>Receipts: Mr. Frantisek G. Hajicek, 3339 West 26th Street, $25; Pilsen Brewing Company, $25; Reverend Vaclav Vanek, $50; John F. Lalla Company, 809 West Randolph Street, $25; Veronica Maur sent through the offices of the Daily Svornost, $1; Builders Brick Company, 118 North La Salle Street, $25; Mr. J. Pachman, 3541 West 26th Street, $5; Benevolent Circle Cerchov, 3422 West 26th Street, $25; Mr. Roman Sedlacek, 2556 Albany Avenue, $5; the Denni Hlasatel sent the following contributions: M.T., $2.50; Mr. Frantisek Moudry, Algoma, Wisconsin, $1; Mr. Josef Srb, Oakland, Minnesota, $50; Obcansky Klub "Pokrok" (Progress Citizen's Club), $1; a total of $5; interest on cash deposited at the Lawndale State Bank, $6.20.</p>
   <p>Total receipts $197.20. Expenditures: checks numbered 3692 and 3625 in the sum of $264.92 were approved for payment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
