<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-23">July 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Worthy of Imitation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0614</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0614.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-23">July 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">WORTHY OF IMITATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The office of the Bohemian Charitable Association reported to us the following example worthy of imitation in the interest of our misfortune-stricken countrymen and particularly in their public intermediary, The Bohemian Charitable Association. The report concerns a generous act, a collection taken at a family entertainment. The family of Mr. V. Kobzina, a business man, at the present time is vacationing at their summer home in Union Pier, Michigan. Miss Libuse Hajek, of Chicago, came to visit them there. Miss Hajek being a friend of Miss Libuse Kobzina, and on the occasion of her visit, she arranged a surprise party in honor of the last named which was attended by friends living in the neighborhood. While the gaiety was at its height, after agreement with Miss Kobzina, Miss Hajek pointed out to those present that it is not the good fortune of all our countrymen to rejoice in life because of temporary hardships, whether or not they are brought on by themselves. Our Bohemian Charitable <pb facs="5418478_6_0615.jpg" n="2"/>Association looks after the alleviation of this suffering, and it in turn needs the cooperation and generosity of the entire Bohemian public. Consequently, the Bohemian Charitable Association should be remembered on all opportune occasions. Miss Hajek confirmed her words immediately by action, starting a collection by being the first to contribute. The other guests having made their contributions, it was found that a total of eight dollars had been collected. The money was turned over to Mrs. Marie Kobzina, who in turn sent it to the office of the Bohemian Charitable Association. Many persons will probably say, of what good is eight dollars? However, if we consider the circumstances under which this money was collected and the purpose, we must admit that it is a meritorious deed worthy of imitation. The Charitable Association can do much good with this eight dollars, and besides this deed should please every Czech because this entertainment was attended mostly by the younger generation. We are much pleased to see that the young people take so great an interest in this noble purpose. We only hope that this example <pb facs="5418478_6_0616.jpg" n="3"/>will be followed many times, and the Association takes this means of expressing thanks for the contribution. Miss Hajek was one of the most active workers on the Bohemian Charitable Association's Tag Day. She won one of the prizes offered for the largest collection on that day. She donated her prize toward the benefit of the Association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
