<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-15">May 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">For Our Native Lands</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0325</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0325.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-15">May 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FOR OUR NATIVE LANDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The collection conducted by the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance) is progressing successfully. Alas, however, more so outside of Chicago than in the city itself. The largest donation this week came from Omaha, Nebraska. The local Narodni Sdruzni there sent $500 to the Chicago office. This sum was collected through the efforts of the Pokrok Zapadu (Progress of the West). The other collection headquarters in Omaha, the Cesky Fond (Bohemian Fund), conducted by the Osveta Americka (American Enlightment), has already sent $1,750 to Europe and has $1,567.80 on hand. It appears that our western compatriots are at the head of the movement, although it is to be hoped that their collections will now be larger because the systematic solicitation is just now getting under way. Both the western and eastern communities can still serve as an example to Chicago, even though commendable work is also being done here.</p>
   <p>Next week collection activities will be started by our ladies and our sokols, <pb facs="5418478_6_0326.jpg" n="2"/>and it is to be hoped that there will not be a countryman who shirks the simple and natural duty of a national tax. Again we appeal to our better situated countrymen, especially our bankers, lawyers, physicians, and businessmen who have but to fill out a check, just a few words, and send it to the American State Bank or to any of the officers of the Sdruzeni.</p>
   <p>Another substantial donation came from Sokol Karel Jonas, of Morton Park--$125.10, the net profits of the entertainment given on Sunday, April 24. Many thanks! [Four donations coming from freethinking societies, totaling $18, are listed. These, together with collection lists reporting donations ranging from 25 cents to $15, are omitted in translation.] Our receipts of the week amount to $668.10, and we express our sincere thanks to all contributors.....</p>
   <p>The national stamp issue of the Narodni Sdruzeni will be ready within the next few days. The stamp was designed by the well-known Bohemian-American artist, Mr. Ruzicka, of New York. These stamps should be affixed to letters <pb facs="5418478_6_0327.jpg" n="3"/>and serve as a means of propaganda for the political action among our countrymen. The stamps may be ordered from our secretary.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frantisek Kopecky, representative of the London Bohemians, will arrive in Chicago today. He is bringing us a report on the campaign for liberation undertaken by our British friends. Mr. Kopecky has made a lecture tour of some eastern Bohemian communities; his last lectures were in Boston and Baltimore. He has been active in our national problems since the beginning of the war, particularly in the endeavor to have our countrymen recognized as Bohemians, not Austrians, and a nation friendly to the English. He is a member of the British Army which he joined with many other London Bohemians. It is quite possible that he will be sent to the Western Front upon his return to London.</p>
   <p>Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni</p>
   <p>J. Tvrzicky-Kramer, Secretary,</p>
   <p>2613 South Avers Avenue,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
