<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-09-24">Sept. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Competitions and Convention of the Fugner-Tyrs Gymnastic Group</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Fugner-Tyrs Group Wants to Withdraw from the Czech Sokol Community and Publish its Own Journal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-09-24">Sept. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">COMPETITIONS AND CONVENTION OF THE FUGNER-TYRS GYMNASTIC GROUP</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Fugner-Tyrs Group Wants to Withdraw From the Czech Sokol Community and Publish Its Own Journal</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The gymnastic competitions and the convention of the Fugner-Tyrs Gymnastic Group began yesterday in the park of the Pilsen Brewery at 26th Street and Albany Avenue.</p>
   <p>The contests among the gymnasts proceeded from 7 o'clock in the morning and were witnessed by many guests and delegates to the convention which however did not begin until late in the afternoon. Contests were held on all the apparatus, broad jump, high jump, running etc., and both the advanced and junior departments participated. Outside of Chicago the following societies were represented: Mladocech from Detroit; Gymnastic Society from Coal City and Palacky from Detroit.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1514.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Contestants participating in these competitions are: ....</p>
   <p>Sokol Dolezal, president of the Miroslav Tyrs Sokol Group, in the presence of the delegates brought the convention to order at about four o'clock in the afternoon with a suitable address. Mr. Joseph Cermak, for the National Sokol Union, thanked the convention for the invitation. Elections were then held and Sokol Dolezal was elected chairman of the convention; Sokol Mejda, vice chairman; Sokol Ditrt, secretary; Sokol Martinek, assistant secretary.....</p>
   <p>Sokol Treska, from Sokol Palacky of Detroit, introduced various motions for the amendment of the bylaws. It was resolved that local delegates should be allowed to represent only one out-of-town society.</p>
   <p>A motion was made that the Fuegner-Tyrs Group should withdraw from the Czech Sokol Community, because there are no advantages derived therefrom, indeed, all the resources of the Group are exhausted and its existence threatened.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1515.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Sokol Ditrt spoke against the motion, saying that it was not possible to expect much in such a short time and protesting against all such motions. The debate was participated in by other delegates.</p>
   <p>In the course of the debate concerning withdrawal from the Sokol Community, the journal Straz Sokola (Sokol Sentinel) was mentioned and the complaint registered that the journal costs too much. The question as to whether or not it would be more advantageous to return to the old system and again publish a journal for the Fuegner-Tyrs Group, because the Straz Sokola dedicates very little attention to the Group, was debated. A committee was then elected which is to investigate whether or not a separate journal should be published for the Groups.</p>
   <p>The convention was adjourned at six o'clock in the evening and will reconvene today.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
