<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-01-24">Jan. 24, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Distribution of Funds in Cherry, Ill. --Mrs. Marie Liska, Reports on the Distribution of Money Collected by the Bohemian Ladies Societies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0669</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0669.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-01-24">Jan. 24, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">DISTRIBUTION OF FUNDS IN CHERRY, ILL. --MRS. MARIE LISKA, REPORTS ON THE DISTRIBUTION OF MONEY COLLECTED BY THE BOHEMIAN LADIES SOCIETIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1--A week ago, we published a report of the generous gift, donated by our Ladies Societies, to the widows and orphans of the coal-miners of Cherry, Ill. The Union of Bohemian Ladies collected $203.25 and the Sisterhood Benevolent Society, $87. Both organizations turned the money over to Mrs. Liska, who then had $290.25 at her disposal.</p>
   <p>This sum she distributed according to the following report, which she made to the public and to her organizations.</p>
   <p>During her stay in Cherry, Mrs. Liska carefully studied conditions existing there. She made inquiries, and in that way arrived at the following conclusions: that no widow, no orphan and in fact no survivor of the unfortunate victims of the catastrophe needs to suffer with hunger or cold; that families are now better provided with necessities than when their supporters were alive.</p>
   <p>The entrance to the mine, where 168 bodies are still buried, is closed at present. The widows held a meeting on the 16th of this month, at which lawyers <pb facs="5418478_6_0670.jpg" n="2"/>and representatives of the company owning the mine were present. As Mrs. Liska was told, the widows were offered compensation, if they would not insist upon the removal of the remains of their dear ones from the mine. The widows however refused to accede to this.</p>
   <p>Numerous families of the survivors have already moved away from Cherry. Some of the widows informed Mrs. Liska, that they will remain there as long as they continue to receive aid from philanthropic or other sources. As soon as that ends, they will move.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Liska in her report writes: "It's an old saying, that it is better to give, than to receive, but here it ought to be just the reverse."</p>
   <p>Mrs. Liska, ought to further explain this sentence.</p>
   <p>Finally Mrs. Liska, thanked Mrs. M. Hodan, of Chicago and Mrs. Katherine Bednarik, of Kengley, Ill., who accompanied her and were of assistance in Cherry, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
