<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-25">Oct. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">For Charity</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech Artists at Harrison High School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0184</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0184.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-25">Oct. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FOR CHARITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech Artists at Harrison High School</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The rules of Chicago schools forbid any admission to be charged for programs arranged on school grounds. An exception was made last night when an "Academy" was given under the auspices of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Czech Benevolent Association) at the Carter H. Harrison High School. [By "Academy" is meant a program in which music, poetry and other intellectual entertainments are offered.] This charitable enterprise was a complete success. The spacious main hall was filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>The Harrison High School orchestra opened with the anthem "America," which was enthusiastically sung by the audience. A medley of Czech folk songs followed, after which Mrs. Marie Sokol, the chairman, explained the aim and endeavor of the Benevolent Association.</p>
   <p>Miss Emily Janovska presented motifs from Czech folklore as arranged by Albert <pb facs="5418478_6_0185.jpg" n="2"/>J. Havranek. This number was chanted with musical accompaniment, and it drew stormy applause. Mr. Joseph Houdek, a well-known musician, played "Adagio," by Simandl, and "Impromptu," by Kukla, on the contrabass in true virtuoso style. The discordant piano accompaniment could not mar the performance. Mrs. Julia Geringer, an accomplished organist, played "Cyprise," by Bendl, and "When the Boys Come Home," by Speaks.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cermak urged the audience to prove their patriotism by bountiful subscriptions to the Second Liberty Loan. His words were lustily acclaimed.</p>
   <p>The high point of the evening was the violin solo rendered by Mr. Vaclav Machek, one of the foremost artists of our Czech Chicago community. He played J. Hubay's phantasy on the opera "Carmen". He had to yield to the clamorous demands for an encore.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Margaret Jiskra rendered "Vltava" from Smetana's immortal "My Homeland," a series of six symphonic poems. Mrs. Jiskra, who is a well-known virtuoso on the <pb facs="5418478_6_0186.jpg" n="3"/>harp, played the arrangement for that instrument by Kaan.</p>
   <p>Joseph Z. Uhlir, judge of the municipal court, reminded the audience of the fact that because of the war, the Czech Benevolent Association will not hold its annual ball, and will therefore lose the resources provided by that entertainment. It will be imperative for the Czech public to give its full support to the contest which is being conducted by the Benevolent Association with the co-operation of Czech businessmen. "Every Czech," the judge declared, "should ask for contest coupons and should urge the businessman with whom he trades to buy some of them from the Association."</p>
   <p>The next number on the program was "Venkovske Obrazky" (Scenes from the Countryside), by Malat, which was played by the quartet composed of Mr. Vaclav Machek, V. Pavlas, E. Lestina, and Mrs. B. Machek.</p>
   <p>The Czech singing society Smetana presented two choruses: "Klucina," by an unknown composer, and "Nase Probuzeni" (Our awakening), by the talented young <pb facs="5418478_6_0187.jpg" n="4"/>Czech Chicago composer, Stephen A. Erst, who directed both numbers. The singers were rewarded with noisy applause.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Slavka Svoboda, well-known Czech actress, gave a charming performance of "Poor Butterfly". Mrs. Svoboda was assisted by eight ladies. The audience showed its appreciation by stormy applause. A one-act burlesque, "Medved Namluvcim" (The Bear as a Wooer), by Kril, was played by Mrs. and Mr. Svoboda, Mr. Henry Weidner, and Mr. Zalovsky.</p>
   <p>All the costumes for the evening were loaned free of charge by Mrs. Antonia Dittert, owner of the establishment at 1136 West 18th Street. Mr. Anton Brousek's orchestra also donated its services.</p>
   <p>The charity program was a complete success in every respect.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
