<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-21">June 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Big Manifestation by the Bohemian Catholic Alliance of the Arch-Diocese of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1523</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1523.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-21">June 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">BIG MANIFESTATION BY THE BOHEMIAN CATHOLIC ALLIANCE OF THE ARCH-DIOCESE OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting held by the Bohemian Catholic Alliance in the Bohemian-American Hall succeeded remarkably. The meeting was begun with Mr. Joseph Pech's orchestra playing an overture. After this the meeting was called to order by the president of the Alliance Dr. Vaclav Chvatal.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jan Straka was the next speaker. He reviewed in detail the history of the past ten years of the Bohemian Catholic Alliance of America. He mentioned the convention of the Alliance held in St. Louis ten years ago, the difficulties which arose, and the final realization of the Alliance idea a year ago.</p>
   <p>Following this the choir of St. Procopius community, under the direction of Mr. A. Petru, sang "Zpevy Lidu Ceskeho" (Songs of the Bohemian People).</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1524.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Another speaker, for the Federation of Catholic Societies in the United States, was Thomas Cannon, Grand Chief Ranger of the Catholic Foresters. He greeted the Alliance, in the name of the Federation and explained briefly the merits of the Federation and its task of the future. The recess was filled in with the band playing an overture after which, in the same sense, former Judge Girten spoke for the Federation of German Societies (Central Verein), of the United States. The Right Reverend Bishop J. J. Koudelka, of Cleveland, Ohio, was the principal speaker for the Alliance. At the conclusion of his address the band played "Kde domov muj," which everyone sang.</p>
   <p>That the local Catholic world is giving the Alliance a great deal of attention was evident from the number of visitors present at the meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
