<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-09-16">Sept. 16, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">A Fine State of Affairs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0704</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0704.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-09-16">Sept. 16, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">A FINE STATE OF AFFAIRS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our youth, as a rule, always shows plenty of life, therefore, it is needless for us to announce especially, that the youth of our Bohemian Pilsen were lively yesterday. Yes, our Pilsen youth were active yesterday, they were so active, that many did not like it.</p>
   <p>Our new reading room on Blue Island Avenue enjoys the marked attention of all who find pleasure in literature. As a result, it is not strange that even the walks around the reading room are crowded every evening. Alas, that it is not readers in search of culture who crowd the walks, but rabble, in truth, rabble, which shouts, argues and fights here, as though the front of our reading room was designated for that purpose so that the outcasts of our youth might create their tumult there. Hundreds of youth gathered about the reading room yesterday and took upon themselves the purpose of annoying the readers in the reading room. They pounded on the windows and created such a racket that not one word could be heard inside. It went so far, that the manager of the reading <pb facs="5418478_6_0705.jpg" n="2"/>room was forced to telephone to the police station and request a special guard. That something unusual was happening here is apparent from the fact that two members of the Library Board were also called and were much surprised over the way our local youth acted. If we did not know that the youth gathered around the reading room were Bohemian, perhaps we could ignore such proceedings with silence.</p>
   <p>However, since we know that they are almost all children of Bohemian parents, and that it is being pointed out from the standpoint of other nationalities, we must call it to the attention of our Bohemian parents, whose duty it is to hold their children in check. Yesterday, the disturbance reached such proportions that the Canalport police station was requested to give special attention to the place. Since many Bohemian parents did not have so much regard thus far as to warn their children against disturbing the peace, they will be forced to do so now, when the police will work to maintain order, where there should be order.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
