<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-05-22">May 22, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Tribune Article on Czechs Causes Displeasure</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0924</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0924.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-05-22">May 22, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">TRIBUNE ARTICLE ON CZECHS CAUSES DISPLEASURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 4 -- The Sunday Tribune had two pages, in small print, about the Czechs in the Plzen (Pilsen) district. We always welcome a just, favorable mention in the English papers, but the article in the Tribune, be it, from the point of view of that paper, ever so sympathetic, could not fill our hearts with much joy or even with satisfaction. In reading it we felt rather peevish, for the writer pictures us according to his own conception and not as we really are. That our districts make a favorable impression upon the unbiased observer, we are ready to believe. Clean streets, nicely fitted out houses, stores testifying to businesslike endeavor, assiduousness, and ability, these things cannot remain unobserved, and they must mean even more, as they represent everything we possess here, the results of strenuous work, painstaking thrift, and diligent cultural education. Ours is no property inherited, or the profit from any haphazard speculation, but the fruits of manifold efforts. From the article in the Tribune, however, one should gather, that we have a leaning towards the churches, and what a multitude of churches and parochial schools we are supporting, and how we flock for Sunday service. The article concludes by the statement that every Czech is a Sokol (of the gymnastic society). Children, lads and lassies are supposed to be ardent <pb facs="5418478_6_0925.jpg" n="2"/>members of gymnastic clubs. O, if it only were so! What is said in the article of alderman Hurt we do not care to mention. The Czechs just chuckled, and in the opinion of other nationalities - for whom it was evidently written - it cannot but profit Mr. Hurt, which we wholeheartedly wish for him. We think, however, that when newspapers undertake the printing of treatises on immigrant nationalities they should entrust the writing to able representatives of the respective nationalities. Such articles would then not be teeming with lies and clotted nonsense, they would not be trite, they would on the contrary render considerable service to said nationalities and, at the same time, offer valuable truthful information. The type of essay as offered by the Tribune last Sunday merits only a cursory glance and then the waste basket.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
