<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-02-23">Feb. 23, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">News from Our Plzen</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Pilsen Auditorium Building Changes Hands</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0753</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0753.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-02-23">Feb. 23, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM OUR PLZEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Pilsen Auditorium Building Changes Hands</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Pilsen auditorium building, located on Blue Island Avenue, between 16th and 18th Streets, which was the property of the Borivoj Building and Loan Association until recently and which was the cause of a sad experience and disappointment to the members of the association, finally changed hands. Thus, at least something will be saved for the shareholders of the above-mentioned association. And there is no doubt that the shareholders will be glad that this unpleasant matter will come to an end, even though they know that the association will not receive as much for the building as could have been obtained not long ago when a large real-estate establishment offered them the sum of sixty thousand dollars. The board of directors at that time did not accept the offer. Consequently, to the detriment of the association, the building remained unsold until now, when it became the property of an altogether different enterprise. But we take pleasure in informing you that <pb facs="5418478_6_0754.jpg" n="2"/>the enterprise is entirely Bohemian.</p>
   <p>The building, the erection of which originally cost about sixty thousand dollars and various alterations almost an equal sum, was sold to the Lawndale Amusement Company, now located at 22nd and Troy Streets, for the sum of $32,500. The deal was closed in the office of Anton Vanek and Sons, real-estate brokers, 3707 West 26th Street.</p>
   <p>The Borivoj Building and Loan Association received $16,500 in cash and made a first mortgage for the remaining sum of $16,000, which will be payable at the rate of $300 a month.</p>
   <p>The officers of the above-mentioned company, which has become the owner of the Pilsen auditorium, are the following countrymen: Mr. Bohumil Mudra, <pb facs="5418478_6_0755.jpg" n="3"/>president; Mr. James F. Mudra, secretary; and Mr. John Ungerman, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The new company will establish a new restaurant, a new billiard room, and about thirty-two bowling alleys on the premises. It will be the most modern establishment of its kind on the Southwest Side.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
