<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-02">Nov. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Our Singers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1396</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1396.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-02">Nov. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SINGERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (Federation of Bohemian Singing Societies) held its usual annual conference in Mr. Zajicek's hall on 22nd Street and Sawyer Avenue. The Jednota comprises seven societies each of which is entitled to three delegates.....</p>
   <p>The program started with an address by President Anton Vanek....who stressed the fact that our singing societies have just as prominent a role in our national life as the Sokols. They are purely national bodies which have practically no other purpose but to promote national consciousness and pride through the cultivation of Bohemian music and song, and through proper methods of appearing before the public...</p>
   <p>Secretary Kosar presented a detailed report on the activities of the Jednota....including its brief history.....It was founded December 13, 1906.....Its greatest success was a visit to St. Louis, where a concert was arranged, in <pb facs="5418478_6_1397.jpg" n="2"/>which over one hundred singers took part.....After this, a reaction set in which, fortunately, is being overcome during these times.....</p>
   <p>Last year's activities comprised participation in the Olympic games at Grant Park, June 29, 1913. An excursion to Hanso Park was arranged the following July 13, then there was a concert in the Pilsen Sokol hall on November 27 which met with tremendous moral success. A real triumph was the production of Dvorak's monumental work, "Stabat Mater," in Sokol Chicago hall on May 10. The Jednota participated in celebrations marking the end of the teachers' course of the Slovanska Gymnasticka Unie (Slavic Gymnastic Union) May 16, and in the Tyrs memorial in the Pilsen Park pavilion August 7. There were a number of minor concerts.....Thus it may be said that the Jednota has been developing an almost feverish activity this past year.....</p>
   <p>The Jednota's active membership now consists of 144 men and 96 women. Its library contains music for seven orchestral compositions, 146 choirs, and 301 other large compositions, in addition to a large number of minor musical <pb facs="5418478_6_1398.jpg" n="3"/>works valued at $500.</p>
   <p>The report of the technical committee gives a very good picture of the difficulties connected with the presentation of Dvorak's "Stabat Mater". There were twenty-five rehearsals held, covering a period of nine months.</p>
   <p>When the program of the meeting reached the discussion of ways and means by which the Jednota should co-operate with the war-relief action, our singers again showed that they are among the first to support a good thing.....The meeting approved the donation of $200 from the treasury, which amount will subsequently be returned from the collections which each individual society will take among its own members. It was decided that the money be sent to the Ceska Obec Sokolska (Bohemian Sokol Association) [in the old country], which is certainly the most competent body to undertake its distribution among the poor. The Pevecka Jednota will also help by being active at the public drill which the Narodno Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Union) will present in <pb facs="5418478_6_1399.jpg" n="4"/>the Pilsen Park pavilion on November 15.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
