<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-06">Apr. 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Mass Meeting Called by the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of America in Pilsen Park Pavilion Was Well-Attended and Had a Stormy Proceeding</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1111</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1111.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-06">Apr. 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S MASS MEETING CALLED BY THE CZECHOSLOVAK LEGIONNAIRES OF AMERICA IN PILSEN PARK PAVILION WAS WELL-ATTENDED AND HAD A STORMY PROCEEDING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Long before the stipulated hour set for the mass meeting, called by the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of America and held in the Pilsen Park Pavilion, the hall began to fill with people and by the time the meeting opened every seat was taken and many people were standing. As soon as the meeting was called to order by Mr. Ludvik Kaderka, president of the Legionnaires, it was noticeable that the atmosphere was very tense and only a little spark was needed to touch off the storm in all its fury. Several timesit almost came to that, but thanks to the energetic and quick interference of the above-named president, it was warded off in time, although often with great difficulty. In opening the meeting, Mr. Kaderka assured the audience that the Legionnaires are fully aware of their duty toward our people. They are far <pb facs="5418478_6_1112.jpg" n="2"/>from wanting to destroy, in fact they want to build; they yearn for fruitful and useful work. However, they are interested in national purgation and they consider it as their sacred duty to take this purgation into their own hands and to carry it out to the finish. Mr. Kaderka then introduced the first speaker, Doctor Jaroslav E. Salaba Vojan, whose speech we publish in full. He said, "I am going to speak without any oratorical embellishments. The matter under consideration is of vast importance. Oratorical embellishments may temporarily arouse, and bring the spontaneous applause of the audience, but today neither I nor any of the speakers to follow, can be interested in that. I am not speaking to you alone, ladies and gentlemen, but I am speaking to the conscience of all freethinking Czechsin America.</p>
   <p>"This meeting was called by the Legionnaires. Did they have the right to call it? I think that they did. In the resolution of the Executive Committee of the Americka Obec Sokolska (American Sokol Unity), national undiscipline is <pb facs="5418478_6_1113.jpg" n="3"/>spoken about and the District Committee of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe (Czechoslovak National Alliance of America) even speaks about the subversive work of Legionnaires and unanimously condemns it. Please consider impartially! When we, here in Chicago, greeted the first hundred returning Czechoslovak Siberian Legionnaires, and when they told us that the Legionnaires as a whole were very anxious to return home to Czechoslovakia, because they are needed there to help reform the prevailing conditons in the Czechoslovak Republic, when these, our guests, repeatedly proclaimed that they would clean house, they were applauded by Bohemian-Chicago, Bohemian-New York, and in fact by all of Bohemian-America. Do not you think that when all of the Czechoslovak Siberian Legionnaires return to Czechoslovakia and really start to clean house, there will be many people in Czechoslovakia who will proclaim it as a national undisciplined and subversive work?</p>
   <p>"Legally, these people will be in the right! In Czechoslovakia today, elections are held. The elected representatives will be lawful representatives of the <pb facs="5418478_6_1114.jpg" n="4"/>nation; they alone will be able to decide on matters of its destinies and the Legionnaires, as a small minority of several tens of thousands, must subject themselves. That is the language of the law. Are not your feelings enraged? The feeling rings in your ears that those men, who by their own blood and by the blood of their fallen comrades, furnished the most solid material for the foundation of the Czechoslovak Republic--who by their own blood forced the Allies and their diplomats to respect the demands of the Czechoslovak nation--who in the trenches and in the hell of battle sacrificed much more than those who worked in safety at home, and have more than a legal right to voice their opinions. We must not forget that the Legionnaires are 'Deti Masarykovy' (Masaryk's children). The expression 'Taticek Masaryk' (Father Masaryk), although brought to life in Prague on the sixtieth anniversary of President Masaryk's birthday, it was nationalized only through the efforts of the Legionnaires. Here in Chicago, President Thomas G. Masaryk twice publicly proclaimed, the first time at the Harrison High School and the next time at the Auditorium, that the Czech soldiers fully aroused his conscience <pb facs="5418478_6_1115.jpg" n="5"/>as to his duties and as we see today, history tells us that in the year of 1915, at the meeting of young men held in Geneva, Switzerland, President Masaryk said: 'You go and fight! If I were younger, I would take a gun and go into the trenches.' These words laid the foundation of his relationship with the Legionnaires and, therefore, the Legionnaires are his children. Does Bohemian-America think that there are two kinds of Masaryk children? Are only those who return to Czechoslovakia his children, and are those who remain among us in America his stepchildren who can be ignored by us? Of course not! Therefore, I say: the Czechoslovak Legionnaires have the right to ask for a reformation of our national institutions.</p>
   <p>"They have more than a legal right, because they do not want to harm anything but only to reform it. I accepted the invitation to be a speaker at this meeting because in a preliminary meeting of the Legionnaires, they proclaimed: 'We do not want to harm the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe; we wish that it may last for a long time, but we want to reform its policies and leadership.'</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1116.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Even when several leaders of benevolent societies and sokol circles expressed their opinion by saying that it will be a difficult task to regain the confidence of our societies in the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, the Legionnaires again proclaimed that they believe it is possible and that they will persist upon it. This surely is not a subversive thought! For exactly that reason, I accepted the task of speaker.</p>
   <p>"I hereby declare that the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe is our most needed institution, because there are many tasks ahead of us which none of our benevolent and sokol organizations could attempt to bring to a successful end. All that is needed is to definitely designate the tasks of the Cesko-slovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, so that no work is uselessly duplicated by the activities of any other organization. I also think that the branches of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe should not be listed on paper only, but that all of these branches should be active and energetic. To keep them active, many inducements should be offered to them by the headquarters.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1117.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"I defend the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe not only as the secretary of the first conference held in Cleveland, Ohio, the place of its birth where at that time I was elected as its first secretary, not only as a former editor of Slavie and editor of the Czechoslovanic Benevolent Societies' Organ, who in these publications battled for the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe against the Catholics, and against Dr. Frantisek Iska, but first of all, I defend the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe as one of the historians of Bohemian-America who always regretted the passing out of existence of such institutions as were the National Committee and the Bohemian-American Press Bureau. Were these organizations still in existence, many a good deed might have been done by them and much energy might now have been saved. I also defend the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe as a Bohemian-American who longs for the development of sound relations with our native land. The passing out of existence or the incompetence of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe could create a bad impression in Czechoslovakia and we would be judged as incapable of a more intensive life. Our relations with our native land still are not such <pb facs="5418478_6_1118.jpg" n="8"/>as they should be. In the book, soon to be published in Prague, I openly say that people in our native land do not comprehend the sacrifices made by Bohemian-America for the liberation cause and that they are not striving for a closer and more sincere contact with such a meritorious branch of the Czechoslovak nation as is Bohemian-America. To improve this contact, is one of the great tasks of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, it is necessary to specify the ideals of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe more definitely. [Mr.] Vojta Benes, at the convention held in November, 1919, said, 'As far as free thought is concerned, I think it would be a mistake to proclaim the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe as a freethinking organization at the present time, because we are just about half way toward our goal. It is necessary to preserve the politico-nationalistic tendency of our organization at any cost.' These words could have been spoken during the first two years of the World War, when the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe was the only and supreme organization, <pb facs="5418478_6_1119.jpg" n="9"/>when we did not have the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics in America) nor the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe (Czechoslovak National Council in America), the latter being superior to the Ceskovlovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe.</p>
   <p>"When, on May 16, 1917, the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe came into existence and the Board, now the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe, was made the supreme all-nationalistic organization, this impossible state of conditions commenced. We have now an all-nationalistic organization, the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe, uniting the Slovaks, Catholics, and the characteristically uncertain Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, whose all-nationalism thereby disappears. If the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe wishes to continue to be an all-nationalistic organization, then we have two all-nationalistic organizations, upper, the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe, and, lower, the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe. We have a Catholic organization but we have no--free thought organization!</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1120.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>"This does not correspond with actual conditions in Bohemian-America. Tomas Capek, who is known as an impartial observer, in his recently published book, The Czechs in America (page 119), states that fifty per cent of all the Czech-Americans are freethinkers, but he also says that it is his opinion, and I agree with him, that there are probably sixty or seventy per cent freethinkers. It is a fact that we freethinkers are in the majority just now. It is a historical fact that we freethinkers carried the entire burden of the liberation action ourselves from august, 1914 to May, 1917--and for all that we, the freethinkers, do not have the Cesko-slovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe as our own organization, an organization equal to that of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe, nor do we have in the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe a proper representation corresponding with the actual conditions. Today, the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe is without a president; the acting president is a Catholic priest. Today, when the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe is officially represented in public, a Catholic priest speaks in the name of, and represents, Bohemian-America. Is it healthful to continue for long such a state of affairs?</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1121.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>"Only this would be proper: Let us have an all-national organization, such as is the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe. Its president should be an adherent of the free thought movement and he should represent Bohemian-America. In the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe the following groups should be represented: Slovaks by their league; Catholics by their national alliance; Protestants by their organization, and Freethinkers by the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe. He who says that this is not a reasonable demand and a progressive movement, I say is a hypocrite!</p>
   <p>"In that way no dispute will be dragged into the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe. The Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, as a free thought organization, does not have to be a warlike organization any more than the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe. Matters of an aggressive nature can be taken care of by the Volna Myslenka (Free Thought) and the Svaz Svobodomyslnych (Freethinkers Alliance), respectively. The Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe will have many other tasks concerning free thought on its <pb facs="5418478_6_1122.jpg" n="12"/>hands and, therefore, neither the Catholics nor the Protestants will protest. If the Protestants start their own organization, it will be to their benefit. How many Protestants are active in the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe today? Scarcely a dozen of them! when they have their own organization, then they may develop more intensive activity and the ambiguity of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, will fall away.</p>
   <p>"Tasks of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, as announced by its president, should be as follows:</p>
   <p>"(a) To keep in contact with the Czechoslovak Republic and to give assistance whenever it is necessary.</p>
   <p>"(b) To unite all Czechoslovak groups in America against false Americanism.</p>
   <p>"(c) To educate the Czechoslovak people in matters of politics, to inform the American public about the Czechoslovak nation, and to protect its interest <pb facs="5418478_6_1123.jpg" n="13"/>at every opportunity.</p>
   <p>"(d) To demonstrate loyalty to the United States and Canada at every opportunity.</p>
   <p>"(e) I hereby quote this paragraph word for word: 'It is necessary that the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe give their utmost assistance to the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Rada v Americe in order to strengthen and to maintain its activity. This organization should be the joint representative of all Czechoslovak organizations and should be the voice of the Czechoslovak people in America.'</p>
   <p>"It sounds beautiful, but it only shows the confused situation of today. The Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada v Americe should be the representative and speaker, but, nevertheless, it is asked of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe to remain an all-nationalistic organization! Understand it, you who can--I cannot.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1124.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>"If the duties of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe are definitely outlined, it will be an easy task to arrange a program of its work. Today it is impossible, because the duties of both of these organizations are not definitely defined. But we can can say this much: When something is supposed to be done by two persons, each depends upon the other, and in the end no one does it!</p>
   <p>"Outline a specific, workable program of activities for the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe for the future, so that the headquarters, the district committee, and all the branches may know exactly what to do. Give this activity an ideal of free thought structure; ask all sincere, earnest workers to co-operate and appeal to all societies to support your need! Our Bohemian-American life centers around our societies, and if they go along with you, you have succeeded! Without the support of fraternal societies, sokols, women's societies, etc., nothing can be done. It will not be an easy task to seek the support of our societies, because they frequently remain indifferent when it would be better to respond. But you, as <pb facs="5418478_6_1125.jpg" n="15"/>Legionnaires, have a better chance of gaining their support; you have a better chance than anyone else.</p>
   <p>"I do not doubt that the reconstructed Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe could again gain public confidence. If it were a free thought organization, all the freethinking women's and men's societies would be obliged to support it. If the entire financial side of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe is made public--today all regard for the revolutionary action of liberation is unnecessary; today the public has the right to look into the economics of its societies--the confidence and generosity of the widest circles of freethinking people would surely be manifested in a remarkable manner. If you succeed in introducing a new, fresh spirit into the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe; if you succeed in gaining more workers who enjoy the confidence of the general public and who are earnestly willing to work, then you, brother Legionnaires, will accomplish a work of real merit. If you do not succeed in what you are attempting to do, then there is no help! Then you may say to yourselves, using the famous <pb facs="5418478_6_1126.jpg" n="16"/>proverb which is applied to journalism: 'Every people will have such societies as it deserves'."</p>
   <p>The speaker was frequently interrupted, but at the end he was rewarded with boisterous applause. Then the second speaker, Mr. James F. Stepina, took the floor. He assured the audience at the beginning of his speech, that he had no intentions of harming an organization which is so necessary to us. He said he had no personal motives, but that he was compelled to state before hand, that the present leadership in the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe is not satisfactory. He talked about the unwillingness of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe to publish the names of those who had contributed toward the national liberation fund or the amounts of the individual contributions. He related his efforts to get this information and although several times it was promised to him he did not receive it. "If the total amount collected, $325,000, has been made known, why not publish the names and amounts of individual contributions?...."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1127.jpg" n="17"/>
   <p>He concluded his speech by mentioning the Ceskoslovansky Pomocny Vybor (Czechoslavonic Aid Committee), and how financially this organization helped the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe in its most trying times. At that moment the speaker was interrupted by a passionate outburst from the audience, "What became of the money? I want to know!" The speaker assured the inquirer that all the money collected was sent directly to Thomas G. Masaryk who gave a signed receipt which he is willing to show to anyone interested. Continuing, he said that the Ceskoslovansky Pomocny Vybor was dissolved without authority by the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe. "Although in a past conference of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe the delegates resolved that the funds of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe should be given to our charitable causes, so far nothing has been done." In the treasury there is $23,000 worth of Liberty bonds besides cash on hand, the amount of which is unknown to him. Ending his speech he proclaimed, "We have gotten rid of the autocratic government of Austria-Hungary, and we shall do the same in the Ceskoslovenske Narodni v Sdruzeni v Americe!"</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1128.jpg" n="18"/>
   <p>The chairman of the meeting, Mr. Kaderka, then announced that although the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe was invited to send its representative to this meeting, it refused to do so on account of the short notice given. Mr. Kaderka then read the resolution drafted and requested those of the audience who were in favor of it to show their approval by arising. Practically the entire audience arose. While on the other hand, only about five persons arose to show their disapproval. The resolution reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"We the people assembled in the mass meeting at Pilsen Park Pavilion on April 5, manifest our concurrence with the action undertaken by the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago for the purpose of the purgation of our national life.</p>
   <p>"We approve of the demands of our Legionnaires and we protest that an institution, which pretends to be the representative of our Bohemian people in America, continue to be headed by people about whom it has been proved that during the period of national mobilization they failed to fulfill their patriotic duty and <pb facs="5418478_6_1129.jpg" n="19"/>to keep their promises, and about whom the public is convinced that they are not competent to fill such important offices at the head of a national institution as is the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe. We join in the demand of our Legionnaires and request that Messrs. Frank J. Kubec, Joseph Paskovsky, and Ferdinand L. Musil, be urged to resign their offices in the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe; we also request that the officers of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe publicly proclaim whether or not, in the future, they wish to appear in public in the role of true representatives of our progressive and freethinking people of America or if they wish to restrict their activities to those of a simple patriotic society.</p>
   <p>"We appeal to all present members of our national and sokol societies to explain and discuss the standpoint of the Czechoslovak Legionnaires at their meetings and to make an effort to secure reforms in the interest of our national cause.</p>
   <p>"After the approval of this resolution by the majority of those participating, <pb facs="5418478_6_1130.jpg" n="20"/>it should be published in our Bohemian newspapers and the contents should be made known to Bohemian journalists and official circles in Czechoslovakia.</p>
   <p>"Chicago, Illinois, April 5, 1920."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
