<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-27">Feb. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Czechoslovak National Council Gives an Explanation about the Steamship "Liberty Glo"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-27">Feb. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHOSLOVAK NATIONAL COUNCIL GIVES AN EXPLANATION ABOUT THE STEAMSHIP "LIBERTY GLO"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The shipment of gifts, which were received at the receiving depot of the Czechoslovak National Council in Chicago, was forwarded to Czechoslovakia, through the commercial department of the Consulate-General of Czechoslovakia in New York. Mr. V. J. Kubelka, manager of the commercial department, took charge of the transportation from New York to Czechoslovakia and also of the insurance.</p>
   <p>When the first report that the steamship "Liberty Glo" was lost at sea was received, officers of the Czechoslovak National Council at once sought information from Mr. Kubelka. For a long time the reports on the condition of the ship conflicted. On December 22, Mr. Kubelka wrote that according to last reports the entire shipment had been lost; immediately following this, he reported that part of the shipment would be salvaged. On January 8, he announced that the insurance company, in which the shipment was insured, <pb facs="5418478_6_0059.jpg" n="2"/>promised an early settlement. In the same communication he stated that the portion of the shipment which had been salvaged, although drenched, would be sold at auction for the benefit of the insurance company, who, in turn, would pay the full insured amounts to the senders. It surely was not in the interests of our people to have these boxes, which were hoisted from the ship drenched with salt water, sent to Czechoslovakia. In fact it was too bad that the ship, which had struck a mine, did not sink altogether. Where the cargo is not lost but only damaged, the collection of insurance is prolonged.</p>
   <p>In the last communication sent to us by Mr. Kubelka from the New York Consulate-General, on February 4, he states that the insurance company will be ready to pay compensation in about three weeks. We also call attention to the fact that even the United States Post Office was under the impression that the cargo aboard the ship "Liberty Glo" had been saved. In a letter sent to the commercial department of the Czechoslovak Consulate-General we asked for further reports which we shall announce to the public within the next few days.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0060.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Czechoslovak Consulate-General assured us that the insurance company will pay full compensation on the entire undelivered shipment.</p>
   <p>For the Ceskoslovanskou Narodni Radu v Chicagu (Czechoslovak National Council in Chicago).</p>
   <p>Reverend Innocent Kestl, president;</p>
   <p>Dr. Jaroslav F. Smetanka, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
