<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-26">July 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Emergency Relief Action for Victims of Catastrophe</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0312</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0312.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-26">July 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN EMERGENCY RELIEF ACTION FOR VICTIMS OF CATASTROPHE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting for the purpose of organizing a permanent committee for the relief of the unfortunate victims of the Saturday catastrophe is called for 2:30 P. M. today, in the hall of Sokol Pilsen on Ashland Avenue and 18th Street. Among the victims are a large number of our countrymen, and some families have lost their providers or supporters. There will be collections organized throughout the city of Chicago for these victims, and our nation, to which a large percentage of the victims belong, must not lag behind other nationalities. Therefore, it is the purpose of the undersigned to gather together at this meeting and discuss the steps that should be taken for the relief of our countrymen who are affected. All countrymen are invited who are willing to help us either by donations or by work. In most cases, financial help will be needed, but in others legal assistance, etc., may be required. Let all those who consider it their national duty to help in this emergency, come and bring with them their friends.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Anton J. Cermak, James F. Stepina, Adolph J. Sabath, <pb facs="5418478_6_0313.jpg" n="2"/>Reverend V. Vanek, John A. Cervenka, Frank G. Hajicek, John Toman, Otto Kerner, Vaclav Dibelka, Joseph A. Holpuch [and eleven other men].</p>
   <p>Chief Bailiff Anton J. Cermak reports that he has detailed a number of his assistants in his office in Room 804 in the City Hall to assist countrymen who need any information concerning the victims of the catastrophe of the Steamship "Eastland". Families whose members are still missing, those who want admission to the morgues, etc., should use the services of that office today or tomorrow. Mr. Cermak's assistants will take you to the morgues, or hospitals, and everyone will receive any available assistance free of charge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
