<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-29">June 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Proclamation to All Bohemian Freethinkers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1671</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1671.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-29">June 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A PROCLAMATION TO ALL BOHEMIAN FREETHINKERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago branch of the Svaz Svobodomyslnych (Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers) is the center of our Free Thought activities. As such it has established the usage of holding a festival and a mass meeting of all our Bohemian freethinkers during the first days of July. This custom will be continued this year and will serve as a sort of review of all the work already achieved, and as a means of laying plans for any new work confronting us during the ensuing year. It is not without significance that we have chosen just this time to hold the festival, for on July 4, 1776 the United States became an independent nation, and on July 6, 1415, the master, John Huss, suffered his martydom. Both of these significant dates will be recalled by a number of specially invited speakers who will address us in Bohemian and in English. The mass meeting will be held on July 2, 1922 in the Pilsen Park pavilion, Albany Avenue and 26th Street.</p>
   <p>Our entertainment committee took great care to make this mass meeting not only <pb facs="5418478_6_1672.jpg" n="2"/>educational, but a source of joy and entertainment for the many thousands of our freethinking countrymen who will make this day and place their rendezvous. Besides classical musical numbers, there will be attractions of all kinds, such as dancing and refreshments. We therefore invite all of our freethinkers, their friends, families, and children to attend this great mass meeting, and to prove by their attendance that the wiles and fury of all the reactionaries and enemies of the personal rights of man are in vain--that the Free Thought movement is gaining momentum among the Czechs of America, and is prepared to meet all its enemies no matter where such may be.</p>
   <p>Therefore, all sincere Bohemian freethinkers, make it your honorable duty to attend the mass meeting in Pilsen Park this coming Sunday afternoon, and indicate by your large attendance that we are true freethinkers, not by word alone, but by deed, and that we are ever ready to respond whenever and wherever a duty calls! One half of the net proceeds will be used for the support of Bohemian Free Thought schools!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
