<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-05-15">May 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Our Proclanation in Recard to the Dispute between the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago and the Czechoslovak National Alliance of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-05-15">May 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PROCLANATION IN RECARD TO THE DISPUTE BETWEEN THE CZECHOSLOVAK LEGIONNAIRES OF CHICAGO AND THE CZECHOSLOVAK NATIONAL ALLIANCE OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recent stormy meetings of the Bohemian public, one called by the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago and the second by the Czechoslovak National Alliance of America, presented sufficient explanation of the existing conditions. As it appears, there is no necessity whatsoever for carrying on this dispute in our daily newspapers. It would only be dangerous and harmful to continue this dispute and would not help the good cause. Similar attacks and disputes carried on through our newspapers cannot do any good whatsoever, because one attack creates another. Many of our generous workers are only discouraged by these quarrels and are diverted from a worthy national endeavor.</p>
   <p>Our attitude in this dispute has been absolutely neutral. Both sides were given an opportunity to present their arguments to our public, and we <pb facs="5418478_6_1081.jpg" n="2"/>presumed that the matter was ended, at least as far as publishing the attacks in our newspapers was concerned. We see absolutely no reason to renew it. We therefore consider it our duty to announce that no more attacks will be published by us in this matter. We are forced to do this in the interest of our readers and in the interest of our Bohemian people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
