<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-04">Apr. 4, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation by District Committee of the Czechslovak National Allance of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-04">Apr. 4, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION BY DISTRICT COMMITTEE OF THE CZECHSLOVAK NATIONAL ALLANCE OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The District Committee of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe (Czechoslovak National Alliance of America), in regard to the proclamation of the Czechoslovak Legionnaires, in which the active workers of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v America, Frank J. Rubec, Joseph Paskovsky, and Ferdinand L. Kusil, were attacked in an unworthy and unjustified manner, considers it its obligation to proclaim the following:</p>
   <p>"The District Committee of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe rejects, with full determination, the groundless attacks on these active workers, who, untiringly and generously, worked with us for the liberation of our nation, and we hereby proclaim that we have full confidence in them for their honest work.</p>
   <p>"The District Committee of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe <pb facs="5418478_6_1132.jpg" n="2"/>hereby proclaims that reproaches made in the said proclamation against the above-mentioned active workers are absolutely unjustifiable and untruthful, and that the said proclamation is only an attempt to drag personal matters into our public life and to discredit our organization.</p>
   <p>"The District Committee of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe hereby proclaims that its obligations toward the legionnaires who returned, were discharged in every respect. Aid was given to all those who were in need, and today this is still being done. Together with the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics and the Slovak League, it has made drastic financial sacrifices for this cause.</p>
   <p>"The District Committee of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe hereby unanimously condemns the subversive work of the Czechoslovak Legionnaires, which has been going on since the beginning of their organization, against the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, which has always performed and is still honestly and successfully performing its duty <pb facs="5418478_6_1133.jpg" n="3"/>toward our newly born republic in its most trying times.</p>
   <p>"For the District Committee of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe:</p>
   <p>"Julie Hrych, vice-chairman;</p>
   <p>"Karel Kouba, secretary."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
