<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-16">May 16, 1911</date><title level="a">The Bohemian Charitable Association Considers Offering a Reward for the Capture of the Murderer of Eila Paroubek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0732</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0732.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-16">May 16, 1911</date><title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION CONSIDERS OFFERING A REWARD FOR THE CAPTURE OF THE MURDERER OF EILA PAROUBEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The executive committee of the Bohemian Charitable Association held a special meeting relative to the Paroubek case. Judge J. Z. Uhlir presided. It was announced in this meeting that the fifty dollars, which was appropriated to aid in the search for Ella Paroubek, had been disbursed. The main proceedings of the meeting centered around the $500 which had been subscribed as a reward for the discovery of Ella alive. Now, since it is known that she is dead, it has been moved that this reward be offered to the one who finds her murderer. The motion carried, and it was decided to write to all those who subscribed to the original reward to find out if they agreed with the decision, and if they were willing to dedicate the sum subscribed toward this purpose.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0733.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In as much as the Paroubek family, by reason of the misfortune, is absolutely penniless, a motion was made and carried, that a loan in the sum of fifty dollars be made to it. In accordance with the motion, a three member committee, consisting of Messrs. Loula, Turek and Foucek, are to visit and speak to Mr. Paroubek.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt but that all those who subscribed sums for the discovery of the missing girl will also agree that this same fund shall apply as a reward for the discovery of the murderer. If the money were not successful in finding the child, it will aid the desire of people in bringing the criminal to justice, thereby making him harmless in the future, and serve as a warning to others who might seek to cause misfortune to some other family.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
