<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-21">Sept. 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Meeting of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0518</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0518.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-21">Sept. 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A MEETING OF THE CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) was held in the society's offices last Friday night.....Among the incoming letters there was one from Mrs. Rosalind Klein and Mr. Sol Klein, executors of the last will of Mr. Leo Klein, reading as follows:</p>
   <p>"To the Directors of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, Chicago.</p>
   <p>"According to paragraph six of the testament of Leo Klein, deceased, the executors of that said testament have been charged with the duty of dividing the sum of $25,000 among such Chicago institutions as do charitable work among the population of Chicago's West Side. We are pleased to enclose a check for $1,000 for the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, which amount should be used for the promotion of the Association's aims and objectives."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0519.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Signed: Rosalind Klein, Sol. Klein, executors."</p>
   <p>This bequest was gratefully received, and the secretary was instructed to draft a letter of thanks to the noble donors. Mr. Klein's noble deed certainly merits emulation by our wealthy countrymen. The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost is doing a great deal of charitable work which should be remembered and supported by our people on various occasions. The expenses of the society are steadily growing. There are many hundred needy Bohemian families on its books, and without the interest of the general Bohemian public, the Spolecnost could not fulfill its mission.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the ball committee, Mr. John A. Sokol, made the announcement that the preparations for the forthcoming ball of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost are in full swing. The ball will be held in the Pilsen Park pavilion on the first Wednesday in November, that is, November 5.....The ball and the tag day are the two principal sources of Association's revenue, and <pb facs="5418478_6_0520.jpg" n="3"/>it is up to the members to stimulate their friends' interest in the undertaking.....</p>
   <p>The total income reported in the meeting was $1,053.32; expenses from August 6 to September 19, $325.87.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
