<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-21">Feb. 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Letter of Acknowledgement</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Czechoslovakian Red Cross Thanks the Central Committee of the "Jednota Ceskych Dam" (Bohemian Ladies' Unity) for its Liberal Gifts</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0069</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0069.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-21">Feb. 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">LETTER OF ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Czechoslovakian Red Cross Thanks the Central Committee of the "Jednota Ceskych Dam" (Bohemian Ladies' Unity) for Its Liberal Gifts</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. Anna Stolfa, secretary of the Central Committee of the Bohemian Ladies' Unity, received a letter from the office of the Czechoslovakia Red Cross at Prague, Czechoslovakia, thanking our ladies for the generous work done so far for the orphans of Czechoslovakia. The letter reads:</p>
   <p>Prague, October 28, 1920.</p>
   <p>"Dear compatriots:</p>
   <p>To you, as the secretary of the Central Committee of the Bohemian Ladies' Unity, I take the liberty of sending our most sincere thanks for the gifts <pb facs="5418478_6_0070.jpg" n="2"/>which were sent to us. We received more than one thousand new dresses for girls from three to four years of age, and eight dozens of boys' trousers. Besides this, we also received in provisions two hundred pounds of bacon, two hundred pounds of lard, eight hundred pounds of green coffee, sixteen hundred pounds of white flour, sixteen hundred pounds of rye flour, two hundred pounds of oats, eight hundred pounds of rice, two hundred pounds of farina, one hundred thirty packages of tea, eight boxes of condensed milk, twelve boxes of Pet milk, eight boxes of Eagle milk, six boxes of Bohemian soap, four boxes of Borax soap, eight boxes of Superior soap, two boxes of sweet chocolate, one hundred packages of pepper, one hundred packages of new spices, one hundred packages of ginger. We also received supplementarily, thirty-six dozens of handkerchiefs, and some other provisions sent by the Bohemian Ladies' Unity. The entire shipment was received in good order, and now we have started to distribute it among the people who suffer most. The joy of the recipients will surely be great, and you beyond the ocean may rejoice in the knowledge that you have helped many unhappy women, old men, soldiers, and others.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0071.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Further, you ask if we are in need of more of your help. We are deeply touched with the thought that you are willing to help us and to support the cause of the Czechoslovakian Red Cross in the future. We are in need of much more. Conditions in our republic are much better already, but nevertheless we have been unable thus far to transform the Czechoslovakian republic into a state where everybody would be happy. We have here invalids and sick soldiers, widows and orphans of dead heroes, sickly old men, weak children, and whole families suffering with consumption. It is necessary to feed, clothe, cure, and to secure aid for all of them. We still are in need of provisions, clothes, underwear, and drugs. Only because of your assistance do we hope to accomplish our burdensome mission. We beg of you then for further support in our task of human love for our fellow-creatures. The Czechoslovakian Red Cross penetrated into our national life, and all the sufferers look to it as to their refuge, where they will always receive desired help. For that reason, stay by us and support our actions in the interest of the sufferers. Henceforth, seek <pb facs="5418478_6_0072.jpg" n="4"/>all the new ways and means toward it, in order to help us. Do not grow weary in your task!</p>
   <p>With warmest greetings and recollections,</p>
   <p>Signed: Dr. Alice Masaryk, president."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
