<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-22">Oct. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Czechs Make Wholesale Preparations to Celebrate the Czechoslovak Independence Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Abstract)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1667</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1667.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-22">Oct. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO CZECHS MAKE WHOLESALE PREPARATIONS TO CELEBRATE THE CZECHOSLOVAK INDEPENDENCE DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Abstract)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Extensive preparations have been started by the local branch of the Sdruzeni Ceskoslovenskych Legionaru (Czechoslovak Legionnaires), the Sokol unions and all the other nationalist organizations in Chicago, to celebrate the Declaration of Independence of Czechoslovakia, in the Pilsen Park pavilion.</p>
   <p>On July 26, 1914, a world conflagration was started by a flame which burst out in the Balkans. [Here follows the usual description of the events which led to the World War, allusions being made to German imperialism, the Hapsburg alliance with Germany, the exploits of the allied armies, the long-drawn-out campaigns, the final victories of the Allied armies, the <pb facs="5418478_6_1668.jpg" n="2"/>fall of the Hapsburg regime and the creation of a Czechoslovak state.].....</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovaks of America, ever since the beginning of the great conflict, have tried to be of service to their old homeland, have supported the revolution with a generous hand, and have most willingly helped to make the victory assured.</p>
   <p>As during previous years, so this year also, the day of Czechoslovak independence is to be celebrated on the memorable day--the day of October 28--by festive processions and parades to bring back to our memory the sanguine days of the birth of the [Czechoslovak] Republic.</p>
   <p>In the city of Chicago the celebration will be held on October 28, in the spacious halls of the Pilsen Park pavilion. The event, for which preparations <pb facs="5418478_6_1669.jpg" n="3"/>have already been begun, is to be celebrated by the following organizations: The Druzina Ceskoslovenskych Legionaru in cooperation with the Sokolska Zupa Stredni (Central District of the American Sokol Union), and the local branch of the Americke Narodni Sdruzeni (Czechoslovak veterans of the Spanish-American War, as well as the entire membership of the Lawndale and Crawford posts of the American Legion, will also participate.</p>
   <p>The program which has been prepared for this year is very rich. It has aroused much interest and comment in the widest circles of our Czechoslovak population. Dr. Frantisek Jaroslav Smetanka, Consul General of Czechoslovakia, is to make an address on the theme, "The Czechoslovak independence and the Czechoslovaks of America". Brother Jarko Kosar, agent of the Sokolska Obec v Americe (American Sokol Community), will speak on the subject of the first beginnings of the Sokol idea and of the founders of it, Jindrich Fuegner and Miroslav Tyrs. Besides the various national and <pb facs="5418478_6_1670.jpg" n="4"/>military organizations, the representatives of the Allied governments have also been invited. The artistic part of the program will consist of orchestral music, vocal music, and recitations. Some of the outstanding Czech artists will take part in the program. Admission per person is fifty cents.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
