<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1908-09-21">Sept. 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Concert in Libuse Hall.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0673</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0673.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1908-09-21">Sept. 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT IN LIBUSE HALL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday evening a concert was arranged by Bohemian immigrants from Myto in the Libuse Hall on 12th street, for the benefit of their countrymen in Europe, who, because of a fire, lost their fortunes. As soon as the news of this disaster reached us, a number of the countrymen from Myto got together and after a thorough and harmoniously conducted consultation made arrangements for a concert for the benefit of those who were affected by the disaster.</p>
   <p>A resolution was adopted and carried through. A committee was sent to call upon our business houses to solicit contributions for this concert. The committee was warmly welcomed at the business concerns they contacted and liberal donations were given to make this concert a success for the benefit of the destitute countrymen in Myto.</p>
   <p>Then a program was arranged by way of soliciting advertisements from various businessmen. Not a thing was overlooked to make this concert a success.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0674.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A large attendance was expected by the committee. The concert was held in Libuse Hall owned by Mr. Belohlavek. The cozy hall was filled to capacity and there were many people in the gallery who were obliged to stand. Every seat was occupied.</p>
   <p>In the lower hall a number of our prominent businessmen were discussing the need of this concert for the benefit of our unfortunate countrymen.</p>
   <p>Shortly after 8 o'clock an announcement of the program was made by Mr. Edward Hribal and he earned a big applause. He then made his exit with a graceful bow. After that there appeared on the stage the familiar face of our well-known old,--I beg your pardon--ever young actress, Mrs. M. Fridl, dressed in the national costume which was very becoming to her. She played the role of cook, "Prague style," very well, especially owing to her natural comical manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0675.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>She made the audience laugh so beautifully that the hall was in an uproar. After a prolonged applause she was obliged to make several appearances on the stage and she also sang a number of ditties.</p>
   <p>The next number was a similar one by Miss. E. Triner.</p>
   <p>Mrs. M. Fridl again appeared on the stage singing a solo with an added ditty of how much she enjoys herself among her countrymen. Then Miss M. Geringr, appeared on the stage and sang the song, "Stars Shine On High." She earned a repeated applause.</p>
   <p>The last number on the program was reserved for the appearance of the Vilimtrio, which in true virtuoso style presented the Cavatina by Raff, El Fresco by Zavrtal, and Marche Militaire by Schubert. This number ended the program of the concert, after which the younger folks enjoyed themselves by dancing. The music played waltzes and two steps. This concert was a successful one and of great benefit to our people in Myto. Many thanks to the liberal donors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
