<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-06-24">June 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">For the Reorganization of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni V Americe</title><title level="a" type="sub">Representatives of the National Organizations Resolved to Preserve the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1067</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1067.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-06-24">June 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE REORGANIZATION OF THE CESKOSLOVENSKE NARODNI SDRUZENI V AMERICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Representatives of the National Organizations Resolved to Preserve the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's meeting in regard to the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe (Czechoslovak National Alliance of America) was attended by 118 delegates, representing 68 societies and organizations. The course of the meeting was smooth and dignified, and although it lasted until late in the evening, all the delegates and assembled public remained in their places.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by Mr. Ludvik Kaderka, who greeted the delegates and urged them to elect a chairman for the meeting. Mr. James F. Stepina was nominated and unanimously elected to this office. Mr. Josef Vosatko was then elected secretary. In a brief speech Mr. James F. Stepina mentioned that he accepted the chairmanship only because it is a part of his patriotic obligation. Mr. Frana Klepal, the next speaker, explained <pb facs="5418478_6_1068.jpg" n="2"/>the point of view of the legionnaires and presented the report of activities undertaken by them in this matter.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frauenknecht then asked if the delegates of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe were present at this meeting. The chairman answered that they were not. Mr. Ludvik Kaderka explained that the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe had not been invited because of past experiences; and he stated that this meeting had been publicly advertised, and the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, knowing that the meeting would be held, could have sent its delegates.</p>
   <p>Then there followed a lengthy debate as to whether the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe should be preserved or whether a new organization should be started. Mr. Mestak advocated the preservation of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, but at the same time he advocated that a resolution be adopted against its present leadership. Mr. Karel Smiricky, Mr. Frana Klepal, Mr. Pesice, and Mr. Bukovsky introduced various <pb facs="5418478_6_1069.jpg" n="3"/>proposals, all pointing out the various ways of reorganizing the Alliance.</p>
   <p>Dr. Karel Neumann mentioned that nowadays there is not one tenth of the enthusiasm which existed at the time when the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe was founded. He remarked that at that time it was no trick whatsoever to organize such an immense body. Under the existing circumstances, it would be impossible. He mentioned the consequences of the World War and its effect upon our local social life. It is necessary, therefore, to rouse a new enthusiasm; and it is necessary that we do not forget ourselves. Following the speeches of several other delegates, Dr. Karel Neumann introduced a resolution that the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe be preserved, but at the same time that it should be reorganized.</p>
   <p>In accordance with the motion of Mr. Vitek, a resolutions committee consisting of the following nine members was appointed: Dr. Karel Neumann, Mr. W. Havelka, Mr. Karel Smiricky, Mr. Frana Klepal, Mr. Eduard Schultz, Mrs. Emilie Jakoubek, Mrs. Ruzena Lusk, Mrs. Marie Zeman, and Mrs. Barbora Scheffel. This <pb facs="5418478_6_1070.jpg" n="4"/>committee immediately worked out a resolution which was later unanimously adopted. In accordance with the motion of Mr. J. Vosatko, it was resolved that this committee shall continue to exist as a regular resolutions committee, and it will arrange further necessary steps.</p>
   <p>The adopted resolution reads:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The recent events, which by their unfavorable influence do harm and make any co-operation in our public and national life impossible; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The critical situation originated partly by the influence of unfavorable post-war circumstances, by improper conduct of individuals, and by absolute indifference toward our most noble, cultural, and national causes; therefore, be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we approve the program of the Druzina Ceskoslovenskych Legionaru v Chicagu (Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago), in which the <pb facs="5418478_6_1071.jpg" n="5"/>just reformation of our national life and the reorganization of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe is sought and promoted in such a way that this representative institution may be competent in the fulfillment of its tasks, and that it may be considered a promoter and proponent of the common interest of the Bohemian people of America.</p>
   <p>"The present delegates and authorized representatives of the national and Sokol organizations, after taking into consideration the serious state of affairs, consider it necessary, because of the present situation, to control the administration of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, and by this resolution appeal to the officers of the above-mentioned institution and to all its district alliances and branches all over the United States, in the interest of a common cause, to call a new conference which must not yield to any trifling matters of personal character, and one in which the program of reorganization would be discussed and the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe would be preserved.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1072.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"In the supposition that this sincere effort will receive due recognition; that it will gain many followers among our nationally conscious people; that it will be a warning to those who are responsible for this present state of affairs; that it will be a guide to the possibilities of practical and co-operative work in the future, we recommend that the organizations and societies which are members of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe designate a place and time for the above-mentioned conference, and also appoint delegates who are well informed about the state of conditions; and who, by their influence, could bring the proposed reorganization to a successful end.</p>
   <p>"Inasmuch as the unfriendly propaganda of the American and foreign press seriously threatens and harms the economic and cultural interest of the Bohemian nation in the United States, we consider it necessary to unite all ranks of our people for the purpose of co-operative national work in which the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe should occupy the first place and be a representative of all the liberal organizations. For <pb facs="5418478_6_1073.jpg" n="7"/>these serious reasons we approve the program of our legionnaires, and we recommend the reorganization of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe on pure free thought principles."....</p>
   <p>The meeting was adjourned by the chairman, who expressed his gratitude to all who participated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
