<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-16">Nov. 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">To Mitigate Human Suffering</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0410</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0410.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-16">Nov. 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TO MITIGATE HUMAN SUFFERING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The local units of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Union) wrote a new page into the large book of their worthy activities last night. In co-operation with the Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (Federation of Bohemian Singing Societies) they arranged gymnastic and vocal entertainment in the Pilsen Park Pavilion, for the benefit of needy countrymen in Bohemia, and judging by the huge attendance and the festivity, the funds of the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor (Bohemian-Slavonic Auxiliary Committee) will be increased by a substantial sum.....</p>
   <p>To be exact, the festivities started in the afternoon with a lecture by the noted Bohemian-American poet and writer, Dr. Anton Mueller.....</p>
   <p>This was followed by a drill of 130 girls....and dance routine of five groups of women Sokols of twenty members each.....</p>
   <p>No less effective were gymnastics performed by senior Sokols on apparatus.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0411.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The speaker of the evening was Dr. Jar. E. S. Vojan who talked on the topic "Seas Cannot Separate What Hearts have United".....</p>
   <p>Our singers, both men and women, have proved again their mettle.....Their performances were perfect in every respect.....</p>
   <p>The attendance of the general public was very large indeed, but there was one fact that surprised many of us; the very poor participation from the ranks of the Sokols. Barring the performers, the Sokols distinguished themselves by their absence. The only exception was the Sokol Tabor, which came, in spite of the nasty weather, marching in parade with its eighteen-piece band of buglers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
