<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-25">Oct. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Women in Action</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0433</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0433.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-25">Oct. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN WOMEN IN ACTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At its convention in St. Louis, the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Women's Unity) proved that Bohemian women sympathize with their suffering sisters in the old country. The donation to Bohemian war relief voted there shows that our ladies are ready to do all that is in their power to alleviate the sorrow caused by the war abroad. Upon the request of the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor (Bohemian-Slavonic Auxiliary Committee), the central committee of the Jednota Ceskych Dam has assessed its members with a ten-cent tax. In addition to this, the individual lodges will contribute according to their means. The Lodge Karolina Svetla has voted fifty dollars, and other lodges have contributed similar amounts. The total contribution of the Jednota Ceskych Dam in the State of Illinois is estimated at fifteen hundred dollars, and there is no doubt that this strong organization will show similar results in other states of the Union.</p>
   <p>Other women's organizations, though less strong in membership, show equal <pb facs="5418478_6_0434.jpg" n="2"/>generosity in the humane effort to help the old country. The Jednota Ceskych Vlastene (Unity of Bohemian Patriotic Women) has pledged one death benefit. Favorable news has reached us from the Ceska Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Mutual Benevolent Sisterhood) and the Jednota Cesko-Americkych Dam (Bohemian-American Women's Unity). The ladies' auxiliaries of Sokol bodies have been working with us from the start, and when our reports are published, the amounts contributed will show conclusive evidence of their benevolence.</p>
   <p>The Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor has been receiving many calls from representatives of our largest organizations, and almost all of them--with very few exceptions--are represented in the Vybor by their own delegates.</p>
   <p>The Vybor now holds its meetings only once a month, on the third Friday. The secretary is busy preparing letters to our societies, lodges, etc., requesting them to give us a helping hand and to appoint representatives to the general committee of our Vybor in which all our Chicago organizations <pb facs="5418478_6_0435.jpg" n="3"/>will be represented. The general committee will meet as soon as it has a sufficiently large membership. The Vybor is now working on the organization of an all-American body in which all of us would join in an effort of true patriotism and brotherly love.</p>
   <p>Cesko-Slovansky</p>
   <p>Pomocny Vybor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
