<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-03">Nov. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Brothers! Bohemians!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0253</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0253.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-03">Nov. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">BROTHERS! BOHEMIANS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The terrible offensive of the German-Austrian armies, directed lately toward the complete destruction of Serbia and Montenegro, is an excruciating ordeal for the two nations attacked. It is absolutely necessary to put forth every effort in order to stave off this danger and save these two nations from complete annihilation.</p>
   <p>No well-meaning and Slavic-feeling Bohemian wants to see the Teutonic enemy succeed in his criminal undertaking, and therefore it is the duty of all of us to help in any way we can. The Serbian and Montenegrin heroes fight for the Slavic cause, that is, for our existence, just as well as their own, and it is necessary to help them by collections of money, clothes, linen, footwear, peas, sugar, coffee, tea, and other commodities. This will help not only the suffering warriers, but also the Slavic prisoners of war, and among those the Bohemian captives in the first place.</p>
   <p>The Benefactor and friend of Slavdom, Mr. Frothingham, is sending a new <pb facs="5418478_6_0254.jpg" n="2"/>expedition to Montenegro which will leave in the middle of November and take with it all these commodities. It will take care that everything is properly distributed.</p>
   <p>Contributions of money are to be sent to the Montenegrin Consul, Captain A. V. Seferovich, 112 West 40th Street, New York, New York. Other material should be mailed or otherwise forwarded to the Bohemian Travel Bureau of Mr. A. G. Tvrdy at 1418 Second Avenue, New York, New York.</p>
   <p>P.S.: The expedition will consist of some six members. All donations should be sent not later than the tenth of this month because the ship on which the expedition will sail will leave New York on or about November 17. The expedition, in all probability, will go by way of France and Italy to Greece, and from there to Montenegro.</p>
   <p>For Captain A. V. Seferovich,</p>
   <p>Dr. Duro Guca.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
