<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-31">May 31, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Memorial Day Celebrations at Our Bohemian Cemeteries</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1725</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1725.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-31">May 31, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE MEMORIAL DAY CELEBRATIONS AT OUR BOHEMIAN CEMETERIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Amid ideal weather conditions Memorial Day celebrations were held at all Chicago cemeteries yesterday, and one of the most successful and most dignified celebrations was the one held at the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery).</p>
   <p>The celebration started soon after 8 A. M. in front of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies' Hall where an imposing parade was formed and which, to the tune of Mr. Rubringer's military band, marched down 18th Street to Blue Island Avenue and southwest to 22nd Street. The following groups and organizations participated in the parade: the Veterans of the Civil War, the delegates to the Bohemian National Cemetery Association, the Bohemian Veterans of the Spanish-American War, a company of the Lawndale-Crawford Post No. 98 of the American Legion, the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago, the Czechoslovak Veterans and the Sokols. At 22nd Street the participants of the parade boarded the streetcars and were taken near the Frantisek <pb facs="5418478_6_1726.jpg" n="2"/>Zdrubek Bohemian Free Thought School. There the parade was formed again, and it marched to the Cemetery, arriving there soon after 10 A. M.</p>
   <p>At that early hour thousands of people had already assembled around the speakers' tribune and around the Veterans of the Civil War monument. The memorial services opened with military ceremonies at the veterans' monument. Then came the program prepared by the board of directors of the cemetery. Mr. Rubringer's band played "The Star-Spangled Banner" and Mr. Jan Pecha, chairman of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association, addressed the audience. Following his address the band played a medley of American folk songs and Mr. Pecha then introduced the principal English speaker of the celebration, Judge Anton Zerman of the Circuit Court, whose speech was published in our newspaper yesterday. Miss Vlasta Stipek, an inmate of the Bohemian Orphanage, recited two poems. Then the principal Bohemian speaker of the celebration, Mr. Otto T. Pergler, chairman of the Illinois Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies, was introduced. His speech has <pb facs="5418478_6_1727.jpg" n="3"/>also been published by us. The last three numbers of the program were two musical selections and an English poem which was recited by Miss Marenka Otahaly, an inmate of the Bohemian Orphanage. After the program the people visited the graves of their dear ones.</p>
   <p>A great number of the people traveled to the Hrbitov Svateho Vojtecha (St. Adalbert Cemetery) yesterday, in order to attend the impressive Memorial Day celebration held there. The program was opened by the chairman of the Chicago district committee of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America) , Mr. Karel Roubik, who, after addressing the audience, introduced the principal Bohemian speaker of the celebration, Reverend Frantisek W. Jedlicka. Reverend Jedlicka's speech was published yesterday. The principal English speaker was Mr. Timothy D. Hurley, a well-known Chicago lawyer.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Frantisek Kovarik presided at the Memorial Day celebration which was <pb facs="5418478_6_1728.jpg" n="4"/>held at the Hrbitov Vzkriseni Pane (Resurrection Cemetery). The speakers at this celebration were Reverend Frantisek Bozenek, who delivered his speech in the Bohemian language, and Judge Kickham Scanlan, who spoke in English. This celebration was also attended by the members of the Marshall Post of the American Legion who decorated the graves of their comrades with flowers. This cemetery was also crowded with people and the celebration was dignified in every respect.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
