<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-04-29">Apr. 29, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Report of the Meeting Held by the Associated Bohemian Liberal (Freethought) Schools of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1571</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1571.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-04-29">Apr. 29, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF THE MEETING HELD BY THE ASSOCIATED BOHEMIAN LIBERAL (FREETHOUGHT) SCHOOLS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting of the Associated Bohemian Liberal (Freethought) Schools of Chicago, held on April 16, in the Ladimir Klacel hall was brought to order by the chairman, Mr. K. Kopecky. The minutes of the previous meeting were read and accepted. The reading of communications then followed. For the most part, they concerned the question of adjustment of school rentals. This matter already had been discussed in a previous meeting, and because of differences of opinion, action was not taken. After a somewhat lengthy debate, it was decided that the sponsors, and particularly all schools, should retain tuition fees received, and with the proceeds thereof pay for the cleaning and rental of classrooms. The salaries of the teachers will be taken care of by the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodo Myslnych Skol v Chicagu (Associated Bohemian Liberal (Freethought) Schools). (A list of schools and teachers are given).</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1572.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The interest of the societies and delegates in the improvement of the schools continues to grow, and the number of students is increasing, so that we hope in the near future to realize the desired results in the education of our Bohemian youth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
