<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-24">May 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Karel Havlicek Borovsky Monument Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1550</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1550.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-24">May 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE KAREL HAVLICEK BOROVSKY MONUMENT ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting was held yesterday in Mr. Welky's hall, by the Karel Havlicek Borovsky Monument Association. The chairman, Mr. Sedlacek, brought the meeting to order, and after the reading of the minutes of the previous meeting, communications received were announced. The secretary announced that the communications really belonged to the Arrangements Committee, and for that reason he would not stop to read them. The National Bohemian Council of Prague recommends that Editor Karel Stanislav Sokol be the speaker for the occasion. Mr. Sokol is willing to appear, providing he is furnished transportation. On the motion of Mr.Glaser, the communication was referred to the committee. Mr. St. Vraz read a proclamation to Bohemian people in the old country, inviting them to participate in the celebration. All of the representatives signed a memorial paper, which will be deposited within the pedestal of the monument. It was resolved that well-known Bohemian writers be requested to make literary contributions for the memorial book. Messrs. Vraz and Zmrhal have promised to send their contributions.</p>
   <p>Vice-chairman Mr. Polivka complains that the representatives of newspapers are <pb facs="5418478_6_1551.jpg" n="2"/>not attending meetings of the association. This, of course, does not apply to Denni Hlasatel, which sends representatives to all important occasions. A motion that the lettering on the monument be made more distinct was referred to the committee.</p>
   <p>Regarding the program for Sunday, the Arrangements Committee decided that only a concert be given, followed by an informal entertainment.</p>
   <p>Receipts at this meeting were: Union Wholesale Liquor Company, $25.00; Mr. James F. Stepina, $25.00; Dr. William Semerak, $5.00; Mr. Horacek, $5.00.</p>
   <p>Disbursements: National Printing Company, $3.50; Heller &amp; Company, $3,000, as part payment for the monument foundation.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will take place the second Wednesday in June.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
