<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-23">May 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A New, Splendid Donation to Bohemian Prisoners of War in Serbia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0320</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0320.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-23">May 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW, SPLENDID DONATION TO BOHEMIAN PRISONERS OF WAR IN SERBIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor (Bohemian-Slavonic Auxiliary Committee) held one of its monthly meetings May 21. In that meeting a number of letters were read which were sent to the Vybor by the members of the Bohemian-American mission in Serbia. These letters again depict the pitiful state of Austrian prisoners of war in that country, a large percentage of whom are Bohemians, our compatriots and countrymen. Dr. Jicinsky and Brother Klepal tell us that a Bohemian auxiliary committee has been formed in Skoplje whose duty it is to care for the physical well-being, including the health, of Bohemian prisoners of war throughout Serbia, and not merely within the confines of the Skoplje district. So far, the typhus has been the chief enemy of the Serbian people, but with the coming summer worse diseases are expected. In parts of Greece the black plague is raging. Its spread to Serbia is being anticipated with <pb facs="5418478_6_0321.jpg" n="2"/>fear. But the worst scourge the summer is likely to bring is the cholera.</p>
   <p>If exhausted Serbia could not give any large amount of care to its prisoners in the past months, it will be still less able to do so now, because a new offensive against Austria is being prepared, and the field hospitals are being made ready for a new influx of wounded.</p>
   <p>The Pomocny Vybor, after reading these letters, and considering all circumstances, adopted the proposal of Mr. Nigrin, together with an amplification by Mr. Langer, to make every effort to save now the fathers and husbands of Bohemian wives and mothers, rather than to try to mitigate their irreparable loss by paltry donations later on. Therefore a sum of $2,500 was voted for the purchase of clothes and linen. Prior to this, $1,085 was voted for the same purpose, and the three hundred suits bought with that money have already been sent to Serbia. By buying linen and clothes for the Bohemian prisoners <pb facs="5418478_6_0322.jpg" n="3"/>and having them distributed principally to those who are in the greatest need of them, the Pomocny Vybor is doing a great deal toward the saving of their lives, because the diseases are spread mainly through lack of cleanliness, and prisoners who are clad in rags are unable to keep clean.</p>
   <p>This may be a good opportunity to review the help given to Bohemian prisoners of war in Serbia so far:</p>
   <p>In October, $750, the amount collected for the Serbians at the meeting of July 28, was given to the Serbian Red Cross. The amount of $34.11 was donated by us for the purchase of medical instruments for the Bohemian medical mission to Serbia. In December, for the same mission, $100 was contributed to buy pharmaceutical preparations and bandages; to this $200 was added later on. In April, we donated $1,000 to the Serbian agricultural fund for the purchase of seed grain and farming implements . For the purchase of clothing for the Bohemian prisoners of war, a total of $3,585 was given. Since collections for <pb facs="5418478_6_0323.jpg" n="4"/>Serbia have been in progress in other places, the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor deems it proper to request such collecting bodies to correlate their work to ours. This would make it possible for us to make sure that the donations reach their destination, and also enable us to keep a correct and complete record of the work of Bohemian America in these stirring times. The Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor will give due credit to each of the collecting bodies. Undoubtedly the Vybor, after ten months of successful work, is deserving of the confidence of every one of our countrymen.</p>
   <p>We wish to add that we have received an official report on the medical and surgical work done by the Bohemian-American expedition to Serbia. It will be published as soon as its translation is prepared.</p>
   <p>The expedition is in good health now, very busy, and doing its work gladly and with zeal. Its members send greetings to their countrymen overseas, and hope that they [the countrymen] will do their national and humane duties with a <pb facs="5418478_6_0324.jpg" n="5"/>similar love and pleasure.</p>
   <p>For the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor:</p>
   <p>Jaroslav V. Nigrin, secretary, 1825 Blue Island Avenue, Chicago, Illinois;</p>
   <p>James F. Stepina, chairman;</p>
   <p>O. Vasak, treasurer.</p>
   <p>Note: The Friday meeting of the Pomocny Vybor was also attended by Mr. Kopecky, our guest from London, who has come to give us the greetings of London Bohemians, and to express to us their admiration of our exemplary and diligent work. He assured us that wherever Bohemian hearts are beating, they are filled with love for the Bohemian cause which will and must win in the end.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
