<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-03-14">Mar. 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Proclamation to All Organizations Represented in the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada, and to All Bohemian People in General</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-03-14">Mar. 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A PROCLAMATION TO ALL ORGANIZATIONS REPRESENTED IN THE CESKO-AMERICKA NARODNI RADA, AND TO ALL BOHEMIAN PEOPLE IN GENERAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Never have we Bohemian-Americans suffered such a brutal and savage public attack as in the last few months, when Professor Ross, a man otherwise respected in his profession and enjoying a good reputation, assailed the Bohemians and the Slavonic races in general, using most offensive language in speaking of us.</p>
   <p>He described us as people made of the "worst material that was left in the workshop of the Creator".</p>
   <p>As an educated people we certainly want the truth to prevail, especially when this means rejecting the stigma unjustly fixed upon us by a man whose hatred of us is so great that he has stooped to a type of attack completely at variance with the ethics of a scholar. To accept these insults quietly would be proving that we are in fact "people without brain and honor," as Professor Ross calls us.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1421.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Therefore it is our duty to voice an energetic, but dignified objection, and show Professor Ross and the Century Magazine how greatly we have been wronged.</p>
   <p>Therefore we appeal to you, brothers in the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council), and announce that at the last meeting of this central body it was agreed that a mass meeting should be held next Sunday afternoon in the Pilsen Park pavilion. There an energetic answer to the wrongs and insults heaped upon us will be formulated.</p>
   <p>This matter is of such interest that none of you must be absent from this meeting. You want to prove that you are proud of your Bohemian origin; that you are not the outcasts of society as Professor Ross declares; and that we as men know how to defend truth and honor!</p>
   <p>Na Zdar! (To success!)</p>
   <p>For the Narodni Rada: E. St. Vraz, Vladimir Spatny, Jaroslav Zmrhal, John A.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1422.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Cervenka, Joseph M. Triner, Jan Pecha and James Stepina. For the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs (Fuegner-Tyrs Gymnastic Association): Bohus Zak.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
