<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-01">May 1, 1911</date><title level="a">A Successful Pan-Slavic Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-01">May 1, 1911</date><title level="a">A SUCCESSFUL PAN-SLAVIC CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The concert given yesterday by the Ceska Vstredni Jednota Pevecka (Central Bohemian Singing Society), assisted by the augmented Antonin Dvorak orchestral club, the Filaretow chorus, and the Croatian society, Lora, was a grand success. The participating singers and musicians prepared a pleasant, agreeable evening, which will long be remembered by our music-loving public.</p>
   <p>The concert began with the rendition of the overture to Mozart's "Don Juan", by the orchestral club. The Croatian singing society Lora, under the direction of Mr. K. M. Coufal, then sang the "Hymn to Zvonimir" by Zajce with such success that the audience did not cease its applause until the singers gave an encore. The Ladies Singing society, Lyra, under the direction of Mr. John Kalas <pb facs="5418478_6_1568.jpg" n="2"/>gave very fine rendition of "Nasim Zenam" (To Our Wives) by Malata. The Polish Filaretow Chorus was charming in its rendition of Beethoven's "Oh, You Stars." The Filaretow Chorus has a sound reputation in singing circles and there is no doubt that it sent its best voices to participate in this Pan-Slavic concert. In order to relieve the vocalists, the orchestra played Elgar's "Pomp and Circumstance." Following this, the powerful Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society, under the baton of Mr. John Kalas, sang Smetana's "Rolnicku," (Song of the Peasant). Its presentation was new proof of the activity and ardor with which this society dedicates to the cultivation of good music. The last and most picturesque number on the program was "Koleda" by Wendler, (this is a post-holiday song used by serenaders) sung by the Central Bohemian Singing Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1569.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One hundred eighty trained voices took part in the rendition of this great work. Thunderous applause greeted the conclusion of the concert, and after it had quieted down, the audience was still ready to listen to more. This is sufficient proof that it will await the next concert with joyful expectancy. After the concert, the performers were entertained at an informal dinner. The public was satisfied in the fullest sense of the word, and for that reason the performers and directors of the concert were well pleased with their work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
