<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-05-31">May 31, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">In Memory of Our Deceased</title><title level="a" type="sub">Memorial Day at the Bohemian National Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-05-31">May 31, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">IN MEMORY OF OUR DECEASED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Memorial Day at the Bohemian National Cemetery</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the Bohemian National Cemetery became a meeting place of a great throng of people who came from various parts of the Chicago metropolis to decorate the graves of their loved ones and to participate in a Memorial Day celebration. Beautiful weather prevailed during the entire celebration. The air was pure and invigorating, the sky cloudless; and in these green surroundings of awakening nature, a dignified celebration of one of our most beautiful national holidays was held--a day when those who have remained here turn their thoughts toward those who have gone to the beyond.....</p>
   <p>As in previous years, a parade preceded the celebration. The parade formed near the Bohemian-American Free Thought School and marched through the streets of the Pilsen district to the streetcars which transported the participants to Irving Park. Here, in front of the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage, the parade was formed again, and it was shortly after <pb facs="5418478_6_1749.jpg" n="2"/>10 A.M. when the parade passed the cemetery gate and marched to the tune of the immortal Chopin sonata to the tribune which was erected near the Civil War Veterans' Monument. The parade itself created a deep impression.....</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Robert E. Crowe, chief justice of the criminal court of Cook County, Illinois, was introduced as the principal speaker. Justice Crowe is very well known to many of our countrymen and has among them many personal friends, because he spent many years of his life in the old Bohemian settlement of the Nineteenth Ward where he was brought up. As a speaker he enjoys a very good reputation, and his speech yesterday was great in every detail. Justice Crowe first brought out the significance of the Memorial Day celebration and then paid his respect to the bravery and patriotic sentiment of Bohemian people here and in the old country. He said: "It is a real honor to be invited to address the Czechoslovak people who contributed such a great deal to the Allied victory in the World War. For centuries the Czechoslovak people fought for their liberty and independence under the most difficult <pb facs="5418478_6_1750.jpg" n="3"/>conditions. They succeeded only because of their bravery, courage, and unquestioned loyalty toward the principles of freedom....."</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Vaclav J. Petrzelka, speaker for the Svobodna Obec (Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers) who was selected to deliver this year's Memorial Day address in the Bohemian language, commenced his speech. Here also the selection of the arrangement committee proved to be most fortunate, because Mr. Petrzelka is an excellent speaker, and his address was most remarkable both in its deep ideas and patriotic sentiments.....</p>
   <p>In conclusion Mr. Jan Pecha briefly expressed his gratitude to all who participated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
