<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-16">June 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Activity of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni in Canada</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1350</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1350.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-16">June 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE ACTIVITY OF THE CESKE NARODNI SDRUZENI IN CANADA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The headquarters of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance) in Chicago has just received a reply to the letter sent to Canada's Premier, Sir R. L. Borden, requesting him to treat the Bohemians in Canada as members of a friendly nation.</p>
   <p>Our readers will recall the successful meeting called by the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni, at which a resolution was adopted clarifying the relation of the Bohemians to Great Britain. This resolution explained that the Bohemians in England, France, and Russia have been sealing their friendship to the Allies by their very lives. Premier R. L. Borden has replied to the president of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni by two letters showing that the Canadian Government really desires to have the few cases where Canadian Bohemians have suffered considered as exceptions, perhaps errors similar to those which are so likely to occur in war times.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1351.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Premier Borden writes that he is certain that Mr. Tvrdy of New York, representing the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni of New York and the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni of Chicago, has seen evidences of friendly treatment of Bohemians by the Canadian Government during his trip through that country; Premier Borden promises that all Bohemians, except in those cases in which it would be impossible to ascertain immediately the nationality of a person considered an Austrian, will be given an opportunity to take advantage of the privileges enjoyed by the Bohemians in Great Britain. Further, he promises to examine all cases called to his attention by the Narodni Sdruzeni, and will see to it that any injustice is righted.</p>
   <p>In his second letter Premier Borden writes: "Again in regard to your letter of May 29, I wish to give you the assurance that the Canadian Government desires most earnestly to treat all Bohemians in Canada with the utmost consideration. We know how to appreciate their fine qualities, and we shall bear in mind your point of view as expressed in your letter."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1352.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This is distinct evidence that the Canadian Government and its esteemed representative have a most friendly feeling for the Bohemians. It also shows a great deal more consideration for the Bohemians than has ever been made evident on the part of Austrian consuls who are paid, in part, by Bohemian money.</p>
   <p>It now becomes our duty to show our appreciation of the fact that we have been recognized as a nation friendly to the Allies. Still more, however, it becomes a duty of Bohemians in Canada to act as members of a friendly nation, which implies a bit of manly reserve and patience in cases where they, by some mistake, suffer temporary inconvenience and unjust treatment, until the Narodni Sdruzeni has opportunity to request the Canadian Government to right the matter. But let us have all complaints written with restraint and in the knowledge that everybody suffers to some degree in the present war, and if the Bohemians suffer it is not because of their nationality but because of their--frequently voluntary--allegiance to Austria. To demand, however, a <pb facs="5418478_6_1353.jpg" n="4"/>better lot than the Canadians themselves have would be, of course, sheer folly.</p>
   <p>Of course, our countrymen frequently cause their own troubles because of their contacts with Austrians and Germans, a thing which is now more than dangerous. Therefore, let all our countrymen avoid all public and private places where they would come in touch with the Germans, and never use the German language as an "auxiliary" one in contact with people of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Let all the Bohemians and also Slovaks, in Canada contact the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni in Chicago in any cases where they may need help or advice, and let them--and this would be of great value to our cause--start local chapters of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni in places where they do not yet exist, thus joining the organization of American Bohemians.</p>
   <p>The press committee of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni will be sending releases <pb facs="5418478_6_1354.jpg" n="5"/>to all the larger Canadian newspapers concerning the relationship between the Allies and the Bohemians. This, we are certain, will help a great deal in providing the proper kind of information for the, wider, English-reading Canadian public.</p>
   <p>All countrymen in Canada are requested to communicate their wishes to the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni by addressing its secretary, Mr. J. Tvrzicky-Kramer, at 2613 South Avers Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
