<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-05-29">May 29, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Charitable Association Preparing to Hold a Convention in Near Future.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0653</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0653.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-05-29">May 29, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION PREPARING TO HOLD A CONVENTION IN NEAR FUTURE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.--Last Friday evening a regular meeting of the delegates of the Bohemian Charitable Association was held in the office of this institution.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the previous meeting were read and approved. Communications were read requesting aid. These communications were referred to the investigating committee, which later made a report. This report stated that some of the persons who had applied for relief were really in dire need, and aid was given them immediately.</p>
   <p>The secretary then read a financial report, according to which the increase of funds was not as large at the present time as in the past.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0654.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, the dues are being paid regularly. Under these circumstances we should be careful of our expenditures. A discussion was held in regard to the convention, which matter had to be decided by this meeting. After a lengthy debate it was definitely resolved to hold the convention on Friday, June 17th of this year.</p>
   <p>The managing committee is to announce the place where the convention is to be held; it will also be the duty of the delegates to contact Bohemian sections of our city in order to solicit contributions for the expenses of the convention.</p>
   <p>Another report was read on behalf of the Bohemian Club which pledged its financial support and had elected a delegate to represent that Club at the convention. The receipts of this meeting were donations from: J. Cejka, $10; A. Denemark, $5; Ad. Rys, $25; A. Moravec, $5; California Ice Co, $5; Ludwig Kolar $5, and J. O. Horacek, $5; making a total of $60.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0655.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The disbursements were $12.50. The meeting was then adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
