<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-11">Sept. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky Voice a Protest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-11">Sept. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKO-SLOVANSKE PODPORUJICI SPOLKY VOICE A PROTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Associations) dealt in their last meeting with the shameful behavior of the Austrian Ambassdor in Washington, Dr. Dumba, and adopted a strong resolution which follows:</p>
   <p>"The recent regular meeting of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky, with a membership of 50,000 American citizens of Bohemian origin, adopted unanimously the following resolution:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The Austro-Hungarian Ambassador, Dr. Dumba, gravely insulted the Bohemian citizens of this country when he stated in a press conference that the Bohemians from Austria are ignorant and uneducated, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, He tried to cause former Austrian subjects to commit deeds which would violate the neutrality of our country; be it therefore <pb facs="5418478_6_1338.jpg" n="2"/>"Resolved, That we condemn the statements of Dr. Dumba concerning our countrymen as absolutely false and his activities among former Austrian subjects as detrimental to the welfare of our country. As a proper reply to this insult we urge all Bohemians in the United States who have not yet become citizens of the great Republic, to secure their naturalization papers as promptly as possible. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That the necessary steps be taken for the protection of our country against the interference of Dr. Dumba and other organs of the Austrian government with the internal affairs of this nation.</p>
   <p>"(Signed) Eugene Frydl, president</p>
   <p>"Otto T. Pergler, secretary"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
