<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-02">Sept. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Citizens' Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-02">Sept. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CITIZENS' COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A mass meeting held in the hall of Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs, Lawndale Avenue near 26th Street, last Saturday night, was one of the largest in the neighborhood in recent times. It had been called by a committee which bears the official name "83rd Exemption Division Citizens' Committee of the State Council of Defence". We dwelt upon the importance of this body, which was organized recently, in an earlier news item. One of its purposes is to induce parents and other relatives of soldiers at the front, and young men who for various reasons are not in the military service, to join in activities for the purpose of giving relief to either the soldiers themselves or their needy dependents. This patriotic, humanitarian work is to be directed from a centralized headquarters in order to make it more efficient.</p>
   <p>The meeting was for the purpose of instructing all those who join in the movement how to collaborate in their patriotic efforts with other members in the community--for instance, in the raising of Service Flags in a grand patriotic <pb facs="5418478_6_0091.jpg" n="2"/>celebration, at which one single flag is to be unveiled which will stand for the entire 83rd Recruiting Division--i.e., the southern half of the Thirty-fourth Ward. We wish to disclose to our readers that this flag will be constructed of electric bulbs, which will show, at certain times, the number of soldiers enlisted from the 83rd Recruiting Division. This flag with changeable numbers could be placed in the window of the recruiting office of the 83rd Division, which is located on 26th Street and Ridgeway Avenue, where the offices of the Citizens' Committee are also established.</p>
   <p>The Saturday meeting was attended by all the officers, headed by Mr. John A. Cervenka, chairman of the Committee. The body meets every second Thursday of the month in the Hubbard Memorial Church, on Lawndale Avenue. Many new members were secured at the meeting, and the membership is expected to increase rapidly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
