<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-03">Sept. 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Unification for More Intensive Action</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0477</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0477.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-03">Sept. 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A UNIFICATION FOR MORE INTENSIVE ACTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The members and representatives of our three most important public national bodies, recognizing again the validity of the saying that "in union there is strength," met together last night in order to discuss ways and means by which the most effective help could be given to our brothers in Bohemia and in other Slavic countries which are now in a desperate situation.</p>
   <p>We refer to the members and representatives of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council), the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau), and the Cesko-Slovansky Cerveny Kriz (Bohemian-Slavonic Red Cross).</p>
   <p>The meeting, held in the Svobodomyslna Skola Vojta Naprstek (Free Thought School Vojta Naprstek) started a most important development. It founded the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance), consisting of the three bodies, and elected officers, so as to make real work possible immediately.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0478.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The executive committee of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni will publish a detailed statement of the body's purpose later on, but one of its principal duties will be to organize collections of funds to be sent to Bohemia so that they can be used where the real need is greatest.</p>
   <p>But the supreme aim of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni is to follow an idea which is much more far-reaching, though yet very hazy, and which must not be disclosed publicly without a thorough preparation of the ground. Then it will be launched in a very definite form, carefully but decisively, and will be followed with all the strength and vigor the body can muster.</p>
   <p>Immediately after the formation of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni, the election of officers took place with the following results: Dr. L. J. Fisher, president; Mr. Emanuel Beranek, first vice-president; Mrs. Stanek-Bujarek, second vice-president; Mr. S. Vinklarek, secretary; Mr. James F. Stepina, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The president was authorized to appoint an executive committee of nine members, <pb facs="5418478_6_0479.jpg" n="3"/>three from each component body with representatives from four Bohemian dailies of Chicago, to act in an advisory capacity. As we have already mentioned, all other details about the purposes of this new body will be made public in the committee's own report.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
