<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-03">Apr. 3, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">T</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1134</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1134.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-03">Apr. 3, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">T<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Executive Committee of the Americka Obec Sokolska (American Sokol Union), at its last meeting, held March 2<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, 1920, deliberated on the proclamation, "From the Legionnaires to the Czechoslovak People", signed by the Executive Committee of the Czechoslovak Legionnaires and published in Denni Hlasatel, March 25, 1920. In this proclamation, our brother sokols, Joseph Paskovsky, supreme commander of men classes of the Americka Obec Sokolska, Frank J. Kubec, member of the Executive Committee, and Ferdinand L. Musil, member of the Executive Committee of the Central District, are blamed for ungentlemanly manners. It was unanimously resolved to take steps to defend the above-named brother sokols and it is toward this goal that we, the undersigned, proclaim the following:</p>
   <p>"1. We declare that none of the above-mentioned brother sokols has committed any dishonorable act or action repugnant to the conception of sokol honor and discipline. On the contrary, the truth is that at every opportunity they have <pb facs="5418478_6_1135.jpg" n="2"/>always acted as good and honest sokols against whom nothing dishonorable can be proved.</p>
   <p>"2. In the matter of the Czechoslovakian Army, they all complied with the commandments of sokol discipline. Brother sokol Paskovsky was exempted from service in the army after presenting his reasons, and when he attempted to resign his office as supreme commander of the Americka Obec Sokolska, his resignation was not accepted by the Executive Committee. Brother sokol Kubec applied to the Czechoslovak Army, but was ordered by his superiors to stay here in Chicago as chairman of the Military Committee. Brother sokol Ferdinand D. Musil was drafted into the American Army. After six months service, he was discharged; he tried to join the Czechoslovak Legion in Siberia and the Czechoslovak Army in France, but he was rejected by both. In this matter then, they do not deserve to be censured.</p>
   <p>"3. Knowing these three brother sokols, we, therefore, condemn with full determination the attack upon them as a sad example of national discipline, <pb facs="5418478_6_1136.jpg" n="3"/>and we express our regret that anything like this is possible at a time when all our people in America should work together toward one goal, to the greater honor and glory of Czechoslovaks.</p>
   <p>"We respect the organization of the Czechoslovak Legionnaires, but we request its members not to appear before the public against our for most members in such a drastic manner before they have brought their complaints, if they have any, before circles in which these members are active. We cannot permit similar attacks or view them in silence, especially when these people do not deserve such attacks.</p>
   <p>"As resolved by the Executive Committee of the Americka Obec Sokolska.</p>
   <p>"Chicago, March 29, 1920.</p>
   <p>"Joseph Placek, president;</p>
   <p>"Tomas Vonasek, secretary."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
