<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-11">Dec. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Promising Start</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-11">Dec. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A PROMISING START</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian Charitable Association is preparing to make Christmas a time of joy for our poor. It has been doing so for many years. Five hundred baskets filled with food, even some delicacies, and toys for the children will be distributed among needy Czech families on December 24. The list of applicants has been investigated carefully, so that only deserving cases will be considered.</p>
   <p>Although the humanitarian activities of the Association have found full recognition among our public, its financial condition does not allow it to take complete action without aid from sources other than its own.</p>
   <p>A coupon contest was held recently which brought substantial sums of money into the Association's coffers. However, more is needed, for some families have been forced to depend entirely upon the mercy of the society.</p>
   <p>This body feels compelled to appeal for outside help from our more prosperous <pb facs="5418478_6_0168.jpg" n="2"/>countrymen. The first call for help was answered in a gratifying manner.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cermak, chief bailiff of the municipal court, succeeded in obtaining a gift of fifty dollars from the Bailiffs' Association. This will pay for ten baskets. Mr. Cermak is a director of the Charitable Association. County Judge Thomas F. Scully gave Mr. Cermak a check for twenty-five dollars..... [Translator's note: A list of other donors follows.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
