<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-02-24">Feb. 24, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">In Memory of the Father of Our Country</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-02-24">Feb. 24, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">IN MEMORY OF THE FATHER OF OUR COUNTRY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As usual, the annual celebration of George Washington's birthday was held under the auspices of the Plzenske Sokolky (Women members of the Pilsen Sokol) last Tuesday evening in the Pilsen Sokol hall. The Plzenske Sokolky have been arranging these celebrations for many years, and although every one of these celebrations has been marked by piety and dignity, last Tuesday's celebration was one of the most beautiful of all. Credit for it must be given to the arrangement committee, consisting of Sisters Terezie R. Dobias, Marie Herda, Ruzena Kapoun, and Marie Novak, who succeeded in securing some of the most talented artists in our community. The beautiful program and the significance of the evening attracted so many people that the hall was filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>The program was opened by the orchestra, consisting of the most advanced pupils of the Chicago Conservatory of Music, under the direction of their <pb facs="5418478_6_1730.jpg" n="2"/>teacher, Professor Joseph H. Capek. They played the American, Bohemian, and Slovak national anthems. Their presentation was really excellent, and the audience rewarded them with thunderous applause.....</p>
   <p>Dr. Jaroslav E. S. Vojan, who was selected as the speaker for the festival, performed his task in a truly remarkable manner. In his speech, he mentioned how the founders of Sokoldom, Jindrich Fuegner and Miroslav Tyrs, admired George Washington because of his love of freedom and his civic virtues.</p>
   <p>The program lasted until 11 P. M. Individual items on the program vied with each other in excellence, so that the audience scarcely noticed the late hour.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
