<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-04-14">Apr. 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution Adopted at the Great Mass-Meeting of March Fifteenth Distributed Throughout America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-04-14">Apr. 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION ADOPTED AT THE GREAT MASS-MEETING OF MARCH FIFTEENTH DISTRIBUTED THROUGHOUT AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bohemians scattered all over America are sending letters of thanks for the good accruing to them through the energetic intervention of the Narodni Rada.</p>
   <p>"The Bohemian head will puncture a wall", Karel Havlicek (Bohemian journalist) wrote many years ago, and what he wrote was the truth. Whenever the Bohemians presented themselves energetically, they always were able to go through a wall of prejudice and ignorance; and that happened in this instance.</p>
   <p>The resolution adopted at the mass meeting was sent to the various newspapers, magazines and influential institutions throughout the country. It is doing excellent work in chasing away the clouds of ignorance which still exist among Americans concerning us and our culture.</p>
   <p>We here present the translation of the resolution, so that our readers can <pb facs="5418478_6_1418.jpg" n="2"/>comprehend how the battle was fought against the wrongs and injustices per-pertrated on the Slav people:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, in the monthly magazine Century there appeared a number of articles written by Professor E. A. Ross, in which the Slav immigrants were described in an extremely insulting manner, which articles were the culmination of prejudice, and not of a scientific study; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, those articles tended to anger and prejudice the Americans against Slav immigrants and Slav people of this country; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, as true American citizens, we believe that justice and truth should prevail;</p>
   <p>Therefore, be it resolved by those here assembled that we unanimously condemn the above-named articles as unscientific, un-American, and unworthy of a scholar and fellow citizen; that the monthly Century deserves an emphatic <pb facs="5418478_6_1419.jpg" n="3"/>rebuke for the wrong done by the publishing and approving of said articles; that Professor E. A. Ross and the editor of Century are hereby requested to right the wrongs perpetrated on the Slav immigrants by those articles; that copies of this resolution be sent to Professor Ross, to the editor of Century, and to others when they may be needed; that the Narodni Rada (Bohemian National Council) is empowered to elect a standing committee, whose duty it will be to forestall such attacks, or at least to lessen the evil they may do.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
