<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-06">Sept.6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">First Month's Report of the Cesko- Slovansky Vyponocny Vybor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0472</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0472.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-06">Sept.6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST MONTH'S REPORT OF THE CESKO- SLOVANSKY VYPONOCNY VYBOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesko-Slovansky Vypomocny Vybor (Bohemian-Slavonic Auxiliary Committee) is entering upon its second month's work with a degree of success which, in view of our conditions, is certainly satisfactory.</p>
   <p>There is now over eleven hundred dollars in cash in the hands of its treasurer, over six thousand dollars in pledges, and some three thousand dollars in the hands of newspapers and other collectors. Thus, by now, the result of the collections is about ten thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>Our Sokols have taken the lead in the solicitation of funds. The Telocvicna Jednota Sokol (Gymnastic Association Sokol, has sent out ninety collection sheets from its main office to its several units, and the Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs (Sokol unit called Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs) has distributed fifty such sheets. With them, the Sokols have inaugurated collections among themselves and their <pb facs="5418478_6_0473.jpg" n="2"/>friends. Our other large national bodies will be asked to start similar moves, so that systematic solicitation will be inaugurated soon.</p>
   <p>The Cesko-Slovansky Vypomocny Vybor has arranged three mass meetings in Chicago already: One in Pilsen Park, July 28, the day of the outbreak of the war; one in Oak Park, August 29; and one in the Sokol Pilsen hall, September 3. In addition to this, its members actively co-operated with the Serbs, Croatians, and Slovaks with the organization, and also attended their meetings.</p>
   <p>A systematic house-to-house canvass is in preparation in Chicago. Patriotic ladies who are ready to help us in this action are requested to send their addresses to Mrs. F. Stanek-Bujarek, at 1539 West 19th Street.</p>
   <p>Our artistic circles have promised the Committee their help by arranging a number of festivals where the public will be treated to real artistic and refined entertainment. The festivals will take place in the very near future, and all they net will be used for the support of our suffering brothers in the <pb facs="5418478_6_0474.jpg" n="3"/>old country.</p>
   <p>TO OUR FRIENDS OUTSIDE OF CHICAGO</p>
   <p>The first request we direct to you is to work with us toward our common goal. Let us all do our duty, forgetting petty interests which are local or personal in character. We have been receiving many contributions from the old country, but we beg our out-of-Chicago countrymen not to stop at personal donations, but rather to organize collections among their friends with the aid of the collection sheets which the secretary and the treasurer have available upon request. Both should be addressed to 1825 Blue Island Avenue, Chicago, Illinois. Very, very much money will be needed to mitigate the terrible misery which, like a horrid specter, haunts our Bohemian meadows. No one is so poor that he cannot contribute, and contribute more than once.</p>
   <p>Let us not be confused by reports of despicable actions of some renegades which have been reaching us from the old country. Our sympathies go to the Bohemian people, not to some imperial councellors or climbers a la Gros [mayor of Prague <pb facs="5418478_6_0475.jpg" n="4"/>at that time]. These people whose sons are bleeding on the battlefields, whose crops are rotting for lack of men to reap them, whose shops are closed, are calling to us for help. It is they in whom we are interested. Then down to work, and with united efforts, let us forge ahead!</p>
   <p>(Signed): Jaroslav V. Nigrin, Secretary,</p>
   <p>Cesko-Slovansky Vypomocny Vybor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
