<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-02">June 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Women Work for the Red Cross</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0108</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0108.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-02">June 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH WOMEN WORK FOR THE RED CROSS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czech ladies' group of the American Red Cross is meeting regularly at the Hubbard Memorial Church, 2520 South Lawndale Avenue. It is composed mostly of residents of the district around Lawndale and Crawford Avenues. They were asked by the Czech headquarters of the Red Cross to devote their efforts toward a membership drive during the past two weeks. They requested the captain of that Red Cross district, Mr. Jos. F. Bolek, to pitch tents on Streets, from which the soliciting could be conducted. Under the able direction of Mrs. B. Kafka, head of the ladies' section, a large number of tents grew up in the neighborhood over night, so to speak, and activity which demonstrated the real patriotic sentiment of our women was aroused. To Mr. Ant. Petrzelka, 2417 South Millard Avenue, goes much credit for the acquisition of the tents.</p>
   <p>Our ladies worked untiringly from morning till night, not only in and around the tents, but in theaters and moving-picture houses. How many of you fellow <pb facs="5418478_6_0109.jpg" n="2"/>countrymen, while walking west on 26th Street, have observed the little five-to-ten-year-old girls trying to outdo each other in approaching prospective members and donors.</p>
   <p>Thirty of our women worked on Decoration Day, especially, soliciting the crowds which were moving toward the Bohemian National Cemetery and the Catholic cemetery. [There follows a list of donors and amounts collected.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
