<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-12-18">Dec. 18, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A Beautiful Evening</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-12-18">Dec. 18, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A BEAUTIFUL EVENING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The spacious hall of the Pilsen auditorium was filled yesterday with educated Slavic people who came to hear the speech of Dr. Pavel Blaho, the well-known resort physician of the spa of Luhacovice, and one of the greatest sons of the Slovak people.</p>
   <p>The evening was a welcome prepared for Dr. Blaho by the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau), and we have not the slightest doubt that the progressive Slovak patriot was more than pleased with this welcome.</p>
   <p>The lecture was scheduled for 8 P. M., but the program did not start until one hour later, because the public, composed mostly of business and professional men and women, were slow in arriving.</p>
   <p>The evening started with two selections for the piano presented by the young Slovak artist, Arnost Krizan. He played Dvorak's "Dumka" (Meditation) and <pb facs="5418478_6_1458.jpg" n="2"/>"Furiant" [name of a lively dance], and his performance was rewarded by stormy applause.....</p>
   <p>The second number on the program was Miss Maruska Geringer's presentation of two Slovak songs, which were received with such enthusiasm that the youthful artist had to play two encores before she was permitted to leave the platform.</p>
   <p>After Miss Geringer's performance, the delegation of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar, with Dr. Blaho, stepped to the platform. Banker Stepina, as president of the Bureau, said a few words in the way of welcome and introduced the first speaker of the evening, Mr. E. St. Vraz. Mr. Vraz was greeted with spirited applause and fulfilled his task in a very simple, original, and sympathetic way. In a few sentences, which evoked bursts of approval, he recalled the beautiful days be spent with Dr. Blaho in the spa of Luhacovice where, during clear summer nights, they observed the starry sky--stars which seem so small and tiny to the naked eye and yet represent whole independent worlds. The Slavic world used to be like one of these stars, but now it has <pb facs="5418478_6_1459.jpg" n="3"/>presented itself to the world as an independent, great entity with characteristics of its own. Vraz and Blaho used to dream about the future greatness of the Slavic people during these nights. Both men are ardent Panslavists and patriotic sons of their nation who never thought that Slavdom would so suddenly show its greatness and its power to the whole world, as it did by its victory in the Balkan War.....He introduced Dr. Blaho, who again was welcomed by huge applause.</p>
   <p>Dr. Blaho's speech can well be divided into two distinct parts. The first was devoted to a discussion of Slovak songs and Slovak music in general, to which the speaker was inspired, at least to some extent, by Miss Geringer's share of the program. Slovak songs have an ardent admirer in Dr. Blaho.....</p>
   <p>The second and principal part of his speech dealt with Bohemian-Slovak mutuality of interest and national brotherhood. In this part, Dr. Blaho showed his great knowledge of Slavic problems to the best advantage.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1460.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Dr. Blaho's speech took more than an hour and a half and was constantly interrupted by applause.</p>
   <p>The first part of the evening was brought to a close with a few words by Mr. Psenka, and the whole party adjourned into the dining hall where an elegant banquet was served in honor of the guest.....</p>
   <p>Short but fitting speeches were presented during the banquet by several well-known representatives of Chicago's Slavdom. Mr. Karel J. Vopicka spoke for the Bohemians, Mr. Josef Tomko and Mr. Andrew Sustek for the Slovaks, Prof. Ziz-kovic for the Serbs, and Mr. Palandic for the Montenegrins. The credit for the presence of our Yugoslav brothers is due to our noted Pan-Slavist, Mr. Emil Bachman.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
