<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-28">Oct. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Newspapermen in Bohemia Are in Distress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-28">Oct. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">NEWSPAPERMEN IN BOHEMIA ARE IN DISTRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The war has dealt a harsh blow to many a newspaperman in the old country. Newspapers that refused to publish only what was given them by the military authorities and tried to retain the right to their own opinions have been suppressed; others have reduced their staffs considerably. A committee has been formed to solicit contributions so that at least the most acute suffering of unemployed newspapermen can be prevented. Could not we in America send some of the money collected for war relief to that committee? We are convinced that such action would be fully within the intentions of the contributors. When such intelligent and educated people are in need, their situation is worse than it would be with other poor workingmen, because the former are trying to hide their plight and are ashamed to ask for help. Only their colleagues know about that situation, but in these bad times, even they cannot give them any help. Therefore, in behalf of the distressed, these men have turned to the Bohemian public, and we hope <pb facs="5418478_6_0428.jpg" n="2"/>that their call for help may be answered not only in Bohemia and Moravia, but also among us.</p>
   <p>With this help, young, capable men may be saved, and they will repay the debt to their country many times over in the future. These men will be grateful for any assistance extended to them in these times of suffering and need. And those old men who would be helped at the same time do not deserve to have the nation let them despair at the end of a life fully devoted to their nation and its interests. Newspapermen of such a small nation as ours do not sleep in beds of roses even in normal times and never get such monetary rewards as their colleagues in great nations. In days such as these, they should therefore be entitled to some help from their nation, and Bohemian America should also contribute its share.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
