<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1885-05-19">May 19th, 1885</date>.
<title level="a">The Corporation Bohemian Settlement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0963</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0963.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1885-05-19">May 19th, 1885</date>.
<title level="a">THE CORPORATION BOHEMIAN SETTLEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Corporation Bohemian Settlement, is composed of Bohemian Citizens, who really intend to move out of Chicago. The corporation has resolved to move to one of the south-western states, which will be recommended by a committee, sent there previously. The corporation cannot promise other privileges than the following: 1, the journey will cost half of the amount paid in by a single traveler; 2, the agricultural implements can be bought more cheaper than by a single person, and the factory must send it free to the place related; 3, establishing our own market we will be able to compete successfully with the big farmers; and 4 by buying land collective colonization the price per acre will be much lower. The corporation has decided to buy a tract of land in the middle of the state, to survey it and to make subdivisions in such a way, that every member of the Bohemian Settlement will receive one lot of about one acre in size. The homes will be displayed each in its marked position in such a manner, that the whole acquired tract will be occupied with the homes of the members of the Bohemian Settlement and everyone who will follow us <pb facs="5418478_6_0964.jpg" n="2"/>to the settlement must be satisfied with the lots situated farther from the central part of the village.</p>
   <p>The corporation Bohemian Settlement, is not composed of capitalists and does not possess any capital, consequently it cannot advise the people without any means to participate as members in the corporation.</p>
   <p>Everyone should know that the start will be very hard and will inevitably require some amount of money with which to start. We found that everyone must have at least $200 besides transportation expenses.</p>
   <p>Everyone,who is a Unites States Citizen or in the possession of his first paper can buy a house. Everyone, who pays fifty cents, initiation fee to the secretary can be a member of the corporation. This fifty cents fee is required of the members as a kind of obligation or guarantee and it used for the current expenses. The clerical work in the organization is performed by the employees without any compensation, and they are rewarded with the <pb facs="5418478_6_0965.jpg" n="3"/>consciousness that they are working for the benefit of this countryman. When the committee for the purpose of making a definite selection of the location will be elected, the final estimate of expenses will be divided among all members of the corporation. The corporation organized in Chicago is sixty members strong. Josef J. Wolf is the secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
