<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-09">Oct. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Prepare for Liberty Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1755</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1755.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-09">Oct. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PREPARE FOR LIBERTY DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Czechoslovaks should take part in the parade on Liberty Day in truly impressive numbers. This event is sponsored by the central committee for the Fourth Liberty Loan campaign. It is an occasion when we Czechoslovaks must show anew our everlasting loyalty to the Government and to President Wilson. October 12, 1918, has been designated as a national holiday by President Wilson, and the parade through the downtown streets will be the high point of the Liberty Loan campaign.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak section of the campaign has assumed the task of making arrangements for the part which the Czechoslovaks will take in the procession, so that our section shall be the best arranged, and excel all other nationalities. The arrangements committee of the Czechoslovak section cannot achieve the desired results without the vigorous co-operation of our people; individuals, associations, corporations, etc. For this reason, the arrangements committee addresses itself to our public, and to our organizations in particular.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1756.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is not much time available for preparation but we should remember that we made a wonderful showing on last Fourth of July under the same conditions-- and yet, our parade was one of the most elaborate that day in the entire United States. There is no reason whatever why we should not be able to repeat on this occasion. The success of this patriotic enterprise depends mainly upon the zeal of the heads of our organizations. Some of the organizations may not have scheduled meetings before the event, nevertheless the officers should contact the members and urge them to take part in the parade.</p>
   <p>We are not yet in a position to present a specific program, because we do not know at the moment which place will be assigned to the Czechoslovak section in the procession. We may be able to give more information tomorrow. It is absolutely essential that our organizations appear with their banners and emblems. Our ladies' societies, whose members took part in large numbers in last Monday's meeting of the executive committee, are working diligently, and at this moment are issuing the following appeal:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1757.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Sisters of the Czech Ladies' Unit, Aid Societies and Sisterhoods, Central Unit of Czech-American Women, Unit of Czech Patriot Women, Association of Czech-American Ladies, Catholic Slav Women's Units, Czech Catholic Societies, and members of all other units and associations, should begin preparation today for the parade on Saturday, to make our participation outstanding. All our Sisters are requested to come dressed in white. It goes without saying that organizations march behind their banners.</p>
   <p>Sisters! Be mindful of the glory attached to the Czechoslovak name! Let us do again what our national honor dictates.</p>
   <p>Signed: Marie Smrcek, Frances Piper, Dr. Mary Urban, [and others.]</p>
   <p>The Sokols, this pioneer group of ours, which has given its best soldiers to this country, will surely be represented to the last man in the parade. Jarka Kosar, that ardent Sokol, is requesting all those who intend to participate to report at 1928 South 63rd Court.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1758.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Our butchers will join the parade in the garb of their guild, and will be one of the most colorful groups in the Czechoslovak division. Our Vcelky (Little Bees), and the Czech women's auxiliaries of the Red Cross, are sure to add luster to the Czechoslovak division. Any information concerning the parade is at the disposal of participants at the Czechoslovak main offices, 3342 West 26th Street, Telephone Lawndale 105.</p>
   <p>All workers in the Fourth Liberty Loan campaign are invited to a meeting in the Pilsen Brewery Park, Thursday evening when important questions regarding the campaign are to be discussed, and the finishing touches of the parade decided on.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
