<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-22">May 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Slovanska Lipa</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Brief Summary of the History of an Old Sokol Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1552</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1552.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-22">May 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">SLOVANSKA LIPA</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Brief Summary of the History of an Old Sokol Society</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Toward the end of the year 1901, Sokol Slovanska Lipa was on the decline, and it was thought that this society would vanish entirely. The reason for this was that Bohemians were rapidly leaving DeKoven Street, and seeking a new center for themselves in Bohemian California, on 18th Street. The reasons which lead to the disintegration of the Slovanska Lipa are diverse.</p>
   <p>The chief reason was that the members were not allowed to cultivate athletics, although the majority endeavored to do so. To this, however, the president of the society, Mr. Vaclav Zahrobsy, the commander, Mr. Flor. Holek, and other older members, did not want to agree. The result of this was that the membership began to leave the Slovanska Lipa and join other societies. Because Slovanska Lipa did not have enough members, training was discontinued, <pb facs="5418478_6_1553.jpg" n="2"/>and no younger members were accepted. The homes on DeKoven Street which were abandoned by the Bohemians, were occupied by Italians, who live there to this date. Time went fast, and little by little Slovanska Lipa would have been forgotten.</p>
   <p>However, being moved by an inward instinct, the former leaders of Slovanska Lipa began work to again revive it. They succeeded, after several meetings in acquiring a young membership, and a new instructor, Mr. Joseph Petr, was engaged, who again brought everything back to the old order, after a dormant period of eight years.</p>
   <p>Mr. Petr is instructing eight adult members, six members over fourteen years of age, and twenty-five female sokols. Slovanska Lipa now has a total of 190 members. It is progressing forward with a will, and sponsors entertainments and educational lectures. This society is again working with new strength and vigor toward the indicated goal. A brief review of the history of Slovanska Lipa, which we bring here, will surely interest every reader of <pb facs="5418478_6_1554.jpg" n="3"/>this paper.</p>
   <p>Sokol Slovanska Lipa From 1865 to 1870</p>
   <p>Sokol Slovanska Lipa, otherwise formerly called "Janet" (Unity), was created from "Cesko-Americky Sokol" (Bohemian-American Sokol). Sokol also was a branch of this unity, and used the insignia and attire of the original Sokol of Prague. Because of diverse opinions about attire and gymnastic matters, part of the society organized into an independent society, Cesko-Americky Sokol, after which all such societies had their own administrations. May 5, 1868 was the day of dissolution. The origin of the first society of the Slovanska Lipa cannot be given definitely for in the oldest minute books available, those of March 2, 1865, the officers of the society already had been elected.</p>
   <p>At that time, the societies were regularly managed, and books kept. Sick benefits were being paid and records of receipts, disbursements, and minutes of meetings kept. Libraries were established and books loaned.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1555.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>From observation, it appears that each branch belonging to the unity had its own management and library. The president of the society communicated a password to each member, without which the member was not permitted to attend the meeting of the Slovanska Lipa.</p>
   <p>It is also remembered that the Bohemian school at that time was managed by four members, and the school children were accepted for training. Bohemian plays were given, such as "chytrousek," "Prazsky, Flamendr" and others. On the day when President Abraham Lincoln was assassinated, merriment and training was postponed, and preparation begun for the attendance of Slovanska Lipa at the funeral. On April 17, 1865, the Bohemian public was invited to a general gathering in the hall of Slovanska Lipa, so as to collectively express their grief over the loss of the President. Bohemian girls were requested to decorate the hall in a suitable manner.</p>
   <p>With the arrival of a more educated class of Bohemians in America, the membership <pb facs="5418478_6_1556.jpg" n="5"/>of Slovanska Lipa increased visibly. Additional books were bought, and a library established, which was complete for that period. Public gymnastic exhibitions were given, and evening dances were given in a hall especially rented for the purpose.</p>
   <p>The by-laws of the Slovanska Lipa in the year 1870 were as follows::</p>
   <p>(1) To cultivate and maintain the Bohemian nationality.</p>
   <p>(2) To endeavor to establish and maintain a Bohemian-English liberal school.</p>
   <p>(3) To cultivate dramatic art through Czech-Slavonic songs.</p>
   <p>(4) To maintain libraries and public reading rooms.</p>
   <p>(5) To cultivate physical culture.</p>
   <p>(6) To give assistance in case of sickness and accident.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1557.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The Manner in Which Members Were Accepted Into the Slovanska Lipa</p>
   <p>Members were classified as regular and honorary. Regular members were those who were admitted into the organization in accordance with the constitution and by-laws. Honorary members were those who were declared as such by the organization. Any Bohemian-Slav, who had reached eighteen years of age, and had not passed fifty years, who was healthy in body, mind, and morals, irreproachable, and willing to live up to these by-laws, could become a regular member. It was also expected that he be honorable, and attend meetings regularly. Under conditions of these by-laws, members were accepted into the organization.</p>
   <p>The first happenings of Cesko-Americky Sokol for the year 1868 were not fully preserved. This body was strictly governed and the members stressed not only physical education , but mental education also.</p>
   <p>In order to furnish the organization with a banner, zealous Bohemian girls <pb facs="5418478_6_1558.jpg" n="7"/>sponsored dances. Cesko-Americky Sokol also arranged exhibitions, and performed Bohemian theatricals in the gymnasium. When enough money had been gathered, the presentation of a banner was accomplished. The presentation of the colors occurred on July 3, 1868, and every member was required to attend. After the dedication of the colors, the organization provided itself with black sashes and sokol insignia. For the purpose of increasing acquaintance, contacts were maintained with German societies, and mutual visits made during celebrations.</p>
   <p>When they had all preparations completed, it was resolved to apply for a charter to the State. The sokol attire was used only for public exhibitions. Toward their attire, they felt a sort of sacred reverence and respect.</p>
   <p>All members had permission to attend so-called national meetings. New apparatus was purchased and arranged according to the system used in the old country. In 1868, they began to use their own seal, around which was inscribed: "Cesko-Americky Sokol v Chicago, Illinois." In the year 1869, the members <pb facs="5418478_6_1559.jpg" n="8"/>decided to build their own hall, each member being required to contribute five dollars toward the purpose.</p>
   <p>The members were compelled to pay this sum, if they did not wish to be expelled. That year a site was purchased on DeKoven Street. The construction of the hall was soon begun, and shares were issued which the members bought. Bohemian societies were also asked to contribute. The societies willingly complied with the request, and gave entertainments and theatrical performances for the benefit of Cesko Americky Sokol.</p>
   <p>In 1869, the hall was dedicated.</p>
   <p>There are no other memoirs available, but it is known nevertheless, that Slovanska Lipa had quite a long pilgrimage. It grew powerful and strong, and then again traveled briefly in the abyss of disintegration. However, the spirit of the times did not permit that such a long existent sokol society should disintegrate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
