<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-14">Oct. 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our Societies and Clubs</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary of Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-14">Oct. 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SOCIETIES AND CLUBS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary of Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"At the close of the summer season which is never noted for great activities, our organizations are making plans for enlivening the coming winter time.....The war has placed many brotherhoods in a serious, if not downright critical situation. To better these conditions a larger attendance in the meetings will be highly desirable.....The approach of the general assemblies of the associations will be accompanied by the usual complaint that the attendance is frequently so small that it is difficult to elect officers....."</p>
   <p>"The Cleveland, Ohio,Czecho-Slavonic Aid Society has a great deal to say about this question....It points to the cold, businesslike manner in which the meetings are disposed of. No entertainment is offered, and nothing instructive is <pb facs="5418478_6_1198.jpg" n="2"/>presented. There is nothing to attract the members. New York Czech societies suggest that ladies, relatives of the members, visit the meetings to create a more cheery atmosphere. Their particular gift in this respect is appreciated by all organizations.....</p>
   <p>This aptitude of women accounts for the fact that ladies' singing societies are far ahead of ours, and therefore we should ask ourselves just why we did not give this due thought long ago. There are widows of members who would appreciate being invited and might even take an active interest in the affairs of the club. In aid societies the duties and benefits are equal for men or women. The latter should therefore be brought into closer contract with the agenda of the organization.</p>
   <p>The times when we delegated our women to the kitchen or laundry are gone. We have among us today many progressive women who are perfectly familiar with the business pertaining to associations; women who possess the power of independent thought and the fearless manner necessary to give it expression.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1199.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It may be that many a disinterested inert brother was stirred up to more zealous activity by the enterprise of women in the organization. Let us think this over, and admit that the presence of women may improve conditions considerably.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
