<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-07-05">July 5, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">We Protest</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Inconsiderate, Shameless Attack against the Bohemian People by the Socialist Newspaper, Daily World</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0916</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0916.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-07-05">July 5, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">WE PROTEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Inconsiderate, Shameless Attack against the Bohemian People by the Socialist Newspaper, Daily World</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This morning's edition of the Socialist newspaper, Daily World, contains an abusive attack against the Bohemian people in its report of the Gotch-Smejkal wrestling match.</p>
   <p>It is our duty to protest against this attack in the name of all the Bohemian people. We cannot let this assault against the Bohemian people, against our women and girls, pass unnoticed.</p>
   <p>The Daily World writes: "In one of the front boxes sits a company consisting of Smejkal's close relatives. Here they create a whole Bohemian community. They speak Bohemian and are attired a la Ellis Island. This group was a riddle <pb facs="5418478_6_0917.jpg" n="2"/>to the American guests. Aside from Negroes and Bohemians, there were no other ladies within this circle, although the galleries swarmed with variegated petticoats and hats of the most diverse kinds, etc."</p>
   <p>The Socialist paper apparently ranks Bohemian women and girls with the Negro women, and even gives the Negroes a sort of preference. It proclaims it a shame and perhaps even a provocation if the people speak Bohemian. It laughs at the Bohemians, saying that they are dressed in immigrant attire, or "a la Ellis Island".</p>
   <p>At the present time, protests are being made against the so-called Bellingham-Root Senate bill which is aimed against immigrants. The Daily World took an active part in these protests, but now it comes forward with an attack against the Bohemians, their women and girls. The Bohemian language is laughable to that paper. The latter ridicules the Bohemians for their workingmen's attire, and it jokes that it was the Bohemian community which was a "riddle" to the <pb facs="5418478_6_0918.jpg" n="3"/>Americans.</p>
   <p>This is supposed to be a Socialist newspaper which propagates equal rights; this is a newspaper published by immigrants who make their living and fatten on trusting people, against whose patience and confidence they sin. If the Bohemian people are to be the laughing stock for such a yellow sheet; if the Daily World does not know any more about the Bohemian people than it printed in its slanderous publication today, then it is a sad example of its journalistic knowledge, and it would be much more proper if these gentlemen used manure forks instead of editorial pens.</p>
   <p>We protest against this insulting attack on the Bohemian people; we believe that our protest will not be in vain, and that the Bohemian people will now fully recognize what kind of people are trying to be the leaders of the workingmen.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian people will recognize these first-class know-nothings attired as <pb facs="5418478_6_0919.jpg" n="4"/>Socialists, or rather, these howling wolves in sheep's clothing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
