<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-03-23">March 23rd, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Citizenship Papers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0987</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0987.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-03-23">March 23rd, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Citizenship Papers.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All those wishing to vote at the coming spring elections must be citizens and they must have their names entered on the registration books of voters.</p>
   <p>No one can be registered as a qualified voter who has not secured his second papers. (Citizenship Papers) Last week there were two days during which registrations were held and there will be one more day of registration, the last, of which we are reminding you now, this week.</p>
   <p>There are still many Bohemians among us who should have been entitled to vote long ago, who have not taken advantage of this privilege because they have not as yet obtained their final citizenship papers. There is absolutely no difficulty in connection with the obtainment of these papers. They can be had from any State or Federal Court if the applicant brings with him two citizens as witnesses. For the better convenience of their countrymen citizens Belohradsky, Hudek, and Jandus have decided to make the necessary arrangements for all those entitled to citizenship who present themselves to them.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0988.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the 5th precinct of the 6th ward our countrymen can present themselves to citizen Jan Morava of 18th Street, he is the precinct captain there, and he will arrange to accompany the applicants to the proper authority.</p>
   <p>Workingmen do not forget to cast your ballot for the Socialist candidates at the coming election, for they are the only ones from whom we may expect anything better than that which has thus far been given us. What the workingmen can accomplish was shown at the last election when they succeeded in electing three of their candidates.</p>
   <p>There should be no question this time as to our success if only the working men do not lack the will to accomplish it. Whoever has not received their citizenship papers and if they are entitled to them should take steps to secure the same as soon as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
