<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-03-12">Mar. 12, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[Need for Playgrounds]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0744</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0744.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-03-12">Mar. 12, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[NEED FOR PLAYGROUNDS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The period of school vacations makes one most keenly aware of the advantages of well-located and properly equipped children's playgrounds. A mother who lives in the vicinity of such grounds can without worry let her children leave the house, knowing where they are going and being sure that they will spend their time in an agreeable and healthful way.</p>
   <p>There are no such provisions for the children of the two Bohemian districts formerly known as "Lawndale" and "Crawford", which now form a part of Bohemian "California". No public school there has a playground, and there is not even a small park in that neighborhood. The children either have to take a long walk to Douglas Park, stay on the streets, or spend their time in vacant lots near the Drainage Canal. Everybody will admit that there is very little safety--<pb facs="5418478_6_0745.jpg" n="2"/>either for the children's bodies or for their morals--on the streets or at the Canal.</p>
   <p>Both taxpayers' and improvement associations have dealt with this question. Various promises have been made to meet this need, but so far nothing has been done in that direction. Spring is around the corner, and in about three months vacations will be here. If anything is to be accomplished by then, it will be necessary to present this matter before the respective authorities, that is the City Council and the Board of Education immediately. At the new Gary School on Lawndale Avenue there is ample vacant space for a playground. Its establishment would be a real blessing for children living within a radius of one mile of the school. Just let us make it known to the proper authorities that such a playground is wanted, that we demand it in full seriousness. We shall get it, and get it in time for our children to enjoy during their next vacation. It will be a source of pleasure and healthful fun for them; and for our parents it will be an assurance that their children are <pb facs="5418478_6_0746.jpg" n="3"/>spending their free time without endangering their lives and morals, a danger to which they are exposed in the streets and vacant lots.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
