<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-17">Dec. 17, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0598</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0598.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-17">Dec. 17, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The monthly meeting of the board of directors of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) was held on Friday evening in the office of the Pilsen Brewery Company. Mr. Joseph Z. Uhlir presided. Mr. John Cervenka excused himself for being absent from the meeting. The minutes of the previous meeting of the board of directors and the executive committee were read and accepted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Thomas Kalal, 3245 West 26th Street, sent $5; a certain fellow countryman who had been helped with a loan sent $20 as a payment on his loan; Mrs. Mary E. Storkan, 1918 South Avers Avenue, sent $10 in payment of annual membership dues; Mr. Lurie contributed $5 by remitting a bill payable; Mr. S. B. Store, 3539 West 26th Street, contributed the proceeds of a bill paid, $5.06. Out of bills incurred for the dance the following amounts were remitted as contributions [to the Association]:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0599.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Frank Brezinsky, $5; Mr. Anton Dolezal, $2; and Mr. John Kalik, manager of Pilsen Park, $2.</p>
   <p>From the report presented by the office manager of the Bohemian Charitable Association, Mr. Turek, it is apparent that many of our fellow countrymen are applying for assistance. All cases reported were conscientiously investigated, and all those found to be deserving received assistance. In the last fifteen days, from December 1 to December 15, $234 has been paid out in relief, including payments for groceries, for clothing and footwear, for the care of poor children, for coal, for rent, and for burial expenses. Some of the cases reported were tragic. Mr. Turek found one family of which the father had died a year ago. He had been ill for a year before he died. The family now consists of the mother and eight children. At the time of the father's decease they owed seven hundred dollars. The wife paid the debts and the funeral expenses out of the husband's insurance, and the family was left penniless. They did not have even a stove; <pb facs="5418478_6_0600.jpg" n="3"/>three boys had no shoes to wear to school. This family was aided with $20.80, and the board of directors authorized the agent to buy clothing and shoes for the three boys, ten, twelve, and fourteen years of age. There are many sad cases in which the father is unemployed, the mother is ill, and the children are without clothing or shoes. Any Bohemian family able to contribute shoes or clothing is requested to send them to the Bohemian Charitable Association. Many needy people will be helped thereby, especially in this winter period when there is little work to be had, and suffering and want are the daily lot of many persons.</p>
   <p>Money is still being received for tickets for the Association's dance, so that the net proceeds now amount to $1,968.64.</p>
   <p>Representatives of our daily papers have been requested to announce in their journals that applications from needy families for Christmas baskets must be received not later than December 19. By that time every application for a <pb facs="5418478_6_0601.jpg" n="4"/>Christmas basket must be in, either in the offices of the newspapers or in the office of the Association. The committee must investigate each application, and since it must know by Tuesday the number of applications to be handled, it is necessary that those who intend to apply for Christmas baskets shall do so before Tuesday. It will be impossible to pay any attention to requests received later.</p>
   <p>The investigating committee of three, Messrs. Vanek, Krasny, and Klenha, will have a joint meeting next Tuesday with the executive committee and the ladies of the Bohemian Charitable Association to confer upon the Christmas baskets and to decide in what manner distribution is to be made. A report about this will appear in Denni Hlasatel after the meeting.</p>
   <p>The chairman, Mr. Joseph Z. Uhlir, has announced that the idea of giving a charity concert in the Auditorium for the benefit of the Bohemian Charitable Association, the Old People's Home and Orphanage, and St. Joseph's Orphanage <pb facs="5418478_6_0602.jpg" n="5"/>has been given up because the joint committee could not meet the conditions imposed by the Czech artists of the Metropolitan Opera Company of New York. The committee will continue, however, to endeavor to arrange something big among Czechs for the benefit of these three organizations.</p>
   <p>The committee appointed to secure a share of the proceeds of the general tag day in the city will try to obtain for Czech humanitarian purposes a proportionate share.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank J. Petrie was authorized to call upon the Florida Land Company and to endeavor to get them to keep their promise to give to the Association a ten-acre tract of land.</p>
   <p>Because many of our compatriots are applying for Christmas baskets, well-to-do Bohemians are requested to help with one or more baskets and thereby reduce the expenses of the Association. The Association in this cruel winter period <pb facs="5418478_6_0603.jpg" n="6"/>finds it a difficult task to take care of hundreds of needy people and supply them with food, fuel, and funds for the payment of rent. Anybody who is willing to help in this cause, whether with Christmas baskets or with money, should call at the office of the Bohemian Charitable Association before Tuesday evening. The Christmas holidays are a time of rejoicing, and our poor people should not be forgotten by those who live in the midst of abundance and can afford to help.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
