<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-02-18">Feb. 18, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost to Build a Home for Young People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-02-18">Feb. 18, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST TO BUILD A HOME FOR YOUNG PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the meeting of the directors of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) held last Friday, the following donations were received: [A list of contributions totaling $175 is given.]</p>
   <p>Dr. Bernauer again offered to arrange a concert and lecture for the benefit of the Dobrocinna Spolecnost, but the Dobrocinna Spolecnost again declined his offer, because it will not assume sponsorship for anything but its tag day and charity ball.</p>
   <p>Mr. Voller became a member of the Board of Directors as the representative of the newspaper Narod.</p>
   <p>Disbursements were: groceries, $21.85; coal, $11.50; medicines, $2.75; office expenses, $10. Total expenditures, $46.10.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0573.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The election of officers for the Board of Directors was then held and the results are as follows: Judge Joseph Uhlir was again unanimously elected chairman; Mr. Frank J. Petru, first vice-chairman; Mr. John A. Cervenka, second vice-chairman; Mr. Stanley J. Loula, third vice-chairman; Reverend Vaclav Vanek, secretary; Mr. Roman Sedlacek, assistant secretary; Mr. Anton J. Cermak, financial secretary; Mr. Frank G. Hajicek, treasurer; Messrs. John A. Sokol, Drije, and Dr. Jiri Rezanka, auditing committee; Mr. Joseph Turek, office manager.</p>
   <p>Receipts were $175; disbursements $46.10.</p>
   <p>In the future meetings will be held every fourteen days; that is, on the first and third Friday of each month. The next meeting will be held on March 1, 1912.</p>
   <p>When the meeting had been adjourned and the officers were on the verge of leaving, discussions were resumed as a result of the splendid offer made by <pb facs="5418478_6_0574.jpg" n="3"/>our well-known Czech banker, Mr. Frank G. Hajicek.</p>
   <p>There had been a previous discussion about this problem of Czech children in our communities who, as the result of disturbed domestic conditions, have been forced into beggary. For example, several hungry and cold children came to a certain home in Bohemian "California" the other evening begging for something to eat. The mother of these children is sick and the father is in the Bridewell, although the children said he had died. This has happened more than once of late. Further discussion disclosed that there are many young boys and girls who have no family life, no home or shelter.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hajicek made a motion that a refuge be built for young people who go to work and are without homes. For this purpose he offered to donate a lot at the corner of California Avenue and 26th Street and to sell the adjoining lot for the same purpose for $500. Each of these lots is valued at $1000. This offer was made with the provision that the Dobrocinna Spolecnost proceed with the building of the said shelter in the course of one year. The <pb facs="5418478_6_0575.jpg" n="4"/>gift was accepted with thanks and a temporary building committee was immediately elected, consisting of the following members:Judge Joseph Uhlir as chairman ex officio, and Messrs. John A. Sokol, Frank J. Petru, Anton Schnabl, Joseph Turek, Drije, and Dr. Jiri Rezanka.</p>
   <p>Mr. Petru announced on behalf of the elderly philanthropist, Mr. Theodore W. Finney, the proprietor of the Vapenek (lime kilns), who has been most generous toward the Dobrocinna Spolecnost, that he will donate all the crushed stone and lime needed for this building free of charge. There is no doubt that with such enthusiasm this enterprise will be fulfilled. An appeal will be made to our labor unions of all trades to be as generous with their work as possible. Builders, material dealers, architects, etc., will also be asked to help in every way possible.</p>
   <p>Such an institution will surely be the culmination of all our Czech enterprises. It will be significant evidence of our national generosity, philanthrophy, and achievement toward which the entire Bohemian public in <pb facs="5418478_6_0576.jpg" n="5"/>America will look with enthusiasm and admiration. Our countrymen from other communities visiting in our city will find shelter here and will not have to look for quarters in the city. Messrs. Sokol and Drije will furnish the institution with all the coffee needed for two years. That our Czech public will welcome this report with enthusiasm and that everyone will lend a helping hand is certain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
