<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-15">Sept. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Cesky Vypomocny Vybor Disbands</title><title level="a" type="sub">Money given to the General Fund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-15">Sept. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKY VYPOMOCNY VYBOR DISBANDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Money given to the General Fund</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The last meeting of the Cesky Vypomocny Vybor (Bohemian Relief Committee) is now a matter of history. It was held yesterday morning and wound up the work or the Committee, which has been in operation for almost two months. They have done a job of which they can be justly proud, a job which was very important and at times extremely difficult.</p>
   <p>It met in the Conway Building, at the corner of Clark and Washington Streets, at 11 A. M. under the chairmanship of Chief Bailiff Anton J. Cermak. A sufficient number of members were present to make a quorum.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cermak gave a short explanation of the purpose of the meeting, and the general principles which were followed by the committee. He mentioned that the manner of distribution of the funds, among the families of the victims of the "Eastland" disaster, had been decided on. He further stated that the relatives <pb facs="5418478_6_0256.jpg" n="2"/>of the Bohemian victims of the catastrophe will receive one full third of the money now in the Mayor's fund. The money which will come to our people from the general fund is quite a respectable sum and is in excess of the $10,000 contributed by us.....</p>
   <p>These details, and the information of the fact that Mr. Cermak succeeded in persuading the general committee to increase the amount due to the Bohemian families by $12,050, has convinced the Bohemian committee that no Bohemian family will get less than its fair share, so they agreed that the money collected by the Cesky Vypomocny Vybor should be turned over to the Mayor's fund, which is now being managed by the American Red Cross.....</p>
   <p>The committee is reminding those who have made pledges and have not yet redeemed them to do so by September 20; otherwise their names will appear on the final list, which is being prepared for publication by the American Red Cross, of persons who have pledged an amount but failed to make the promised donation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0257.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is one point, however, which we desire to bring to your attention. The other day we promised to publish the names or those who will benefit by the contributions, and the amounts to which they are entitled. After a thorough consideration of all the circumstances disclosed to us by the general committee, we have decided to abandon the idea, because it would do more harm than good. A report is being circulated that there is a large number of families who have retained lawyers to protect their interests, and promising them half of the money they will receive as a reward. If the names of the families and the amounts due were published in the newspapers, the lawyers could go to the court and secure an injunction in behalf of their clients, which would delay the liquidation of the whole activity. We wish to say, however, that there are no Bohemians among those who have engaged legal counsel, and that any advice which may have been given to them by our Bohemian lawyers has been free. Also, some of those who will receive a share of the funds are in debt, and in some cases there is a judgment against them. Thus the publication of such a list would cause harm to many of those whose names it would contain. Also, the share the families will receive will vary according to circumstances.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0258.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Some families will receive considerably less than others, and the publication of these amounts would lead to jealousies and envy. Finally, the American Red Cross is not in the habit of publishing the names of those who benefit by its munificence, for purely ethical reasons; that is, rather for reasons of delicacy, with which not only we, but also all members of the Cesky Vypomocny Vybor fully agree. We have, therefore, gladly complied with the request not to publish the names of those who will get a share of the Mayor's funds, and have done so in the interest of all concerned.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
