<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-20">May 20, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-20">May 20, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">MATICE VYSSIHO VZDELANI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(The Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani [Council for Higher Education] has just distributed the following circular letter to its members:</p>
   <p>To the members of the Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani, greetings!</p>
   <p>The executive committee calls to the attention of the membership that with this year comes the election of four of the seven members of the executive committee and three members of the supervising committee.</p>
   <p>We call attention to the following rules of the constitution, according to which the election is governed:</p>
   <p>1. Every individual member or member-society is entitled to one vote for four executive committee candidates for each five-dollar annual contribution paid during the past two years. At the same time, they are entitled in a like <pb facs="5418478_6_1481.jpg" n="2"/>manner to vote for all of the three candidates for the supervising committee.</p>
   <p>2. Votes for the nomination of candidates should be sent to the secretary, Mr. P. A. Korab, Iowa City, Iowa, before June 1, 1912.</p>
   <p>3. From those nominated, the executive committee will pick eight candidates for the executive committee and six candidates for the supervising committee. These will be picked from those having the largest number of votes. The names of these candidates will be announced in at least three newspapers. The members will then vote for those selected until July 1, 1912.</p>
   <p>4. At the present time, the following three members of the executive committee, according to the constitution, still have two years to serve: M. W. Houser, Cedar Rapids, Iowa; W. F. Severa, Cedar Rapids, Iowa; Professor B. Simek, Iowa City, Iowa. Therefore, these three are not to be nominated or voted on.</p>
   <p>5. The executive committee here presents the names of all member-individuals <pb facs="5418478_6_1482.jpg" n="3"/>from among whom members and member-societies are to nominate four candidates to the executive committee for four-year terms and three candidates to the supervising committee for two-year terms. (List of members attached) [Translators note: List of names omitted with the exception of the following, who are Chicagoans.] Marie Blahnik, Jaroslava Bohac, James B. Dibelka, John Karel, Bohumil Kral, Otto Kubin, John Kralovec, Robert L. Pitte, Joseph A. Trojan.</p>
   <p>6. The term of office of the following members of the executive committee expires July 1, 1912: Professor F. W. Bouska, Augusta, Georgia; Professor (Miss) Sarka Hrbka, Lincoln, Nebraska; P. A. Korab, Iowa City, Iowa; Joseph Mekota, Cedar Rapids, Iowa.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
