<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-03">Jan. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Upon the Threshold of the New Year</title><title level="a" type="sub">Gigantic Participation in the New Year Celebration of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1285</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1285.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-03">Jan. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">UPON THE THRESHOLD OF THE NEW YEAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">Gigantic Participation in the New Year Celebration of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great fraternal union Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky is doubtless one of the most outstanding factors of our public well-being in the United States.</p>
   <p>From insignificant beginnings, for which the foundations were laid sixty years ago in St. Louis, Missouri, an organization was built whose branches reach almost into every State of our union, and is growing delightfully year after year.</p>
   <p>The cultural significance of our organization is becoming properly evaluated everywhere, especially in Bohemian-Chicago, the home of many other lodges with very large memberships; and where our countrymen naturally had the opportunity to convince themselves of the good work done by our great fraternal union.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1286.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>How interesting are these human activities of our great union to our Bohemian public, and how much sympathy this public shows by coming to the aid of our unions is best shown by the interest it takes in the entertainments of our individual lodges, and especially in our New Year celebrations arranged under the patronage of the Grand Lodge of Illinois.</p>
   <p>These manifestations and celebrations always draw large audiences. This one, like every other public celebration on New Year's Day, was no exception to the rule.</p>
   <p>The program was to have begun at two o'clock in the afternoon, but long before that the large hall was so filled with people that the committee was forced to close the doors, and about five hundred persons had to be sent away because not even standing-room was available in the spacious hall of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies, 18th and May Streets.</p>
   <p>The first number of the afternoon program was Kalivoda's "Overture Number One," <pb facs="5418478_6_1287.jpg" n="3"/>played by a large orchestra made up of some of our best musicians, under the direction of the popular Rolf Rubringer.</p>
   <p>Then our highly regarded president of the Grand Lodge, Mr. Jan Pecha, greeted the assemblage and introduced brother Tlusty of Cedar Rapids, Iowa, who came especially to congratulate the Chicago brothers upon their great achievement during the past year, and to exhort them to even greater activity for the good of the organization.</p>
   <p>Little Miss Bozena Kozeluh played two piano compositions and was applauded vociferously.</p>
   <p>The men of the Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society then filled the stage and sang, under the direction of their director, Mr. Josef Houdek, Foerster's "Krivankovi" (To the lark). The singers added two more songs.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vaclav Husa played a cornet solo, "Frances," and as an encore gave the <pb facs="5418478_6_1288.jpg" n="4"/>melodious, "Darling, I am Growing Old," in which the sweetness of tone of his instrument seemed to surpass the rendering of the first composition played.</p>
   <p>A male quartet, composed of Messrs. Vlaciha, Pomazal, Hezoucky and Kriz, sang a number of songs, and had to repeat many times, so much were they liked. Mr. Kriz, who is a talented tenor then sang a song, which was rewarded with sustained applause.</p>
   <p>The well-known xylophone player, Mr. Bohumir Vesely, then played a beautiful and lively tune. He was well repaid for his effort by prolonged applause.</p>
   <p>Little Miss Klainka Zaher sang a song. She is unusually talented, and her voice is strong for such a young girl.</p>
   <p>The program next introduced two sisters, Ruzena and Lillian Sula, who played the well-known overture, "Poet and Peasant," for four hands, which the young ladies played with genuine skill.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1289.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The speaker of the afternoon was Dr. Frantisek Iska, a well-known speaker. The committee could not have made a better choice. We will print his address in tomorrows' issue.</p>
   <p>The program continued with an amateur performance by two little actresses from the Bohemian Orphanage: Miss Marie Neboska, who presented the number "Kucharinka" (The little cook), and Miss Emilie Kunt, who very ably recited "Detsky Ples" (The children's grand ball). Both of these young girls have talent. Due credit must be given their teacher, Mrs. Gusta Dusek for the "find".</p>
   <p>The last number on the program was a one-act play performed by the pupils of the Free Thought school, under the direction of their teacher, Mr. Veverka. Nine children played in this fairy play, called "Popelka" (Cinderella), and were amply rewarded by the great interest the audience showed for the play.</p>
   <p>Altogether the afternoon program contained nineteen numbers. Mr. Rubringer's <pb facs="5418478_6_1290.jpg" n="6"/>orchestra provided a number of them; the orchestra played only concert selections.</p>
   <p>The success of this celebration of the Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies was complete, and it is proved that the resident lodges of this great body are steadily gaining in favor with our public, which will be an encouragement in the new year for further work for humanity.</p>
   <p>To the motto "Equality, Concord, Fraternity" we add our sincere Nazdar! (Success).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
