<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-01-10">Jan. 10, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">The Pilsen Station</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0933</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0933.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-01-10">Jan. 10, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">THE PILSEN STATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our readers, especially those who inhabit Bohemian Pilsen will surely be interested in the publication of some data concerning our post-office branch, the so called Pilsen Station. According to the statistics which we print below, is can readily be seen that our quarter is one of the most businesslike sections of Chicago. These reports were furnished to us by Mr. Jos. Vlcek, the manager of this post-office branch. Although Mr. Vlcek has been in this responsible position only since the 21st of July of last year he has made many important improvements. He undertook to provide a better delivery service and has thereby ingratiated himself with almost all the businessmen found in his district. It will surely be of interest to know how extensive the district served by the Pilsen Post Office is. It extends from 16th Street to the river on the east, along Halsted to Harrison Street (Halsted Street belongs to the district only between 16th Street and the river), along Harrison Street to Ashland Avenue, along Ashland Avenue to 12th Street, <pb facs="5418478_6_0934.jpg" n="2"/>along 12th Street to Robey Street, along Robey Street to the Burlington Railroad tracks, along the railroad to Western Avenue to 18th Street, then west to California Avenue, taking in part of Marshall Blvd; from there it again extends to the river, encompassing large factories and lumberyards. As can be seen it is a larger territory and we will surprise no one when we say that it requires the service of sixty letter carriers to properly take care of the volume of business transacted. The following named Bohemians are among the letter carriers: I. G. Turek, F. R. Srachta, A. B. Stluka, H. Tetrev, F. Binz, J. P. Traznik, Ant. Zajicek, E. T. Cihlar, F. Kvasnicka, L. Hildebrandt, and Ant. Kostecka. The oldest letter carrier is Ant. Zajicek. There are fifteen clerks in the post-office among whom are the following Bohemians: F. J. Slepicka, who is employed in the money order division, L. F. Jirka in the registered division, Jan Cernoch, mail sorter and Otto Hartman, also a sorter. During Mr. Vlcek's administration two carriers were added to the force, F. Srachta and A. Nevman. There are also employed eight collectors, who are engaged in making collections from mailboxes, some of which are emptied fourteen times daily.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
