<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-22">July 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">For the Victims of the War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-22">July 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE VICTIMS OF THE WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our fellow-countryman Charles J. Vopicka, Chicago merchant, and United States Minister to the Balkan States, is about ready to leave Chicago, to resume his diplomatic activities in Jassy, Rumania, the present seat of the Rumanian government, and also of the Allies' military headquarters for those regions. He has given a signal example of what can be done for the destitute people in the countries exposed to invasion by the enemy. He has been extending his helping hand particularly to the Serbians and kindred Slavonic peoples. Clothing and money is being sent to the Allied front. In the sector called Dobrudza there is a large percentage of Czechs, Slovaks, and Croats, who were taken prisoners by the Allies and were then allowed to join the ranks of the Allied soldiers in their struggle against the Central Powers. Besides soldiers, there are many civilians suffering from the war.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0200.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>No wonder, therefore, that Mr. Vopicka manifested great joy when the American Red Cross placed $250,000 at his disposal for the purpose of the relief action headed by him. In addition to this pecuniary contribution, the Red Cross is supplying a staff of twenty-one physicians and twelve nurses, among whom are several of Czech, or other Slavonic descents.....</p>
   <p>The Pomocny Vybor [Relief Committee] is headed by Mr. Vokral, a member of a Sokol society, who is experienced in matters of war relief. All gifts, of money or other things, will be received and directed through the proper channels by the American Red Cross, which has been facilitating the transportation to, and the distribution at, the place of destination.</p>
   <p>Gifts and inquiries are being taken care of at Mr. Joseph Vokral's office, 1735 West 18th Street, Chicago. Each gift will be registered; information in regard to delivery will be given by the Relief Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
