<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title level="a">Letter from Vladimir Geringer, President Svornost, to J. Monaghan</title>,
<date when="1937-09-30">September 30, 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0811</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0811.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CZECH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title level="a">LETTER FROM VLADIMIR GERINGER, PRESIDENT SVORNOST, TO J. MONAGHAN</title>,
<date when="1937-09-30">SEPTEMBER 30, 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are 315,000 Czechs and Slovaks in Chicago. Three daily Bohemian papers and one Slovak, are published.</p>
   <p>There are over five hundred Czech societies, fraternal, building and loan, charitable, singing, gymnastic, with a membership of many thousands in metropolitan Chicago. Their activities are regularly noted in our papers, which, like the English papers, give all the news of a general character, both local and national, as well as special news both by cable and telegraph, together with local reports not carried in English language papers, concerning items of interest to all our people both young and old.</p>
   <p>Recently the Western Czechoslovak Fraternal Union held a convention to plan merging all our fraternal orders into one organization. Should this worthy object be accomplished the new society would then have a membership of almost 500,000 members and since Chicago is admitted to be the largest Czechoslovak city outside of Prague, Czechoslovakia, the membership in metropolitan Chicago would exceed 100,000 members.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0812.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is conceded by all students of building and loan associations that the Czechs have more building and loan societies than any other group in this city. We have 124 building and loan associations with a membership of 50,000, holding 550,000 shares which have a maturity value of $55,000,000.</p>
   <p>These are matters of record. This is another fact on which we base our estimate of our national strength. It also gives you an idea of the progressiveness of our group, their saving habits, property ownership, etc., all of which indicates high purchasing power.</p>
   <p>There are 573 grocery stores, 210 drug stores, about 2,500 meat markets, bakeries and other retail stores, many factories, wholesale and commission houses, and homes owned by citizens of Czech descent. On the southwest side of Chicago where Svornost is located, there are hundreds of blocks which are improved with thousands and thousands of residences, apartment and commercial buildings belonging to Czechoslovak-Americans. The large towns of Cicero, <pb facs="5418478_6_0813.jpg" n="3"/>Berwyn, LaGrange, Lyons, Riverside, Brookfield, etc. are really a continuation of the great Southwest side. On these streets you hear Czech spoken as a rule.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
