<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-19">May 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost Tag Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-19">May 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST TAG DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A joint meeting of Bohemian women and the directors of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) was held Friday evening in the office of the Pilsen Brewing Company. The meeting was presided over by Judge J. Z. Uhlir. A large delegation from the women's department of the Pilsen Sokol and many other women ready to help sell tags on May 30 were in attendance. Many important matters were discussed. It was decided that the women's next meeting should be held next Wednesday at 7:30 P. M. in the Pilsen Brewing Company's pavilion, and that all women willing to help sell tags should be invited to attend. A special invitation is extended to all women sokols of various Chicago sokol societies to take part in the meeting. At next Wednesday's meeting, a permanent women's department of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost is to be created. According to the report of the Tag-Day committee, two thousand letters have been sent to Bohemian businessmen with a request for permission to place collection boxes in their places of business. Bohemian women have been requested to help sell tags. Up to the present, about five hundred collection boxes have been distributed among <pb facs="5418478_6_0569.jpg" n="2"/>the business establishments of the Pilsen, California, and Town of Lake districts. Whereas, aside from the Charity Ball, the collection on Tag Day is, so to speak, the only source of revenue of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, it is to be desired that the collection on Tag Day meet with every success, so as to enrich the treasury of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, to which are referred hundreds of poor Bohemian families of this city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
