<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title/>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0698</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
                    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0698.jpg" n="2"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>just before the crash. He also would not admit that his son has had any knowledge of his shady manipulations, and supported him in his protestations of innocence on the ground of his alleged ignorance of the elder's actions. His bail was set at only $3,000, a disproportionately low figure, considering that the defalcations involved $170,000. There was great disappointment visible on the faces of the complaining victims who had crowded the courtroom in expectation of sterner action on the part of the judge, who, just to top the surprise of those present, allowed the defendants to remain at liberty, upon their word of honor not to leave town.</p>
   <p>The security enjoyed since then by Robert L. Pitte and his son proved to be only a film enshrouding their future. The temporary freedom granted</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0699.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>them by Judge Landis was just another demonstration of the erratic temper of the jurist, who, while known as a very capable and severe representative of the bench, is a sphinx, even to his closest associates.</p>
   <p>Yesterday at mid-day, out of a clear sky, the judge sent a telephone call each to attorneys Cermak and Stafford, directing the latter to produce R. L. Pitte and son in court. When the two appeared, he eyed them with a piercing gaze under his knitted forehead, which foreshadowed uncanny happenings. After some lengthy, scorching remarks about the past activities of the two men, the judge turned them over to the federal grand jury. The elder Pitte, in the judge's opinion, was concealing funds which he had failed to include in the petition in bankruptcy, while his son, in addition to this, had perjured himself in court. The elder Pitte's bail was set at $10,000, his son's at $20,000. Both were taken into custody of the United States Marshal, after a motion by Attorney Stafford for the defense that a few days release be allowed to arrange for bail had been categorically denied.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
