<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-19">Oct. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Conference of the Sokol Community in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">by F. L. M.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-19">Oct. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CONFERENCE OF THE SOKOL COMMUNITY IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">by F. L. M.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the various resolutions passed at the conference in Cleveland, Ohio, the following was placed on the records of the Czech Sokol community in America:</p>
   <p>Members of church societies and other organizations associated with the clergy and churches, and followers of bodies which help the efforts and aspirations of the clergy, shall not be accepted by the Sokol Community. This, and other principles of the community, will be printed to form a book of statutes.</p>
   <p>A lively debate dealt with the lack of interest in members with regard to the wearing of uniforms, which are a necessary medium of efficient representation in public.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1174.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One of the soundest propositions was one advocating the collaboration of the Sokols in America with those in the motherland, and the introduction of the same Sokol dress, so that the Sokols will be the same, not only in spirit, but dress also, here and in the motherland.</p>
   <p>The executive committee was instructed to work out a plan under which the Sokol community will have a legal right to the property of all units.</p>
   <p>The headquarters of the community will be located in Chicago. The delegates were not in favor of New York as headquarters for the community. The next conference is to be held during the last week of August, five years hence. Mr. Joseph Paskovsky was re-elected head of the community.</p>
   <p>Czech schools in America will receive $400, to be distributed among the settlements of New York City; Astoria, New York; Winfield, New York; <pb facs="5418478_6_1175.jpg" n="3"/>Elizabeth, New Jersey; Dutchhills, New York; Newark, New Jersey; Bronx, New York; Union Hill, New York; Yonkers, New York; Baltimore, Maryland; Cleveland, Ohio; Chicago, Illinois; Little Ferry, New Jersey; Milwaukee, Wisconsin; Omaha, Nebraska; St. Louis, Missouri; Detroit, Michigan.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Placek of Chicago, chairman, closed the meeting by relating how several Sokols had met in the Statler Hotel and Messrs. J. F. Stepina of Chicago and Joseph Dusek donated $1,000 each to the community. Ferd. L. Musil, secretary of the community, proposed that the money be donated to the Bohemian National Alliance. This was agreed, and the latter became recipient of $3,000, since the community had voted a gift of $1,000 before.</p>
   <p>The conference closed at 4 P. M. All the delegates expressed gratification over the harmony among the members of the three organizations which have merged today into one large body--the Sokol community. A large amount of work was accomplished at this conference, without loss of time in parades, banquets, <pb facs="5418478_6_1176.jpg" n="4"/>and various other customary concomitants. We are growing and progressing, proof of which is this conference which was dedicated to earnest and dignified discussions of the mission of the Sokol organizations--to educate and enlighten. The delegates parted with a feeling of intense satisfaction, conscious of having done a job of honest work which will bear excellent fruit.</p>
   <p>Na Zdar! (Success!)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
