<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-26">July 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Let's Open Our Hearts and Hands</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Denni Hlasatel Starts Collection for Victims of Lake Catastrophe with $500</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-26">July 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S OPEN OUR HEARTS AND HANDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Denni Hlasatel Starts Collection for Victims of Lake Catastrophe with $500</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hundreds of Bohemian families have been driven to the brink of despair. Most of these are families belonging to the working classes whose providers, or at least members who had been aiding in their support to a considerable degree, have been taken away from them by a horrible death. The survivors may be small children left without a father, or a mother, or both; they may be old parents deprived of good children who were their hope for the future, on whose earnings they were dependent, and without which they would be in distress if the love of their countrymen should not provide for them.</p>
   <p>Our people do not need to be urged for a long time to do their humane and civic duty toward their own countrymen. This has been proved many times, and will be proved now again in a particularly spectacular way. Our city, our Bohemian <pb facs="5418478_6_0310.jpg" n="2"/>community, has never before been visited by a catastrophe of this magnitude. Similarly, the help that will be made available to the surviving members of the victims' families will out do everything that has been done before in a similar emergency. Those of us who are fortunate enough to be spared direct losses of friends or members of immediate families will do all possible to show their warm sympathy, their true love to those bereft, by mitigating the pain caused by their losses.</p>
   <p>Tens of years will pass before the "Eastland" catastrophe will cease to be a topic of conversation. Let us see to it that while it is such a topic it should always call to memory the Bohemians' love for their countrymen. It should always recall the way in which we have proved to be members of the same large family in which there are no selfish wretches but only loving, generous brothers and sisters.</p>
   <p>The publishers of the Denni Hlasatel decided as early as Saturday night to <pb facs="5418478_6_0311.jpg" n="3"/>donate $500 for the support of those who not only have suffered losses in their immediate families, but also have become materially distressed by them. It is to be wished that this $500 may be the foundation for an immense collection which would be contributed to in large amount by the rich, in small amount by the poor, but to which everyone of us who possibly can would make his contribution. To take care of those who lost their providers by this terrible catastrophe will be the most beautiful and at the same time most adequate monument we could erect to the unfortunate victims.</p>
   <p>Let us open our hearts and hands, in these days of general depression and let us assuage the sorrows wherever possible.</p>
   <p>Contributions will be received and received for by this newspaper and will be used for immediate help wherever the need of such aid is made apparent among our countrymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
