<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-20">July 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czechoslovak Emblems</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1781</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1781.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-20">July 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHOSLOVAK EMBLEMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every Czechoslovak in Chicago, indeed, in the United States, ought to wear a visible token of his ancestry. These badges were introduced, and their wearing approved for the Fourth of July celebration, by the arrangements committee of the Czechoslovak parade. They are very beautiful, for they were designed by the Czech Artists' Club of Chicago, and no Czechoslovak should fail to wear one. They may be obtained for only ten cents at the office of the Czech Bureau, 3342 West 26th Street. They will be on sale from now on at all important entertainments and festivities, as for instance, at the Czechoslovak Old Settlers' picnic, to be held at the Pilsen Brewery Park July 24, and at the Havlicek Memorial in Douglas Park July 27.</p>
   <p>In this manner our people will recognize each other as Czechoslovaks. Our organizations should provide the badges for their members, and promote a lively sale at their gatherings. The proceeds are destined to help supply the soldiers of our glorious Czechoslovak Army with smoking material and <pb facs="5418478_6_1782.jpg" n="2"/>other articles. This fact should provide an incentive for every Czechoslovak man and woman to procure a badge.</p>
   <p>By the way, our people are not forgetting the Czechoslovak Army. Numerous gifts have recently arrived at the Czech Bureau, all for our boys, who are demonstrating that our nation craves for freedom, and that its children know how to die for it. The names of some of the generous donors follow: Joseph Kasak, $2; Anna Bocek, $1; Anton Kozan, $.50; etc.</p>
   <p>It is pleasant to record that in the first fourteen days after the founding of the Czech Bureau--where the recruiting office under Sergeant Kimmel, U. S. Army, is also located--thirty-six young men applied for enlistment, and only two were rejected. One man enlisted in the Czechoslovak Army; he was sent to the respective quarters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
