<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-02-09">Feb. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1447</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1447.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-02-09">Feb. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">CESKO-AMERICKA NARODNI RADA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) started the year with the election of new members for the executive committee, which is composed of the following ladies and gentlemen: Mrs. Bujarek Stanek, Dr. Ludvik Fischer, Mr. Jan Geringer, Mr. J. Kosar, Mr. J. Ort, Mr. J. R. Psenka, Mr. James Stepina, Mr. Joseph Triner, Mrs. Lud. Vesely, Mr. E. St. Vraz, Professor Jar. Zmrhal. The newly elected associate members are Messrs. E. Beranek and F. J. Skala for the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau), and Dr. J. Salaba Vojan for the Cesko-Americky Umelecky Klub (Bohemian-American Arts Club). To the information and reception committee were elected: Messrs. J. M. Kralovec, V. B. Dibelka, Dr. F. Novak, E. Bachmann; Mrs. A. Stolf, Mrs. M. Smrcka, Miss Jar. Bohac, and Miss Emilie Sustr. As representatives of other important lodges and organizations were elected: For the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies); Mr. Jan Pecha; for the Velkoloze Jednoty Taboritu</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1448.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(Grand Lodge of the Taborites Union), Dr. Ant. Mueller; for the Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Bohemian-Slavonic Unity), Mr. Fr. Benes; for Sokol Chicago, Mr. Vaclav Roubal; for Sokol Tabor, Mr. Jindrich Ort; for Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs [Zupa is the central body of Sokol units in one area] (Sokol Central Body Fuegner-Tyrs), Mr. Ant. Dolezal; for Druzstvo Havlickovo [society for the erection of the monument of Karel Havlicek-Borovsky which now stands in Douglas Park], Mr. Vojta Sedlacek; for the Ceska Ustredni Jednota Pevecka (Central Bohemian Singing Society), Old. Harnach; for the Pevecky Sbor Lyra (Singing Society Lyra), Dr. Wedeles; for the Rad Amerika, C. S. P. S. (Lodge America of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky), Mr. Leo Tauber. The Bohemian newspapers occasionally send their delegates to the meetings of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada. Other associate members of the executive committee are: Messrs. V. Brazda, J. Bartusek, O. Horacek, J. A. Cervenka, Fr. Honsik, Ant. Charvat, J. Klicka, J. Laadt, Ad. Lonek, H. J. Podlesak, Fr. Randak, Tomas Vonasek. The executive committee has elected as president, Mr. E. St.Vraz; as vice presidents, Mr. Karel J. Vopicka, Mr. James Stepina, Mrs. Lud. Veselsky and Mrs. Bujarek Stanek; as secretaries, Mr. Jar. Kosar <pb facs="5418478_6_1449.jpg" n="3"/>for Bohemian matters and Mr. Boh. Kral (Professor at Harrison High School) for English matters; as treasurer, Mr. J. Triner; as president of the Svaz Osvetovy (Committee On Culture And Education), Dr. Lud. Fischer. The present secretary and president of the Svaz Osvetovy, Professor Jar. Zmrhal, did not accept his election as secretary for English matters because his studies at the university do not permit him to devote as much time to the secretarial work this year as the office requires. The president of the C. A. N. R.thanked Mr. Zmrhal for his energetic and untiring work on behalf of the organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
