<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1896-11-12">Nov. 12, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">The End of the Bohemian League.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1641</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1641.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1896-11-12">Nov. 12, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THE END OF THE BOHEMIAN LEAGUE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday evening there was called a meeting of representatives and patrons of the Bohemian League. The attendance was very scanty. Franz Kaspar opened the meeting.</p>
   <p>The question that was up for decision was should the League continue to exist or not. The majority of those present was unanimous that it is impossible to even think of the future existence of the League, in view of the surprising carelessness of the management of the whole enterprise.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kaspar suggested to read the letter of Mr. Lepsa; the letter firmly stated the activity of the League should not be discontinued and the money now in the treasury should be in no way used on any Bohemian-American enterprise but exclusively for the Bohemian cause; - the money could be loaned to northwest Bohemian tradesmen. The suggestionsof Mr. Lepsa were seen as humane and good - anyhow the opinion of the members who were in the League for a long time was that the resurrection of the League is impossible.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1642.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The masses of the Bohemian population are indifferent; nobody appears at the meetings; the Bohemian press never used propaganda through the League and, finally, the dishonesty of a few individuals soon shortened the life of this organization. It was then clear from the whole discussion of the present members that no one believed that the League could exist in the future.</p>
   <p>As a result of this decision the meeting started to deliberate on how to dispose of the cash in the League's possession.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cerveny, treasurer, declared there is in the treasury $370 or a little more. Suggestions for the dividing of the money were different; many members opposed the sending of the money to Bohemia. It was positively decided that the League absolutely must be closed as a unit and the day for this purpose was set for the first Sunday after New Year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
