<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-12-03">Dec. 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Report of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1391</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1391.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-12-03">Dec. 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A REPORT OF THE CESKE NARODNI SDRUZENI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. James F. Stepina, president of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau), presented the following report of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance) concerning steps taken for the benefit of the Bohemian cause in England at a meeting held in the American State Bank last night.</p>
   <p>"The president of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar received a letter on November 9 describing the situation of London Bohemians. Since contact with prominent men in England has been maintained for some time, a meeting of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar was called for the night of November 10, at which time an agreement was reached concerning the steps to be taken in the matter of Bohemians residing in London and in other parts of England. Experiences encountered during the meeting with the Belgian delegation, as well as information and suggestions gathered from contacts with Chicago French and English leaders, have led to the decision to give the English action a deeper, <pb facs="5418478_6_1392.jpg" n="2"/>more serious foundation. It was therefore decided that the president of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar should discuss the matter with the British Consul in Chicago and prepare a memorandum for the British Ambassador and forward it to Washington.</p>
   <p>"The conference between Mr. Stepina and the British Consul took place November 11.</p>
   <p>"The same day, a telegram from Mr. Vozka of New York was received requesting that a delegate from Chicago be sent to Washington.</p>
   <p>"In accordance with the understanding reached with the British Consul in Chicago, the plan to send a delegate from Chicago to Washington was abandoned, but the Cesko-Slovansky Vybor v New Yorku (Bohemian-Slavonic Committee of New York) was requested by wire to have Mr. Thomas Capek also represent Chicago Bohemians.</p>
   <p>"A telegram from Washington dated November 14 brought the advice that <pb facs="5418478_6_1393.jpg" n="3"/>Mr. Vozka, Mr. Capek, and Mr. Tvrdy had been in Washington.</p>
   <p>"The New Yorkske Listy (Bohemian New York Daily) carried the text of the telegram, adding that Mr. Capek also represented the Chicago Bohemians. Another conference between the British Consul of Chicago and the president of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar was held on November 16.</p>
   <p>"Mr. Capek's reply to the question of whether the statement of some Bohemian New York newspapers to the effect that Chicago Bohemians did not participate in the English action is true came on November 25. Mr. Capek writes among other things: 'You will have seen in the papers that we were in Washington--Mr. Vozka, Mr. Tvrdy, and myself. Mr. Vozka and Mr. Tvrdy represented New York, and I was asked to speak for Chicago.....The Ambassador received us most kindly....He already heard of the action from Chicago'.....</p>
   <p>"The Ambassador advised us in his own handwriting on November 23 about the reaction of the British minister of foreign affairs, Edward Grey, to the <pb facs="5418478_6_1394.jpg" n="4"/>Bohemian petition, and intimated that the London Bohemians will get all possible help and support."</p>
   <p>This report was received with a great deal of satisfaction, and the president of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni expressed his and his organization's full confidence, and thanks to Mr. Stepina for the tactful and competent conduct of these negotiations.</p>
   <p>The members at the meeting agreed that Mr. Stepina's report is the last political report that is being made public.</p>
   <p>The Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni and the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar request the Bohemian public to continue giving them its full confidence, but not to expect news or reports on their political activities for the benefit of the old country, except in cases of unusual importance and timeliness.</p>
   <p>The Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni requests our Bohemian-American press to support it <pb facs="5418478_6_1395.jpg" n="5"/>in its work and to publish all its releases with even greater readiness than that found in a few instances.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
