<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-27">July 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Cesky Vypomocny Vybor Has Been Founded</title><title level="a" type="sub">Over $4,000 in Contributions and Pledges Received</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-27">July 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKY VYPOMOCNY VYBOR HAS BEEN FOUNDED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Over $4,000 in Contributions and Pledges Received</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we reported yesterday, the Chief Bailiff of the Municipal Court, Mr. Anton J. Cermak, called a huge meeting at the hall of Sokol Pilsen at Ashland Avenue and West 18th Street for yesterday afternoon. The purpose of the meeting was the organization of a committee to take care of those who have been left helpless by the victims of the terrible catastrophe of the Steamship "Eastland". The calling of the meeting was a most noble action of great merit. A large majority of the victims of that catastrophe are our countrymen. Many of them have left behind one or more persons who will be in great need of help, some just temporarily, or in the immediate future only, while others will have to be taken care of permanently. Wives have lost their husbands, and children have lost their parents; while in some families the losses are such that the husband will need financial and moral help, to say nothing of counsel which, in some cases, will be of particular importance in taking care of matters <pb facs="5418478_6_0303.jpg" n="2"/>pertaining to inheritance, and other emergencies.</p>
   <p>The whole city is today in deep sorrow and willing to do for the victims all that is needed through an organization that has been already perfected. It is now up to us to set up an organization for Bohemian relief, as most of those who perished Saturday morning were Bohemians and the members of their families must not be left helpless.....</p>
   <p>It was in this vein that Mr. Cermak talked to the many prominent Bohemians who attended the meeting. The first action was to elect officers, and Mr. Cermak was elected chairman, Reverend Vaclav Vanek, secretary, and Mr. Joseph A. Holpuch, treasurer of the executive committee.....</p>
   <p>After a lengthy discussion it was decided that the committee should be called the "Cesky Vypomocny Vybor" (Bohemian Relief Committee). Mr. Cermak intimated that he had talked that morning with the Mayor's representative, Commissioner <pb facs="5418478_6_0304.jpg" n="3"/>of Public Works Moorhouse, who promised that the Bohemian committee would become a part of the large general committee appointed by the Mayor and some of the largest corporations of Chicago. He said that it would be necessary for the committee to have a downtown office where a secretary would always be present. Finally the committee was enlarged by the election of the representatives of the four Bohemian Chicago newspapers, Congressman A. J. Sabath, the Bohemian members of the Senate and House of Representatives in Springfield, the representatives of the Cicero and Berwyn Town Halls, and the following: J. F. Stepina, J. A. Cervenka, F. G. Hajicek, W. Kaspar, John A. Sokol, J. Z. Uhlir, K. Walleck, Jos. Hlavka (Cicero),F. R.Dubsky (Town of Lake), Jiri Petrtyl (Berwyn), J. W. Jedlan (Warren Park), Otto Prochazka (Northwest Side), and K. Ricker (Brookfield).</p>
   <p>A considerable debate followed Mr. Cermak's question as to how those present thought the relief action should be conducted. It was decided that money collected by the committee should be turned over to the public fund in charge <pb facs="5418478_6_0305.jpg" n="4"/>of the general committee downtown, which would be enlarged by a number of Bohemian members. Some of those present were of the opinion that money collected by the Bohemian committee should be given to Bohemians exclusively, but the majority maintained that it is now up to us to show that we are not only good Bohemians, but also good citizens of Chicago who feel for all those who need help now, without regard to nationality.....</p>
   <p>Several additional suggestions were made, regarding the establishment of branch offices, help for funerals in the form of automobiles and carriages, of which there is a great scarcity in Chicago, co-operation with the Chicago office of the American Red Cross, immediate help wherever necessary, etc. These proposals were passed on to the executive committee, which will make its own decisions in regard to them.....</p>
   <p>The Cesky Lekarsky Spolek (Bohemian Physicians' Association) offers help, free of charge, to all those who have contracted typhoid fever. This refers particularly to those who were saved Saturday, and those who have since then come <pb facs="5418478_6_0306.jpg" n="5"/>in contact with the survivors. Our physicians will give them injections against typhoid fever for which, in turn, our pharmacists will be glad to donate the necessary serum.....</p>
   <p>Finally, a resolution was adopted demanding that Bohemian representatives be present on all committees investigating the cause of the catastrophe.....</p>
   <p>Bohemian undertakers will be given the suggestion that mass burials be arranged wherever feasible--that is, that the undertakers take the bodies to the respective cemeteries in the morning hours, and hold a common ceremony in the afternoon. This should save the use of transportation accomodations. This was considered a good idea, but perhaps not quite timely, because in most cases all funeral matters have already been decided upon and preparations have been made by now.....</p>
   <p>An appeal was made to contribute to the American Red Cross instead of buying flowers.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0307.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Mr. Holpuch was collecting donations during the meeting and soon had more than $4,000 in cash and pledges.....</p>
   <p>The Denni Hlasatel initiated the collection by a donation of $500.....</p>
   <p>Meeting of the Executive Committee</p>
   <p>After the general meeting the executive committee met and made the following decisions:</p>
   <p>The offices of the Cesky Vypomocny Vybor will be located in the premises of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) at 2603 South Kedzie Avenue, Telephone, Rockwell 1787, where two secretaries will be present throughout the day: Reverend V. Vanek and F.R.Matousek. The downtown office will be in Room 705, City Hall Square Building, at 139 North Clark Street near Randolph, and will be in charge of Mr. Venecek and Mr. Kreml, the secretaries.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0308.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Branch offices will be in Mr. F. A. Svoboda's premises at 26th Street and Ridgeland Avenue in Berwyn, telephone Berwyn 510; in Town of Lake at 1824 West 47th Street, telephone Drover 3300 (Mr. Felix Janovsky); in Pilsen in Mr. F. J. Petru's offices at 1443 West 18th Street, telephone Canal 806; on the Northwest Side in Mr. Otto Prochazka's offices at 1053 Milwaukee Avenue, telephone Monroe 1577; and in the Fifth Ward in the premises of Alderman Chas. O. Hahn at 1322 South Grove Avenue. All these offices will be given all available information concerning help for the funerals of the needy ones, etc. City Clerk John Siman was appointed chairman of the committee; he will call up all Bohemian undertakers on the matter of common funerals. All those who lack money for the funerals should apply to the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost.....</p>
   <p>The following seven members were elected to join the general Chicago committee.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
