<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-12-12">Dec. 12, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Charitable Association Poor Bohemian Families Will Receive Ample Christmas Gifts Seventy-Five Needy Bohemian Families at Present Receiving Aid</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0635</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0635.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-12-12">Dec. 12, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION POOR BOHEMIAN FAMILIES WILL RECEIVE AMPLE CHRISTMAS GIFTS SEVENTY-FIVE NEEDY BOHEMIAN FAMILIES AT PRESENT RECEIVING AID</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.2--The officers of the Bohemian Charitable Association held a meeting yesterday afternoon on the premises of Mr. F. G. Hajicek, the banker, on Twenty-sixth Street. The meeting was opened by the vice-chairman, Mr. F. J. Petru. Later the chairman took charge, Judge J. Z. Uhlir. After the reading of the minutes of the previous meeting, the secretary, Mr. C. G. Foucek, read the communications received, most of which were requests for aid. Winter has arrived with all its fury. It has entered the households of our poor compatriots, and along with it its faithful companion, misery. What wonder, then, that requests for aid are increasing! Indeed, we are very much surprised that there are not more, for we believe that this year more suffering than usual is afflicting the families of our countrymen.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0636.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A letter from Dr. Marie Motys-Funk was read, stating that she is willing to treat free of charge poor Bohemians who are sent to her by the Bohemian Charitable Association. This communication was acknowledged with gratitude.</p>
   <p>Vice-chairman F. J. Petru presented a communication from Mr. Anderson, business manager of the Chicago Union Lime Company, who extends the good wishes of the company to the Bohemian Charitable Association for its work and sends a contribution of seventy-five dollars. This firm deserves recognition, for it remembers the Charitable Association in a generous manner. After all the requests for aid had been taken care of, and the reports of the investigating committees had been heard, it was found that the Association is taking care of seventy-five needy families and aiding at least a hundred and fifty other families with smaller contributions.</p>
   <p>There was a discussion about Christmas gifts for needy Bohemian families. After a thorough discussion of the matter it was proposed by Mr. A. J. Cervenka and resolved that all families recommended by the committee should <pb facs="5418478_6_0637.jpg" n="3"/>share in the distribution. We are heartily in accord with this resolution, and we firmly believe that all charitably inclined countrymen of ours, the businessmen first of all, will so help the Association that happiness will be provided for every family. The committee is made up of the following: F. J. Petru, J. A. Cervenka, O. R. Fuerst, Roman Sedlacek, A. J. Cermak, and Joseph Turek.</p>
   <p>A committee of three members was elected: Messrs. Joseph Z. Uhlir, A. J. Cermak, and J. A. Cervenka, to see to it that the Bohemian Charitable Association is not forgotten in the distribution of the $200,000 collected for the welfare societies. Yesterday's receipts were as follows: Chicago Union Lime Company, $75, Flor. Holek, $5, and F. B. Zdrubek, $5; total, $85. Disbursements were $27.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
