<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-10-10">Oct. 10, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">General Interest the Collection for the Coal Miners Met with Great Enthusiasm Among All Sections of Our People. it Has Already Brought Over $400.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-10-10">Oct. 10, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">GENERAL INTEREST THE COLLECTION FOR THE COAL MINERS MET WITH GREAT ENTHUSIASM AMONG ALL SECTIONS OF OUR PEOPLE. IT HAS ALREADY BROUGHT OVER $400.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1- Although we know the generosity of our people and know that they always have a heart and give a helping hand, where help is really needed, still we did not expect the collection for the coal miners to amount to so much. It is only a little over a week since the petition of the Bohemian coal miners of Luzerne, Pa. asking for assistance, made it's appearance in this paper and already over $400 has been gathered for the alleviation of the suffering of the strikers. Yesterday alone, over $100 was collected, the chief contributor being the Bohemian brewery Atlas, which deserves recognition because it is always generous when Bohemians are in need of help. The brewery deposited with the administration of this paper $50. In addition, Alderman Novak, contributed $10. In the tailoring shop of Vojt Kalne, $10.55 was collected. Our lodges added to the contributions as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0691.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Lilie Lapadu Lodge #201 C.S.R.D. (Czecho-Slovak Knights and Ladies), $2.</p>
   <p>Dvur sv. Matyase C. 52 K.L. (St.Mathew Lodge #52 Catholic Foresters), $10.</p>
   <p>We are sending this money immediately to Hnevkovke, in Luzerne, Pa. We also wrote to the gentleman asking him to send us a detailed report as to the distribution of benefits so that our public may have proof, to the last penny, that the money was properly used.</p>
   <p>If any of our countrymen knows of any other place where Bohemian miners are suffering because of the strike, let them notify us giving us the name of the person to whom we can forward the aid required. We find that with the successful conduct of the collection, the benefits can be widened to include all Bohemian and Slovak families of strikers who find themselves in the greatest need.</p>
   <p>Thus far a total of $402.85 has been collected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
