<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-05-01">May 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">To Bohemians of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1436</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1436.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-05-01">May 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">TO BOHEMIANS OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For two years the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) has been active in our public life, but it seems that it has not yet fully become an integral element in our blood and organism; that our public has not yet fully grasped its aims and objectives which are without a possible doubt of greatest importance and deep seriousness for the co-operative efforts of our nation in this new home of ours.</p>
   <p>The awareness of its existence has not yet penetrated into our foremost social organizations for whose benefit it works and which could use the results of its efforts to their own lasting advantage. It has not yet penetrated into the minds of our public for which it was organized and for which it is endeavoring to uphold and build up the prestige of the Bohemian people in this country.</p>
   <p>Those few self-sacrificing enthusiasts who have taken upon themselves the entire <pb facs="5418478_6_1437.jpg" n="2"/>burden of the great tasks of the Narodni Rada cannot keep on working indefinitely and making a success of the activities which are being planned, if the general public remains indifferent to all the important undertakings which the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada has in its program.</p>
   <p>Of course, the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada and its departments are working silently but effectively, without any publicity, on many odd but important little jobs entirely unknown to the public, the results of which, however, will be clearly apparent in time. It is just these odd jobs which have contributed so much to the fact that today Bohemians are esteemed in this country; that the ice of prejudice against us has been broken; and that we have succeeded in making contacts in places which some time ago had been inaccessible.</p>
   <p>It would serve no good purpose to mention separately each of these little jobs which the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada has done. They will become well known by their results in the near future, and their being appreciated and recognized <pb facs="5418478_6_1438.jpg" n="3"/>by the public will be the best reward to the modest national workers who devoted so much time and effort to them.</p>
   <p>Nothing has been done, there has been no activity in recent times to which the Narodni Rada did not extend either the initiative or a helping hand; nothing has been undertaken to which the Narodni Rada did not lend its co-operation, either through its departments or through spirited individuals who worked in the Rada's behalf.</p>
   <p>Here we should mention how effectively the Narodni Rada, or rather its educational department, worked with its recent lectures (by E. St. Vraz and Professor Jaroslav Zmrhal) in American public schools, disseminating in that way true information about our people and our native land. These lectures met with success and appreciation and have fulfilled their mission. They were accompanied by the projection of stereopticon slides ordered by the Rada from Bohemia.</p>
   <p>Because of the encouragement given to us by the Chicago Daily News and the <pb facs="5418478_6_1439.jpg" n="4"/>Chicago Board of Education, similar lectures but of a much wider scope are planned for the coming year and will be extended to high schools and colleges. We have the consent of Mr. Jos. J. Kral, Professor Zmrhal, Miss M. Sustr, and Miss A. Bohac to deliver these lectures. Unquestionably, this method of spreading information about Bohemians is most efficient, and those who have worked in this way for our interests are deserving of deep gratitude on the part of our public.</p>
   <p>Of greatest merit is the action of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada in introducing into the high schools the teaching of our native tongue. How much time had to be spent, how much work done, and how many interventions undertaken before we succeeded in establishing our right! It is due to the efforts of the influential members of the Rada, Mr. Charles J. Vopicka, Mr. Jaroslav B. Dibelka, and M. Kralovec that we have achieved our aim--in spite of the regrettable indifference of a large part of our public. Now the question of teaching the Bohemian language has been solved favorably, and it is only up to Bohemian parents <pb facs="5418478_6_1440.jpg" n="5"/>to make our achievement permanent by seeing to it that all their children without exception enroll in the Bohemian classes every year.</p>
   <p>So far we have Bohemian classes only in the Farragut High School, the only one in which the enrollment justified the opening of such classes. Now it depends upon our parents to take advantage of the hard-won privilege and have Bohemian classes established in other districts in which there are schools with a large number of pupils of Bohemian descent. Their requests for Bohemian classes will prove that we know how to appreciate this privilege, and thus create in the American mind a still better opinion of Bohemians.</p>
   <p>Having acquired the right to conduct Bohemian classes in our high schools, the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada has by no means arrived at the solution of the whole problem. Now there arises the question of able and competent teachers and of the necessary equipment. In the first place there is the problem of a model textbook, a grammar, and a chrestomathy of the Bohemian language, and a <pb facs="5418478_6_1441.jpg" n="6"/>high school reader which would serve as means of successful and methodical instruction. The Rada has appointed a committee whose duty it is to prepare such a book for the coming school year. This is not an easy assignment, but one of great responsibility, and one which requires, in addition to scientific and literary work which we have already been offered, considerable money to defray the cost connected with the publication of the reader.</p>
   <p>As we have said before, because the awareness of the existence of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada has not yet sufficiently penetrated into the minds of our public, it still has not a large enough membership to receive the necessary moral and the all-important financial support of its projects. Therefore, nothing else remains but to address an appeal to all self-respecting Bohemians--just as our brothers, the Poles, whose National Alliance now has hundreds of thousands of members are doing--for support by joining the small body of the Narodni Rada and helping financially through payment of membership dues to accomplish all the tasks which the Rada has made a part of its program in the interest of Bohemians in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1442.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>In order to popularize the membership in the Narodni Rada--if we may use this expression--and make it accessible to all, not only to those individuals of means, but also to the general public and to all of our lodges and societies, the executive committee of the Narodni Rada has decided to issue a very nice looking membership emblem, the model for which was made by Mr. Malik and which everybody will receive with the payment of two dollars as a yearly fee of a supporting member of the Narodni Rada.</p>
   <p>By contributing the paltry sum of two dollars a year, each patriotic Bohemian will have the satisfaction of knowing that he is supporting an entirely worthy objective--an objective of great merit, a purely and genuinely Bohemian objective--that he is supporting an organization whose far-reaching aims may be achieved by the harmonious co-operation of all of our countrymen.</p>
   <p>Identification cards and membership emblems may be secured from all active members of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada and also from accredited persons in Bohemian wards and precincts whose names will be published in Bohemian newspapers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1443.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>It would indeed be a shame if we could not secure at least ten thousand members for the Rada in our huge community. Only with a large membership and the income derived therefrom will it be possible to put into successful execution all of these projects, both practical and idealistic, which have been suggested. Therefore, everybody who calls himself a Bohemian must gladly agree to contribute in accordance with his means and help in our work toward the progress and good reputation of his nation in this country. In other words, it is a duty of every good Bohemian to become a member of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada.</p>
   <p>He who gives now gives double! Do not delay, do not say, "Tomorrow"! Do it today! Let us all join hands and stand as one man behind our dear native tongue, behind the good name of Bohemians, behind the work of the Ceska-Americka Narodni Rada!</p>
   <p>The Executive Committee of the Cesko-</p>
   <p>Americka Narodni Rada</p>
   <p>E. St. Vraz, president</p>
   <p>Jarka Kosak, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
