<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-18">Oct. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs Becomes a Member of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-18">Oct. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE ZUPA FUEGNER-TYRS BECOMES A MEMBER OF THE CESKE NARODNI SDRUZENI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday was a memorable Sunday in the annals of the Bohemian-American movement for Bohemian independence. The Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs (large Sokol unit called Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs)did its duty as a truly enlightened national organization. It decided by a unanimous vote of its member units to become "in corpore" a member of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance), which means that all its members, men and women Sokols as well as members of their ladies auxiliaries, are now members of the Sdruzeni, or, in other words, that the membership of the Narodni Sdruzeni has grown over night by 23,000 members. When the decision was made, all those making it were greatly moved.</p>
   <p>By this deed--since it is impossible to believe that the member units will fail to ratify the spontaneous votes of their representatives--the Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs has set a shining example to all our national organizations and all other Sokol groups, and has made a definite breach in the wall of seeming indifference <pb facs="5418478_6_1305.jpg" n="2"/>toward the future of the Bohemian nation which some of the organizations had built around themselves.....</p>
   <p>This deed is of the utmost importance for the financial security of the work of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni, but it has also a great moral and educational significance. The meeting in which the decision was made discussed also some veiled attacks on the Sdruzeni. The secretary of the Narodni Sdruzeni, who was present at the meeting, explained that the purpose of these slyly written attacks is to create confusion. He presented a resume of the activities of the Sdruzeni and discussed the future program of its work in which the Sokols, founded as a defense organization, should be very keenly interested. He showed why all the reports of the press bureau of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni are correct and truthful, and explained why they are being disputed by a few of our papers. He presented also a review of the situation in Bohemia and among Bohemian organizations outside of the old country, and urged the Zupa to do the right thing, to do its Sokol duty. The Sokols must be the core of the Bohemian organizations overseas. There must not be <pb facs="5418478_6_1306.jpg" n="3"/>a single Sokol unit, or a single individual Sokol, outside of the Narodni Sdruzeni. The old slogan "Co Cech, To Sokol" (When Bohemian, it's Sokol) must now be changed to "Co Sokol, to Cech" (When Sokol, it's Bohemian)--all fighters for the Bohemian cause. The time predicted by Fuegner and by Tyrs has come, and at this time a Sokol must be the whole man. The motion that every member of every Sokol unit become a member of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni was seconded by the editor of the Borec (full-fledged athlete ready for gymnastic or other competition, the official Sokol organ), Mr. Vinklarel.</p>
   <p>The commander of the Zupa, Mr. Dolezal, strongly supported the motion, and so did the secretary of the Zupa, Mr. Martinek, Mr. Skrivanek, and other representatives, and the motion was unanimously adopted. This fact is most eloquent proof that the honest work of the Narodni Sdruzeni is being appreciated by our patriotic countrymen. The Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs has proved that its understands its own mission and knows how to give a splendid example to others.</p>
   <p>In addition to this, the Zupa has favorably decided a request of confidential <pb facs="5418478_6_1307.jpg" n="4"/>character submitted to it by the Narodni Sdruzeni. This also was a decision of far-reaching importance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
