<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-04">Oct. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-04">Oct. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular meeting of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) was held last Friday night under the chairmanship of Judge J. Z. Uhlir. Secretary Hospodsky reported that more than seventy persons applied for relief during September; employment was found for twelve of these, and twelve families were given relief amounting to from three to eight dollars. Six persons were given food, clothing, and shelter, and several other family matters were dealt with by the office of the Spolecnost.</p>
   <p>There was a protracted debate of the question whether the Spolecnost should adopt the custom of publishing in the newspapers the names of families getting its support. It seems that frequently remarks are being made in various societies, lodges, etc., and also in public, to the effect that the Spolecnost is supporting people who do not deserve its support. It was agreed <pb facs="5418478_6_0451.jpg" n="2"/>to submit this question to the newspapers and to the whole public for discussion. So far the Spolecnost has not been publishing the names of those who have been receiving its charity because it has found the anonymous method more delicate and considerate. This, however, according to our opinion, has not done a great deal of good either to the Spolecnost or to those whom it treated with such consideration. In fact, it would seem that this delicate way of handling its business was being used by malicious people to damage the Spolecnost, and by voicing their suspicions damage its action, themselves not contributing a single penny to its expenses. The Spolecnost has paid out over $5,000 in donations since the beginning of this year, most of which has been spent on rent for needy families.</p>
   <p>Chairman John A. Sokol of the ball committee reported that his committee had begun its work by sending out invitations to lodges, associations, etc., and also to individuals asking for co-operation and energetic action because the funds of the Spolecnost have been getting low and bad times must be expected during the winter. Already requests for help are streaming into the office.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
