<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-31">Jan. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech-American Sokols Unite into Community</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0877</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0877.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-31">Jan. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH-AMERICAN SOKOLS UNITE INTO COMMUNITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We brought the news some time ago about the impending amalgamation of all the Sokol societies into one mighty organization, the "Cesko-Americka Obec Sokolska" ("Czech-American Sokol Community"). This unification evoked joyous response in all Czech-American settlements. Its main components were two large associations, the Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Union) and the group Fuegnertyrs. The plan for the action has been under discussion for many years, actually since the last general meeting of the delegates of all the Sokol associations, under the leadership of Doctor Scheiner, which was held in the United States. What appeared to a great number of doubters to be a dream for many years, impossible to come true, has become a reality. The difficulties in the path of the reorganization seemed unsurmountable indeed, yet the transformation took place, in an historically significant, and a portentous moment at that, just after <pb facs="5418478_6_0878.jpg" n="2"/>the Austrian persecutors arbitrarily, and in a spirit of revenge, had dissolved the most representative Czech association of the old homeland: the "Ceska Obec Sokolska" (Czech Sokol Community) and a great number of units belonging to it. The Czech-American Sokol Community has thus become the only heir to the tenets and ideals formerly upheld by the now defunct Community, whose headquarters were in Prague, Bohemia.</p>
   <p>The instant the formal unification had taken place, plans began to crop up for the conduct of the activities of the new body. Many ways had been devised for this purpose, prior to the unification, and as many had to be abandoned, until the final, more concrete ideas about the administration were conceived. The first fruit born out of these was the establishment of a main executive committee, into which are vested all of the agenda formerly handled by the National Sokol Union, and the group Fuegner-Tyrs, separately. The committee consists of <pb facs="5418478_6_0879.jpg" n="3"/>members of both sexes.</p>
   <p>The group Fuegner-Tyrs, in a touching farewell party to the public, wound up its affairs formally some time ago, although its official activity does not cease until today, when the National Sokol Union will give up its existence also. Tomorrow, the new Sokol community will begin a vigorous organized activity in order to emphasize its virility. The members on the committee are Sokol workers of previous excellent standing, so that the success of the biggest Sokol organization now in existence seems well assured.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
