<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-03-27">Mar. 27, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Charitable Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-03-27">Mar. 27, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1--The board of directors of the Bohemian Charitable Association, at last Friday's meeting, resolved to establish permanent headquarters suitable for that purpose in a spacious room, in the rear of Mr. Charles G. Foucek's drug store, which Mr. Foucek is placing at the disposal of the society, free of charge. The office will be opened tomorrow and perhaps, for a few days Mr. Foucek, will himself manage the business affairs of the society. The directors will seek suitable help of some kind, which will be engaged for the office. The directors' meetings, will take place in the future in the new office and this Friday's meeting, will be held there also.</p>
   <p>The meeting was brought to order by the chairman, Judge J. Z. Uhlir, and the directors were well represented. After the minutes were read and approved the investigating committee gave its report. The reports were given by Messrs. Stastny, F. G. Hajicek, Anton J. Cermak, and Joseph Turek, who also reported Mr. Sinagl's investigation findings, as the latter was not able to attend this meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0658.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following applied for membership in the society: John Pecha, James Stastny, Louis Schoeffel, Frank J. Nedbal, Joseph Kovar, and Joseph Cerny. It was reported by Mr. Anton Zahrobsky, that the Garden City Brewing Co., has donated the sum of $50 and at the next meeting the donation will be brought. Receipts from various sources were $70 and disbursements were $20.50.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
