<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-20">Feb. 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Sixth Yearly Report of the Secretary of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost for the Year 1915, Presented at the Annual Meeting, February 18, 1916, at Sokol Chicago Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0213</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0213.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-20">Feb. 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE SIXTH YEARLY REPORT OF THE SECRETARY OF THE CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST FOR THE YEAR 1915, PRESENTED AT THE ANNUAL MEETING, FEBRUARY 18, 1916, AT SOKOL CHICAGO HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Czech Charitable Association) has just finished its sixth year. It was founded in February, 1910, and has disbursed $28,452.32 during its existence. The cash on hand December 31, 1915 was $3,504.32. The total collections during its six years of existence amount to $28,956.54.</p>
   <p>At the regular annual meeting held February 6, 1915, a board of directors numbering twenty-four was chosen as follows:</p>
   <p>Directors whose term of service expires in 1916: Reverend Vaclav Vanek, Antonin Schnabl, Jan Sokol, and Karel V. Janovsky. Directors representing <pb facs="5418478_6_0214.jpg" n="2"/>our daily newspapers: Denni Hlasatel, (The Daily Crier) Jan A. Hospodsky; the Svornost, (Concord) Karel G. Krasny; the daily Narod (Nation), Jan W. Volner; Srravedlnost (Justice) did not announce its representative.</p>
   <p>The following directors term of service expires in 1917: Judge J. Z. Uhlir, F. G. Hajicek, F. J. Petru, Roman Sedlacek, Karel Novak, Antonin Laadt, Josef Bolek, and Stanislav J. Loula.</p>
   <p>The directors whose term of service expires in 1918: Petr Drije, Jan A. Cervenka, Antonin J. Cermak, Vaclav Cihak, Josef C. Pisa, Jan Chraska, Dr. F. J. Jirka and Louis Solar.</p>
   <p>During the year 1915 the following directors were added: Antonin M. Pekarek, Josef Zalusky, Eduard Kvidera and Frantisek Kreml.</p>
   <p>The directors selected the following officials: chairman, Judge <pb facs="5418478_6_0215.jpg" n="3"/>J. Z. Uhlir; first vice-chairman, (for Pilsen) Frantisek J. Petru; second vice-chairman, (for Czech California) Jan A. Cervenka; third vice-chairman, (for Merigold) Stanislav J. Loula; fourth vice-chairman, (for Town of Lake) Jan Klekr. He was later replaced by Karel V. Janovsky. The Reverend Vaclav Vanek was re-elected secretary. Antonin J. Cermak was elected financial secretary; F. G. Hajicek is treasurer; the business agent is J. A. Hospodsky. Representative to the United Registration Bureau, John A. Sokol. The auditing committee is composed of Antonin Laadt, Josef Bolek and Vaclav Cihak. The Tag Day committee is composed of F. J. Petru, Josef Bolek, Peter Drije, Jan W. Vollner, S. J. Loula, Louis Solar and K. V. Janovsky. A grand ball committee was selected and is composed of J. A. Sokol, A. J. Cermak, Jan A. Cervenka, Roman Sedlacek, F. G. Hajicek, K. G. Krasny, and Antonin Laadt. The following gentlemen were chosen as members of the Christmas gift committee: Reverend Vaclav Vanek, K. G. Krasny, J. A. Hospodsky, and Dr. F. J. Jirka.</p>
   <p>The board of directors met eighteen times during the year; they were <pb facs="5418478_6_0216.jpg" n="4"/>well-represented and took an active interest in the proceedings.</p>
   <p>The cash on hand on January 1, 1915, was $2,673.56. The depression was upon us; work was scarce; there were many requests for assistance. Toward the end of November our financial condition was so acute, that we expected our resources would be completely exhausted by the end of the following February.</p>
   <p>The secretary was requested to send statements to members in arrears. The ladies organized an auxiliary, and thanks are due to our many friends that with all those expenses we were able to end the year with cash on hand of $3,504.22,which is$830.66 more than we had last year.</p>
   <p>The Tag Day arranged by the auxiliary on Memorial Day yielded $768.14. The total receipts from the two grand balls of 1914 and 1915 were $3,038.51; from the Businessmen's 26th Street Carnival, we received $164.25; membership dues totaled $1,086.50; good will contributions amounted to $1,007.21; <pb facs="5418478_6_0217.jpg" n="5"/>interest on money deposited $53.93. Total receipts $5,954.29; balance from last year $2,673.56; total cash on hand $8,627.85</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Paid to indigents</cell>
     <cell>255.65</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Paid for rentals for indigents</cell>
     <cell>3,769.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Groceries, coal, clothing, shoes, and medicine</cell>
     <cell>198.91</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Incidentals and office rent</cell>
     <cell>899.57</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total disbursements</cell>
     <cell>$5,123.63</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash in hand at end of year</cell>
     <cell>$3,504.22</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>On July 24, a great catastrophe visited us with the sinking in the Chicago river of the steamer Eastland, and a couple of hundred of our countrymen lost their lives.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0218.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Our offices were immediately opened to the Cesky Pomocny Vybor (Czech Aid Committee), who devoted themselves to aid the dependents of the victims of this great catastrophe.</p>
   <p>The Cesky Pomocny Vybor organized through the kind offices of our superintendent, A. J. Cermak, did a most noteworthy work for humanity. More than $9,000 has been collected among our Czechs, and most of our trustees have been active in these commendable activities.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the Cesky Pomocny Vybor is A. J. Cermak; the secretary, Reverend Vaclav Vanek; and the treasurer, J. A. Holpuch.</p>
   <p>The Czech survivors of this catastrophe received their quota from the common fund of about $100,000.</p>
   <p>On December 7, the Damsky Odbor of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (The Ladies' Auxiliary of the Czech Charitable Association) was organized, <pb facs="5418478_6_0219.jpg" n="7"/>and immediately became very active. The club collected $702.65, which was used to purchase Christmas baskets for indigent families. To this fund was added $100 donated by Loze Bohemia Ceskych Zednaru (Lodge Bohemia of the Czech Masons). Whole rows of automobiles belonging to our well-wishers and friends distributed Christmas baskets to those living at a distance from our offices.</p>
   <p>With great pleasure we announce the formation of two more clubs, which will work for the benefit of the poor in our Czech communities. Through the meritoriouswork of Director R. V. Dvorak, the wives of businessmen of Chicago and vicinity have met for the purpose of starting another Cesky Damsky Pomocny Vybor, and a Junior League composed of young girls belonging to the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, organized to help the mother organization in its activities.</p>
   <p>At the December meeting it was necessary to make a change because of the illness of Miss Hospodka who filled the office of lady superintendent.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0220.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Miss Marie Hutter was elected to manage that office.</p>
   <p>The treasurer issued 1,000 checks during the year 1915. Eight hundred and fifty-six persons received aid. One hundred and twenty-five persons were helped in securing employment. Night lodgings were given to one hundred and thirty persons. Twenty-two persons were sent to old people's homes and orphanages. Six children were adopted. At the Christmas entertainment three hundred and sixty-five baskets were distributed,and six hundred children received useful presents. Sixty coal certificates were issued to families needing coal.</p>
   <p>Especial thanks are due our ladies for their services on Tag Day, the charity ball, and Christmas distribution of baskets; without their cooperation our activities would have been stinted.</p>
   <p>We thank our Czech dailies for their moral support. We thank our donors and corporations, for their support of our benevolent institutions with <pb facs="5418478_6_0221.jpg" n="9"/>regular liberal donations, and we thank other benevolent societies for their support.</p>
   <p>We thank Dr. Frantisek J. Jirka for the treatment free of charge to indigents recommended by our association. Thanks are due attorneys Josef C. Pisa and Josef Z. Klenha for free legal services, and we thank Mr. Frantisek G. Hajicek for his free services as bookkeeper, and for the preparing of our annual financial report. The books of our association were audited by Mr. H. C. Goettsche free of charge, and were found to be in good order.</p>
   <p>The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost has performed many good deeds during its existence; saved many families from ruin, and dried many tears of suffering. Had it not been for the existence of our association, many an indigent Czech family would not have been able to exist. Much is still needed. Chicago is the greatest Czech settlement in America, and the number of indigent people will grow year after year.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0222.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>With the growing community and the disregard of the rich for the sufferings of the poor, caused many times by our social conditions, by sickness, and by the inability to get work--for those our work here is mapped out. We must come to the aid of our brothers and sisters and help them carry their burdens, so that they may assert themselves to gain a better livelihood, which finally culminates in those so helped leading happier lives.</p>
   <p>Be members of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, you individuals and Czech societies, in whose hearts the love for our Czech poor, our sick, and our orphans, has not died; you are expected to come and join us.</p>
   <p>The yearly subscription is five dollars or more. There are no specified limits to your contributions.</p>
   <p>Reverend Vaclav Vanek, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
