<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-24">May 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Twelfth Ward Mass Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-24">May 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TWELFTH WARD MASS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Twelfth Ward had its big day yesterday. A gigantic parade marched through the main streets of the Czech district to the pavilion in Pilsen Brewery Park, where a mass meeting was held. The band from the Great Lakes Naval Station headed the procession, in which our ladies, in the uniforms of Red Cross nurses, attracted the special attention of the thousands who lined the sidewalks.</p>
   <p>The meeting in the pavilion was opened by Mr. Anton J. Cermak, chairman of the Czech Section of the American Red Cross. Among the speakers were Congressman Adolph J. Sabath; Judge Robert Crowe; Vojta Benes, secretary of the Czech National Alliance; J. J. Salat, secretary of the Czech Section; and Reverend Vaclav Vanek, chairman of the publicity committee of the Czech Section.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cermak thanked the principals of schools for their co-operation in the campaign; he also thanked the ladies and, last but not least, our Czech press.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0114.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He exhorted the assembly not to cease their activities.</p>
   <p>After a few patriotic remarks by Mr. Vojta Benes, Judge Crowe took the floor, eulogizing the Czechs for their patriotic activities, singling out Congressman Sabath and Mr. Cermak. "You have every reason to be proud of these two men," he said, "and though we are not Czechs, we too are proud of them, just as America is proud of you Czechs, who have proved to be such great American patriots."</p>
   <p>Turbulent applause rewarded the speaker, especially at his mention of ultimate victory--which means the fulfillment of the Czechs' fondest hopes for the creation of an independent Czech nation. All the speakers urged our people to work fervently for the support of the Red Cross. Congressman Sabath showed his desire to help by immediately handing over a handsome gift for the Red Cross.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0115.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mrs. Slavka Svoboda and Mrs. Slavka Krejci delighted the crowd with their singing. The Great Lakes band also played songs, some of which were patriotic. When the latter were played the crowd stood and listened with hats off. During the ceremonies on the stage, our ladies busied themselves in behalf of the Red Cross, signing up new members, and collecting gifts. The Assembly was also informed about an entertainment, arranged for the benefit of our soldiers, to be held in the Marshall Square Theater tonight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
