<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-04">May 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Minutes of the Meeting of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-04">May 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The chairman of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association, Mr. Pech, brought the well attended meeting to order, and had the minutes of the previous meeting read. The minutes were approved, as were also bills against the association. Communications received were read by the secretary, Mr. Halik. Rudolf Rubringer offered the services of his "Plzenska Kapela," (Pilsen Band) for the Decoration Day ceremonies, sixteen men for eighty-five dollars. Antonin Konopasek made a like offer. Ceska Ustredni Unie Tiskarskych Remesel (The Bohemian Printing Trades Central Union) sent a communication signed by its president, Mr. Sramek, and its secretary Mr. Hlobil, in which are explained the reasons for its organization, and asking for the support of the Association.</p>
   <p>The building committee of Sokol Chicago calls to the attention of the <pb facs="5418478_6_1566.jpg" n="2"/>Association the fact that bonds have been issued for the loan being made to finance the construction of the addition to "Sokol Chicago" hall, and asks the Association to buy as many as possible. This matter was referred to the managing committee for investigation.</p>
   <p>The Association on behalf of the erection committee for the erection of the Karel Havlicek Borovsky monument, thanks the Bohemian National Cemetery Association for the $1500 contribution, and encloses a receipt for the money.</p>
   <p>The following named officers were elected: John Pech, president; Evzen Frydl, vice-president; Stanislav J. Halik, secretary; Joseph Jurka, treasurer. The managing committee for two years is: Vaclav Psenicka; for one year, Karel Kopecky. The auditing committee, V. H. Cerny, Thomas David, and John Klaus. Receipts were $8,447.55; on hand $11,305.40; disbursements, $15,373.25; and the balance in treasury is $4,379.70.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
