<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-24">Feb. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">George Washington Birthday Celebration in Pilsen Sokol's Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-24">Feb. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">GEORGE WASHINGTON BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION IN PILSEN SOKOL'S HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The twenty-second day of February is one of the very few days, the significance of which will never be trivial with the people of America--just as the historical profile of George Washington, to whom this national holiday is consecrated, will never fade. The American nation will always look up to this leader of the heroic Revolutionary Army as one of its greatest sons, as the Father of his country, who was first in war, first in peace, and first in the hearts of his countrymen. That the Americans pay their dignified homage to George Washington every year is understood, and if his birthday is remembered by the immigrants, then it is evidence of their spiritual intelligence. The people who founded their homes and secured their freedom on the shores of America, which they lacked in their old countries, cannot better manifest their gratitude than to esteem the memory of these great geniuses, to whom we should be thankful for all these free institutions enjoyed in the United States. First in this respect among us Bohemians, is <pb facs="5418478_6_1752.jpg" n="2"/>the Sbor Plzenskych Sokolek (Women's Pilsen Sokol Association). Its annual celebrations arranged in past years, have their own familiar characteristics, not only in the purpose itself, but also in the selected program. This year's celebration, held last night, was in this regard especially successful. The hall was almost filled; the mood of the audience was festive.</p>
   <p>The speaker of the evening was Mr. Frank Comerford, who recently returned from Europe where he was active as a member of the American Press Syndicate, and who also stayed for sometime in the Czechoslovak Republic. He is a stirring speaker and disposed of his task in a grand manner. Other numbers on the program were of an artistic nature, and were heartily applauded.</p>
   <p>Considering all, last night's celebration was a success in every respect. The president of the association, Mrs. Frances Hulka, who arranged the program may be fully satisfied with the results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
