<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-25">Oct. 25, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">October the Twenty-Eighth</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-25">Oct. 25, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">OCTOBER THE TWENTY-EIGHTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Perhaps it will be the first time in the history of the Czechoslovaks of America that delegates representing the various organizations of war veterans attend and take part in the celebration of our Czechoslovak independence. Among them also will be a mere handful of aged [Czech] veterans of the Civil War, who in the dim past, during the memorable years of 1861-1865, under the presidency of Abraham Lincoln, stood embattled under The Star-Spangled Banner to shed their blood for the equality and the rights of humanity. Cermak's Historie civilni valky (History of the Civil War) acquaints the reader with the bravery of our Union soldiers and gives the names of a considerable number of our countrymen in America who even in those days--the stirring days of that national struggle--stood in the fratricidal conflict of the democratic North against the aristocratic South.....After that conflict was over, another one--the war with Spain--occurred, and here too the number of American Czechoslovaks who participated was quite amazing, these men having voluntarily <pb facs="5418478_6_1665.jpg" n="2"/>taken up arms against the common foe. Among the Czechoslovaks who so enlisted Chicago contributed the greatest number. Then came the World War, and again .... our Czechoslovak countrymen of America volunteered..... There were more than twenty thousand American Czechoslovaks who thus voluntarily enlisted under Columbia's flag. Some of them were mere striplings, freshly graduated from the schools of our country; but there were also many adults among them, men who tearfully left their families behind....</p>
   <p>At the celebration of the Czechoslovak Independence Day to be held in Pilsen Park on Saturday, as previously arranged by the Druzina Ceskoslovenskych Legionaru (local branch of the Czechoslovak legionnaires) in co-operation with all the local Chicago and suburban Sokol unions, as well as all the important Czechoslovak fraternal and benevolent organizations, there will be present for the first time in the history of the Czechoslovaks of America representative bodies of American veterans in full uniform. Our women will come dressed in the costume of the Czechoslovak peasantry, and everybody who takes part in the <pb facs="5418478_6_1666.jpg" n="3"/>celebration will be imbued with the festive spirit of the occasion.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovaks of Chicago are hereby respectfully asked to come in the greatest possible numbers to pay their respects to all the war veterans. The Czechoslovak consul general, Dr. Jaroslav F. Smetanka, is going to deliver an address on the theme "Czechoslovak Independence and the Czechoslovaks of America," and Brother Jarko Kosar will make a speech on behalf of the American Sokol Union..... Let October 28 be a festive day for all the Czechoslovaks of Chicago!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
