<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-24">Oct. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czechoslovak Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III H (Slovak)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-24">Oct. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHOSLOVAK CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A conference of representatives of the Czechoslovak people in America, was held in Cleveland, Ohio, October 16, 1918. It was called by the Czech National Alliance, the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America, and the Slovak League.....Attorney Thomas Capek of New York presided; Mr. J. Tittelbach of Chicago was elected to record the minutes.....</p>
   <p>[Names of those present given....]</p>
   <p>The following items were on the program of the Czech National Alliance group: Report on organization, finance, amendment of statutes, [Czech] National Tax, election of delegates for the executive committee of the Czech National Alliance and for the Czechoslovak National Council, and motions.....</p>
   <p>.....A delegation of Ruthenians [Carpatho-Russians, also called Rusini] appeared to greet the convention, and, through Mr. Mikula, requested that <pb facs="5418478_6_1168.jpg" n="2"/>the action for the liberation of the Czechoslovaks be extended to help the Ruthenians. Mr. Mikula assured the assembly that his people will collaborate to the utmost. Captain Spacek, from Vladivostok, Siberia, who has been in America only a few days, reported on conditions in Carpatho-Russia.</p>
   <p>It was decided that representatives of the Czechoslovak National Council, the Slovak League, the Czech National Alliance, and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics, should meet separately in three groups during the first days, and join in a common meeting later.....The political report compiled by Mr. Pergler was one of the most important in this session.....</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak National Council is to be reorganized, and will be composed of ten Czechs and ten Slovaks. They will meet at least once a year. The Bohemian Review will be the official organ of the Council, appearing from now on as the Czechoslovak Review. A mansion was rented at Washington, D. C., which will be the headquarters of Professor T. G. Masaryk, head of the <pb facs="5418478_6_1169.jpg" n="3"/>provisional government of the future Czechoslovak Republic. With him will be his daughter Olga, K. Pergler our diplomatic representative in the United States, and Captain Hurban of the Czechoslovak Army in Russia.....It is intended to create an historical museum of the American Czechs and the Czechoslovak revolution.</p>
   <p>The Committee on Military Affairs reported that needy families of soldiers in the Czechoslovak Army are being supported by the American Red Cross, in proportion to their needs.</p>
   <p>During the session a telegram arrived from the Czechoslovak Army in France stating that our soldiers are ready to fight to the finish, and until complete liberty is assured. President Wilson, Secretary of State Lansing, and Professor Masaryk, commander in chief of the Czechoslovak Army, were sent telegrams expressive of gratitude and loyalty.</p>
   <p>A detailed discussion of the composition of the Czechoslovak National <pb facs="5418478_6_1170.jpg" n="4"/>Council resulted in a decision that of the 20 members, 6 should be from the Czech National Alliance, 4 from the National Alliance of Czech Catholics, and 10 from the Slovak League.</p>
   <p>One of the most important decisions made was a change in the statutes, which shall do away with misgivings and establish mutual trust and confidence which were not always found among the Czechoslovaks here. There had been frequent complaints that the heads of the Czech National Alliance were being selected mostly from Chicagoans. From now on, the president, secretary, and treasurer of that organization are to be elected by the vote of all settlements in the United States, by a general, popular vote.</p>
   <p>It was further decided that meetings of the Czech National Alliances must be held at regular intervals, and that representation there must be impressive. This body is to be regarded as the highest tribunal of the Czech people in America. Special meetings, held every other year, will serve for a review of activities of that body. Not only officers of the Alliance, but delegates <pb facs="5418478_6_1171.jpg" n="5"/>of all our organizations shall take part.</p>
   <p>The introduction of a National Tax, levied on our people in the United States and Canada, was unanimously approved by delegates of the Czech and of the Catholic Alliance alike. Collections will begin next Thanksgiving Day.</p>
   <p>The financial reports showed that the accounts were in perfect order, and that the Czech National Alliance is beginning to dispose of its resources with discrimination and sound judgment. It was suggested that the figures of both the accountant and the treasurer be entered in the same book to make a single system of bookkeeping.</p>
   <p>The results of the conferences are far reaching. The entire system has been simplified and placed on a popular basis, as evident from the new way of electing officers. The meetings also gave us an opportunity to meet men from faraway districts, e.g., Mr. Smid, of Winnipeg, Canada, representing Canadian Czechs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1172.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The last session was held Thursday. The question of the design of the flag for the new Czechoslovak Republic was taken up. Dr. Ludwig Fisher, of Chicago, stated that Czechs in the motherland, and Slovaks as well, favor white, blue, and red.....</p>
   <p>The Czech Sokol Community of America held their first rally in Cleveland, during the days of this conference, and donated $1,000 to the Czech National Alliance; $1,000 was donated by two Sokol brothers, Mr. Joseph Dusek, merchant, and Mr. J. F. Stepina, Chicago banker....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
