<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-03-14">Mar. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Youngster Dedicted by Grand Jury for Robbery and Murder</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-03-14">Mar. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN YOUNGSTER DEDICTED BY GRAND JURY FOR ROBBERY AND MURDER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The March Grand Jury has sent to the office of the State's Attorney, a number of indictments against persons who committed various crimes. It is necessary to mention that indictment by the Grand Jury is not a proof of guilt, but in most cases the evidence placed before the jurors is so convincing that there is little doubt that the defendant is guilty.</p>
   <p>The indictment is very serious against Richard Putz, a Bohemian youngster who until the time of his arrest lived at 627 East 61st Street. He is accused of robbery and murder, and according to the police officers he has confessed this crime. The youngster, who is only about 16 years old, entered the Shapiro Store on February 17, to buy himself a pair of stockings. This, of course, was only a pretense because Putz immediately drew a revolver and aimed it at the clerk, John F. Barcham, who lived at <pb facs="5418478_6_0708.jpg" n="2"/>3433 Walnut Street. Barcham, although 63 years old, resisted and the youngster shot him, the bullet piercing his abdomen. The wounded man was taken in a police ambulance to the Garfield Park Hospital, where on February 20, he died. After the crime was committed the youngster fled, but soon afterward he was captured by the police. He was taken to the inquest held in the undertaking establishment at 645 North Cicero Avenue, under the direction of Deputy Coroner Herman. Because of the evidence presented, the youngster was then held and the case presented directly to the Grand Jury without the usual preliminary trial at the Municipal Court, and he was formally indicted. Mrs. Barbora Putz, his mother, lives at 4415 North Keeler Avenue, and his father is an inmate of a sanatorium near Fox Lake. About six years ago the youngster was examined by City Psychiatrist Dickinson, who found him to be feebleminded. The Shapiro Store, the scene of the crime, is located at 205 South Kedzie Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
