<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-13">Oct. 13, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Exposition of the "Pamatnik Odboje"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1049</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1049.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-13">Oct. 13, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">EXPOSITION OF THE "PAMATNIK ODBOJE"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is an immense significance to the word "Odboj" (Insurrection; "Pamatnik Odboje"--Memorial of Insurrection). It means all that the Czechoslovak people have done in and about the insurrection against the German and Magyar oppression. It means the cry of resistance and opposition ending in the rattle of broken fetters in which the Czechoslovak has been pining for the last three hundred years. The mighty cry resounded all over the world wherever there was a member of that oppressed nation. The resistance, opposition, and insurrection reached the culmination point in the formation of the Czechoslovak Legion in Russia, France, Serbia, and Italy. While the nation at home was engaged in passive resistance, the Legion became active. And the Legion while it--with the exception of its Russian part--was not particularly numerous, was deing deeds of such courage and bravery as can be done only by those who are activated by something more than mere military duty. It must be that the activation is as strong as national consiciousness, ardor for the sacred cause of one's own blood and country.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1050.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To write about the Legion now would mean to write a whole section of our nation's history. But even after reading the whole section many people would fail to understand what it was, how it lived, and what it has done for the liberation of our country and the better future of the coming generations of the Czechoslovak nation. The Ministry of National Defense has bent every effort to secure all documents and testimonial material pertaining to the activities of the Legion, and has assembled them in the "Pamatnik Odboje," whose director is the now well-known commander of the Siberian reconnoitering troups, standard-bearer, now Lieutenant-Colonel Medek, the poet of the Siberian Czechoslovak army. The Ministry of National Defense has sent two Russian Legionnaires, the Brothers Ruml and Wanner, with the "Pamatnik Odboje" to America so that our American countrymen who have made such a splendid contribution to the liberation of our country may see what the Legion had done. The documents of all that will be on exhibition in Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs from October 25 to October 28, which is the anniversary of our Czechoslovak declaration of independence. It will end in a festival arranged in co-operation with the Druzina <pb facs="5418478_6_1051.jpg" n="3"/>Ceskoslovenskych Legionaru (Fellowship or Czechoslovak Legionnaires) which every participant will remember as long he lives. Don't forget: "Pamatnik Odboje".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
