<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning Czecroslovak Independence</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1759</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1759.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING CZECROSLOVAK INDEPENDENCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are celebrating a day which has brought us nearer to our ideals than we have ever been before. This day we look ahead with the rosiest hopes. We can visualize independence for our old motherland. We of Chicago, and Czecns of all settlements in this great Republic, are indebted for this day to the far-sighted, wise, glorious American Government at whose head stands the greatest man of our era--President Woodrow Wilson, through whoson proclamation Czechoslovakia was pronounced by the American Government an independent state.</p>
   <p>The recognition awarded to Czechoslovakia dates from September 3, true enough. At that time, Secretary of the State Lansing, acting in the name of the President, asked our great leader, Professor Thomas G. Masaryk, to his office, to inform him of the decision reached by the U. S. Government after <pb facs="5418478_6_1760.jpg" n="2"/>a thorough consideration given to various weighty matters. Not only was the Czechoslovak army, fighting now on three fronts, recognized as one of the Allied armies, but the Government also acknowledged the Czechoslovak National Council as the de facto government of the independent Czechoslovak state, with which the United States Government is ready to initiate diplomatic contact.</p>
   <p>This recognition filled every one who thinks and feels as a sincere Czech with exuberant emotions, which spreand to Czech settlements all over the United States.</p>
   <p>This great event had been anticipated in happy suspense, yet it came some-what as a surprise. Our settlements in America were not prepared to show their indescribable happiness in a manner befitting the magnificence of the event, nor the degree of their gratitude and loyalty. This is the reason why the manifestation was postponed till today, September 14, when it will be held in every one of our settlements in the United States in a manner <pb facs="5418478_6_1761.jpg" n="3"/>in keeping with prevailing conditions. On this day, official Washington is to be swamped with telegrams, some of them from even our tiniest hamlets. This will show our gratitude, and assure the United States Government that American Czechoslovaks are a grateful people. Their gratefulness springs from their love for the motherland, which had been abused and oppressed in spite of its former greatness and glory.....</p>
   <p>We have arranged for the celebration which is sponsored by the Czech National Alliance, the National Alliance of Czech Catholics, and the Slovak League. It will begin with a parade this afternoon and end in a mass meeting in Grant Park where the War Exposition is being held at present.</p>
   <p>No place more convenient could have been selected. The Exposition in Grant Park is sponsored by the United States Government--the same which, by recognizing the Czechoslovak state as an independent state, has granted us the right to direct and govern our own affairs. We should, therefore, like to see Grant Park filled to capacity with people of our kind. We wish this, <pb facs="5418478_6_1762.jpg" n="4"/>not for the sake of Czechoslovaks who will assemble there, but for the people of other nationalities who will be present, especially those of native American stock, all of whom must witness the manifestation of our spontaneous joy, our enthusiasm, and our eternal gratitude, so that they be in a position to inform Washington of it, in long and impressive reports, just as our local English language newspapers surely will give our great celebration prominent space.</p>
   <p>We also would like to see, among the gigantic masses that will throng the Exposition, our own people showing their sentiments in a plain, yet enthusiastic manner. They should testify to our gratitude to President Wilson and, right after, to Professor Thomas G. Masaryk, who has been acknowledged as the head of the independent Czechoslovak state.</p>
   <p>Let us manifest our sentiments well aware of these facts: Had it not been for Masaryk and his unbending convictions, unafraid of struggles and sacrifices, the latter touching some of the most sacred relations, i.e., his <pb facs="5418478_6_1763.jpg" n="5"/>own family--had it not been for the tireless work and the superhuman exertion of this man of high age for the sake of freedom and independence of our nation--our cause would never have reached the advanced stage of today, when the war is not even finished yet.</p>
   <p>Let us consider that it was Masaryk who, regardless of the interests of his own person, his family or other considerations, thought of his motherland and his people only--who worked day and night, started out on long voyages and missions at any time of the day or night, no matter whether they required (even a trip around the world)--who organized, urged and arranged until today, when we have an accomplished fact before us.</p>
   <p>Also, do not let us forget our heroic Czechoslovak army, which we have to thank in the first place for the success with which our movement for the liberation of Czechoslovak land has been meeting up to the present. This army has worked wonders, not only in Russia, but everywhere else. This army has accomplished marvels in awakening national consciousness and <pb facs="5418478_6_1764.jpg" n="6"/>self-assertion, which hitherto had been dormant or insensitive. Let us give thanks for everything our army has done for the enhancement of our movement. The same gratitude is due to the Czechoslovak National Council, the Czech National Alliance, the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America, and the Slovak League--and not less to all brothers and sisters across the ocean, who have supported us in our struggle--they lent us strength, and we should do the same for them. Gratitude is due to all the co-workers. It is meet to state that the work is not finished, and more will be demanded.</p>
   <p>The measure of success attained is not a signal for rest; on the contrary, it is, for us, an incentive for more intensive, energetic work, for sacrifices which will increase in importance. To be ready for these future sacrifices should be the essence of the resolutions that we shall make this evening in the meeting! Let us make these resolutions with gladness and joy, consecrated in our hearts by our ardent love for the old motherland and for our new homeland as well. We shall, in this manner, best honor the memorable day of September 3, 1918, the day on which Czechoslovakia <pb facs="5418478_6_1765.jpg" n="7"/>was proclaimed an independent state by the greatest, most glorious and, be it emphasized, the most democratic Republic of the whole world-- the United States of North America!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
