<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-01-15">Jan. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Distinguished Guests Among Us</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Bohemians of Chicago Greet Jan Masaryk for the First Time, Say Farewell to Karel Pergler, and Hear Bohdan Pavlu and Dr. Pisecky</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1160</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1160.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-01-15">Jan. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">DISTINGUISHED GUESTS AMONG US</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Bohemians of Chicago Greet Jan Masaryk for the First Time, Say Farewell to Karel Pergler, and Hear Bohdan Pavlu and Dr. Pisecky</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, the arrival of two diplomatic representatives of the Czechoslovak republic was reported, that of Jan Masaryk, son of the first president of the liberated Bohemian nation, and Karel Pergler, former journalist and lawyer, whose name is almost inseparably connected with our liberation actions in America, and who was recently appointed Ambassador to Japan.</p>
   <p>Jan Masaryk, at present, charge'd'affaires with the Czechoslovak legation in Washington, D. C., arrived in Chicago yesterday about eleven A. M., and Karel Pergler, delayed by important matters, did not arrive until late afternoon. In Jan Masaryk's company was another guest, Bohdan Pavlu, who, until recently, represented the Czechoslovak government in far away Siberia.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1161.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the depot, they were awaited by Messrs. Karel V. Janovsky, Frank G. Hajicek and Votava. After a formal greeting, they were taken to the Blackstone Hotel. Officially, they were greeted at the Morrison Hotel, where a reception was held, to which scores of our prominent Bohemian workers and American representatives were invited. The reception was attended by representatives of commerce and industry, pedagogues, journalists, etc. The elite of American intelligentsia was represented. Our guests were greeted so warmly that they will hardly forget the occasion.</p>
   <p>The reception was arranged by the Bohemian National Alliance, the Bohemian National Catholic Alliance, and the Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce. Also present were Dr. Pisecky, official of the Bank of Bohemia, who arrived in the United States on business matters, and Mr. F. Filip, well-known banker and sokol leader from Cedar Rapids, Iowa.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1162.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dr. Joseph P. Pecival, chairman of the Bohemian National Alliance, introduced Jan Masaryk as a representative of the Czechoslovakian government, and as a son of the first Czechoslovak President. He assured him that the co-operation and sympathy of the American Czechoslovaks would follow him in his responsible position. After the prologue of Dr. Joseph P. Pecival, Mr. Jan Masaryk spoke, and in a few introductory words, he quickly gained the sympathy of his listeners.</p>
   <p>Young Masaryk is a sympathetic man in every detail. He speaks the English language fluently, and gives the impression of a man of great energy. He expressed appreciation for the warm reception, and said he was proud of the honor of being the representative of one of the new countries risen up from the ruins of the Central Powers.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1163.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Dr. George L. Knapp, member of the editorial staff of the Chicago Evening Journal, who, in his editorials, had rendered us so many invaluable services, made a very nice speech. In a few words, he spoke in beautiful English of the three hundredth anniversary of the landing of the Pilgrims, who sought a new country, liberty, and freedom, on the shores of America, while the Czechs were losing them in their own country. But history has its own logic. Today, not only the United States stands firm, but Czechoslovakia also is awakening from mortal slumber to a new life. He also paid homage to President Masaryk, whom he ardently worships, and places him among the five greatest statesmen of the world at the present time. Other speakers were: Mr. Taylor, Professor Sam. H. Harper, Mr. White, Mr. Anthony Czarnecki of the editorial staff of the Chicago Daily News, Captain Charles E. Merriam, professor at the University of Chicago, and others. Again, we were convinced that among the American intelligentsia we have a great number of friends, whose social and economic influence can be our best security in the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1164.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>For a long time, the Bohemians of Chicago have not had a meeting of such importance as the one held last night. The meeting was sponsored by the Czech National Alliance, the Czech National Catholic Alliance, the Slavonic League, and the Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce. Our public was given an opportunity to hear a great number of competent speakers, and as evidenced by the crowd, they did not intend to miss this opportunity. The hall of Sokol Chicago, long before the opening time, was filled to capacity. Especially, were the words of Bohdan Pavlu eagerly awaited. He is on his way from far off Siberia to his homeland, Czechoslovakia. He is one of the organizers and creators of the Czechoslovakian Legionnaires in Russia and Siberia. In his speech, Bohdan Pavlu expressed his gratitude to our American-Bohemian public for all that was done for the liberation of the Czechoslovakia, and for the Legionnaires in Siberia.....</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Jan Masaryk, who said in substance: "Esteemed friends, <pb facs="5418478_6_1165.jpg" n="6"/>brothers and sisters: Very gladly I accepted the invitation to be introduced to the largest Czechoslovak community in the United States. Thanks, to all of you in the name of the Government, in the name of the President and in the name of our Nation, for all that you have done, for all that is being done, and for all that I hope will be done in the future.</p>
   <p>"On the twenty-eighth day of October last, we celebrated the first anniversary of our independence, and it can be said that we are not ashamed of it. On the twenty-seventh day of October, we retired as the subjects of the Austro-Hungarian Empire, and on the next day we awakened as free Czechoslovaks. At that time, there were no political parties, nor special interests. At that time we did not dream of the terrible task awaiting us. Therefore, today we can proudly proclaim that the Czechoslovak republic is a pioneer of sound, social politics in Central Europe. Almost anyone can criticise, but not everybody has so much moral strength <pb facs="5418478_6_1166.jpg" n="7"/>as to admit frankly and openly his faults, and then honestly exert himself to correct them ....."</p>
   <p>Karel Pergler, in his speech said, "that our tasks are not accomplished as yet. Many other things have to be done before the freedom and safety of the Czechoslovak republic will be established ....."</p>
   <p>Dr. Pisecky assured the audience that the financial and economical standing of the Czechoslovak republic was sound. He also described the difficulties he is having to establish a credit .....</p>
   <p>Our Vcelky (the association of Bohemian ladies) undertook a collection for the benefit of the Alice Masaryk fund, and collected the sum of $303.30.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
