<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-02-08">Feb. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Meeting of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0495</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0495.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-02-08">Feb. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF THE CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Friday night the fourth annual meeting of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) was held in the pavilion of Pilsen Park, at Albany Avenue and 26th Street. The meeting was opened by the president, Judge J. Z. Uhlir, after which the minutes of the last annual meeting were read by the secretary, Reverend V. Vanek, and were approved. The next item on the program was the reading of the secretary's report, which was as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost has completed its fourth year of work, having been founded in February, 1910, and it now takes pleasure in presenting to its members and to the entire Bohemian public the following report:</p>
   <p>"At the annual meeting in 1913 the following board of directors was elected: For three years: Dr. Geo. Rezanka, Peter Drije, John A. Cervenka, A. J. Cermak, Vaclav Cihak, F. J. Nedbal, Jos. C. Pisa, and Jan Chrastka. For a two-year period the following members were retained as directors: Reverend V. Vanek, Anton Snabl, Jan Sokol, Jos. F. Triska, J. A. Hospodsky [for the Denni Hlasatel], Karel G. Krasny [for the Svornost], Jan W. Woller[for the Narod], and Frank Gruener <pb facs="5418478_6_0496.jpg" n="2"/>[representing the Spravedlnost]. The following men were elected for one year: J. Z. Uhlir, J. S. Loula, F. J. Petru, Vaclav Lisy, Roman Sedlacek, Karel Novak, and Anton Laadt.</p>
   <p>"This board of twenty-four directors has elected from its midst the following officers: J. G. Uhlir, president; F. J. Petru, vice-president representing Pilsen; Jan A. Cervenka, second vice-president for Bohemian 'California'; Stanley J. Loula, third vice-president for Merigold; and J. F. Triska, fourth vice-president for Town of Lake; V. Vanek, secretary; Roman Sedlacek, assistant-secretary; Anton J. Cermak, financial secretary; and F. G. Hajicek, treasurer.</p>
   <p>"The board of directors held twenty-one meetings during the year, all of which were well attended, and the officers have diligently performed all their duties. In April Mr. Franke, the owner of the California Theater, arranged three performances for our benefit which netted $163.10. In May a committee of two composed of Messrs. Cermak and Vanek called on the investigating committee of the State Legislature and filed a report concerning the management of our office. This <pb facs="5418478_6_0497.jpg" n="3"/>report proved that our management was the most efficient and least expensive of all the charitable societies in the city. To the Bohemian Orphanage and Old People's Home, the Spolecnost donated $175 for Bohemian orphans and an equal amount to the Bohemian orphans in Lisle, Illinois.</p>
   <p>"The tag day held on Decoration Day netted $1,365. The manager of the Pilsen Brewery remitted to us a $50 prize from a contest. At the meeting of September 19, we received the good news that Mr. Leo Klein bequeathed one thousand dollars to the Spolecnost. This was the first time in the history of the Spolecnost that we were remembered in this way. The charity ball held on November 5 at Pilsen Park surpassed in attendance all those held in previous years and netted $2,495.82. [Translator's note: There follows a report on Christmas and other donations, contributions for groceries, coal, clothing, medicine, and funeral expenses which the Spolecnost made during the year.]</p>
   <p>"Our total expenses were $4,995.80. Altogether we rendered assistance to 583 families with 736 children. Four hundred and two persons asked our office to secure employment for them, and 243 of them were placed. Fifty single persons <pb facs="5418478_6_0498.jpg" n="4"/>were given assistance, mostly from the emergency fund. The hospital expenses of 35 persons were paid. Our employment bureau does not yet function as well as it should. It will be necessary to cultivate contacts on a large scale with shops, stores, and farming regions, in order to increase our efficiency in this respect. Among the families which we support, there are many pathetic cases in which our support cannot be discontinued. Many of them are receiving our aid regularly throughout the year. In some cases the men are bedridden at home or in institutions. Some are in the Bridewell, and the wives and children must not be left in need. [There follow expressions of thanks to various firms and individuals for donations of pieces of equipment, material, and services.]</p>
   <p>"There is a great deal yet to be done. The Spolecnost should have at least five hundred members with a minimum dues of $5. It should also be more frequently remembered by Bohemian corporations. Considering the size of the Bohemian colony in Chicago, it is deplorable that membership dues during the year 1913 totaled only $1,247.....Vaclav Vanek, secretary"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
