<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-08">Feb. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">For the Freedom of the Czechoslovaks in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech and Slovak Noncitizens Should Be Called "Friendly Foreigners"(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0992</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0992.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-08">Feb. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE FREEDOM OF THE CZECHOSLOVAKS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech and Slovak Noncitizens Should Be Called "Friendly Foreigners"(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The war which the United States has entered has placed Czechs and Slovaks who are not yet naturalized in the class of alien enemies, although President Wilson magnanimously acknowledged, just as Congress did, that an exception should be made in this case, in order that Czechs and Slovaks may enjoy freedom of movement and not be subject to registration. The Czechs and Slovaks would find it a heavy economic burden should a decision be made against them. This would be a severe blow especially to many of our fellow citizens who are working in ammunition plants and other war industries.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0993.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For this reason, the Czech National Alliance has intervened in official places, mainly through Mr. K. Pergler, who also represents the Czech National Alliance of America at the headquarters of the Czechoslovak National Council in Paris, France. We can say today that the Czech National Alliance has achieved pronounced successes in this respect.</p>
   <p>We cannot, of course, give detailed reports on what steps are being taken by our representative, Mr. Pergler, in Washington, D. C. Our fellow countrymen in France, England, and Russia are already in a position similar to the one we are trying to create for them in America. Nothing has been left undone, however, to gain full recognition of Czechs and Slovaks as sincere friends of America and the Allies.</p>
   <p>Suffice it to say that the important resolution passed by the Czech National Alliance is being brought to the attention of all those in responsible official positions by Mr. Pergler, and that its vigorous style and its pungency have <pb facs="5418478_6_0994.jpg" n="3"/>attracted widespread attention in American political circles. This will have important consequences.</p>
   <p>The resolution is worded as follows: "The Czech people, in a free election in 1526, called the Hapsburgs to the throne of their land, which had nothing in common with the other lands except a common reigning house. Independence of the Czech state was guaranteed by a solemn oath on the part of the Hapsburgs.</p>
   <p>"Czechs have never ceased to insist upon their rights of independence from Austria. They have always opposed the present constellation of the Dual Monarchy. This has been acknowledged by President Wilson himself, who declares in his book, The State:</p>
   <p>"'Neither the course of time nor the battering of their hopes seems to be able to effect a reconciliation of the Czechs with their incorporation into Austria.' Even now, the Emperor of Austria still uses the name 'King of <pb facs="5418478_6_0995.jpg" n="4"/>Bohemia'.</p>
   <p>"No Czech parliamentary assembly ever approved the declaration of war [on Serbia]. Ever since the beginning of the war, the Czechs have stood against Austria-Hungary. They have done this with the utmost exertion of their powers. This is demonstrated by the attitude of the Czech representatives in the Austrian parliament, by the manifestos of Czech writers and those issued by the Czech workingmens' organizations. A result of this was the cruel persecutions and the wholesale executions perpetrated on Czechs by the Austro-Hungarian Government during the entire duration of the war.</p>
   <p>"The legal existence of the Czech state is further documented by the existence of the Czechoslovak Army in France and in Russia. This army is sponsored and directed by the Czechoslovak National Council, which is headed by Professor T. G. Masaryk.</p>
   <p>"The Czechs in Russia issued a proclamation recently, according to which the <pb facs="5418478_6_0996.jpg" n="5"/>Hapsburgs are dethroned from the rule of the lands of the Czechoslovak crown and of Slovakia. Our Czechoslovak forces are prosecuting a war against Austria-Hungary. They are under the command of the Czechoslovak National Council. This is a regular army, and should, according to existing international laws, be recognized as such.</p>
   <p>"Emperor Karl of Austria-Hungary is, as far as Czechs are concerned, nothing but a usurper who never was crowned king of Bohemia and who possesses no right to rule over the Czechs. The throne of the kingdom of Bohemia, therefore, is vacant.</p>
   <p>"Czechs and Slovaks belong to the same nation. The only difference between them is this: The Czechs suffer under German autocracy in Austria, whereas the Slovaks groan under Magyar rule in Hungary. Both the Czechs and Slovaks issued a manifesto in Paris, France, last November, proclaiming themselves enemies of the Austro-Hungarian dynasty. They asked for independence of the <pb facs="5418478_6_0997.jpg" n="6"/>Czechoslovaks and the establishment of an independent Czechoslovak state.</p>
   <p>"Czechoslovaks in the Allied countries are not classified as alien enemies; they enjoy perfect freedom in England and France. Merely on the strength of their identification as members of the Czechoslovak National Council, they are recognized as belonging to a friendly nation. The recently established Provisional Government of Russia granted privileges to all members of any Czechoslovak organization in that country.</p>
   <p>"Czechs and Slovaks joined the United States Army in large numbers the instant war was declared on Germany by the United States. They furnished a contingent proportionally larger than that of any other national group in America. They excelled in the purchase of war bonds. They demonstrated in this way, and in numerous other cases, the loyalty and sincerity of the Czechs and Slovaks to the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0998.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"Therefore, be it resolved that the President and the Congress of the United States be requested not to classify Czechs and Slovaks as alien enemies, and to exempt them from laws concerning the latter."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
