<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-20">Sept. 20, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A Generous Gift for the Benefit of the Bazar Svobody Arranged by Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1064</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1064.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-20">Sept. 20, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A GENEROUS GIFT FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE BAZAR SVOBODY ARRANGED BY CZECHOSLOVAK LEGIONNAIRES OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently a general drive has been started throughout Chicago by the Bazar Svobody (Liberty Bazaar) arrangement committee for the purpose of collecting the largest possible number of gifts for the benefit of the bazaar, which will be held in the near future. We joyfully report that the sincere efforts of members of the arrangement committee have met with unexpected success.</p>
   <p>Monetary contributions and various gifts of good will are coming in from all sides. Our generous businessmen and large American firms showed their sympathy with the purposes of this project by donating various commodities, products, or monetary contributions. One of these generous benefactors in Chicago is a well-known financier among our Bohemian people, and is connected with the Lawndale National Bank. The Bank, through its president, Mr. Frank G. Hajicek, just recently sent a congratulatory letter enclosing a check for three hundred dollars to Mr. John A. Cervenka for the benefit of the Bazar Svobody.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1065.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is unnecessary to mention that each contribution of this sort gives the members of the arrangement committee a great deal of satisfaction. The remarkable number of gifts and contributions which are coming in not only is evidence of the sympathy felt for the project itself, but is also good proof that the Bazar Svobody, as far as its financial success is concerned, has met with the approval of our people, as the project justly deserves.</p>
   <p>At the next meeting of the arrangement committee, which will be held next Monday, and to which not only the delegates, but also all the people of good will are invited, a complete report of the preliminary work will be presented. Also various committees will be appointed. Many will be needed because this project is being arranged on a large scale. To accomplish such a colossal program, many experienced and generous workers will be essential, and therefore anybody who possibly can, should respond to the call. The arrangement committee will gladly accept anybody of good will who is willing to help in any manner <pb facs="5418478_6_1066.jpg" n="3"/>whatsoever to make the Bazar Svobody a great success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
