<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-10-31">Oct. 31, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Ball of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_0544</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0544.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-10-31">Oct. 31, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE BALL OF THE CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As in previous years, the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) held its annual ball in the Pilsen Park pavilion. The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost is an organization which has acquired a most enviable reputation during its short existence. It is generally considered the best and noblest Bohemian organization in Chicago. Its membership consists of men and women who, in spite of the fact that their time is almost entirely taken up by their business and professional activities, devote a great deal of effort to the one all-important goal: helping their poor, needy, unfortunate, and sick countrymen.....</p>
   <p>No doubt it is its noble and humane purpose that has gained for the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost the great many members and friends whom we had an opportunity to meet at its splendid annual function last night. It has found friends not only among Bohemians, but also among most of the other nationalities represented in our great metropolis, and it has thousands of them.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0545.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They all view with a great deal of pleasure the work and the progress of this comparatively young organization which, in a very few years, has carried on so many worthwhile activities. Its non-Bohemian friends, and especially Americans of several generations, prove their interest by attending all of the functions of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost in large numbers, and by contributing more than a little to the Association's financial success.</p>
   <p>A great many friends attended yesterday's ball and joined our own people who came in really imposing numbers. Of course,it was a ball--just dancing, you may say. But it was blessed--for it was a means to a noble end.....</p>
   <p>As was mentioned above, the ball, the Association's third so far, was held in the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewing Company on 26th Street and Albany Avenue. But it was not the pavilion we know. Last night it appeared in a garb of truly magic beauty. The decorations night have been called somewhat melancholy, but they were in keeping with the season, when nature blends her red and orange foliage with the depressing yellow tones which harbinger the <pb facs="5418478_6_0546.jpg" n="3"/>impending transition to winter's deep quiet.....There were many flowers everywhere, even in the baskets carried by charming young ladies, who no doubt earned a pretty penny for the Spolecnost by their sales. Roses, carnations, and even some orchids in the men's buttonholes proved that a generous crowd had assembled.</p>
   <p>Equally successful were the ladies who undertook the task of selling chances on the many prizes exhibited on the platform. But the splendid gowns of the assembled ladies--trains, decoletages, silks, chiffons, diamonds, laces--and the men's "tails" and tuxedos did not prevent the crowd from enjoying a most informal fellowship long before the dance music began. The music was provided and directed by our well-known conductor, Mr. Rubringer. His orchestra of more than forty men played--with the permission of the Chicago Federation of Musicians--for this charitable enterprise entirely free of charge.</p>
   <p>But our readers should not be worried if we have conveyed the impression that everything was "high-toned" that night. There were also quite a number of <pb facs="5418478_6_0547.jpg" n="4"/>unsophisticated, simple citizens with no "boiled" shirts, just in plain, everyday jackets, and they, too, had a good time. Nobody was in anybody's way, and everybody tried to spend a few happy hours--and they stayed all night!</p>
   <p>Shortly before 11 P. M., the "grand march" began. It was led by Judge Joseph Z. Uhlir, and ended behind the festively decorated tables, which were soon loaded to capacity with tasty dishes served by the ladies of the organization.</p>
   <p>Among non-Bohemian dignitaries attending yesterday's ball were Governor Charles Deneen, Coroner Hoffman, Sheriff Zimmer, Judges Walker, Gemmill, Blake, Himes, Cottrell, Scully, Trude, Rooney, Courtney; the progressive candidate for the office of coroner, Dr. Napieralski, and many other candidates for various offices without distinction as to political party. Of the many Bohemian politicians and public officials, almost every one was present.</p>
   <p>Finally a word about the ball committee: It consisted of all the present officers of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, and all of them had plenty to do.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_0548.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>But they did it very well indeed, and they can be fully satisfied with the result. The ball has no doubt contributed a generous amount to the Association's treasury.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
