<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-03-11">Mar. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Cesko Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1577</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1577.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-03-11">Mar. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">CESKO AMERICKA NARODNI RADA (BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN NATIONAL COUNCIL)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A promising step toward its realization was taken yesterday through its organizer, E. St. Vraz. The Bohemian-American National Council, as explained by its organizer, Mr. E. St. Vraz, in a meeting held in Pilsen Sokol hall yesterday, will be an organization having a colossal signification for our national life. Therefore, it is not strange that thus far its organization has not been completed, only a few of the foundation stones for its creation have been laid. Chief among these are the interest and enthusiasm which the organizer aroused among those present for this grand institution.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by Mr. Vraz in the presence of a group of sincere patriots, who not only by words, but by deeds also, propose <pb facs="5418478_6_1578.jpg" n="2"/>to work for the realization of this great idea. Mr. Vraz extended a warm welcome to all present, and announced that besides those present, many others had sent their written agreement with this work, excusing themselves for being absent because of participation in other meetings.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vraz, who already has worked several months on the organization of the Bohemian-American National Council, announced that branches have already been established in New York, Cleveland, and Omaha, from whence a telegram was received yesterday, stating that officers had been elected and the branch put upon a firm foundation. Cedar Rapids, St. Paul, Baltimore, and other cities, also are seeking branches. Aside from these, individuals in smaller towns are also applying for positions as trustees, who want to cooperate in the activities of the Council. He said that the work is progressing satisfactorily, that understanding is appearing everywhere, even though there are doubters here and there, which could hardly be expected to be otherwise. All local newspapers, <pb facs="5418478_6_1579.jpg" n="3"/>with the exception of one labor paper and one weekly, and newspapers from out-of-town, brought sympathetic reports about this movement. However, there are thousands of people who are hoping for the realization of the organization of the Bohemian-American National Council, and look toward this realization with enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian-American National Council will not be a branch of the Bohemian National Council in Prague, but will be an independent body, whose purpose will be the building and fostering of the patriotic characteristics of Bohemian-Americans, so that we can profess our attachment for our kind as a single body.</p>
   <p>Neither will it be merely a big society, which would seek to gain a large number of members, but an organization, in which all will work toward the good of Bohemian-Americans which will be systematically centered. If only so much can be achieved, if in every town, twentyfour <pb facs="5418478_6_1580.jpg" n="4"/>capable patriotic men should meet once each month to talk over national needs, a great work will be done.</p>
   <p>With what interest, the steps for the realization of the organization of the Bohemian-American National Council are looked upon by the Bohemian National Council in Prague is shown by the characteristic communication which Mr. Vraz read and commented upon. In the motherland, they welcome our efforts with enthusiasm, and hope sincerely that with the founding of this organization, our contacts with the old country will be renewed, at the same time they are promising, that they will make efforts to correct the mistakes which they made in regard to us.</p>
   <p>Mention is also made in this communication of the introduction of patriotic discipline in this country, to which the organizer added that although we do not have it here as yet, perhaps the time will <pb facs="5418478_6_1581.jpg" n="5"/>come when every American-Czech will learn what his duty is, and will endeavor to live up to it. The realization of our organization is looked upon, as in the communication from the Bohemian National Council, with confidence. It is said here that the future will show how important a role our organization will play in our lives. It will mean the fullest expansion and culmination of Bohemina-American life, and we look toward this with longing.</p>
   <p>A letter from the secretary of the Bohemian National Council also was read, in which are pointed out the many doubts which existed about the success of the organization at the time of its foundation in the mother-country, and the great significance acquired by it in a few years. The secretary asks that the Bohemian-American National Council join with the Bohemian National Council, whereby it would certainly gain in significance, and its independence would in no way suffer therefrom. He also makes mention of financial means, and recommends that necessary <pb facs="5418478_6_1582.jpg" n="6"/>funds be not obtained by collections, because protests about collections would ensue, but through subscriptions from members and friends.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian-American National Council is to serve so that national sentiment and race consciousness will rise. It may become a branch of the Bohemian National Council, but here in America it will work independently.</p>
   <p>"Our work will be quiet, peaceful, and moral. We will not move mountains, but will work there, where our work, our encouragement, and our support are needed. For that reason, I cannot understand how some papers could say that we want to perform miracles," said the organizer. We will not need much money for our work, but nevertheless, some money is necessary.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian-American National Council will probably be organized along the same lines as the Bohemian National Council, which is made up of <pb facs="5418478_6_1583.jpg" n="7"/>members and active bodies in the cities, and trustees in the smaller communities. This organization will devote its time to spiritual and deliberative work. Its task will be to oversee the workers on our national field, to review the work of the past, and advise what should take place in the future, and to see to it that the work everywhere goes on systematically and with a purpose. The organization is to have various departments, each of which will have only one certain branch of work to look after, and be able to properly do so. Among these for example are the following:</p>
   <p>The publicity department, which will be one of the most important. That the Bohemian-American Press Bureau should join the Council as such a department has been thought of, and the Press Bureau at its meeting resolved to join the Council as soon as it is requested to do so.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1584.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>A department for immigrants, which would look after their interests and see to it that every immigrant became familiar with conditions in this country.</p>
   <p>A department on societies, to be composed of delegates from benevolent and welfare, gymnastic, singing, amateur theatrical, workingmen's societies, etc. This department will have the care of maintaining contacts with all representative societies, and in case of need, advise and encourage them. In cases of national celebrations, to see to it that they demonstrate their full strength and significance.</p>
   <p>The department for enlightenment will sponsor lectures, establish libraries, and reading rooms, and work with every possible means to elevate the already enlightened horizon of the Bohemian people in America.</p>
   <p>The department for youth will endeavor to unite Bohemian-American youth <pb facs="5418478_6_1585.jpg" n="9"/>into a representative society.</p>
   <p>The industrial department will be composed of Bohemian industrialists who will take care of the expansion of Bohemian industry.</p>
   <p>The department for business will advance the expansion of Bohemian business.</p>
   <p>The department for agriculture, composed of specialists, will act as adviser to people who wish to become farmers, acquainting them with conditions in various parts of the country.</p>
   <p>All told, the Bohemian-American National Council will have about twelve active departments, at the head of which will be experts. From these departments, will emanate initiative and encouragement to strenghten activities wherever need indicates. In that manner, the Bohemian-American <pb facs="5418478_6_1586.jpg" n="10"/>National Council will become the center and mirror of our whole national, social, enlightened, economic, industrial, and business life.</p>
   <p>This organization will not be concerned so much with a large number of members, but rather with good workers, so that its work will not be hindered by untimely and poorly thought over ideas. It is to be a central body, but nevertheless, embracing all branches.</p>
   <p>The organization of the Bohemian-American National Council is not concerned merely with organizing just another society, but with the concentration of strength and activities.</p>
   <p>During the meeting, a debate arose in regard to the manner in which the necessary money is to be obtained, but because there were so many different ideas exchanged on the matter, nothing definite was done, <pb facs="5418478_6_1587.jpg" n="11"/>and the matter will be discussed again at the next meeting.</p>
   <p>In view of the fact that the program of the Bohemian-American National Council is so far-reaching, it was resolved to publish it in condensed form, so that societies and the public in general can become thoroughly familiar with it. To take care of this, a committee of five members was chosen, composed of Messrs. E. Stan. Vraz, J. R. Psenka, Professor J. Zmrhal, Miss Suster, and Dr. Ant. Miller.</p>
   <p>It was then resolved to hold the next meeting on the last Friday of this month, March 31, when there will not be any lodge meetings, and anyone interested in the Bohemian-American National Council will be able to attend.</p>
   <p>Thirty-five participants and delegates from lodges presented themselves as members at yesterday's meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1588.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Before adjournment of this meeting, several people, enthused over the course of the meeting, spoke in favor of the movement, whereupon Mr. Vraz thanked them for their participation and urged those present to go to work so that this patriotic work may become a reality in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
