<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-04-14">Apr. 14, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">For the Benefit of Immigrants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1493</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1493.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-04-14">Apr. 14, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE BENEFIT OF IMMIGRANTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is generally known to our public that the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) addressed an appeal to Congressman and chairman of the Appropriations Committee John F. Fitzgerald in favor of the bill introduced by the Bohemian Congressman Adolf J. Sabath, which provides for the establishment of a $75,000 immigration station in Chicago. The purpose of this proposed station is principally one of human kindness; and when it is established, it will keep the immigrants under federal protection until the time when they arrive at their destination, or until they are taken care of by their friends. In this way their exploitation by sharpers and unscrupulous agents, as well as white slavers, will be prevented. The Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada, fully aware of the importance of such an institution for our incoming countrymen, has sent a letter to Congressman Fitzgerald urging him to support the request for the necessary appropriation. Congressman Fitzgerald replied a few days ago with a letter reading as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1494.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Mr. E. St. Vraz,</p>
   <p>"Chairman of the Executive Committee, Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada,</p>
   <p>"Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir, I acknowledge herewith the receipt of your letter of April 1, 1912, concerning Bill H. R. 21220 which deals with the establishment of a federal immigration station in Chicago. I assure you that it will be my pleasure to give this matter all such consideration as it deserves.</p>
   <p>"Sincerely yours, John F. Fitzgerald."</p>
   <p>It should be mentioned that the branches of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada in many other cities in the United States have also addressed letters to the Appropriations Committee similar to the one sent from Chicago, and it is therefore to be hoped that Congressman Sabath's bill will soon be passed. It would not be amiss, however, if the Appropriations Committee would receive <pb facs="5418478_6_1495.jpg" n="3"/>additional appeals, particularly from the main offices of our benevolent societies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
