<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-10-28">Oct. 28, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Second Anniversary of the Czechoslovak Republic</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czechoslovaks of Chicago Celebrate Anniversary of the Liberation of Our Nation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1739</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1739.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-10-28">Oct. 28, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE SECOND ANNIVERSARY OF THE CZECHOSLOVAK REPUBLIC</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czechoslovaks of Chicago Celebrate Anniversary of the Liberation of Our Nation</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The thoughts of the Czechoslovak people of Chicago and Czechoslovak settlements of America today will be carried away to our far-away old homeland. With love and enthusiasm we shall recall October 28, 1918, the most significant and the most glorious day of our nation.</p>
   <p>The young Czechoslovak Republic is celebrating the Twenty-eighth of October, a national holiday, with the same fervor and enthusiasm as the Fourth of July is celebrated in our new homeland. The people of Czechoslovak origin who celebrate the anniversary of American Independence with patriotic enthusiasm will recall with the same feeling of true and generous patriotism the never-to-be-forgotten Twenty-eighth of October when a great historical document was signed in Paris, France.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1740.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>at that time Professor Thomas Garrique Masaryk, General Milan R. Stefanik, and Dr. Eduard Benes, in the name of the temporary government, said that "we hereby proclaim the Hapsburg dynasty unworthy of leading our nation, and we reject all its claims to rule the Czechoslovak countries, the people of which we hereby proclaim as members of a free nation. We hereby accept and hold fast to the ideals of modern democracy, because those have been the ideals of our nation for many centuries. We accept those principles proposed by President Wilson--principles of liberated mankind, actual equality of nations, and governments obtaining their just power by the confirmation of those who are governed.</p>
   <p>"We, the nation of Komensky (Jan Amos Commenius), cannot but accept these principles--principles that are manifested in the American Declaration of Independence, principles of Abraham Lincoln, and the proclamation of the rights of a man and of a citizen."</p>
   <p>In Czechoslovakia the Twenty-eighth of October is celebrated as a most <pb facs="5418478_6_1741.jpg" n="3"/>significant national holiday, because on that day the freedom of our nation was born. All the American Bohemians and Slovaks who proudly make known their origin, consider this day as significant as the Fourth of July, and with real love they look toward the young Republic. They are rejoicing that after a period of depression brought about by the war, after two years of internal struggles, a better and happier future is nearing. She withstood the storms of the first two years, and the Czechoslovak people of America cannot wish anything better for their liberated native land than that this coming third year of independence should bring a contentedness to all classes of people of the nation, a full economic growth, and the long-desired prosperity.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak people of Chicago will celebrate the second anniversary of the Czechoslovak independence at two festivals, and there is no doubt that both of these patriotic meetings will be attended by large throngs of Czechoslovak people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
