<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-14">Apr. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation of the Cicero Branch of the Czechoslovak National Alliance of America.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_6_1104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_6_1104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-14">Apr. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION OF THE CICERO BRANCH OF THE CZECHOSLOVAK NATIONAL ALLIANCE OF AMERICA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In view of the fact that recent attacks have been made against several workers and officers of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe (Czechoslovak National Alliance of America), by people, who by all manner of means are striving to remove these persons from their offices, even though our people know not why; because among those attacked is a member of our branch, brother Frank J. Kubec, the Cicero branch of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, resolved at its meeting held on April 12, to proclaim the following:</p>
   <p>"Brother Frank J. Kubec, a member of the Cicero branch of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, was lawfully elected as our representative to the District Committee of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe by the majority of our members. Any of our Bohemian people who followed the activity and work of brother Frank J. Kubec, done in or out of our branch since the year 1915, must have noticed the magnitude of his work and activity leading to a point of exhaustion. He worked and sacrificed himself as much as possible in <pb facs="5418478_6_1105.jpg" n="2"/>order to reach our goal. Now that at last the goal--liberation of our nation from the yoke of tyrants--has been attained, comes the reward: They are seeking to remove brother Frank J. Kubec from his office, but the reason why this should be desired, is not made clear. Perhaps simply for the reason that now, after the work has been done, someone who did not exert himself much for our cause would like to repose on the laurels! We will never let it come to pass that he, who, so honestly worked for our goal, who, because of his efforts, gained many friends among our well-meaning Bohemians, be condemned and humiliated, that he be asked to resign his office by a few individuals who are not members of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v America and who do not have the right to judge our member brother Frank J. Kubec. Therefore, we wish it to be known that brother Frank J. Kubec is supported by a great majority of the members of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v America. We wish, and insist upon, that Frank J. Kubec continue to keep his office, because he was honored by our confidence and by the confidence of those who elected him as president of the District Committee of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v America. Here individual <pb facs="5418478_6_1106.jpg" n="3"/>wish does not decide; here the wishes and confidence of the majority decide; here speak clearly the activities and work of our brother Frank J. Kubec, of whom the Cicero branch of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe is justly proud."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
