<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Volume V. <date when="1912">1912</date>, No. 3.
<title level="a">Olive Oil, Free of Duty!!!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0316</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0316.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Volume V. <date when="1912">1912</date>, No. 3.
<title level="a">OLIVE OIL, FREE OF DUTY!!!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. L. E. Schoenfeld, member of our Chamber, has written a letter to the Honorable James R. Mann, congressman of the 2nd Congressional District of Chicago. Mr. Schoenfeld is one of our most active members and one of his greatest hobbies is olive oil. Not only is he sending this letter to the congressman of this district, but he is working on a great petition signed by all the importers and dealers of olive oil, which will be sent to the Tariff Commission. The following is the letter:</p>
   <p>To The Honorable James R. Mann,</p>
   <p>Congressman, 2nd Congressional District,</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>Enclosed you will find an extract from my article, "Foreign Olive Oil," <pb facs="5425702_2_0317.jpg" n="2"/>published in the Bulletin of the Italian Chamber of Commerce, April, 1912.</p>
   <p>The logical deduction of this article is that there is no reason whatever why such a high rate of duty on olive oil should be appraised!</p>
   <p>To protect the home industry? California does not produce today 10 per cent of the total amount of olive oil imported into this country</p>
   <p>California will not be able to produce 20 per cent of the total demand of olive oil in 1925.</p>
   <p>The only logical reason for keeping an exorbitant high tariff on this article is to aid a very few growers toenrich themselves at the expense of the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0318.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Olive oil is a necessary food, as necessary as bread, meat or sugar. It is also one of the principal drugs. Doctors prescribe it daily.</p>
   <p>Why force the people to pay a higher rate of duty than the rich pay for diamonds, pearls and other luxuries, or force those of us, who cannot afford to pay the high price for olive oil, to use drying oils detrimental to the system.</p>
   <p>Your Honor, I believe that this is one of the greatest injustices of our protective tariff, and I appeal to you as the representative of my congressional district to take the initiative, and use your great influence to either enter olive oil on the free list, or reduce the rate so as to put this necessary food and drug in the home of even the poorest individual.</p>
   <p>Yours truly,</p>
   <p>L. E. Schoenfeld.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
