<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-01-10">Jan. 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Infiltration of the Black-Frocked Sect into the Hull House</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-01-10">Jan. 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE INFILTRATION OF THE BLACK-FROCKED SECT INTO THE HULL HOUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Until yesterday we believed, with many others, that this philanthropic institution called Hull House was really a "free institution" as some ladies like to call it.</p>
   <p>We are sorry to say that we have made a mistake. We have lost our illusion since it was openly told to us that Hull House does not want to sever the friendship with the Bishop of this Diocese of the Roman Catholic Church by allowing admittance to anti-clericals. I was commissioned by the Club Giordano Bruno, of which I am a member, to rent Bowen Hall, in Hull House. The club planned to hold an affair in that hall in commemoration of "February 17," in honor of the great martyr for whom the club is named. I went to Hull House to carry out my commission. I was told that Miss J. Addams was sorry to refuse the use of the hall to the club, but the Catholics of Hull House were against the club and would not tolerate its presence. Because Hull House has classes in which aliens are taught to read and write, and classes <pb facs="5425702_2_0566.jpg" n="2"/>in manual training for the young; because they sponsor a strong philanthropic organization known as the "Juvenile Protection Association;" because they have a public library branch, open every day; a theater which is rented to anyone; several meeting rooms also rented to anyone; because many organizers of foreign groups are taking advantage of these opportunities and are always using Hull House whenever they feel like it; and because Hull House is located near the foreign colonies in order to help and lead the newly arrived immigrants seeking an education and a better life; for these reasons, priests (with or without the white collar) are trying hard to control activities in Hull House and promulgate their ideas. This infiltration of the clergy was a subtle task which took a long time but was in the end successful.</p>
   <p>And now that they are in (allow us to say so, mesdames of the Hull House), yours is no more a free institution, because no institution in the world can be free under the domination of the clergy. Is it necessary to quote history? You have studied and are supplied with a vast background of culture, experience and knowledge. It seems to me that the experience of 18 centuries has taught <pb facs="5425702_2_0567.jpg" n="3"/>you nothing, because not only do you tolerate the imposition of the Roman Church in your home, but you also take it in good humor. Your resolutions have changed with the years. Where has your liberal spirit gone--that spirit that urged you to erect Hull House on Halsted Street, among the foreigners, in order to help them?</p>
   <p>I am speaking to you, most distinguished and venerable Mesdames Addams and Starr, to you who pretend to be liberals and progressives, to you who are very cultured and who should remember what shameful infamies the Roman Catholic Church has perpetrated; the most atrocious crimes which history records. You naively believe that the Church may reform itself, and for that reason you acknowledge it. You believe that it is necessary for the people to have a religion, but you will soon realize that the Roman Catholic Church is not a religious institution, but a political party.</p>
   <p>Behold, your effort at the beginning was commendable, because you had good intentions, and in good faith accepted persons of any religious or political creed; you tolerated everything and everybody. But now that the priests are among you and the Church is imposing its will upon you, you no longer <pb facs="5425702_2_0568.jpg" n="4"/>tolerate what the Church refuses to tolerate and you accept the impositions of certain bigots who influence you.</p>
   <p>The priests told you that the Club Giordano Bruno is not constructive--but destructive toward what the Church has built.</p>
   <p>Some fanatic women have told you that the Giordano Bruno Association of Rome is fomenting hatred against the Roman Catholic Church, and that the Club Giordano Bruno of Chicago is affiliated with this association, thus it is to be dreaded and driven out from Hull House. You believe and accept the tale without any personal investigation or without making any effort to seek the truth.</p>
   <p>Well, you did wrong, because they have deceived you. The members of the Giordano Bruno Association of Rome, Chicago, or elsewhere, are not fomenting hatred, nor are they criminals or fanatics. They are all men who are interested in the welfare of humanity.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0569.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The organization which has fomented hatred among men and still is doing so, is the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
   <p>They said that our Club is destructive rather than constructive. But--please--explain what it is that we may destroy or construct?</p>
   <p>It is true, we want to destroy, but what we want to destroy is superstition, that insolent fanaticism and damaging fear of eternal punishment, which the Church, for her own profit, has throughout the centuries impressed on the minds of the people; yes, we want to destroy. We want to destroy the darkness created by the ignorance in which humanity is kept by the Church.</p>
   <p>We will construct afterwards, little by little, strong consciences in the breasts of free men, and we will make them free to believe in God as they see fit, if they want to believe in some God.</p>
   <p>Is it unjust to quote history for evidence of infamies perpetrated by the Church or others?</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0570.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>And if we find history tell us that the Roman Church has been tyrannical, cruel, and unjust, is it our fault?</p>
   <p>But your informers are bigots and fanatics and that is why they hate us.</p>
   <p>Soon the Bishop will tell you to refuse the use of the Hull House to the Jewish people, then to the Protestants, and you will obey--in order to keep his friendship.</p>
   <p>If you accept my "suggestion," you will avoid many troubles in the future, and besides, you will get not only the friendship, but even the blessing of the Bishop.</p>
   <p>Place a Crucifix over every door of Hull House, and in place of the Stars and Stripes, wave the flag of the Pope.</p>
   <p>Hull House will then be frequented only by clericals, and you will not be <pb facs="5425702_2_0571.jpg" n="7"/>compelled to say what you have said to me, "I am sorry but you cannot enter here. Rome does not permit it."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
