<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1908-11-21">Nov. 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Employment Agencies - the Guilty and Their Victims</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1908-11-21">Nov. 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">EMPLOYMENT AGENCIES - THE GUILTY AND THEIR VICTIMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sometime in last September a crew of forty-five men was shipped from Chicago by Andrea Filippis and Giuseppe Renzino, employment agents. These men had been engaged for a job which was supposed to last through the entire winter, at the daily wage of $1.35. The employment agents exacted for themselves from $3 to $8 per individual. Accompanied by a slave-driving scoundrel who was supposed to act as interpreter, our laborers arrived on location and soon discovered that the job was limited to two weeks, and that the wages would be $1.25 a day instead of $1.35.</p>
   <p>The men got together and refused to work. However, not having enough money to return to Chicago, they decided to go to the nearest town in search of employment. Through this same renegade Italian known as their interpreter our friends were again engaged, and again they were forced to submit to the payment of $2 each, plus $11 more to be paid on their first pay-day! Moreover, when they reached their second location, they found that the job consisted of draining and leveling an awful swamp, in the depths of endless woods. Some of the men who were not encumbered with heavy luggage found a way to escape. I say escape because it was reported that they were watched by bosses armed with rifles and revolvers, including the slave-driver mentioned above.</p>
   <p>But the others regained their freedom only after paying in work, the sum of $11 <pb facs="5425702_2_0160.jpg" n="2"/>which they had pledged plus a charge for board which amounted to sixty or seventy cents per day.</p>
   <p>Some of these men were even forced to pay double in order to cover the fee pledged and the board-bill of those who had succeeded in escaping!</p>
   <p>Among the fugitives was Salvatore Accordi, who after defying the risk of being shot by the renegade Italian, Alfredo Martini, wandered for four days in the woods, living on grass and wild berries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
