<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy</title> in America - Illinois Lodge,
<date when="1936-01">January 1936</date>.
<title level="a">The Campaign for the Red Cross Is Still On. the Grand Venerable Makes Another Appeal</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0730</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0730.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy in America - Illinois Lodge</title>,
<date when="1936-01">January 1936</date>.
<title level="a">THE CAMPAIGN FOR THE RED CROSS IS STILL ON. THE GRAND VENERABLE MAKES ANOTHER APPEAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Sisters and Brothers:</p>
   <p>As you know, under date of December 5, 1935, I addressed to you a communication on behalf of the Italian Red Cross enclosing therein a subscription blank authorizing you to collect funds. In my letter I urged each and everyone of you to do your utmost for this worthy cause and to remit the contributions you would collect, either to the Venerable of your Lodge or to the office of the Grand Lodge.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0731.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>By December 15, last, we had received from the Venerables and members a number of subscription blanks with contributions totalling the sum of $3,541.70, which sum was on the same day in the name of the Order Sons of Italy in America turned over to Dr. Commandatore Mario Carosi, Royal Italian Consul General in Chicago. At the time this money was turned over to Commandatore Carosi, I assured him that this was merely the first donation on the part of the Order.</p>
   <p>Many of you have not as yet sent in to your Venerable or to the office of the Grand Lodge the subscription blank which was sent to you. I urge you, therefore, to do so not later than the 20th of this month, as I am anxious on that day to turn over the fruits of your efforts. I hope and trust that you will have collected by that time, if not already, something on behalf <pb facs="5425702_2_0732.jpg" n="3"/>of this noble cause. I want to also remind you that many pieces of gold, such as rings, earrings, and so forth, were collected by many of our members and turned over to the office of the Grand Lodge. I want you also to do all you can in this regard. The names of all who contribute either money, regardless of the amount, or gold, will be given due publicity. By all means do not forget to turn over the subscription blanks as we must account for each and everyone sent out. It is needless for me to remind you that you need contributions among members only, but in your list you may include any and all who desire to contribute to this humanitarian act on our part.</p>
   <p>In soliciting funds do not conclude that it is too late, or that everyone has contributed, because in the state of Illinois only about $30,000 has been collected so far and there are, in this state, more than a half million of our people. Futhermore, bear in mind that the fact that people have contributed does not mean that they should not contribute more and more.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0733.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Remember that our brothers in Africa are, in the name of justice, humanity and civilization, fighting for the glory of our mother country. It is our duty to help in whatever manner we can.</p>
   <p>Let me not fail to see your subscription blanks together with funds collected, at the office of the Grand Lodge by January 20, 1936.</p>
   <p>Spatuzza,</p>
   <p>Grand Venerable.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
