<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italian Chamber of Commerce in Chicago</title>,
<date when="1924-11">Nov. 1924</date>, Page 7.
<title level="a">The Great Celebration of the Chamber of Commerce</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0409</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0409.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italian Chamber of Commerce In Chicago</title>,
<date when="1924-11">Nov. 1924</date>, Page 7.
<title level="a">THE GREAT CELEBRATION OF THE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One thousand guests of the Italian Chamber of Commerce of Chicago met in the Hotel La Salle to commemorate the birthday of King Victor Emmanuel of Italy, Armistice Day and the (Fascist) March on Rome.</p>
   <p>All Italian societies were represented and many Americans of the business and art world of Chicago also attended. Italian Consul, Commendatore Zanini in the name of King Victor Emmanuel, presented the following decorations:</p>
   <p>Commendator of the Crown of Italy to Samuel Insull, Public Utilities Executive of Chicago; Giorgio Polacco, Art Director of the Chicago Civic Opera Company; Chevalier Official Pietro Cardiello, Italian Consul in Detroit; <pb facs="5425702_2_0410.jpg" n="2"/>the Cross of the Chevalier Official of the Crown of Italy to John M. Handley, publisher and secretary for the Italy-America Society; and the Cross of the Chevalier of the Crown of Italy to the prominent businessman, Mr. Barto Chiappe.</p>
   <p>The main speakers of the evening were Commendator Zanini and Commendator di Silvestri, Supreme Venerable, Order Sons of Italy in America.</p>
   <p>The banquet was followed by a dance, Maestro Luigi Quaglia and his orchestra supplying the music. Telegrams of congratulation were sent to King Victor Emmanuel and the Honorable Mussolini.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
