<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1915-01-24">January 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Generous Contributions from the Colony for Italian Victims of the Earthquake</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0975</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0975.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1915-01-24">January 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GENEROUS CONTRIBUTIONS FROM THE COLONY FOR ITALIAN VICTIMS OF THE EARTHQUAKE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Answering to the appeal given by the Italian Chamber of Commerce to the Italian societies, about fifty conationals assembled at a meeting held Wednesday night in the Sherman Hotel, for the purpose of forming a committee to raise funds for the victims of the earthquake.</p>
   <p>Even though the meeting was not attended by a large number, we have united the most efficient forces of the colony, for the work which will raise assistance for the quake victims.</p>
   <p>After an appeal made by the Italian Consul Conte Bolegnesi in which he enlarged on the seriousness of the new catastrophe and the hopes of these ruined cities that the conationals solidly stand behind and help. A subscription was started, which resulted inmore than one thousand dollars being collected.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0976.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then they proceeded to the selection of the various committees.</p>
   <p>The Executive Committee consists of the following people:- Cav. Frank Cuneo, president, Cav. Dr. C. Voleni, first vice-president, Mr. B. P. Barasa, second vice-president, Cav. Dr. A. Lagorio, treasurer, Mr. A. Gualano, secretary and G. Rodighiero, assistant secretary. Consul Bolegnesi was chosen honorary president. Other committees formed to urge subscriptions in the Italian wards, are as follows:- Messers. Stefano Malato, C. Raggio, Oscar Durante, E. Longhi, G. Inalato, D. Baeci, Sam Tognotti, J. Bertelli, Pietro Costa, John Raggio, A. Mastrovalerio, J. Pellegrini, M. Mastrogiooanni, H. Lawton, R. Romano, J. B. Lavezzorio and the Reverends Cav. Gambera, Angelurci.</p>
   <p>It is our duty to help in this terrible misfortune that the Italian government is in. It has declared itself unwilling to accept any help from other governments.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0977.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And so it is up to us to offer our assistance to our unfortunate fatherland. Let us sacrifice something that we can spare and let us give where it will do the most good.</p>
   <p>The first list of subscribers have raised $1,265.00.</p>
   <p>The money given by those who subscribed was sent last Thursday morning to the Central Committee of the Italian Red Cross. The money was sent by cable money order through the Fort Dearborn National Bank. All contributions to be sent to Italy from the Consul's office, may be sent without charge.</p>
   <p>The Italian Women's Welfare Society always ready to give a helping hand, has sent a check of fifty dollars to the executive committee treasury.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0978.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the meantime,other societies have planned to hold meetings the first week of the month also for the purpose of raising funds. Private individuals are also prepared to do their duty.</p>
   <p>The concert to be given at the Colliseum under the direction of Mr. M. Ferullo, will be a benefit performance, and Mr. M. Petrini has also offered his band gratis.</p>
   <p>A great sentiment of brotherhood has developed in the hearts of the Italians following this new disaster in our fatherland, and each one feels that it is his duty to give whatever he can to his suffering countrymen.</p>
   <p>Lawyer Barasa is doing all he can to have one day set aside as Italian tag day to help the unfortunates in Italy in this economic misfortune. Mean-while, the distribution of subscription blanks for the collecting of funds has been started. The Executive Committee informs us that the only blanks authorized by it are those that carry the seal of the Italian Consul of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
