<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1919-03">March, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Illinois Affirms Italian Rights in Dalmatia</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0891</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0891.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1919-03">March, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ILLINOIS AFFIRMS ITALIAN RIGHTS IN DALMATIA</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On February 5th, the Legislature in Springfield approved the following resolution introduced by the Honorable Charles Coia.</p>
   <p>House Joint Resolution No. 5.</p>
   <p>Whereas, the Allied Powers associated with the United States are assembled in conference for the purpose of drafting terms of peace affecting the settlement of various questions arising our of the World War; and for the purpose of drafting agreements affecting the rights of the nations involved in said war; and for the purpose of readjusting conditions brought about by the war, relative to those nations whose people are either subject to or whose national integrity has been endangered by the autocratic powers responsible for the war, and</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0892.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whereas, in addition to the sympathy and interest which the people of the United States of America have shown for Italy as an ally, there is a sentimental interest in Italy because she was the mother of modern civilization, and because she is the birthplace of Christopher Columbus, who discovered America; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, Italy has fought with heroism and great sacrifice since its entry in-to the war, and has done its share in bringing about the great victory of the Allies; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, Italy is making claims at the Peace Conference for the restoration of certain lands and territory formerly belonging to her, and for lands and territory necessary for her economic needs, and national security and preservation; now therefore</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0893.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Be it resolved, by the House of Representatives of the State of Illinois, and Senate concurring herein, that the Representatives of the people of the United States at the Peace Conference be requested to exercise their influence to bring about a just consideration of the claims of the Italian Government for the restoration of its lands and territory, and be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, that these resolutions shall be spread on record in the journal of the General Assembly of the State of Illinois, and that a copy of the same, properly attested with the great seal of the State and signed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives, the Secretary of State and the Governor of Illinois be forwarded to the Presidents of the United States and to the Representatives of the United States at the Peace Conference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
