<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1936-02">February, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">The (I. A. N. U.) President's Message at 40th Anniversary Banquet. February 2nd, 1936</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1936-02">February, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">THE (I. A. N. U.) PRESIDENT'S MESSAGE AT 40TH ANNIVERSARY BANQUET. FEBRUARY 2ND, 1936</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two score years ago our society was conceived by a small group of Italian immigrants, who came to this distant land of promise in search of fame and fortune.</p>
   <p>Strangers in a new world of people of many tongues and customs, longing for their dear ones and their ancestral home from which they were separated by thousands of miles of ocean, they were soon confronted with the hardships common to all immigrants, who came during the turbulent boom period of the early nineties; especially those who ventured as far as the Middle West which, even to the native eastern Americans, seemed to be one of the last frontiers.</p>
   <p>Their difficulties accentuated their nostalgia; their contacts with the heterogeneous people of the United States made them conscious of the wonderfully rich historical heritage which was theirs; their daily social and business dealings with other nationalities, who were practicing the same natural tendencies, made them realize the keen necessity, that they, too, must unite with their compatriots for their mutual assistance and protection and <pb facs="5425702_2_0335.jpg" n="2"/>preservation.</p>
   <p>As we look back on nearly half a century of achievement we feel, with a just sense of pride, that we have lived up to the high ideals, concepts, and tenets laid down by the founders of our society; that we have unequivocally practiced Liberty, Equality, Fraternity, Unity, Strength, and Protection. We feel also, that our motto, "God and Country," has spurred us to carry on, in a sincerely Christian and genuinely patriotic spirit, the good work of true brotherhood; that during these years our generous helpfulness has been accorded to our less fortunate brothers, and all needy people both here and abroad, and that our assistance and comfort has greatly helped, morally and materially, to ease the sorrow and want of widows and orphans of those who have departed from us.</p>
   <p>We do not deem it essential to quote the actual figures of the several thousands of dollars which our society has contributed for charitable and welfare purposes, nor of the nearly two million dollars in claims we have paid, nor even of the several millions of dollars of insurance in force on our books. Figures and statistical tabulations are unromantic and are only interesting to a technical mind.</p>
   <p>But we deem it necessary that the "Italo-American National Union" being based <pb facs="5425702_2_0336.jpg" n="3"/>on a scientific and thoroughly modern insurance foundation, be replete potential possibilities for the good of our people. What shall we do to develop these great possibilities? The answer is: Bring in the young people. Every organization, from the family to the nation, must have a sufficient flow of young blood to assure its continuity, therefore, since the usual replenishment of a society like ours is no longer possible, because of the restrictive immigration measures, we must enroll the children of our members and their offspring.</p>
   <p>To those who have contributed to the past success of our society, we express our deepest sense of appreciation; to the ones who will cooperate with us in our future progress, we extend our sincere thanks.</p>
   <p>Our growth can be assured, only, if we work together with one objective in mind. Let us strive to do in 1936 even better than the good work we accomplished in 1935.</p>
   <p>Let us persevere always in doing the things that reflect honor to ourselves, our family, our country, our "Italo-American National Union."</p>
   <p>P. L. D'Andrea, Supreme President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
