<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1904-02-06">Feb. 6, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">False Accusation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1904-02-06">Feb. 6, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">FALSE ACCUSATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are happy to report that Dr. Re who had been accused of selling alcohol without placing the 'Poison' label on the bottle, was declared not guilty by Coroner Treager who officiated at the inquest into the death of five negroes who died from having drunk wood-alcohol supposedly bought in Dr. Re's drug store located at 438 Dearborn Street.</p>
   <p>The American papers of this city conscientiously reported the arrest of Dr. Re and the charge for which he was held for the inquest, but failed to mention the coroner's verdict.</p>
   <p>The story as reported: A negro had gone into Dr. Re's drug-store and had bought from a fourteen year old boy who is employed there, a bottle of alcohol on which the boy did not place the 'Poison' label. When he arrived at his home, the negro was joined by four friends, and together they drank the alcohol. They were soon in terrible pain. The result: four died that same day and the fifth two days later. Dr. Re was held for the inquest.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0166.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the inquest Dr. Re was able to prove that neither he nor the boy had sold the negro any alcehol. Further investigation completely cleared Dr. Re and his employe of negligence. It was brought out that the negro had gotten the alcohol from his landlord's home, where he had gone to do some repair work, not knowing that it was wood alcohol, a deadly poison.</p>
   <p>We are happy to report the exoneration of Dr. Re who is one of the best-liked residents of our colony, since it leaves the American press without any notice for its malign insinuations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
