<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1927-09">September, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Italo-American Millionaires Provoke Dangerous Dreams</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0655</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0655.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1927-09">September, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE ITALO-AMERICAN MILLIONAIRES PROVOKE DANGEROUS DREAMS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Prohibition, among other evils, has produced in the Italians the desire for emigrating to the United States. And this is natural. The 18th Amendment of our Constitution has rapidily enriched a large number of persons, who never even would have dreamed of saving a thousand dollar bill.</p>
   <p>Becoming bootleggers by profession, many have earned too much money and they are going back to Italy to pay visits to their home town where, with their diamonds and with their generosity in squandering the money, they are astounding their old friends and receiving great honor from the civic officials, instead of the frequent medals and distinction.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0656.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>You meet them in Rome, in Montecatini, in Viareggio, the Lido of Venice, Capri, Sorrento, etc. They are recognized as Americans, born in Italy, and soon everybody knows that money was easily earned. Naturally everyone wants to come to a country where by selling bad wine, and very bad liquor, poisoned alcohol and illegal beer, he can earn a large sum of money. For that reason we see the smuggling of immigrants increased and the relative deportation causing, not rarely, a tragedy.</p>
   <p>Almost every week the liners are taking back to Europe those, who, lured by easy fortune, which they were to gain in the United States came in with fake passports. Today, as we did in times past, it is our duty to warn those who are trying to come to America, clandestinely, and dreaming of becoming rich like others, through violation of the prohibition law.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0657.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is wise to know, that though it is true that the 18th Amendment made some people rich, it is even more true to say that the era of the bootleggers has gone for ever. Those who earned large amounts of money in the prohibition era are retired from the business. Those still active in the bootlegging business do not want any competition and will not tolerate any intruders. They who wish to come to America for the purpose of imitating those whom they met in their home town of squandering money, are making a grave mistake.</p>
   <p>Even if they can stay in the United States, if they have money they will lose it, and if they try to intrude into the bootlegging business they will lose their life.</p>
   <p>Therefore be on the alert!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
