<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1930-03">March, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Banquet Given in Honor of the New Chevaliers</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0764</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0764.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1930-03">March, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">BANQUET GIVEN IN HONOR OF THE NEW CHEVALIERS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The banquet given in honor of the new Chevaliers, Dr. Italo Volini, Dr. Frank Lagorio, Edward Fiori, Maestro Vittorio Trevisan, Rev. Father Luigi Giambastiani and Rev. Father Luigi Valletto, was a huge success.</p>
   <p>On this occasion the Royal Consul General Dr. Castruccio presented them with their relative insignia. At the banquet which was held at the Sherman Hotel, the outstanding personalities of our colony were present. Besides the guest of honor, among those present were Dr. &amp; Mrs. Castruccio, Maestro Georgio Palacco, Chevalier Dell Agnol, Vice Consul; Chevalier &amp; Mrs. Ferme, and the new Chevaliers already named.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0765.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Adrogna, our president, acted as toastmaster and the official speaker was Dr. Castruccio, Consul General who, revealing himself as a master orator, recalled and praised highly the merits of the newly decorated gentlemen.</p>
   <p>The Grand Officer, Dr. Antonio Lagorio, the oldest Italian physician residing in Chicago, impressed the audience when in his speech he recalled the memory of his deceased friend the senior Dr. Volini, with whom he was decorated four times by the Italian Government. He is proud to see that their children are following in their foot steps.</p>
   <p>Dr. Italo Volini, in the name of his friends, thanked everyone for the honor conferred upon them.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0766.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mrs. Cavadore, Mr. Boveri and Blanchard Selfridge rendered some operatic selections. The musical program of the evening was under the leadership of Maestro De Rosa.</p>
   <p>The banquet was followed by a dance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
