<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1921-03">March, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Extraordinary Session of the Commission Imports and Exports. April 22, 1921</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0284</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0284.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1921-03">March, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">EXTRAORDINARY SESSION OF THE COMMISSION IMPORTS AND EXPORTS. APRIL 22, 1921</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The session opens at 8 p. m. President De Nictolis explains the purpose of this meeting. A proposal has been made to send a telegram to Boise Penrose, chairman of the House Finance Committee, and to the Honorables McKinley and McCormick, Senators to Congress from Illinois protesting against the Emergency Bill 2435.</p>
   <p>Messrs. Gallagher and Frost explain proposed bill to the members present. After some discussion it was decided to send a telegram.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0285.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>April 22, 1921.</p>
   <p>We beg to address you on the subject of House Bill 2435.</p>
   <p>The claim has been made that an undue advantage is accruing to importers of foreign goods on account of the depreciation of the currency in the country of origin of the merchandise they deal in, which it is claimed causes the cost of such merchandise to be extremely low. We take the liberty to enter our protest against this claim at least at to importations from Italy and to deny the truth of the same, because the present prices paid in American money by the importers of Italian notwithstanding the depreciation of Italian currency are much higher for the same goods than they were before the war.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0286.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We emphatically deny that there is any dumping on this or any other market of Italian goods. On the contrary owing to limited production, lack of raw materials and other reasons Italian goods are slow and difficult to obtain and Italy is still at present a seller's market. We strongly protest against the paragraph providing that the depreciation in currency shall not be estimated at more than sixty-six and two-thirds per centum; this limitation in addition to the present very high prices of Italian merchandise would be equivalent to laying an embargo against importations from Italy.</p>
   <p>Board of Directors,</p>
   <p>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce.</p>
   <p>(The above telegram transcribed from original English text.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
