<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1929-06">June, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Customs Question of America and the Italian Chamber of Commerce of Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1929-06">June, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE CUSTOMS QUESTION OF AMERICA AND THE ITALIAN CHAMBER OF COMMERCE OF CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italian Chamber of Commerce, which is very much interested in the Customs Question and on the project introduced to the House of Representatives for the approval, sent to the Representatives and Senators of Illinois the following letter with a copy of the report made, last March, by the Italian Chamber of Commerce of New York:</p>
   <p>Sir:</p>
   <p>This Association, incorporated under the laws of the State of Illinois and whose membership is chiefly composed of American citizens interested in trade relations with Italy, respectfully requests your attention to the briefs submitted by the Italian Chamber of Commerce in New York to the Committee on <pb facs="5425702_2_0245.jpg" n="2"/>Ways and Means of the House on the subject of Tariff revision, a copy of which we are sending you under separate cover.</p>
   <p>We fully endorse the conclusions of those briefs and concur in them, and we further beg to express our opinion that the bill known as H. R. 2667 now under discussion in the House does not represent the limited revision of the Tariff advocated by the President, but is rather intended to build a wall against all outside trade by providing on many articles rates of duties so high as to be altogether unnecessary for the legitimate protection of American labor and industry.</p>
   <p>No country, however, large and powerful, can suffice to itself in erecting such a wall, for if we wish to sell our goods to foreign countries, we cannot shut them entirely, or nearly so, out of our markets, and we must be prepared to let them pay for at least a part of what they buy from us by taking some <pb facs="5425702_2_0246.jpg" n="3"/>of their products in exchange. The bill referred to, if enacted into law will make it extremely difficult to do so, and therefore will be detrimental to the interests and welfare of this country.</p>
   <p>We specifically and particularly object to the provision of Section 336.</p>
   <p>(a) Change of classification of duties.</p>
   <p>(b) Change to American selling price.</p>
   <p>And to subsections of Section 402 having reference to the determination of the so called "United States value" and "American selling price." We strongly recommend that all provisions for an American valuation be altogether done away with on account of the exorbitant increase in the rate of duties which would generally result from such valuation, the difficulty in determining it and applying it and especially the element of uncertainty that it would introduce <pb facs="5425702_2_0247.jpg" n="4"/>into business which would make the importation of merchandise well-nigh possible. We believe that when certain duties have been decided upon by Congress on a certain commodity they should remain as established for a reasonable period of time and not be subject to change from day to day.</p>
   <p>"We also beg to enter our protest against subsection (B) of Section 402 providing for the finality of the Appraiser's decision, subject only to that of the Secretary of the Treasury and without recourse to the United States Customs Court as at present and in the past; we believe that the adoption of this provision would confer altogether too great a power on the Appraiser and on the Secretary of the Treasury, and that would be contrary to the inalienable right of every American citizen to appeal to the courts of his country for the settlement of the difficulties he may become involved in.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0248.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Section 487 is also objectionable for it would prevent the importer from amending a Custom House entry after it is filed, thus eventually subjecting him to unjust penalties and possibly to litigation.</p>
   <p>Finally, we beg to suggest that the thousands of American business men, who have invested years of labor and millions of capital in supplying the public with the merchandise made abroad that it requires, are entitled to fair dealing and, as well as other business men, to a reasonable measure of protection in their legitimate undertakings, and that such fair dealing and protection would be denied to them by the adoption of the provisions we have mentioned.</p>
   <p>Submitted by the Italian Chamber of Commerce of Chicago.</p>
   <p>(Signed) I. E. Canini, president.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0249.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Among the numerous answers arrived from Washington we report those received from the two Senators Glenn and Deneen:</p>
   <p>Dear Mr. Canini:</p>
   <p>I thank you for your letter of May 27th, and copy of the briefs submitted by the Italian Chamber of Commerce of New York to the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives relative to tariff revision.</p>
   <p>I am not a member of the Finance Committee which will consider the Tariff Bill this summer, and presume it will not be debated upon the floor of the Senate until next September or October.</p>
   <p>I am glad to have the benefit of the views of your Association, which I will keep in mind when studying this legislation.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Otis F. Glenn.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0250.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>My Dear Mr. Canini:</p>
   <p>Your letter relative to tariff legislation is at hand.</p>
   <p>I thank you for giving me your views thereon and shall be pleased to give them consideration when the measure comes before the Senate Finance Committee.</p>
   <p>Appreciating your interest, I am</p>
   <p>(Signed) Charles S. Deneen.</p>
   <p>On occasion of the discussion of the project of the new Tariff in the House of Representatives, this Chamber sent to the Legislators of Illinois the following telegram:- Respectfully urge you to vote against flexible Tariff American Valuation finality Appraiser's decision.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
