<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1930-10">October 1930</date>, p. 7.
<title level="a">The Whole World Glorified Columbus</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0399</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0399.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1930-10">October 1930</date>, p. 7.
<title level="a">THE WHOLE WORLD GLORIFIED COLUMBUS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The universal echo of this great epic, the celebration of the great Genoese, whose gigantic figure shines with an eternal light in the cycle of history and of whose example of mastery and glory our race can well be proud of, is a testimonial, in most solemn form, that no foreign fabricato of charming stories or fantastic fables can contest the Italian claim to Columbus as a son of that noble land that,"Appenines divide, the sea and the Alps surround."</p>
   <p>The bust, erected by this cosmopolitan metropolis to the famous "Leif Erickson" pretended explorer of these lands, is born out of the folklore of the Swedish people. It was placed there to satisfy the fanaticism envy and jealousy of those people impelled by an incontrovertible spirit of hatred for everything Italian.</p>
   <p>It was a perfidious act; and perfidious were all those who groping in the dark, search for other discoverers of this great nation or else dispute the Italian <pb facs="5425702_2_0400.jpg" n="2"/>origin of the bold Italian navigator.</p>
   <p>Books of historical facts, manuscript, public and private acts, photographs, authentic documents, accumulated with diligent care and research by our government and by valiant writers prove without a doubt that Columbus belongs to the glory of Italy.</p>
   <p>The entire world has spoken and the universal celebration held in every corner of the earth rings with reproaches and protests against those who would dare to create a doubt and soil the true story.</p>
   <p>It is a perfidy that Herbert Hoover first citizen of this great nation has cancelled with a noble and historic telegram to Chevalier Confessa, president of the Sezione Colombiana of New York which we reprint:</p>
   <p>"The White House,</p>
   <p>September, 1930.</p>
   <p>Dear Mr. Confessa:</p>
   <p>The story of the discovery of America by Christopher Columbus will never lose the fascination that it has for us, not because it relates to us <pb facs="5425702_2_0401.jpg" n="3"/>events which made possible the actual existence of this nation but because the example of his enterprising life, the energy, patience, resourcefulness and courage has been very influential in keeping present those qualities before the eyes of our children as traditions that should be followed.</p>
   <p>Cordially yours,</p>
   <p>(signed) Herbert Hoover.</p>
   <p>It is a perfidy that His Excellency, Giacomo De Marino, Italian Ambassador to Washington has erased with his message to all Italians.</p>
   <p>With the Columbian celebration the Italians also celebrated the two thousandth anniversary of the death of Virgil the great poet.</p>
   <p>For the occasion Gov. Louis Emerson of Illinois made a very interesting speech, The celebration was held at the Navy Pier. More than seven thousand Italians were present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
