<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1908-05-23">May 23, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">[Terelli Youngest Band Leader in America]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_1080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1908-05-23">May 23, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">[TERELLI YOUNGEST BAND LEADER IN AMERICA]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today the Terelli Band will inaugurate Sans Souci Park. Terelli is very well known, and it is therefore unnecessary to introduce him to our readers. He was born in Naples and finished studying at St. Peter's Conservatory in Marella. He was the first choir boy of the theater when only seventeen years old. He has been in Germany at different times and has had the opportunity to excel in German music. After coming to America, he became the director of the Ellery Band, attaining great success. He is only 29 years old, and is the youngest director in America. He loves Italian music, because he is Italian, but he also fervently admires the German music. His band occupies first place among the great bands and, for that reason, will return to Ravinia Park, this year, where he will retake the stand for the New York Symphony orchestra, which takes the place of Thomas' orchestra from Chicago. The band is composed of fifty players elected from among the best in America. In place of the soloists we find last year's orchestra members are the same.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1081.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Domerico Palmo is the first cornet player, Guiseppe Siniscalchi, Clarion player, and singer. Leborio Lamonte is the trombone player, who is well beloved by the public, for the sweet and artistic manner in which he plays. Filippo Cincione is the first bass and also well known and liked by the public, for his beautiful and strong voice. The Terelli Band, besides being in prime condition promises a quartet of soloists that would enrich any band.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
