<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1925-03">March, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The Inauguration of the Direct Cable between America and Italy</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0816</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0816.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1925-03">March, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE INAUGURATION OF THE DIRECT CABLE BETWEEN AMERICA AND ITALY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last March 16, at 9 a. m., about one hundred members met in the office of the Italian Chamber of Commerce to inaugurate the direct cable between America and Italy.</p>
   <p>The great event, which was the realization of the Italian colonies, deserves to be remembered in the history of our colony. Many expressions of gratitude and joy were addressed to our beloved King and to His Excellency Mussolini, who conceived and accomplished a deed which was never even considered by past governments.</p>
   <p>The accomplished undertaking which is celebrated today makes us feel nearer and more attached to our motherland, Italy.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0817.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the celebration were present the Executive Council of the Chamber of Commerce; the personnel of the Royal Consulate headed by Consul General Comm. Lunini; Mr. T. F. Moran, division cable manager of Western Union; Frank J. O'Brien, city cable manager; Chevalier Edwardo Buccaloro, director of Banco di Napoli; Chev. A. Mastrovalerio, for the Tribune; Chev. A. Ferrari for L'Idea; C. Vitello, vice president of the Unione Siciliana; Dr. F. La Piana, grand master of the Order Sons of Italy; Lt. A. Raiani and Lt. J. Gallo, respectively, president and secretary of the National Association of Italian Veterans.</p>
   <p>The first messages on the new cable were exchanged between Chicago and Rome at 9 o'clock sharp to:</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0818.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>S. E. General Cittadini</p>
   <p>Aide to H. M. the King - Roma</p>
   <p>Today inaugurating the new cable which put in direct communication two of the greatest nations, strengthening their friendship, promoting prosperity. Italians of Chicago greet Italian prosperity which under the leadership of H. M. the King is advancing to higher destinies.</p>
   <p>(Signed) General Consul Lunini.</p>
   <p>In the evening our Italian Consul General Comm. Lunini gave a dinner for the Ambassador at the La Salle Hotel. At 10 p. m. the Ambassador was a guest of the Pottor Palmers and at 11:30 p. m. he left Chicago for Denver and California.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
