<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1912-07-07">July 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Colony Has Done Nothing Towards an Air Fleet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_1017</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1017.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1912-07-07">July 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE COLONY HAS DONE NOTHING TOWARDS AN AIR FLEET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have received and published the following letter:</p>
   <p>"Dear Editor:</p>
   <p>I am sure your courtesy will not deny one of your readers a small space in your worthy paper for some personal observations.</p>
   <p>The appeal of the fatherland for assistance in donating an air fleet to the armed forces of our country, of which we can justly feel proud, has been answered by many individuals as well as entire colonies.</p>
   <p>But among these I am sorry to say that Chicago does not figure.</p>
   <p>The colony of Chicago has the duty of upholding the patriotic traditions. It always has been thoughtful and generous in times of national misfortune and disaster. It erected an imposing monument to our national hero, Garibaldi. And its duty is to continue in the same manner, to show that it holds for its own the ideal of Italians, the grandeur of Italy.</p>
   <p>But perhaps the initiative is missing in those who are charged with keeping firm the tie that binds the colony in the motherland. For they have not done <pb facs="5425702_2_1018.jpg" n="2"/>their duty, which is to nourish and stimulate the sentiment of patriotism in the colony. I want to hope that they will remember before the new fleet, made possible by Italian determination, flies over the cities and fields in the pure ozone and azure sky of Italy, bearing witness to the grandeur and strength of Italy.</p>
   <p>Worthily yours,</p>
   <p>An Humble Reader"</p>
   <p>No comments are necessary on the foregoing letter. Other colonies, especially in South America, have shown their attachment for the fatherland by subscribing to the purchase of one or more airplanes. The Chicago colony instead has turned a cold shoulder to it, although it numbers among its members many who are wealthy. When will the colony awaken to its responsibilities, form a committee, hold meetings, and try to revive in the more phlegmatic that love of country.</p>
   <p>This paper has always given its support to everything that was to the colony's advantage and is ready, now, to give its support morally and financially to whatever is initiated in this good cause.</p>
   <p>Editor's Note.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
