<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous - "<title level="a">The Roman Question and Fascism</title>," <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1929-03">March 1929</date>, pp. 5-6

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0774</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0774.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous - "<title level="a">The Roman Question and Fascism</title>," <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1929-03">March 1929</date>, pp. 5-6
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Certain historic events, like the concordat between the government of Italy and the papacy, are as we see them the result of ideas conceived in the minds of men and have their epilogue because of the labor and the will of God.</p>
   <p>We cannot analyze the causes and the consequences which this event may produce on the politico-religious life of human society because the future is in the hands of God, the one and only infallible power that presides over all the happenings and acts of our life, before whose grandeur we are as pygmies, very infinitesimal beings.</p>
   <p>If we venture to make some comment or deduction, therefore, it is only for the purpose of succinctly presenting our point of view and our opinion on a fact important enough to attract the attention of the greatest men and nations.</p>
   <p>With this premise, that the accord between the Italian government and the papacy will not in the least affect our faith and our religious principles, <pb facs="5425702_2_0775.jpg" n="2"/>the fruit of ponderous reflection and long experience. We must explicitly state that in spite of our religious ideas, which are free from fanaticism and prejudice, we are still in sympathy with Fascism and the Duce because he has merely brought to completion an accord which had been maturing for many years, and which other governments had also tried to achieve.</p>
   <p>A change of attitude would signify that we had acted for our own personal ends and had not been animated by clear and just motives.</p>
   <p>To feel that Mussolini should have refused to sign the accord and thus have left the Roman question unsolved in order to please us would be folly.</p>
   <p>Are we expected to applaud the former governments of Italy, which left us on the edge of the precipice in danger of falling into anarchy and bolshevism? Most certainly not!</p>
   <p>We are devotees of order and discipline, and as such we have admired a government capable of restoring order and discipline internally and the <pb facs="5425702_2_0776.jpg" n="3"/>name and prestige of Italians abroad.</p>
   <p>Certainly many will be surprised at the courageous stand which we have taken.</p>
   <p>Because of our attitude criticism and reproach will be heaped on us by those who act in bad faith, but we shall not be alone. Many who like us, cherish profound religious convictions, will suffer the same consequences.</p>
   <p>We are certain that no persecution of persons who are not Roman-Catholics will ensue because of this agreement between Church and State. The Italy of today is not the Italy of the past, and Mussolini himself would not countenance persecution in any form.</p>
   <p>Apropos of this we value a public statement made by our illustrious colleague, the Rev. Paul Boiso, rector of the largest Waldensian church in Rome, who is making a lecture tour in the United States. This statement, which appeared in various newspapers and periodicals, was an opinion expressed as part of a lecture given in Hartford, Conn. We reprint it <pb facs="5425702_2_0777.jpg" n="4"/>from Corriere D'America.</p>
   <p>"The Reverend Mr. Boiso and Mussolini. The Rev. Paul Boiso, who has come here from Rome, where he is pastor of the Cornelius Baker Memorial Church, to conduct a short mission of five lectures in five Waldensian religious centers has words of unconditional praise for the work of reconstruction begun by Mussolini in Italy. He says that Italy, which after the war was on its way to the abyss of bolshevism, has found in him an anchor of security. Mussolini is a profound thinker with a program which, though arduous, he will nevertheless carry to successful completion."</p>
   <p>The Rev. Mr. Boiso then added that Protestantism had nothing to fear from the Italo-Vatican accord, and that Mussolini had earned the respect of all creeds.</p>
   <p>We add this item which was reported by Rastignac in the Progresso Italo-Americano:</p>
   <p>"It is important to know that Il Duce has given the lie to persons of bad <pb facs="5425702_2_0778.jpg" n="5"/>faith who see the possibility that other creeds may suffer because of the concordat between Italy and the Vatican. As in the past, all creeds in Italy will enjoy freedom of worship.</p>
   <p>"The popular demonstrations of good will with which the words of Il Duce have been received, besides showing the immense popularity enjoyed by the Liberator, signify the perfect solidarity behind the accomplished fact and the truth of the formula enunciated at the end of the speech that Italy is Fascism, and Fascism is Italy.</p>
   <p>"Meanwhile, whether or not we care to cast reproaches, they will not change the course of events. It is not by opposing and decrying Mussolini and Fascism that we can reach the goal which we have set for ourselves - in fact, we should consider such conduct inconsistent with our principles.</p>
   <p>"Whatever the propaganda against Fascism may be, it will not serve to remove the type of government which the Italians want.</p>
   <p>"Every nation has the government which it desires.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0779.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"Italy has done well to support the Mussolini Government, which after all is preferable to former governments and former systems.</p>
   <p>"The remembrance of the occupation of the factories in Milan by the workers, the bloody days of Rossi, the general strikes throughout the peninsula, etc. etc., is still too fresh in our minds. We will hold to our opinion, to the course hitherto followed, even at the cost of being criticized by our dearest friends and colleagues who erroneously see in Fascism an enemy to their ideals and their faith."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
