<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
            <date when="1935-11">Nov., 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Against the Boycotting of Italian Products by the United States</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0240</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0240.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1935-11">Nov., 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AGAINST THE BOYCOTTING OF ITALIAN PRODUCTS BY THE UNITED STATES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is well known that England and other nations participating in the League, (League of London) tried to include the American Government in the economic sanctions against Italy.</p>
   <p>It is well known also that the acquiescence of the United States of such spiteful conduct will be damaging to the interests of this country and of the importers and exporters.</p>
   <p>For the foregoing reasons the president of this Italian Chamber of Commerce, Chevalier, A. Mattucci, called a meeting, October 17, of a large number of merchants and professional men to discuss this important issue.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0241.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the meeting held in the offices of this Chamber, it was resolved to send to the Secretary of State, Cordell Hull, and to the Secretary of Commerce, D. C. Roper, the following telegram:</p>
   <p>October 18, 1935.</p>
   <p>The Italian Chamber of Commerce of Chicago, representing as it does a large part of the business interests of approximately three-hundred thousand Italian-Americans in and around Chicago, heartily approves the neutrality stand of the United States of America believing, as it does that it is for the best interests of the entire American population to avoid doing anything which might involve it in foreign entanglements or international complications. Newspaper reports that the United <pb facs="5425702_2_0242.jpg" n="3"/>States is considering a participation in international boycott of Italian goods. We earnestly urge, in view of fact that we are not members of the League of Nations, that this is not our affair and that we should not join in this movement, nor should economic sanctions be imposed by us.</p>
   <p>Such action we feel would be detrimental rather than enhance the cause of neutrality, as nations members of the League by enforcing sanctions, are definitely taking sides in the present dispute. Millions of Italians have elected to become residents or citizens of the United States, and business relationship between the Kingdom of Italy and the United States for many years have been very satisfactory and of considerable importance to all American people, especially inview of the fact, that all times exports to Italy have far exceeded value of imports from Italy.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0243.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We feel that this business should not be lost and while we do not disagree with position taken relative to munitions and armaments of war, we feel that nothing should be done to discourage trade in legitimate articles of commerce.</p>
   <p>(Signed) A. O. Mattucci, president.</p>
   <p>Encouraging replies were received by Chev. Mattucci from the mentioned secretaries, who stated that the Government of the United States will observe its neutrality strictly and will limit its ban to arms and ammunition exports, and discard other sanctions of an economic character.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
