<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title level="a">Garibaldi Institute and St. John Presbyterian Church</title>. <title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1931-03">March 1931</date>, pp. 20-21.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0508</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0508.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item><item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title level="a">Garibaldi Institute and St. John Presbyterian Church</title>." <title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1931-03">March 1931</date>, pp. 20-21.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has been said that all great movements are centered around a great personality. This is particularly true as regards the great work of those two Christian Americanization institutions, known as Garibaldi Institute and St.John Presbyterian Church.</p>
   <p>Wound in and out of every activity stands the personality of Rev. Pasquale Riciardi De Carlo. For forty-one years Mr. De Carlo has been a minister. He has been editor of an Italian and English magazine published monthly. In addition to the duties involved therewith he is actually engaged as field representative of the Church Extention Board, Presbytery of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. De Carlo Dream.-</p>
   <p>Before him constantly is the dream of seeing his Italian people gathered in unity <pb facs="5425702_2_0509.jpg" n="2"/>of purpose serving one God the Father of all mankind,through but one intercessor, Jesus Christ.</p>
   <p>He saw the Italian people gaining high places of honor in education, in music and in art.</p>
   <p>He saw them in all their natural generosity, kindliness and affection caring for those more unfortunate than themselves.</p>
   <p>He saw them leading exemplary lives as fathers, mothers and children.</p>
   <p>Obstacles in the way. -</p>
   <p>How could such a dream be realized when parents of Italian children were entirely separated from their children's interests by lack of education, language, and knowledge of American ways; when parents depend upon their children for the interpretation of life; when their children get into all sort of trouble with the laws of the country, securing for themselves the names of criminals, gangsters, <pb facs="5425702_2_0510.jpg" n="3"/>racketeers, etc.</p>
   <p>Steps Necessary for Progress -</p>
   <p>1. The parents must learn the English language.</p>
   <p>2. Parents must become American citizens.</p>
   <p>3. Parents must receive an education and training fitting them for the responsibility of helping to mold the character and well being of their children.</p>
   <p>4. Parents must cast aside their superstition and open their minds to seeing plain facts built upon knowledge.</p>
   <p>The Children.-</p>
   <p>1. The Children must be taught to respect the parents' background, feeling that they have a heritage to be proud of.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0511.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>2. The language of the parents should be acquired and spoken correctly.</p>
   <p>3. They must understand that the laws of the country are made for the benefit of all, and must be observed by every individual and that money cannot pay for every infringement.</p>
   <p>4. They must be taught that truth and honesty are treasures to be sought after. What has been done about it?</p>
   <p>Mr. De Carlo started the working out of his dream in Connecticut. He was called from there to take charge of the Italian work in Detroit, Mich.</p>
   <p>His unique, outstanding Christian character and work created attention and admiration.</p>
   <p>Sixteen years ago he was called by the Church Extention Board of the Presbytery of Chicago to come and organize the Italian work in Chicago. He left the Detroit work in able hands, accomplishing just such things as he had dreamed of originally, and like the Master, he moved to the greater need in the large city, Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0512.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Here he saw the terrible poverty, suffering and oppression of his people and he set himself to work immediately in trying to alleviate it.</p>
   <p>Italian Christian Institute -</p>
   <p>At 567 Taylor St., the Italian Christian Institute was opened. The work soon outgrew these quarters, and the old Lessin Club on Taylor and Racine Ave. was bought and remodeled to take care of the work. Into this building moved the organized church of St.John Presbyterian Church, with its 58 charter members, and was duly recognized by the Chicago Presbytery in the year 1920.</p>
   <p>Garibaldi Institute -</p>
   <p>Mr. De Carlo has always advocated the social recreational and educational needs of the people being cared for by the Church. Under the name of Garibaldi Institute all these activities were housed and built upon the spiritual foundation of Jesus Christ.</p>
   <p>Into this work were called young men and women of high scholastic achievement and <pb facs="5425702_2_0513.jpg" n="6"/>Christian character to take on the different responsibilities that require supervisory capacity. Garibaldi Institute presents the following activities.</p>
   <p>Kindergarten for children, in which they are prepared for entry into the public school with special nurses and case workers.</p>
   <p>Older children in health classes.</p>
   <p>Girls in cooking and sewing classes.</p>
   <p>Vocal and instrumental lessons provided for those who revealed the best talent.</p>
   <p>Athletic games and showers.</p>
   <p>Mother Club -</p>
   <p>Every week the mothers with babies in their arms and small children following behind them meet for instruction of various kinds, social hour and refreshments.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0514.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The children are cared for in the nursery, giving the mothers the opportunity of recreation free of responsability.</p>
   <p>The New Church Building -</p>
   <p>Worship as a necessity to the soul life of the individual is emphasized, and it was only fitting that the organized church at Garibaldi Institute should wish to be housed in its own edifice. In 1929 out of the heart-felt gratitude and loyalty of the members of the St.John Presbyterian Church, the present structure at 2101 W. Harrison St. was erected. Beautifully simple in all its architectural features, it is complete in every detail, tending to give the worshiper the feeling of reverence and peace. In the pulpit stands the present day prophet, Mr. De Carlo, pleading with his people to see the desirability of such a life as he presents to them. To the right of him sings a choir of twenty voices, earnest, clear eyed, aspiring young people, calling themselves "Endeavorers" for the same cause for which their leader is giving his life.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0515.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Americanization -</p>
   <p>Following out the steps necessary to complete the dream, there are classes in the new Church. In the night classes for Americanization there is an average of 130 individuals. These individuals are made up of the parents, young people and children.</p>
   <p>Social Service Department: -</p>
   <p>As Director of the Social Service Department Mr. De Carlo follows out another of the Master leader's admonitions, caring for the poor, the sick, the discouraged and despairing, trying to make them understand that there is One who cares for them - "God the father of all mankind."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
