<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-01-17">Jan. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Club Giordano Bruno's Mass-Meeting the Clerical-Consular Boycott</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0988</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0988.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-01-17">Jan. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE CLUB GIORDANO BRUNO'S MASS-MEETING THE CLERICAL-CONSULAR BOYCOTT</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mass-meeting called by the Club Giordano Bruno, as a protest against the deed of the Italian Consul in giving the management of the so-called lodging house to the nuns, should have taken place in the Roma Theater.</p>
   <p>But at the last moment, the proprietor, influenced by somebody who thought that in the meeting improper facts would be discussed and revealed, refused the use of the theater.</p>
   <p>We did not give up. We immediately found another place, the Dante Theater, and the mass-meeting took place just the same, in spite of the supporters of Count Bolognesi and the clericals.</p>
   <p>The mass-meeting was presided over by Mr. Eugenio Pecori a member of the Club. First in Italian, and then in English, he explained the noble purpose of the mass-meeting, which was to protest against the Consul for having entrusted the management of that overcrowded "shanty" which is called a lodging <pb facs="5425702_2_0989.jpg" n="2"/>house, to the nuns-who are using that hypocritical privilege to gain merits and to propagate their abominable Catholic doctrine.</p>
   <p>He vindicated the high mission of the Club, [and refuted] the stupid insinuations of hysterical clericals, who had so influenced Hull House against the Club, that the Club was refused the use of Rowen Hall for the commemoration of Giordano Bruno, free thinker martyr.</p>
   <p>Then Comrade T. Lucidi, official speaker of the Club, delivered a very interesting speech. He recapitulated the painful history of our immigration to America, and described the efforts exerted by consular officers, priests, and outstanding Italians, for the welfare of the suffering mass, in contract to the efforts of those who are assuming airs of benefactors when they really are mystifiers, liars and leeches of humanity. He praised the high mission of the Club, which mission is that of illuminating the darkness, which has been imposed on humanity by sacred dogma, with the torch of truth. He attacked the Italian Consul, who, availing himself of the fund which the Italian government put at his disposal for the welfare of the needy, used it to make propaganda for the priests and nuns. They-in turn-with the excuse of charity, conspire against the intellectual and economic redemption of the <pb facs="5425702_2_0990.jpg" n="3"/>working people, whom they try to hold down as slaves of religious superstitions and the present politico-economic system.</p>
   <p>Mr. E. Gradinetti then addressed the meeting, in the name of the Socialists of Chicago. He deplored the acts of Consul Bolognesi and condemned the wretchedness of such acts. Talking about the Consular's office, he described it not as an office for protection and aid, but as an agency of international espionage.</p>
   <p>At the end, one of the inmates of the famous lodging house described, in a few words, the place where the indigents are suffering from starvation, cold, and the abuses of the "good Sisters." He said that the ten inmates who came to our office to protest against the treatment received at the lodging house were thrown out of [the shelter] by policemen.</p>
   <p>It was resolved to draw up a petition and send it as a protest, with a telegram, to the Secretary of Foreign Affairs in Rome.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0991.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As a consequence of the mass-meeting, we were informed that in the lodging house certain acts of coercion were used against the inmates who had the courage to protest; and a few, who refused to submit themselves to shameful impositions, were, as was said at the meeting, thrown out of the lodging house by the police.</p>
   <p>"Worthy of praise" is the imperative admonition of a well known doctor, a satellite of Consul Bolognesi. He said, to the protesting immates: "If you do not like to stay here, get out!" And yet they do not ask for too much, dear doctor. They, in suffering the humiliation of charity, wish, at least, that their stomachs be filled, so that their liberty of conscience should be respected and not be gagged-as in the times of the Holy Inquisition-every time they feel inclined to make a just protest or to reveal the truth.</p>
   <p>Go ahead, then, Mr. Consul, priests, nuns, and self styled benefactors! You show that you are afraid of those who have the courage to openly criticize your acts. We take advantage of your fright, and we will continue to reveal to the public your outrages and scandalous acts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
