<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1922-09">September 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago against the Custom Tariff</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0270</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0270.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1922-09">September 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO AGAINST THE CUSTOM TARIFF</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italian Chamber of Commerce, in unison with the sister Chamber of New York, through the local organizations and the voters, sent the following protest to the Senators of the United States:</p>
   <p>Sir:</p>
   <p>The members of the_____composed of American citizens, beg leave to offer a few suggestions which they hope will promote commerce and friendly relation between the United States and Italy, and the prosperity and welfare of both countries. We would remind you that our devotion to the welfare of the Republic as American citizens has been exemplified in the late war and in the subsequent period of reconstruction, both by the large number of our sons whom we sent to the colors, and the liberal contributions we have made to Liberty Bonds and the payment of other heavy obligations to support the country in its period of stress and upheaval.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0271.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We feel, therefore, that we should be allowed, as for it lies within your power by legislation to retrieve our losses in part, and that our trade with Italy should be promoted and not hampered.</p>
   <p>The members of this Association are well aware of the conflicting interests involved and the difficulties of tariff revision in this critical time, when the country is passing through a period of readjustment after a war that has caused the greatest upheaval ever known in the economic history of the world.</p>
   <p>We are addressing you now in order that you use your good offices to avoid, or at least to mitigate, the great injustice and iniquity that would be perpetrated by the adoption of some of the proposed rates included in the tariff bill now in conference.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0272.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We speak especially of the large increase proposed on articles of absolute necessity to the people whom we represent. They are already hard pressed by the continued high cost of living, with a decreasing wage and not always certain employment. The adoption of higher tariff rates will mean an additional higher cost, not only for the foreign articles, but for the domestic product as well. We state to you in all frankness that we consider some of the proposed rates an outrage against the consumer and a direct threat and menace to the laboring classes. The increased rates against which we are particularly desirous of calling your attention, and of protection against their exorbitant measure are the following:</p>
   <p>Lemons.....increased from one-half (1/2) cent to two cents per pound, notwithstanding they are an indispensable commodity even to the poorer class. Olive Oil.....increased from 30 cents per gallon to 7 1/2 cents per pound, equivalent to over 62 cents per gallon, if in containers weighing with the the immediate container less than 40 lbs. Olive Oil, not specially provided <pb facs="5425702_2_0273.jpg" n="4"/>for, raised from 20 cents per gallon to 6 1/2 cents per pound, equivalent to over 50 cents per gallon, and this, notwithstanding its being an article of prime necessity for our population and not a luxury as it is considered in some quarters. Macaroni.....raised from 1 to 2 cents per pound; Cheese, increased from 20 per cent to 25 per cent ad valorem; Tomato Paste, increased from 25 per cent to 45 per cent ad valorem; Fish in Olive Oil - increased from 25 to 30 per cent ad valorem, and Inbrine - from 15 to 25 per cent ad valorem; Unshelled Almonds - increased from 3 to 5 cents per pound. Unshelled Walnuts - from 2 to 4 cents per pound. Unshelled Filberts - from 2 to 2 1/2 cents per pound. Shelled Filberts - from 4 to 5 cents per lb. Shelled Almonds - from 4 to 15 cents per pound. Shelled Walnuts - from 4 to 12 cents per pound. Dried Beans - from 25 cents per bushel of 60 pounds to 2 cent per pound. Mushrooms - from 2 1/2 cents per pound to 45 per cent ad valorem. Preserved Meats - from exemption of duty to 20 per cent ad valorem, and so forth.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0274.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We are firmly convinced that there is not a single item, above enumerated whose increased rate can be justified upon the plea of a legitimate protection. It is purely poundering to special interests and at the expense of the ultimate consumer.</p>
   <p>The general public has long since tired on these methods and we cannot conceive that they can be in any greater sympathy with them in these critical times, when earnings are generally decreasing and cost not showing corresponding declines.</p>
   <p>The consumers generally will be hurt by the higher prices. Those of Italian descent, numbering thousands among your constituents, will in particular feel the hardship as they are the main consumers of many of the articles now seriously advanced.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0275.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We earnestly and sincerely hope that you will recognize the error of the proposed course and that you will exert your good offices to the end that we may be saved and consequences of such ill-advised and exorbitant rates as those on the commodities above stated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
