<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy of Illinois</title>,
Vol. 8, No. 6.<date when="1936"/><title level="a">A Day at the Zoo Set Aside for the Italians</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0328</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0328.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy of Illinois</title>,
Vol. 8, No. 6.<date when="1936"/><title level="a">A DAY AT THE ZOO SET ASIDE FOR THE ITALIANS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Zoological Society,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois,</p>
   <p>June 1, 1936.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank D'Amico,</p>
   <p>Sons of Italy,</p>
   <p>201 N. Wells Street,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Dear Mr. D'Amico:</p>
   <p>As I stated in our telephone conversation the officials of the Chicago Zoological Park at Brookfield, Illinois, have set aside Sunday, July 26, as Italian day at the Zoo.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0329.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Admission to the Zoo will be free on this day and we hope to have a record turn out of Italian people that day. Your promise to cooperate with the Zoo authorities in bringing out as many as possible is deeply appreciated by us.</p>
   <p>We believe that the hundreds of animal exhibits, several of them new this year, will give the Italian people an enjoyable day on July 26.</p>
   <p>The day should be one on which the Italians of Chicago and surrounding territory should come out in family groups and make a full day of it. They are urged to bring their lunches as we have ample picnic facilities on the grounds where they can enjoy their meals in comfort.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0330.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For those who are unable to bring their lunches light meals are served at reasonable prices at the park.</p>
   <p>Enough time will elapse before the event to allow you, if you will notify your members and their many friends of the plans for the day. You can through your meetings and notices, I know, bring thousands to the Zoo.</p>
   <p>Our publicity department will undertake to aid in letting the people know that July 26, is Italian Day. We will give the newspapers interesting stories and pictures which will tend to create considerable interest for the occasion. In order that all might know how to reach the Zoo I am enclosing a copy of the directions to the Zoo.</p>
   <p>Thanking you for your cooperation, I am,</p>
   <p>Very truly yours,</p>
   <p>David A. O'Conner, director of special</p>
   <p>events. Chicago Zoological Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
