<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1917-10-07">October 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To Honor the Dead of Termine</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0946</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0946.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1917-10-07">October 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO HONOR THE DEAD OF TERMINE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The local residents of Termine Italy, held a meeting in which it was decided to have a stone-tablet made carrying the names of Terminesi from Chicago, who had fallen on the field of battle. The tablet will be placed on the wall of the Town Hall of the smiling Sicilian City.</p>
   <p>A committee headed by Mr. Joseph Malato, has been formed of Chicago residents of Termine Imerese to raise funds necessary for this work. The committee got to work and assured itself of the collaboration of the well-known countryman Cavaliere Professor Francesco Paolo Mule, that he work the dedication of the tablet, to the honor of the Chicago Termitana colony which conceived it and donated it to the memory of the heroes to whom it is dedicated.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0947.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Executive Committee consists of Joseph Malato, honorary president; Andrea Russo, president; Stefano Malato; Dr. Joseph Damiani; Dr. V. Indovina; Joseph Mirabella, vice president; C. Palumbo Sattile, cashier; F.D'Amico, secretary.</p>
   <p>The General Committee consists of V. Formusa; Dr. S. Mirabella; P. Russo; Dr. V. Scaletta; A. Muffoletto; V. Sansone; M. Indovina; T. Russo; L. Emanuele; Dr. A. Formusa; E. Melato; F. Palumbo; M. Rinella; F. Ciresi; G. Vainisi; Dr. S. Damiani; G. Guarino; Wm. Campagna; R. Russo Di Andrea; G. S. Coppola; S. Di Cola; G &amp; F. Borrelli; F. Messineo; N. Guardalabene; G. Comella; and son, F. Tomasello; F. Mazziotta; A. Geraci; A. La Mantia; Wm. Raimondi; Ciresi Brothers &amp; Company; F. Battaglia; Frank Battaglia; and C. Caporici.</p>
   <p>We wish them much success!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
