<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1916-02-27">February 27, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Dafino Case</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1916-02-27">February 27, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE DAFINO CASE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Because they had written threatening letters to Modestinio Mastrovalerio, 3710 Grand Boulevard, Nicolo Dafino and his wife, Parla, were charged with the bombing of the Mastrovalerio's home.</p>
   <p>The Dafinos had written asking Mastrovalerio to repay them the one-thousand dollars, which they had deposited in his private bank and which they had lost when the bank failed to the tune of $100,000.</p>
   <p>Their first letter had been very courteous, but when Mastrovalerio chose to ignore it, Mrs. Dafino, since her husband is illiterate, wrote a letter in very menacing terms. Soon after came the bombing of the Mastrovalerio's home.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0128.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Dafinos claimed to have been at home at the time of the bombing and Antonio Bondi, grocer at 28th and Lowe, testified that Dafino was in his store at the very moment of the explosion.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, the Dafinos were held to Grand Jury, which set their bail at $5,000 each.</p>
   <p>And so, the Dafinos, who from all indications are innocent of the crime, not only will have lost their hard earned money, but have also incurred the expenses and gove through the anxieties of a court trial. All this is so because the laws of the country allow any penniless nobody to set himself up in business as a banker and live on the grand scale of a Morgan or Rothschild.</p>
   <p>The Dafino trial is set for March 8.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
