<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1919-01-12">January 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A Banquet in Honor of Capt. Merriam</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0910</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0910.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1919-01-12">January 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A BANQUET IN HONOR OF CAPT. MERRIAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A splendid demonstration was organized by the Italian press in honor of Capt. Charles Merriam, who in the holy name of justice, has made himself heard in more than one occasion in defence of Italy's part in the World War.</p>
   <p>The banquet was given at Rome Restaurant, 127 N. Clark Street. There were many prominent Italians who paid homage to the guest of honor. Ario Flamma, acted as toastmaster, opening a series of talks with elegance efficient and the highest concepts. He was much applauded. He was followed by the Vice Consul G. Dell Agnol, who said a few words in defence of Count Bolognesi, and then exalted Capt. Merriam's good work in behalf of Italy.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0911.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Another speaker, M. Lo Franco, who represented the Italian press, was also applauded. The lawyer Malato and Captain De Lungo both spoke words of the occasion, they were congratulated. At the end of the banquet, Captain Merriam was given an ovation. He got up thanking all and glorifying Italy, saying, "Italy is the nation which contributed a great deal for the realization of the allied victory."</p>
   <p>He spoke in Italian and English telling about the sacrifices made by the Italian soldiers; he is considered the best friend of the Italians in the United States. Mr. Italo Pellegrini, the proprietor of Rome Restaurant, was praised for his good food.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
