<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1903-05-23">May 23, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Italian Counterfeiter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1903-05-23">May 23, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Italian Counterfeiter</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For some time Federal authorities have suspected the existence of an Italian counterfeiting-gang in Chicago. Counterfeit coins of various denominations which found their way into the cash-register of north-side merchants resulted in many complaints being made to the police.</p>
   <p>Although arrests were made from time to time, the source of the coins remained a mystery.</p>
   <p>The suspicion fell on the Nicolosi Brothers, who operate a saloon and lodging-house at 84 Oak Street.</p>
   <p>An Italian secret-service operator, Guiseppe Bassini, was called in from New York and put on the case.</p>
   <p>Posing as an unemployed laborer, he procured lodgings with the Nicolosi's and proceeded to gain their confidence by profering a knowledge of metals. So well did he succeed that in a short time he was shown the room which contained all the equipment for the minting of coins.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0169.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The arrest of two members, Francesco Cannella, and Guiseppe Bullaro, while passing false fifty-cent pieces, put the gang on guard, and suspicion fell on Bassini as being a police-spy. He was invited to join them in a glass of beer, but no sooner had he drunk it than he became unconscious and did not come to until three days later, when he was found gagged and tied in a dark and damp basement-room.</p>
   <p>He was then accused of being a secret-service man, but was able to convince them of his innocence, and so was freed.</p>
   <p>He reported his findings to Capt. Porter, who despatched a squad to the place, but a thorough search of the premises failed to reveal the presence of the minting outfit. The only person in the place, Guiseppe Nicolosi, was placed under arrest. The search was carried to neighboring houses but failed to reveal anything of importance.</p>
   <p>The gang, it seems, had judiciously disposed of all incriminating paraphernalia during the three days of Bassini's imprisonment.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0170.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Federal authorities are searching for Mariano Sagona, whom they believe to be the leader of the gang.</p>
   <p>Unable to furnish the required bail, Nicolosi is still in jail and will have a hearing this morning before U.S. Commissioner Humphrey.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
