<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1907-02-02">Feb. 2, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">A Church Jubilee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0589</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0589.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1907-02-02">Feb. 2, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">A CHURCH JUBILEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Rejoicings are in progress at the Assumption Church of the North Side. Tomorrow, Sunday, February 3, the Italian colony of the North Side will celebrate the Silver Jubilee of the Church of the Assumption, between Franklin and Orleans Streets.</p>
   <p>The celebrations of the 25th Anniversary of the Church of The Assumption are in honor of its being the second sacred edifice of the Italians in Chicago. The first celebration was in 1880, when Father Moretti bought the ground where the church now stands. Work was begun immediately. The dedication took place Sunday, April 17, 1881.</p>
   <p>This church at first was a humble building that only faintly resembled a place of worship.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0590.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1884 the church was enlarged and was blessed by Monsignor Feehan, August 15, 1886.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, the Italian Colony was moving away in large numbers, spreading to different parts of the city, and the necessity was felt for new Italian churches in those localities.</p>
   <p>Father Moretti, founder of the Church of The Assumption, and first Italian priest in Chicago, died in 1892. His successor, the Rev. Tommaso Moreschini, dedicated his energies to the betterment of the sacred temple, decorating the interior with holy pictures and statues imported from Italy.</p>
   <p>Rev. Pellegrino Grangrandi, priest in charge, contributed a marble altar, which is to be dedicated tomorrow.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0591.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For this event great festivities have been planned. There will be a High Mass and Benediction at the new altar.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
