<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Tribuna Italiana</title>,
<date when="1904-06-25">June 25, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">["The Power of Darkness" Aganist Coribadi and Copernicus]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_1048</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1048.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Tribuna Italiana</title>,
<date when="1904-06-25">June 25, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">["THE POWER OF DARKNESS" AGANIST CORIBADI AND COPERNICUS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When we speak of the "Power of Darkness" we do not speak of the famous drama written by Ibsen, but of the Jesuitical Irish, by that we refer to the fanatical ignorance and intolerance against Giuseppe Garibaldi, the hero of two worlds, and Copernicus, the great German astronomer and philosopher, who was followed by the great Italian, Galileo Galilei, who was tortured by the Holy See, for believing "The sun stands still while the earth goes around it."</p>
   <p>Tuesday night at the meeting of the Board of Education, the names of Garibaldi and Copernicus, suggested for two public schools, were brought before the Board and were discarded - ten to nine respectively. Yet there are three public schools named after three Irish saloon-keepers. Letters of protest sent by Italians to the president of the Board were read by the secretary, but they were not enough to change the attitude of the Board. We are pleased to say that not one Italian wrote protesting against the name of Garibaldi. Therefore, the statement made by Mrs. O'Keefe and the other Irishmen, who are on the school-naming committee, that our countrymen <pb facs="5425702_2_1049.jpg" n="2"/>seriously objected to the name of Garibaldi being given to the old school on W. Polk street, is no more than a lie.</p>
   <p>We also believe that H. E. Monsigner Quigley, Archbishop of Chicago, ordered the Italian families not to send their children to the school if it was named after Garibaldi. This clearly shows the hatred of the Irish priests and scholars against Garibaldi. The Reverend Father Dunne, in his letter to the New World, which we translated into Italian, stated, "We prefer the devil rather than Garibaldi."</p>
   <p>Mr. Cameron, a senior member of the Board, together with Mr. Durante, editor of L'Italia, held a conference with Mr. Cooley, superintendent of the school, and after a half-hour's discussion, they agreed that the name of Garibaldi would be given to that school. Then at the Board meeting, they decided to have the name of President Polk. At first nearly all of the members were duly interviewed, and a memorandum was given everyone present at the meeting, on which was written every reason why the school should be named after Garibaldi.</p>
   <p>This victory for the Irish will be of no importance. Through the efforts of the new members of the Board of Education, who will be appointed within the <pb facs="5425702_2_1050.jpg" n="3"/>next fifteen days by Mayor Harrison, the victory can change into defeat. We hope that the mayor, when selecting new members, will appoint an Italian to the Board of Education.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
