<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>L'italia</title>
      <date when="1911-11-25">Nov. 25, 1911</date>
      <title level="a">Donations</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_1020</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1020.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>L'Italia</title>
     <date when="1911-11-25">Nov. 25, 1911</date>
     <title level="a">Donations</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italian Red Cross of Chicago sent 4,000 lire, for the benefit of the families of the deceased soldiers of the Italian Turkish War subscribed to by the Colony of Chicago. The Committee of the Italian Red Cross of Chicago, has sent the following letter to the President of the Sicilian Union.</p>
   <p>Dear President:</p>
   <p>In the name of the Italian Red Cross of Chicago we wish to express our sincere thanks for the generous contribution of $2,000 given by the members of your society for the Benefit of the Families of Dead Soldiers of the Italian Turkish War.</p>
   <p>We congratulate you and your society for the splendid contribution</p>
   <p>We Remain</p>
   <p>The Committee of the Red Cross</p>
   <p>Dr. Cav. C. Volini</p>
   <p>Dr. Cav. A. Lagorio</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Pagano, secretary</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1021.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A telegram sent to the King of Italy by the Sicilian Union Mutual Benefit Society.</p>
   <p>To the King of Italy:</p>
   <p>Rome, Italy</p>
   <p>The Sicilian Union Mutual Benefit Society to show their sorrow and gratitude, for the deceased ones, sends $2,000 to your majesty to be distributed to mothers, wives, and orphans, of the deceased heroes, in the name of civilization and progress and the greatness of our native land, Italy.</p>
   <p>King Victor Emmanuel answers the telegram as follows:</p>
   <p>President of the Sicilian Union Mutual Benefit Society, Chicago His Majesty sends his sincere thanks to this mutual benefit society for your patriotic offer.</p>
   <p>A telegram was sent to Mr. Hearst to notify him of the banquet to be given in his honor by the Italians of Chicago:</p>
   <p>William Randolph Hearst, New York</p>
   <p>The Sicilian Union, the largest Italian society in Chicago wishes to express its sincere thanks for your sincere and courageous conduct in favoring the Italians during the Italian-Turkish War. The society has voted to give a banquet in your <pb facs="5425702_2_1022.jpg" n="3"/>honor, in the near future, given by the Italian Colony of this city at what ever time convenient to you. Can you notify the committee giving the date, the month, and the hour when you will be present?</p>
   <p>Mr. Hearst accepted the invitation, gladly, and has fixed the date for the banquet as December 15, 1911.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
