<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1920-09-12">September 12, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Sacred Duty of Our Colony</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0859</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0859.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1920-09-12">September 12, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE SACRED DUTY OF OUR COLONY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As the notices continue to come in with news of more earthquakes, the spectacle of death, destruction and misery attains a vaster and more terrible size. The eyes of the world are turned on Italy with an impetus of solidarity and sympathy. All the petty hates have vanished. In the hearts of the civilized world there is but one sentiment; The sentiment of brotherliness and grief enfolding the many who have piteously lost their homes and their loved ones in this tragic twist of nature.</p>
   <p>The Italians in America today, feel themselves very close to the Italians in Italy. The tie that binds us in adversity has shortened distances and the terrible vision has been brought within sight of all. We do not believe any stimulus is necessary to the accomplishment of our duty. The voice of our heart cries loudly to be heard and all those who have a conscience and a sincere thought for Italy know that no sacrifice is too great for those who are suffering pain and bitterness beyond the power of imagination. Our colony will do again what it has done during the national catastrophes in the past.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0860.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Italians of Chicago will sacrifice on the altar of duty all their petty wraths and resentments, and will unite enmasse to do all that is possible for the relief of the earthquake victims. The colony, we are sure, will answer this appeal with enthusiasm and will again demonstrate that its Italianism is a concrete reality that can accomplish the impossible when required, in a beautiful and generous cause.</p>
   <p>His Excellency, Baron Camillo Romano Anezzano, Italian ambassador in Washington, has sent the following telegram to the Italian Consul in Chicago, Conte Giulio Bologuesi, in which he acknowledges receipt of the offer of the Delegation of the Italian Red Cross in Chicago and finds much pleasure in the initiative taken by the colony for the victims of that disaster.</p>
   <p>Italian Consul, Chicago - Much pleased at speedy, generous initiative for earthquake victims. My thanks to all who help.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Romano Anezzano.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
