<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title level="a">Carrying On</title>," <title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy, Illinois Lodge</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1937-04">April 1937</date>, p. 4.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title level="a">Carrying On</title>," <title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy, Illinois Lodge</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1937-04">April 1937</date>, p. 4.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before discussing with you the purpose and the contents of my future contributions to our most worthy monthly bulletin, I wish to take this opportunity of thanking, with absolute sincerity, the worthy officers and members of the Grand Lodge - Order Sons of Italy in America, and especially those of Lodge Chicago Lawn, piloted by our esteemed and very capable Venerable, Joseph Ardizzone, for the honor bestowed upon me in accepting me as one in such a noble organization. What could be nobler than what is symbolically expressed in our insignia, "Liberty, Equality and Brotherhood."</p>
   <p>It is beyond my humble capacity to try to express my innermost feelings towards you as brother members, therefore, in order to show further my appreciation, I accepted with joy the invitation tendered to me by our most worthy leader, Chevalier J. Spatuzza, attorney, to <pb facs="5425702_2_0708.jpg" n="2"/>contribute to the mentioned bulletin.</p>
   <p>The choice of my topics for discussion is guided by several motives. I shall briefly mention what I consider the principal ones.</p>
   <p>First of all we must remember that the requisite of good citizenship is not only the knowledge and obedience of the fundamental laws of a nation, but also some knowledge of the historical background upon which the nation was founded. The historical background to which I am referring, as a scientist, is the historical development of science including the great men who made such epochal history. The nation in question is our great country, Italy.</p>
   <p>With this knowledge in reserve we are able to inform our friends of other nations what constitutes the very essence of our great Italian <pb facs="5425702_2_0709.jpg" n="3"/>civilization. On the other hand, they shall then be better able, if they are willing to accept facts, to conclude for themselves what the world owes Italy.</p>
   <p>The historical background is necessary in order to fully appreciate the significance of the present problems facing us, because the future of a nation or an individual, with absolutely no exception, depends on its past as well as on its present state of affairs. In short, it depends upon the very foundation upon which it was originally built. If built on solid ground, so to say, we are certain to advance with radiant colors, but if built on quicksands we are certain to perish in shameful defeat.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0710.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In order to fulfill the above purpose I shall therefore take up the historical development of such sciences as mathematics, physics, astronomy, chemistry, medicine, etc.</p>
   <p>I do hope that the program outlined above will serve its purpose, and spur you on to further individual study. It is with that hope that I am devoting my time to such writings.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Amelotte Emilio</p>
   <p>E. N. Prof. Emilio Amelotte of the University of Chicago, in graciously accepting an invitation to write for the bulletin, has rendered the Order an invaluable service if the Order has the very important task of contributing to and fostering the mental education of its members.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0711.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>His articles, treating subjects of general interest, should especially appeal to the ever increasing number of college boys and girls who every day join us.</p>
   <p>Being part and parcel of the new generation of Italo-Americans upon whom depends the future of our Order and the prestige of our race, Professor Amellotte's efforts are primarily directed to those from whom he expects a cordial response.</p>
   <p>The editor, in tendering Professor Amellotte sincere thanks, hopes that his articles not only meet with the approval of our readers but that they may prove to be an incentive to others that they may follow on the path he has blazed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
