<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy</title> - Grand Lodge of Illinois,
<date when="1932-03">March 1932</date>, p. 2.
<title level="a">Italo - Americans</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0737</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0737.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy - Grand Lodge of Illinois</title>,
<date when="1932-03">March 1932</date>, p. 2.
<title level="a">ITALO - AMERICANS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is strange, very strange, how the young Italo- American men and women of today shut their eyes to the plainest facts and live in oblivion and absolute ignorance of the romantic language and customs of the land of their fathers. Busy in their daily tasks and pleasures, swept into the whirl of thought and feeling of the day, they care not nor stop one moment to inquire just a little concerning their parent's nativity. They dwell in the thought of the modern world. Hastily, not infrequently superficially, and if asked of the land of birth of their parents, the majority answer in the negative or a care not manner.</p>
   <p>Our young people have dropped into the furrows of modern life, their sould within them have been smothered, their intelligence has become mechanical and they seem to live only for the day, forgetful of the morrow, never once reviewing the past.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0738.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, it is not wholly their own fault for they have been placed in this environment and have followed exclusively the teachings presented them. Their own parents have also been lax in not planting within them the rhythmic beauty of the language and the historic past of the land from whence they migrated.</p>
   <p>Even in the dialect one will show a habit that should not cause embarrassment. Our language is not one withered by age nor staled by custom. It is one adopted from the gradual progression of the race embodying all the past literary, political, and artistic culture. It is one portraying vividly the struggle, emotions and faith of our people.</p>
   <p>It is not our purpose to criticize our young Italo-Americans nor to make them feel ashamed but to inspire within them a duty which they have neglected and which probably is not entirely by their own fault.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0739.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>United in mind and feeling we think that the children of all Italians should have some knowledge of Italy, her language and traditions, her past and her present role in world diplomacy, and that they should become more interested in the purpose and aims of our organization.</p>
   <p>We also think that it is the duty of every father to teach his sons and daughters the language of his country, and that to be born of Italian parentage is a mark of honor, wisdom and nobility.</p>
   <p>The young Italo-Americans of today should be curious, eager for new impressions, and should at all times respect this great country in which they live and serve her in every capacities possible.</p>
   <p>They should be honest and industrious and should always remember that their nativity, alone, gives them an advantage towards mankind, a success of life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
