<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy</title>-Grand Lodge of Illinois,
<date when="1932-03">March, 1932</date>. p. 1.
<title level="a">The Aims of This Organization</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy-Grand Lodge of Illinois</title>,
<date when="1932-03">March, 1932</date>. p. 1.
<title level="a">THE AIMS OF THIS ORGANIZATION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Order, Sons of Italy, is founded on the principles of liberty, equality, and brotherhood.</p>
   <p>On the basis of those principles it proposes to unite into one group the Italians in America, the Dominion of Canada, territories and dependencies and Italians who have the requisites desired by the Laws of the Order, wherever they may be found, with due regard for differences in religions, philosophic and political opinions.</p>
   <p>To promote among these Italians moral, intellectual and material amelioration and thus, emancipate the masses from every prejudice and superstition.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0349.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To teach them the benefits of mutual assistance and humanitarian foresight, instilling in the mind of its members, principles in harmony with the modern conceptions of social unity and stigmatizing all that which has to do with privilege and favoritism.</p>
   <p>To concur with all its force for the protection of each member, and operate so that in every colonial initiative or movement, the Sons of Italy, in unison, shall take the action suggested by the circumstances.</p>
   <p>To perpetuate the flame of Italian culture and maintain in its integrity faith in the future of that culture, while at the same time to be generous with respect for the land which harbors us.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0350.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To spread the conviction that to take an active part in the political life of America is a leading factor towards social betterment. To that end the Order will encourage and assist those who are in the process of becoming American citizens.</p>
   <p>To support any initiative for the diffusing of the Italian language in America by adopting it as the official language of the Order.</p>
   <p>To give every assistance to projects for the benefit of Italians, and to jealously guard all monuments and memorials existing in America in commemoration of Italian heroes and geniuses.</p>
   <p>To defend the conviction that the Italian has a mental capacity sufficient to be considered an effective factor in the social progress and greatness of this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
