<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-07-19">July 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Our Solidarity with the Socialists of Italy</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_1009</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1009.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-07-19">July 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SOLIDARITY WITH THE SOCIALISTS OF ITALY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1 - Comrades and sympathizers!</p>
   <p>During the next three months the Socialist party in Italy will fight one of its most memorable election campaigns. The Italian proletariat, beaten in its strikes, fired upon in its demonstrations, shipped off to an unjust war with its protests unheeded and its groans stifled, facing starvation because of unemployment, taxed to the limit, robbed by a thieving government, manhandled by bosses, by priests, and by the police, is finally in a position to raise its voice and have its say.</p>
   <p>One little word on a piece of paper, vindication and its freedom. One little word may signify for the proletariat of today, and for future generations, justice, liberty, and equality.</p>
   <p>Comrades! We must in some way aid our comrades in Italy. In some way we must demonstrate our sympathy for their aims in the coming battle.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1010.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They need more than verbal support. They are not lacking in energy nor in initiative. They need money, the lack of which is so prevalent in Italy, and without which the fight cannot be carried on. Without money an intensive electoral campaign cannot be promoted. Propaganda diffused through the medium of newspapers, placards, meetings, pamphlets, and books requires ample funds in order to be effective.</p>
   <p>To send money is the practical solution within our power. The more we send, the more we can influence the outcome of the campaign.</p>
   <p>The Executive Committee of the Italian Federation of the Socialist party hereby launches an appeal to all comrades and readers of La Parola and cherishes the hope that a favorable answer will be returned from every corner of the United States.</p>
   <p>Comrades, get busy! Let every one of you take a petition to his neighbor and his friends in the colony and solicit money. The chances are that you will be surprised at the number of our compatriots who will gladly contribute to the success of the campaign in Italy.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1011.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And every one in making his contribution may say: "This is my protest against an unjust war and against the misery, the unemployment, and the illiteracy which afflict my fatherland; this is my protest against the clerical ignorance, against the ferocity of the police, and against the governmental corruption which dishonors my country."</p>
   <p>All funds should be sent to the Central Committee of the Italian Socialist party. It is inadvisable to send any money to individuals, since to divide is to weaken. The directors of the Socialist party of Italy are in a better position to judge what will be the best way to spend this money.</p>
   <p>As soon as the funds begin to come in, La Parola will publish lists of the contributors.</p>
   <p>Italo-American workers! It is not true that we cannot help our comrades in Italy.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1012.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>From this side of the Atlantic, we can in large measure influence the result of the political campaign which will terminate in October. Our contributions will be a protest against that corrupt Third Italian Government of the monarchy, the priests, and the bosses. May our demonstration of affection for our Italian comrades and of solidarity with them be enthusiastic!</p>
   <p>Let every man do his share!</p>
   <p>The Executive Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
