<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1919-07">July, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Commemoration of Italian Constitution Day</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1919-07">July, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">COMMEMORATION OF ITALIAN CONSTITUTION DAY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, June 1, Italian Constitution Day was solemnly observed at the offices of the Italian Chamber of Commerce, and a vermouth party was given for the Chicago Italians, who received the insignia of the Commendator and the Cross of Chevalier of the Crown. The guests of honor were Dr. A. Lagoria, Dr. C. Volini, S. Malato, Judge B. Barasa, (absent), G. Rigali, O. Durante, and P. Russo who were raised to Commendators and received the title of "Chevalier of the Crown."</p>
   <p>Count G. Bolognesi, Italian Consul, gave a brief but eloquent speech, recalling the heroic sacrifices of Italy during the war, the generous cooperation of the whole colony in Chicago and especially the newly decorated members toward the fatherland and ended:</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0430.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"That the inviolable aspirations of Italy should be sanctioned by the Paris Conference, which is the desire of all the Italians commemorating Constitution Day, which signifies the seal of the Unity of Italy realized today with the redemption of Trento and Trieste and we firmly hope of Fiume."</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Lagoria then spoke for the members who had been honored. At the suggestion of Mr. C. Palamba, secretary of the Chamber, a telegram was sent to the King of Italy.</p>
   <p>"His Majesty, The King of Italy,</p>
   <p>Rome, Italy,</p>
   <p>"On commemorating statue day by those who received honors, the Italian Chamber of Commerce sends to the heroic King wishes for greater victories."</p>
   <p>F. Bragno, president.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0431.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The local press was represented by A. Mastrovalerio, A. Ferrari, and N. La Franco. Mr. Vecchione, who was unable to attend because of illness, sent a letter to the secretary in which he congratulated the new officers. Mr. Canini, vice president, was also absent because of the recent death of his mother.</p>
   <p>In answer to the telegram above sent by the Chamber of Commerce to His Majesty, the King of Italy, the King replied:</p>
   <p>"President of the Italian Chamber of Commerce,</p>
   <p>"His Majesty, the King is very thankful for the kind thoughts, and for the patriotic votes."</p>
   <p>Mittioli.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
