<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy</title><date when="1936-10">October 1936</date>, Vol. X, p.3.
<title level="a">The Banquet of October 12</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0391</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0391.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Grand Lodge of Illinois - Order Sons of Italy</title><date when="1936-10">October 1936</date>, Vol. X, p.3.
<title level="a">THE BANQUET OF OCTOBER 12</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The appeal launched by our Order for a banquet to appropriately commemorate Columbus Day, which was legally declared an official holiday by the founders of the organization, received enthusiastic support from our members and many Italians of Chicago. Quests of honor were the 1936 graduates of Italian birth or extraction from the colleges or universities of our country. All the graduates are residents of Illinois.</p>
   <p>Grand Venerable, Cavaliere George Spatuzza, spoke in English of the event that was being commemorated. He said: "We are gathered here this evening under the auspices of the Grand Lodge of the State of Illinois of the Order Sons of Italy in America, to commemorate the 444th anniversary of the discovery of the Western Hemisphere by Christopher Columbus.</p>
   <p>"We are also here to initiate what we fervently hope may become a yearly event in the history of the activities of our people within the commonwealth of Illinois - honoring the 1936 university and college graduates of Italian birth or extraction residing within the confines of our state as a symbol of appreciation and rejoicing for their achievements in the field of learning, and as an expression of good wishes on the part of our community in the undertaking of <pb facs="5425702_2_0392.jpg" n="2"/>the respective duties that their particular profession or degree of learning calls for."</p>
   <p>Cavilere Spatuzza at the end of his speech presented the first orator of the evening, Mr. Mario Palmieri, who is head of the Chicago section of the Dante Alighieri Society. Mr. Palmieri gave a resume of the main historical events which occured after the discovery of America by Columbus.</p>
   <p>Other speakers were Michael Rosinia, City Prosecutor of the City of Chicago and Giovanni di Silvestri, Supreme Venerable of the Order. Both Mr. Rosinia and Mr. Silvestri spoke of the increased prestige of the Italians throughout the world, because of Mussolini's admirable conquest of Ethiopia.</p>
   <p>In introducing the Italian Consul, Dr. Mario Carosi, Mr. Spatuzza said: "I take great pride in addressing our greetings to Dr. Carosi, Italian Consul in Chicago. My relations with Dr. Carosi in his capacity of agent for the Italian government in Chicago have been very pleasant. I have admired him since his first day in Chicago. Besides being cultured and courteous, he has a clear understanding of the needs of the Italians in America. I have asked him to speak tonight and proudly present him to you, not only as a representative for Victor Emmanuel <pb facs="5425702_2_0393.jpg" n="3"/>and Mussolini but also as our very good friend."</p>
   <p>Dr. Carosi spoke on Italy, past and present; on Mussolini and the reawakened spirit of national unity with which Italy is today inspired.</p>
   <p>The last speaker was Dr. Ermelinda Mastri, one of the 1936 Loyola graduates. Her speech was followed by a musical program in which Nicola Berardinelli, of the Berardinelli School of Opera, Frida Savini, and John Pane-Gasser sang several operatic arias.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
