<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-05-10">May 10, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Chicago Comrades Fete Morgari</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_1013</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1013.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-05-10">May 10, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHICAGO COMRADES FETE MORGARI</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although Morgari arrived in Chicago practically unexpected and for a visit limited to forty-eight hours, the Italian Socialist clubs were able on short notice to gather at the Milano restaurant and have a drink in his honor.</p>
   <p>Comrade Corti in a brief talk welcomed Morgari in the name of the comrades of Chicago. Corti expressed himself as pleased to know that Morgari would soon be in Italy to resume his fight for the working class.</p>
   <p>Morgari was not asked to talk. He seemed to be exhausted in body and in spirit, and that is easy to understand when one considers that he had just crossed a continent which for him contains innumerable things of interest.</p>
   <p>Comrade Morgari will leave Chicago to visit the most important cities of the East. He sails for Italy toward the end of the month, thus completing the tour of the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1014.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>La Parola, in the name of all Italian-American Socialists, salutes Morgari, who is undoubtedly one of the most eminent men of the Italian Socialist party. It hopes that he will continue his present course, never swerving to right or to left but marching straight ahead.</p>
   <p>The suggestion of a lecture tour of America in the near future seemed to find much favor with Morgari, who hinted that it is not an impossibility. The Italian-American Socialist Federation would sponsor the tour.</p>
   <p>(Morgari was a Socialist member of the Italian Chamber of Deputies). Translator's note.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
