<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-05-23">May 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Carotis' Proposal to the Italian Government for an Investigation of the Lodging House of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0984</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0984.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-05-23">May 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CAROTIS' PROPOSAL TO THE ITALIAN GOVERNMENT FOR AN INVESTIGATION OF THE LODGING HOUSE OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last week, Comrade Caroti, member of the Italian Chamber of Deputies, introduced a proposal for an investigation of the clerical acts committed by Consul Bolognesi in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It seems that the Consul does not move a finger in behalf of our countrymen without asking for the help of the priests and nuns.</p>
   <p>We are informed, in a telegram from Italy, that the Undersecretary of Foreign Affairs, Mr. Borsarelli, answering the proposal of Caroti, declared himself in favor of Consul Bolognesi, and approved his policy of entrusting the lodging house for the needy of Chicago Italians to the worthy Sisters of the Sacred Heart.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0985.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are not a little surprised by the approval of the Italian Government of the clerical conduct of Consul Bolognesi, and we do not expect that Mr. Bolognesi will even be scolded by his Government.</p>
   <p>Our goal, completely reached, was to have the question discussed by the Italian Chamber of Deputies, and to thus let all liberal Italy know how the taxpayer's money is spent in foreign lands.</p>
   <p>Two Italian newspapers commented benignly on the decision rendered by the Undersecretary. They said that the act of the Italian Consul of Chicago "has received the commendation of the colony."</p>
   <p>This assertion is completely false. Proof of this is the fact that the Consul closed the lodging house "for lack of funds," because the miserly leaders of Chicago's Italian colony, after giving a few pennies, refused to support it any longer.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0986.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Where was the approval of our colony? What were the colony's comments on the lodging house? All were protests against the Consul's attitude.</p>
   <p>And the ten famous benefactors, led by Dr. Volini, who were supposed to support the shelter home, independent of the subsidy of the Italian government--where have they hidden themselves?</p>
   <p>Once more we affirm that our campaign was not a protest against the lodging house as an institution, but against the methods of the Consul, who used that institution for [the dissemination of] monastic propaganda.</p>
   <p>Such institutions must be organized without any distinction of creed or sect.</p>
   <p>Our colony, like those of other nationalities, has energy enough to erect and support any institution only if it is based on humanitarian sentiments--and <pb facs="5425702_2_0987.jpg" n="4"/>not on the desires of private and partisan propagandists.</p>
   <p>We Socialists do not believe in the debasing system of philanthropy, but we are not against it when it is done for purposes other than deceitful political or religious objectives.</p>
   <p>However, we think that our propaganda is much more effective than that of any philanthropic institution, because if the poor people would follow the teaching of our propaganda, there would not be any more unemployed, nor would there be any necessity for a lodging house, clerical Consuls or miserly self-appointed leaders of the colony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
