<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-12-20">Dec. 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Colonial Chronicles Dedicated to the Italian Consul in Chicago</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Italian Womens' Welfare Society</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_1002</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1002.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-12-20">Dec. 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">COLONIAL CHRONICLES DEDICATED TO THE ITALIAN CONSUL IN CHICAGO</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Italian Womens' Welfare Society</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>My dear Mr. Consul:</p>
   <p>You may recall my writing to you in one of my other letters about the welfare society of the Italian women of this city.</p>
   <p>I wish to repeat: if the administration of this Society is not changed, it will have the same end as the Dante Alighieri, because it operates on the same basis, that is, vanity and personal ambition. To you, therefore, falls the responsibility of reviving this useful organization, not only because it is Italian, but because it was initiated by your superior, our Ambassador to Washington.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1003.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As you can see for yourself, the Society is losing ground every day. You are aware of the fiasco which resulted from this year's dance given in the Auditorium Hotel's most aristocratic ballroom. Despite the most extensive newspaper publicity carried on for two months up to the date of the dance; despite the arduous work of the committee, composed of the most prominent women in the colony, it was a veritable fiasco. Of one hundred and twenty-five thousand Italians in Chicago, only two hundred and fifty attended and that number included the members and their families. So, actually, only about one hundred outsiders attended.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, the newspaper L'Italia boldly reported that the attendance reached the five hundred mark and that it was a great success, of which the colony could well be proud.</p>
   <p>One should, it is true, encourage beneficent institutions, but they must be institutions with a serious program, and led by capable persons. In our <pb facs="5425702_2_1004.jpg" n="3"/>colony, especially among the women, that element is missing. We have good mothers, good housekeepers, but for administering a society, we have no one. The newspaper L'Italia is fully aware of this, but dares not mention it -- for fear, perhaps -- of losing subscribers.</p>
   <p>Therefore, Mr. Consul, if you do not wish to see this Society disappear, do as I advise, without considering the fact that the advice comes from the [minority] in our colony. I advise you to enter as a member, to bring in with you others of good will, and to try to persuade the brave women that the best thing for the organization is to ally itself with an American Charitable organization -- for in doing that -- it would be acting for its own good.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
