<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1920-06-27">June 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">[Independence Day Celebration]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0419</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0419.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1920-06-27">June 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">[INDEPENDENCE DAY CELEBRATION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To those who bemoan the lack of Italianism in our colony we will demonstrate the fallacy of their assertion when inumerable Italians will meet to celebrate July Fourth.</p>
   <p>The Lega Nazionale Fiume, has wanted to pay a debt of gratitude to Senator Sherman, for his support of Italy in a critical period and has invited him to participate at the celebration of American Independence, coupled with the anniversary of the birth of Giuseppe Garibaldi, the Italian national hero. In order to make an impressive showing, the Lega has sent invitations to all Italian associations. A large number have already sent word that they will take part in the demonstration. Those who have given no indication cannot accuse the Lega of playing favorites.</p>
   <p>The Lega Nazionale Fiume has done much for the Italian cause. It has contributed a great deal to the creation of an atmosphere favorable to Italy's aspirations <pb facs="5425702_2_0420.jpg" n="2"/>in the U. S. Senate and checkmating its opponents. It does not need publicity, but a certain quietude, in order to develop its program of Italianism and sincere Americanism.</p>
   <p>The Lega has decreed that any one using its name or the organization, to further his own personal ends, shall be expelled from membership. This clause was inserted in the regulations to block any attempt on the part of unscrupulous persons to hide their ignoble purposes under a mantle of false patriotism. Since the Lega is not aiming at personal ambitions, why does its existence inspire so much envy? Only in existence ten months, it has a membership and vastness of program that make it respected in the colonies throughout the U. S. Success will not fail to smile on its efforts for the Fourth of July. It will again be demonstrated that the Italian masses are still inspired by faith and patriotism. The program for the day is varied and interesting and will be carried out with competence. Senator Sherman and Miss Italia Garibaldi, will be guests of honor and those who attend, which should be all the Italians in the colony, will not regret having been present.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0421.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Republican presidential candidate, Warren G. Harding, who is a sincere friend of Italy and of the president of the Lega Nazionale Fiume, writes as follows: "Although I cannot accept your kind invitation I assure you that it would have given me much pleasure had it been possible for me to be present." The reason why Mr. Harding cannot accept the invitation is that the Republican National Committee, which has charge of the campaign, does not want to arouse any antagonism by having the candidate accept certain invitations and refuse others. In the preceding election, Hughes was beaten in California for that very reason. Senator Harding will speak only from the front porch of his home for the entire campaign, thereby avoiding any charges of partiality.</p>
   <p>The banquet will be held in the Red Room of the Hotel La Salle, an ideally cool place for this hot weather. Toastmaster for the occasion is the lawyer, Stefano Malato who will be assisted by Mr. Vincenzo Tomabene. Among the speakers, besides the guests of honor, will be Edward Brundage, Attorney General for Illinois, and Senator Medill McCormick who is the other senator from Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
