<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-06-27">June 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting of Protest against Policies of Italian Government</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0981</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0981.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-06-27">June 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING OF PROTEST AGAINST POLICIES OF ITALIAN GOVERNMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday at Bowen Hall, in Hull House, a mass-meeting was held by that part of our colony which resents the bloody reaction accomplished in Italy by the Government of Salandra, Premier of Italy.</p>
   <p>The meeting room was crowded with sympathizers attracted as usual, by the great event in our colony.</p>
   <p>At 8: o'clock, Dr. A. Molinari, acting as chairman, opened the meeting. He then gave the floor to Mr. Carlo Bartalini, who praised the solidarity displayed by the Italian workers of Chicago by financially and morally helping their brothers, who are at present, suffering in Italy.</p>
   <p>Dr. Molinari said that the Italian workers in need of substanial help, which help may be given only by contributing and not simply by meetings <pb facs="5425702_2_0982.jpg" n="2"/>of protest and sympathy.</p>
   <p>For this purpose $24.80 was collected among those present, a good beginning for a larger amount to be collected in our colony.</p>
   <p>Then, Mr. Vincent Vacirca, Director of our newspaper, gave a resume of the history of the working-class movement in Romagna. He said that if the overt pretext was the Ancona incident, the real cause of the massacre was a product of the economic situation in Italy: the crises produced by the unproductive war in Libya.</p>
   <p>At the end of the meeting, it was resolved to formulate the following protest: "The Italian workers of Chicago, assembled at a meeting held at Hull House on the evening of June 20, 1914, under the auspices of the Italian federations of the Socialist Party, protest against the assassinations of unarmed Italian people by the agents of the Italian Government, <pb facs="5425702_2_0983.jpg" n="3"/>and pledge their moral and financial solidarity to their brothers in Italy who are struggling for their freedom, and who wish for the early establishment of a Communist Republic."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
