<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1927-08">July-August, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Rev. Pasquale R. De Carlo</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1927-08">July-August, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE REV. PASQUALE R. DE CARLO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Aurora of Philadelphia, in its issue of June 25th, had the following to say about our very dear director the Rev. P. R. De Carlo. We cite the main points of the article:</p>
   <p>We are pleased to make known to our readers that ten Italian ministers are attending this year's Northern Baptist Convention. They are, Basile, Buffa, Cordo, Di Domenica, Franconi, Mangauo, Panizzoli, Saltarelli, Silvestri, Solimene, The Rev. Pasquale R. De Carlo, Presbyterian pastor of that city (Chicago) and Field Secretary for the Presbyterian Church Extension Society, honored the ten Italian ministers with a dinner at an Italian restaurant.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0481.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the course of the dinner, the writer of this article gave a short speech in which he sketched briefly the missionary career of our brother De Carlo, whom he has known for thirty years, praising his gifts as missionary, pastor, field secretary and organizer on a large scale in the ecclesiastic field, as well as in the field of Italian-American journalism.</p>
   <p>In the latter field, years back, he published a weekly, Il Cittadino, which at that time was considered one of the best Italian-American publications in circulation. Because of his ministerial duties, he was forced to discontinue it, and when it passed into the hands of others it soon went out of existence. At the present time the Rev. De Carlo is publishing a monthly review called The Vita Nuova, well set-up and well edited with a <pb facs="5425702_2_0482.jpg" n="3"/>very artistic cover. He has the collaboration of eminent Italian and American writers. The Rev. Dr. Mangano also talked and praised his kind host.</p>
   <p>The Rev. De Carlo with unequaled modesty thanked the brothers, Di Domenica and Mangano, for their beautiful testimony, and assured them that he is kept informed of the work done among Italians by other denominations, following with interest their conquests for Christianity. He related the story of an Italian who came to attend the Eucharistic Congress of Chicago, the past year, and had been converted to the Gospel after reading the Bible.</p>
   <p>After a vote of thanks given to De Carlo, the ten Italian ministers went back to the Coliseum where the convention was being held. They were much satisfied at having attended because they had learned much to pass on to their congregations. The following year this convention is being held in Detroit, Mich., one week before the Baptist World Convention which is being held in Toronto, Canada.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
