<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous - "<title level="a">Important Revelations by Rev. P. R. De Carlo</title>," <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1929-06">June 1929</date>, pp. 6-7.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0770</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0770.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous - "<title level="a">Important Revelations by Rev. P. R. De Carlo</title>," <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1929-06">June 1929</date>, pp. 6-7.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a great satisfaction to note that the Italian colony is waking up and taking much interest in the "accord between the Italian government and the Pope." From the comments it appears that all the Italians and all the press have approved the irrefutable and stern conduct of the head of the Italian government, who settled the dispute with the following words:</p>
   <p>His Excellency Mussolini said: "There are two distinct sovereignties well distinguished, perfectly and reciprocally recognized. But in the state, the church is not sovereign and not even free. It is not sovereign for the contradiction which does not allow it to be. It is not even free, because its institutions and its members are subject to the laws of the state and are subject to the special clauses of the agreement. For that reason the situation may be so defined: 'The church is a sovereign state within the kingdom of Italy.' The Catholic church with certain prerogatives is loyally and willingly recognized. Freedom of worship for all other creeds is recognized."</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0771.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thus we have a reason for demonstrating our satisfaction in opposition to those who have the belief that the Catholic Church is in a condition to take possession of the Italian Kingdom and Mussolini's Government.</p>
   <p>This statement made by the man who rules the Nation, like water, extinguishess the fire of enthusiasm of the opposition and left them undeceived.</p>
   <p>The real Italian citizen, who has respect and devotion for his Mother Land, prefers his patriotism as against the pretenses of the Roman Church whose intention is to substitute itself for God and the King. The Church's pretentions to temporal power, this time, have been broken.</p>
   <p>The unanimous opinion expressed by the Italians shows that they had a clear perception of the event and saw, far ahead, the road of civil progress.</p>
   <p>Certainly we have cooperated in moulding public opinion in this historic event with our articles in Vita Nuova, in which we stated our immutable support of <pb facs="5425702_2_0772.jpg" n="3"/>Mussolini and his Government, and with the speeches made by our Director, the Rev. P. R. De Carlo, Pastor of the Presbyterian Church of St. John, every Sunday, at the services.</p>
   <p>It is unnecessary to extoll the efforts made by Rev. De Carlo. He is very modest and his achievements, made with the faith of an apostle, aimed at the glorification of God and the conversion of those who foolishly are not following the doctrine of the Gospel.</p>
   <p>He is very well known to our colony for the help and benefit he has given to friends and adversaries, and to many of our Italians for whom he has often obtained employment.</p>
   <p>Rev. De Carlo, who is treating the subject "The Christianity of Christ" in opposition to "Christianity of the Pope", and the "Blessed Virgin in the Bible", has used irrevocable arguments and with plain and clear language, has enlightened the minds and hearts of his listeners. In mentioning the question of the "Concordat" he said that only the State has the right to arrange the moral and <pb facs="5425702_2_0773.jpg" n="4"/>spirited laws which are the people's guide. He was deploring the excessive enthusiasm of the Priests, as well as the exaggerated criticism of his colleagues who, with their aptitude, are damaging the Evangelical cause in Italy.</p>
   <p>We are not in a condition to reproduce all the speeches of Rev. De Carlo, but we can affirm that we draw from them enough knowledge to help highten the enthusiasm and the prestige of a faith, which many do not know.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
