<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-03-28">Mar. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">To the Sound and Honest Part of Our Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-03-28">Mar. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE SOUND AND HONEST PART OF OUR COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our colonies in America, as you know, [have experienced] many outrages which are discussed every day with indignation and shame for the reputation of Italy.</p>
   <p>You know very well the origin and development of such conditions better than any Italian writer, who, after a rapid excursion through the United States, gives an erroneous statement of the condition of our colonies.</p>
   <p>You, as the sound and honest part of our colony, have the great fault of remaining absolutely inactive in correcting such outrages.</p>
   <p>Is that outstanding man a jail-bird type? Was he a swindler, thief, a murderer? Still he is respected, esteemed, elected president of a society; he sponsors banquets and patriotic celebrations, and is supported by misinformed Americans for a public office.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0138.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And you, knowing that the prominent man is unworthy, not only remain quiet, but you join the others in bowing to him, in shaking his hand, in complimenting and praising him. Thus, that self-styled outstanding man, a regular knave, is going places and rises every day to higher esteem; thanks to your indirect help. Further, he uses the position he has gained to accomplish other knavery.</p>
   <p>The recovery of our colonies will be possible, only when the honest people influence the Italo-American public opinion with their own sound and honest sentiments, instead of bowing to the unscrupulous and accepting the public opinion manufactured by the native element.</p>
   <p>The moral recovery of our colonies cannot be accomplished by the American or the Italian Government. It can be accomplished only when honest Italians are organized in a special public health committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0139.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If we are unable to fight the rascals with law at least we must try to fight them through pressure by the masses, the victims of their malfeasances.</p>
   <p>In our colonies, the Italian press, with few exceptions, is the main lever for the elevation of these rascals, and is an accessory to all the disgraceful things befalling our colonies.</p>
   <p>It is, then, upon the Italian press that the sound and honest part of our communities should use its influence and moral control.</p>
   <p>I exposed one of these newspapers, and now I leave it to you, honest Italians, to judge it.</p>
   <p>Now you have the opportunity to tell one hundred thousand Italians which newspaper is or is not honest. Your judgment will have more weight <pb facs="5425702_2_0140.jpg" n="4"/>than that of a regular American court, and thus many other newspapers may refrain from wrongdoing to avoid an inquisition of themselves.</p>
   <p>By a privilege granted me by Mr. Parisi, director of the exposed newspaper, I will beg, personally, a few [representative] gentlemen to constitute themselves an honorary jury, and to inquire about the honorableness of the newspaper Il Movimento. They may then render a verdict as they see fit.</p>
   <p>I hope, and will try hard, to have our Consul, Mr. Bolognesi, as president of said honorary jury--and thus place him in a position to render a great patriotic service to the Italian colony of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
