<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1925-06">June 1925</date>.
<title level="a">In the Name of Justice</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1925-06">June 1925</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE NAME OF JUSTICE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We regret exceedingly to note that from time to time the American press, due apparently to a false, unfounded, and deplorable race prejudice, has attacked unmercifully the Italian people of the United States and, more especially, the Italians coming from Sicily, merely because some individuals perpetrate a crime.</p>
   <p>Crime has no nationality! Crimes have been committed and will continue to be committed daily, by the score, by the lawless of other nationalities - Irish, Jews, Germans, Greeks, Americans - and the newspapers, unless it be an exceptionally sensational case, are contented to report it as a simple news item.</p>
   <p>When the crime however, is committed by an Italian, the papers printed in English give it the greatest amount of publicity, using for the purpose, front page space and large headlines, making uncomplimentary remarks that are insulting to the whole Italian race. We do not intend, in the least, to defend those who have killed. The law must take its course and whether <pb facs="5425702_2_0100.jpg" n="2"/>or not justice is done, is a matter that concerns the administrators of the law. We only ask that the editors of the Chicago newspapers accord the Italian people fair play; to refrain from attacking them in a group for the misdeeds of the few; to limit themselves to the cases as they happen without drawing into the vortex of crime, indiscriminately - men and institutions of the highest proven honor and integrity. Journalism must educate and not be prejudiced. The so-called "scoops" brought in by some quixotic reporter should be analyzed before being published; reporters should be instructed to bring in straight and correct information and not rubbish, for publication.</p>
   <p>The Italians are honest, sober, enterprising, and working people. They love their families, and know how to save and sacrifice, that their children may have a good education. They are law abiding and assimilate as easily as the mythical Nordic. If among them there are some who do not respect the law, it is perhaps because those who should see that the law is enforced, ensconce them.</p>
   <p>To have connected the Italo-American National Union, for mutual benefit, <pb facs="5425702_2_0101.jpg" n="3"/>with a regrettable affair that happened in this city recently, simply because those implicated happened to be Sicilians, is absurd, unjust and harmful to an institution, that for the past thirty years has carried on a sincere work of Americanization, moral and economic upbuilding.</p>
   <p>Imaginary shootings, fabricated by unscrupulous policemen are attributed to Italians. Whenever the perpetrator of some wicked deed makes his escape, the statement in the paper is usually to the effect that, "The assassin is supposed to be an Italian;" as though nobody else is capable of committing a crime and escaping.</p>
   <p>By reading some of the Chicago papers the average person might be led to believe that all the crimes committed in this metropolis are perpetrated by Italians and especially by Sicilians; moreover, that the Sicilians are not Italians, because the Straits of Messina seperate them from the mainland.</p>
   <p>It is a historic and undeniable fact, however, that twice in the history of Italy, Sicily has been the keystone in the completion of Italian unity, <pb facs="5425702_2_0102.jpg" n="4"/>aside from having produced some of the best Italian statesmen. A reference to a history of Sicily by Mommsen, and later to one by Prof. A. Pais, might convince the unacquainted what a mighty and important part of the Italian nation's history Sicily has been.</p>
   <p>All this; all the good qualities of the Italians, however, do not seem to avail us. In the eyes of some people we are the newest immigrants here and, therefore the line of least resistance. It is up to all decent Italians and to the members of our organization then, to carry on the good work and to spread the tenets of our organization so that the people of this, our adopted nation, learn to appreciate the value of the good Italians and that they are here to stay and make good Americans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
