<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chamber of Commerce</title>, (Italian)
<date when="1918-06">June 1918</date>.
<title level="a">May 24th</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0436</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0436.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Chamber of Commerce, (Italian)</title><date when="1918-06">June 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MAY 24th</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This date, as did the Renaissance, and the Rebirth of 1870, make a new era in the history of Italy. On May 24, Italy spontaneously without any secret pressure but by the will of the people, declared war on her secular and object enemy, Austria.</p>
   <p>The Italian Colonies of America cannot be apathetic on the recurrence of such a memorable day. The third anniversary of the war was celebrated in Chicago and in the United States with a fervent patriotic spirit.</p>
   <p>The apostle of democracy, Woodrow Wilson proclaimed thisday as "Italian American Day."</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0437.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Italian Chamber of Commerce of Chicago, for this occurrence held a banquet at the Victor House. At the end of the dinner, Mr. Gualano, lawyer, was asked to say a few words on the occasion, and delivered a very patriotic speech. He fluently spoke of our beautiful mother country, land of martyrs and heroes; he praised the strenuous resistance made by Diaz Army at the bloody battle of Piave and closed wishing for an early victory to our and the allied armies.</p>
   <p>Arso Flammo was the official speaker of the evening, his speech being much appreciated and bringing applause.</p>
   <p>At the suggestion of the Vice President Canini a subscription for the Red Cross was opened and $125 in cash collected.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0438.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Two telegrams were sent by the suggestion of Mr. Cararetta, one to President Wilson; and the other to the Italian Ambassador in Washington. After the banquet all the members of the Chamber of Commerce went to the Municipal Pier to attend a patriotic rally of Italians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
