<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title level="a">A Praiseworthy Act of Our Director</title>," <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1928-12">November-December 1928</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0782</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0782.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title level="a">A Praiseworthy Act of Our Director</title>," <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1928-12">November-December 1928</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Christmas holiday season, in which the figure of Jesus of Nazareth irradiates pure, humanity as it has for two thousand years, awakens in us the sacred sentiment of human charity towards the unfortunate and, especially, towards the homeless waifs who will not know Santa Claus with his sack filled with toys.</p>
   <p>We are happy to mention the work of our beloved Director, the Rev. R. De Carlo in behalf of these homeless waifs.</p>
   <p>The Free Home for Homeless Children is located in Turin. It is an outstanding example of a work of love and charity. The Home, which at present gives asylum to thousands of deserted children of Italy, was made possible through the help, sacrifice and constant attention of our director, P. R. De Carlo.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0783.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are pleased to reprint a touching document that will serve as proof of that which we have affirmed, and also several paragraphs of an article which appeared in the Rivista Patria di Roma.</p>
   <p>"Although it was a complex program, with a serious financial situation complicating its realization, it did not perplex the assiduous workers, or the founder of the Home, Mrs. Girand .....</p>
   <p>"We are hoping that others will feel the desire to emulate Chevalier Pasquale Ricciardi De Carlo.</p>
   <p>"With a highly humanitarian and patriotic sentiment shown by the opening and encouraging of a subscription in his widely circulated newspaper, he has aided the Home with thousands of dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0784.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"And the Home has wished, with the following parchment, designed by Chevalier Vulten of Turin, to accord proper recognition to the Director of the Cittadino di Chicago."</p>
   <p>The following is the inscription on the parchment:</p>
   <p>"A Pasquale Ricciardi De Carlo</p>
   <p>Whose noble spirit, cultured mind and fraternal heart</p>
   <p>Is poured out in the columns of his newspaper, Il Cittadino,</p>
   <p>Gathering around him the elite of the Italian colony of Chicago</p>
   <p>For the purpose of transforming that nostalgia for the fatherland far away,</p>
   <p>Into the joy of benefiting the needy children's charity</p>
   <p>The Free Home for Deserted Children</p>
   <p>Sends an affectionate recognition from the little inmates."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
