<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-11-22">Nov. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Giordano Bruno Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-11-22">Nov. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE GIORDANO BRUNO CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One single appeal launched by a comrade has found an echo in a hundred breasts whose owners are ready to sacrifice the years of their youth, to mortify, to abandon the pleasures of life in order to fight the most shameful institution, the most profound plague that afflicts all humanity: the falsehood of clericalism.</p>
   <p>The appeal was received with unexpected enthusiasm, and an organization named after Giordano Bruno, the great liberal martyr and precursor of modern science, is an accomplished fact. The club Giordano Bruno now begins its fearless work, and with the torch of civilization and truth, will clear the maze and lay bare the outrages of which the priests are the perpetrators and the suffering public, the martyrs. The organization, supported by a nucleus <pb facs="5425702_2_0573.jpg" n="2"/>of youths strong in ideals, shall contend against the already numerous clerical organizations, and bring a ray of comfort and hope to the Italian colony of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The club, until the work of organization is fully completed, will hold its meetings in the Men's Club of Hull House, every Friday evening at seven-thirty.</p>
   <p>Every anti-clerical is under a moral obligation to join this organization, and to sacrifice some of his free hours for the edification of the uneducated in this Italian colony. Anyone desiring information may write or come in person to: 1044 West Taylor St.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
