<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1926-01">January 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Commemoration of French Explorers at the Chicago Historical Society</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0637</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0637.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1926-01">January 1926</date>.
<title level="a">COMMEMORATION OF FRENCH EXPLORERS AT THE CHICAGO HISTORICAL SOCIETY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Luigi Carnovale, prominent Chicago Italian writer and place advocate, sent us an account of the ceremonies attendant on the commemoration of the three French explorers, Louis Joliet, Father Marquette, De La Salle, and the Italian, Henry Tonti.</p>
   <p>The official speaker, Prof. Andrew C. Mc Laughlin of the University of Chicago, who replaced Sir Gilbert Parker, brilliantly exalted with a cultured turn of phrasing the Italian origin and characteristics of Tonti.</p>
   <p>The audience composed entirely of Americans applauded enthusiastically. Carnovale was deeply moved.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0638.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the end of the speeches, Mrs. Holmes Forsyth, president of the Illinois Society of the Colonial Dames, and Miss Caroline McIlvaine, Librarian of the Chicago Historical Society, graciously expressed their appreciation for the fact that, at least, one Italian was present at the ceremonies, and Mr. Carnovale expressed the hope that this recognition of Tonti as an Italian, despite much American opposition which Mr. Carnovale had fought incessantly, was satisfactory to him.</p>
   <p>Then Miss McIlvaine, with much pleasure, showed Mr. Carnovale an original document bearing the signature of the great Italian explorer, Tonti. Mr. Carnovale looked with admiration on the authentic signature of the explorer.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0639.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is the duty of Italians of Chicago to carry on the fight by initiating a campaign for the purpose of apotheosizing this Italian, so that he may have the same recognition that is accorded to the other great Italians; Columbus, Cabot (Cabotto), Vespucci, Verazzano.</p>
   <p>Among other things, Chicago Italians should exercise their influence in order that the City Council will give the name of "Tonti Square" or "Tonti Circle" to that space which lies on Wacker Drive, between Wabash and Michigan Avenues, and on which has been placed the tablet commemorating the deeds of the explorers. And, we think this very appropriate since Tonti was one of the first four white men to cross this territory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
