<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1919-02-09">February 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Italian Societies United to Protest against Insidious Jugo-Slav Propaganda</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0894</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0894.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1919-02-09">February 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ITALIAN SOCIETIES UNITED TO PROTEST AGAINST INSIDIOUS JUGO-SLAV PROPAGANDA</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italian Chamber of Commerce of our city, is promoting among the Italian societies of America, a campaign against Jugo-Slav, which wants to forget the fact that it belongs with the conquered nations of yesterday, believing itself capable of limiting the national aspirations of Italy.</p>
   <p>The Jugo-Slavs hiding their imperialistic designs under a work of humility, are accusing Italy of attempting to deprive them of that which they feel to be their own. This hypocritical propaganda is carried on with a maximum amount of lies and whatever their disloyal weapons come to hand. It is necessary therefore, that Italians in America give the mother country a sign of their solidarity in her favor, so as to balk the insidious Jugo-Slav campaign.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0895.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The presidents of the Italian societies are therefore invited to sign the following resolution, sending it to the office of the Italian Chamber of Commerce, Masonic Temple, Room 12.</p>
   <p>The resolution is as follows:</p>
   <p>The Italian societies of ----- which in their membership embrace American citizens of Italian birth and citizens of Italy, who under all circumstances have given indubitable proof of their loyalty to America, to it's institutions; to it's laws; and to it's principles of liberty and democracy, do hereby declare that,</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0896.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Whereas, the unity and independence of the little nationalities long downtrodden by the oppressor is one of the highest ideals of Italian history and tradition; that,</p>
   <p>Whereas, such a purpose, to which the efforts of all civilized nationalities and especially those of the United States of America are directed, does not require or justify the renunciation of Italian territories revindicated through the sacrifices and blood of almost 2,000,000 men; that,</p>
   <p>Whereas, the Treaty of London is not the consecration of Italy to imperialism, but is rather a compromise by which Italy, under pressure of the Slavs, represented at the time by Russia, abandoned vital parts of its own rightful territory in order to give Slavs of the South (Jugo-Slavs) new approaches of the sea; that,</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0897.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Whereas, the difficulties between Italy and Jugo-Slavia which do not yet exist, have been adjusted and settled by the Pact of Rome of April last, in which the leaders of the Jugo-Slav movement sent by the Jugo-Slav Central Committee of which Dr. Trumbic is the chief took part; that,</p>
   <p>Whereas, the Pact of Rome recognized the unalterable character of the Treaty of London, which is a recognition of the sacred rights of Italy, a resolution was adopted declaring that the Italian National Unity is to the interests of the Jugo-Slavs just as the National Unity of the Jugo-Slavs is to the interest of Italy; that,</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0898.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Whereas, the Jugo-Slav agitation which has become most renounced in America, is the particular expression of an imperialism, which replaces the imperialism of Austria by the usurpation of countries which have Italian tradition in history, in geography, in geology as has been established clearly by the writings of Holdric, (English); Prof. Suess, (German); Prof. Koblet Beck and Prof Mannegetta, (Austrian); and of P. E. Jackson, (American); that,</p>
   <p>Whereas, this movement was supported more obstinately by the Croats and Slovenes and by the Slavs, who invaded Italian territory, all of whom fought fiercely on all fronts of the Austrian Monarchy because apparent, gathered in a Congress at Lyback with the purpose of laying the foundations for a great Jugo-Slav kingdom under the dominion of the Hapsburgs; that,</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0899.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Whereas, Jugo-Slavia is only a political term invented by Austria to assimilate Slovenes, Croats and Serbs, who include five nationalities, three written languages with two different alphabets, two religions and five traditions; that,</p>
   <p>Whereas, we are convinced that it would not be just a politic that Italian nationality should remain suppressed in its own house, and that Italian territory artifically peopled by Austria with Slavs should be torn from Italy which set them free through the martyrdom of its sons and sending hundreds of thousands of soldiers to all the war fronts to fight for all the nations and especially the Serbian people; that,</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0900.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Whereas, we are convinced that in the settlement of territorial questions, historic, artificial, social factors; that</p>
   <p>Whereas, we are convinced that this war, fought in the name of liberty, has secured the life and independence of the small people from Teutonic oppression, which devised many means of denationalization and especially an artificial demography, compelling the unnatural migration of races from one territory of the empire to another; that,</p>
   <p>Whereas, such transmigration was particularly directed toward Italian territories, which have simply resisted the nefarious attempts and absorption, even when the Italian population was reduced to a slender minority, which today is awaiting a just revindication from the civilized world, pursuant <pb facs="5425702_2_0901.jpg" n="8"/>to the same principle of nationality, which as it should protect the small peoples against their oppressors, should likewise protect populations against suppression and absorption, in their national dominions; be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, that we protest against the movements of the Jugo-Slav committees' in America, which are attempting to withdraw from the obligations assumed by the Pact of Rome of April last; which are trying to create a movement of antipathy to Italy in America, describing it as an imperialistic nation, while the imperialistic tendencies are really their own, since their purpose is to usurp Italian territories in which Slav elements have intruded; that we <pb facs="5425702_2_0902.jpg" n="9"/>Protest furthermore aganist the erroneous statement that the Pact of Rome denies the Jugo-Slavs access to the sea; when it is a fact that its terms give Italy the lesser part of the Dalmatian Coast, while to the southern Slavs there remains a coast line longer and more important than the entire of Italian coast; that it be</p>
   <p>Resolved finally that the public conscience of the civilized world, fully enlightened by the friends of truth and justice, who base their arguments on natural and historic forces acknowledge and affirmed by all the greatest thinkers, shall be properly informed that it may repudiate the imposition which under whatever form attempts to create Jugo-Slav imperialism, and may recognize against all and above all rights of Italy on Italian territory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
