<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-06-28">June 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Sinister Activities of Clerical Swine</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0698</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0698.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-06-28">June 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">SINISTER ACTIVITIES OF CLERICAL SWINE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3... For some time it has been evident that a religious revival is in progress among the Italians on the near Northwest side of Chicago.</p>
   <p>I say a religious revival, since at the present time certain self-styled Catholics are making the rounds of the colony and with pamphlets and tracts are attempting to ensnare women and children in their nets, - not a difficult feat since women are more amenable to persuasion than men.</p>
   <p>We cannot mention the Italian church on Grand avenue without abhorrence and disgust. However, we feel bound to report that a week or so ago a lottery was there conducted which yielded to the parish priest who promoted it the sum of twelve hundred dollars. This sum is to be used to pay for repairs on the church property.</p>
   <p>The basement, in particular, is to be made into a modern retreat where at night the most sinister element of the colony may congregate. This retreat will contain a lunch-room, where the top price for meals will be twenty-five cents. The food will be solicited from the poor grocers of the neighborhood.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0699.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There will be bedrooms where lodging will cost fifteen cents a night, and the odors will be pungent, to say the least.</p>
   <p>There will be a pool-room and also moving pictures which will show the miracles wrought by their God; and last but not least there will be a hall where a young man may entertain his feminine friend. And do you know who is going to supervise all these activities? The priest and a group of black-robed women! Some new arrivals have been noted among the old-timers. In short, this house of illusions has been converted into a place of business.</p>
   <p>Has no one ever thought of putting an end to this scandal against humanity? Will no one shout so that the world may hear, "It is high time to stop it, you seven-headed vipers, you noxious worms?"</p>
   <p>And what does the anti-clerical Giordano Bruno club think about this? We hope that among the multitude a few may be found in whom conscience is awakening, and that through the agency of this club war may be declared and waged without quarter against these degraded persons until victory is assured for the anti-clericals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
