<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Fiamma</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1923-11-01">Nov. 1, 1923</date>, pp. 22-24
<title level="a">The Non-Americanization of Immigrants</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">An Answer to Elizabeth Fracer's Article in the Saturday Evening Post</title> Carnovale, L.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0210</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0210.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Fiamma</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1923-11-01">Nov. 1, 1923</date>, pp. 22-24
<title level="a">THE NON-AMERICANIZATION OF IMMIGRANTS</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">An Answer to Elizabeth Fracer's Article in The Saturday Evening Post</title> Carnovale, L.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whoever read the article in The Saturday Evening Post, Aug. 14th, 1923, entitled:</p>
   <p>"Our Foreign Cities-Chicago." by Elizabeth Frazer, certainly received a most deplorable impression of European immigrants, especially of the Italians, in the United States, because the authoress interests herself, particularly, in the lowest class of emigrant and sets forth its deficiencies and misery only. Her information, no doubt, came from one of the many insignificant labor agencies, whose chief are notoriously known as unscrupulous merchants in human flesh, and are not in a position to give just information regarding immigrants in general. On the other hand, <pb facs="5425702_2_0211.jpg" n="2"/>the authoress omits mentioning the good qualities of the immigrants and entirely disregards the better element which European emigration particularly the Italian, has brought to America.</p>
   <p>A conscientious writer ought to set forth not only the "cons" but also the "pros," that is to say, the favorable as well as the unfavorable, especially when subjects of such vital social importance are concerned. Otherwise the reader only sees one side of the truth, (if the truth exists in Elizabeth Frazer's article), and it is upon this one and only side that he bases his opinion on the subject discussed by a careless and unjust writer.</p>
   <p>Elizabeth Frazer treats her subject in such a pessimistic way that she came to the conclusion, that immigrants, the Italian in particular, are absolutely unsusceptible to Americanization and to the assimilation. Consequently, in her conclusion she does not recognize in the immigrant in this country even the natural instinct of an animal towards its own betterment.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0212.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I believe I know the Italian immigrants of the United States well enough, having studied their situation for a long time and having published a book covering my impressions entitled: "The Journal of the Italian Immigrant in North America," (Chicago), therefore, I venture to set forth a few facts quite contrary to the foolish, misleading and slanderous assertions of Elizabeth Frazer.</p>
   <p>For instance, there are hundreds of thousands of Italians in the United States who are naturalized American citizens.</p>
   <p>In agriculture, the industries, in commerce, fiance, politics, sport, science, art and education, in fact, in all fields of American activity, the Italian immigrants have demonstrated in the past, and will demonstrate more and more, that they know how to Americanize themselves and assimilate to the fullest extent that which America offers them.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, the immigrants of today are not like the ones of the old days, to whom, no doubt, Elizabeth Frazer refers with such posthumus zeal.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0213.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Immigration: The American Commissioner of Immigration at Ellis Island is an Italian, Mr. Caminetti, who has held the office for years.</p>
   <p>Labor: The members of the American labor organizations are a good part Italians.</p>
   <p>Agriculture: The vineyards, the orange and lemon orchards, the very finest of their kind in this country, were grown and developed to their present state by Italian immigrants and are in their hands.</p>
   <p>Industries: The Boston fisheries, considered among the most important in the United States, were established and developed to their present flourishing state by Italian immigrants and are in their hands.</p>
   <p>Commerce: South Water Street of Chicago, one of the wonders of Chicago and the most important wholesale fruit market in the United States, was established and developed to its present state by Italian immigrants and it is almost entirely in their hands. An Italian immigrant, Mr. Garibaldi, was for years and up to his death, President of the South Water Street wholesale merchants organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0214.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Among the high grade confectioners in Chicago, the Allegretti Co., has enjoyed a splendid reputation for years.</p>
   <p>Finance: The greatest American Bank of the West from Chicago to California, is the Bank of Italy in San Francisco, established and developed to its present state by Italian immigrants and that bank is in their hands. This bank has numerous branches, among them the New York branch, which rivals the greatest banks of that city.</p>
   <p>The Italians, Conte Minotto, is Vice-President of the Boulevard Bridge Bank in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Politics: The President of the City Council of New York is the Italian, Fiorello La Guardia, who was also candidate for Mayor of New York during the last election.</p>
   <p>The District Attorney of New York City is the Italian, Mr. Pecora. A State Senator of New York is the Italian, Mr. Cotillo.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0215.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Among the Judges in Chicago there are three Italians, Barasa, Borelli, Gualano. Judge Barasa was also candidate for Mayor of Chicago during the last election. And in smaller American cities some of the Mayors are Italian.</p>
   <p>Science: The only American Pasteur Institute in Chicago is the one established and directed by the Italian, Dr. Lagorio. One of the best American hospitals in Chicago is the Columbus Hospital facing Lincoln Park, established and owned by Italians. The Italian, John B. Zingrone of Chicago is one of the greatest American X-ray operators. He was confidential assistant to the famous surgeon, Prof. J. B. Murphy, who appointed him to make the X-ray pictures of President Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
   <p>Art: The Italian, Count di Cesnola, was for years, up to his death, the Director of the Metropolitan Museum of New York. The two greatest American opera companies are in the hands of Italians, i.e., the New York Opera Company being directed by the Italian, Gatticasazza, and the Chicago Opera Company by the Italian, Maestro Polacco. Among the best American moving picture stars is <pb facs="5425702_2_0216.jpg" n="7"/>the Italian, Rudolfo Valentino. There are many others. Not counting the myriads of American singers, music teachers, architects, sculptors, artists, who are of Italian blood. The architect of the Union Station of Chicago, now under construction and said to be the greatest railroad station in the world, is an Italian. The American inventor of artificial lightning is the Italian engineer, Mr. Faccioli.</p>
   <p>Professions: There are hundreds of Italians, naturalized American citizens, who are practicing law, hundreds of physicians as well as druggists.</p>
   <p>Sports: The American Golf champion is the Italian, Sarazene. The American champion of automobile racing is the Italian, De Palma. Among the American ring champions are the Italians, Dundee, Wilson, Gennaro and even Dempsey, who is of Italian descent.</p>
   <p>The American cowboy winner of the recent horse races at Harlem, New York, is the Italian, Tony Pagona. In swimming, running, bicycling and motorcycle racing, <pb facs="5425702_2_0217.jpg" n="8"/>some of the best champions are Italians.</p>
   <p>Hygiene: Several of the finest residences in choice sections of Chicago are occupied by Italian millionaires like Cuneo, Costa, Garibaldi, Dr. Lagorio.</p>
   <p>Education: One of the greatest American educators is the Italian, Angelo Patri, not counting the numerous Catholic American educational institutions, (universities, colleges, high schools), in all parts of the United States, almost all established and directed by Italians. Dozens of professors in the American universities and colleges are Italians.</p>
   <p>In the high school examinations in New York City, two Italian boys, Bernard and Vincent Cioffari, exceeded by 5.03 and 3.77, respectively, the very highest average (92%) ever attained by anyone in the history of New York schools.</p>
   <p>I could mention many other facts to prove that the Italian immigrants desire and <pb facs="5425702_2_0218.jpg" n="9"/>know how to Americanize themselves, that they desire and know how to assimilate the best America has to offer them by securing for themselves American positions of such importance, and in every field imaginable, as to be envied by those Americans whose individuality Elizabeth Frazer so highly praises. Such positions are attained by Italian immigrants notwithstanding the disadvantages they suffer due to the difference in language and, more than anything else, to the cruel prejudice held against them, such as those found in the lines of Elizabeth Frazer's article.</p>
   <p>However, I still want to call attention to the many marriages between high class Americans and Italians in America, which naturally indicates that Italian immigrants do become naturalized American citizens, and, that they assimilate the good America offers to them.</p>
   <p>In addition, there is not an Italian newspaper in the United States, that does not continually preach to Italian immigrants the Gospel of Americanization.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0219.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>At any rate, if the Italian quarters of any city lack cleanliness the fault lies particularly with the American health authorities who neglect such quarters and do not enforce, with the necessary vigor, the observance of the laws covering public hygiene.</p>
   <p>One should not entirely condemn the ignorant, the humble, the poor, and insist that they should spontaneously uplift themselves. Instead, the learned and the rich, who generally neglect the ignorant and the poor, should extend to them a helping hand in order to uplift them to a higher standard of living. This ought to be the mission of real civilization.</p>
   <p>This is the most sacred and most beautiful mission that America has to accomplish, since she believes herself, nowadays, to be the leading Nation of the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
