<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1908-06-13">June 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">[An Appeal to the Patriotism of Chicago's Italians]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_1026</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1026.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1908-06-13">June 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">[AN APPEAL TO THE PATRIOTISM OF CHICAGO'S ITALIANS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We reprint with pleasure the following letter sent to us by the secretary of the Local Committee for the Colonial Congress, and feel that we do not err, when we say that through the admirable members, this committee had the right to be proud of the praise sounded in the words of the Minister of Foreign Affairs. Insofar as the first reunion is concerned, very few can rightfully take pride in their attendance record at later meetings. At none of these did a sufficient number intervene to give weight to any decision proposed. At none of these did any one put forward an idea, a suggestion or precept, that had a bearing on the problems confronting the Italian colonist. And, of the societies that have shown cooperation, there are very few. These problems vitally concern all. All realize how necessary is a representative in Rome to make known the need of protecting the interests of Italians in foreign lands. Questions over which there is much raving and controversy, and on which even those most concerned will not venture an opinion. An opinion, or an attitude, to be proposed and presented by the chosen delegates selected by local committees.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1027.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Here, in Chicago, we followed the advice of the Italian Consul who suggested that all representatives of the societies present, at that first meeting of March 29, be considered as members of the local committees, and thus he gave all an incentive to work toward a common good. What are they waiting for - these societies who lay claim to being the directing forces of the Colony, before they insist that their representatives attend every meeting, and make known their attitudes on the questions that deeply concern the Colony, and also help in choosing the delegates to the Congress, which will present these questions for consideration in Rome, so that Italy may be made aware of the way in which her sons in foreign lands work. Always deaf to pleas of the local committee, are they awaiting the accomplished deed so that they can malign and recriminate against something in which they willingly would not take part?</p>
   <p>(The letter follows:)</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_1028.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>June 8, 1908</p>
   <p>Mr. President:</p>
   <p>The Minister of Foreign Affairs, who because of me is aware of the efforts made by the colonists of Chicago to be represented at the Colonial Congress, in assuming that this will also be brought to the attention of Senator De Martino, has asked me, through you, to make known his pleasure for the manner in which you acted on my proposal at your first meeting.</p>
   <p>I shall be grateful to you if you make this known to all interested, in the hope and assurance that it will tend to encourage my countrymen whom, I am here to serve, to continue on their road which they have chosen.</p>
   <p>Accept, Mr. President, the proof of my worthy consideration.</p>
   <p>The Royal Consul</p>
   <p>Sabetta.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
