<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title level="a">A Solemn Celebration</title>." <title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1931-06">June 1931</date>, pp. 19-20.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0495</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0495.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title level="a">A Solemn Celebration</title>." <title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1931-06">June 1931</date>, pp. 19-20.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One year ago, the week of May 18, 1930, an event took place,in an embrace of fraternal faith and immeasurable joy, among the members and the congregation composing the Presbyterian Church of St. John.</p>
   <p>The echo of those beautiful days in which we installed ourselves in our new temple erected to the Glory of God over which flies the standard of the Gospel of God, is still vivid in our minds.</p>
   <p>It was a week of celebration in which a beautiful and varied program of divine warship, propaganda talks, vocal and instrumental entertainment was held, attended by all members and many of their friends.</p>
   <p>The sacred day of that celebration could not remain neglected, therefore, we have remembered it the evening of Sunday, May 31st., which marks the tenth <pb facs="5425702_2_0496.jpg" n="2"/>anniversary of the founding of the Church, which at first was located in the Garibaldi Institute, 1208 Taylor St., and at present carries on its work of faith and conversion in its new temple at Harrison St. and Hoyne Ave.</p>
   <p>All this is the fruit of the accomplishment of the tireless activities of Dr. Pasquale Ricciardi De Carlo, Pastor and Director of the Church where Italians have found every resource for help and guidance be it spiritually or materially within our means, And where, in large numbers, they have been converted to the Gospel of Jesus Christ.</p>
   <p>In this new temple our work has born fruit and we have been able to set up and maintain a school for the teaching of: English, Italian, American citizenship, a Sunday School for adults, youths and children of both sexes. An extensive social service program and educational entertainments which are supported by the Ladies Aid, Christian Endeavor Society and the Givolamo Savonavola Club are also important features of the work.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0497.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Church services and divine worship take place on Sunday morning and evening and every Wednesday.</p>
   <p>The celebration, therefore, was very timely and it was an affirmation of faith and honor for him who has the rule of the flock in our church, that is, Dr. De Carlo, whose mission is not a lucrative profession but a true and sincere apostolate spent in the glory of God and for the benefit of the Italian people. It would be superfluous to repeat all his good deeds in the field of his activities whether as a Pastor, publisher or upright citizen.</p>
   <p>More than three hundred people filled the church in order to hear a varied program on this anniversary, rendered more attractive because of the participation of Maestro Giuseppe Sirignano and his concert orchestra composed of picked musicians from the leading theatres of the city. Their names can be found on page 24, English section.</p>
   <p>Dr. De Carlo took his place at the pulpit surrounded by distinguished personalties <pb facs="5425702_2_0498.jpg" n="4"/>of the Presbytery and the guests of honor, among whom were Dr. Furno and the Messrs. Duncan, Hills, Bellavia, Knickerbocker and C. Meola. He received a warm receiption after he had given a talk explaining the purpose of this solemn celebration. He then presented Maestro Sivignano who proceeded with his part of the program. The orchestra played the "Overture" of Guarany with perfection of rhythm and colorful melody and the rendition was accorded much applause. - - -</p>
   <p>The Church Choir then rendered the "Pilgrim's Chorus" from Tannhauser accompanied by the orchestra.</p>
   <p>Our tenor Enrico Clausi sang a selection from "Martha" and the "Traumerei" of Schumann.</p>
   <p>Presented by Dr. De Carlo, Bellavia spoke on the work of the Church during the past year. He was followed by Miss Knickerbocker, Director of Garibaldi Institute, Dr.Peter Furno and the prominent attorney, Mr. Hills.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0499.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The congregation then sang the Fascist hymn, "Giovinezza" and the hymn "America the Beautiful." The rest of the program was played by the Orchestra.</p>
   <p>Rev. Dr. De Carlo then spoke to Mr. Carlo Meola representative of L'Italia. He congratulated Chevalier Oscar Durante for his recent appointment as Vice President of the Board of Education. He was influential because of his position, in instituting the teaching of Italian in the High Schools of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Carlo Meola, after revealing his collaboration with Rev. De Carlo on an Italian newspaper of many years ago Il Cittadino, mentioned something about De Carlo's work during their years together. He remembered very distinctly that he had donated more than thirty-five thousand lire to an orphanage in Turin, Italy, despite the fact that it was a Catholic institution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
