<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-01-25">Jan. 25, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter from a Subscriber to the Parola</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0679</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0679.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-01-25">Jan. 25, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER FROM A SUBSCRIBER TO THE PAROLA</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Why are you so much preoccupied with the Burnett-Dillingham Bill as to devote an editorial to it and to print the petition to the President?</p>
   <p>How will that law harm the proletariat? And what is the harm to our party?</p>
   <p>I fail to see that it contains menace; I rather believe, if you will permit me to say so, that you are much in error in this case.</p>
   <p>The more ignorant the immigrant is the easier it is to defraud him, to make him a strike-breaker, and to drag him to the polls to vote against his own interests for a glass of beer or a cigar.</p>
   <p>The better educated he is the more respect will he command, and the less easily will he sell himself to the parasitic class.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0680.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then why beg for the intervention of the Italian Government or its representatives?</p>
   <p>The aim of the Socialist party is to educate and prepare the working class, through the medium of its literature, for the political and economic struggle of the future.</p>
   <p>Now if a law is proposed which will help us by forcing foreign governments to provide their subjects with more education, are we to obstruct it?</p>
   <p>America, you say, needs all classes of immigration, literates, and illiterates.</p>
   <p>You forget that the illiterates are the special victims of the priests, the bankers, and all that class which continually preys on the ignorance of the immigrant.</p>
   <p>Immigration, my dear editor, will not diminish because of any law.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0681.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The worker, even though an adult and forced by necessity to immigrate,can with a few lire learn in a short time to read and write well enough to satisfy the aforementioned law, and when he has arrived in America, he will be much more amenable to our ideas.</p>
   <p>M. Borsini.</p>
   <p>Editor's note: -</p>
   <p>The Socialist party is the champion of liberty for all, illiterates included, especially when as in this case a human right is threatened, the right to live in any part of this world.</p>
   <p>The anti-socialist and reactionary arguments of Comrade Borsini are the same as those used by others against universal suffrage.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0682.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"The illiterate voter would be a sucker for the priests and the bosses!" No matter, say the Socialists, whether he be so temporarily or permanently. This man, although illiterate, is also a citizen, and if for that reason alone, he has certain responsibilities and certain definite rights.</p>
   <p>If you, Borsini, came to America to improve your position, why should you desire that any enterprising peasant, seeking the same opportunities, be forbidden to enter this country because he cannot read and write? Is permission to eat to be dependent on literacy?</p>
   <p>The Burnett Dillingham law, if it is enacted, will not decrease illiteracy in Italy. No law, nor any "serious provisions," has been able to diminish illiteracy (is not elementary education compulsory in Italy?), because illiteracy is the product of environment, a starving plant growing on barren soil.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0683.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Change the environment, and the plant will flourish. The desire or the necessity of coming to America will never force a man thirty, forty, fifty years old to worry over the alphabet. In Italy itself does not the illiterate man know that by learning to read he will improve his lot? And yet he does not make the effort to learn. Why? Because his miserable environment and his indolent temperament keep him down. Not even the prospect of emigrating to America is sufficient to rouse him.</p>
   <p>We believe, instead, that illiteracy will diminish in Italy only with unrestricted emigration to the United States. By coming to this country the immigrant improves his position. He eats better food, dresses better, lives in an environment more elevated, and comes in contact with people more advanced. He feels the desire to improve himself and the need to learn more. But even if he does not improve his education, one thing will happen beyond any doubt; he will send money to Italy, and this money will help his children to become educated.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0684.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Our article in the previous issue was not a defense of illiteracy, as Borsini seems to think. We were merely defending the right of all, whether literates or illiterates, to go where they please. And again we urge all Italian-American Socialists to protest against the proposed Burnett-Dillingham law.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
