<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Buono, Rev. P., "<title level="a">General Report for the Year 1922-1923</title>" <title>La Fiamma</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1923-11-01">Nov. 1, 1923</date>, p. 8.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0551</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0551.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Buono, Rev. P., "<title level="a">General Report for the Year 1922-1923</title>" <title>La Fiamma</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1923-11-01">Nov. 1, 1923</date>, p. 8.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I wish to present to the readers and ftiends of the La Fiamma, a brief history of our work. We quote from the North-Western Christian Advocate the following article published in last February's issue.</p>
   <p>On Sunday, Dec. 10, 1922, Superintendent Polemus H. Swift of the Chicago southern district, organized the quarterly conference of the Third Italian Methodist Church of Chicago, the official name being the Church of Our Saviour.</p>
   <p>This organization is housed in what formerly was the Second German M. E. Church, 2801 Princeton Avenue. This new development promises to become one of the best Italian churches in the city. The work was started a year ago by the organization of an Italian class in the Princeton Avenue M. E. Sunday School, where the Rev. J. J. Rankin was Pastor. This was in charge of the Rev. P. Buono, who still directs the work. He has put himself into the work body and soul. He is ably seconded by his wife <pb facs="5425702_2_0552.jpg" n="2"/>and a number of devoted friends. Soon an Italian Sunday School was started, followed by an evening preaching service and later a regular prayer meeting.</p>
   <p>At the time the quarterly conference was organized, the Church was formally recognized with twenty-four full members and twenty-eight preparatory members. The Sunday School has an enrollment of 125 pupils with an average attendance of sixty pupils. The Junior Epworth League now forms a considerable feature in the work. Stewards, trustees and other officers were elected. One of the strongest Italian congregations in the city will, at no distant day, be found on this corner.</p>
   <p>Our Church membership has increased to sixty-two. The meetings are well attended. We praise God for all his blessings bestowed upon us this year. The Junior Epworth League has kept up the spirit of loyalty both winter and summer.</p>
   <p>The Daily Vacation Bible School, held for four weeks, has given us a new vision for the future. Almost a thousand children attended and received <pb facs="5425702_2_0553.jpg" n="3"/>Bible instruction this summer.</p>
   <p>For two weeks we held revival meetings, in which many came to the knowledge of Christ and of His saving power. We had the privilege to have with us one evening, Dr. Louis Bucaletti, and on another evening, the Rev. A. F. Scorza. We closed the revival meetings with the Lord's Supper.</p>
   <p>Our prayer meetings are well attended, all taking part with prayer and testimony.</p>
   <p>We are sorry to lose our District Superintendent, P. H. Swift. He was compelled to retire on account of his health. This came out at the last day of the Annual Conference of the M.E. Church. Dr.Schultz has been elected to his place. We expect a great deal during the coming year from Dr. Schultz. He has promised me to come to our Church the first Sunday of December and hold the first quarterly conference for this new conference year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
