<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1930-06">June 1930</date>, p. 19.
<title level="a">What the Italian Thinks of the Chicago Crime Situation, J.H.Ambruster</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1930-06">June 1930</date>, p. 19.
<title level="a">WHAT THE ITALIAN THINKS OF THE CHICAGO CRIME SITUATION, J.H.AMBRUSTER</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is common belief among many people that Chicago criminals, gangsters, bootleggers, jailbirds and brothel-keepers are Italian, because now and then the Chicago Press shows in big headlines peculiarly spelled names of certain gangsters who have been slain or captured by the police (and then promptly released) and readers are prone to say, "This is another Italian."</p>
   <p>The good Italian citizen - and there are thousands of them in Chicago - resent this very much. In the first place many of these criminals are not Italian, but may be Polish, Bohemian, Czecoslovakian, or of any other foreign nationality. In the second place if it happens to be an Italian it doesn't follow that every crime committed in Chicago is chargeable to that nationality. There are good and bad Italians just as there are good and bad Americans, Englishmen, Scotchmen or Germans.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0084.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Chicago Daily Press gives the impression to outsiders that Chicago has more murders per capita than any city in the United States, just as it gives the impression that these murders are all committed by Italians. This is wrong. These same newspapers give the impression that many wrongs are attributable to prohibition. When these wrongs are analized they have nothing whatever to do with prohibition. The press sometimes maintains that crimes are committed by men affiliated with a certain religious demonination. As a matter of fact, that conviction of theirs is also wrong. A person may be baptised in one faith, but if he grows to manhood and pays no attention to the church and religious matters, it is not fair that any bad in him should be charged to the denomination of his nationality. Then again, if a man is once a Catholic or a Jew that label remains with him throughout his lifetime; whereas, he may be baptised a Protestant, but if he does not attend the Protestant church he is soon dropped from such church roll.</p>
   <p>In all justice to the good Italians of Chicago, therefore, let us say right here <pb facs="5425702_2_0085.jpg" n="3"/>that the number of Italians who are implicated in thses crimes which daily fill our newspaper columns is no larger than numbers of those of other nationalities. And there is no fair reason or excuse why these daily newspapers should feature the Italians as being people who come to this country to disregard our laws, and try to take things into their own hands, any more than others.</p>
   <p>Would it not be fine if occassionally the Chicago Tribune would devote a column or a page to the good deeds of Italians; of the churches they have built and are filling; of the statues erected in our various parks to Garibaldi and other heroes; of the fine lodge membership which they make up and of the patriotic interest taken in our national holidays, and the fine devotion shown to our national emblem whenever there is occasion for displaying the stars and stripes. We wonder whether the editor of the Tribune would be interested in such a suggestion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
