<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1901-05-04">May 4, 1901</date><title level="a">Italian Workers Swindled</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_2_0174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1901-05-04">May 4, 1901</date><title level="a">Italian Workers Swindled</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following close upon the heels of Lovece, who recently swindled two hundred Italian laborers out of eight dollars each, on the promise of employment as section hands and then decamped with the sixteen hundred dollars, three hundred others were the victims of another unscrupulous "boss", also an Italian.</p>
   <p>Posing as a railway employment agent, charged with hiring track-laborers, Guiseppe Lamorta, collected three to five dollars from each of three hundred Italian laborers. He told them to meet him at the railway depot on Cause Street, at eight-o'clock that same night.</p>
   <p>At the appointed hour the waiting-room of the depot was filled to overflowing with travelers, their friends, and relatives.</p>
   <p>Express-wagons filled to capacity with bags, boxes, and trunks, had stopped outside the depot, while the owners of the baggage awaited the arrival of Lamorta with their passes to the section camp.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_2_0175.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But time passed and"Don Pepe" did not make an appearance, for the reason that he had taken flight in another direction with the fees gotten from his gullible countrymen.</p>
   <p>Because of the frequency of these swindles, with the ensuing bad feeling to our countrymen, we suggest that the Italian Consulate take the responsibility of investigating these agents, before the Workers hand over much needed money for a job that does not exist.</p>
   <p>We make this appeal to the good-sense and good-will of Count Rozwadowski, to the end that he take into consideration the above facts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
