<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-06-08">June 8, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[Socialism and Politics]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0799</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0799.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-06-08">June 8, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[SOCIALISM AND POLITICS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During an interview with Berlinske Tidende of Copenhagen, Admiral Richelieu reports about his audience with President Roosevelt:</p>
   <p>"Our conversation concerned Denmark and, said the president: "There is one thing about Denmark we in America do not understand, How can it be that a people whose standards of education and culture enable it to produce so many outstanding personalities can be so much under the influence of Socialism as is the case in Denmark at the present time? We have an old saying 'that when the mule grows too fat it is liable to kick.' This, it seems to me, is the only way to explain this state of affairs."</p>
   <p>So spoke the president of the United States. Whether or not Admiral Richelieu had a chance to comment on his statements the paper does not inform us. It <pb facs="5420780_3_0800.jpg" n="2"/>appears as though the president has put up a question and - on the basis of his omniscience - answered it himself.</p>
   <p>However, if Admiral Richelieu did have an opportunity to answer the question correctly that the Socialistic movement is prominent in Denmark because the Danes maintain a high standard of education and culture. If the president believes that the progress of the Socialistic movement is guided solely by peoples' material standards he is all wrong. Starvation wages and discontent are not responsible for people going Socialistic. Neither are high wages with consequent arrogance and a liking to kick with the hind-legs the causes, nor something in between these extremes. The cause of Socialism is a realization of the fact that the prevailing conception of a profit system which is able to function only at the cost of wage slaves is inhumane brutal and unworthy of a civilized people. The sponsors of the Socialistic movement are to be credited with the progress it makes in this country. Even the Socialist hater Roosevelt must have a feeling that the Socialistic movement carrying with it a better general understanding of social problems is not entirely objectionable because in the course of the conversation he expressed his desire to have the whole country of Denmark moved to America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
