<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title level="a">Danish National Committee, Niels Nielsen, President</title>, <title>World's Fair Year Book</title>,
<date when="1933">1933</date>, pp. 49-50.
<title level="a">The Danish National Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title level="a">Danish National Committee, Niels Nielsen, President</title>, <title>World's Fair Year Book</title>,
<date when="1933">1933</date>, pp. 49-50.
<title level="a">THE DANISH NATIONAL COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For a number of years prior to the organization of the Danish National Committee, the Danish Brotherhood Lodges of Chicago held annual joint festivals in Elliot Park, arranged under the auspices of the Central Committee of the D.B.S. in Chicago with Mr. Christ Hermansen as Chairman. In the meantime, the feeling became gradually apparent of the desirability of co-operative effort between Danes of all factions, the churches, societies and various organizations, and due largely to the initiative of Mr. Hermansen the "Danish National Committee" was accordingly organized in the fall of 1908. The original Committee was composed of 26 members, representing as many societies, and to Mr. Claus Jensen fell the honor of being the first President.</p>
   <p>The first joint festival arranged under the auspices of the Danish National Committee was held on June 5, 1909, on the occasion of Denmark's national holiday. <pb facs="5420780_3_0153.jpg" n="2"/>This affair met with the whole-hearted approval and support of the Danish Colony, with the result that a similar affair has been held every year since, attracting thousands of Danish people from Greater Chicago and surrounding cities, towns and viliages.</p>
   <p>Besides arranging these annual affairs, the committee has on many occasions sponsored worth while undertakings such as, the organization of th Danish Relief Fund in 1911, which has been of inestimable help to many of our countrymen in time of need and distress. In order to more impartially serve the Danish colony, this Relief Committee became an independent organization in 1927, and its officers and members are doing a noble and unselfish work for unfortunate Danish people without any compensation whatsoever.</p>
   <p>Lack of space make it impossible to narrate the many worth while activities sponsored and undertaken by the Danish National Committee during the twenty-five <pb facs="5420780_3_0154.jpg" n="3"/>years of its existence. The scope of our work has been wide, including the raising of a memerial to Jacob A. Riis in 1929 in the park bearing his name at Narraganset and Fullerton Avenues, in honor of that great Dane whose name will go down in the history of the medical profession, Dr. Christian Fenger. Entertainments of national interest have been arranged, such as the showing of films from Denmark; arranging of plays such as "Elverhoj," "Gongehovdingen" and "Capriciosa"; and in short, many interesting affairs for the benefit of the Danish people of Chicago. In all these undertakings and on every occasion when calling for united action and support, it must be said that the response from the people of our Danish colony has been whole-hearted and prompt.</p>
   <p>In closing I should like to exphasize that although we call ourselves the Danish National Committee, we are vitally interested in all work for the benefit of the common good.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
