<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>De Forenede Staters Danske Almanak</title>, <date when="1915">1915</date>, p. 131.
<title level="a">[The National Committee]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>De Forenede Staters Danske Almanak</title>, <date when="1915">1915</date>, p. 131.
<title level="a">[THE NATIONAL COMMITTEE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The officers of the National Committee for 1915 are Jos. Jensen, president; Claus Jensen, first vice-president; Mrs. Sine Jensen, second vice-president; R. Egebergh, secretary; Arnold Rasmussen, treasurer; and J. C. Jensen, financial secretary.</p>
   <p>The following are the delegates with the names of their societies in parentheses:</p>
   <p>Mrs. Wm. Nelson (Old People's Home); Niels Ohlsen (Walhalla); S. C. Jensen (Good Templar Lodge); Marinus Petersen (Danmarks Sonner); Chas. Th. Knudsen (Sydsidens Danske 100-Mandsforening); G. Bense (Arbejdersangforeningen); Geo. Hansen (Harmonien); C. J. Christensen (D. B. S. No. 17); R. Egebergh (D. B. S. No. 18); P. L. Petersen (D. B. S. No. 58); A. M. Petersen (D. B. S. No. 35); P. C. Mygil (D. B. S. No. 140); Claus Jensen (D. B. S. No. 289); C. Petersen (Danish Children's Home); Jos. Jensen (Dania); Mrs. W. Mogensen <pb facs="5420780_3_0174.jpg" n="2"/>(Dania Ladies' Society); Wald. Bauer (Dansk-Amerikansk Sygeforening); C. M. Christensen (Folkesamfundeskredsen Fremad); C. F. Geckler (Den Danske Hundred-Mands-Syge-og Begravelseskasse); Jans Lundsberg (Dansk Skytteforening); Mrs. Rasmine Petersen (D. S. S. No. 4); Mrs. Margrethe Petersen (D. S. S. No. 42); Mrs. Sine Jensen (D. S. S. No. 139); Anna Jensen (Sangforeningen Ekko); Mrs. Thora Larsen (Sangforeningen Illinois); Robt. Hechmann (Sangforeningen Magneten); J. C. Jensen (Sangforeningen Hejmdal); Fritz Nielsen (Vaabenbrodrene); Mrs. Marie Estrup (Valkyrie); Antonia Mickelsen (Danmarks Dotre); Arnold Rasmussen (Sydsidens Danske Laeseforening); Rudy Hansen (Danish-American Athletic Club); Arthur Carlsen (Danmark Lodge No. 908) and Mrs. L. Hansen (S. S. S. af 1895).</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Of the above societies the following no longer exist: Sangforeningen Ekko, Sangforeningen Magneten, Sangforeningen Hymdal, Sydsidens Danske Laeseforening.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
