<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, La Salle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, 1899, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 55-56.
<title level="a">John P. Hanson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_1130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, La Salle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, 1899, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 55-56.
<title level="a">JOHN P. HANSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John P. Hanson, the well-known cigar manufacturer of Chicago, was born March 22, 1843, in nor Tonnder, Schleswig, Denmark. His education was such as the common schools of his locality afforded, and he remained in the vicinity of his birthplace until he reached his majority. In 1864 he resolved to seek his fo tune in America, and following the footsteps of many of his countrymen, emigrated to Wisconsin, settling in Racine. Thence he wandered West and was employed by the Government in the building of fort Lyons, Colorado. In 1867 he came to Chicago, where he worked as a mason until 1869. During that year he suffered from a disease which affected the bone of his left ankle and was obliged to undergo an emputation.</p>
   <p>This misfortune disabled him for continuing the work in which he had been engaged and, after due consideration he apprenticed himself to learn the trade of a cigarmaker, with Mr. Burckhart, at what was then No. 33 Milwaukee Avenue. He worked faithfully to learn the business until October 4, 1872, when he had <pb facs="5420780_3_1131.jpg" n="2"/>made sufficient progress to open a factory of his own. This he did, at what is now No. 361 Milwaukee Avenue. His business prospered, showing that he had made good use of his apprenticeship, and in 1879 he was able to build a factory and residence at No. 351, in the same street. In this building he has since continued his business, and has aimed to have the model cigar factory of Chicago. In fact it was so pronounced by three experts who were visiting this country from Germany. His output has greatly increased as his product gained reputation and, as early as 1883 he manufactured and sold four million cigars, He employs from sixty to seventy-five hands, and has two men on the road disposing of the product.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hanson has invested his savings to good advantage in various business enterprises. He was one of the organizers of the American Varnish Company, and still owns stock in that concern, which is in a prosperous condition, having in 1897 transacted business amounting to $280,000. He was also a promoter of the Milwaukee Avenue State Bank, is one of its largest stockholders and on its board of directors. Among the other concerns in which he has stock might be <pb facs="5420780_3_1132.jpg" n="3"/>mentioned the North Side Street Railroad, the National Biscuit Company and the Chicago Heights Land Company.</p>
   <p>He has always taken a lively interest in the affairs affecting the city, and especially the portion in which his home is located. Mr. Hanson has always been a very industrious man, and this, coupled with the most rigid economy in the beginning, accounts for his success in life. While still an apprentice, he was able to accumulate three hundred dollars, and during the first three months of his business career he doubled his investment three times. During the first six years that he conducted business for himself he worked almost night and day, allowing himself no more rest than nature absolutely demanded.</p>
   <p>In 1868 the subject of this notice was married to Miss Katie Rasmussen, the ceremony taking place at Racine, Wisconsin. Their union has been blessed with twelve children, six of whom are living, namely: Anna, who is her father's bookkeeper; Freda, residing at home. Rudolph, a salesman for his father's <pb facs="5420780_3_1133.jpg" n="4"/>factory; Carrie, a teacher in the public schools; Jennie, who graduated in 1898 from the Wicker Mark School, having the highest standing of any pupil in her class; and Robert, who is still attending school. Since 1889 the family has resided at 0.24 Ewing Place, in the elegant modern residence which the father built in that year. Mr. Manson has bean an honored member of the Knights of Pythias since 1873. In politics he is a Republican.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
