<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Hejmdal</title>,
<date when="1875-06-12">June 12, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">Dania</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Hejmdal</title>,
<date when="1875-06-12">June 12, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">DANIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dania had all its laws and bylaws revised about thirteen years ago, on November 23, 1862. Doctor J. Foster, who is now in Milwaukee, and a few other Danes, started a Danish brotherhood. The organization had its difficulties at first, but on February 16 Dania was given its first charter by the State of Illinois. The idea was to give expression to Danish social life; a Danish library and a sick benefit association were other objectives. Dues were to be small. The men who accomplished this,finally, certainly deserve a great deal of credit.</p>
   <p>Last year one thousand dollars was paid to its sick members. This sum was large enough to give members full reimbursement for their losses during illness. There is a rule that every time a member dies, the entire membership must pay fifty cents each. As Dania has four hundred members, two hundred dollars is thus collected, which is certainly a considerable sum.</p>
   <p>All the laws of Dania show a real feeling of brotherhood. After the Great Fire <pb facs="5420780_3_0288.jpg" n="2"/>of October 9, 1871, Dania lost all its furniture, but the club was so strong that the loss was quickly replaced. The greatest loss was a beautiful banner donated by the Danish women. The club secured new rooms at 17 Milwaukee Avenue, where there is a large hall.</p>
   <p>After a short time the membership became so large, that it was necessary to enlarge the quarters. The reading room was made into a very cozy lounge, with beautiful rugs on the floor, and works of real art on the walls. In the center of the room is a pretty table made of hazelwood. In the same room you will find the library, containing several hundred books. In the corners of the room, easy chairs and lounges are along the sunny side of the walls. Two large gas chandeliers hang from the ceiling. In the billiard room, the members must pay five cents per game.</p>
   <p>Dania hopes to get its own home. Dania also has a singing society. Last of all, it should be mentioned that Dania works to assist newly arrived immigrants in securing positions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
