<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-10-26">Oct. 26, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[Danish Teachers Would Like to Visit America]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0783</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0783.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-10-26">Oct. 26, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[DANISH TEACHERS WOULD LIKE TO VISIT AMERICA]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Teachers in Denmark inquired whether they would be given an opportunity to earn the money necessary for a trip to America, by working temporarily among the Scandinavians over here. The idea may seem appealing; it is, nevertheless, hardly practical for one thing, the Scandinavians of America keep themselves segregated along national lines. Each national group maintains its own schools, often in conjunction with the churches, and as a rule, have very limited funds. There are, moreover, plenty of teachers available at anytime the private schools are able to provide the funds with which to pay their salaries. Scandinavian grammar schools in this country will never be anything but an appendix to the American school system. So far as the adults are concerned, they have, at least in the cities, excellent opportunities to learn the English language and add to their knowledge by attending evening courses offered by the Public Schools, they seem to favor this method of learning.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0784.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>No doubt a trip to America would be beneficial to many schoolmasters of the old country; but why not let the Danish Government make an annual appropriation for the purpose of financing these trips to America for a few teachers each year? In the final analysis, it is the state that will benefit by such educational travels. Students of industry and trade receive scholarships for such journeys every year, not to speak of writers, artists and scientists. Why are not the teachers, whose works of educating the young generation is just as important, given the same privileges? A state, that can afford to spend 25,000,000 Kroner for military purposes every year, should be able to spare a few thousand Kroner for such educational purposes as the training of its teachers. Or is the military extravagance perhaps the reason for strict economy when cultural values are at stake? If it is, the teachers of Denmark are not without means with which to change the situation, which is a deplorable one, to say the least.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
