<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1921-11-26">Nov. 26, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The First Thanksgiving</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1921-11-26">Nov. 26, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST THANKSGIVING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The founders of this great republic of the United States came here from England when all this land was one vast wilderness, inhabited by Indians. To make a home here on the shores of America was indeed a heroic task. What brought the first immigrants to these shores? What was it that made them leave the well-cultivated lanes of old England; the cozy homes they loved so much, all that was dear to them, and come here and suffer the indescribable hardships of pioneer life? The answer to this question is indeed a wonderful story of devotion to truth, to freedom of conscience, of untold courage.</p>
   <p>There in their English homes they were happy until King James began to persecute all who broke away from the State church, the Church of England.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0307.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The persecution was very severe. Men and women were jailed, flogged, pilloried, and otherwise tormented for their faith. They were not allowed to worship in their own way. Rather than submit to the king's will, these men and women of deep convictions decided to leave England. First they sailed to Holland (1607 and 1608), to the cities of Amsterdam and Leyden, but they found that it was hard to make a living there and especially that their children were forgetting the English language, their mother tongue. For these reasons they decided to go to America, where they hoped to lay the foundation of a country all their own, where they might enjoy both religious and national freedom. Because of this going from place to place, those who started for America were called the Pilgrims. That is why we sing "Land of the Pilgrims Pride."</p>
   <p>These Pilgrims started from Holland in the summer of 1620. They were <pb facs="5420780_3_0308.jpg" n="3"/>delayed in England until September 6. The name of the ship on which they sailed was called the "Mayflower," a comparativly small sailboat. For nine terrible weeks the Pilgrims were tossed about on the waves of the Atlantic, until they finally landed near Cape Cod on December 21, 1620. It was here they decided to settle. It was a bitter cold day and all that there was to welcome the brave little band were woods laden with thick snow and the cold north wind howling through the branches. Only the bravest could stand the hardships of the first days. Fortunately, the Pilgrims were the bravest of the brave, fired with a passion for freedom. They were not discouraged by the difficulties, however great, but set to work to build their homes in which they were determined to live for the rest of their lives.</p>
   <p>Their first year in America was full of hard work, sickness, famine, and <pb facs="5420780_3_0309.jpg" n="4"/>danger. What heroes to suffer all this so that they might be free! What a precious jewel freedom must be, to be worth such great sacrifices! Do we value it enough? What are we doing to keep, to preserve, the priceless treasure left us by the Pilgrim Fathers?</p>
   <p>Their labors and sacrifices were not in vain. The time came when the terrible winter passed, during which many of their number had died. In the fall they were finally able to gather in their crops and celebrate their first victory over the wilderness. The cornerstone of their new country had been laid. They knew now that they would have a home of their own, where they could enjoy freedom of conscience and remain true to their national ideals.</p>
   <p>It is no wonder that they decided to celebrate this event, and that they <pb facs="5420780_3_0310.jpg" n="5"/>set aside a few days during which they were to feast, to rejoice, and to give thanks. The first Thanksgiving Day was a great event. Even the Indians were invited. They had helped the settlers during the hard winter by selling them corn and furs; they had shown them how to plant the corn and were great friends of the white men. They brought five deer for the feast and entertained the settlers with wild Indian games. The white men in turn gave the Indians exhibitions of military tactics and evolutions.</p>
   <p>In 1623, another day of feasting and thanksgiving was held. Every year after that a day was set aside as Thanksgiving Day, until now, in our time, the last Thursday of November is set aside as a national holiday. On this day it is well to think of the work and sacrifices of those brave souls who have gone before us, and to resolve to keep it intact for all days to come, even if we have to make as great sacrifices as the great founders of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
