<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1927-12-09">Dec. 9, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Immigration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0597</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0597.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1927-12-09">Dec. 9, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">IMMIGRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An analysis of the new quota distribution will show that the present quota of the Scandinavian countries will be reduced by sixty-five per cent or about two-thirds, while England's quota simultaneously will be increased by thirty-nine thousand yearly admissions. Russia, Italy, and Austria-Hungary's quota were more than doubled.</p>
   <p>The following is a comparison between the present quota distribution and the new one. The old one is based on the census of 1890, and the new one based on "national origin," to become effective July 1, 1928, if this clause is not annulled by Congress. It is illustrative in the following manner:</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0598.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Present Quota (1927)</p>
   <p>Nations gaining, based on Census of 1890</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Great Britain and Northern Ireland:</cell>
     <cell>34,007</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Austria-Hungary:</cell>
     <cell>1,258</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Italy:</cell>
     <cell>3,845</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Russia:</cell>
     <cell>2,248</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>41,358</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Present Quota (1927)</p>
   <p>Nations losing on Census of 1890</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Sweden:</cell>
     <cell>9,561</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Norway:</cell>
     <cell>6,453</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Denmark:</cell>
     <cell>2,789</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Germany:</cell>
     <cell>51,227</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Irish Free State:</cell>
     <cell>28,567</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>98,597</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0599.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Estimated Quota from July 1, 1928.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Based on Nation Origin</cell>
     <cell>Gains</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>73,039</cell>
     <cell>39,032</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2,453</cell>
     <cell>1,195</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>6,091</cell>
     <cell>2,246</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>4,781</cell>
     <cell>2,533</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>86,364</cell>
     <cell>Total Gain 45,006</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Estimated Quota from July 1, 1928</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Based on National Origin</cell>
     <cell>Losses</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>3,259</cell>
     <cell>6,302</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2,267</cell>
     <cell>4,186</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1,044</cell>
     <cell>1,745</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>23,428</cell>
     <cell>27,799</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0600.jpg" n="4"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>13,862</cell>
     <cell>14,705</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>43,860</cell>
     <cell>Total Loss 54,737</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>These figures show that Sweden, Norway, Denmark, Germany, and the Irish Free State, will lose annually two-thirds of their present quotas in favor of England, Hungary, Austria, Russia, and Italy.</p>
   <p>This is then a direct appeal to the voters of Scandinavian descent to urge their Senators and Congressmen to vote for the retention of the present quota distribution. A Written or personal request to our Representatives in Congress may help bring about the desired result.</p>
   <p>The Scandinavian voters also have a strong ally in the head of the United States Immigration Department, who recommends in his annual report of June 1925 that the present quota distribution be continued, and the new one rescinded, closes his recommendation with the following words: "The Immigration Department is of the opinion that the proposed change will lead to great confusion, and result in complexities, and accordingly, it is <pb facs="5420780_3_0601.jpg" n="5"/>recommended that the pertinent portions of Section 11, providing this revision of the quotas as they now stand, be rescinded."</p>
   <p>If the Commissioner General's recommendation is not supported by the voters themselves, through its Congress, and if that portion of section 11 pertaining to the distribution of the quotas on the basis of national origin is not rescinded, then the immigration from the Scandinavian countries will dwindle from a total of 18,803 to 6,570 per year, or from 1,567 per month to 548 per month. Five hundred forty-eight immigrants from Scandinavia per month distributed over the forty-eight states, is such an insignificant number that Congress might just as well have forbidden all immigration from the Scandinavian countries.</p>
   <p>The result will be that American citizens of Scandinavian extraction will not be able to help relatives or friends come to this country, except after many years of waiting, and all our various institutions, societies, etc., all that the Scandinavian-Americans, from the earliest times to this day, have built <pb facs="5420780_3_0602.jpg" n="6"/>up at a great sacrifice, will crumble and slowly, but surely, die.....</p>
   <p>Appeal to your Senators and Congressmen.</p>
   <p>Have this new quota distribution bill stopped at once.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
