<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, La Salle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, <date when="1899">1899</date>, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 438-439.
<title level="a">Johan M. Pettersen.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_1166</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1166.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, La Salle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, <date when="1899">1899</date>, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 438-439.
<title level="a">JOHAN M. PETTERSEN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Johan Martin Bertel Moerch De Eich Pettersen, a druggist at No. 439 West Fullerton Avenue, was born April 23, 1844, in the village of Saeby, peninsula of Jutland, Denmark. He received a good education in the public school of his native village. At the age of sixteen years he entered upon a five years' apprenticeship to learn the business of druggist. On the expiration of his term of service he received a diploma for the practice of pharmacy. He then went to Schleswig and filled a position as prescription clerk in a drug store two years. The two succeeding years he was employed in the same capacity at Frysenberg.</p>
   <p>In 1869 Mr. Pettersen came to the United States, locating first at Jamestown, New York, where he was employed two years as clerk in a drug store. He then went to Foxburg, in the oil regions of Pennsylvania, and followed his profession about nine months.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1167.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Pettersen arrived in Chicago in 1872, and was first employed in a drug store at the corner of Division Street and Milwaukee Avenue, and after a short time was in the service of Hunton Hall, at their store at the corner of Leavitt and Lake Streets. From there he went to the employ of N. Bruun, who was located at the corner of West Indiana Street (which street is now Grand Avenue at this point) and Center Avenue. He was a clerk at this store seven years, proving himself a worthy and valued man of tact and perseverance.</p>
   <p>In 1881 he decided to establish a business of his own and purchased a business at the corner of Cottage Grove Avenue and Twenty-ninth Street, which proved to be a poor location, and moved the store, in a short time, to Twenty-fifth Street and same avenue. A few months later he removed to the corner of Milwaukee Avenue, where he soon built up a profitable business.</p>
   <p>In 1890 he purchased a business at the corner of Rockwell Street and West Fullerton Avenue, and conducted both stores eight years. In 1898, however, he disposed of the former and successfully continues the one where he resides.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1168.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He is a member of the Royal Arcanum and of the Independent Order of foresters, also being identified with the Knights and Ladies of Security. He was made a Mason in Jamestown, New York, but has not affiliated with any lodge since he left that city. For thirty-eight consecutive years he has been a druggist, and has had a long and varied experience which is invaluable to him.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pettersen was married in Philadelphia, Pennaylvania, in 1871, to Miss Augusta Gad, a native of Denmark. They became the parents of six children, three of whom died in childhood. Annie, the eldest now living, is the wife of L.J. Lunoe, judge of the criminal court of Copenhagen. Ella, the next in order of birth, is at home, as is also Holger, who is attending school.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pettersen has always taken a keen interest in the affairs of his adopted country and home city. He is a supporter of the Republican party, but has always refused to accept a nomination for office of any kind. He and his family are members of the Danish Lutheran Church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
