<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-08-14">Aug. 14, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of Denmark's "Hill of Memories"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0682</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0682.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-08-14">Aug. 14, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF DENMARK'S "HILL OF MEMORIES"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Speech made by Mr. S. Heiberg of Chicago, father of the idea to dedicate a spot of our native soil commemorating emigrants of Denmark:</p>
   <p>"From time immemorial Danish men and women have emigrated, leaving their childhood homes and native surroundings, to fight for and win a place in the sun for themselves in other countries. Much has been said and written about the agony of longing they have suffered, and their inability to ignore the feeling that tied them to the homeland. Only earnestness of purpose and hard work along the lines leading from the doorsteps of our childhood homes outward can calm these feelings.</p>
   <p>"Every emigrant of conscientious purpose will remain honest with himself. Therefore, he will always remember what he owes the country where he was born, equipped and trained to fill a place of responsibility.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0683.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"As more and more emigrants left and became citizens of countries, far off and widely separated, this feeling of connection with the mother country became more apparent, and the idea of giving it visible expression was conceived. A group of Danish born Americans founded the Rebild Park, now recognized by all as a rallying place for Americans born in Denmark. It is only natural that the World War strenghtened the relation between the mother country and her emigrated sons and daughters.</p>
   <p>"In this spirit the Memorial Park outside the city of Aarhus was laid out for the purpose of preserving the memory of Danes whose accomplishments in foreign countries have been recognized as important to civilization and human progress, and also to express our sympathy with those men of Danish extraction who served and died in the World War.</p>
   <p>"This 'Hill of Memories,'in beautiful Sondermarken outside Copenhagen,is commemorating the emigrants as a type constituting a group numbering hundreds of thousands of individuals. It is our token of gratitude and a symbol of the love <pb facs="5420780_3_0684.jpg" n="3"/>we feel for our homeland, and besides, it is meant to preserve the memory of thousands who left and never returned.</p>
   <p>"Many are the plans and suggestions that have been submitted as to what the definite purpose of this memorial should be. Location chosen, landscaping and purpose agreed upon is the combined result of successful co-operation. As it appears today, ready to be dedicated by King Christian on behalf of the Danish nation, it represents a gift to Denmark made by Danish emigrants from all corners of the world.</p>
   <p>"It is a great pleasure for me to be chosen for the undertaking of representing Danish emigrants from everywhere, whose thoughts are turned homeward today. I know that in spite of marked differences of opinions, and various degrees of social accomplishments, we do heartily agree with each other when we gather to celebrate our precious memories.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0685.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"We hereby humbly pray for this spot on which we have erected this little token of loyalty as a visible expression for our feelings. We trust that the symbolic pieces of art adorning this spot will appeal to the hearts of young and old, in such a way as to make them understand that art is a true and symbolic expression of the spirit in which the voluntary contributions to this cause have poured in."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
