<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>, (The Review)
<date when="1909-10-02">Oct. 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[Danish Orphanage Society Celebrates Anniversary]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0040</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0040.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>, (The Review)
<date when="1909-10-02">Oct. 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[DANISH ORPHANAGE SOCIETY CELEBRATES ANNIVERSARY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.col.5........The Silver Jubilee of the Danish Orphanage Society was celebrated on Friday September 24, at the Y.M.C.A. Auditorium on LaSalle Street. The auditorium was well filled, only a few of the cheaper seats in the upper gallery being empty. The majority of the audience consisted of people from the many Danish churches of Chicago who are the main sponsors and supporters of the orphanage.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by an overture by the justly popular Knudsen Ericksen Orchestra after which Pastor Rordam (director of the orphanage) welcomed the audience and introduced the speaker of the evening Rev. K. C. Bodholt, president of the United Danish Church. Rev. Boldholt spoke feelingly of the wonderful care given the young inmates of the Danish Children's Home and expressed his deep appreciation for the whole-hearted financial and moral support given by the Danish-American Lodges of Chicago. Continued and ever-increasing success was assured by such co-operation and generosity. On behalf of the United Church be thanked all Chicago for their faithful support during the twenty-five years since the home was <pb facs="5420780_3_0041.jpg" n="2"/>organized, and for the promptness, and efficiency with which they had put over the campaign for and building the new home.</p>
   <p>The well known organist G. Dupont - Hansen (who played' at the dictation of the new home three and one half years ago) was at the console at the Trinity Church Choir with Miss B. Hansen and Mr. J. Hendricksen as soloists repeated the contata (by Rev. Adam Den) that was heard for the first time at the dedication.</p>
   <p>The real heart throb of the evening was the recitation, by Mrs. Rev. Rordam of "The little match girl."</p>
   <p>That Miss Harriet Hertz sang herself into the hearts of all was apparent by the applause and flowers awarded her. Harmonien Chorus sang "den Store Hvide Flok" (The great white throng) with the director, Prof. Joel Mossberg, singing the solo. To close this very enjoyable program the audience joined the talent in singing "I alle de riger og lande" (In all kingdoms and all lands) leaving with a feeling that all had received a real benediction throughout the evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
