<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1929-11-01">Nov. 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Denmark's Disarmament</title><title level="a" type="sub">Fight Near in Denmark for Army and Navy Reductions to Police Forces</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0667</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0667.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1929-11-01">Nov. 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">DENMARK'S DISARMAMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Fight Near in Denmark for Army and Navy Reductions to Police Forces</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the new Danish Parliament assembles in October, the coalition Labor-Radical Government, headed by Theodore Stauning, veteran Socialist leader, will evidently insist upon immediate action making disarmament something tangible in Denmark. Since the coalition has seventy-seven deputies in the Lower House (sixty-one Socialists and sixteen Radicals), against an opposition of seventy-one, composed of forty-three Agrarians, twenty-five Conservatives, and three Land Taxers, and since the Last three are expected to support the disarmament proposal, Premier Stauning will have clearer sailing than he did in 1926, when his government was wrecked on the question of increasing unemployment benefits and a small capital levy after its disarmament bill had already been put through the Lower House.</p>
   <p>One argument used by opponents of the plan to save about $10,000,000 a year <pb facs="5420780_3_0668.jpg" n="2"/>to the Danish taxpayers by substituting a sort of glorified police force for the existing army and navy, is the contention that, even if little Denmark wanted to disarm, she would not be allowed to do so by the big powers, because of her important geographical position in relation to keeping open the entrance to the Baltic Sea in time of war.</p>
   <p>But this point lost a great deal of its weight when Ramsay MacDonald, soon after being named British Prime Minister last June, when asked by a representative of a European Socialist paper what he thought about the Stauning plan, replied that he always had insisted that it was foolishness for a tiny nation to waste money on miniature armies and navies which would not amount to anything in a real war. This statement is being used by the Danish Socialists to reinforce their demand for quick action by Parliament.</p>
   <p>What may be considered the official position of the Danish Socialist Party is presented by Alsing Andersen, secretary of that organization, in an article written for the Zurich Bureau of the Socialist and Labor International. It <pb facs="5420780_3_0669.jpg" n="3"/>reads in part as follows:</p>
   <p>"When Parliament assembles, the Government will present its proposals in particular, [and it] will, of course, let loose the political fight.</p>
   <p>"The 'international' of the militarists functions in such instances quite as well as the international of the working class. In the great and small military States the militarists are already at work to cross with the help of the Danish militarists, in a press campaign, the clearly expressed will of the Danish people. There is a majority of about 100,000 votes for disarmament. International disarmament is still awaited ten years after the establishment of the League of Nations. The great majority of the Danish population has declared by its vote that it can no longer wait for others and bear a burden of millions year after year for the sake of maintaining a military apparatus which all experts have declared to be futile.</p>
   <p>"The disarmament proposals, which will again be adopted by the Lower House <pb facs="5420780_3_0670.jpg" n="4"/>before the end of this year, provide for the following new arrangements.</p>
   <p>"The army and the fleet will be transformed into a frontier police and a State marine, to enable Denmark to fulfill its duties as a neutral State and member of the League of Nations, in accordance with the existing regulations.</p>
   <p>"The new institutions will be subordinated to the Prime Minister. The War and Marine Ministries will be abolished. The fortifications will be dismantled. The general obligatory military service will be done away with. All men over twenty years of age will be registered every year. Those who do not wish to be trained in the frontier police or the marine must inform the authorities. From the remaining men fit for service, the necessary number for training (1,600 men) will be drawn each year. Voluntary military bodies are forbidden.</p>
   <p>"The combined strength of the frontier police will be about 13,000 men. The State marine will be composed as follows: Six ships of not more than eight thousand tons in all, twenty-four ships of not more than thirty-six hundred tons <pb facs="5420780_3_0671.jpg" n="5"/>in all, some mine and depot ships and twelve cutters. The yearly payments for both institutions will be reduced from fifty to sixty million crowns to seventeen million."</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: This article created a lot of discussion in the Danish colony, and caused a split.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
