<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
LaSalle Book Company, <title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, LaSalle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, <date when="1899">1899</date>. 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 439-440.
<title level="a">Erik Pedersen.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_1137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
LaSalle Book Company, <title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, LaSalle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, <date when="1899">1899</date>. 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 439-440.
<title level="a">ERIK PEDERSEN.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Erik Pedersen. The subject of this sketch is a native of the village of Hundtofte on the island of Fyen, Denmark, and is the youngest of the seven children of Peter Knudsen and Maria Christophersen, both natives of Fyen. Both parents, spent their lives in Fyen, his father dying in 1861, and his mother in 1876.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pedersen was reared and educated in his native village, where he remained until he was fourteen years of age, and was engaged in farming for a time; then, becoming desirous of following the sea, he shipped as a cabin boy and for many years was employed on board a ship in various capacities. From <pb facs="5420780_3_1138.jpg" n="2"/>his native land he sailed to Scotland and Prussia, then to Liverpool, and there shipped aboard a Dutch vessel and sail to Riga, Russia. From there he went to Holland, then took a position on a South American vessel and went to New Orleans, landing in America for the first time in 1860. After a short visit in New Orleans he was employed on the American vessel "Scranton," on a trip to Liverpool. He then shipped on board a Swedish ship, which was bound for Shields, England; and went to Rio Janeiro, Brazil. The ship being southern property, could not get a clearance, so the captain represented that they were going to Cork, Ireland, for orders. Instead he went into St. Thomas, in the West Indies, to learn how the Rebellion was progressing. Then they found three Northern men of war, and the "Globe" was held there eleven months. Mr. Pederson remained on board the "Globe" eight months and then got a berth on board a Danish vessel and went to San Domingo, from there to Hamburg, Germany, thence to his native village and found that his father had died. He then went to Hamburg and shipped in an American Vessel bound for Shields, England.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1139.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Later he embarked on a Prussian vessel, came to New York and cruised along the eastern coast, visiting Baltimore, Jacksonville and Galveston, and then went on a trip to Newfoundland and Nova Scotia.</p>
   <p>Returning to New York he shipped on a German vessel for France, touching at Marseilles. On going to New York, they were detained in the harbor at Gibraltar by a head wind for about twenty-four hours. The captain did not know that the law required every ship that had been lying at anchor in the bay to hoist its flag while passing the Spanish fort. Neglecting to comply with this regulation, his ship was fired at from the forts and the twenty-four pound shot struck the railing, passing through, the side of the ship, broke the cook's leg, knocked off a leg of the stove and lodged in a sail locker. The Government sent a tug to take them back into the harbor at Gibraltar, where they had to report to the Consul how the trouble happened, after which they returned to New York. Mr. Pedersen then shipped on a Nova Scotian vessel, called "Lillian," and went to Buenos Ayres, Brazil, with lumber, and from there returned to Boston. After getting his pay he took passage on a steamboat to New York, where he made his home. He then <pb facs="5420780_3_1140.jpg" n="4"/>went to Buffalo, New York, and continued his journey as far West as Omaha, intending to go into the mining regions of the Rocky Mountains. Instead he took a trip down the Mississippi River and spent the winter in New Orleans. While on the levee in that city looking for work, he heard a man ask a negro to go to work for him, and at once recognized to voice as that of a Mr. Bruen, who had been second mate of the ship "Globe." He made himself known, renewed the old acquaintance and friendship and got profitable employment with his old friend. In the spring of 1871 he came to Chicago, sailing on the lakes during the following summer. In the fall of 1871 he went to New York and made two trips to Santiago, and on his return visited his brother in Racine, Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>In the spring of 1873 Mr. Pedersen came to Chicago and engaged in the sale of sewing machines. Five years later he started in that business for himself, and first located at No. 332 West Chicago Avenue, where he reamined about four years; at the end of that time removing to his present place of business No. 278 West Chicago Avenue.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pedersen was married in 1877 to Miss Ella Johnsen, a native of Norway, who came <pb facs="5420780_3_1141.jpg" n="5"/>to Chicago in 1870. She died in 1879, leaving one child, Mary Pedersen, who is a most efficient assistant to her father in his business.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pedersen is a valued member of the Danish Benevolent Society, and is independent in his political opinion. He is essentially one of the self-made men of Chicago, having established himself in business wholly by his own efforts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
