<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title level="a">Danish National Committee, Mrs. Anna Eddy, Supreme Secretary, World's Fair Book</title>,
<date when="1933">1933</date>, p. 60-63.<title level="a">The Danish Sisterhood of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0379</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0379.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title level="a">Danish National Committee, Mrs. Anna Eddy, Supreme Secretary, World's Fair Book</title>,
<title level="a" type="sub"><date when="1933">1933</date>, p. 60-63.</title><title level="a">THE DANISH SISTERHOOD OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two years, almost, after the founding of the Danish Brotherhood in America, the idea of founding a Danish Sisterhood in America, as an independent association for the purpose of aiding and assisting Danish women in America after the principles of the Brotherhood, began to take form.</p>
   <p>The initiative came from Mrs. Kirstine Hemmingsen, born Jan. 30, 1840, in Roholte county, Sealand, Denmark and married to a member of the Danish Brotherhood, Niels Hemmingsen, Negaunee, Mich. This founder of our association, Mrs. Kirstine Hemmingsen, worked so incessantly and energetic, that she finally, at her home in Negaunee on November 21, 1883, could gather enough interested parties to found the first lodge of the Danish Sisterhood of America.</p>
   <p>December 15th of the same year the first meeting of our association took place in the home of the founder. When it became apparent that there were not <pb facs="5420780_3_0380.jpg" n="2"/>enough ladies present to fill the offices necessary, it was moved, seconded and unanimously adopted as a rule: that members of the brotherhood were permitted to join the sisterhood--which, however, was not kept very strictly, as will be shown. We therefore see the following members at the first meeting of the first lodge of D. S. S. in America, held January 8, 1884, viz.: Niels Hemmingsen, supreme president; Catherine Jensen, president; Karen Hansen, vice-president; Agnes Johnson, secretary, and Kirstine Henningsen, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The Sisterhood thrived in the succeeding years. Members of the Danish Brotherhood joined the baby association in increasing numbers, and Danish women became interested in steadily increasing degree. Of the passive members, several became members of the supreme lodge and held offices in the same; for instance, L. L. Ries, who served as our supreme treasurer from 1887 to 1908; Chr. Boyshou, who served as our first supreme secretary; and Ludwig M. Hoffenblad, that true friend of D. S. S., as supreme secretary, <pb facs="5420780_3_0381.jpg" n="3"/>loyal and true, never tiring in his efforts for the welfare of the sisters. It is thanks to the work of such "passive members" of the D. S. S. that we today have reached out present impregnable position.</p>
   <p>The first convention of D. S. S. in America took place January, 1887, in Burlington, Ia. The following officers were elected: J. Chr. Eskildsen, supreme president; Chr. Boyshou, supreme vice-president; Ludwig M. Hoffenblad, supreme secretary, and L. L. Ries, supreme treasurer. The second convention of D. S. S. in America was held in Chicago, Ill., 1890, where all officers of the supreme lodge were unanimously re-elected and supplemented with our first supreme trustees of the Sisterhood, namely: Mrs. Henriette Capion and Mrs. Sophie Nicolaisen.</p>
   <p>The following year saw a heavy struggle for us to maintain the Sisterhood during years of hardship and strenuous work, but also years of faithful adherence to the principles of the Danish Sisterhood and the Brotherhood as well. The <pb facs="5420780_3_0382.jpg" n="4"/>victory was won finally, when the Danish Brotherhood in America, at its convention in Racine, Wis., in October, 1902, resolved to aid and assist the Danish Sisterhood in America with all its might. Thanks to this resolution of the brothers, we now had smoother sailing, so that we, at our 25th anniversary celebration in October, 1908, could show a membership of 5,190 members, of 106 lodges, spread over the entire U. S. A. We could also show that during the 25 years we had paid out insurance to the amount of $5,135, 916.00, and help to sick members of $93,000.00, and aided poor members and their families to the amount of $12,000.00. During these years we had held conventions in Burlington, Ia. (1887), Chicago (1890), Racine, Wis. (1899), Omaha, Neb. (1897), Marinette, Wis. (1904).</p>
   <p>The convention is Council Bluffs, Ia. (1910), saw the election of only active members as supreme officers. The passive members (the men) had served D. S. S. well and were given a rousing exit.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0383.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The officers then elected were: Hansine Madsen, supreme president; Sophie Lauritzen, supreme vice-president; Caroline Nielsen, supreme secretary; Louise Rasmussen, supreme treasurer; Mette Jensen, Bothilde Hansen and Hanne Jorgensen, supreme trustees.</p>
   <p>The Convention in Kansas City, No.(1928), saw the application for a new charter for the D. S. S. in America, which at that time changed from an association for life insurance to an association for funeral and sick-benefit. Mr. Julius Andersen, supreme vice-president of D. B. S. in America, assisted us in this work, so that we in 1929 had our new charter and were ready to adopt new members on our new charter.</p>
   <p>The later years have seen a steady growth of membership in D. S. S., so much so that we today, in the year of our Lord, Nineteen Hundred and Thirty-three, in the fiftieth year of our existence, can show a membership of 7,248 members <pb facs="5420780_3_0384.jpg" n="6"/>in 142 lodges. We have paid out in funeral benefit $960,801.75 and paid sick-benefit to members and their families.</p>
   <p>The following are our supreme officers today, viz.: Supreme ex-president, Elisa Tonder, Lodge No. 6; supreme president, Mrs. Adele Hauge, Lodge No. 16; supreme vice-president, Marie Mogensen, Lodge No. 68; supreme secretary, Mrs. Anna Eddy, Lodge No. 139; supreme treasurer, Louise Rasmussen, Lodge No. 50, and supreme trustees: Ellen Hojrup (L. 23), Marie Hansen (L. 22), and Lona Holt (L. 13).</p>
   <p>The lean years this world is passing through have also put their mark on D. S. S. in America, but we are not afraid of them; we look to the future with anticipation of a still greater success for our association, because we know and believe, that truth always must conquer, and that the work we are doing-"helping human beings to help themselves"- never is and never will be done in vain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
