<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>De Forenede Staters Danske Almanak</title>,
<date when="1914">1914</date>.
<title level="a">The United Danish Evangelical Lutheran Church.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0464</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0464.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>De Forende Staters Danske Almanak</title>,
<date when="1914">1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNITED DANISH EVANGELICAL LUTHERAN CHURCH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 74. This church was formed by the union of two Danish church societies. At a meeting in Argo, Burt County, Neb. in September, 1884 some ministers formed "Det Danske Evangelisk Lutherske Kirkesamfund;" they had left "Den Norsk-Danske Evangelisk-Lutherske Konference" (The Norwegian-Danish Evangelical-Lutheran Conference) at a meeting in Omaha, Neb. 1884.</p>
   <p>In 1893, there was another split within the Danish Church (Det Danske Evangelisk-Lutherske Kirke in Amerika, which led to the formation of what later was called "(The Danish-Evangelical-Lutheran Church of North-America) of the North-Church, as it some times was called. To begin with they had 19 ministers and 2 missionaries.</p>
   <p>At a meeting in Minneapolis in October, 1896, the North-Church and "Det Danske Evangelisk Lutherske Kirkesamfund" united and thus began the existence of "Den Forenede Danske Evangelisk-Lutherske Kirkesamfund i Amerika." (The United Danish Evangelical-Lutheran Church of America) Or The United Church.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0465.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Sixty three ministers, eight missionaries, one hundred twenty-seven congregations and thirty three preaching was its original church set-up. It now has one hundred twenty-seven ministers, three candidates, four missionaries and one hundred seventy nine congregations and preaching places.</p>
   <p>The United Church has an American Indian Mission, and another in Japan, and Mission in Utah. A seaman's Mission in San Francisco, and an Emigration Mission in New York and Boston is also maintained.</p>
   <p>Their center is Blair, Nebr. where they have Trinitatis Seminary and Dana College and the Danish Lutheran Publishing House.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
