<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-10-09">Oct. 9, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Danes on the Retreat</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-10-09">Oct. 9, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">DANES ON THE RETREAT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Twelve or fifteen years ago we were not in doubt as to the location of the Danish settlement in Chicago. Alighting from a street car at the corner of Western and North Avenues and walking westward, we found the window signs on both sides predominantly Danish. Saloons, of which there was one on every corner all the way to California Avenue, were all owned by Danes, employing Danish bartenders, Danish waitresses, and Danish janitors. Danish also were the customers who passed in and out, quenching their thirst. At its best the language spoken in these places was a wonderful mixture of English and Danish in all variations and dialects.</p>
   <p>Through the windows of residences in the neighborhood you would catch glimpses of Danish flags decorating mantelpieces; and on entering you would be treated to a sandwich made of real Danish rye bread.</p>
   <p>But times have changed. In the course of only a few years Little Denmark in <pb facs="5420780_3_0119.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago has been liquidated. One business place after another has been taken over by Jews or Poles. The Danish mail-carriers have remained, however, but they do not carry so many letters with Danish stamps as before. It is the vividly colored Polish and Russian stamps which predominate.</p>
   <p>Of course many Danish businessmen are still to be found in that neighborhood, and there are also a great many Danish families. Likewise several Danish societies do still have their headquarters there; but the majority of Danes have left, going farther west and northwest, and with their departure the West North Avenue district has ceased to be a typical Danish settlement. The older Danish settlement at Milwaukee and Chicago Avenues has completely disappeared, even though you may happen to discover a Danish sign squeezed in between Jewish and Polish ones. And so the Danes are on the retreat again. Are they going to conquer new territory collectively, or will they remain dispersed?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
