<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-07-27">July 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Danish Literature in U.S.A.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0792</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0792.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>II A 2 (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>III H (Norwegian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-07-27">July 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">DANISH LITERATURE IN U.S.A.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have received the following communication from Gyldendalske's Book-store in Copenhagen:</p>
   <p>"Increased interest in a closer connection between Scandinavian in America and their respective home countries is being expressed by the demand for Scandinavian literature, both classical and modern. For that reason various attempts to establish connections between literary centers and Scandinavians throughout America have been made. So far, however, the movement has been unsuccessful.</p>
   <p>"In order to obtain satisfactory results our company has taken a bold step and has made arrangements with Alb. Cammermeyer's Publishing Company in Chicago to establish a Scandinavian Publication branch.</p>
   <p>"Up to now three main obstacles have hampared the progress of selling Scandinavian literature in America, namely;</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0793.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"1. The difficulty in obtaining the books.</p>
   <p>"2. Too many delays in delivery.</p>
   <p>"3. Prohibitive prices.</p>
   <p>"With our new arrangements we are removing the three obstacles all at one time by stocking our branch with an especially large selection of modern and classical Danish and Norwegian literature. Above all we will strive to maintain the original prices as far as possible. But even to the economic result may fail to correspond with our expectations, if the enterprise is not supported morally to fullest extent by Scandinavians all over America.</p>
   <p>"Therefore we appeal to all Scandinavians of America, but to the Danish and Norwegian press in particular. We fully appreciate the importance of the great contribution made by the Scandinavian press in its efforts to preserve the language and culture of the mother countries. So do we hope to make our contribution. We also hope for continued support on the part of <pb facs="5420780_3_0794.jpg" n="3"/>the booksellers who did a pioneer work in introducing Scandinavian literature to America.</p>
   <p>Our veteran representative in Hristiania, Norway, Mr. Knud Lasseu, will be entrusted with the management of the branch and will arrive in Chicago in the first part of August.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
