<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anton Kvist, <title>Fra Lincoln til Hoover</title>, Amerikas Danske Pioneer Forening Dania, Chicago, 1862-1930. Et Bidrag til Danias Historie (From Lincoln to Hoover, America's Pioneer Danish Society Dania, Chicago, 1862-1930. A Contribution to the History of Dania). (Copenhagen: Politiken, <date when="1930">1930</date>), 28 pages.
<title level="a">[Dania]</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Excerpts)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anton Kvist, <title>Fra Lincoln til Hoover</title>, Amerikas Danske Pioneer Forening Dania, Chicago, 1862-1930. Et Bidrag til Danias Historie (From Lincoln to Hoover, America's Pioneer Danish Society Dania, Chicago, 1862-1930. A Contribution to the History of Dania). (Copenhagen: Politiken, <date when="1930">1930</date>), 28 pages.
<title level="a">[DANIA]</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Excerpts)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first Danes came to Chicago in 1837. They were both sailors. The one was Captain Christoffer Johnsen, from Alsinge, Denmark, and the other was Peter T. Allen from Copenhagen, Denmark. Chicago then had 4,000 inhabitants.</p>
   <p>Captain C. Johnsen was for several years treasurer of Dania.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0156.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago got her first railroad in 1848. A railroad station was built, and the first locomotive was sailed to Chicago by"The Old Whale," Georg Jergen Petersen, on his own ship "Helena". Mr. G. J. Petersen was of Danish descent and an eager member of Dania....</p>
   <p>Georg Hansen, born in Odense, Denmark, was the first Danish Consul in Chicago. Before that time the interests of the Danish government were in the hands of the Swedish consul in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Georg Hansen worked hard for the election of Abraham Lincoln in 1861, and was appointed American consul at Helsinger, Denmark shortly after the election.</p>
   <p>Just before he left he was present at the organization of Dania or Dana, as it was called to start with. The meeting was held in a cigar shop on East Randolph Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0157.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dania was started in Chicago in 1862 with twelve members, each of whom paid an initiation fee of two dollars. The aim of the organization was to gather all Danes in Chicago for social affairs and for the cultivation of the Danish tongue and the sharing of all old memories.</p>
   <p>The first president was Johan Foster, from Copenhagen, Denmark; the secretary was P. C. Petersen, from Lolland, Denmark.....</p>
   <p>Dania's first meetings were held in a wine cellar on La Salle Street, known for about twenty years as "Wilkens' Cellar". Here one would meet all the prominent Danes, who loved wienerwurst, sauerkraut, and muscatel wine. Here the Danes had a table of their own. The old basement disappeared in 1926, when the street was made wider, but the old oak table is now to be found at the student cafe in Copenhagen, to which it was given by Dr. Max Henius.....</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0158.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Dr. N. P. Pearson (Peterson), born in Kolding, Denmark, became Danish consul in Chicago after Mr. Hansen left. Dr. Pearson had been Army surgeon during the Civil War. He was also president for Dania for several years.....</p>
   <p>Druggist Emil Dreier, the first Danish apothecary in Chicago, became the successor of Dr. Pearson both as Danish consul in Chicago and president of Dania. He was a powerful personality and became the leader at the Danish table at Wilkens' Cellar. Here you might meet such famous Danes as the two architects Hammerich and Lautrup, the former of whom had opened a school for drawing in Dania for young Danes that just had arrived in the city. You would also meet Dr. Christian Fenger, Professor Frederiksen, the sculptor J. Gelert, the library critic Clemens Petersen, and the civil engineer William Harlew.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0159.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>You would also meet the first Danish Socialist leaders, recently deported from Denmark, Pio, Geleff, and "Sorte" (Black) Hansen. Later on the circle was joined by two young men, the politician Henry L. Hertz and Dr. Max Henius.....</p>
   <p>Henry L. Hertz became president of Dania in 1880.....</p>
   <p>The famous Danish author Johannes V. Jensen paid Chicago a visit in 1903 during a trip around the world. The loop gave him the idea for his social novel, Hjulet (The Wheel).....</p>
   <p>The famous editor of the Danish newspaper Politiken, Henrik Cavling, visited America and Chicago in 1893. He wrote a well-known book about his trip entitled Fra Amerika (From America). In this book you will find an excellent chapter about Chicago and the Dreier circle.....</p>
   <p>The author Norman Hansen wrote Chicago Noveller)Chicago Novels), which were widely read among Danes in the United States and in Denmark.....</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0160.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Louis Henius, the brother of Dr. Max Henius, lived in Chicago during the latter part of the last century and the early part of this century. He was a teacher in chemistry in this town and a member of Dania. He left for Denmark and never returned.....</p>
   <p>Fritz Frantzen, an old officer in the Danish army of 1864, became president of Dania in 1871 and again in 1921. He died from apoplexy during a meeting of Dania in 1921.....</p>
   <p>When the body of Abraham Lincoln passed through Chicago on its way to Springfield for interment, Dania placed a beautiful decoration on his casket.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
