<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title level="a">Danish National Committee, D. J. Voss</title>, <title>World's Fair Year Book</title>,
<date when="1933">1933</date>, p. 87-88.
<title level="a">Biography</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0937</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0937.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title level="a">Danish National Committee, D. J. Voss</title>, <title>World's Fair Year Book</title>,
<date when="1933">1933</date>, p. 87-88.
<title level="a">BIOGRAPHY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of Chicago's best known druggists of Danish birth, Mr. D. J. Voss, passed away this year in his beautiful home in Park Ridge.</p>
   <p>Mr. Voss was born in Assens in 1868. He began his career as an apprentice in a drugstore and later studied pharmacy at the University of Copenhagen.</p>
   <p>In 1893 he came to Chicago and found employment as pharmacist in Christensen's Drugstore at Rockwell and North Ave. Soon afterward he became Manager of same and remained as such until 1902 when he opened a drugstore of his own at Cortland and Washtenaw Ave. Five years later he moved his business to the N.E. corner of Talman and North Ave. Mr. Voss, a first rate pharmacist and business man, was very successful. He bought the building in which his drugstore was located and remained there until 1925 when he sold out, with the intention of going out of business, to rest and enjoy life, after his many years of continuous service in his profession.</p>
   <p>He built a fine residence in Park Ridge and moved out there with his family, <pb facs="5420780_3_0938.jpg" n="2"/>consisting of his wife, Karen Cristine, nee Scheel, born in Aarhus, and children: Else, Karen and Erik. Else is married to Mr. Sigvald Nielsen, a building contractor; they have five children.</p>
   <p>Mr. Voss owned a fine sum erhome, "Vosshill," at Carey, Ill., on the Fox River, where he and his family in past years have spent many happy days together.</p>
   <p>Mr. Voss' intention of going out of business in 1925 did not last as a reality for long; his vigorous energy and love of work soon forced him into activity again.</p>
   <p>In 1926 he bought a drugstore at Keeler and North Ave. and managed same until sickness and death overtook him.</p>
   <p>Mr. Voss was a fine, cultured gentleman, a lover of literature and other fine arts. In 1913, accompanied by his wife, he visited Denmark and his beloved home town.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0939.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He was a member of Dania Society, D.B.S. Lodge No. 18, The Old People's Home Society, and of the Shriners.</p>
   <p>Mr. D.J. Voss was a man of high esteem among his countrymen, and truly a good citizen of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
