<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-02-04">Feb. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[The Young People's Home]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-02-04">Feb. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[THE YOUNG PEOPLE'S HOME]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.col.3-4........"Revyen" has received many inquiries as to whether there is, in Chicago, a Danish young peoples home or community center. Yes, we have a Young Peoples Home at 3925 South Michigan Avenue. This is run by the Danish Community Committee "Fremad" and is not run for profit. The object is to provide a place where clean cut Danish youth can find a home with wholesome environment, where they may obtain a clean room and good food at the lowest possible cost. Here they have access to all the best Danish Books, Papers and Magazines both from Denmark and America, lectures, recitals and many other items are offered in the way of mutual advancement and recreation.</p>
   <p>The "home" has not been too extensively advertised due to the fact that the building housing the home is a rented one in which the length of tenancy is uncertain. There is a possibility that by spring the "home" may be made homeless by the completion of a possible sale of the building.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0561.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This home has not only been a haven for young Danes working in Chicago but has proved itself a convenient and safe place for people visiting here and for numerous immigrants who as strangers in a strange land would the protection of such an institution risk becoming a victim of the everlasting swindlers for whom the newcomer constitutes legitimate prey.</p>
   <p>Danes of Chicago - Will you give a little thought of the following questions? Is a permanent and adequate "home" of this kind worth consideration and support? Would such a home be appreciated to the extent of raising funds for a building where our Danish youth could live reasonably, and with congenial surroundings, where drinking, gambling and other vices would be strictly taboo? Are we presumptive in suggesting that an organization be formed to provide such a home and that an appeal to Danes throughout the land for funds would meet with a hearty response?</p>
   <p>We believe all this can be brought to pass and trust that the foregoing will be accorded thoughtful consideration that will in turn bring about the erection of a Home of which every Dane, here and in Denmark, may be justly proud.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
