<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-02-22">Feb. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavian Art Exhibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0727</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0727.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2) (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>III H (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>IV (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2) (Swedish)</item>
     <item>III H (Swedish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-02-22">Feb. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIAN ART EXHIBITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Scandinavian Art Exhibition at the Art Institute, will be open to the public from February 28 to March 16.</p>
   <p>The exhibition consists of 150 paintings, each of the Scandinavian countries having contributed fifty. The majority are modernistic, the Danish collection being mainly from The Free Exhibition in Copenhagen. Christian Brinton and American art critics made the selections, assisted by experts from the respective countries. Director Karl Madsen and the author Otto Benron represented Denmark. The paintings have attracted a great deal of attention,and the modern expressive form of art, which is still rather unknown and little appreciated in America, has been widely discussed by Americans as well as Scandinavians. For that reason alone, the exhibition is of importance in its function as a fanfare of young, modern Nordic culture.</p>
   <p>As a forerunner for the exhibition a rather daringly designed poster has arrived, <pb facs="5420780_3_0728.jpg" n="2"/>made by Gunnar Hallstrom, which portrays a viking ship plowing the ocean. A catalogue, with introductory chapters by Christian Brinton, Carl G. Laupin, Karl Madsen and Jens Thus, as well as pictures of some of the exhibiting artists and their paintings, is available.</p>
   <p>The exhibition has been arranged by the American-Scandinavian Society which obtained $5,000 from the American-Scandinavian Foundation for this purpose.</p>
   <p>The American-Scandinavian Society was founded in 1908 for the promotion of the exchange of culture with America and the Scandinavian countries and also among Scandinavians in America. For the initial capital stock, the manufacturer Niels Poulsen, of Brooklyn, donated $100,000. In addition to this, before his death in 1911, he established a fund of $500,000, known as the American-Scandinavian Foundation, a foundation intended to work in cooperation with the Scandinavian-American Society.</p>
   <p>The board of directors of the Foundation, which is self-perpetuating, consists <pb facs="5420780_3_0729.jpg" n="3"/>of the following:</p>
   <p>Danish: John D. Hage, New York; Prof. Wm. Howgaard, Boston. Norwegian: John A. Gade, New York; Consul G. Haugau, Chicago. Swedish: A. E. Johnson, New York; Rev. Frederick Lynch, president; Consul-General Raon, vice-president; Wm. H. Short, treasurer; Dr. Henry Goddard Leach, secretary.</p>
   <p>The board of directors of the Scandinavian-American Society are as follows: John A. Gade, president; Rev. F. Lynch, vice-president; Dr. Henry Goddard Leach, secretary; Hans Lagerlof, treasurer. On the board of trustees are the following Danes: Eckhardt V. Eskesen, John D. Hage, Carl Lorentzen, and Frode W. Rambusch, of New York.</p>
   <p>The following are honorary vice-presidents: U. S. Minister to Denmark Egau, Copenhagen; Andrew Carnegie; Governor Eberhardt, Minnesota; Supreme Court Justice Hughes, Washington, D. C.; President Judson, University of Chicago; former president Theodore Roosevelt; Peschke Koldt, wholesaler, Copenhagen.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0730.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>True to its purpose, the society has been instrumental in the exchange of professors in Scandinavian and American universities. It has also done much in the granting of scholarships to Scandinavian students who wish to study at American universities, as well as to American students of Scandinavian descent who wish to study at Scandinavian universities.</p>
   <p>The society has begun publishing the American-Scandinavian Review, a periodical now issued every other month, but which in the near future is to become a monthly. The art exhibition, which will come to Chicago via New York, Buffalo, and Toledo and which is scheduled to end in Boston next month, is the latest undertaking of the society. Of course, the society is interested in getting as many members as possible in order to be able to serve its purpose. The membership dues are only $2.00 annually, and this includes a subscription to the magazine.</p>
   <p>Secretary Leach arrived in Chicago about a week ago. His mission is to represent the society in preparations for the exhibition, which will be formally opened on February 27. A group of Chicago members of the society, prominent Scandinavians and Americans, and representatives of the press have been invited to attend the <pb facs="5420780_3_0731.jpg" n="5"/>opening ceremonies.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian painter Henrik Lund will arrive in a few days to supervise the placement of the paintings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
