<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1909-06-12">June 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[Danish Colony Celebrates National Holiday]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0336</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0336.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1909-06-12">June 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[DANISH COLONY CELEBRATES NATIONAL HOLIDAY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>June 6 was a great day in the history of the Danish colony in Chicago. On that day the different societies assembled in Riverview Park and celebrated the sixtieth anniversary of the Danish constitution. The Danes made a valiant effort to beat the record of 1899, when about ten thousand Danes came together in Elliott Park to celebrate the fiftieth anniversary of the Danish constitution.</p>
   <p>Guests from out of town met at the hall of Danish Brotherhood Lodge No. 17. First to arrive were two hundred guests from Racine. The total number of guests from out of town rose to seven hundred before the day was over.</p>
   <p>Seven thousand people paid to get into the amusement park. Children were admitted free, and there were many other free tickets. Hence it is estimated that ten thousand people gathered in Riverview Park, beating the record crowd <pb facs="5420780_3_0337.jpg" n="2"/>of 1899 by a wide margin.</p>
   <p>In the afternoon, between two and three o'clock, twelve men gave a gymnastic exhibition under the direction of C. G. Andersen. There was a children's chorus of eighty boys and girls dressed in red and white, the Danish national colors. There was singing by the Harmonien, Magneten, and Hartman singing societies. Hans Nielsen's orchestra played Danish music. The chairman of the festival committee was Claus Jensen.</p>
   <p>Henry L. Hertz was made master of ceremonies. A telegram was sent to Mr. Neergard, the Danish prime minister. Siphus Neble, editor of Den Danske Pioneer, of Omaha, spoke on the Danish constitution. Governor Deneen made a speech about America, the most powerful democratic nation on earth. Consul George Beck spoke for Denmark. Then came a wrestling match between members of the Sparta athletic club, and a tug of war between Sparta and Lodge No. 17 of the Danish Brotherhood, which was won by the latter.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0338.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There were six hundred and fifty guests at the banquet in Park Casino at Riverview. Henry Hertz was toastmaster. There were speeches by Carl Antonsen, Niels Juul, Sophus Neble, and James Skallerup. Mr. Neble said that he would like to see Danes get together every year on a day like this.</p>
   <p>The net profit of the festival will probably be about one thousand dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
