<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title level="a">Danish National Committee, Augie Louis Hansen</title>, <title>World's Fair Year Book</title>,
<date when="1933">1933</date>.
<title level="a">Biography of Haggard, J. M.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0940</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0940.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title level="a">Danish National Committee, Augie Louis Hansen</title>, <title>World's Fair Year Book</title>,
<date when="1933">1933</date>.
<title level="a">BIOGRAPHY OF HAGGARD, J. M.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Augie Louis Hansen, inventor and manufacturer, was born in Viborg, Denmark, August 3, 1879. His parents were Lebrath Winkleman and Clara (Von Halle) Hansen, who came to the United States of America in 1887.</p>
   <p>He graduated from public and high schools in Chicago, Ill., and completed a four-year course in mechanical engineering. He married Agnes Hilegard Stark of Evanston, Ill., Aug 14, 1906. His children are, Virginia (Mrs. George Hoffman), William Stark, Betty Jane (Mrs. E. J. Driscoll), and Jack Augie. At the age of eight he came to America, and despite the handicap of not knowing the English language, Mr. Hansen overcame this obstacle quite readily and developed rapidly in his studies.</p>
   <p>He began his business career as a tool and die apprentice with the Western Electric Company 1893. He was with E. W. Bliss, Brooklyn, N. Y. and Greise Manufacturing Co., New Haven, Conn., from 1897 to 1905, and with the Acorn Brass Manufacturing Co., Chicago, as works manager from 1905 to 1909.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0941.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1909 Mr. Hansen organized the Justrite Manufacturing Co., Chicago, Ill., of which he was vice president and general manager. He sold out his interest in the Justrite Manufacturing Co., in 1920 and organized the A. L. Hansen Manufacturing Co., 5037 Ravenswood Ave., Chicago, of which he is president, general manager and director.</p>
   <p>He is exceptionally versatile and original in his ideas as an inventor, having upwards of 250 patents to his credit. These inventions are used not only throughout the United States but in many foreign countries. Among them are the carbide miners' lamp, automatic liquid measuring machine, tetrachloride fire extinguisher, fireproof chemical container, letter-folding machine, tatting shuttle, hook rug needle, foot pedal refuse container, revolving gum display stand, and numerous other inventions. He has acted as counsellor in the development of inventions for concerns and individuals, but with his varied activities his services in this respect are available only in rare instances. In addition to the wide range of patented products mentioned, Mr. Hansen is also the inventor of a complete line of motor body hardware, including door locks, window regulators, corner braces, etc., and more recently <pb facs="5420780_3_0942.jpg" n="3"/>has developed a variety of refrigerator body hardware, the first of its kind to be produced. During the World war he engaged in designing gas masks and in allied activities.</p>
   <p>He is a member of the Illinois Manufacturers Association, member of the Zoning Commission of Evanston, Ill., and has membership in leading clubs, including the Manistee River Fishing and Hunting Club. His principal recreations consist of golf, fishing and hunting, especially fishing. He is a Republican, Lutheran and Mason. His home is 2129 Central Park Ave., Evanston, Ill., His business address is 5037 Ravenswood Ave., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>One of Mr. Hansen's long cherished hopes, namely to revisit his native land, was fulfilled in June, 1932, when he returned to his homeland, visiting his birthplace in Viborg and other points of special interest and significance to him.</p>
   <p>Combining in an almost equal degree both executive and inventive ability, Mr. Hansen is one of the few exceptions in this respect. He is not an idle dreamer, but a practical, far-sighted business-man, who has made a success not only as an inventor, but in the manufacture and marketing of his products, <pb facs="5420780_3_0943.jpg" n="4"/>all of which we originated in his prolific brain. Besides being intensely practical and highly creative, Mr. Hansen is at the same time a man who possesses the confidence and friendship of his acquaintances, friends, business associates and employees. The mention of his name, either as an individual or a trade-mark upon his products, is a symbol of integrity, solidity and dependability.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
