<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-25">Feb. 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Outline of the Danish-American Association's Activity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0218</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0218.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-25">Feb. 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">OUTLINE OF THE DANISH-AMERICAN ASSOCIATION'S ACTIVITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Danish-American Association is not intended to supplant or render superfluous any other existing Danish-American consolidation. Its policy is one of co-operation; its objective is the furtherance of Danish-American community interests; its goal is unity; its method of government is democracy. The Danish-American Association strives to unite, not to divide.</p>
   <p>The period since the previous annual convention has mainly been devoted to the internal development of the Association, and to the development of plans for the immediate future.</p>
   <p>It has been encouraging to watch the steadily growing interest in the Association of groups of the most varied types, and in this connection it may be mentioned that since the previous annual convention the Association has accepted seventy-one new shareholders. Of these, fifty-six were from America and <pb facs="5420780_3_0219.jpg" n="2"/>fifteen from Denmark.</p>
   <p>The last annual convention voted to organize three district committees for New York, Chicago, and San Francisco. The chief task of these committees was to direct permanent subcommittees from the eastern, the middle western, and the western states, which, each by itself, might arrange meetings and lectures, and entertain the lectures on their tours throughout the United States. In addition the subcommittees were to arrange such socials or exhibitions as local societies might be unable or unwilling to undertake, or which might lie beyond the sphere of activity of such local groups.</p>
   <p>The composition of the Chicago district committee is as follows: Peter J. Noer, chairman; A. M. Petersen, secretary; Henry L. Hertz, Carl Antonsen, O. E. Agerbeck, Henry Ockenholt; Jens Fulsang, Magnus Holm, L. M. Hoffenblad, A. W. Hansen, Max Henius, ex officio members.</p>
   <p>Since the organization of the district committee in Chicago, two changes have <pb facs="5420780_3_0220.jpg" n="3"/>been made. Mr. Peter J. Noer has died, and in his place Mr. Henry Ockenholt was elected chairman, while Mr. Charles Wilde has been made a member. Results of the work of the Chicago district committee are already apparent in the great festival at the Garrick Theater on February 21. It was decided that any surplus from this festival would be used for benevolent undertakings.</p>
   <p>The Chicago district committee further arranged for a most successful excursion to Racine, Wisconsin, on September 26, 1908. This excursion, however, can hardly be considered of more than local significance.</p>
   <p>A change in personnel has taken place within the board of directors of the Association in that Dr. Axel Hellrung of New York has taken the place of Professor Carl Lorentzen who resigned in order to be free to work for a Scandinavian-American exchange of professors at the institutions of higher learning, a matter altogether outside the sphere of the Danish-American Association.</p>
   <p>A critical estimate of the Danish-American exchange of professors, as discussed <pb facs="5420780_3_0221.jpg" n="4"/>in the press, considers this exchange as a greater success than was originally expected. The special committee, under the leadership of which this exchange had taken place, and in which the chairman, Professor Carl Lorentzen, had done much valuable work, has been dissolved. In the future this work will be conducted by the board of directors of the Association.</p>
   <p>The most important reasons for the proposed complete reorganization of the Danish-American Association have already been presented in the introduction to the present annual report, and, besides, have been extensively discussed with the shareholders in a circular sent to them. The chief reason for the proposal is to arrange for practical and reliable guarantees and conditions in order that the Association can devote itself to purely ideal objectives without depending in any way upon shareholders who, as the name implies, might expect financial returns from the activities of the Association. Another, and equally important, reason is the desire to make the Association as democratic as possible, in the conviction that this is an important factor if the Association is to be successful in its undertakings.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0222.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The reorganization means, briefly, that the present Danish-American Association will be dissolved; that the shares will be absorbed, either at their present market value or by the granting of life memberships in the new organization to the shareholders, the shareholders to choose which method they prefer; that a new society be incorporated in place of the present one, under the same name, but without capital and shareholders and "financial profits", the members to pay an annual membership fee.</p>
   <p>The board of directors is strongly convinced that such reorganization is needed in order that the Association may attain its goal. The board has received much encouragement from the letters received from shareholders which indicate that the latter unanimously endorse the stand taken by the directors.</p>
   <p>The board of directors believes that the Association is on the right track, and that under a new and more democratic form of government it will be possible to take more fully into consideration the demands of the Danish-Americans, thereby moving always closer to the ideal which is our goal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
