<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-07-05">July 5, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavians at Kuhn's Park Celebrate Fourth of July.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0363</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0363.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-07-05">July 5, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIANS AT KUHN'S PARK CELEBRATE FOURTH OF JULY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There was dancing by day light and electric light at Kuhn's Park yesterday. Speech making in Danish and in English in the afternoon, and the flow of beer all the time. The picnic of the Danish Veterans Association was a pronounced success and lasted from noon until midnight. It was a fine old Northland picnic imported to America. Thousands of the Danish, Swedish and Norwegian residents of the Northwestern part of the city were there, all in their gala dress or in the uniform of one society or another. The committee having charge of the affair was made up of Maj. T.L.Alstrup, N.C.Gram, T.Z. Eskeldsen, Z. Thorn, L. M. Hoffen-bled, Viggs A. Danielsen and Hardld Schmidt. Everything happened as it should, and the committee was much complimented.</p>
   <p>The column which marched to the picnic grounds at the end of the Milwaukee Avenue cable line formed at Milwaukee Avenue and Ohio Street and, headed by the North Star band marched through Ohio, May, Erie, Center, Huron and Robey Streets and Milwaukee Avenue to the park. All the Scandinavian societies and lodges were <pb facs="5420780_3_0364.jpg" n="2"/>in the column. At the grounds the band furnished dance music in the pavilion and the rag babies and baseballs, the wheel of fortune, the scheme where you get five rings for ten cents and "de can you ring de can you git" - all these and more held out their beguilements.</p>
   <p>At 3 o'clock the speakers were escorted to the stand by the Committee of Arrangements, Stephen A. Douglas and Anthony A. Ellwig advanced patriotic sentiments in English and A.M.Salmonsen and Dr. Tuhlson endorsed the Fourth of July in Danish. After the speaking more dancing and visiting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
