<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-08-17">Aug. 17, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[Heresy and Goldmine Stock]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0484</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <!--
                    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.E.2"/>
    -->
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0484.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III E 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-08-17">Aug. 17, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[HERESY AND GOLDMINE STOCK]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Danish Pioneer expresses its annoyance over the fact that the Reverend Mr. Konow, of Norway, opposes the dogmas of the Immaculate Conception of the Virgin Mary and of the Resurrection of Christ, and yet he is unwilling to retire from his job as a minister in the Church of Norway. In other words, the Pioneer takes sides with the ultra conservative and orthodox elements who have tried for a long time to expel the minister because he is too honest to play the hypocrite. Centuries ago a minister of that sort would have been burned without mercy. There were those who were burned for lesser offenses than the one of which the Reverend Mr. Konow is guilty. In our days stupidity and sentimentality are limiting the efforts to that of getting him out of the Church. But not even that is an easy matter, because the Reverend Mr. Konow refuses to resign on the ground that modern Christianity is something else and more than that of perpetuating old tales and faith in miracles conceived at a time when people did not know better; and there are indications that his superiors inside the Church are of the same opinion, inasmuch as no steps have yet been taken to expel him.</p>
   <p>The Pioneer finds the Reverend Mr. Konow's attitude "somewhat disgraceful," because, after all, there is plenty of room in this world and, therefore, <pb facs="5420780_3_0485.jpg" n="2"/>he should not be so insistant on sticking to one particular place. Oh well! Would it perhaps be better for the Reverend Mr. Konow to join hands with the Pioneer in its more "honorable" occupation of selling stock in a questionable gold mining enterprise to unsuspecting people of its own nationality?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
