<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende</title><date when="1925-06-19">June 19, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Lawlessness</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende, (Danish Times)</title><date when="1925-06-19">June 19, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">LAWLESSNESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All during last week Chicago papers were much concerned about the fact that several police officers has been killed by gansters who thus took revenge.</p>
   <p>The major and chief of police both have proclaimed that there is going to be a cleanup. Suspects have been arrested by the hundreds, and thousands of gallons of alcohol have been confiscated. The guardians of law and order were going to make themselves respected.</p>
   <p>Countless are the pages written on the subject of the prohibition issue, but peculiarily enough, nobody ever writes about the actualcause of this everlasting squabble between the underworld and the police although everybody knows what's wrong, for the simple reason that it cannot be hidden.</p>
   <p>Some time ago while two rival gangs were fighting is out one of the "big shots" was Killed. His friends gave him a princely funeral with fifty automobiles in the parade, and lavishing about thirty thousand dollars worth of flowers, all in order to express their sympathy.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0060.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Be that as it may, but we noticed a number of high public officials such as aldermen, judges and noted politicians etc., attending the funeral. This is not only objectionable, it is out right scandalous, and more so, because this openly admitted connection between the underworld and our public servants is accepted as a matter of course.</p>
   <p>Prohibition is responsible for this sad state of affairs and it will be that way as long as the 18th ammendment is a part of our Constitution.</p>
   <p>Prohibition can be enforced perchance in a small country where the people are closer associated but never in a country as big as the United States. Too much money luring and tempting; millions of dollars have been made by people who otherwise would be ready for the gutter; our law-enforcers are only humans and very frail at that. They are apt to screw the price up too high and a new flare-up of the war is the consequence. Then the police is very stern and merciless, raiding saloons and spilling whiskey. The sacred law is enforced - apparently.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0061.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But it's all bluff. As a rule the warring factions arrive at an understanding very quickly. The saloon keepers are giving repossession of their property or they open up some other place (making the proceedure less offensive) and soon everything is peace and harmony. The cops appear regularily to collect their "dues" and to get their regular "brick in the hat" which they do not attempt to hide.</p>
   <p>It is this fight about the spoils that is going on right in front of us, a fight about an illegal commodity that is demoralizing the respect for law and order, and conditions will hardly improve as long as we have prohibition. It will be a job to get rid of it because the worst offenders are its most eager advocates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
