<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-05-03">May 3, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">M. Salmonsen Passes Away</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Condensed)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_1062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-05-03">May 3, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">M. SALMONSEN PASSES AWAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Condensed)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>M. Salmonsen died last Thursday in his home on Newgard Avenue after a few days illness, at the age of seventy.</p>
   <p>He came to Chicago forty-two years ago, and for the last thirty years held the job of clerk at the marriage license bureau of Cook County.</p>
   <p>Besides assisting young couples in getting married, M. Salmonsen found time for considerable and successful literary activity and was noted as a keen observer and student of human nature and human relations. His From the Marriage License Window had a large sale, as had a play, "We Mortals," and a selection of short stories under the title Among Jews, written with tender feeling and a classical mastery of form.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1063.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While the above mentioned works were written in English, and catering to the general American public, he has, from the time of his retirement, a couple of years ago, been working on his memoirs, which shortly are to be published by Glydendal in Copenhagen under the title Mixed Memories from a 40-Year Sojourn in Chicago, particularly addressed to the Chicago Danish colony and to the Danish public in general.</p>
   <p>The author had a wide acquaintance among the Danish-American leaders and an intimate knowledge of Danish activities in Chicago, and the Memoirs will be a valuable contribution to our knowledge of the city's Danish colony from its earliest days and up to the present time. It is only regrettable that he should not live to see it published.</p>
   <p>Mr. Salmonsen was an honorary member of the society Dania.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
