<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1931-01-02">Jan. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Denmark--A Co-Operative Commonwealth</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1931-01-02">Jan. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">DENMARK--A CO-OPERATIVE COMMONWEALTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: This is one of a series of lectures given throughout the United States.]</p>
   <p>Denmark covers an area of 17,000 square miles, twice the size of Massachusetts, and has a population of three-quarter million. Thirty-six per cent of the inhabitants are engaged in agriculture.</p>
   <p>A deep pessimism spread over Denmark after the War of 1864, when the country lost one of her most valuable provinces to Germany--North Schleswig. The nation went through a period of profound despair, and the people seemed most inclined to give up all hope for the future. If it had not been for the deepseated conviction in one single individual of the mission of Denmark as a nation, and his implicit faith in the Danish people and their future, Denmark might today have been an impoverished and highly insignificant country, not worthy <pb facs="5420780_3_0651.jpg" n="2"/>of mention in the society of nations.</p>
   <p>That man was the educator and reformer, Bishop N. F. S. Grundtvig. He instilled hope into a nation possessed by gloom and despair, and today Denmark is one of the most prosperous countries in Europe. Bishop Grundtvig's methods were educational. He established people's high schools [Translator's note: government subsidized colleges] all over the country which the sons and daughters of farmers attended. In these schools stress was laid upon national history and culture. He instilled in his pupils national pride, and taught them the value of labor. Through these schools, which are unique in character, Grundtvig awakened the youth of Denmark intellectually and spiritually and fitted them for great tasks. He implanted mutual trust and helpfulness in the young Danish farmer, and out of their living together in the high schools, developed a spirit of working together, the spirit which lies at the root of the widespread and internationally known Danish co-operative movement.</p>
   <p>The first co-operative dairy was established in 1881, and today there are more <pb facs="5420780_3_0652.jpg" n="3"/>than 1,400 co-operative dairies in Denmark. A co-operative dairy is usually started by a group of farmers who contribute to its erection, and pledge themselves to supply the milk from a certain number of cows. When the building is completed a trained dairyman is placed at the head of the dairy. The dairy is immediately linked up with an expert butter association, controlled by the farmers, and as soon as the dairy has started, its products join the stream of butter, which is exported to England, Germany, and other countries every day of the year. England has for many years been the chief customer of Danish agricultural products and still is.</p>
   <p>When the Danish farmers had achieved success in co-operative butter production, and raised their butter to a standard quality so that it was considered the best butter in the world, they saw in the traditional English breakfast bacon a new field for their products. They began to raise hogs, and using the same methods employed in the establishment of co-operative dairies, they now began to establish co-operative packing houses. Today there are about sixty large <pb facs="5420780_3_0653.jpg" n="4"/>co-operative packing houses in Denmark, and ninety per cent of the swine butchered in Denmark, are dressed in the co-operative packing houses. In 1924 more than three million swine were killed and exported to the English market. Some of the largest packing houses killed more than one hundred thousand swine in a year. The farmers who are members or share holders in the co-operative packing houses deliver their swine on certain days of the week, and are paid current prices. Each member has one vote in the management of the co-operative. Nobody has more than one vote.</p>
   <p>The co-operatives are managed by experienced men, paid by the farmers. The manager is responsible to all members for the management of the business. He has to be in close contact with the European marketing conditions, and must notify the farmers about different demands from the buyers, demands for heavier or lighter hogs, etc. Likewise he must keep in touch with new methods of combating diseases and inform the farmers of this.</p>
   <p>Once a year, on the day of the general meeting, the surplus or net profit is <pb facs="5420780_3_0654.jpg" n="5"/>divided and paid out through one of the banks. This is paid out in cash and received personally by the farmer. Each year shows an increase in the surplus. Besides being paid for his hogs according to the world market prices, the Danish farmers receive a profit out of the packing house of which he is part owner. His market is always secure, and he is always entitled to the highest prices obtainable.</p>
   <p>In more recent years the Danish farmers have concentrated on another important article on the English breakfast table--eggs. Co-operative egg collecting societies were established in several places in the country, each society covering a certain district. At each of these places the eggs are carefully examined, dated, numbered, and packed to be exported to England. Millions of eggs are exported each year. Being packed in specially designed boxes, the eggs are fresh, when they reach the English customer, and newlaid eggs are in great demand in the large English centers.</p>
   <p>By a very shrewd system of classification and marketing, the packing houses <pb facs="5420780_3_0655.jpg" n="6"/>can trace each of the millions of eggs handled annually to the producer, who runs a great risk of being excluded from the co-operative society if he is responsible for sending in eggs that are not fresh. In the buildings of these egg collecting societies are great tanks, where millions of eggs can be preserved for months and thrown on the British market when the eggs supplied by other countries are scarce. In thirty years, from 1881 to 1912, the value of the exports of Danish agricultural products increased from twelve million dollars to one hundred and twenty-five million dollars. In 1928 the sum was $434,700,000, and it has been steadily increasing since. There are now three hundred thousand small farmers in Denmark. In 1922 2,544,000 tons of wheat, rye, barley, and mixed grains were raised from three million acres.</p>
   <p>As may be expected, the Danish farmer has also learned the great advantage in co-operative import. Large co-operative concerns buy corn and forage, including oil coke, from abroad. Before the war, 1,700,000 tons of oil coke were bought annually. Likewise agricultural machinery and implements are bought by cooperative associations, so that the individual farmer reaps the advantages <pb facs="5420780_3_0656.jpg" n="7"/>through wholesale buying. The Danish farmers have also established hundreds of co-operative retail stores, mostly grocery stores, which are supplied with goods manufactured in their own factories or imported by their co-operative association. In all departments of life the Danish farmer has seen the advantage of co-operative efforts.</p>
   <p>The co-operative associations have representatives in all the larger European countries and in the United States, who investigate marketing conditions and report upon them month by month. The Danish government pays large sums to agricultural experts who experiment with the newest methods beneficial to the farmers. As soon as new methods have proved their worth, the Danish farmer is quick to adopt them. He uses all discoveries which are to his own advantage, and he is always on the alert for any new improvement.</p>
   <p>The Danish farmer is self-reliant and rich in initiative. He feels himself a member of the whole movement, and feels the responsibility he holds as contributing to the success of the movement. He has a world outlook, knowing that <pb facs="5420780_3_0657.jpg" n="8"/>his success is dependent on the equality of his products. He is, with few, rare exceptions, a man of education, and farmers have often held important positions in the government.</p>
   <p>He often has a library of his own. He is alive to all the questions of the day, and each Danish village has an assembly hall where, in the fall and winter months, prominent speakers give lectures on important subjects. He sends his sons and daughters to the people's high schools that he attended in his youth, and they are very early impressed with the importance of the movement and the high place it holds in the life of their nation.</p>
   <p>Many of the young men attend argicultural high schools, and when they start out to farm for themselves they possess an intimate knowledge of scientific farming methods and of the intricacies of the marketing system of the co-operative movement, and they are well qualified to join the ranks of those men who are not inaptly called "the best farmers in the world".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
