<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-03-29">Mar. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Askov, Minnesota</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-03-29">Mar. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ASKOV, MINNESOTA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following is written by Mr. A. Berntsen, a nephew of Premier KI. Berntsen of Denmark:</p>
   <p>"I figure that most Danes in America who are familiar with, and conscious of, our peculiar position as residents of a foreign country know what and where Askov, Minnesota is, and that Askov is a Danish colony organized by Dansk Folkesamfund.</p>
   <p>When I arrived here, together with my family in February, 1908, the Colony numbered seventeen families. The town, or settlement, at that time called Partridge, was located in Pine County, and was insignificant in appearance. The surrounding territory was covered with thousands of stubs and scattered underbrush, the pitiful remains of mighty forests, reminding the newcomer of the disastrous Hinkley fire which went over this section sometime during the Nineties, killing animals and people by the hundreds.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0128.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But in the Spring of 1908, the settlement woke up to life, physically and spiritually. Twenty new families arrived and settled. Carpenters, builders and laborers did a rushing business during the summer, and before Fall, a great many new homes stood ready for occupation. A pretty new bungalow was dedicated to the minister of the settlement, Rev. H. C. Strandskov, who arrived in August. It was clear to all that the work started here was something which should not be stopped now.</p>
   <p>Five years have elapsed since then, a period rich with good memories, and characterized by rapid development. Progress has been made individually, and collectively. As an average of twenty families moved in and settled every year, so we are about six hundred Danes altogether now, and expect the traditional addition this year.</p>
   <p>What does the town of Askov look like now in 1913? There are two grocery stores, a hardware store, a well organized bank, a blacksmith shop, a sawmill, and two painting contractors. Even the station master is a Dane from the Chicago <pb facs="5420780_3_0129.jpg" n="3"/>Southside. We have a fine, modern hotel managed by our friends, Mr. and Mrs. Olsen, also from Chicago's Southside. There are about ten families from Chicago, all apparently happy in their enjoyment of the country's peaceful way of living, so different from the noise and struggle in the big city. During the summer of 1911, a new and modern creamery was built. Our famous countryman, dairy expert, Carl Miller, from West Denmark,Wisconsin, is the manager. The farmers of Askov have their own cooperative feed store, and Mr. L. Masback has started a nursery.</p>
   <p>Much land around Askov is now in excellent shape. A mighty steam threshing machine has been traveling from farm to farm the last two seasons to take care of bumper crops, which is almost a tradition in Askov. Besides dairying and chicken farming, we have another important source of income, namely; potatoes. Unfortunately, the price on potatoes has been low this year, but we feel satisfied in knowing that people living in the city can afford to buy them. A fine, new school has been built. We have a male principal and three female teachers, all Danes. One of them teaches exclusively in Danish four months of the year, and one hour daily is dedicated to Danish <pb facs="5420780_3_0130.jpg" n="4"/>as a regular subject throughout the season.</p>
   <p>The congregation has resolved to build a church next summer. For that purpose, Dansk Folkesamfund has donated $2,000, and the members of the colony have collected $3,000.</p>
   <p>Social activity in Askov is making fair progress. The Ladies Society, whose motto is "Neighborliness above all," is blooming. So is a Young Peoples' Society carrying the beautiful name of "The Forest Rose." Then we have a Farmers' Society, a Cooperative Insurance Society, a Sick and Benefit Society, a Brotherhood Lodge, and the Congregation, each serving its proper purpose for the blessing and benefit of the settlement.</p>
   <p>Our young people are actively engaged in gymnastics and physical culture, which is good for their health.</p>
   <p>The above has been written in response to requests made by friends in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0131.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>I hope that a great many of you may yet make up your minds and come to Askov where the air is pure, and health and happiness are waiting. Are you dissatisfied with conditions in the big city, or are you suffering under the yoke of Capitalism? Come out in the country to live as free and independent citizens.</p>
   <p>Even very limited means will enable you to start on the road to independence. Here, you will have an opportunity to raise a family, healthy and happy, as is the ideal of every father and mother. Masons, carpenters, and laborers can get all the work they want. Of course, even if you have a trade, and depend on that for a living, everybody living in the country ought to have a few acres, say five or ten to cultivate. On such a little farm, there will be plenty to do during periods when nothing else is going on. Thus, your time is not wasted, but made into money.</p>
   <p>Prices on cut over land a few miles outside Askov range from $15 to $20 an acre.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0132.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Cultivated land near the town is not cheap any more. However, there are five and ten acre lots near the town that can be bought at a reasonable price. A few farms, both large and small, situated close to town, are for sale because the owners want to return to Denmark and live in retirement.</p>
   <p>I am at your service in case anybody wishes to be further informed about conditions in Askov. There are those who prefer to listen to a private party, rather than to land agents or banks, etc. I will be happy to respond to such inquiries from friends or from strangers. I shall strive to give the most impartial and accurate information possible. I consider myself in a position to do so, because I am not interested in the sale of land or in any other way financially connected with the development of Askov."</p>
   <p>A. Berntsen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
