<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1927-05-27">May 27, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">From Wilken to Wivel</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0675</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0675.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1927-05-27">May 27, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">FROM WILKEN TO WIVEL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The Round Table," at which the old colonists used to sit during the Eighties and discuss topics of the day in the well-known Wilken's Cellar, on La Salle Street, has at last found a permanent resting place.</p>
   <p>From the sand covered floor of Wilkens, the "table" has crossed the Atlantic to be placed in one of the beautiful dining rooms of Wivel's Cafe in Copenhagen, facing the Tivoli Gardens, where it will rest as a memorial to those who have emigrated to America.</p>
   <p>The room in which the table will be displayed, is to be called the Danish-American Room. One of the best Danish artists has been engaged to paint murals in the room which will portray his arrival at Ellis Island, and his life in America; a life full of joy and sorrow, success and failure.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0676.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It will portray the emmigrant leaving the city, his trip West where he picks up the covered wagon on his way to the prairies. The artist will also portray how after a time he longs for his native soil....</p>
   <p>In the top of the table, many of the men who had sat at the table, have carved their names; many of the old emigrants have now passed away, but then memories still linger.....</p>
   <p>Way back in 1878, when the city limits were not very far from State and Madison, few Danes were found in Chicago, and only a small amount of these settlers met in Wilken's Cellar.</p>
   <p>A few, whose names will be found in the top of the table, are: Poul Geleff, Louis Pio, William Hansen, Poul Loutrop, Professor N. C. Frederiksen, his brother Frederik Frederiksen, the silent Madsen, Monrad, Doctor Pearson, whose name really was Pedersen, Adolph Boysen, and many others.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0677.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was in 1881 that Consul Dreyer introduced the then young Max Henius. In those days, they had the never to be forgotten free bench and five cent wine.</p>
   <p>The Germans who patronized Wilken's, called the "Round Table," "Der Tisch der Danen."</p>
   <p>In its new home, the table probably will not feel at home; it may miss the free bench and ten cent wine.</p>
   <p>Whenever Danish-Americans visit Denmark they will always stop to gaze with pride at the table. They will still see in their thoughts those whose names appear there.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
