<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
LaSalle Book Company, <title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, LaSalle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, 1899, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 412-413.
<title level="a">William Mogensen.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_1175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
LaSalle Book Company, <title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, LaSalle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, 1899, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 412-413.
<title level="a">WILLIAM MOGENSEN.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>William Mogensen, though a native of a foreign country, is a notable example of what may be accomplished by that untiring energy and thrift for which Americans are justly noted. He was born in the city of Copenhagen, Denmark, June 26, 1864, and is the son of a butcher of that place. He received the advantages of a common school education, supplemented by a course in a high school. At the age of fourteen years he entered his father's shop to learn the trade, and put forth every effort to become a practical workman. He continued in his father's employ until 1886, when he married and opened a shop of his own, which he conducted successfully about four years. He had already shown an aptitude for business, and in 1890 left his native town, traveling directly to Chicago, where he knew many of his fellow-countrymen had found comfortable homes and good business advantages. Having acquired but little knowledge <pb facs="5420780_3_1176.jpg" n="2"/>of the language and business methods of the city of his adoption, Mr. mogensen was not able to take up the business for which he had already fitted himself, but was obliged to seek some form of manual labor. His determination to succeed, however, made him welcome any form of honest employment, his first attempt being as a hod carrier. He subsequently worked five months for the Illinois Central Railroad Company, and six months for Marshall Field. He saved his money carefully, at the same time doing his best to master the English language, age, and in 1892 was enabled to open a meat market in Armitage Avenue. His capital at that time amounted to but sixty-five dollars, and some idea of the success of his business may be obtained from the fact that his present stock is valued at ten thousand dollars. To his skill as a practical butcher is due to small amount of his success, but the greater part must be attributed to his rare business sagacity and persevering energy. Though at first his business was necessarily small, he soon won the trade of the best people in his locality, his judgment in the selction of goods being of the first order. He had served an apprenticeship in all branches of his trade and as his business increased, he <pb facs="5420780_3_1177.jpg" n="3"/>began packing meats, and manufacturing various meat products. He found a ready sale for these and has a good trade among other retailers in the northwestern part of the city. In 1898 he bought the building at No. 759 Armitage Avenue, so that his establishment includes three buildings. Nos. 755,757, and 759, in that street. As Mr. Mogensen is still comparatively a young man, it is easy to predict for him continued success and the accumulation of a considerable fortume.</p>
   <p>Despite the fact that business cares take a large part of his attention, the subject of this notice finds ample time for various social obligations. He is a member of Denmark Lodge No. 112, Knights of Pythias; Commonwealth Council No. 72, of the Royal League; Jefferson Lodge No. 20, Order of Columbian Knights; and Chicago Lodge No. 17, of the Danish Brotherhood. Politically he is a Republican. His business connections have given him a wide acquaintance and he has many friends among all classes. Mrs. Mogensen is also a native of Copenhagen, and has been a true helpmeet, assisting her husband very materially in the conduct of his business. They have one son, William.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
