<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
LaSalle Book Company, <title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, LaSalle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, 1899, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 522-523.
<title level="a">Karsten Mikkelsen.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_1142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
LaSalle Book Company, <title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, LaSalle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, 1899, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 522-523.
<title level="a">KARSTEN MIKKELSEN.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Karsten Mikkelsen, who has resided in Chicago more than a quarter of a century, was born September 2, 1852, in the northern part of the province of Schleswig, which was formerly a part of Denmark, but now belongs to Germany. His parents were Niels and Elizabeth Mikkelsen, and he is the third of the six sons born to them. They were both natives of Schleswig, where the subject of this notice spent his boyhood and early youth. He attended the common schools a few years, but when twelve years old, began to learn the tailor's trade with his father. He continued to work with his father during the next six years, and became a rapid and skillful workman.</p>
   <p>But the opportunities for advancement were not great enough to keep him in his native country and accordingly, he began to look for greater advantages in some foreign land. Those of his fellow-countrymen who had emigrated to <pb facs="5420780_3_1143.jpg" n="2"/>this country, sent back glowing descriptions of good business openings to be found in the United States, and young Mikkelsen resolved to try his fortune in the Great Republic. In 1871 he made the journey to Chicago, to which city a large part of the immigration was directed, and there found work at his trade. Until 1878 he worked by the piece, laying by as much as possible of his income.</p>
   <p>To this rigid spirit of economy his start in business is due, as in no other way could he have obtained the necessary capital. With his brother Theodore Mikkelsen, as a partner he established a tailor's shop in Ohio street, which was continued about five years. At the end of that time the partnership was dissolved, each of the brothers going into business by himself. Karsten Mikkelsen first located in Huron street, where he carried on a good business for some time. In 1888 he built his present factory, at No. 286 West Superior Street. He now does a large business in the manufacture of clothing, employing twenty-five hands. He has not abandoned the frugal habits of his earlier days, and the results have been correspondingly greater as his income has increased. Besides owning his business establishment, he has erected a residence at No. 48 Evergreen Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1144.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1878 Mr. Mikkelsen was married to Miss Caroline Nelsen, also a native of Denmark. Their family consists of four sons, Victor, George, Henry and Irvin, all of whom were born in Chicago. The eldest was graduated from Metropolitan College, and has been in the employ of Marshall Field &amp; Company four years.</p>
   <p>The others are still attending school. The subject of this sketch has, in his long years as a business man of Chicago, gained a wide acquaintance, especially among his fellow-countrymen, and has the respect and confidence of all who know him. He is one of the strongest members of the Dania Society, having been connected with that organization since 1874. In political principles he is a Republican, but does not allow his party zeal to prevent his voting for the candidate whom he considers to be the best fitted for official station.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
