<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-03-23">Mar. 23, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[Greetings from the Danish King]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0807</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0807.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-03-23">Mar. 23, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[GREETINGS FROM THE DANISH KING]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the Danish playwright Taugenberg left Copenhagen to visit America, it was solemnly announced that the Danish King had asked him to bring his royal "kind regards" to all Danes over here. We considered the incident a pleasant joke, some sort of superflous politeness for which we have no respect, and we did not expect Mr. Taugenberg to pay any attention to his "royal commission".</p>
   <p>However, we have learned from our "true-to-the-King" paper Nordlyset that Mr. Taugenberg actually pronounced his greeting from "Fatherland and King" at his very first stage performance, and from New York we have the report that he customarily brings "the Danish King's greeting" and proposes "nine cheers for King Frederik".</p>
   <p>Presuming that Mr. Taugenberg intends to carry his royal greetings and cheers <pb facs="5420780_3_0808.jpg" n="2"/>with him farther into the country, we hereby take the liberty modestly to recommend that he put his ear to the ground and proceed with caution. Not all Danes in America have so much fondness for royal frankincense as our snobbish colleagues in the East pretend to have Mr. Taugenberg is going to encounter various opinions as to the necessity and the advisability of a country of Denmark's size having royal institutions, and he is going to meet Danes who are so loyal to this Republic that they resent any sort of propaganda pointing in the opposite direction.</p>
   <p>Mr. Taugenberg comes as an individual. His personality and his art are sufficient greeting from our native land, its people, and its culture. He has as little business to greet us for the King as Mr. Borgbjerg would have had to greet us for the Socialist party, the circumstances being equal.</p>
   <p>If an artist went on a tour in his native Denmark opening and closing every performance with "greetings from the King," people would think he had gone "nuts"; that is, if his audience was not made up of babies or of the inmates <pb facs="5420780_3_0809.jpg" n="3"/>of a conservative club. What we want to point out is that our intellectual standard is above that kind of silliness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
