<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1933-10-27">Oct. 27, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A Well Deserved Honor</title><title level="a" type="sub">To Mrs. George Rasmussen from the America-Denmark Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1933-10-27">Oct. 27, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A WELL DESERVED HONOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">To Mrs. George Rasmussen From the America-Denmark Committee</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Century of Progress, has marked another of the great events in the history of Chicago. Though economic conditions prevented direct participation by most of the nations of the world, this loss has been largely overcome through the active interest of the sons and daughters who trace their descent from these foreign peoples.</p>
   <p>So those of Danish ancestry, have joined as one of the many groups representing foreign nationalities to aid in giving an international cast to A Century of Progress.</p>
   <p>In contributing to the scientific exhibit, Denmark and the Danish race have <pb facs="5420780_3_0914.jpg" n="2"/>been most worthily represented. The story of science, and the contributions made by sons of Denmark to the development of science, and the influence of these developments upon the progress of the world, is told in these exhibits in such a way that has made all those with Danish blood in their veins, feel proud of these accomplishments.</p>
   <p>However, the full and proper representation of the Danish people would not have been complete without something of their capability and their accomplishments in the industrial field being also shown to the millions of visitors who came to view the handiwork of the various peoples of the world.</p>
   <p>To you, and to you alone, the America-Denmark Committee--the Danish people of <pb facs="5420780_3_0915.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago, and of the United States--and also the people of Denmark, are indebted for bringing about this most desired result.</p>
   <p>You steapped in when all others failed; you acted when others hesitated, with the result that when A Century of Progress opened its doors to the world on May 27th, the Danish Industrial Exhibit proclaimed to all in the exhibits of your exquisite Tonder laces, the distinctive Royal Copenhagen porcelain, the Jensen silverware, and Sorensen bronzes, that the love of beauty and the spirit of art was part and parcel of the industrial mind of the Danish people.</p>
   <p>The members of the American-Denmark Committee, as well as Americans of Danish descent throughout the United States, wish to express their appreciation of your work and your efforts in making the Danish participation in A Century of <pb facs="5420780_3_0916.jpg" n="4"/>Progress so marked a success.</p>
   <p>As a memento of this memorable event in the history of Chicago, and as a token of our sincere appreciation, the America-Denmark Committee has the honor of presenting to you this small memorial of your exhibit in the Court of Nations in the Travel and Transport Building of the 1933 A Century of Progress. May it ever remain to you a testimonial, not only as an appreciation of this committee for your worthy action in behalf of the Danish exhibit, but also of the high esteem, as well as the love and affection, in which you are held for the many charities you have so liberally supported, and for the happiness and blessings you have brought into the homes of the many who have been in need.</p>
   <p>America-Denmark Committee</p>
   <p>By</p>
   <p>Peter B. Nelson, President.</p>
   <p>Jens Eriksen, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
