<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1920-01-10">Jan. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Danish Churches of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0448</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0448.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1920-01-10">Jan. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANISH CHURCHES OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are six Danish churches in Chicago; they represent our old mother church in Denmark; they perpetuate the same Gospel which first came to Denmark with Saint Ansgar; they proclaim the same doctrine which sounded from the lips of Hans Tausen in the Viborg Cathederal; they sing the same glorious hymns which are incomparable endowment of Kingo, Brorson, and Grjnotvis. The history of these churches contains the names of such church pioneers as Rordam, P. F. Nielsen, L. Pedersen, Reverend Adam Dan, and I. M. Hansen; and among the laymen we think of such names as S. N. Nielsen, Linden, and many others.</p>
   <p>The recent years have been,here as elsewhere, a period of transition, but although we have been transplanted to the soil of the American commonwealth, and even though we largely employ the American tongue, we are still of the same spirit which governed the hearts and minds of our forebears; we speak the same faith as our church fathers, and it shall <pb facs="5420780_3_0449.jpg" n="2"/>continue to be our purpose to bequeath these spiritual heritages to the coming generations. You will recognize the voices within our churches as being kindred to those of the Landsbykirke [peasant church or rural church.] or Demkirke [High Church at Virborg, Denmark], from which you may hail.</p>
   <p>For your information, and with the hope that you may be able to visit them, we list the churches here in alphabetical order:</p>
   <p>Ebenezer--Reverend C. M. Videbeck, pastor--1655 North Rockwell Street.</p>
   <p>Gethsemane--Reverend N. Plang, Pastor--2624 Fairfield Avenue.</p>
   <p>Golgatha--Reverend C. Justesen, pastor--8000 South Mighigan Avenue.</p>
   <p>Saint Stephan--Reverend Viggo Hansen, pastor--8500 Maryland Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0450.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Siloam--Reverend P. C. Rasmussen, pastor --4314 Cortland Street.</p>
   <p>Trinity--Reverend A.W. Anderson, pastor--2846 Cortez Street.</p>
   <p>Trinity is the oldest of the churches. Golgatha and Saint Stephen's have just been erected and dedicated new edifices, each based on characteristic architectural motifs. Golgatha, in particular, approximates the famous Grundtvig's Church in Copenhagen by the distinguished architect, the late Jensen Klint. Ebenezer is at present contemplating the erection of a new building.</p>
   <p>God's Word is our great heritage</p>
   <p>And shall be ours forever,</p>
   <p>To spread its light from age to age</p>
   <p>Shall be our chief endevor,</p>
   <p>In life it guides our way,</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0451.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In death it is our stay;</p>
   <p>God, grant while words endure</p>
   <p>We keep its teachings pure</p>
   <p>Throughout all generations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
