<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1920-07-17">July 17, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Danish Youth Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1920-07-17">July 17, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANISH YOUTH SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 2, 1889, the members of the Danish Folk Society met in the home of Johannes Jacobsen, 261 West Ohio Street. Here, the Danish Youth Society was organized with a membership of seven. All the organizers had attended the liberal folk colleges in Denmark, and were very much interested in extending Danish culture in America. Of the charter members, only one is living today, Soren Nicolay Nielsen. Christ Christensen, who later joined the Society, has done much in building the organization and making it the important factor it is today in Chicago's Danish colony. Another old member, Lars Jensen, has been instructor in athletics for many years.</p>
   <p>Rasmus Hansen was the organization's first president. Hans Jensen for many years functioned as editor of the Society's paper, Alvor og Gammen [Sorrow and Rejoicing or Sadness and Cheer]. This little paper was first published in longhand and later printed. Its circulation was large.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0536.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the first meeting of the Society, the following executive staff was elected: Christ Christensen, vice-president; Rasmus Hansen, president; Soren N. Nielsen, treasurer. It was decided at this first meeting that a hall should be rented and twenty-two dollars spent for furniture. At the second meeting, held June 12, in the new hall, 63 West Huron Street, eight new members were admitted. It was also decided to have a library consisting of both Danish and English literature. A fund was set up to help Danish youths attend the Danish colleges in the United States.</p>
   <p>At a meeting held on January 15, 1890, it was decided to work for the opening of a Danish college in Chicago. On May 28 the Society moved to new quarters at 512 West Chicago Avenue. In the early part of 1892 the Society moved into its own home at 1214 Irving Avenue. On September 24 of the same year an evening school was started. Rasmus Mortensen was made principal of this school. In 1891 the Society had fifty-two members.</p>
   <p>The Society was growing quite fast, and it soon became necessary to have <pb facs="5420780_3_0537.jpg" n="3"/>larger quarters. In 1891 a sick benefit group was established. On June 12, 1892, the Society met in a new and larger building--Wabansia Hall. In this building many interesting open forums, round table discussions, and book reviews were held. The years 1900 to 1912 were the most active years in the history of the Society.</p>
   <p>During the years 1912 to '17, when the Society was in the midst of a period of educational activity, it operated a young people's home. In that period new people joined the Society, people who in later years were to become leading men and women in the Danish Colony. In 1911 Axel M. Anderson was elected president; in June, 1914, he was elected secretary, and 1919 he was again elected president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
