<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, LaSalle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, <date when="1899">1899</date>, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 44-45.
<title level="a">Lauritz Paulsen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_1178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, LaSalle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, <date when="1899">1899</date>, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 44-45.
<title level="a">LAURITZ PAULSEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lauritz Paulsen, who has been identified with the building interests of Chicago for many years, comes of that strong, aggressive Scandinavian stock which has played such an important part in the World's history. He was born in Denmark September 16, 1853, and in his native town received a common school education. At the age of fourteen years he was apprenticed to a carpenter and, for a period of five years, diligently applied himself to learning the trade. He continued to work as a carpenter in his home town until 1881. In that year he followed the tide of emigration which had been flowing strongly toward America several years, and journeyed to Cleveland, Ohio, where he found work at his trade. Hearing of the greater opportunities for gaining wealth in Chicago, he went to that city the next year, and was employed twelve months by Palmer &amp; Fuller, in twenty-second Street.</p>
   <p>Like all other men who have acquired fortunes from small beginnings, Mr. Paulsen had early adopted frugal, economical habits, and had always saved a <pb facs="5420780_3_1179.jpg" n="2"/>portion of his earnings. He was, therefore, able to enter business on his own account and, having by his two years' residence in this country gained a knowledge of American methods of building, he resolved to apply his efforts in such a way that the profits should be his own. He therefore began buying lots, on which he erected residences. These he sold at a fair profit, and the plan was not only advantageous to him, but also aided in building up the city and furnishing comfortable homes for many of its people. This business was continued until 1893, and resulted in the erection of about fifty houses. With part of the capital thus acquired, Mr. Paulsen opened a lumber yard in 1894 at No. 781 North Avenue. He carries in stock all kinds of lumber required by the builder, both for rough and finishing work. He long experience in superintending the work of building and also as a practical mechanic, render his judgment in the selection of materials as good as the best, and he is patronized by a large number of the first-class contractors in his section of the city. He is the owner of the property where his yards and office are located, and also of a modern residence.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1180.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Though he came to this country comparatively poor, the subject of this notice soon became imbued with American ideas and has shown a fair share of that enterprise and energy for which his adopted country is noted the world over. Not only has he acquired a competence, but has become an honored and respected citizen of his section of the city, where his honesty and integrity are well known. In politics he shows that same independence of character which has marked his business life, but in national affairs he supports the principles of the Republican party. He was married in 1881 at Cleveland, Ohio, to Miss Marie Lassen, a native of Denmark.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
