<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, La Salle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, 1899, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 58-59
<title level="a">John L. Feddersen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_1127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_1127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Album of Genealogy and Biography</title>, La Salle Book Company, Chicago, Illinois, 1899, 11th Edition, Revised and Improved, pp. 58-59
<title level="a">JOHN L. FEDDERSEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John Ludolph Feddersen, one of Chicago's self-made business men, affords a notable example of what pluck and perseverance will accomplish in all the affairs of life. He was born November 25, 1853, in the kingdom of Denmark, and is the third child of Andrew L. Feddersen, who died when his son was but five years of age. The latter remained in his native town until he reached the age of fifteen years, getting his education in the schools of Aventoft.</p>
   <p>Having inherited that love of the sea which made his horse forefathers rulers of the deep, he secured a position as cabin boy on a sea-going vessel at the age of fifteen years. His first trip was from Hamburg to the West Indies; the journey occupying six months. The next trip was to Rio Janeiro, which also consumed six months. He then started for China and, six months later, after arriving at Hong Kong, he was made a full sailor. He remained there three years trading on the coast of China. Subsequently he was promoted to second mate of a Norwegian ship, and in that position followed the sea about <pb facs="5420780_3_1128.jpg" n="2"/>three years. His last cruise was from Hamburg to Philadelphia, and he landed in the latter city in 1875. He worked on a farm in Pennsylvania two months, receiving twenty-five dollars per month, and then started for Chicago, which was the goal towards which many of the emigrants journeyed. He arrived in that city July, 1875, and, taking whatever work was offered, was employed about two onths in a brick yard. He then worked for the same employer on a farm, and in the winter returned to the city, where he found work of various kinds in the Union Stock Yards. He then went to Lake View and hired himself to a gardener,,with whom he remained a year.</p>
   <p>In 1877 he married and, during the hard tames incident to that year, found it hard to make both ends meet, but he persevered, establishing in that year a wholesale fish business. This was the first effort at doing business on his own account, and though at first he had many discouragements, his trade gradually increased, and in the course of two years his reputation as an honest dealer drew to him a lucrative patronage. Three years after his opening the fish market he added oysters to his stock, and has built up a large trade in <pb facs="5420780_3_1129.jpg" n="3"/>both lines. He has been ruled throughout his business career by the same careful methods which made it possible for him to build up a successful business, and has acquired a comfortable property. Besides the house at No. 22 Potomac Avenue, where he lives, he also owns a two-story flat building at No. 14 Mormon Street, which is rented.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Feddersen, whose maiden name was Anna Christensen, was born in Denmark and came to America at the age of twenty-seven years. To Mr. amd Mrs. Federsen have been born five children, namely: Louis, who is married and in business in Chicago; Chriatina, living at home; Andrew, who assists his father; and Jens and Ludolph, both residing at home. The subject of this notice is a member of Wicker Park Lodge No. 281, Independent Order of Odd Fellows, and has received all the honors which the subordinate lodge can confer. Politically he is a Republican.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
