<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-12-27">Dec. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Danish Nonsense</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0617</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0617.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A (Greek, Italian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-12-27">Dec. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">DANISH NONSENSE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The society Danish Land, has asked a number of more or less prominent Danes about their opinion in regard to Danish emigration and the best means of stopping or reducing it. We want to call to our readers' attention two of the answers which the society received.</p>
   <p>One is from a farmer by the name of Abel, who thinks that "the emigrants are for the greater part people who have made themselves impossible at home, and who do not like to work." This man Abel is chairman of the board of directors of Danish Land, and we wonder what kind of society it can be that will place such a narrow-minded person as one of its top officers. The statement is thoughtless, irresponsible nonsense to say the least.</p>
   <p>The second answer is that from a Mr. Westenholtz, an industrialist, who <pb facs="5420780_3_0618.jpg" n="2"/>considers emigration "an unqualified evil." He himself is spending most of his time outside of Denmark. He goes on to say that Danes who settle in America do not seem to care for the mother-land in the manner that,for instance, Greeks and Italians do.</p>
   <p>It might do Mr. Westenholtz some good to read the little book The Danish-born American, which was published last year. It would give him an idea of the deep affection which the emigrated Danes have for the country of their birth, and what they have done during the past generations to maintain the spiritual connection with homeland and preserve their Danish cultural heritage.</p>
   <p>It is right that we do not imitate the Greeks and Italians, who, in most cases, only stay here for a few years, trying to scrape together as much money as possible. We settle here, make our homes here, and take pride in being good citizens of our adopted country, and for doing so, <pb facs="5420780_3_0619.jpg" n="3"/>we are being discredited by people of Mr. Westenholtz's type. Fortunately, many leading Danes, such as Ambassador Molkte, Professor Rovsing, Johan Skjoldborg, and others, take another view.</p>
   <p>The industrialist is a very wealthy man of the type that are unable to appreciate any other values than the dollar. He, therefore, speaks contemptuously of the Rebild Park (Translator's note: The Rebild Park is a gift to Denmark from Danish-Americans) as "a microscopical national gift which is a good measuring stick for what the emigrated Danes can do." This is in contrast to Mr. Dalgas, who stated that "thanks to the generosity of Dr. Henius and like-minded Danish-Americans, the park is laid out and will be preserved as a silent but living witness of the magnificence of the desolate heath."</p>
   <p>Men like Abel and Westenholtz should attend to their own business and refrain from discussing matters that they do not understand.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0620.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Their statements in regard to emigrated Danes only serve to discredit themselves and the society Danish Land.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
