<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-06-10">June 10, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The National Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">Trata-ta-Bom! Trata-ta-Bom!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_3_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-06-10">June 10, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE NATIONAL FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Trata-ta-Bom! Trata-ta-Bom!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1.... All that noise was caused by the National Festival procession as it marched under Bengal lights along the Danish thoroughfare, North Avenue, last Saturday night.</p>
   <p>The ladies committee was riding up in front, greeted by waving and shouting onlookers. Next came the president, Bauer, surrounded by the Children's Choir, dressed in white, then the national dancers in multi-colored costumes and finally the bands.</p>
   <p>At 3:30 P.M. Sunday the large throng gathered about the speakers' platform in Riverview Park.</p>
   <p>After having delivered his welcome speech, M. Wald Bauer, president of the general committee, nominated Dr. Max Henius, as master of ceremonies.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_3_0322.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(Acclamation). Mr. Carl Antonsen spoke for the Danish constitution and briefly reiterated its history. He mentioned the "Kasino" men, Orla Hehmann, Ploug and Tcherning and also touched upon the attitude of Frederick the 7th and Christion the 8th towards the constitution.</p>
   <p>Corporation counsel L.D.Mathias, representing the mayor of Chicago paid tribute to Denmark, characterizing it as a model country, and its citizens as free men and women not slaves of the exploiters (Hear!) Free men and women of Denmark. I greet you! (Wild applause).</p>
   <p>Ex-mayor of Racine, Peter B. Nelson, talked about America, and particularly discoursed on its legislation, maintaining that the less strictly a government hangs on to the letter of the law, the better it is.</p>
   <p>Consul George Bech spoke for Denmark. Our memories and our language form the strongest ties between us and the old country. The women are specially desirous to preserve the language and he felt sure there was not a mother in the audience who had not taught her child to say "The Lord's Prayer"in Danish. Between speeches the audience was entertained with singing among <pb facs="5420780_3_0323.jpg" n="3"/>others, by the great childrens' choir. Following the last speech "Harmonien" and "The Worker's Singing Society sang together from the platform "In Denmark I was Born."</p>
   <p>Later on there was a successful gymnastic performance by members of "Freja" and songs by "Magneten" and by"Brage" from Kenosha, etc.</p>
   <p>After the speechmaking everybody visited the restaurant operated by the Childrens' Home, and the manager Mrs. Petersen told us later that two hundred pounds of coffee and three thousand sandwiches were consumed; the tavern, Three Bottles" enjoyed a thriving business to the tune of twenty-seven barrels of beer.</p>
   <p>The folk dancers, wearing national costumes, performed on a platform erected for that purpose, and drew a large and enthusiastic audience, which greatly enjoyed the "Tantoli", Sailor's dance, French heel, the "Ax" dance, "Kulla" dance, etc.</p>
   <p>The number of participants increased during the evening and reached 11,000 to 12,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
