<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-19">July 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Without a Title</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0665</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0665.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-19">July 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">WITHOUT A TITLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How everything changes in this world! As long as a person finds himself in a large city, he also feels himself to be great, wise--he has at his command an inexhaustible supply of titles for articles. Nothing is difficult for him, he knows everything--he comprehends everything; all the others, that is, those from the country, are unenlightened, uneducated, and uninformed people, being incapable of acquiring great ideas with which even the air is saturated in the large cities. Such large cities have great ideas and, hence, great people are necessary in them. But how everything does change in them! Usually, when a person leaves the metropolis and this himself to some remote spot in the unenlightened countryside, although everyone respects and honors him as a person coming from the large city and from higher educational institutions, he feels somewhat deprived of these great ideas and views; he becomes so similar to the rural illiterati that he even loses the ability to write a silly title for an article with which he hopes to <pb facs="5423968_6_0666.jpg" n="2"/>enrich Polish-American literature.</p>
   <p>Not so long ago, I do not recall when, during or after a certain dinner, a prominent and educated man--most likely a professor of the French language in some academy--said the following words: "These people under Prussia (Poles) are the worst people, because each of them knows how to write and read. There Bismarck compelled them under a whip to attend school. Through force, they have somehow learned to spell and scribble. Arriving here in America, when something happens or when something is unfavorable to them, they immediately swamp the press with correspondence." Yes, he is right; I, too, come from Posen, hence, from the Prussianpart of Poland, but I do not recall that anyone compelled me to attend school under threats of physical, corporal punishment. I attended one school, then another which was very distant from my home location. I even visited schools that had great pillars, with large windows, and great massive doors that look like enormous gates--where students just sit with open mouths and drink in the <pb facs="5423968_6_0667.jpg" n="3"/>words that are poured forth by those great men called professors. Here these last-mentioned schools are called universities. Only great people come out of these schools, but I would not wish to be included among them.</p>
   <p>Although I come from Posen, thus far I have sat quietly. Living in a large city and working from morning until night, although I wanted to feel great, I was compelled on several occasions to bow my head low in humility before the geniuses of the large cities. Enough of this now. There, exhausted from work, on the one hand and from fear of antagonizing literary lights on the other, I was almost forced to keep quiet, examining and admiring the creations of these geniuses of the people.</p>
   <p>Now, however, ridding myself of the idea that these great men are omnipotent, I find myself free of this fear--I can openly come out and express my opinion and I presume that it is not merely a personal one.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0668.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Knowing how to read, I was greatly interested in the fine literature of the Polish-American newspapers, and have often admired the style, the depth of views, the intellectual loftiness and strength of the people writing to these newspapers. At times I was elated beyond measure, and, at other times, the spirit of these ideas have cast me into an abyss of hell. I have read various Polish papers and the thing that particularly induces me to write these words is only the assertion of these newspapers that all of them consider themselves to be Catholic, defending the interests of the Church, and to be patriotic, defending the causes of Poland and the Polish people, although they are most contradictory in their ideas and arguments.</p>
   <p>Some base their Catholicism on some kind of a "pure" gospel; they write calumnously against the Church, on the abuses committed by the Polish priests; they blacken and disgrace them. They thus claim that they always write the "truth" about everyone. They wish to purge the Catholic people of the idlers, fanatics, biased, ignorant parasites, and the like. They <pb facs="5423968_6_0669.jpg" n="5"/>write that they have no other purpose in their writings but the good of the people. But, I ask, what kind of a good do they wish to inculcate through calumny as well as through moral poison, sowing discord, suspicions, and lack of confidence in the spiritual leaders. True, abuses do occur occasionally, but there is an ecclesiastical authority for this, and it is for the bishops to place a restraint against such abuses. But who gave them the power and authority to treat of matters in their worthless papers; to treat of items which they do not understand and of which they lack the slightest knowledge, published by people deprived of faith; people who could be called moral bankrupts of society, and who were and still are avowed foes of the Church and truth? "Cobbler, stick to your last." That is a maxim that should be applied here and I assure you that the result would be successful. Let the writers express their tendencies clearly, let them abide by them; to camouflage oneself with someone else's mantle is really a Judaic and treacherous procedure, and sooner or later the truth will out, and every honest person will spit in the face of the hypocrite.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0670.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>There are a few Polish periodicals that proclaim their Catholicism throatily but no one believes in their assurances because their schismatic tendencies are but too clear. Some of them, presumably carrying this title [Catholic] rightfully, keep quiet and do nothing to enlighten the people and strengthen the faith in the public. They write of everything but the matter that was the cause of a scandal and which should be explained and culpability for it indicated. This they pass over in silence. That is what enables those who sow dissention and misunderstanding openly to give vent to their malice. Others, again, base their Catholicism and patriotism on the habit of scoffing at everything that is not in accordance with their ideas. They ridicule and condemn everything and, in addition, they often resort to words that are improper and use terms that burn the ears. When I remarked, with reference to one of the great Catholic literati, that everything should be treated with dignity and that one should never engage in personal polemics, I received a reply of this type: "But do they spare us, do they not write against me continually?....." An old proverb says, "If some one casts a <pb facs="5423968_6_0671.jpg" n="7"/>stone at you, then you cast bread at him." That, I think, is the best method of battle. Every matter should be treated Calmly, if I may so express myself. Every matter should be treated with deliberation, dignity, and decorum. If it hurts us when we are scratched, it also hurts the others when we scratch them. What is unpleasant to you should not be done to others. The main principle of Catholic writers should be love for truth and dignity. I believe that if writers were governed by this principle, everyone would readily see their tendencies. He will concieve the principles and know their value.</p>
   <p>Especially during the last days, a certain widely publicized "Catholic" paper, "whose title begins with capital W, and which is edited in a city whose name begins with W, began to fill its columns, even entire pages, with the most detestable calumnies against greatly respected and worthy priests, religious orders, and Polish institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0672.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Two W's are evidently too many, and I should not wish to admit that the author of this filth and these lies is a man who has supposedly attended great schools, the ones that have great pillars, large windows and enormous doorways, and in which professors teach. No, I should not wish to attribute that title to the author of such a work. All those who have or have not finished great schools call him "King of authors". In my opinion I would use the two capital W's and would call him "The Great Ox" (Wielki Wol), for, like an enraged beast he will throw and cast himself on the people, destroying and crushing everything he meets. An enraged animal stampedes ahead; it does not look ahead nor does it see any danger to itself until it falls and perishes. So too, will it be with the author of the calumnous articles. It is hoped that he will take note before that happens, because I believe that he will be unable to run that way very far.</p>
   <p>Really, upon reading these articles, knowing the style of the writing, knowing who their author is, I wonder whether that man suffers from a <pb facs="5423968_6_0673.jpg" n="9"/>fever,or from attacks....In truth, it reflects shame on the author, shame on the writer, who publicizes any such thing and at the same time claims vociferously that he is a Catholic, that he states the truth to all, that he has the good of the Church and the good of the Polish people at heart. May God protect us from such a plague and from a similar attack. For my part, I claim that everyone who supports this writer with his money, degrades himself because he supports a writer that degrades and dishonors his brothers. The writer of these articles is contemptible and deserving of the name of a liar--because through lies and insults he dishonors the good name of his brothers.</p>
   <p>Everyone who feels himself to be a Catholic should hold in contempt such a filthy writer who dares call himself a Catholic. So long as he will not alter his tactics he should be thrown out through the door so as not to degrade the home.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0674.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Only now do I see that the professor of the French language was justified in making the previously mentioned statement, because it is really better not to know how to read or write than to fill columns with filth, which every respectable person must hold in contempt.</p>
   <p>Thus, toward the end, various ideas began to come to my mind, as to the title, but these were so confused that it was difficult to make a selection and for that reason I leave it as it was written.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
