<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-08-15">Aug. 15, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The American Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-08-15">Aug. 15, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICAN PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The report of the Census Bureau of Washington informs us that the American press ranks very high among the leaders of industry, its net income for the year 1909 being $883,584,000.</p>
   <p>In 1909 there were 31,455 publications in the United States. They provided with means of existence 258,434 regular workers, 90,608 pensioned employees, and 30,424 owners, or a total of 388,466 people, who earned $268,086,000 annually.</p>
   <p>We have 2,600 daily newspapers in this country, 520 Sunday papers, 15,097 weekly and 2,491 monthly papers. Of the total amount of these publications 17,698 are called political and information newspapers, 1,251 newspapers serve various religious denominations, 685 are concerned with commercial <pb facs="5423968_6_0470.jpg" n="2"/>affairs, 419 serve various organizations and 340 are greatly interested in art and literature. Many of these papers and periodicals are published in languages other than English; there are over sixty such publications printed in the Polish language. These figures may not be quite accurate.</p>
   <p>The subscription to these Polish publications brings an annual amount of $135,000,000., and from advertisements these publications earned $196,000, 000.</p>
   <p>With the exception of several professional publications, magazines and a few daily and weekly newspapers, the American press stands on a very miserable ground.</p>
   <p>Let us take the first best American publication; at once we will orientate ourselves as to its origin and value. In the first place we have to look at the classified ads, as the main source of income of the paper; the news <pb facs="5423968_6_0471.jpg" n="3"/>items, on the other hand, are of secondary importance.</p>
   <p>By its principles and cautious methods, the American press, especially as a political-informer, should rank very high; however, it does not, because it is in the hands of exploiters and dishonest financiers. The technical side of the American press is conducted excellently.</p>
   <p>American newspapers greatly favor the millionaire centers in New York, Chicago, Philadelphia, etc. This is so despite the low price of the papers and the small percent of illiterates in the United States( i.e. despite the fact that these papers are accessible to and are actually read not only by the rich, but also by the toiling masses). We must take into consideration that the United States has a population of over 100,000,000 people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
