<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-12-19">Dec. 19, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Enrollment in Kosciuszko Gymnasium</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0909</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0909.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-12-19">Dec. 19, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ENROLLMENT IN KOSCIUSZKO GYMNASIUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Kosciuszko Park Gymnasium, opened by the Northwest Park District about ten days ago as a recreation center for Polish boys and girls in the neighborhood of Avers and Diversey Avenues, already has an enrollment far in excess of what even the sponsors had hoped for.</p>
   <p>Under the direction of George Sonnenlieter, physical instructor, and Julia Schulte, his assistant, more than two hundred Polish youngsters are now attending classes at the gym which was provided by the district board as an experiment to see how the Polish children would take to the idea.</p>
   <p>Alderman Frank Ringa, who with Joseph Gubbins, president of the district, and Eden T. Brekke, secretary, was instrumental in inducing the board to establish the gymnasium, has expressed himself as elated with the large enrollment.</p>
   <p>"Two hundred are already in our classes, and more are coming" Mr. Gubbins declared. "We can take care of them all. Although the entire neighborhood has manifested great enthusiasm, we are particularly pleased with the unanimous <pb facs="5423968_6_0910.jpg" n="2"/>acceptance of the gymnasium by the Polish youngsters."</p>
   <p>The gymnasium is given over to the boys on Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays from 4 P. M., to 10 P. M., and to the girls on Tuesdays and Thursdays at the same hours. There are classes is gymnastics, wrestling, boxing, basket-ball, volley ball and many other athletic games.</p>
   <p>Frank M. Kalteaux, director of receation of the district, has announced that he plans to have young amateur boxers trained in the gymnasium for the various club amateur bouts held throughout the city and the annual Chicago Tribune Golden Glove tournament. Already six boxers have developed sufficient ability to be entered.</p>
   <p>The Northwest Park District has fourteen recreation centers and playgrounds over its area, but this is the first plant of this kind established by the organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
