<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. 25, No. 59,
<date when="1921-10-19">October 19, 1921</date><title level="a">The Press about Our Newspaper</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. 25, No. 59,
<date when="1921-10-19">October 19, 1921</date><title level="a">THE PRESS ABOUT OUR NEWSPAPER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(EDITORIAL)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our newspaper, the Dziennik Zjednoczenia is a success.</p>
   <p>We announce this fact with a great satisfaction and pride.</p>
   <p>True Polish patriots and good Catholics appreciate the appearance of such a newspaper as Dziennik Zjednoczenia; they prove this by their letters of praise to our editors.</p>
   <p>The opinion about our paper, for which we care most, has been expressed by those who have a great influence in one community and who know something about the matter.</p>
   <p>For this great appreciation we are thankful to our patriotic Polish clergy. Such words of praise and appreciation give us an encouragement and strength to fight the evil, which is being spread among our people in America by the subversive elements.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0318.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What is the attitude of the Polish American press towards our newspaper?</p>
   <p>From the material which we have on hand in our office now, we judge that our "colleagues of the pen" consider our newspaper one of the most influential and respected organs of our nationality.</p>
   <p>Other newspapers, related to us spiritually and ideally, compliment us, and none offer any serious criticism. However, our newspaper is the "salt of the earth and a thorn in the side" of our Polish American subverters. They have shown very plainly their great displeasure. They care more for the pocket books than the souls of their adherents. They never commit the sin of discrimination between right and wrong.</p>
   <p>The leftists' press in general, expressed uneasiness, for they know that they will have a hard battle to fight, for our newspaper will have some very convincing arguments which cannot be easily contradicted by any silly phraseology, because our argument will be based on facts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0319.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We know the subverters and their deeds very well and this knowledge is very painful to them.</p>
   <p>The editors of the leftists' press calling themselves progressives try to ridicule us but do not offer any constructive criticism.</p>
   <p>Frankly speaking, the whole subversive press is losing a lot of sleep on account of our newspaper.</p>
   <p>We thank our colleagues very kindly for devoting so much of their time to our newspaper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
