<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-27">Mar. 27, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Literary and Educational Foundation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0055</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0055.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-27">Mar. 27, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH LITERARY AND EDUCATIONAL FOUNDATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Sigmund Slupski, who resides at present in Chicago, has originated the idea of creating a fund to support a new Polish institution. Such an institution as he contemplates could provide a material impulse to our cultural advancement. The project is well on the way toward realization. It is to be a fund having for its aim the establishment of Polish literary and scientific competitions. Thus, competitions will be established in writing of short stories, novels, satires, plays, and scientific treatises. They are to be written in Polish, using Polish-American life as a background.</p>
   <p>It is needless to say that an idea of this sort, handled intelligently, can do much to stimulate thought among our Polish-Americans. While the number of representatives of the Polish intelligentsia in America is small, even in this group it could create new impetus and possibly bring new talent forward. On the other hand, such works could give the people of Poland a much more accurate picture of conditions here than that which mere newspaper accounts give them. The only problem, then, is to establish the fund.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0056.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Slupski assures us that definite progress has already been made in this direction. Our famed artist Mr. Paderewski has offered three hundred dollars to start the fund, and Mr. W. Dyniewicz, publisher of the Polish Gazette, has offered one hundred dollars. It is hoped that further contributions will be made by the public, and that the fund will be increased later by profits made from the publication of prize winning works. Further, dramatic societies presenting stage plays will be expected to set aside a percentage of their receipts for this fund. In consideration, such societies will be permitted to present, free of charge, plays that receive awards in the competition.</p>
   <p>The headquarters of the foundation is to be in Chicago. The foundation will be directed by a committee consisting of Peter Kiolbassa, M. Labuy, M. Drzemala, J. H. Xelowski, and Sigmund Slupski. New judges will be named every time a separate competition is announced, and final judgment will probably be passed in Poland, in Krakow or Lwow.</p>
   <p>In a short time, further details will be made public by the committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
