<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-12-03">Dec. 3, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Sunday Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-12-03">Dec. 3, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SUNDAY SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nothing has been mentioned about the meeting attended by Polish secular and clerical representatives relative to laying plans for Sunday schools in Polish parishes throughout Chicago and to giving instructions to the teachers. So many persons attended that it is possible for eight Polish parishes to open classes on December 12. Lecturers were chosen for each parish and instructions given as to the nature of the topics to be presented. The only obstruction met at the meeting held Wednesday, December 1, was the time element. Some pastors desire to have the school sessions held in the morning while others want them held in the afternoon, and still others in the evening. In order to come to a definite understanding as to the time, another meeting is scheduled for next Tuesday evening.</p>
   <p>It seems that this matter did not go so smoothly at the last meeting as it was <pb facs="5423968_6_1063.jpg" n="2"/>anticipated. This assumption is based upon the following facts.</p>
   <p>There is no definite knowledge as to planning a program for the public. The arrangement of such a plan is no easy task. This matter was turned over to a committee at the first meeting held over six weeks ago. For some unknown reasons this group was unable to meet at a time when all could be present to iron this matter out. Consequently a meeting was called for last Wednesday, and a skeleton was made up, unfortunately without foundation.</p>
   <p>If in all the eight parishes regular classes are to be held and the lectures based on religion, Polish history and literature given once a week, it is hoped that some unity as to subject matter will be retained, so that after about twenty lectures each field will be completely covered. In this respect the second talk must be a continuation of the first, and so on. Without this the lessons presented by various priests and secular teachers will have no conformity, which will undoubtedly be very confusing to the young listeners.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1064.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In order to make this program a success, each speaker must be prepared to give a series of talks in perfect sequence on a given subject. As long as this is not going to be fulfilled and readily comprehended by the committee as well as the pastors, such a program will not be of great value.</p>
   <p>It is deemed that the proposed speakers will acknowledge this fact and will work in the direction of unity in order to make their presentations a success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
