<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-09-05">Sept. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">After the Convention</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-09-05">Sept. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AFTER THE CONVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention of Polish newspapermen who sympathize with the [Polish] National Department has come and gone, and was successful, if not by the number of newspapermen who attended, then at least by the far-reaching decisions it made. It must be noted here that those who arranged the convention understood that this would only be a preparatory convention, and that the second one being planned will be in every respect a general convention of Polish newspapermen of America.</p>
   <p>Great words were uttered at this convention, great mottoes expressed. The most important decision, perhaps, was the one to drop all partisanship and to reach out a fraternal hand to political opponents for the good of a common cause, the Polish cause which can be strengthened, not by our disunity, but by our mutual co-operation and harmonious action.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0419.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The resolution adopted by the convention amid tremendous enthusiasm and applause included these paragraphs:</p>
   <p>"The Convention of Polish newspapermen of America recognizes the fact that, for the achievement of our peoples' aims, it is vital that the Polish-American press be unequivocally united--for the cause of our homeland demands that we stand, not divided into factions and struggling among ourselves, but united, for a unanimous aim requires a unanimous front.</p>
   <p>"Casting aside the quarrels and disagreements of the past, we call upon the entire Polish press of America to desist from quarreling and from base and destructive polemics, to reshape its policies with respect to the Polish cause, and to lay upon the altar of that cause all personal differences, real or imagined. We call upon all publishers to join hands and close our nationalist ranks into one file."</p>
   <p>The convention, then, calls upon the entire Polish-American press to unite <pb facs="5423968_6_0420.jpg" n="3"/>because Poland's cause requires union; it asks further that our newspapers desist from destructive quarrels and bickerings among themselves and to reshape their policies with respect to the Polish cause, to a reaching out of fraternal words and a closing of the ranks into one file. What more could have been done? Did not the convention act just as it should have acted?</p>
   <p>Let this step be judged by those who did their best to ridicule the convention in order to discourage from attending, some of the newspapermen who disagreed with the idea of the convention but who now must and should agree with its decisions.</p>
   <p>We have offered our hands in peace. We have offered a fraternal hand, "casting a veil upon the quarrels and disruptions of the past," we have appealed to everyone for mutual effort in behalf of those ideals so sacred to all Poles today, and it is our opinion that this step will meet the approval of the entire American Polonia, and that everyone will look to it with favor. We wait to see how our pure, sincere intentions, unblemished by any wrong or unworthy <pb facs="5423968_6_0421.jpg" n="4"/>thought, will be received by our opponents. We believe that they will receive it in the same spirit in which it was created, and that the desire to serve the Polish cause will be the golden bridge to unity on which we shall all meet.</p>
   <p>Before we begin to discuss other matters that were discussed and decisions that were made at the convention, before we can begin to evaluate the real significance of the convention, we wish to give this matter of unity our first attention, for, at least in our opinion, it towers above all others. One of the guests from Europe who attended the convention justly observed that politics is compromise, and whoever cannot compromise is not and cannot be a politician; the delegates at the newspapermen's convention opened the way to compromise, feeling that an elimination of partisanship is not only possible, but is essential, and can be accomplished only through compromise.</p>
   <p>The press should be the first to appeal for a compromise, for when an understanding is reached amongst its members, when vain and fruitless quarrels amongst its members cease and real co-operation begins, then the entire nation will cease <pb facs="5423968_6_0422.jpg" n="5"/>its internal quarrelling and will begin to work for our mutual aims and ideals.</p>
   <p>With this in mind, we set the next convention at a date not too far ahead and all [Polish] newspapermen will be asked to attend. It may be that some sort of Modus Vivendi will be found before then, if there is any understanding of the problem and desire for harmony on the other side. Detroit was chosen as the place for the next convention, and this for the simple reason that it should be in the city of Detroit, where the bitterest struggles between the two camps occur, that a fraternal understanding be reached.</p>
   <p>We want to believe, and we do believe, that this will happen. The situation today demands it, and we are under the impression that there is none amongst us who, once convinced of the right, will not forsake the path of wrong and enter upon the straight and narrow road that leads directly to the resurrection of Poland. Let the slogan "Nothing for myself, everything for my homeland" become the base for our efforts and our activity. Let us cast a veil upon what has been, let us forget those things that divided us into two hostile camps, <pb facs="5423968_6_0423.jpg" n="6"/>and we shall show that Thanksgiving Day in Detroit will be a "second Pittsburgh" for the two embattled camps, that it will be a day of new enthusiasm and mutual vows for the good of our homeland, our Mother Poland.</p>
   <p>Dziennik Zwiazkowy, Sept. 6, 1917.</p>
   <p>AFTER THE CONVENTION</p>
   <p>(Editorial)</p>
   <p>II</p>
   <p>Weighing further the decisions of the Polish newspapermen's convention, we find it necessary to emphasize two, namely, the establishing of the [Polish] National Department in authority, and decision to form the Association of Polish Newspapermen of America. Both of these matters are worthy of attention.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0424.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The convention of Polish newspapermen proved itself to be a gathering of disciplined and thoughtful people. The chief concern here was to obtain unqualified support and establishment of its authority for the National Department which, as a body consisting of representatives of all of the Polish organizations, religious, civil, and nationalistic, here in America, must be our highest authority in nationalistic matters and must enjoy the general confidence of the Polish element here.</p>
   <p>Attempts have been made, from time to time, to criticize this or that in the National Department with respect to its agenda relative to the Polish press. This was done, however, only for the purpose of correcting errors, of properly normalizing conditions between it and ourselves so that the National Department can be certain that, in supporting itself upon the press gathered beneath its banners, it can count upon unqualified support and proper discipline.</p>
   <p>We have given proof of this. Whenever it happened that--whether it was in a motion brought forward by the motions committee, a discussion, or a suggestion--the <pb facs="5423968_6_0425.jpg" n="8"/>competence of the National Department was questioned, or matters were touched upon in which the first decision should have come from the National Department, there were always those present who called attention to the fact that this or that was out of order, that at best the press agrees in this matter, or that decision and action should be left to the National Department.</p>
   <p>And that is how it must and should be. Organized society must have leadership, a brain that will think for it and make decisions. The constitution and quality of the leadership depends entirely upon the given society. In nations consisting of philosophers, the leaders will be philosophers; in nations of savages, the leaders will be savages. With us, the leadership must consist of representatives, people who have earned the confidence of the majority, and who head various organizations. This is a simple matter, and all questioning of a body consisting of such representatives arises either from evil intentions or is out of place.</p>
   <p>The convention of Polish newspapermen recognized this, and with all confidence <pb facs="5423968_6_0426.jpg" n="9"/>submitted itself to the direction of the National Department, pointing the way to others.</p>
   <p>The second extremely important decision made by the convention was that of creating the Association of Polish Newspapermen of America. In truth, no constitution nor aims have yet been set, but that will be taken care of by a commission selected for this purpose which will submit its program before the editors and publishers at the convention in Detroit; but the matter stands now upon a firm foundation.</p>
   <p>More than once we have been witnesses of the organization of similar newspapermen's and publishers' associations. None survived the test of time. The need, however, of such a professional organization is a real one, since it is ever discussed and considered.</p>
   <p>From the enthusiasm with which the convention received the proposal, it can be assumed that this newly organized Association of Polish Newspapermen as a <pb facs="5423968_6_0427.jpg" n="10"/>completely nonpartisan, purely professional organization in every sense, and will be able to survive, providing that its principles and fundamental laws will be such as to permit everyone's agreement with them.</p>
   <p>The chief concern here is professional co-operation, a normalization of conditions between workers and publishers from which both sides can benefit. It is our desire that the Association include publishers, editors, and all employees connected with the editorial department of their newspapers.</p>
   <p>An association such as was proposed by the convention has a great field of activity before it. Everyone who has ever had anything to do with newspapers internally understands this well.</p>
   <p>But then, after all, there will be time enough at the next convention in Detroit to consider ways and means of fixing membership, as well as rules and regulations upon which the association may be founded. It may, in time, include all Polish organizations, and thus become a powerful factor in our affairs here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
