<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-11">Jan. 11, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">New Dangers for the Unnaturalized</title><title level="a" type="sub">Greater Hardships Imposed; Cost of First and Second Papers Increased by S. Kolanowski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0912</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0912.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-11">Jan. 11, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">NEW DANGERS FOR THE UNNATURALIZED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Greater Hardships Imposed; Cost of First and Second Papers Increased by S. Kolanowski</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The unnaturalized Poles of Chicago and of the rest of the United States are threatened with great hardships. New obstacles and dangers, which will be difficult to overcome, await the negligent. For many years, the Government has been making changes in the naturalization laws, but never were they so drastic as the ones that will come up before Congress for passage this session.</p>
   <p>The Naturalization Bureau has recently issued a brochure which contains an account of its activities since 1906. The subject of naturalization is covered in detail. The brochure also makes recommendations for the future. These recommendations must be fought through our Senators and Congressmen.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0913.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Polish organizations will have to deal with this matter immediately, since Congress may pass these laws during the present session. Much effort and money are necessary to combat American chauvinism, which is endeavoring to make drastic changes [in the naturalization laws], thereby imposing hardships on members of foreign-language groups who wish to become naturalized.</p>
   <p>Of the many recommendations cited by the Naturalization Bureau, only four deserve to be considered by Congress. The rest should be rejected because they are harmful. The recommendations are as follows:</p>
   <p>The Naturalization Bureau to be authorized to issue certificates of landing to all those who have entered the country legally or illegally before June 5, 1921, regardless of whether or not their names can be found in the port of landing.</p>
   <p>A photograph of the candidate to be attached to the first or second papers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0914.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The first papers of all persons who came into this country illegally after June 3, 1921 to be cancelled.</p>
   <p>Every candidate applying for first papers to be required, first of all, to secure a certificate of landing as proof that he came into the country legally.</p>
   <p>The old law to be abolished which states that the candidate must live at least one year in the State in which he is making application for papers.</p>
   <p>A stay beyond the borders of this country that is longer than six months to be forbidden; anyone absent for a longer period to be considered as a new arrival into the country.</p>
   <p>Permission to renew actions that have been thrown out not to be granted, unless the renewal is made the same month the action was thrown out.</p>
   <p>Widows and minors not to be permitted to apply for second papers on the strength of the expired papers of the husband and the father, respectively.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0915.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Every applicant for citizenship papers to be required not only to be able to speak, but also to read and write English, and to present evidence to an examiner that he actually can speak, write, and read English before he can apply for the papers.</p>
   <p>Every applicant for citizenship papers to appear in person, together with his witnesses, before the examiner.</p>
   <p>A copy of the certificate of naturalization to be issued to each individual naturalized as a result of the naturalization of the head of the family; however, every such individual must call in person at the court for said copy.</p>
   <p>The first papers to cost five dollars, and the second, ten dollars. A stipulated sum to be set up for an additional copy of second papers.</p>
   <p>The citizenship papers of all those who have been found guilty, before a court of justice, of some crime committed within five years after naturalization, to <pb facs="5423968_6_0916.jpg" n="5"/>be revoked.</p>
   <p>The naturalization procedure in its entirety to be placed in the hands of the administrators of the Naturalization Bureau, Federal judges to be relieved of this duty.</p>
   <p>The law to be repealed which automatically confers citizenship upon minors when their parents become naturalized.</p>
   <p>Only those persons to serve as witnesses who have had their citizenship papers at least five years.</p>
   <p>All unnaturalized persons living in the United States to be required to register, the cost of registration to be borne by the unnaturalized.</p>
   <p>These are, in brief, the recommendations which the Naturalization Bureau has presented to Congress. The attention of all Polish organizations is called to <pb facs="5423968_6_0917.jpg" n="6"/>the severe hardships with which all unnaturalized Poles in the United States are threatened by the Government. Last year more than thirty-six thousand Poles received their citizenship papers, but if the present Congress adopts the foregoing recommendations, not even ten thousand Poles will be naturalized in any one year.....</p>
   <p>[Note]: At the present time, three Polish citizenship classes are being conducted by S. L. Kolanowski. Those who are not naturalized should take advantage of this opportunity while it is still easy to obtain citizenship papers.</p>
   <p>Classes are held every Monday evening from 7:30 to 8:30 at Stakiewicz's Hall, Noble and Emma Streets. Every Sunday at 1 P.M. instruction is given at the Sacred Heart Parish hall, 46th and Lincoln Streets. The third class is conducted at the Five Holy Martyrs school hall, 43rd Street and Francisco Avenue, every Sunday at 2 P.M. This class has been recently opened by S. L. Kolanowski.</p>
   <p>People interested in obtaining citizenship and citizenship papers are urged to <pb facs="5423968_6_0918.jpg" n="7"/>attend any of the above-mentioned classes, or to call at the office maintained by S. L. Kolanowski at 1942 West Chicago Avenue, near Robey Street, any Tuesday or Thursday evening between six and eight, or any Saturday between the hours of two and eight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
