<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-04-30">Apr. 30, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning the Building of the Kosciusko Monument in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1340</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1340.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-04-30">Apr. 30, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING THE BUILDING OF THE KOSCIUSKO MONUMENT IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have received a new appeal from the committee to build the Kosciusko monument in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The committee, it seems from this appeal, has decided to bring the matter of building the monument to a head. The committee reports that the building of a greater monument, as was originally projected, is impossible because of inadequate contributions for the purpose; it will be necessary to be satisfied with one much more modest in appearance. The fund lacks a few thousand dollars for even such a monument.</p>
   <p>Greater donations for this purpose were expected on the one hundred and fiftieth anniversary of the birth of our immortal Thaddeus Kosciusko. Certain sums were donated, but not as large as expected; they are not sufficient to build the monument.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1341.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The committee, therefore, appeals to everybody for more donations, and especially urges all the Poles in Chicago to take part in the picnic which is to take place July 4 in Schuetzen park, under the auspices of Polish societies.</p>
   <p>An itemized report of funds gathered for building the monument is included in this appeal.</p>
   <p>The report follows:</p>
   <p>Receipts</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Donations received to date</cell>
     <cell>$7,717.65</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest from the treasurer, Mr. Stensland</cell>
     <cell>250.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest from the Holy Trinity Parish for two years (the last payment due September 19, 1896)</cell>
     <cell>500.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total receipts</cell>
     <cell>$8,467.65</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1342.jpg" n="3"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Advertising the contest</cell>
     <cell>$ 940.38</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Seal</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Charter</cell>
     <cell>4.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Record book for financial secretary</cell>
     <cell>1.25</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Minute book for recording secretary</cell>
     <cell>1.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Printing of appeals, receipt books, letterheads, envelopes, etc</cell>
     <cell>37.25</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Telegram to Mr. Dunikowski</cell>
     <cell>4.80</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Postage stamps on appeals to societies of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, Polish National Alliance, Polish Union, priests, local and out-of-town papers</cell>
     <cell>12.45</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Postage stamps purchased by the recording secretary</cell>
     <cell>2.40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Postage stamps purchased by the financial secretary to mail out receipts, answer correspondence, etc</cell>
     <cell>7.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Freight from Europe to New York of model by Mr. Baracz</cell>
     <cell>131.59</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Freight from New York to Chicago</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1343.jpg" n="4"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Express from the exposition to the city</cell>
     <cell>$ 3.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Repairing Mr. Baracz's model</cell>
     <cell>50.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Freight for Marconi and Beltowski models from Lwow to Chicago</cell>
     <cell>44.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Repairing these models</cell>
     <cell>30.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Three woodcuts</cell>
     <cell>15.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Photographs of the models</cell>
     <cell>8.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total expenses</cell>
     <cell>$1,328.12</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Balance</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Receipts</cell>
     <cell>$8,467.65</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Disbursements</cell>
     <cell>1,328.12</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$7,139.53</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Still in the hands of collectors</cell>
     <cell>250.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total on hand</cell>
     <cell>$7,389.53</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1344.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>As can be seen from the above report, the committee possesses a sum of $7,389.53, which is not sufficient to build a monument. This sum should be increased.</p>
   <p>Concerning this, the appeal continues: "At least three or four thousand dollars more are necessary to build even a modest monument. One half of this sum, it is expected, will be raised at the picnic, and the other half we hope will be donated in Chicago and other Polish colonies. The committee will then be able to bring the plan projected four years ago to a successful conclusion, and will be very happy when this is accomplished."</p>
   <p>In conclusion, the committee once again warmly appeals to the Polish people for additional donations for the monument. We heartily endorse this appeal.</p>
   <p>The monument must be built. This should have been done a long time ago. The Kosciusko monument should be built in Chicago as soon as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
