<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-06-06">June 6, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Our Advertisements</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0646</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0646.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-06-06">June 6, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">OUR ADVERTISEMENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A newspaper, especially here in America, presents a highly important business aspect. One of the main principles in American newspaper business, the basis upon which rests the success of a paper, is advertising. And so, we believe our readers will not hold it amiss if we say a few words on advertising.</p>
   <p>A cursory glance at the advertisements in Dziennik [Chicagoski] is enough to show that this paper is one of the more important Polish advertising mediums in America. The proof lies as much in the number as in the nature of the ads which, in announcing special sales at a given time and place, have often benefited our readers. They would bring still greater benefit were it not for the prejudice against advertising that exists to a certain extent among our readers. There are some Poles who would rather visit a small, out-of-the-way shop, haggle for an hour, and in the end pay ten cents for an article worth a penny, than to patronize the stores that advertise but where there is no haggling, and where one pays no more than an article is worth. Those stores <pb facs="5423968_6_0647.jpg" n="2"/>that advertise often sell goods at half price, as during the so-called "special sales" which are customary with American businessmen. During these sales, some articles are often sold at less than cost in order to draw customers into the store.</p>
   <p>We ask our readers, then, to read the advertisements in this paper, and to patronize those who advertise in it. Many of our countrymen who do not understand conditions here, say that whoever advertises must charge more. They are wrong. Advertising is an American business principle. A business that does not advertise is not worth much. Every penny spent on advertising may bring hundreds of dollars in profit. Advertising gains customers for a firm, and permits it to operate at a smaller profit. Advertisers should be patronized for the customer's own good; and from another point of view, businessmen support Polish newspapers by their advertising and thereby earn Polish patronage. Whether or not they be countrymen of ours, they are recommending themselves to the Polish public and the Poles should not forget them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0648.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Once more, we repeat the request that our readers patronize our advertisers, sincerely believing that we will derive mutual benefit therefrom.</p>
   <p>The Publishers of Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <p>P. S. When making purchases at a store that advertises in Dziennik, it is best to carry a clipping of its advertisement. In this way, you can see that the prices are as advertised.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
