<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-02">Nov. 2, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Hiding the Truth under a Bushel</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-02">Nov. 2, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">HIDING THE TRUTH UNDER A BUSHEL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Numerous readers of the Polish newspaper Dziennik Zwiazkowy inform its publishers that on October 30, 1910, a sermon was delivered at St. Stanislaus Kostka Church in which it was denied that the publicized crime perpetrated in the shrine at Poland's Czestochowa was the result of one of the Pauline friars.</p>
   <p>To this information the reverend speaker added an order prohibiting boys from distributing the Dziennik Zwiazkowy in the above-mentioned parish. The same was repeated in the parochial school.</p>
   <p>It is a sad thing that a crime occurred at Czestochowa and that it was committed by a monk. But this does not mean that the truth should be hidden. The Pauline fathers themselves admitted that frankness in such instances is better than hiding and, in their reply to the people, they condemned the crime of the individual. Moreover, they all admitted the existence of laxity and lack of control in the religious order at Czestochowa. Truth will always <pb facs="5423968_6_0493.jpg" n="2"/>come to the fore, and then the people will turn their indignation not only against those who were guilty but also against those who did not permit truth to come to the light of day.</p>
   <p>Relative to prohibiting the newspaper boys from distributing the Dziennik Zwiazkowy, we must admit that it is a weak method of fighting with a newspaper which is not antagonistically inclined toward religion, and which does not conduct any warfare against the Resurrection Fathers. [Translator's Note: The Stanislaus Kostka Parish is one of several Polish Roman Catholic churches in Chicago under the supervisorship of the Resurrection, a religious order. It is entirely distinct and has no connection whatever with the Pauline order, in whose defense the Resurrectienists have made a futile stand.]</p>
   <p>Such prohibitive orders will avail very little. Honest people will be found who, in one way or another, know how to obtain a newspaper that conscientiously informs its readers of all current world events.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
