<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1929-07-15">July 15, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Legend of Wanda Homeland Music on Radio Chain</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0901</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0901.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1929-07-15">July 15, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">LEGEND OF WANDA HOMELAND MUSIC ON RADIO CHAIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The magic of radio permits us to be transported to the homeland, to revisit old familar places, loved scenes of our childhood, in the twinkling of an eye and in the comfort of our homes.</p>
   <p>On Wednesday night, at 10 o'clock a turn of your dial will bring to you the immortal legend of Wanda, beautiful and heroic daughter of Krakus, founder of the city of Cracow. It will bring to you the colorful historical events that Poland so well may cherish with reverence. Once again you can live in the century when the Poles, that small but brave nation, were shedding their blood in a noble fight trying to retain their rightful possessions.</p>
   <p>Every Pole who has the true spirit of Poland in his blood will spend a fascinating thirty minutes that will live long in his memory, bringing him an inspiration to greater deeds; his patriotism will be warmed up, and he will <pb facs="5423968_6_0902.jpg" n="2"/>feel proud of his ancestors.</p>
   <p>A 23-piece band under the direction of Hugo Mariani will play the stirring Polish "Kujawiak" and the famous "Polonaise." The immortal "Trumpet Call at Sundown" will be rendered by a well-known concert pianist. All the native musical instruments of the brave, the beautiful, and heroic old Poland, with its historically beautiful background, will be brought to you.</p>
   <p>This program, given by the American Bankers' Convention Voyagers and sponsored by the American Bankers' Association n Department of the Bankers Trust Company, New York, will take you back to Poland, for a half hour of vocal and instrumental music that you will long remember.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
