<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-03-24">Mar. 24, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Professor Popiel, the Polish Sculptor, Will Design the Kosciuszko Monument</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1250</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1250.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-03-24">Mar. 24, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">PROFESSOR POPIEL, THE POLISH SCULPTOR, WILL DESIGN THE KOSCIUSZKO MONUMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Masterpieces of this famous sculptor will soon be exhibited in the Art Institute. The secluded studio of Professor Popiel, located at Milwaukee Avenue and Leavitt Street has been transformed, as if by magic, into a temple of art. His work-shop is adorned with beautiful statues and statuettes made of clay by the creative hand of the sculptor. The productions are considered excellent by connoisseurs and critics. Many vistors, not only from Chicago, but also from other parts of the country, come every day to see the artist and admire his work.</p>
   <p>A plan for exhibiting his collection at the Art Institue of Chicago has been proposed by Professor Popiel; if approved, it will receive the assistance of all members of the Chicago art world who feel that they have in their midst an artist unequaled on this continent. This exhibition will very likely be held when the statues of Kosciuszko and others have been <pb facs="5423968_6_1251.jpg" n="2"/>completed. The plaster of paris model of Kosciuszko is almost finished; it is most imposing and will be the center of attraction. At this exposition our artist will also display a few small figures, cast in bronze; they are considered master-pieces. Besides the aformentioned subjects, a number of miniatures will be included which are now nearing completion.</p>
   <p>Professor Popiel is an artist endowed with sterling qualities; his achievements are an ever-living testimonial to his greatness, but aside from his talent, we must admire his proverbial ant-like diligence.</p>
   <p>Anyone not familiar with the intricacies of art cannot know how much time is devoted to such creative work.</p>
   <p>Those who visited our artist the other day, had an opportunity to learn many secrets.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1252.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Every minute detail of the body is carefully reproduced by the artist; it must be perfect. Special heat resisting molds are prepared for the molten metal.</p>
   <p>The model of the Kosciuszko monument will be exhibited before it is cast in bronze.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
