<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-04-18">Apr. 18, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish "Peoples University" in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1003</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1003.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-04-18">Apr. 18, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH "PEOPLES UNIVERSITY" IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance, or rather the newly organized Educational Department of this organization, is really bringing closer to realization the long-projected plan of a "People's University" for the Poles in America.</p>
   <p>No further details as to the method of establishing such a university have, as yet, been announced by the Educational Department.</p>
   <p>It is known only that two European professors, Dr. Siemiradzki, a historian and philosopher, and Mr. Kurcyusz, a scientist, arrived a few days ago and that classes will be started soon here in Chicago, with the co-operation of a few of the more educated local residents. The classes are to last three <pb facs="5423968_6_1004.jpg" n="2"/>or four months, after which time the professors expect to visit other Polish Communities.</p>
   <p>The teaching in the classes will be done mostly through lectures, and the classes will probably be held in the evening. There will be no admission charge.</p>
   <p>That is all the information we have to date about this proposed" People's University", but we have heard that the lectures will be of a high standard and will include such subjects as biology, political economics, higher mathematics, natural sciences, etc. We are publishing this information merely from what we have heard, for as yet no definite program of lectures has been officially announced. We will probably have more information after tomorrow's welcome to the newly arrived professors.</p>
   <p>One way or the other, we will have a "university".</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1005.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is something that, when considered in connection with our Polish-American system of living, is unusual and almost beyond belief. It is well, therefore, to devote some time to reflect on it.</p>
   <p>In general--and we mention this in advance--we consider all efforts toward the spreading of education among the Polish people as a most noble undertaking, worthy of all praise and of full support. That is our opinion of the travelling "People's University", which the Polish National Alliance is attempting to establish.</p>
   <p>We give our unstinting praise to the proposition. It is none of our business to consider who will supply the funds for such an expensive undertaking; the Polish National Alliance and its members will take care of that.</p>
   <p>But two important considerations come to our mind. We sincerely hope that this future "People's University" will bring actual benefits to our countrymen<pb facs="5423968_6_1006.jpg" n="4"/>, and not harm, and that statement suggests the two important points we have in mind.</p>
   <p>The first point is that in the lectures the Christian and Catholic faith of our people should be given due consideration. This is most important. The entire success of the "People's University", depends on this. Our people are Catholics and should remain so. Here, in America, religion cements our nationality. Our education, therefore, should rest on a catholic foundation, or, at least, it should not deny our catholic spirit or weaken our religious beliefs.</p>
   <p>So, if the "People's University", should follow the too liberal course desired by the Polish National Alliance, we would be forced to consider it a dangerous thing for our people, and would,of necessity,be bound to condemn it.</p>
   <p>The second consideration involves the kind of lectures to be given. The lectures, if the rumors about them are true, are decidedly too high-brow.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1007.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Lectures on astronomy, biology, economics, aesthetics, higher mathematics, etc., are in our opinion, over the heads of our people. Nobody will understand them; therefore they will not benefit anybody. This is an undeniable fact.</p>
   <p>The gentlemen planning this "People's University," if their intentions are as outlined above, evidently do not understand our people or their actual necessities. The grand name "university" is too pompous. It suggests that they wish actually to create a university. They seem to forget that, actually all the so-called "People's Universities" in Sweden and in England, and, not so long ago, in Austria, gave haphazard popular lectures, without any pretense of being universities with strict courses of study. They are, in fact, just places for giving lectures for people properly educated in excellent public schools.</p>
   <p>It is different with our people here. The ability simply to read and write among our people, who have recently arrived here from the old country, is <pb facs="5423968_6_1008.jpg" n="6"/>a mark of distinction, and not at all common. How is it possible, then, to talk about abstruse subjects whose names, even, our people will never be able to understand?....</p>
   <p>Our people, arriving in our midst, want to enlighten and educate themselves. They learn by attending national celebrations and lectures, by reading the papers and books, and by attending the night schools.</p>
   <p>This desire to learn can be and should be taken advantage of by our people. But do not place before them studies that are confusing; do not expect people, most of whom are unable to read or write, to study abstract subjects...A system of study should be offered them organized on a school pattern, and based on our English nomenclature and system, lectures on arithmetic (fractions included), geography, Polish and English history, lectures on local laws, practical hygiene, drawing, physics, and on subjects pertaining to practical trades, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1009.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Such a program of lectures would bring to our people untold benefits. Probably such a course would not deserve to be designated by the term "university", but surely we should be concerned not so much with a flamboyant name as with the subject matter itself.</p>
   <p>Perhaps our fears about the high-brow quality of the lectures to be given are groundless. So much the better! In any event we considered it necessary to make these pointed remarks, because a sensible discussion of such an important matter is always timely.</p>
   <p>One way or the other, we sincerely advise the initiators of this so-called "People's University" to remember this sage advice: "Before we attempt to fly, we must learn how to walk!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
