<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>. Vol. VI, No. 13,
<date when="1887-03-30">March 30, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">From Our Press</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0800</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0800.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>. Vol. VI, No. 13,
<date when="1887-03-30">March 30, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR PRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Courier, the first Polish daily in the United States, has stopped its presses forever because it was not supported, It is very sad to say that a paper of this calibre, dealing with Polish politics and the welfare of the Polish people, could not be supported by true Poles.</p>
   <p>The editor of the Courier, Mr. Sadowski, takes this opportunity to thank the people for their best efforts to keep this newspaper in circulation, and he is very sorry that in spite of the large number of Poles in the United States, this paper had to stop its publication due to lack of support.</p>
   <p>This paper supported all the Polish movements, their enterprises, their very lives; still it didn't do enough to exist among their own blood. I hope that everyone who contributed to its downfall is satisfied, because our existence was not one road strewn with flowers.</p>
   <p>It is hinted that Mr. Sadowski will be the editor of the new Polish <pb facs="5423968_6_0801.jpg" n="2"/>newspaper, Poles in America, which will soon be put in circulation in Buffalo.</p>
   <p>We do not think that we need a horoscope reading in regard to the value of this new Polish newspaper or the articles appearing in it, because we know the record and the good work of Mr. Sadowski. Therefore we feel that his work will be honest and sincere.</p>
   <p>We feel that Mr. Sadowski is broad-minded and can go far in bringing before the eyes of the Polish people the news that interests them most.</p>
   <p>In this belief we wish the Poles of America a success, and we send our heartiest wishes to our colleague, and hope that he meets with less misfortune than he did while in the services of the Courier.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
