<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-10">July 10, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Picnic Held for Support of Polish Library in South Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0169</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0169.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-10">July 10, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">PICNIC HELD FOR SUPPORT OF POLISH LIBRARY IN SOUTH CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Societies of the Immaculate Conception Parish of South Chicago gave a picnic on June 20 for the purpose of raising funds for the local Polish library. The picnic committee has received support and co-operation from many people. Roman Przybylinski lists the following contributions: Saint Josaphat Society, articles valued at $10; Knights of Saint Mary Society, $4.70; Legion of Saint Joseph Society, $3.57; Albert Furman, eight bottles of wine; Charles Witkowski, six bottles of wine; John Szymborski, fifty cigars; Jacob Lukstedt, 60 cents; Joseph Przeskowiak, $1; Martin Wiora, half a barrel of beer; A. Ryzewski, agent of the American Brewing Company, one barrel of beer; Adam Walkowiak, six bottles of wine; Francis Szwajkowski, one barrel of beer; Francis Zurawski, fifty cigars; Francis Semran, two barrels of wine; W. Lamka, four loaves of bread; Albert Kaczala, fifty cigars; John Szarafin, one hundred cigars; Stanislaus Dudek, three pictures valued at $3; P. Maciejewski, five loaves of bread; Stephen Sulski, one ton of coal;</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0170.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>P. Golik, 50 cents; Hummel, half a barrel of beer; Michael Ignowski, one hundred cigars; Thomas Gordon, one hundred cigars; Granacki, $1; Joseph Wisniewski, one bottle of whiskey; P. Schoen, druggist, one hundred cigars; Frank Szczacharski, a trunk valued at $2; Peter Daszkiewicz, hardware valued at $1.45; Dr. P. Stanoch, $1; Dr. P.M. Borucki, $4; John Manikowski, one ham valued at $1.25; and P. Gryniewicz, half a barrel of beer.</p>
   <p>Through the efforts of Peter Dambek the following donations were given: Adam Walkowiak, one case of soda; P. J. Rybicki, one hundred cigars; Mr. Madaj, one bottle of wine; Louis Puchocki, one bottle of wine.</p>
   <p>Sincere thanks are extended to all donors and participants.</p>
   <p>Joseph Rudnik, Secretary,</p>
   <p>8748 Escanaba Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
