<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-01-08">Jan. 8, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Newspapers Take on New Form</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-01-08">Jan. 8, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH NEWSPAPERS TAKE ON NEW FORM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first issues this year of some of the Polish-American newspapers reveal a change in format. Yesterday's issue of the Gazeta Katolicka (Catholic Gazette), a weekly, has been completely changed. Instead of being published on four large pages with nine columns each, hereafter it will contain eight pages with six columns each. Its general make-up is not only more attractive but also more readable. As to its policy, it is still the same; it continues its Polish Roman Catholic policy.</p>
   <p>The first issue of the Dzien Swiety (Holy Day), a weekly, contains thirty-two interesting pages. As before, it will continue to be published as a weekly containing sixteen pages.</p>
   <p>W. Dyniewicz's Gazeta Polska (Polish Gazette), a weekly, is the same as before, although the first issue of the new year consists of twenty-four pages. Its pages are as large as ever. There are many advertisements of the Dyniewicz <pb facs="5423968_6_0560.jpg" n="2"/>Publishing Company.</p>
   <p>Zgoda (Harmony), official weekly organ of the Polish National Alliance, has also taken on a new format. Instead of having six columns it now has seven. Its contents are the same as before. It is warring with the Petersburg "government" (sic) and with Dr. Siemieradzki, who was brought to America by the educational department of the Polish National Alliance to "educate" us.</p>
   <p>The Wiara I Ojczyzna, a weekly, has become a twelve-page periodical. Its columns contain, besides local news items, a feature story, "Religious Activity," two articles for Polish youth, "Educational Activity," a story about the Polish city, Kruszwica [a city of the Piast dynasty 1000 A. D.], and a complete story, "Skutecznosc Modlitwy" (The Efficacy of Prayer).</p>
   <p>The second number of the Narod (Nation), official organ of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, was also out today. It contains many interesting articles <pb facs="5423968_6_0561.jpg" n="3"/>which will appeal to its members and to the Poles of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
