<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-06">Jan. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Dziennik Chicagoski's Polish Hour to Be Broadcast Over Station Wcfl Tonight at Eight O'clock</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0903</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0903.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-06">Jan. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">DZIENNIK CHICAGOSKI'S POLISH HOUR TO BE BROADCAST OVER STATION WCFL TONIGHT AT EIGHT O'CLOCK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tonight at eight o'clock, another Polish program will be presented over station WCFL under the auspices of the Dziennik Chicagoski. This evening's radio presentation will be a variety show. Perhaps this program will not compare favorably with the richness of last week's, when the famous Nowe Zycie (New Life) Polish Choir was presented under the baton of the esteemed director, J. J. Kapalka. But we are certain that this group will honor us again within the near future and appear on our program. However, in their absence, we are compelled to rely on our local talent to fill their place. Yet this does not mean that the artists who are to appear tonight are unknown to the Polish public, for it has had many an opportunity to see them on the concert stage.</p>
   <p>One of the attractions of this evening will be the appearance of the popular Polish tenor, John Krawiec. This artist will sing fragments <pb facs="5423968_6_0904.jpg" n="2"/>from the opera, Halka. Another feature will be the presentation of the well-known singer of national songs, Miss Kulczycka-Obrzut.</p>
   <p>A comedy will also be presented on this evening's program. The title role will be played by Thaddeus Kantor. He will be supported by Miss Pedecini and M. Marski. Miss Kulczynska-Obrzut will take the role of a servant.</p>
   <p>Besides this, Alexander Bonczkowski, pianist, and Miss Mary Gruszczynska, singer, will appear. If time permits Christmas carols will also be sung.</p>
   <p>We sincerely thank those who sent in letters and we beg for more. The first half of the program will be devoted to requests that have been received.</p>
   <p>In reply to some of the questions received, we inform the senders that the Brunswick Recording Company, which cooperates with the Dziennik Chicagoski in presenting these programs, has many recordings of the songs presented in recent concerts for sale.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
