<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-10-15">Oct. 15, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Catholic Almanac in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0891</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0891.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-10-15">Oct. 15, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH CATHOLIC ALMANAC IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Just off the press. A Catholic Almanac in the Polish language, for 1892, published specially for the Poles in America by the Polish Publishing Company, publishers of Dziennik Chicagoski. The price is twenty-five cents.</p>
   <p>This is the third edition of the Polish Catholic Almanac in America, and it is larger and better than the previous ones. It is printed on good quality paper, contains 208 pages, covers a great variety of interesting subjects, and is beautifully illustrated. Every purchaser of this almanac will receive absolutely free a beautiful wall calendar for 1892. The illustration on this calendar represents an image of our Lord's countenance, according to an original [painting] preserved at the Basilica of Saint Peter in the Vatican.</p>
   <p>Besides the calendar, the publishers are also giving fifty beautiful prizes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0892.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These prizes, which are worth from fifty cents to two dollars each, will be raffled off in July of next year. Every almanac is provided with a number on the outside cover, giving the purchaser a chance to win one of these articles. The result of the raffle will be announced in the Almanac of 1893.</p>
   <p>As a novelty, every page of this almanac bears a reproduction of famous paintings and statues found in different parts of Poland. Each reproduction is fully described.</p>
   <p>These reproductions represent famous and miraculous pictures of the Holy Virgin of Budziszen, the Denevolent Virgin of Grebanin, the Holy Virgin of Wisniowicz, the Miraculous Virgin of Limanowa, and other famous pictures in Poland.</p>
   <p>The almanac contains many interesting features, such as "Old Year, New Year, <pb facs="5423968_6_0893.jpg" n="3"/>and Christmas," poem by [S.] Zahajkiewicz; "Lives of St. John Cantius, St. Casimir, and Beatified Andrew Bobola"; "Discovery of America," "Deprive Me Not of My Faith!" "Persecution of Christians by Nero," "O Polish Mother" (a poem), "A Few Words on Celebrations", "Excommunication of Caesar Theodosius by Bishop Ambrose", "Peter Kiolbassa, the city treasurer," the Constitution of the United States, a list of Polish priests in the United States, and the Polish business directory of Chicago.</p>
   <p>This almanac also contains several full-page pictures, as follows: "Christmas," "The Faith of a Child," "Persecution of Christians by Nero," "Where is Consolation?" "Commemoration of the One-Hundredth Anniversary of the Polish Constitution of the Third of May," "Excommunication of Theodosius by Bishop Ambrose," and "Death of Saint Josephat."</p>
   <p>There are also other reproductions of paintings, some of them covering almost <pb facs="5423968_6_0894.jpg" n="4"/>an entire page. These are "The New Year," "Before the Meal," "Sister Mary from St. Peter's Convent of Tours, France," "M. Dupont of Tours, France," "The Creators of the Constitution of the Third of May," "Warsaw Gazette of May 7, 1791," "Church of St. John of Jerusalem in Posen, Poland", and a portrait of Peter Kiolbassa.</p>
   <p>This almanac, in beautiful cardboard covers, especially adapted to the needs of the Poles in America, costs only twenty-five cents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
