<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-05-30">May 30, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Decoration Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1393</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1393.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-05-30">May 30, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">DECORATION DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It cannot be denied that Americans know how to select fitting days for national celebration--and to celebrate them accordingly. On the Fourth of July, they celebrate joyously the signing of the Declaration of Independence; the twenty-second of February is the anniversary of the birthday of George Washington, the father of his country; the last Thursday in November is set aside for the purpose of giving thanks to God; and it speaks well for their religious feeling, regardless of creed, that Christmas Day is included among the national holidays, so that everyone observes it, Christian and non-Christian alike.</p>
   <p>Equally stirring is the holiday which Americans celebrate today, May 30. While other days have been set apart for the celebration of happy events, this day is one of sadness. On this day, homage is paid to the soldiers who died for their country, irrespective of whether or not they had achieved <pb facs="5423968_6_1394.jpg" n="2"/>fame. Everyone who fights for his country deserves to be remembered for the simple fact that he has offered it his life. Today, wreaths will decorate the graves and monuments of fallen defenders of liberty.</p>
   <p>Decoration Day is observed usually in cemeteries and about the monuments of great national heroes. It is not a day of mourning in the strict sense of the word. In accordance with the conception of most nations, he who dies in defense of right and justice is not to be mourned, but honored. We lay wreaths upon the graves of dead soldiers to show that we have not forgotten those who have served us, and that we are grateful to them.</p>
   <p>Appropriate exercises will be conducted today in various public buildings, especially in schools, where teachers and others will speak to the children on American history. Classes will be closed; in some states, all public offices are closed also.</p>
   <p>Practically every national group in America has its own heroes whom it honors <pb facs="5423968_6_1395.jpg" n="3"/>on Decoration Day. The Poles have Kosciusko and Pulaski, besides many whose names are unknown. Let us hope that in not so long a time, we will have a monument to Kosciusko in Chicago, before which, on Decoration Day, we can conduct special Polish exercises in honor of our great hero.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
