<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-11">Apr. 11, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Warning against Gazeta Robotnicza</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0637</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0637.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-11">Apr. 11, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">WARNING AGAINST GAZETA ROBOTNICZA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The last issue of this loathsome journal, Gazeta Robotnicza (Workers' Gazette), of which unfortunately seven issues have been published already, was not delivered to us. Consequently, we did not know what filth and what infamous attacks were inserted in its columns by its historical editor and well-known anarchist, J. Rybakowski.</p>
   <p>It was not until today that an honest Polish workingman, Paul Kostkiewicz, residing at 32 Chapin Street [now Haddon], called at our office and asked us to warn, in his name, all Polish Catholics and all our workingmen against this diabolical and poisonous sheet, Gazeta Robotnicza, which is panting with venom of hate toward the Holy Father [the Pope] and the Catholic Church, besmirching everything that is decent and noble. Mr. Kostkiewicz's indignation at the time of asking us to give this warning was really great.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0638.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He explained that an acquaintance of his presented him with a copy of Gazeta Robotnicza, and he, not knowing what kind of a "bitter seed" it was, began to read it. Now that he realizes the kind of a journal it is, he desires to warn all Christians and Catholics against this poison, against the filthy insults and base advice given in this journal.</p>
   <p>We will gladly grant his wish. Indeed, we judge from the issue presented to us that Gazeta Robotnicza has surpassed itself in wickedness. It is a pasquin from the beginning to the end, a muddy blot, dirt flung at persons and ideas. Nothing could be more hideous than the article entitled "Pope's Politics". It is not fit for print. It will suffice to remark that such expressions as "despot," "satrap," in reference to the Holy Father, and the charge made against the head of the church that he took a bribe from the Czar of Russia, are the mildest "arguments" in this obnoxious article, which is not fit for public consumption. The whole four pages are covered with it. Insults upon insults are heaped upon priests, patriotic ideas, and upon <pb facs="5423968_6_0639.jpg" n="3"/>everything worth while. Filth, insults, wickedness!</p>
   <p>Indeed, honest workingmen should be warned against the so-called Gazeta Robotnicza. It is not a workers' gazette, but Satan's gazette. Its object is to attack religion, overthrow the social order, and establish anarchy. Its means are ignoble insults and gutter phraseology. In reality, this newspaper has not done anything for the workingmen up to the present time and is not willing to do it in the future. It leads them nowhere and desires to make anarchistic criminals out of them, without God or patriotism.</p>
   <p>Away with this infamous rag! No workingmen's honest hand should be soiled by touching it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
