<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-10">May 10, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">New Rotary Press Installed</title><title level="a" type="sub">10,000 Copies of Dziennik Chicagoski Published per Hour</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0609</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0609.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-10">May 10, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">NEW ROTARY PRESS INSTALLED</title><title level="a" type="sub">10,000 Copies of Dziennik Chicagoski Published per Hour</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Dziennik Chicagoski and the Polish Publishing Company know how to follow the times. This is evidenced by the installation of a new rotary press two weeks ago in the press room in which the Dziennik Chicagoski and the Wiara I Ojczyzna (Faith and the Fatherland) is published. The natural increase of business was responsible for this move.</p>
   <p>During the course of a few years, the circulation of the Dziennik Chicagoski has increased fourfold. Of recent date, from eight to ten thousand more copies per day had to be published. Our circulation covers a wide territory in Chicago and vicinity. Our paper is read everywhere. Over 50,000 copies a week are printed.</p>
   <p>The publication of this vast number took considerable time, and created two serious problems:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0610.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>1. It compelled us to close the columns much earlier, and this proved detrimental to the availability of the last-minute news.</p>
   <p>2. It delayed the appearance of the paper on the newsstands, especially at points outside Chicago.</p>
   <p>The company decided to take steps to remedy this situation. It was agreed to have the Dziennik Chicagoski comparable to the American papers. A new rotary press and stereotype equipment was obtained, the same as are possessed by the largest newspapers in America.</p>
   <p>The machine has been in operation for some time. With the new machinery, from ten to twelve thousand copies may be printed in an hour. As a result we are on equal footing with American newspapers, and ahead of the German.</p>
   <p>We are now in a position to give our readers last-minute telegraph dispatches and other news immediately after it has occurred. In the course of two hours <pb facs="5423968_6_0611.jpg" n="3"/>over 20,000 copies are ready for distribution, and over 35,000 in three hours!</p>
   <p>It is our opinion that we were able to reach this large circulation through our energetic work and public support.</p>
   <p>The rotary press and stereotype equipment was purchased from the Seymour-Brewer Printing Press Company, of Chicago, Illinois. The Machinery has been built according to the latest improvements in the printing world.</p>
   <p>The papers on this new rotary press are printed from an endless stream of paper which is found on a roll at the end of the machine. This paper passes through the machine, where it is printed, cut and folded.</p>
   <p>In technical terms this roll of paper is called a "web." This ribbon of paper, in order to be printed, must pass through two cylinders upon which are placed stereotype plates or forms; these are cast from a frame of composite type. Then the printed ribbon passes through cylinders which cut it into the uniform length <pb facs="5423968_6_0612.jpg" n="4"/>of the newspaper. After this stage the cut paper passes through a folder which puts it into the form distributed to the reader.</p>
   <p>It can easily be comprehended how this process simplifies and expedites the printing of the paper. And all this is executed with unheard-of rapidity.</p>
   <p>In order to give an understanding of this speed, we say that it does not require more than one-third of a second for the white ribbon of paper to be printed, cut and folded and ready for distribution as a complete issue of the Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <p>In order to have one edition of the Dziennik Chicagoski ready for circulation, five miles of the white paper ribbon must pass through the press with lightning speed. During the course of an hour, from ten to twelve thousand copies are printed, cut, folded, and tied in bundles of equal number.</p>
   <p>If it were not for electricity this great rate of speed in printing the <pb facs="5423968_6_0613.jpg" n="5"/>newspaper would not be possible. Despite the speed, the machine runs comparatively silently. No special motor is required. The press rests on a specially built foundation, which eliminates vibration of the whole building.</p>
   <p>On the whole the new rotary press must be of perfect construction in order for its intricate manipulations to be executed in good order, without delay or shutting down.</p>
   <p>On the rotary press the printing is derived directly from the letters or type set by compositors; this is called stereotype, that is, a metal plate that has been cast from the frame of composite type. These stereotype plates must be made into the form of half-cylinders. The work about the stereotype equipment is very interesting, and it requires special training and skill to operate it.</p>
   <p>After receiving the composed frame of composite type, the stereotype man places it under a special press, and from soft material having the texture of gruel models a form called a matrix. This matrix, from the beginning level, is placed <pb facs="5423968_6_0614.jpg" n="6"/>into the bottom of the cylinder called "casting box", into which is poured special molten metal. This metal forms the bent stereotype plate. Then such tools as "trimmer," "tail cutter" and "shaver" finish off the plate in order that it may sit perfectly on the cylinders of the press.</p>
   <p>The ink flows automatically on the plate during the course of the operation of the machine, while the white ribbon of paper that passes through the press and cylinders gets the impression of the print.</p>
   <p>The entire stereotype process does not take longer than several minutes. As a consequence the latest news may be published with lightning speed for public consumption.</p>
   <p>Our rotary press is the first one of its kind among the Polish press in America. We are justly proud of this fact.</p>
   <p>In Poland the first rotary press was installed in 1889 by the publishers of Kuryer Warszawski (Warsaw Courier). Thus far there are very few of these machines in use in Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
