<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIV, No. 101,
<date when="1903-04-30">April 30, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">About the Monument of Kosciuszko</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIV, No. 101,
<date when="1903-04-30">April 30, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE MONUMENT OF KOSCIUSZKO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About two weeks ago, as is well known, there came a report from Springfield that there had been entered in the Illinois Legislature a bill providing a $5,000 fund for the erection of a monument of Kosciuszko here in Chicago.</p>
   <p>A couple of days ago the news was spread that this bill was rejected. This last report was received at the same time as the news stating that the name of Judge M. A. La Buy, as justice of the peace, had not been approved during the selection of the peace judges.</p>
   <p>Mr. M. A. La Buy's persistence in recognizing this Kosciuszko Monument Bill was a defeat for him and the bill. This seems to have been done as of spite.</p>
   <p>So now, the latter report should be straightened out. The committee erecting this monument of Kosciuszko had already for the past couple of days decided to withdraw this bill from the Legislature (at the time of M. A. La Buy's affairs), although its aim was to bring about, from <pb facs="5423968_6_1277.jpg" n="2"/>donations of the Poles, an unveiling of this monument some day, for the state of Illinois, as a gift from the Poles.</p>
   <p>It then seems to be ridiculous to demand the passing of this bill and then presenting this gift to them, in the name of the Poles.</p>
   <p>The American press greatly praises the procedure of this committee. A magazine or a periodical, the Chicago Chronicle, edited a special article highly praising the Poles in their effort.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
