<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-29">Mar. 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Monument Project</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-29">Mar. 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE MONUMENT PROJECT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The project undertaken by Chicago Poles to raise funds to erect a statue of Kosciuszko in one of the city parks deserves praise and support.</p>
   <p>In this materialistic world of ours, where beautiful ideals are short lived, where our brilliant past is getting obliterated from our minds, where there is a continual severance from our forefathers' principles and spirit of endurance, this patriotic attempt merits applause. The spirit of our youth, especially of our immigrant parents, has cooled considerably in the appreciation of the endeavors, struggles, sacrifices, and heroisms of our forefathers. Today, as the current of materialism is enveloping the world, our youth is snatched by its undercurrent, and as it rises to think for itself, it finds only a smattering of Polish tradition. Yet, out of this materialistic chaos, a noble and praiseworthy project has been born.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0290.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We firmly and emphatically aver that the Pole of today still carries a warm feeling in his heart for patriotic ideals and remembers those who have, either by pen, word, might, or sacrifice, brought fame to their country and earned credit for their accomplishments.</p>
   <p>At present we are entering a period which marks the one hundredth year of our last day of freedom. The century mark is about to pass that marks the time when three greedy enemies tore asunder our country to perpetrate dastardly crimes at the expense of our forefathers. Our country was eradicated from the face of the map of free peoples. Our forebears were placed in a tomb. The once freedom-loving Poles were shorn of their privileges and placed in shackles of servitude. The flower of our people either perished on the field of battle for freedom or succumbed on the field of exile of the frozen Siberian steppes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0291.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, this one hundredth anniversary, although sad to the hearts of all Poles, has not passed without praise. Our heroes and martyrs who gave up their lives for a national cause are our pride and joy today, for they have shown to the world the kind of metal the Poles are made of, despite the loss of their country.</p>
   <p>At the head of these heroes we place our immortal leader, Thaddeus Kosciuszko. If we have fallen, we have fallen with honor and praise. "Tout est perdu, hor l'honneur." All is lost, but honor. We can rightfully use this French saying in our case.</p>
   <p>The praise and honor of salvation have been exemplified by our hero, Kosciuszko, who was the first to rally our provincial people under the banner of the white eagle; the first to strike at the enemy with scythes. By the might of the scythes, he captured the cannon of the archenemy and fought until the last drop of his blood gave out. He gave up because of <pb facs="5423968_6_0292.jpg" n="4"/>the superior forces of the invaders, but he fell like a hero, fighting to the last minute, just as long as there shined a ray of hope.</p>
   <p>Thaddeus Kosciuszko fought not only for the freedom of his people but also for the freedom of our adopted country. The battlefields of two worlds saw his heroic prowess, and on American soil he won undying fame.</p>
   <p>Noble and true is the idea that the Poles in the United States want to pay tribute to this great man by erecting a bronze statue in his memory.</p>
   <p>Just as the proponents of this project, who have come to the front to defend the honor of our hero and country, we wholeheartedly pledge our support to make it possible for the day when all of us will commemorate the one hundredth anniversary of our struggle for freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0293.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In connection with this noble cause, we have been entertaining an idea that we would like to express to our readers. We want to present this idea without any pretense at obstructing or condemning other plans. We would rather have the public take it as a frank, open statement submitted to their judgment.</p>
   <p>Our hero, Thaddeus Kosciuszko, above all, fought for the freedom of Poland, of whom he was a son. He also fought for the freedom of America, but as a friend and worshiper of those who love freedom.</p>
   <p>Our compatriots always remember the heroic deeds of this great patriot of freedom, and many statues in his honor have been erected throughout Poland. In the old palatial fortress of Wawel, many treasured relics of his are buried with the great men of Poland and many of his memorable letters and bulletins remain untouched in the archives. His tomb has been built with the aid of thousands of people, and it is for that reason that his name will live forever.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0294.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>In this country, Thaddeus Kosciuszko did not battle for the freedom of Poland, but for the freedom of America. At that time, when Polish blood was protecting the soil of the United States, no one ever gave a thought to the idea that the Poles would some day seek the protection of this land. This thought did not even occur to Kosciuszko, for he refused the vast grants of land offered him by Washington for his military prowess.</p>
   <p>Therefore the people in America ought to build him a monument. If the United States is so liberal in building statues to war heroes whose deeds do not compare with Kosciuszko's while under the command of Washington, then it would be a noble gesture on its part to pay its respects to him for his services.</p>
   <p>The hospitality bestowed upon our hero was not because of his meritorious deeds, but because it was customary. Thousands of others were feted to a <pb facs="5423968_6_0295.jpg" n="7"/>greater extent, and yet they did not pretend to equal the feats of Kosciuszko. America does not praise the immigrants for their sacrifices and journey. Not at all! It is done primarily for the best interest of America. The immigrants are a great source of wealth because they work hard. Where would America be today without them?</p>
   <p>We repeat that we are not opposed to honoring our hero, but we would like to alter the form of memorial, that is, to erect one of such a character as to prove beneficial to the Polish immigrants.</p>
   <p>A monument is merely bronze; its value is idealistic, gaining momentary prominence and then fading with the years. Although the sacrifices would be great, its advantage to the people would be small, let alone the hero, for whom it would gain very little respect among our materialistic generation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0296.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>But a monument erected in honor of our noble hero, with our money, for the purpose of helping our people, would be a greater and nobler memorial, one that would give assistance to the unfortunate immigrant Poles.</p>
   <p>During his life, Kosciuszko did not gather any laurels, passing them on to Napoleon, but his heart was always filled to the brim with Christian goodness and hospitality to all. His famous horse would stop, out of habit, before every beggar, for his master never avoided the poor.</p>
   <p>What pride and honor would a memorial institution bring to our hero and our people if it were to be erected on one of the better sites of Chicago with the inscription of "Kosciuszko's Polish Memorial Hospital!"</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0297.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>This kind of monument would combine both praise for our hero and compassion for our suffering people. It would forever evoke prayers of thanks for the soul of Kosciuszko. This, in reality, would be the best memorial, aere perennius, more lasting than bronze! In this memorial shelter, those getting relief from their pains would forevermore extol words of thanks to him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
