<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-14">Nov. 14, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Judge Payne's Motive</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0578</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0578.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-14">Nov. 14, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">JUDGE PAYNE'S MOTIVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In an adjoining column we are giving the complete report of the verdict delivered against Segers, who was found guilty of libel and sentenced to four months' imprisonment by Judge Payne. This decision rings with authority and nobleness. The words are supported by the deep understanding of the law and of the social conditions under which we live. They treat the matter in such a way as to be understood by all.</p>
   <p>They can and should serve as an important lesson to our immature social performers, wranglers and dynamic [reactionary] journalists. By these words they should know what freedom is on American soil.</p>
   <p>These individuals already had begun to have the opinion that freedom in <pb facs="5423968_6_0579.jpg" n="2"/>America means the right to complete lack of restraint, absolute wantonness, and unarchical morality. Today they were told otherwise from the high seat of justice.</p>
   <p>They ought to read carefully the pronouncements of Judge Payne. He stated clearly and emphatically that in America one is privileged to pursue any religious belief, or free not to pursue any; one is also free to criticize the beliefs of others; but by virtue of these convictions it is forbidden to take away one's honor, to attack another brutally and to smear one with slander. It is forbidden to strike criminal blows against another's honor and person.</p>
   <p>If the judge had not adhered strictly to the subject of the process, but had gone further, he certainly would have said that it was also forbidden to meddle with other people's religion in a quackish way. But at this time <pb facs="5423968_6_0580.jpg" n="3"/>we are not so much concerned with this.</p>
   <p>We desire once again to call attention to the importance of Judge Payne's verdict in the case of Mr. Segers. The judge involuntarily gave Segers a lesson--a lesson where it was most needed, for the indignation of society had been aroused.</p>
   <p>The judge said, "Away with scandalous attacks upon the honor of an individual! Away with criminal ill will as well as criminal negligence! The rights of an individual can no longer be violated by dishonest journalists. Hands off!"</p>
   <p>In the event our disturbers do not heed the warning given them in this decision, they will suffer the consequences in the long run.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
