<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-01">Feb. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Commerce and Industry</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0341</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0341.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-01">Feb. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">COMMERCE AND INDUSTRY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With today's issue of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, we open our commerce and industry section. Commerce and industry can rightfully be regarded as the foundation upon which depend the strength and growth of every nation. The United States is the best example of this. It is a large country and a great nation, and although it cannot boast of a great many deserving men in the field of science and invention [sic], it is at any rate the common peoples' dream, especially the common people of Europe.</p>
   <p>The people who struggle the hardest for existence seek the things that will best satisfy their needs. It is not strange, then, that the masses have been emigrating from Europe for decades, nay centuries, to settle in America. America is the land of labor, and wherever there is labor there is industry, a highly developed commerce, and prosperity.</p>
   <p>The same things that are said of American can be said of England and Germany, the <pb facs="5423968_6_0342.jpg" n="2"/>people of which countries also emigrate to the United States; not, however, to make a living at hard labor, but with the idea of getting rich quickly, which can most easily be done in a country where there is a great demand not only for labor but for people with energy, courage, and a knowledge of commerce and industry. To such individuals this country is open: to some it provides a means of livelihood; to others, an opportunity to get rich. Both the first and the second--that is, the influx of laborers and those who work with their brain--are a blessing to this country.</p>
   <p>If, at the present time, the United States is called the warring Allies' "bank", that "bank's" wealth was accumulated by labor and creative individuals, among whom we will permit ourselves to include capable businessmen and industrialists.</p>
   <p>But in thinking of all this, we [the Poles] ought to stop and consider what part we play in the realm of commerce and industry in this world of prosperity. We ought to consider whether our Polish element is really fortunate in this country. If it is, then why? And if not, why not?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0343.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>With sorrow, we must admit that thus far we have gained neither the wealth nor the importance achieved by other national groups--groups smaller in number than ours. Our development here has not been normal. We are not gaining those things that give a nation strength and importance, and so it is not strange that the Polish element here cannot be said to be fortunate. To see that this is true, one need but look into the emaciated faces of Polish laborers, or to see a Polish community and compare it with neighborhoods populated by other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Physical labor itself does not bring contentment or happiness to an individual or to a society. The Poles work mostly at hard labor, though there are a few doctors and lawyers, and here and there a few struggling businessmen.</p>
   <p>It is of these last, of our business and industry, that we will write in this section. America is a country of unusual experiments, a country of unusual opportunities, a country of good fortune to people who are intelligent, courageous, enterprising, hard-working, and energetic; American businessmen and <pb facs="5423968_6_0344.jpg" n="4"/>industrialists have these qualities. Americans are the descendants of those European pioneers, those brave people who faced the dangers of the trip across the ocean, who fought the Indians, who accomplished everything by industry and enterprise.</p>
   <p>We came later. We came at a time when they already had everything, when they owned rich mines and factories and business enterprises of all sorts. And what happened to us? We harnessed ourselves to work, and we are contented to have a livelihood, shelter, food, clothes, and so on. We are satisfied with our condition, and we never stop to think how these people acquired such wealth and prosperity; we never consider imitating or competing with them. And an experiment of this sort, even if it would not help us, could at least do us no harm. If we studied the lives of these wealthy Americans, these owners of large factories and business enterprises, we would find that a majority of them are not men who inherited wealth, but men who acquired it themselves through work, education, thrift, and enterprise. As we can see, those are attributes that we also have. There is no lack of thrifty and hard-working people among us.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0345.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Perhaps we have fewer among us who are educated in business and industry; perhaps we have fewer daring and enterprising men, but if we felt like examining the career of the manufacturer or store owner for whom we work, the ambition and possibly the ability and means of accomplishing the same thing would come to us. There must only be the desire; one must only know that there is something that one can understand and do.</p>
   <p>Conditions are bad among us, and we are far behind other national groups that are smaller in numbers than we, and as national groups are younger than we. Conditions ought to be better, however, and it is toward this end that we are instituting a commercial and industrial section in the columns of our paper. The purpose of the articles in this section will be to encourage work and thought along the lines we have discussed rather than to present news from the commercial world, or dry statistics which no one, especially those not engaged in business, would be interested in.</p>
   <p>It is the time now to consider what will happen after the war, what awaits us <pb facs="5423968_6_0346.jpg" n="6"/>and our country. We must consider what awaits our people here, and how we should apply ourselves so that we can progress with the times and keep pace with other national groups; so that even if we cannot be equal to the foremost we will not be behind nations that are less developed culturally than we are.</p>
   <p>Business of any kind cannot be considered without capital. The question arises, then, Where shall we get that capital? There is no lack of examples of how to obtain capital--the Americans have given us those. The Americans, whose example we shall follow, have, in creating building and loan, insurance, benefit, and similar organizations, shown us how to raise the necessary capital for industrial organization and to draw profit from it. Partnerships, corporations, syndicates, and trusts are all commercial and industrial organizations that have created the wealth in this country, bringing wealth to a few individuals and attracting the masses of workingmen from Europe. In a word, they are examples of how we can accumulate great masses of capital and draw profit from them, thereby enriching ourselves and the country we live in.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0347.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>But in order to remain in contact with what has already been done in this field, this section will concern itself partly with Polish businessmen's organizations which, although they do not accomplish much, have done and are doing something at, least, in the field of Polish-American business enterprise.</p>
   <p>In recent times, the Polish Association of Businessmen and Industrialists especially has become more active in raising capital, one result of which is the Associated Polish Traders and Importers Corporation, incorporated under the laws of Illinois at $100,000. At present this corporation has been successfully selling its shares among the Polish grocers. In the near future, we can expect it to develop into a great wholesale food concern. Last Sunday, this corporation held a celebration at Walsh's Hall, which was attended by all right-thinking businessmen. From the speeches made by Z. Ulanowski, Krzeslowski, S. Jakiel, Perlowski, and Flaczynski, the consensus appears to be that everyone feels the need of greater co-operation among the Poles in the field of business and industry.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
