<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-06">Apr, 6, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Publishers Association of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0698</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0698.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-06">Apr, 6, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH PUBLISHERS ASSOCIATION OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The board of directors of the Polish Publishers Association convened for their monthly meeting at their headquarters on Division Street, Monday, April 4.</p>
   <p>After the reading of the administrative and financial reports of the organization, Father K. Domagalski, the present chairman and editor of the organization, signed a contract to serve another two years. The contents of the contract primarily concern the management of the editor. Therefore, no space will be given to this transaction.</p>
   <p>The following resolutions, however, have been adopted and are made public:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0699.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>1. The periodical Wiara I Ojczyzna, together with the Dziennik Chicagoski, are the exclusive property of the Association.</p>
   <p>2. The weekly, Wiara I Ojczyzna, is the exclusive organ of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, as has been agreed upon at the conference in South Bend, Indiana last November.</p>
   <p>3. Dziennik Chicagoski, a daily newspaper, is not an organ of any specific party or group. It has as its aim the political and material interests of the Polish people in the United States, especially that of the Polish citizens and candidates in Chicago.</p>
   <p>4. Besides the department heads of the organization, no one has the right to make laws, give orders, etc., to the editor-in-chief or his <pb facs="5423968_6_0700.jpg" n="3"/>assistants. This right has been vested in the board of directors, solely who decide by a majority vote the rules and regulations of the Association.</p>
   <p>N.B. It is hoped that after this announcement, the many queries from strange and sundry sources, which are not desired, will come to an end. The insinuations of the meddlers are uncalled for.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
