<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 214,
<date when="1904-09-12">September 12, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Unveiling of Kosciuszko Monument</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Archbishop Assures Us That "Poland Lives"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1263</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1263.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 214,
<date when="1904-09-12">September 12, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">UNVEILING OF KOSCIUSZKO MONUMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Archbishop Assures Us That "Poland Lives"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Procession:</p>
   <p>To raise funds for his monument, picnics were given in honor of Kosciuszko, and the attendance was so great that it cannot be estimated.</p>
   <p>At last the day of unveiling of the monument came to reality. Early yesterday morning the skies were cloudy but this did not discourage the people; trains from all over the country were filled with people coming to witness this great memorial. Many spoke the Polish language and wore the badges of different organizations and societies beside the Kosciuszko button.</p>
   <p>About noon time, between North Avenue on the north, Chicago Avenue on the south, the River on the east, and Paulina Street on the west, Polish people began to meet at their respective places; the Sokol and different church organizations began congregating and were anxious to start. Beautiful carriages could be seen standing, awaiting the signal, and policemen on horseback were doing their utmost to maintain law and order. On the main streets where the paraders were to march could be seen houses decorated with flowers; flowers <pb facs="5423968_6_1264.jpg" n="2"/>strewn over the streets, Polish and American flags, different Polish banners, and a picture of Kosciuszko - the hero of two nations - in almost every window.</p>
   <p>About 300 societies from different cities began taking their respective places while the orchestra played Polish marches and the people shouted and whistled from joy. The people marched on Paulina Street to Division; west on Division to California Avenue; north on California to Wabansia Avenue; west to Humboldt Boulevard, and then south to the monument.</p>
   <p>At 1 o'clock the different Sokols marched on exhibition, lead by a Polish marshal, following the Sokols came a platoon of police, the state militia, the Guards of Kosciuszko, from Milwaukee; the Golden Order of Sokols followed by the building committee responsible for the erection of this monument; organizers of different societies, bishops, priests, and many more people of distinction.</p>
   <p>After the cheering quieted down a number of orchestras, the First Corps of the Polish Army consisting of Hussars, Cracovians, cadets, sharpshooters; the Columbia Marines; a band from Hawthorne and Kensington - all combined as one band, played Polish songs and marches.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1265.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The second division consisting of societies from La Salle, Toledo, and Michigan City, marched in review, followed by societies and groups from Kensington, Blue Island, Harvey, and South Chicago. In all, there were twelve divisions in review.</p>
   <p>We are nearing the park where thousands of people are massed near the monument and the police finally made the main boulevard clear for the officials. The lawn on the right-hand side of the monument was occupied by men's and women's choirs, which totaled 700 singers; a stand in the center was occupied by an orchestra accompanying the choir singers. Then an exhibition was given by 1,500 men and women; women marching from the left side and men from the right side, which was a splendid spectacle.</p>
   <p>At the foot of the monument we had the American flag on one side, Polish on the other and in between the banners of the Wisconsin State Militia, known as the "Guards of Kosciuszko," consisting entirely of Poles.</p>
   <p>Next came John F. Smulski, vice-president of the Polish committee responsible for this splendid monument, and he highly praised all the people for their kind contributions which had made it possible to erect this monument. All <pb facs="5423968_6_1266.jpg" n="4"/>the church choirs under the direction of Emily Wiedensmana sang "Kosciuszko looks at us from Heaven."</p>
   <p>Before unveiling the monument Mr. Smulski read the following telegram from President Theodore Roosevelt:</p>
   <p>My dear Sir:</p>
   <p>I wish it were possible for me to be present in person on the occasion of the unveiling of the monument of the great patriot Kosciuszko. It has been my good fortune to help in securing the erection of monuments in Washington, both of Kosciuszko and Pulaski. They are entitled to the love and veneration of all Americans no less than all Poles, and indeed I may go further and in justice say that they are entitled to the profound admiration and respect of all lovers of free government throughout the world.</p>
   <p>It is eminently proper that the monument of Kosciuszko should be erected in the great City of Chicago. Here in the United States a new people has been formed, and is still in process of formation. This people derives its blood from many different Old World sources. Each nation has already contributed much of <pb facs="5423968_6_1267.jpg" n="5"/>value to our citizenship and its share toward the leadership of the nation. In the Revolutionary War men like the Poles, Kosciuszko and Pulaski; like the Frenchmen, La Fayette and Rochambeau; like the German, Steuben; like the Irishman, Barry; like the Scotchman, Paul Jones, came over to help our struggling nationality - a nationality already of mixed ethnic origin as shown by the names of our generals who won distinction in the field as supporters of Washington - men like Wayne, Greene, Sullivan, Muhlenberg, Schuyler, Marion, Sumter, and Putnam. So it was in the time of the Civil War, when all our people without regard to diversity in national origin, rallied to the defense of the flag they, all alike, held so dear.</p>
   <p>Here in the United States we are all alike endeavoring to do our duty as good citizens and the only rivalry we know is the generous rivalry in good citizenship.</p>
   <p>I congratulate you and your associates on the admirable work you have done in connection with the erection of this statue to so great a man and I only wish it were in my power to greet you in person.</p>
   <p>With renewed good wishes and felicitations, believe me</p>
   <p>Sincerely yours</p>
   <p>Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1268.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>After Mr. Smulski read the President's message, Miss Mario Szopinski pulled the cord that unveiled the monument, which was greeted by whistling, tooting horns, and clapping of hands.</p>
   <p>This monument was built by Kazimierz Chodzynski. The members of the committee are M. A. La Buy, John F. Smulski, Leon Szopinski, T. M. Helinski, M. Stecynski, Michael Majewski, P. O. Stenland, Joseph Palczynski, Stan Bokusz, and Adam Majewski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
