<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-16">Nov. 16, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Educational Department Holds Meeting at St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-16">Nov. 16, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATIONAL DEPARTMENT HOLDS MEETING AT ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Monday, November 11, a meeting of the Educational Department of the Polish League, which was organized last year, was held at the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish School hall. Additions were made to this branch and the staff is now composed of: Reverend John Kasprzycki and Reverend John Piechowski, J. W. Jozwiakowski, P. Gibasiewicz, P. Ligman, H. Nagiel, L. Szopinski, J. Szczepanski, Tomaszewski, and I. Kowalski.</p>
   <p>As in the past, so at the present, the Educational Department is working on plans to open more libraries and reading rooms, arranging national [Polish] celebrations, lectures, and contests.</p>
   <p>Plans for an eighth library have been completed. The Department will send one hundred books to Antrim, Pennsylvania. The opening of other libraries will be announced shortly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0186.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All members of the Educational Department are invited to attend a meeting to be held on November 18 in the editorial rooms of the Dziennik Chicagoski. It is imperative that all attend.</p>
   <p>The following contributions have been received: Reverend J. Kasprzycki, $3; Reverend F. Matuszewski, $2.50; Reverend J. A. Babski, $2.50; and Reverend V. Barzynski, $1. Sincere thanks are extended to the donors.</p>
   <p>All those that are in favor of this movement are requested to make further contributions of books and money. Let everyone give as much as he can afford, and in this way he will be making a definite contribution for a cause for which our youth will be grateful.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Educational Department,</p>
   <p>I. Kowalski, secretary,</p>
   <p>141-143 West Division Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
