<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-11">Aug. 11, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">News about the Kosciusko Monument Fund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-11">Aug. 11, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS ABOUT THE KOSCIUSKO MONUMENT FUND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Kosciusko Monument Fund Committee held a meeting on Wednesday, August 7. At the meeting the committee deliberated on the proposition made by Mr. Beltowski, artist and sculptor, of Lwow, who created the work "Two Hemispheres" [one of the prize models for a monument].</p>
   <p>In a letter sent to the committee, by a brother of the above artist who resides at Minneapolis, Minnesota, it is stated that the above mentioned work can be completed at the cost of sixteen thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>The figure of Kosciusko astride a horse, made of bronze, would cost about $12,500 and would be completed in Europe. The base, to be made of granite, could be finished at the cost of $3,500. This part of the work could be done in America, probably from granite at St. Cloud, Minnesota.</p>
   <p>In the event of any required changes in the figure, the sculptor would gladly <pb facs="5423968_6_1374.jpg" n="2"/>agree to make them.</p>
   <p>The sculptor has agreed to post a twenty-thousand-dollar bond as a guarantee that the work will be satisfactory.</p>
   <p>The committee accepted this offer and turned it over to a commission made up of Michael Majewski, Max Drzemala and John F. Smulski for further consideration. This commission has the right to consult the best authorities in this field of work.</p>
   <p>In the absence of Dr. C. Midowicz, John F. Smulski acted as secretary, and he will continue in this capacity until Dr. Midowicz returns. All communications should be addressed to John F. Smulski, 565 Noble Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Another meeting will be held on August 21.</p>
   <p>In the name of the committee,</p>
   <p>John F. Smulski, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
