<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 15,
<date when="1894-04-11">April 11, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Pulaski Hall Proclamation to the Polish Brothers in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1388</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1388.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 15,
<date when="1894-04-11">April 11, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">PULASKI HALL PROCLAMATION TO THE POLISH BROTHERS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear fellow-citizens:</p>
   <p>Every Pole knows the situation that confronts our immigrants; we understand this very well, and besides the churches, schools, etc., these institutions are indispensable to us Poles and for the good of our national existence, we should have a Polish hall, where we can gather and discuss with our fellow brothers the affairs of the Poles here and in our father-land.</p>
   <p>We have a Polish hall on the Southwest Side of our city, called Pulaski Hall. It was built in less than two years with the money collected by the different Polish societies; money loaned from a few rich businessmen and with the aid of loans from banks operated by Poles, interested in this great movement.</p>
   <p>During its first year of existence the Pulaski Hall was prospering nicely, after paying all the interests and some of the smaller loans in full, it paid off $1,000 on the biggest loan from the Polish bank.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1389.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The second year in which most of our brothers did not have such employment, the societies had to meet all the bills and payments, thus saving the hall from bankruptcy, but at the same time suffering because they were weakening their own treasury and were near closing of their office, due to lack of funds.</p>
   <p>Poles who loaned money to complete this hall, and were unemployed were demanding their money, but there was little money in the treasury with which to repay them. Times were so hard that the treasury did not even have enough money on hand to meet the interests due on the loans.</p>
   <p>The board of directors and the officers were confronted with a very grave situation. They tried various means of obtaining money to meet this situation but to no avail; at last the board of directors agreed to let the Polish people of Chicago know of their situation and asked them for their support and aid.</p>
   <p>That is why, dear brothers, we are asking for your support in this critical moment; penny to penny makes dollars and dollars to dollars make a good sum of money; this is what is needed to meet the payments and debts on this hall, thus saving the honor and word of the Poles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1390.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We know that it is a serious matter to have to ask for your support, when you people are critically hard pressed at this moment, but where can we turn for help, if not to our own people, the foreigners of other nationalities will not help us.</p>
   <p>That is why we are pleading with the Poles who own commercial or business enterprises, to come to our rescue. Save us if not by kind hearted donations, then, please, loan us the money until we get on a stronger foundation.</p>
   <p>We, on our part, will do the same for you some day, when we are able, and if necessary, we will loan you people money when you are hard pressed and ask us for help.</p>
   <p>We, the board of directors, and officers in charge of this hall send all Poles our heartiest good wishes, in the name of the Society for Building the Pulaski Hall.</p>
   <p>B. L. Maciejewski</p>
   <p>Board of Directors:Ant. Pileno</p>
   <p>F. Mareinkowski</p>
   <p>Joseph Rozanski</p>
   <p>John Bednarz</p>
   <p>John Jezeczek</p>
   <p>Joseph Napiewralski</p>
   <p>Fr. Smietanka</p>
   <p>Joseph Kruczkowski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
