<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-16">Aug. 16, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[Our Position]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0658</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0658.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-16">Aug. 16, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[OUR POSITION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For lack of space in today's issue of the Dziennik Chicagoski, we shall postpone until tomorrow further discussion of the dissension between the two main camps among the Polish immigrants in the United States. [Editor's note: A certain group of Poles were against the meddling of the Church in Poland's politics and constituted one camp. The other camp was composed of more conservative Poles, who supported the right of the clergy, as Poles, to work for the fatherland.] In the present article we will limit ourselves to a discussion of the position of our paper in regard to this matter. Up to now our articles have dealt with the origin of the dissension and the kind of people composing the opposing factions. We have also mentioned the fact that the main field of operation is the press and that most of the warfare is in the form of newspaper articles.</p>
   <p>The Dziennik Chicagoski takes an active part in this struggle, along with the earlier and more conservative Poles in the United States, who sympathize <pb facs="5423968_6_0659.jpg" n="2"/>with the clergy. The Polish Publishing Company is composed of such citizens. However, the author of the article in the immigration Review [published in Poland] is wrong when he says that this newspaper is prejudiced in behalf of the Resurrection Fathers. As a matter of fact, this erroneous belief can readily be excused since it is practically impossible for anyone not interested in the matter or not living here for a time to formulate an entirely impartial opinion. were one to base his conclusions on the numerous articles published by the various newspapers here that belong to the opponents of the clergy, the impression would be that Dziennik Chicagoski is an organ of the Resurrection Fathers or at least the most influential friend in the United States of this congregation.</p>
   <p>Since these attacks--to say nothing of the questions raised now and then by articles in our enemies' newspapers--are mainly directed against Resurrection Fathers, particularly against a clergyman who belongs to our newspaper, all our efforts to fend them off have proved a boomerang.</p>
   <p>People who have read this paper ever since its inception on December 15, 1890, <pb facs="5423968_6_0660.jpg" n="3"/>are aware that Dziennik Chicagoski is not an organ of the Resurrection Fathers or of any individual. Our newspaper stands for the defense of all those whose principles are deemed just.....In addition, this newspaper discusses matters impartially and peacefully, not with violence.</p>
   <p>As soon as an issue becomes personal, this paper immediately switches the subject onto a broader field. Our polemics are impersonal, dealing with general questions, which we discuss from an unbiased standpoint. Examples of this, we believe, are our articles of a week ago in reply to the Emigration Review.</p>
   <p>To enlighten the European readers and to rid them of an erroneous judgment, let it be stated here that Dziennik Chicagoski is headed by a layman. Only on rare occasions--in proportion, less than in other newspapers--is it that a clergyman writes an article for this newspaper. When such is the case, the full name or pen name of the writer appears on the article.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0661.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We mention this because we now have taken upon us the task of describing newspaper polemics in a sensitive manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
