<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 1,
<date when="1904-01-06">Jan. 6, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Attention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1274</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1274.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 1,
<date when="1904-01-06">Jan. 6, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">ATTENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lately there has been brought about a beautiful thought worthy of a wholehearted support, the erecting of a monument of Kosciuszko in the city of Washington, as a gift of Poles to America.</p>
   <p>This project has gained general recognition, and the fulfillment of it will bring honor to the Polish people and will help elevate their status in the United States.</p>
   <p>We have lived in this country many years, we have here our liberty and are well off, we have protection and are acquiring more rights as citizens; this land is to us like a sister to our fatherland and not like a step-mother, therefore we owe her gratitude, we ought to show her our faithfulness and bestow upon her the honor that we sincerely feel for her.</p>
   <p>The people of all other nationalities living here have shown the United States some proof of their devotion, only the Poles have failed to do <pb facs="5423968_6_1275.jpg" n="2"/>that up to the present time. It is therefore time to keep in line with others and we will gain greater sympathy and recognition and display the interest in our life as citizens.</p>
   <p>At the present time America is also showing her gratitude. The United States government at its own expense is erecting in Washington a monument of our hero Kazimierz Pulaski. Let us not overlook this act of a gift to our people but while receiving it with an appreciative heart, we will offer a similar token to America in the form of a monument of Kosciuszko. By common effort and desire this can be accomplished at a nominal cost. Therefore we earnestly direct the brothers of our Catholic Union to respond wholeheartedly to the appeal of the committee, as announced in a previous issue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
