<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-24">May 24, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Tribune and the Lotteries</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0694</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0694.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-24">May 24, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE TRIBUNE AND THE LOTTERIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American press finds pleasure at times, even in greatly exaggerated articles, in defending certain legislation, although it may be inappropriate. In its day, the Republican press, The Tribune, praised itself about its strict adherence to the rules governing the usage of mails for lottery purposes. We are also basically opposed to lottery; we are not opposed to the ban placed upon the use of the mails to send circulars, tickets, papers supporting and propagating lottery, and the like. We have conducted ourselves accordingly and evidently we have not instituted it (with, perhaps, the exception of bazaars or raffles for benevolent purposes) nor would we give it support.</p>
   <p>The Tribune, on the other hand, is itself conducting a lottery. They print a blank in their columns intended for its readers to guess who will <pb facs="5423968_6_0695.jpg" n="2"/>receive the presidential nomination from among the Republican candidates at the convention to be held on June 7, 1892, and by what majority. It adds that one may submit as many guesses as he chooses, which infers that it encourages the purchase of several or more editions of their paper for the purpose of cutting out these blanks. "Whichever "prophecy" shows to be the nearst to the true result of the convention will receive a reward of $50.00. It is evident that by the known desire of the Americans to construe prophecies of that nature, The Tribune will sell so many more editions of its periodical that the $50.00 will be manifoldly covered and, simultaneously, the circle of its readers would be widened. Is this not lottery?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
