<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-12">Mar. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Official Statement of the Polish League's Educational Department</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0203</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0203.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-12">Mar. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">OFFICIAL STATEMENT OF THE POLISH LEAGUE'S EDUCATIONAL DEPARTMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the outstanding organizations having the interests of the Polish masses in the United States at heart is the Polish League. Its most active branch is the Educational Department, which was organized on December 4, 1894. An administrative body was chosen at that time to head the new branch. The initial assignment of that body was the planning and opening of Polish libraries at locations where they would be needed the most. Arrangements for lectures were also included in those plans. The treasury of the Polish League had practically no funds outside of those earmarked for the National Fund, which could not be touched. As a consequence, the beginning for the Educational Department was a very difficult one.</p>
   <p>Steps had to be taken to get funds for the support of this new organization; so on December 12, 1894, a meeting of the officials of the Educational Department <pb facs="5423968_6_0204.jpg" n="2"/>was held for the purpose of devising means of raising money for an active program.</p>
   <p>Henry Nagiel and Reverend E. Sedlaczek presented detailed plans for these purposes which were accepted in the main. The following measures were adopted:</p>
   <p>1. Instituting new libraries or adding to old Polish national libraries in the United States of America, especially in those communities where an agency of the Polish League exists.</p>
   <p>2. Arranging popular Polish lectures.</p>
   <p>3. Publishing Polish books.</p>
   <p>4. Supporting Polish schools, especially those newly erected.</p>
   <p>5. Setting up a scholarship fund.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0205.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>6. Announcing literary and educational contests.</p>
   <p>In general, the Educational Department desires to contribute to the development of education among the Polish people of America along the lines of national and religious principles. The purpose of this is to preserve the Polish culture, religion and love for the fatherland.</p>
   <p>The funds of the Educational Department are to be made up of voluntary contributions from the general Polish public, from collections taken at the exercises to be given during the coming year of national mourning [Translator's note: 1895 was set aside to commemorate the 100th anniversary of the third partition of Poland], entertainment programs, lectures, and celebrations. The assembled officials made the initial contributions; they also recommended that Henry Nagiel work out a plan for a literary contest, and instructed the library committee, composed of Reverend E. Sedlaczek, L. Szopinski and I. Kowalski, to undertake the purchase and collection of books.</p>
   <p>To realize those plans, an appeal was made on December 20 to the members of the Polish League and to the Poles at large to make contributions of money. The <pb facs="5423968_6_0206.jpg" n="4"/>first donation was offered by the St. Casimir Young Men's Society of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, which gave fifteen dollars.</p>
   <p>Plans for the literary contest were presented by the contest committee at a meeting held on January 7, 1895. The plans included two specific contests: one for Polish youth, and a future one for Poles in general.</p>
   <p>The contest for Polish youth has been announced. Its theme is: "The duties of Polish youth in America." Other particulars have been published.</p>
   <p>The arrangements and details for the lectures were taken over by the St. Casimir Society of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish. Henry Nagiel gave the first lecture on February 17, in the school hall on Bradley Street. The second will be given by the secretary of the Educational Department, Ignacy Kowalski; the third and fourth, in the form of readings, will be given by Szczesny Zahajkiewicz and S. Szwajkart respectively. These lectures are to be combined with songs, piano solos and declamations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0207.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It will be necessary to keep up the present flow of contributions of books for the formation of libraries. From the first day of the drive for books to the present, four hundred and ninety-six books have been donated. These books were on a variety of subjects.</p>
   <p>It must be pointed out, however, that all books sent in were not in condition to be used. Also a number of them were set aside because their contents did not correspond to the aim of the Educational Department. All donations of books, including the names of the donors and titles of the books, were acknowledged in Dziennik Chicagoski. In every instance sincere thanks were extended to the donors. The contributors will reap abundant rewards in the future. "The education of the people will create a miracle"; remember this always.</p>
   <p>Out of the 496 books received, only five per cent were bound. It was necessary, therefore, to have most of them bound; others were purchased to complete the collections.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0208.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The funds in support of the aims of the Educational Department are coming in gradually, but without the contribution of the St. Casimir Society and the proceeds, $74.20 to be exact, from the program staged by the St. Stanislaus Kostka College, the plans for the libraries would have been postponed. Despite these hardships it was possible for the Educational Department to open three libraries and complete plans for two others.</p>
   <p>The first library was opened by S. Szwajkart, in the name of the Educational Department, at Mill Creek, Michigan. The second was opened at Ludington, Michigan, and the third at Calumet, Michigan. The fourth and fifth will be opened shortly.</p>
   <p>It must be acknowledged that Mr. Szwajkart voluntarily paid for all the expenses incurred in opening the library at Mill Creek. The Educational Department extends to him sincere thanks.</p>
   <p>The Educational Department made a special effort to make sure that all fields of Polish literature would be represented in each library, by sorting all gifts of <pb facs="5423968_6_0209.jpg" n="7"/>books and assigning a definite variety to each. At the present time, books published in America only have been collected; however, an attempt will be made to get Polish books that have been published abroad. There is hope that an appeal to our fellow countrymen in Europe will bring results.</p>
   <p>Through the efforts of the Educational Department, the first brochure, Abecadlo Historyczne (Rudiments of Polish History), was published and it will be distributed free of charge to all members of the Polish League and to studious children. Another pamphlet, containing thirty-six pages, will be printed shortly, and in the event the funds warrant it a book after the pattern of that of the Macierz Polska (Polish Alma Mater) of Galicia will be published.</p>
   <p>That financial matters have been handled to the best ability of the Educational Department, is evidenced by the facts published below.</p>
   <p>The financial report for the first quarter, December 5, 1894 to March 7, 1895, is as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0210.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Income</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>From St. Casimir Young Men's Society</cell>
     <cell>$15.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>From members of the Educational Department</cell>
     <cell>2.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>From a collection at W. Burda's home</cell>
     <cell>.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Proceeds from St. Stanislaus Kostka College program</cell>
     <cell>74.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>J. F.</cell>
     <cell>1.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>S. Szwajkart</cell>
     <cell>1.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Dr. S. Kociel</cell>
     <cell>1.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>J. P.</cell>
     <cell>.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>From St. Adalbert Parish</cell>
     <cell>7.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>From St. Cecilia Society</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>From members of the Educational Department (sic)</cell>
     <cell>2.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$116.20</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Expenses</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Printing matter</cell>
     <cell>$2.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0211.jpg" n="9"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Postage and express</cell>
     <cell>$ 1.70</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Seal</cell>
     <cell>1.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Record book</cell>
     <cell>.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Binding of 123 books at $.23 and $.35</cell>
     <cell>28.54</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Binding of 120 books at eleven cents each</cell>
     <cell>13.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Purchase of 155 new books including a few score bound books, and the printing of 1000 brochures</cell>
     <cell>58.72</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$105.91</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>J. F. Smulski and Co. allowed a discount of from thirty-three to fifty per cent from the list price at the time of purchase.</p>
   <p>Balance:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Income</cell>
     <cell>$116.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses</cell>
     <cell>105.91</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$ 10.29 on hand.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0212.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>From December 5, 1894 to the present time, the Educational Department held ten meetings; this accounts for the execution of all the plans by the various committees.</p>
   <p>The undersigned wish to extend their thanks in appreciation for all the contributions, and we ask, in the name of the Educational Department of the Polish League, for further donations of books and money.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Educational Department,</p>
   <p>Reverend E. Sedlaczek, C. R., president;</p>
   <p>I. Kowalski, secretary;</p>
   <p>141-143 West Division Street</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
