<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 289,
<date when="1908-12-11">Dec. 11, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">"H. Sienkiewicz" Literary Circle at St. Stanislaus College</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 289,
<date when="1908-12-11">Dec. 11, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">"H. SIENKIEWICZ" LITERARY CIRCLE AT ST. STANISLAUS COLLEGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>St. Stanislaus College, besides its regular lessons in the Polish language, literature and Polish history, possesses also another factor which is contributing in a considerable measure to grant this institution a mark of Polish origin, namely, it is from a good many years in existence the "Henryk Sienkiewicz" Literary Circle, whose founders (and these were some of the students) were guided by the light of a glorious thought of a more basic training in the Polish language, at the same time a better mastering of that language. Above that the main aims of this society are: broadening the national spirit, to awaken a fondness for annals of the Fatherland and the guarding of the parental language among co-colleagues. Meetings of the "circle" take place regularly every other Friday afternoon.</p>
   <p>The program of these meetings is made up of readings, debates, declamations, dialogues, etc., conducted by the students themselves. During this year the moderator of the society, Rev. W. Zapala, initiated also appearances of so-called guests or persons, standing beyond the "circle" or the institution so that by this method enliven to a great extent the <pb facs="5423968_6_0040.jpg" n="2"/>activity of the youth.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly the work of students from their own free will uniting themselves in a society with such beautiful aims and enjoying the well-wishing support of the Rectorate and group of professors, is giving out the desired results and in its entirety answers to the resolved task.</p>
   <p>Besides that it has also this good side, that left to the students it completes autonomy at the meetings, it prepares them for greater self-activity, for public appearances and becoming familiar with a practical method of organizing societies and the conducting of deliberations. In this aim also the administration of the Literary Circle changes semi-annually. Likewise the institution of three critics, appraising the elaboration of these colleagues, possesses an extraordinary pedagogical meaning because it helps teach the youth sincerity and perpetuates in them the inclination to an impartial rendering of judgments. Also deserving of attention is the Bi-weekly of the H. Sienkiewicz <pb facs="5423968_6_0041.jpg" n="3"/>Society, in which are placed the works of the students, prepared for the meetings, lists the protocols and conducts somewhat a small chronicle of the institution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
