<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-28">Jan. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Anniversary Dinner at the [Polish] Press Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-28">Jan. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ANNIVERSARY DINNER AT THE [POLISH] PRESS CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dinner sponsored by the Alliance publications in celebration of the tenth anniversary of the founding of Dziennik Zwiazkowy was held on Saturday at the Polish Press Club on Pierce Avenue. All of the employees of the editorial, administrative, and printing departments were present. Altogether, there were about sixty participants, among whom was a guest, Thaddeus Wronski, who is visiting Chicago. N. K. Zlotnicki, a director of the Polish National Alliance, was chosen toastmaster. He delivered a short address in behalf of the Central Administration, after which he called upon the heads of each department of Dziennik Zwiazkowy for a few words. J. Olbinski, general manager of the Alliance publications, delivered the following address:</p>
   <p>"Ladies and Gentlemen! In the first place, I would like to express my great joy in having lived to see this happy moment when together with the many <pb facs="5423968_6_0349.jpg" n="2"/>employees present here who have contributed their efforts and their labor to the growth of Dziennik Zwiazkowy from the very beginning, I can observe this tenth anniversary of the founding of our paper. And we can celebrate this anniversary with greater joy and happiness because we have placed our Dziennik Zwiazkowy on a higher level than that attained by any other daily paper twice as old as ours. Today, our paper has the largest circulation, the best equipped printing department, and, what is most important, it has, in addition to an established following, a large cash capital which assures it independence and a safe future.</p>
   <p>"But we reached this state only after great efforts and after overcoming great obstacles. Catastrophe threatened us several times during the course of ten years. Already at the very founding of the paper, things did not go as we had planned. Even though the convention in Baltimore approved the establishment of Dziennik Zwiazkowy by a great majority, members of the Alliance in Chicago as well as those elsewhere did not support it as they should have and as had been expected. The number of subscribers was not <pb facs="5423968_6_0350.jpg" n="3"/>large enough to sustain the paper. In addition to this, opponents and competitors of Dziennik Zwiazkowy tried in every way possible to destroy this newcomer in the field of journalism. There is probably no other newspaper in the world that has been exposed to such chicanery and persecution. You will admit that under such conditions it was difficult to work at expanding Dziennik Zwiazkowy. Then, too, there was a lack of experienced help in the administrative department. Besides the bookkeeper, I was practically the only one who was familiar with the publishing business--I had no capable and experienced assistants. I had to open letters myself, take in money, take care of correspondence, run the treasury, pay out money, give orders, and keep an eye on the entire business. In a short time, I saw that ruin threatened us, and I informed the Alliance authorities to that effect. They appointed a new manager. Under the new manager, it was possible, though not without great effort, to avert catastrophe, but even then Dziennik Zwiazkowy's existence was uncertain. It was necessary to be extremely diligent and careful. Almost five years of strenous effort was <pb facs="5423968_6_0351.jpg" n="4"/>necessary before we could relax and regard Dziennik Zwiazkowy as firmly established.</p>
   <p>"In the succeeding years, there were disturbances that three times brought us into real trouble. The first was when the Central Administration reduced the subscription rate to two dollars. This proved to be an unwise step, and we were soon forced to return to the previous rate of three dollars. The second was at the beginning of the European war. The circulation of Dziennik Zwiazkowy had jumped within three months to 52,000. We were all extremely pleased over this rapid growth, but in the meantime this expansion fairly shook our foundations. Subscriptions do not in themselves cover the costs of publishing. New efforts were necessary, new agents and premiums had to be established, advertising rates had to be increased, the paper enlarged. After a year, we returned to normal. A third time was a year and a half ago, when the price of paper and printing materials increased almost threefold. What saved us then was the immediate increase of our subscription rates to four dollars, the extension of our paper contract for almost nine months longer <pb facs="5423968_6_0352.jpg" n="5"/>at the old price, and reducing the size of the paper.</p>
   <p>"Today, when the price of paper is more moderate, our circulation moderately high, our volume of advertising fairly large, and the advertising rates sufficient, we not only stand on firm financial ground, being able to meet all expenses, but we can effect considerable economies. This was proved last year, when we saved more than twenty thousand dollars. The capital that we are now accumulating must be used for the erection of a new Alliance building for Dziennik Zwiazkowy, and for new machinery. At the present time, we are too crowded; we need more space: we need our own building. We also need new machines for folding newspapers, and it will soon be necessary to consider the purchase of a new rotary press, for the old one will have outlived its usefulness in a few years. These are the things we are saving money for.</p>
   <p>"Thus I have given you a sketch of the administrative department's activities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0353.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It should be added that we never kept any regular hours, but worked ten and twelve, and sometimes fourteen hours a day, without additional pay. Great efforts were necessary, and there were many difficulties. More than once, I spent sleepless nights worrying about the consequences, for as general manager I would be held responsible. Thatstrenuous labor had its effect on my nerves; it made my hair white, and it certainly did not add any years to my life. Despite all this, I am very happy to have lived to see this moment,happy that I can see the results of our mutual effort. No matter how hard things were, there was always enough money for salaries and even for advances.</p>
   <p>"In the face of constant difficulties and a constant pulling to make ends meet for almost ten years, today's success and sound financial condition seem to me to be a beautiful dream, and I am afraid that I will awaken to face stark reality. Fortunately, it is not a dream, but reality itself!</p>
   <p>"I now turn to you, my colleagues of the administrative and editorial <pb facs="5423968_6_0354.jpg" n="7"/>departments, of the printing department, to you who from the very beginning have worked with me as well as to those of you who joined us later. I will name no one, for then I should have to name everybody--all of you have worked sincerely, perseveringly, and zealously, and all of you are entitled to equal acknowledgment. Accept the thanks of your old chief for your hard and diligent work. The creation of great things always presents difficulties and requires sacrifices, and we, by our efforts, have created a truly great thing, for we have sustained and made permanent the Alliance's daily newspaper. With the creation of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, the Polish National Alliance freed itself of partisan influence; it no longer needs anybody's good favor--it has its own champion and defender in every need. We nurtured and put this giant on his feet!</p>
   <p>"Once more, my sincere thanks to you, ladies and gentlemen. Long live the Polish National Alliance! Long live Dziennik Zwiazkowy!"</p>
   <p>The company spent a few hours in pleasant conversation, and even the fear <pb facs="5423968_6_0355.jpg" n="8"/>of another snowstorm that might prevent them from reaching their homes at a "decent" hour, did not prevent the participants from having a good time, and from recalling memories from the first days of Dziennik Zwiazkowy's existence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
