<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-04-01">Apr. 1, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Press in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-04-01">Apr. 1, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH PRESS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Like mushrooms after a rainfall, almost every year there appear new publications in Polish-American sections. It is recognized that many, from the initial appearance will be short lived; others will appear like meteors, flash now and again, and quickly disappear. Some manage through a longer time to eke out a meager existence, fed by the work of others from day to day, from week to week. At times some appear like parasites even as a nymph that is transformed into a beautiful butterfly to hover over flowers for their common good, touching this one and that during its lifetime.</p>
   <p>In addition to the many colorless, little-known papers there are found in America some fine Polish journals. These in one age went against more important editions and succeeded greatly. Consequently it not only helped their own cause, but materially gaining through their value the public demand. These last few years especially, brought about many <pb facs="5423968_6_0499.jpg" n="2"/>changes in this respect. Today the existence of some weekly editions which were mere pamphlets prior to this, is due to the backing of some politician or business firm with the purpose of opening Polish purses, often creating more harm than good.</p>
   <p>Today these conditions are definitely improved. Indeed many provincial publications, we name them so, are yet in need of a change. At any rate this step ahead is noticeable. Some of the local papers are beginning to print a daily chronicle of the daily events. They also take more interest in the various affairs. Not only do they write about the most important matters but the minor incidents of the day are written along with the activities of the neglected mass movement, thereby promoting better living.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the life of society and its development, which is composed of these small stepping stones, will with the coming of years create <pb facs="5423968_6_0500.jpg" n="3"/>monumental buildings.</p>
   <p>The Polish-American press span of existence is between fifty and sixty years. As soon as some fall, others take their place and begin to wage anew the war for existence. At times creating envy and friction between various factions and other local papers. Often the surroundings are affected. When the paper introduces a new movement, it becomes difficult for it to thrive in materialistic America.</p>
   <p>That is why newspaper competition in America continues without any break. Often it is heated, and scandalizing.</p>
   <p>This is due to misrepresentation, momentarily becoming calm, only to spring up again with greater force.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0501.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It must be admitted that competition, in many instances, is necessary and when of great character, it brings in outside influence. Without this warfare there would be no interest created. This must be admitted with sadness, for not even a half of the present readers would be subscribers. The readers situation is actually the result of these sporadic wars and the wiping out of movements, parties and wheels of friction, and separate personal problems. Polish sections, in the United States, did not rid themselves of old country small-town character, therefore, every story greedily commented upon creates great interest. Thus Polish-American press grew out of its infancy into importance, and through the merit of their stories the papers gained a wide circulation. All of this created an interest which aroused the Polish reading mind. From the competitive wars in the groups, with news of major importance that came to light, the press came to a better understanding with the Polish people in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0502.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Today the Polish Press is still waging its wars. However, this time, it is over grave questions. At times the old methods of the press which sailed on stormy seas seeking a safe harbor, are still used.</p>
   <p>Great steps forward have now been made. The Polish Press in America has gained materially, influence and financial stability. In many sections of the country the Polish paper has become an illuminating mirror of local affairs.</p>
   <p>Amid all this Dziennik Zwiazkowy took a foothold and triumphed despite this keen competition. When the efforts of the opposing forces were defeated, this young Polish organ began to win praise. It began to publish facts about working conditions; improving conditions along the line. It is because of this that the other Polish dailies in America are changing their style of writing news.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0503.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Dziennik Zwiazkowy through these efforts has gained great respect for its candid presentation of the news. Through these efforts and changes it is expected that this daily paper will grow in value, and set a definite form of ethics through its writings. We will have a lasting value, furnishing examples and models, as well as educational inspiration for its large range of readers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
