<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-28">Feb. 28, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Poles of Switzerland Appeal for a Monument to Reytan, Polish Patriot</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1377</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1377.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-28">Feb. 28, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">POLES OF SWITZERLAND APPEAL FOR A MONUMENT TO REYTAN, POLISH PATRIOT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following appeal, dated February 2, was received from Zurich, Switzerland:</p>
   <p>Fellow countrymen! Among the great men that are held in high esteem by the Poles, Thaddeus Reytan[also Rejtan], great Polish patriot immortalized by Matejko, Polish artist, holds an undisputed place in the first rank. He was one of the bright rays who spoke about the new tomorrow of our Republic, a tomorrow of common brotherhood, supported by the righteousness of society. Through his own actions, he built his own immortal statue. Everyone of us owes him a debt of gratitude.</p>
   <p>Many years ago, twenty Poles living in Switzerland honored Reytan by erecting a monument to him at Soleure, next to that of Kosciusko. But through the years this memorial became worn by the weather to such an extent that it is beyond repair. In view of this, a Polish society has been organized in Zurich with the idea of building a new statue to Reytan at the Pantheon in <pb facs="5423968_6_1378.jpg" n="2"/>Rapperswyl, on the free land of Helvitia, as a national memorial.</p>
   <p>This idea, it is believed, will find support among our countrymen, and material aid will be willingly given to this noble cause. Therefore, we turn to them to send gifts of money, even the smallest amounts, to the following address: S. Buryan, Zurich, V. Sprensenbuehl Street 40, Switzerland.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Polish Society of Zurich,</p>
   <p>S. Buryan, engineer, president,</p>
   <p>John Lipinski, secretary,</p>
   <p>Theodore Eisenbelt, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
