<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-09-04">Sept. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution Adopted by the Convention of Polish Newspapermen in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0428</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0428.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-09-04">Sept. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION ADOPTED BY THE CONVENTION OF POLISH NEWSPAPERMEN IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention of Polish newspapermen of America, meeting in Chicago on the second and third of September--on the threshold of the fourth year of a war, of which one result must be a free and independent Poland--considers it a duty and an honor to express its deepest respect for the great president of the United States, Woodrow Wilson, who was the first leader in world affairs to bring a war-torn nation hope at a time of its greatest trial, by declaring that Poland must be given justice, that it must be independent, united and free.</p>
   <p>The convention of Polish newspapermen of America is unanimous in its belief that the course of events during the war, and especially the collapse of czarist Russia and the proclamation of a new, democratic Russia, which has ended the Polish-Russian dispute and the Russian occupation of Polish territory, and thus achieving approbation of the new and independent Poland on the part of the Allied powers, has sufficiently brightened the political horizon of our <pb facs="5423968_6_0429.jpg" n="2"/>nation, alike in Poland as here among the Polish element in America, to unite all honest hearts to support one program and one aim, for the achievement of which we should be willing to impose upon ourselves the utmost self-sacrifice, for which we should be willing to give up our lives and material goods.</p>
   <p>The convention of Polish newspapermen of America recognizes the fact that, to the achievement of our peoples' aims, it is essential that the Polish-American press be unequivocally united, for the cause of our homeland demands that we stand, not divided into factions, ungovernable, and struggling amongst ourselves, but united, for a single aim requires a solid front.</p>
   <p>Casting aside the quarrels and disagreements of the past, we call upon the entire Polish press of America to desist from quarreling and from base and destructive polemics, to reshape its policies with respect to the Polish cause, and to lay upon the altar of that cause all personal differences, real or imagined. We call upon all publishers to join hands and close the nationalist ranks into one file.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0430.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The convention of Polish newspapermen of America takes this occasion to express its recognition of, and solidarity with, the activity to the Polish Central Relief Committee and the [Polish] National Department up to the present time. It earnestly supports the efforts of those organizations to create a Polish army, and obligates itself to popularize the idea of a non-partisan commission as the nucleus of a Polish government.</p>
   <p>Recognizing the useful activity of the Polish Central Relief Committee and the National Department as legitimate representations of the largest [Polish] national organizations in America, the convention calls upon the Polish press to use its influence to help create the largest possible number of societies that will affiliate themselves with the National Department properly taxed for the good of the cause, and thus create a force that will bear the sacrifices, now and in the future, that are necessary for the rebuilding of Poland.</p>
   <p>To oppressed Poland, now arising to freedom, we take this occasion of expressing our sincere homage and unbounded fidelity, while to her faithful sons who <pb facs="5423968_6_0431.jpg" n="4"/>are now working for her union and independence, whether it be on the field of battle or in diplomatic circles, we express our gratitude and agreement with their efforts.</p>
   <p>All hail, free, independent, united, and autonomous Poland! All hail, faithful sons of Poland who have persevered and who will continue to persevere in her defense!</p>
   <p>Resolutions Committee:</p>
   <p>Leopold Koscinski,</p>
   <p>Stanislaus Orpiszewski,</p>
   <p>Ignace Osostowicz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
