<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-04-13">Apr. 13, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Poetry of Szczesny Zahajkiewicz Published in Book Form</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0085</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0085.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-04-13">Apr. 13, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">POETRY OF SZCZESNY ZAHAJKIEWICZ PUBLISHED IN BOOK FORM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Poezye Szczesnego Zahajkiewicza (Poems by Szczesny Zahajkiewicz), Part I, 1894, has been recently published and has been on sale during the past week in leading Polish book stores. The book is a collection of original poetry written by our well-known compatriot and poet Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, who has been a constant contributor to Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <p>This book of Polish poems is among the few original Polish works that have been published in America. The poems are filled with deep creative thoughts and are written in excellent style. It is, therefore, timely to say a few words about the author and his work.</p>
   <p>In our scant Polish-American literature, Mr. Zahajkiewicz plays an important part. He was born in Galicia [an Austrian-occupied Polish province] and came to America over five years ago as an accomplished literary figure. Prior to his arrival Mr. Zahajkiewicz had his first work, Rymow (Rhymes), published in Lwow; it was well received by the critics. Several other books for children <pb facs="5423968_6_0086.jpg" n="2"/>were also published in Galicia. He also wrote many articles for the Galician press. These are the accomplishments of our poet and writer, who shows a promising future.</p>
   <p>The budding author began to gather laurels soon after his arrival in Chicago. Despite his arduous work in the pedagogical field, S. Zahajkiewicz was able to find time for writing from the very beginning. He created many well-known Polish plays, wrote many articles, stories and poems, which appeared in the Polish press. These poems are the fruit of his years on American soil. These creative contributions to Polish-American literature are indeed worthy of consideration; for they were written during the spare time Mr. Zahajkiewicz found outside of his work as a teacher and as a worker in Polish public life.</p>
   <p>After being scattered for five years throughout the many columns of the Polish press, his songs and verse have finally been collected by B. Straszynski of Milwaukee, a friend of Mr. Zahajkiewicz, and put into book form.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0087.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This collection of poetry is free from any arduous work; it is rather a spontaneous expression of an idea, although it is lyrical. The book contains about seventy poems, many of which were published in Dziennik Chicagoski, or other Polish papers; others are entirely new. All are of unusual freshness, and are simple in structure and style. The rhyme and rhythm just pours out smoothly and is pleasant to the ear. It is felt that S. Zahajkiewicz is not a master poet but a natural singer of song [sic].</p>
   <p>If one is to compare his works, they would be likened to wild flowers which grow freshly and fragrantly, without any care. Although the poems are plain, they are unusually beautiful. But just as in each wild flower, there shines in each a brilliant drop of refreshing dew.</p>
   <p>When the author calls to the lark "Frun", there immediately comes to his mind the thought of the fatherland, and he has the bird use it as a theme in its song. The word "spring" gives Mr. Zahajkiewicz reason to call to his brothers to fight anger, filth and vileness with virtue and love. "The Third <pb facs="5423968_6_0088.jpg" n="4"/>of May" designates "faith" as a means of casting away the stone on Poland's grave [this means that faith in the fatherland will eventually bring about the freedom of Poland]. Some of his poetical works overflow with love for the mother country and a desire to return to it; while others speak of deep religious and Christian resignation. Even bitterness and pain recalls to him the duty and necessity of guarding the "standards of idealism." At other times he urges his compatriot who is enveloped in misery not to be satisfied in only saying in the end "I have done my share," but tells him to cast a "spark after a spark", work, live and battle for truth, and "hang a cross above this standard." He explains with pride that we should be proud to be Poles; for pain he finds a cure in the evangelical maxim "blessed are those who suffer, and finds success and fortune beyond the grave, in Heaven. He says to resurrect Poland through harmony. This Polish poet concludes his work with the following:</p>
   <p>"God is truth--and life in action!"</p>
   <p>These poems contain an unusually refreshing feeling; they are woven by the <pb facs="5423968_6_0089.jpg" n="5"/>healthy spirit of the poet, and are not contaminated with any of the modern poetical trends in Europe or in Poland, where poetry is filled with decadent watchwords and demoralizing ideas.</p>
   <p>These melodic and sincere heart strains, rich and brilliant in song, will undoubtedly receive recognition, which they deserve, when they reach Poland..... They will awaken heartfelt echoes, and prove that among our hard-working people there still are those that find time to sing about Poland.</p>
   <p>This book of poems by Zahajkiewicz is issued as part one. We are anxiously awaiting part two.</p>
   <p>H. N.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
