<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1890-12-15">Dec. 15, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">The First Number</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0795</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0795.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1890-12-15">Dec. 15, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST NUMBER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How is the appearance of this new journal? Everyone will take it, read it from A to Z with great interest, and cast his judgment more or less favorably. There will be sharp criticism, very little praise, and much censuring; certain persons will object to this, and others to other things; defects will be found, and comparison with other journals will bring unprofitable results.</p>
   <p>Such is the fate of every new publication, and we are prepared for such a fate.</p>
   <p>However, we hope that this condition will not last very long. Perhaps the first numbers will not satisfy the needs of our readers, but gradually we will learn about what they like and adjust ourselves to them <pb facs="5423968_6_0796.jpg" n="2"/>so as to make our journal a favored newspaper. Criticism, if not malicious or groundless, will be useful to us and gladly accepted. We will try to adjust ourselves to it, and eliminate the defects.</p>
   <p>Our program will not be the subject of a long discussion. The policy of the paper can be enunciated thus:</p>
   <p>"A political newspaper devoted to the interests of the Poles in the United States." These words explain the program. We have no intention of serving any party, either political or social; we desire to be impartial, pointing out the merits and demerits of different parties.</p>
   <p>If we defend at present the principles of the Democratic party in the United States, which we intend to do in the future as long as its principles remain unchanged, we do so not because we are merely blind tools of that party, but because its principles are advantageous to the Poles living in the United States. This does not mean that our journal is positively Democratic or that <pb facs="5423968_6_0797.jpg" n="3"/>we have a definite political leaning; nor does it mean that we are subservient to any political party. Let us suppose that the platform of the candidates of the Republican Party improves before the next election and becomes more profitable to our interests; we are willing to support it impartially and we do not intend to justify the faults of the Democratic Party or try to conceal them by silence.</p>
   <p>Matters belonging to the immigration of our people will be treated likewise. We shall have an opportunity to take up many problems in which we are greatly interested, and we will endeavor to give them an impartial consideration, without earning the accusation of elevating or degrading something unjustly.</p>
   <p>The first principles guiding us can be expressed in a few words. Having a great respect for the Constitution of the United States, of which country we are citizens, we judge that we should take an active part in the life of this country. We consider it a great Republic, formed of many freedom-loving <pb facs="5423968_6_0798.jpg" n="4"/>nations that despise the knout and slavery. We who are Poles should regard ourselves not as guests but as an integral part of this great nation, enjoying the same rights and bearing the same responsibilities as any other nation represented. As such we should take an active part in its political life, care for its development, power, and purity. Therefore, we should try to eliminate evil and introduce instead that which our conscience dictates to us as good.</p>
   <p>Will this prevent us from being good Poles? Not at all. Whoever maintains such an opinion does not know how to examine this matter properly. If the Irish living in Europe are very enthusiastic on the great influence or great success of their countrymen in America, profiting by it quite often, not only materially, but also politically and morally; if the Germans in Europe proudly describe the success of their Kulturtraeger (culture spreaders)in America, then the Poles living in Europe may also profit by our success, if and when we take an active part in the life of this great Republic and distinguish ourselves as citizens; not isolating ourselves as mere guests and becoming lost completely in the sea of the nation. If we serve the United States as good citizens, we also serve <pb facs="5423968_6_0799.jpg" n="5"/>our own country, and here lies the difficulty of the task: to be good citizens of this country and remain also good Poles at heart. These are our principles, our point of view, which Dziennik Chicagoski will protect and try to explain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
