<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-02">Mar, 2, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Crimes of the Dziennik Chicagoski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0714</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0714.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-02">Mar, 2, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE CRIMES OF THE DZIENNIK CHICAGOSKI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Dziennik Chicagoski has committed several grave crimes in its recent editions, according to some of its dear friends.</p>
   <p>That we have many of these "dear" readers, who watch every issue of the publication with one purpose in mind: to find something that can be discussed and ridiculed in their particular circle, or to criticize some typographical error to such an extent that forgiveness is rendered impossible. We are familiar with these individuals. Their names are well known to us. These attacks to hurt us are not unusual. But it is unusual that these attackers are able to convince others with their ridiculous beliefs. Many times they argue that the Dziennik Chicagoski has done this purposely, that it was our aim to hurt someone.</p>
   <p>There are three such examples that have befallen our recent editions. It is <pb facs="5423968_6_0715.jpg" n="2"/>our contention that our "dear" friends are trying their best to discredit news stories and to mock our efforts before the other readers of our paper. We give the following examples for the public to judge:</p>
   <p>The first story concerns the news taken from the Herald (the article was carefully translated) about the fraud perpetrated by H. Rawicz, Anthony Lewandowski, and Frank Meyer. The victim was Joseph Juszczec (the name originally appeared as Juszency, because it was falsely given, however, this was corrected). Because the name of the proprietor of the saloon did not appear, he took offense at the mispelling of the victim's name. The location of the saloon was plainly written. We wonder if he wants to be held responsible for the incident that happened in his beer palace. Yet there are some who believe that the tavern keeper is justified for feeling offended.</p>
   <p>The second incident concerns the omission of two Polish societies from the article that dealt with the consecration of St. Mary's of Perpetual Help <pb facs="5423968_6_0716.jpg" n="3"/>Church. This also has been corrected. It seems that for such a trifling error no one should have been hurt. But our "dear" readers have not even forgiven this. These "readers" approached the members of the societies and convinced one of them to take offense at so grave an omission. These individuals insisted that this was a deliberate act and that he, as an influential member of the society, should convince the entire group to boycott the Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <p>One of the most amusing incidents happened yesterday, which shows to what extent our enemies reach to throw insults at our publication. Our readers are familiar with our first page. Telegraphic reports from Europe are found in the columns on the left. Next in line are domestic dispatches. In the right-hand column city news is printed. The latter seldom has enough space to appear complete on the front page. At the bottom of the column the heading "continued on page four" directs the reader where to go on with the story. The headline on page four, column one, reads: "Continued from page one".</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0717.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the city news column a headline separates one story from another. These headings are always in bold type. As it happened in this news column in the forty-eighth issue, February 27, the story of the Rowkowski wedding anniversary appeared in the last column of the first page. The last line of the story completed this item and the column. Then followed the "continued to page four" line. The headline on page four was "Young Thieves". Every reader knows that such a heading denotes a new news item. It is only logical that one article be separated from another by a heading or a drawn line. This eliminates any confusion.</p>
   <p>One of the guests of the silver wedding anniversary, who apparently had no knowledge of any discrepancy in the newspaper version of the celebration, received eleven letters, informing him that a grave injustice was done in the treatment of the article. Our "beloved" readers convinced him that the story was purposely set-up so that the "Young Thieves" news item would follow it. They, however, have insinuated that the wedding received an inferior place and <pb facs="5423968_6_0718.jpg" n="5"/>that the story of the young robbers found a better position on the fourth page, which was at the head of the column. They also mentioned that we left off the title of alderman from the name of J. J. Dahlmann. We are sorry that this occurred.</p>
   <p>The surprising thing of the three situations is that neither of the persons concerned have taken offence. They have handled the conversation and correspondence with their informers with intelligence and understanding.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
