<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-08-05">August 5, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Meaning of Sport in Training the Polish Youth</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1146</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1146.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-08-05">August 5, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE MEANING OF SPORT IN TRAINING THE POLISH YOUTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As the end of each man's life draws near and until the open arms of a grave await him, he oftentimes thinks of the grave as a comforter who will soothe his pains and aches and who will finally assure him peace, tranquility and rest. But lives there a man who does not shudder at the serious thought of parting with this world? Who would not gladly form a schedule to meet with his own life, who would not length that life. If this, our temporal life seems to us a volley of tears, and if at times we seem to have to much of life, then it is so, simply because our life is not arranged in the manner in which we would like to have it, and because it does not permit us to realize our demands.</p>
   <p>Should life, on the other hand fulfil our wishes and run along the line we ourselves indicated we would be a hundredfold happier, and death would be as much more dreadful. The battle for existence waged by every man is nothing else than an attempt to bring conditions of life, as close as possible to our ideal of it but a scant few, however can boast that they have achieved, in this respect complete success.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1147.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Besides the battle for existence humanity wages a war with time which is closely interwoven with it. Death is implacable, man cannot avoid it and will to his fate up to the last minute he beleives in the successful outcome of his battle for existence and hopes to have sufficient time to realize his triumph. He wages therefore another battle, a war with time, which is working for death draining nearer with every breathe. If then, we wish to prolong life we must overtake time, living intensively, making use of every fraction of a second of which we have fewer to dispose of every minute.</p>
   <p>Man's race with time continues in every field of his activity. When we read of the travels of our sires, we smile indulgently at the length of time required to travel to the city their ridiclous conveyances-how childish they look alongside our speedy locomotives speeding at the rate of sixty to seventy miles an hour. Both train and locomotive have already become absolete means of locomotion for man; he speeds sixty, eighty, and even one hundred miles an hour in an automobile when this is insufficient,,he turns to his use in an aerial chariot in which he will dart to and fro at the rate of a hundred and one hundred fifty miles an hour. Racing and sport planes will develop a speed exceeding two hundred and fifty miles an hour.</p>
   <p>Contemporary man corresponds by air mail, and radiograms take the place of letters. He does not waste time, instead of attending a concert, he tunes in on the radio and <pb facs="5423968_6_1148.jpg" n="3"/>the concert is brought to him. Factories, today, produce twenty and thirty times as much as did the men of his grandfather's day. Machinery is supplanting manual labor.</p>
   <p>The continuous struggle with time has considerable influence on the struggle for existence. It demands of man a decided character. Only a certain type of people living in this age of speedy tempo, and who manage to hold firm in this struggle with time attain success.</p>
   <p>The 20th century places high demands upon man. Success awaits only men who are hardened and manly. The world of today crowns with success only the man with a strong character and determination, the man who drives his resolutions home; one who believes in himself and his ultimate success; one who will persevere such traits in the face of all obstacles, mental and physical; one gifted with intuition initiative introspect and optimism, one who is ready at a moments notice, to take upon his shoulders a responsibility. Briefly, the world belongs to decided characters; that is why sports often have so much influence on character. What are the educational values of sport, why should it be encouraged in our Polish youth? From time unmemorial, every Slav was looked upon as a delicate man gentle and good natured, but weak willed, and of small perseverance. We have exceptions <pb facs="5423968_6_1149.jpg" n="4"/>which rather tend to round out, and do not disprove this opinion, namely, the attempt to have the origin of the name Slov changed to the Latin "Sclavus" meaning a slave.</p>
   <p>Our national character is not adopted to the age in which we hold the opportunity of nationalistic rebirth; a hundred years of slavery checked our development, and foreign rulers of our country, strove to keep alive in us all our faults, and this they did rather intelligently.</p>
   <p>Thus today, we are behind the times. The whole world for many years has deemed sports one of the most important factors of education in preparing youth and at the same time contribution to the commonwealth the treasurer of healthy and vigorous youth with decided characters, real citizens. Therefore Poles in America and in Poland should concentrate on great sport events until eventually, the notion be refered to as "Poland the Land of Good Citizens."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
