<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-16">Mar. 16, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Copernicus Literary Competition</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter from a prize-winning competitor.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-16">Mar. 16, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">COPERNICUS LITERARY COMPETITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter from a prize-winning competitor.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dziennik Chicagoski has been requested to publish the following communication:</p>
   <p>"Dear Editor: From the article published in yesterday's issue of your newspaper announcing the results of the [Copernicus] literary competition, I have learned that the story Mr. Xavier's Revenge was awarded fourth prize by one judge, third prize by another, and second prize by a third. On the basis of this decision, the story in question received fourth place.</p>
   <p>"As author of this story, before revealing my real name to the Competition Committee, I have the right to ask whether or not the remaining two judges, who did not even mention this work, read the story and after reading it decided that it did not deserve any award.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, I, the author of the story, consider it proper to demand a public explanation from Mr. Satalecki and Dr. Kalusowski. On this explanation will <pb facs="5423968_6_0098.jpg" n="2"/>depend the revealing of my name. In my letter to Mr. Drzymala which was mailed together with the manuscript some time ago, I gave the reasons why I used certain precautions in sending my work and why I desired to withhold my name.</p>
   <p>"I do not care for the award, but I desire justice.</p>
   <p>"Moreover, I consider it proper to add that the plan of the work, which I named A Sketch of the Story, was originally written for the purpose of writing a story. As the time allotted for the first competition was very short, and as the conditions of the competition limited the length of the story, I wrote only a sketch of the story instead of the story which I would have written had I known that the time of the competition would be extended. Of course, a sketch could not compete with the story itself.</p>
   <p>"Submitting my original manuscript, A Sketch of a Story, to Dziennik Chicagoski, for the purpose of proving my authorship, I remain,</p>
   <p>"Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>"Joseph Piotrowski"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
