<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-15">Dec. 15, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Kosciusko Monument Model Contest</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-15">Dec. 15, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE KOSCIUSKO MONUMENT MODEL CONTEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A letter concerning the Kosciusko Monument Contest has been sent to the Gazeta Katolicka (Catholic Gazette) by Dr. E. H. Dunikowski, who was appointed to represent the Kosciusko Monument Contest abroad on his recent good will tour. The letter contained the following conditions, which were agreed upon after Dr. Dunikowski's conference with the members of the Lwow Fine Arts Society:</p>
   <p>1. The monument is to be of bronze, with figure on horse, and is to be one and one-half times natural size.</p>
   <p>2. The figure of Kosciusko is to be in an American uniform, and is to wear an Order of Cincinnatus.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1418.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>3. Two bas-reliefs, one depicting the battle of Savannah and the other Raclawice[Rising aginst Russia on April 29, 1794], are to appear, one on each side of the figure.</p>
   <p>4. The cost is not to exceed 80,000 florins (Austrian), or about $30,000.</p>
   <p>5. The models are to be of gypsum and one-tenth natural size.</p>
   <p>6. Besides the three awards three letters of honorable mention will also be given.</p>
   <p>The Lwow Fine Arts Society has accepted in the main all the proposals of the Kosciusko Monument Society.</p>
   <p>As to the awards, the letter states reasons why the prizes should be increased. This angle was covered in a previous article in the Dziennik Chicagoski; however, the Committee accepted the suggestions. We wish to <pb facs="5423968_6_1419.jpg" n="3"/>point out that the prizes of a similar contest held for a model of Hickiewicz in Cracow were three times as large.</p>
   <p>In general, according to the Kosciusko Monument Committee, ample time has been given for the contest, and the prize-winning models will be on display in the Palace of Fine Arts at the Columbian Exposition in Chicago during 1893.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
