<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1929-07-12">July 12, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">St. Stanislaus College Alumni Outing</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0907</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0907.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1929-07-12">July 12, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">ST. STANISLAUS COLLEGE ALUMNI OUTING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Wednesday, July 24, is the day when the Saint Stanislaus College Alumni will have their outing in Harms Woods Preserve.</p>
   <p>And please note, the alumni affair should hold even more incentive for the tired business and professional man, for the outing will be a stag affair. And no one enjoys stags better than the tired businessman and professional man. Without the incumbrance that a wife or a sweetheart sometime proves to be, he enjoys a stag affair to the utmost, playing golf till he is tired, singing till he is hoarse, eating till he nigh bursts.</p>
   <p>Sounds selfish, lupine, epicurean, but why not? Even gloomy Dean Inge concedes that modern man must turn about face sometime. And John D. Rockerfeller is credited with remarking at one time that his idea of a successful man is the fellow who finds time to chuck up work and care occasionally and grab his khaki duds or golf sticks and hide away for the day.</p>
   <p>Then our clergy surely can find time and inducement to break away on July 24 and join their erstwhile colleagues out in Harms Woods. Maybe Doctor Liss will even teach them golf or break a couple of clubs in the attempt.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0908.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But either way, the Alumni stag on that Wednesday will put them in better shape for the pulpit on the following Sunday. A coat of tan means a healthy body and a healthy outlook.</p>
   <p>So let us forget business acumen and philosophy and epistemology at least for one day. Send in that little questionnaire forwarded to you by post some time ago. Fill it out and pledge your presence. We won't say, "Hear the call of dear old Alma Mater, but hear the call of your old school chums. Please notify the St. Stanislaus College Alumni Association at your earliest convenience that you will be there on the 24th.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
