<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1930-03-08">Mar. 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. John T. Czech New Sports' Editor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1930-03-08">Mar. 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">MR. JOHN T. CZECH NEW SPORTS' EDITOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although it is a few weeks since Mr. John T. Czech tackled his new position of sports' editor, the members of the Saint James Club of Brighton Park extend to him their heartiest congratulations, as to one who has secured a responsible position with one of the fast growing and best Polish newspapers in Chicago. The writer of this article came in contact with the new sports' editor about four years ago, when the Polish Roman Catholic Union Baseball League was inaugaurated; and he holds that the editor-in-chief, of the Polish Union Daily, Mr. Stefanowicz, did not make a mistake by placing our worthy Polish Roman Catholic Union sport promoter at the helm of the sports' department. In our esteem, Mr. Czech is a true intellectual, who endeavors to maintain the best of sports among people of Polish extraction. Prior to the appearance of our sports commission, Mr. Czech worked strenuously endeavoring to make the Polish Roman Catholic Union sports what they are at the present day. His conceptions are wonderful and he contemplates to serve the readers of our sports' page to the best of his ability. The creation of <pb facs="5423968_6_1127.jpg" n="2"/>new columns appearing in the sports' page since Mr. Czech took charge is a proof of the fact that we are receiving some first class service under the new sports' editor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
