<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-30">Jan. 30, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Dramatic and Literary Circle Organized at Bridgeport</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-30">Jan. 30, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">DRAMATIC AND LITERARY CIRCLE ORGANIZED AT BRIDGEPORT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of loading Polish citizens of Bridgeport was held on January 25 at L. Czeslawski's Hall for the purpose of organizing a club to promote education among the Poles. After a long discussion, it was agreed to found such an organization, which will be called the "Dramatic and Literary Circle". The club will organize a library, arrange lectures, present plays, offer training in singing and music, etc.</p>
   <p>In order to give everyone an opportunity to join, the initiation fee has been set at fifty cents. Since the realization of the aims of the Circle requires the expenditure of large sums of money, the administration appeals to the Polish people, especially those in Bridgeport, to support the programs sponsored by the club. It would not be fair to demand large dues from the thirty members now in the Circle, and that is why this appeal is made. Moral and material help, as well as contributions of books, <pb facs="5423968_6_0053.jpg" n="2"/>will be greatly appreciated. The books will be used in the proposed library, and the names of the donors will be published in the Polish press.</p>
   <p>The Dramatic and Literary Circle will welcome any suggestions as to how it may best serve the Polish people. Everyone knows the good such an organization can accomplish for the people.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held on February 1, 7:30 P. M., at Czeslawski's Hall. The present officers of the Dramatic and Literary Circle are M. Wleklinski and Dr. W. Statkiewicz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
