<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-14">July 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a"/><title level="a" type="sub">United States of America, May, 1892</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0845</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0845.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-14">July 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">United States of America, May, 1892</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We request all the Polish newspapers in America to print this reply:</p>
   <p>The Paderewskis, Modrzejewskis, Rzeszkows, <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>ierzwinskis, <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>ieniawski, <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>imaje, little Hoffman and others have gained a great name for Polish art on this side of the ocean. Profiting, therefore, from such a good start, an attempt should be made to stabilize and develop this laudatory opinion, especially since from it not only moral but also material benefit could be gained for our artists and literati as well as for the entire nation.</p>
   <p>Today, beyond those few above-mentioned names, the Americans have little or no knowledge whatsoever either of our art or even less of our literature. It is only is the last two years that the translation of With Fire and Sword made its appearance, and that of The Deluge appeared only this year. In reference to <pb facs="5423968_6_0846.jpg" n="2"/>painting, the only representatives here thus far are Chelminski and <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>ierusz Kowalski, who were in some way successful in gaining the good will of this wealthy country. These fires are sufficiently popular here, and we see their pictures not only in trade but at nearly every exhibition--but the fame of our brush also ends with them. Relative to sculpture, this was at one time represented by the able and productive artist, Dmochowski, but was hidden under an alien, not Polish, name. At any rate, this is ancient history because thirty years have elapsed since his death. Comparatively speaking we have a greater number of musical representatives because besides those listed at the beginning, we also have here the Kontskis, Niedzielskis; Lamberts, d'Ernests, Levs, Oborskis, Jakubowskis, Strzoleckis, Zadors, and perhaps a half dozen others, of mediocre caliber but useful working artists. Moreover, the memory of Chopin lives here, his compositions are heard at every step, but only a handful know that this genius also was born from the Polish spirit.</p>
   <p>This situation cannot continue, it should not. A beginning has already been made, it is necessary to go forward. If we were not to profit from the situation today, it would be a punitive negligence especially since the Fair is coming. It is <pb facs="5423968_6_0847.jpg" n="3"/>necessary, therefore, to acquaint the Americans more intimately with our literature and art, as well as with the circumstances of our spiritual production, which would assure us a new and yet wide and profitable market plus the additional understanding of the American people.</p>
   <p>This task could be best accomplished today by forming a publishing syndicate for the purpose of translating, as well as an agency for the Polish arts and English articles, an agency which would handle only our finest literary productions, and one where in illustrated form, our finest artistic products could be shown, thus to present our literature and art in that way to the strangers from the most profitable angle.</p>
   <p>In the meantime we propose the publication of an illustrated monthly on the pattern of other local publications of that nature. The preparatory work has already progressed so far that the first edition may even appear during this year. It is hoped that the periodical will be well patronized by our readers. According to reports that have been gathered, it is expected that a favorable reception will <pb facs="5423968_6_0848.jpg" n="4"/>be accorded to this periodical.</p>
   <p>The services which it could render to our arts and artists, as well as to our national cause, which it will explain and defend, are so evident that every educated and Polish-spirited citizen will comprehend it so easily that is is unnecessary to discuss these matters any further. At any rate, another reply explains this.</p>
   <p>We also count upon the ardent civic assistance of our literati and artists, especially because we are starting our work not for any personal gain but for the general welfare and we expect to repay every bit of help according to our strength. We ask, therefore, for a more detailed explanation from the person who simply signs himself as F.A. Koziell, 745-141 Street, New York, H.Y.</p>
   <p>We will only say here that literary creations as well as educational ones are desired, ones which would acquaint a stranger with our country and customs, with our spiritual and intellectual present and past developments, with our civilizing work, with our history and present political and social status--with our literature and <pb facs="5423968_6_0849.jpg" n="5"/>arts, with our literati, our people of education and our artists. The illustrations are to be in the same category. We ask that literary productions be written in Polish and the editorial department will endeavor to obtain a most careful translation.</p>
   <p>Experienced translators are greatly desired, even if it was necessary to polish their style.</p>
   <p>We also request all interested persons to communicate with us and to spread this information to others, especially to those in dramatic and literary circles, since because of lack of addresses and time we cannot make individual invitations.</p>
   <p>All reports will be confidential.</p>
   <p>Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
