<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IX, No. 2,
<date when="1905-01-11">Jan. 11, 1905</date><title level="a">Literary Circle under Name of Adam Mickiewicz</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0044</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0044.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IX, No. 2,
<date when="1905-01-11">Jan. 11, 1905</date><title level="a">LITERARY CIRCLE UNDER NAME OF ADAM MICKIEWICZ</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In today's number we begin the regular publication of the works of the recently organized Adam Mickiewicz Literary Circle, under the protection of the Roman-Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>We have mentioned on several occasions in the columns of our paper information in regard to this society. More than once have we printed the works of some of its members. At present, however, we wish to support more intensely and at once the efforts of our youth eager to go to work, and this we can accomplish best by acquainting the wide circles of the numerous readers of our Narod Polski with these works, that is, with its exceptionally fine literary excerpts. In this way we will give the young Polish-American lovers of the pen the opportunity to express and present their talents, and by this we will encourage most likely more than one of the test of literary work of which we have had so few in recent times. Finally, we intend to react to the good taste of our public, because we will publish only good articles well written, since the Literary Circle <pb facs="5423968_6_0045.jpg" n="2"/>itself considers accurately and criticizes all the work of its members, and on this justly depends their self-education.</p>
   <p>Beside the self-education through self-expression, our circle will also work on the extension of knowledge of the masterpieces of our old and new literature. It also intends to have educational readings. Finally, it hopes, by the help of articles written in the English language, to acquaint in the proper way the people of other nationalities with our affairs and our position.</p>
   <p>All of this is very good, useful and praiseworthy, so far as it will be truly fulfilled, which we readily believe because we are acquainted with the enthusiastic and energetic members of the Literary Circle, to whom we warmly wish great deeds, assuring them that sincere recognition of their work will not be lacking.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
