<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous - "<title level="a">A History of the Polish Dental Association of America</title>," <title>The Bulletin of the Polish Medical and Dental Association of America</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1934-02">Feb. 1934</date>, vol. VI, No. 2 pp. 32-33
<title level="a">[The Polish Dental Association]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0260</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0260.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous - "<title level="a">A History of the Polish Dental Association of America</title>," <title>The Bulletin of the Polish Medical and Dental Association of America</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1934-02">Feb. 1934</date>, vol. VI, No. 2 pp. 32-33
<title level="a">[THE POLISH DENTAL ASSOCIATION]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Dental Association of America was organized in Illinois, May 22, 1908, with offices at Chicago, Ill. The founders of the Pol. Dental Society were Dr. W. A. Gorny and Dr. W. W. Nowacki, Dr. P. T. Wybraniec, Dr. N. T. Rybstadt and Dr. J. W. Zielinski.</p>
   <p>Dr. Zielinski is the only survivor of the founders of the Society. He is still practicing dentistry. He completed his dental studies in 1899.</p>
   <p>The first meeting of Polish Dentists took place in the offices of Dr. Zielinski on Milwaukee Ave. and Carpenter St. where he was elected first president of the Association. It was suggested to organize the Polish Dentists in other cities, but the efforts in this direction were futile. In reality, the association existed only on paper until the year 1917.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0261.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the year 1917, Dr. W. Nalecz Koniuszewski a very able and energetic organizer, not knowing of the existence of the Polish Dental Association made an endeavor to organize all the Polish dentists in the United States into one organization. While he was trying to organize the Polish dentists, Dr. Koniuszewski met Dr. Zielinski, from whom he learned that such an organization already existed.</p>
   <p>In April, 1917, the Polish dentists held a meeting in the Polish Women's Alliance Hall, Chicago, where it was decided to renew the work. At that meeting, Dr. W. Koniwszewski was elected president of the Ass'n. A new constitution, similar to that of the Chicago Dental Society was adopted. There was great activity in the association during the first year of its existence; the meetings were held even in summer time during the hot weather.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0262.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A press committee was formed whose object was to prepare popular articles on the hygiene of the month and the teeth, which the Polish press was very glad to publish.</p>
   <p>The association tried to make Przegad Lekarski, (Medical Review) the organ of the Polish Medical Association, the organ of both organizations, but the Polish medical doctors delayed the matter until their organ ceased to exist.</p>
   <p>An attempt was also made to join the Association with the Chicago Dental Society but without success, on account of the national character of the Polish Dental Association, and the location of its members.</p>
   <p>The meetings which were simultaneously business and educational, were held once a month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0263.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The following lectures were given: Dr. Komuszewski- The acute suppuration of the cavity of the tooth. Dr. Nowacki- Professional ethics Dr. Gorny-The rational method of filling the root canals by Dr. Callahan's method.</p>
   <p>Dr. Urbanowicz- Conductive anaesthetics.</p>
   <p>Dr. Pelka - Amalgam fillings</p>
   <p>Dr. Ordon- Baked porcelain crowns.</p>
   <p>In November 1917, the society held an educational meeting in a hall of the Northwestern University (Chicago) where Dr. Bibb gave a lecture.</p>
   <p>In order to bring the members into closer social contact the society arranged a picnic at Ravina Park.</p>
   <p>The society had 16 members at the end of 1918.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0264.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Besides the regular members, there were thirteen guest members who were mostly students of Chicago institutions. Vol. VI, No 3, Mar. 1934, pp. 54-57. In the year of 1918-1919 the society was in the hands of Dr. W. W. Nowacki who was elected president of the society.</p>
   <p>The social and organizational work of the society was also fruitful that year, but there developed some disharmony among the members, in regards to politics. The question was whether the society should send a delegate to the Polish Convention in Detroit, Mich. or not.</p>
   <p>Dr. Koniuszewski opposed any meddling in politics but the majority of the members were of the opinion that the Polish Convention has nothing to do with politics, and that its purpose is the welfare of the Polish immigration in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0265.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>After a discussion it was agreed to send Dr. J. A. Zabrocki as a representative to the Polish Convention.</p>
   <p>The convention was held on the 26th day of August, 1918, but the Association was not benefited by sending its representative. However, the trip made by Dr. Zabrocki to the convention was not fruitless, for there he met Dr. Ruszaj of Buffalo, N. Y. and persuaded him to organize the Polish dentists in his city.</p>
   <p>Thanks to that meeting, there was organized an Association of Polish Dentists in Buffalo, N. Y.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0266.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>On the 7th of October 1918, the association of Polish Dentists in America was saddened by the death of Dr. W. Hryniewiecki a member of the organization. The loss of this member was felt very keenly by every member of the organization. Here is a part of the newspaper mention of him. At 2:30 P.M. yesterday, the remains of the well-known and high respected dentist, Dr. W. Hryniewiecki, were buried.</p>
   <p>The Polish choir "Mlode Zycie" and the Ukrainian choirs sang, during the removal of the body. The funeral was attended by a great throng of Poles and Ukrainians. The Polish Medical and Dental Associations of America and the press were very strongly represented.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0267.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>With Dr. Hryniewicki's death, went into the grave a very popular personality, with a soft heart and a noble character. He was a son of the sister-nation.</p>
   <p>Hatred was unknown to him for he knew only friendship. Therefore, his memory shall forever be with us as a symbol of true friendship and mutual understanding of the two nations.</p>
   <p>The ranks of the Polish dentists in Chicago were getting smaller on account of enlistments in the army. So far, no official of the association had been called, with the exception of Dr. J. P. Kobrzynski, who himself volunteered.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0268.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>The following lectures were given by the Polish Dental Association:</p>
   <p>By Dr. J. A. Zabrocki- Practical and efficient methods of Anesthesia.</p>
   <p>By Dr. S. S. Gorny- Pyorrhea By Dr. W. W. Nowacki- History of dentistry.</p>
   <p>By Dr. S. M. Mioduszewski.</p>
   <p>A view on Dr. W. Koniszewski's pamphlet: How to Take Care of Health. Perhaps the most interesting event during Dr. W. Nowacki's presidency, was a petition of the Association to the Polish authorities, for permission to practice dentistry in Poland by its members from the United States.</p>
   <p>The petition was based on the following reasons:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0269.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>1. The laws of the United States, guaranteeing the right to practice dentistry to those who hold a diploma from a recognized dental school.</p>
   <p>2. Some rating as medical doctors in the American Army.</p>
   <p>3. The right to use anaesthetics and prescribe medicine.</p>
   <p>4. On the very high system of instructions, equal to the level of medicine or law.</p>
   <p>5. On the regulations of the American universities demanding thirteen years of preparation, equal to a so-called certificate of maturity in Europe, from every student of dentistry.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, on the fact that the American dentistry stands very high in every respect and introduction of the American dental system in Poland would contribute greatly to the uplifting of the newly resurrected country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0270.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>The Association received the following reply from the Polish Authentic.</p>
   <p>"Department of Education and Religion Warsaw, Aug. 14, 1919</p>
   <p>To the Polish Dental Association in America 801 Milwaukee Ave. Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>We hereby acknowledge the receipt of your communication of Jan. 6th and received on Aug. 4th.</p>
   <p>The Department wishes to inform you that the matter mentioned in that communication was turned over to the Medical Dept. of the Polish Universities for their consideration.</p>
   <p>Signed</p>
   <p>A. Wrzosek</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
