<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-28">Apr. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting of the Polish Educational Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0944</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0944.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-28">Apr. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING OF THE POLISH EDUCATIONAL SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Educational Society held a mass meeting at 1223 Cornell Street on April 22. More than one hundred people attended the meeting. They listened to the speakers with attention, and, by their generous contributions to the Society and its purposes, showed the need for an institution of this type here.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened at 3 P. M. with a prayer. Because of the large number of matters of great importance to the Society that had to be decided, the meeting did not adjourn until 9: P. M. The meeting closed with the singing of the national anthem.</p>
   <p>The intense interest of our members in the matters concerning the society is truly gratifying. They reach out toward enlightenment and want to benefit by it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0945.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Some intend to return to the homeland after learning to read and write and to do some arithmetic in order that they might work the better on their native soil. Others, more enlightened, want to broaden the scope of their knowledge, taking advantage of the lectures on history, geography, and Polish literature.</p>
   <p>We have, among our members, quite a few people with higher education, which they obtained in the homeland. To these members we have entrusted the direction of our educational matters. They will sacrifice all their spare time in order to bring the light of knowledge in their native tongue to those who were deprived of schools by our enemy invaders.</p>
   <p>The majority of our members are immigrants from the homeland, who, although they speak English rather fluently, have lost the ability to speak Polish, or who speak it incorrectly.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it is the duty of the Polish Educational Society to raise their <pb facs="5423968_6_0946.jpg" n="3"/>mental level, to ennoble their hearts and souls, and to awaken the sleeping national forces.</p>
   <p>Our society is not in competition with any schools, since only adults take these courses--sometimes even people very advanced in years. Therefore all honor to those who, not knowning false embarrassment, eagerly study the primer. At a time when our homeland is about to be resurrected, they rouse themselves from their mental lethargy. He who realizes what a great meaning enlightment has for our people, can easily understand why the Polish Educational Society of America was founded. If this group of people, numbering many thousands, only possessed the art of reading and writing, our mass meetings and national celebrations would not be conducted to empty halls, and it would be much easier for the people to accept, with their hearts and souls, the earnest words uttered by the speakers. At the same time it would be easier for our leaders to warn the people against hostile foreign influence, and preserve them for Poland.</p>
   <p>Iza Poebog</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
