<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-09-14">Sept. 14, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Roman Catholic Baseball League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1145</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1145.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-09-14">Sept. 14, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC BASEBALL LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Roman Catholic Union baseball league held its meeting yesterday at the Union Hall, Augusta Street and Milwaukee Ave. Because of the excessive heat, the meeting was but a brief gathering of several minutes' duration. Next Tuesday night will see the windup of the league for the current season, and prizes will be given the winners. It is imperative that every member of the league be present to decide on a date for the banquet and dance to be held as a topper for the season's work.</p>
   <p>The Polish Roman Catholic Union baseball league dance will be an event in the younger set of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. It will be held in the Union Hall, the latter part of October. Mr. Andrew Kazmierczak, president of the Union, promised full co-operation. The event has already stirred up plenty of enthusiasm and promises a bevy of leaders of our younger set. The president of the Baseball League will send out notices as soon as the date has been decided upon. This season was the initial one for the Baseball League. It makes the coming of a busy athletic life in the ranks of the younger members of the Union.</p>
   <p>This year has been the leader in sports, and next year, it is anticipated, there will be at least ten teams. A special meeting, with this view in mind, will be called toward the end of September and heads of every Circuit in Chicago and surrounding territory will give impetus to the schedule for the coming year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
