<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-08-08">Aug. 8, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Do Not Read Papers That Are Hostile to Our Cause</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-08-08">Aug. 8, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">DO NOT READ PAPERS THAT ARE HOSTILE TO OUR CAUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We read an article with the above heading repeated in the weekly Zgoda. We would agree in advance to the thought and arguments expressed by the editors of the Zgoda, were it not for the fact that we do not agree with the interpretation of the phrase given in the article.</p>
   <p>"Do not read papers hostile to our cause" would literally mean the complete elimination of all vicious papers of which we have so many, and would mean that we should read only the few papers bravely defending all good matters--or the reverse, the elimination of all good papers, and the support of the scandalous sheets endeavoring to pervert our Catholic tenets.</p>
   <p>We are certain that the editors of the Zgoda have in mind those papers embraced in the first category above. It is mistaken in this however.</p>
   <p>The conservative papers, edited in a strictly Catholic vein, will not try <pb facs="5423968_6_0563.jpg" n="2"/>to harm you, if you agree to publish the truth. The conservative papers will not attack you, if you fight on the side of truth--if you do not cause dissension, but work for peace. That the conservative press is unable to find any of these in your paper is not their fault, but yours.</p>
   <p>We certainly agree that we must have parties--otherwise we could never arrive at the truth. The human mind is in a certain sense inexhaustible in inventing new ideas, and thus opposing ideas are necessary.</p>
   <p>The conservative papers believing in this maxim do not wage battles against individuals, but against the evil itself; their code is based on the immutable religious truths; and this, you will agree, cannot be found in your liberal-progressive papers.</p>
   <p>To ridicule an important cause with a vicious news item is really laughable, but the people are not enlightened as much by witty remarks as by a sensible answer to accusations made. There would be more good will among the Polish <pb facs="5423968_6_0564.jpg" n="3"/>newspapers in America if they would co-operate in a sincere spirit; then the reader would benefit more because he would be served good healthy reading matter, instead of poisonous outbursts.</p>
   <p>Eliminate the perverted papers and read only the good, beneficial papers. This is what we advise also.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
