<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 40,
<date when="1908-02-18">Feb. 18, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Society of Polish Physicians in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0281</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0281.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 40,
<date when="1908-02-18">Feb. 18, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIETY OF POLISH PHYSICIANS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the yearly meeting of the Society of Polish Doctors in Chicago, the election and installation of new officers took place. The new officers are: Mr. M. Stupnicki, president; Mr. Dowiat SAss, vice-president; Mr. Julius Szymanski, secretary; and Mr. A. Szwajkart, cashier.</p>
   <p>After settling all formal matters and the current affairs, the undertaking of the following questions to promote and protect the health of the public was taken up.</p>
   <p>The first question under consideration was midwives or obstetricians. The Society of Doctors is greatly opposed to, and is contemplating laws to prosecute obstetricians performing criminal operations.</p>
   <p>Another question that arises is the illegal practice of doctors claiming to be members of this Society of Physicians, calling on sick people and charging more than the society's price for a visit. The Society has issued membership cards to all its members; these are to be shown at all times to people demanding the servics of the society's doctors only. Polish people can receive, by request, a list of all doctors in Chicago who are members of the Society of Polish Physicians.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0282.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All doctors having intentions of joining the Society of Polish Doctors, must pass an examination before they are admitted, so that the bad work of impostors may be prevented.</p>
   <p>Another question that arises is whether or not the present members are in favor of buying all their medicine and equipment from one concern, or whether they would approve of continuing their buying as they have in the past. This question is up to the members to decide and give their answers and opinions at the next meeting.</p>
   <p>Committee</p>
   <p>Society of Polish Doctors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
