<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 49,
<date when="1900-12-06">Dec. 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">About the Monument</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 49,
<date when="1900-12-06">Dec. 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE MONUMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lord be praised!</p>
   <p>The committee in charge of the Kosciuszko monument has at last answered the article of criticism in last week's edition of the Zgoda. Now we can relieve the worried thoughts of our Polish contributors who have been kept in suspense regarding the funds collected, how much progress has been made in bringing this great undertaking to reality and how soon will it be completed. The more we criticize the committee the better results we will get. Let's continue this idea.</p>
   <p>Above all we must remind the committee of their duties and obligations and what they are doing in fulfilling them. The committee should stop and consider these vital words: Words about the committee's neglected duties were first brought up two years ago by the Zgoda, then by the Telegraph, then the Polish Courier, and now the Zgoda again. Beside these, other newspapers, the Polish Daily News, America, and many others have printed articles in regard to this question. Do all the papers have a right to comment on this question? Even if it is allowed, they should admit whether they are only trying to get some action from the central committee, or whether they are awaiting an answer in regard to what the money is being spent for. These <pb facs="5423968_6_1291.jpg" n="2"/>papers claim that their efforts are only in behalf of the people that have donated money for the building of this monument.</p>
   <p>We admit at the present time that the central committee's feelings are hurt by the slandering and criticizing articles of these papers. They are greatly opposed to people writing articles to the newspapers saying that the central committee uses the money as they see fit, whether it is for their own personal use or for the monument. The committee claims this is a lie, because they are fulfilling their offices to the best of their abilities.</p>
   <p>Did the committee finally stand up for their rights after a quiet spell of two years? Then the articles did stir up some action as the Polish Courier claims. Heavens and earth had to be moved before an answer could be received from the central committee. The committee could have given a report every four or six months to the public, and thus avoid all this embarrassment and comment for their neglected duties.</p>
   <p>We know that the model will be made in Crakow and shipped to America where it will be poured and finished. Wouldn't it have been better to wait and consider this problem before sending the signed contract to Crakow? We judge that a savings of a few thousands dollars would have resulted.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1292.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The same can be said about the members of the central committee. Have new members chosen to replace those that have neglected their oath of office and those that have lost interest in this great undertaking. The committee said that they will think this matter over, but we said that it would have saved time and trouble if this had been done at the beginning.</p>
   <p>The committee can see that we are earnest about our insinuations. This is not a joking matter. We say openly that as soon as we notice that the committee is awake and is working energetically, we will send volunteers to help bring to a close this Polish dream of the Kosciuszko monument.</p>
   <p>These volunteers will collect money from people that have given parties and affairs to raise funds for this monument but have not as yet turned the money over to the committee. This will then be kept on record, so a report can be given whenever one is necessary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
