<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-05">Feb. 5, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Educational Department of the Polish League Announces its First Literary Contest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-05">Feb. 5, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATIONAL DEPARTMENT OF THE POLISH LEAGUE ANNOUNCES ITS FIRST LITERARY CONTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the aims of the Educational Department of the Polish League was the awakening of the intellectual minds among the Poles of America by means of literary contests. Rules and information regarding these contests will be announced in the Polish press.</p>
   <p>Even before material means and wider public support permit us to undertake work of more importance in this field, we are, at any rate, in a position to make the initial step, although it is but a feeble one.</p>
   <p>An announcement has been made of the first literary contest, which is a contest that is primarily aimed at Polish-American youth. Its character is not so much literary as it is pedagogical. After careful consideration of the type of contest to be initiated, it was concluded that it should be of this <pb facs="5423968_6_0091.jpg" n="2"/>nature. After all, our future depends on our youth--since youth is exposed the most to strange influences, that is where the most dangers lie. This is why the Educational Department desires to expend most of its effort for this youth; this is why the first contest is open to it.</p>
   <p>This contest is a simple one. Not much is expected in the beginning from the contestants, and large prizes will not be awarded. All beginnings are difficult and small. It is hoped that God will let this beginning gradually spread out until its results are worth while.</p>
   <p>The aims and conditions of this contest are as follows:</p>
   <p>The aim is to stimulate the Polish youth toward intellectual work, toward thinking, toward proper Polish writing, toward the presentation of problems that <pb facs="5423968_6_0092.jpg" n="3"/>confront them, and finally toward nationalistic feeling.</p>
   <p>The object of the first contest for our Polish youth is the writing of an article in journalistic style, on the following theme: "What are the duties of Polish youth in America?"</p>
   <p>The article should not be longer than two and one-half columns of print in Dziennik Chicagoski, or three hundred lines of small print. It can be smaller, depending wholly upon the writer.</p>
   <p>The whole Polish youth of America up to the age of 24 is qualified to enter. Manuscript material should be addressed to Mr. I. Kowalski, Secretary of the Educational Department, 141-143 West Division Street, Chicago, Illinois, not later than March 20, 1895; that is, the postmark on the envelope should not be of a later date. All material sent in should not bear the contestant's <pb facs="5423968_6_0093.jpg" n="4"/>name, but rather a number or a pseudonym; however, a smaller envelope bearing the author's name, address and age should be included with the manuscript.</p>
   <p>Of the envelopes containing the names, only those of the winners will be opened by the judges; the remainder will be discarded.</p>
   <p>The contest will be decided by a committee of the Educational Department. The winners will be announced from ten to twenty days after the date of the close of the contest.</p>
   <p>Book awards will go to the best three manuscripts, namely:</p>
   <p>The author of the best work will receive a special publication of Dziel Adama Mickiewicza (Works of Adam Mickiewicz), in four volumes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0094.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>A beautiful edition of Dziel Chodzki (Works of Chodzki), in three volumes, will go to the second-place winner.</p>
   <p>A beautifully bound and illustrated edition of Zywoty Swietych (Lives of the Saints) will be awarded as third prize.</p>
   <p>The Educational Department realizes that the beautiful book prizes, worthy of addition to any Polish library, is especially for youth, and feels that they will be of more value than money.</p>
   <p>Besides these awards, the contest judges, in case of necessity, will give several honorable mentions. The right to restrict the number of prizes is reserved if the number of entries is inadequate.</p>
   <p>All the prize-winning works will be published separately in Dziennik Chicagoski after the decision of the contest judges has been announced. Arrangements <pb facs="5423968_6_0095.jpg" n="6"/>for this have already been made with the editors. The winning manuscripts will be reproduced in part or in whole.</p>
   <p>These are the stipulations of the contest. The Polish youth of America is cordially invited to enter. The theme of the required work is not difficult. He who knows why he is living, what he is required to cherish, what he sincerely desires, will be the one to find it simple to express from his heart in simple Polish words the duties of Polish youth in America. It is not necessary to resort to flowery or artificial expressions.</p>
   <p>Once more the Polish youth of America is invited to enter this truly worthy contest.</p>
   <p>This is the first of a series of contests to be conducted. Perhaps in the future the public will permit us to call out our brothers of the pen for <pb facs="5423968_6_0096.jpg" n="7"/>bigger and more important fields of competition. In the meantime we hope that the public will bear in mind that although this is only a small beginning it has the common good of all our compatriots in mind.</p>
   <p>Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek, C. R.,president</p>
   <p>I. Kowalski, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
