<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-06">Mar. 6, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Can the Money Collected for the Kosciusko Monument Be Used for Any Other Purpose?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1352</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1352.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-06">Mar. 6, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">CAN THE MONEY COLLECTED FOR THE KOSCIUSKO MONUMENT BE USED FOR ANY OTHER PURPOSE?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To this question, asked of our paper by one of our readers, we can give only one answer--no! "Why not?" You ask. "Surely, we could find other causes more pressing and more important. Why even our papers, the Kuryer Polski (Polish Courier), of Milwaukee, and the Gornik (Miner), of Wilkesbarre, have advocated using this money for educational purposes or for the establishment of a teachers' seminary. Are not these causes worthy of support?"</p>
   <p>They are. They deserve full-hearted support. Nevertheless, we must not, and legally we cannot use the funds collected for the Kosciusko Monument for any other purpose.</p>
   <p>There are a few potent reasons.</p>
   <p>First of all, a monument in honor of Thaddeus Kosciusko is necessary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1353.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It cannot be considered in the sense of a luxury.....The hundred thousand Poles in Chicago, the one and a half million Poles in America, are surely sufficiently well-to-do to be able to erect on this continent a monument to honor him who is a visible tie between us and America. Furthermore, we have monuments here of other famous persons, erected by the Germans and the Swedes, the Italians and the Dutch. From a practical view point, can we afford to lag behind them?</p>
   <p>The second reason is a purely legal matter. The Committee appointed to build the monument was officially incorporated in Springfield for the purpose of gathering funds to erect a monument, and for no other purpose. What would be the legal position of every member of the Committee in respect to the State authorities and to all of the contributors, if they should use the money for any other purpose, no matter how honorable? They would be personally and financially responsible for the entire amount gathered for the monument. They would be outside the law, for they legally cannot change the purpose for which the funds were gathered; namely, for the <pb facs="5423968_6_1354.jpg" n="3"/>erection of the monument. They can only release themselves from this obligation by securing from every contributor, no matter how small may have been his contribution, written permission to change the purpose of his contribution. This is impossible because many of the contributors are already dead.</p>
   <p>The third reason deals with a moral problem. It concerns a very common trait of uncertainty and lack of purpose in our make-up. It has been repeated a thousand times that we easily become inflamed but still more easily lose our fire. We attempt everything--and never finish anything. When we grow tired of working toward one goal, then we at once make the easiest and simplest excuse: that there are other goals, much closer and more important, for which the first goal should be abandoned. It is a habit of mind quite demoralizing to our social structure; a maneuver that is dangerous and tends to harm everything. Nothing can ever be accomplished in this manner because, in the same way in which we discard one activity for another, just so will we discard that for a third, and so on.....</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1355.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We, therefore, from the moral-social viewpoint, condemn this proposal to change the purpose of the funds gathered for the Kosciusko Monument.</p>
   <p>Instead of giving up, let us finish the matter as soon as possible. Contribute offerings; do not stop; let us not create a spirit of unmerited lack of confidence in the Monument Committee; let us not divert their attention from this, by calling attention to some other matter. Then the monument will be erected, and it will not take long....Then we will have time enough to bring to the attention of our Polish public dozens of other important and necessary activities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
