<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-05-27">May 27, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Policemen's Club Makes its Donation to the Kosciusko Memorial Fund</title><title level="a" type="sub">Total Profit from Policemen's Ball $1,019.20</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1398</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1398.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-05-27">May 27, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLICEMEN'S CLUB MAKES ITS DONATION TO THE KOSCIUSKO MEMORIAL FUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Total Profit from Policemen's Ball $1,019.20</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The solemn presentation of the donation of the Chicago Polish Policemen's Club to the Kosciusko Memorial Fund was made yesterday at A. J. Kowalski's Hall on Noble Street.</p>
   <p>The Policemen's Club has been renamed the Kosciusko Club. Besides its representatives, there were also present [the following] members of the Fund Committee: E. Z. Brodowski, P. Stensland, Dr. Charles Midowicz, L. Szopinski, M. Drzemala, and John F. Smulski. Others present were Peter Kiolbassa and representatives of the press.</p>
   <p>The president of the Kosciusko Club, Joseph Polczynski, opened the meeting with a few words as to its purpose. He was followed by Mr. Kroll, the treasurer, who delivered a financial report, showing that the clear profit from <pb facs="5423968_6_1399.jpg" n="2"/>the Policemen's Ball was $1,019.20 He presented a check for this sum to Mr. Brodowski, president of the Kosciusko memorial Commission.</p>
   <p>Mr. Brodowski addressed the meeting in English. He sincerely thanked the policemen and their friends for the untiring efforts that had brought such wonderful results. He said that our Policemen have proved themselves real Poles and citizens. At the close of his speech, Mr. Brodowski handed the money to the Fund's treasurer, Mr. Stensland.</p>
   <p>Mr. Polczynski spoke again, thanking all Poles for their generous support of the Club's enterprise. He was followed by Mr. Peter Kiolbassa. The honorable speaker declared that the Kosciusko monument will be a source of pride to Chicago Poles, and especially to those who have helped to realize it, the Polish policemen of Chicago. In 1866, Mr. Kiolbassa was himself the first and only Polish policemen in Chicago. Today, Chicago has about forty-five Polish policemen. They have really earned acknowledgment for their noble work; they <pb facs="5423968_6_1400.jpg" n="3"/>have proved that they rank amongst the best of Chicago's Polish citizens.</p>
   <p>Attorney [H.] Drzemala and Mr. Stensland spoke in English, and Dr. Midowicz delivered a short address in Polish. As secretary of the Fund Committee, he offered the sincerest thanks to the policemen. He said that their contribution was made possible by Polish hearts beating beneath American uniforms. He expressed the hope that the Polish policemen will continue in their work for the Fund, and that the monument will be unveiled at the one hundredth anniversary of the battle of Raclawice. The doctor closed his address with a whole-hearted "God reward you".</p>
   <p>The following is a statement of income and expense of the ball:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Income from tickets</cell>
     <cell>$873.35</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Income from the ball</cell>
     <cell>524.85</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$1398.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses</cell>
     <cell>379.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$1019.10</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1401.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The expenses included rent of the hall, orchestra, printing, liquor and soft drinks, etc.</p>
   <p>That the policemen worked zealously at selling tickets is proved by the fact that the sale of tickets was the largest source of income. Some of the policemen brought in large sums of money, as for instance, Korzeniowski, $107.10; A. Schultz, 92.70; L. Kroll, $85.00.....</p>
   <p>After the official acceptance of the money by the Fund Committee, the meeting was turned into an informal gathering. Mr. Kiolbassa recalled his experiences from the time when he was the only Polish policeman in Chicago; Mr. John Smulski called the Polish policemen "stars of Polonia". He said that he wished every one of them would soon be a sergeant, a lieutenant, or perhaps even a captain on the police force. Finally, Dr. Midowicz suggested the idea of arranging a "fair" for the benefit of the Kosciusko Memorial Fund. It was received with great enthusiasm. All those present promised their full support, and a committee was organized immediately, consisting of Peter Kiolbassa, M. Drzemala, H. Nagiel, L. Kroll, and A. J. Kowalski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
