<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXII, No. 46,
<date when="1918-11-13">Nov. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Meaning of Knowledge</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXII, No. 46,
<date when="1918-11-13">Nov. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE MEANING OF KNOWLEDGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An eminent Polish writer, Boleslaw Prus, now dead, wrote in his chronicles among others as follows:</p>
   <p>"A person who cannot read or write can only make himself understandable with other people by means of speech, only with a few persons constituting his closest environment.</p>
   <p>"Parents, wife, neighbors, companions at work or in the tavern, usually knowing no more than he, from whom he completes his scant experience, and to them he turns for advice.</p>
   <p>"And what does he find? One understands the other: either ignorance similar to his own or prejudices.</p>
   <p>"Meanwhile a person knowing how to read, if naturally he has close by a small library comprehensible to himself, can at once enter into intercourse with the most vigorous minds of the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0139.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"It is not some old woman who will give him advice in a casual moment of infirmity, but a book on hygiene written by an educated physician. No ignorant neighbor will give him pointers on the breeding of animals, the raising of farm vegetables, but an educated farmer. No old man, begging near a church, will explain to him on what depends the eclipse of the moon or which is the morning or evening star, but this will be done by an astronomer, with the help of a clear description of phenomena occuring in the heavens.</p>
   <p>"In a word, if speech binds us to several people alive and residing alongside of us, then the art of reading is a bridge between hundreds of the wisest and best people, without regard as to where they reside or when they live.</p>
   <p>"An ignoramus in the cares and struggles of life has for his allies a few such as himself, wretches and ignorant fellows. But knowing how to read he will find a whole army of first-class minds in the library, which is waiting to serve him with advice, enlightenment, even with new descriptions of phenomena unknown to him.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0140.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"An ignoramus is a mental wretch. Knowing how to read one is wealthy. Always only under the condition that he finds close by a library composed of books equally suited to his needs and to his comprehension.</p>
   <p>"Where the most ignorant one only sees the world that lies before his eyes, the one knowing how to read, not moving from the spot, can see the whole earthly globe as it is today and as it was ages ago."</p>
   <p>So wrote a man enlightened and wise. From the above we see what great stress Boleslaw Prus placed on the meaning of libraries, and we, members of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, even though we have our own library, rarely benefit from it. We do not care to read; we prefer to be ignorant and unfamiliar with the works of great persons. Let us learn how to read and let us read. Especially you, mothers, prepare your children for reading, so they would not remain ignoramuses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
