<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-20">Apr. 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Dental Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0271</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0271.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-20">Apr. 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DENTAL SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Dental Society of America, incorporated in the State of Illinois in May, 1908--at which time its membership included five Polish dentists from Chicago: Dr. W. A. Nowacki, Dr. W. A. Gorny, Dr. P. T. Wybraniec, Dr. W. L. Rybsztat, and Dr. J. B. Zielinski--and which was discontinued several years ago for lack of new members, has come back to life again. In 1917 Dr. W. Koniuszewski, unaware of the existence of the old society, set out to organize a society of Polish Dentists in Chicago. Among other things, the new society plans to conduct a campaign to teach the Poles the importance of oral hygiene.</p>
   <p>These efforts have met with success. The Polish Dental Society of America has been organized again, has accepted the charter of 1908 as its own, and has elected new officers.</p>
   <p>The society's purpose is to improve its members' professional education so that they may better serve and advise their patients and contribute their share <pb facs="5423968_6_0272.jpg" n="2"/>toward preserving the health of the Polish people by educating them in oral hygiene.</p>
   <p>The Polish Dental Society will co-operate with the Polish Medical Society, on the principle that dentistry is a branch of medicine and that close co-operation of the two professions is essential.</p>
   <p>The formality of accepting the constitution--which is based on the constitution of the Chicago Dental Society--as well as the election of officers, etc., was accomplished at the society's second meeting, held on April 15 at the Polish Women's Alliance Building.</p>
   <p>The officers of the society are Dr. W. Koniuszewski, 801 Milwaukee Avenue, president; Dr. T. Maturzynska, vice-president; Dr. E. G. Urbanowicz, 4650 S. Ashland Avenue, secretary; Dr. J. Marcinkiewicz, treasurer; and Dr. W. Nowacki, librarian.</p>
   <p>Because not all the Polish dentists of Chicago attended these meetings, and <pb facs="5423968_6_0273.jpg" n="3"/>because the names of Polish dentists outside Chicago could not be obtained, a special appeal will be published in the next few days.</p>
   <p>Dr. E. G. Urbanowicz, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
