<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IX, No. 20,
<date when="1905-05-17">May 17, 1905</date><title level="a">Literary Circle in Holy Trinity Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IX, No. 20,
<date when="1905-05-17">May 17, 1905</date><title level="a">LITERARY CIRCLE IN HOLY TRINITY PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For some time the young people of the Holy Trinity Parish have been going ahead quickly and organizing themselves into a Literary Circle, they have been giving readings, held patriotic gatherings and educational lectures, educating themselves in singing and music. They are working for their own good in one word, they wish to reach the pinnacle of general knowledge. Our young people have already manifested to the Polish public that in their hearts lies the love for that which is beautiful and noble -- love for their native country.</p>
   <p>The movement dates back to some time ago, thanks to the untiring efforts of the Literary Circle, which during its existence has done a lot of good for our youth and our social life, mainly: broadening the knowledge among our young generation, giving out readings, elevating the moral development of our youth, and instilling into their hearts good, healthy, Catholic and patriotic principles. Further it has awakened our youth to noble deeds to work in the field of knowledge, and to give it a wider and suitable field for action, for developing their mental faculties.</p>
   <p>The proof of this is forty-five first-class appearances in public, carried out with great success and with the participation of a well selected public.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0043.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Polish youth in the Holy Trinity Parish should join the Literary Circle, because it has here a wide and accessible field for action, a good moral foundation, and the possibility to learn to appreciate everything that is good, useful and noble.</p>
   <p>Here the youth educates itself in spirit and tradition of their father land, and gives itself to a more pleasant and noble form of entertainment. To this circle belongs the youth of both sexes -- the youth of the most horable Polish families in the Holy Trinity Parish, educating themselves and working for their own good and for the good of the Polish social life. The meetings will take place every third Monday of the month.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
