<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1908-04-08">April 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Sports and Benefits Derived There-From</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1177</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1177.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy-Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1908-04-08">April 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">SPORTS AND BENEFITS DERIVED THERE-FROM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Occasionally one will meet with opinions, such as, "Our people cannot become very active in sports because they are too poor." It is true, that a person with money is in better position to give more of his time to sports than one who is handicapped by the lack of it. On the other hand isn't our poverty a direct result of the lack of interest in sports and the fun, the fresh air, sunshine and good health attained through participation in them?</p>
   <p>Good health and a well developed body, enable us to face more squarely the battle of everyday life. Sports, athletics and all physical training and exercise in the open, not overdone, will develop both mind and body. Fatigue and hardship, energy, strength and will power, and even some of the dangers involved, develop in one, confidence and alertness. Sports also develop our ability to cooperate, to be obedient, to work conscientiously and to practice self-control. A young man, who is faced with the problem of a career, is not very easily discouraged, if he has had any athletic training. He knows his strength, and his ability, to think clearly. He proceeds cautiously, but with determination. Obstacles and hard work do not frighten him. He knows his goal and is determined to reach it. He knows that in order to win, he must fight. And in victory he will find satisfaction.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1178.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At this time our system is not interested in this form of education. We implore the children to study hard. We are struggling and trying to earn enough to give our children an education. We seem to forget, however, that we possess a soul, and that our bodies are made of flesh; therefore we completely forget the necessity of physical training and education. The result is a weaker generation, weak minds and little energy, weak bodies, which are incapable of hard work; unfit, both mentally and physically.</p>
   <p>People so incapacitated live a life of misery. In all industry, men are forging ahead with all their strength. Because of our weakness, industry and business lies idly before us. The workaday world demands only the physically and mentally fit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
