<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Ten Years of Service for the Cause and for Poland</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TEN YEARS OF SERVICE FOR THE CAUSE AND FOR POLAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten years of existence on foreign soil is no mean accomplishment for a Polish daily newspaper. Even in Poland, few daily papers, though supported some times by strong political parties, have been able to exist so long. But perhaps because Dziennik Zwiazkowy has served no party in particular, serving only the Polish cause in its purest sense, or because it has never foresworn its watchwords, following steadily the path laid out by its organizers, it has been able not only to hold its own but also to grow; and considering the years of its existence and the costs of publishing, it is now the richest Polish daily newspaper not only in America but in the whole world.</p>
   <p>The political viewpoint of Dziennik Zwiazkowy is completely in accord with that of the Polish National Alliance. Just as the Alliance itself never <pb facs="5423968_6_0374.jpg" n="2"/>has been and is not a party but an organization for people of any viewpoint, desiring to serve Poland and her cause by unifying the societies here, so has Dziennik Zwiazkowy served these same ideals which had as their goal the good of all the Polish people, rather than of certain groups. Of course, it is understood that with the passing years and with the change of political conditions, that good may have often been seen in trends which at first seemed purely of a national character, but which subsequently changed. In such cases Dziennik Zwiazkowy always withdrew immediately from the surroundings in which it found itself, rid itself of the people who had caused it to deviate from its ideals, and, taking its stand for the nation as a whole rather than for some individual group, it continued its work--in the words of Lincoln--"of the people, by the people, and for the people."</p>
   <p>So it was during those memorable years when undercurrents in Poland indicated the necessity of raising a certain armed force. Those were years when diplomatic relations between Austria and Russia were strained to the <pb facs="5423968_6_0375.jpg" n="3"/>breaking point; it seemed that the annexation of Bosnia and Herzegovina by Austria-Hungary must lead to war with Russia. At that time, there was a possibility that the war might be confined to a struggle between these two nations, for if Germany did not intervene no other country would take up arms. In Poland, therefore, it could clearly be seen that the entire Polish nation ought to support Austria in such a war, and in this way rid itself of at least one conqueror and unite at least in part. On the basis of this supposition which, as a matter of fact, subsequent events proved false, there arose in Poland and among the Poles in America a cry for armed action.</p>
   <p>It was at this time that the Falcon fighting units and riflemen, secret military societies, were organized in Galicia and in the Kingdom [Russian Poland]. Everyone wished to participate in this war not only in spirit but actively also. This feeling reached the Poles in America too, and so the Komitet Obrony Narodowej [Committee for National Defense] was organized. Its aim was to support armed action in Poland in every way possible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0376.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Since this was the political tendency in Poland, Dziennik Zwiazkowy not only supported it but tried even to spread the idea among the masses of Polish people in the United States, so as to broaden it and to give it a foundation. Thus, Dziennik Zwiazkowy faithfully supported the K. O. N. until events began to take on a different form than the accepted political viewpoint seemed to indicate. When the Galician Naczelny Komitet Narodowy [National Committee] and its American exponent, K. O. N., took on a partisan aspect and ceased to represent the entire nation, Dziennik Zwiazkowy stopped supporting it. And, when the European war broke out, these organizations alligned themselves unrestrictedly with Austria and even Prussia, so this newspaper opposed them.</p>
   <p>From that point on Dziennik Zwiazkowy has not changed its position, but has struggled against all those who have tried to force views other than those strictly Polish upon the Poles in America. With the help of other newspapers it scored a singular victory, helping to organize the Poles in America into a strong national unit, out of which emerged the Wyozial Narodowy [National <pb facs="5423968_6_0377.jpg" n="5"/>Department] as the chief representative of the Poles in America. Dziennik Zwiazkowy was also powerfully instrumental in organizing the Polish Army and in carrying relief to the innocent war victims in Poland. In advocating a purely Polish position to the masses of its readers, it established through them a conviction that Poland is self-sufficient, that it needs no foreign protectors, that is must be free, independent, and united, and that it must have an outlet to the sea. The political program of the entire Polish element was finally established on these principles; for such is the only program that can and must be followed by the Polish nation in Europe.</p>
   <p>To the Polish National Alliance, Dziennik Zwiazkowy became not only the official organ, not only a defender and champion of the first rank, but it also became the greatest propagator of its watchwords and its tendencies. In the course of ten years, it has brought the Alliance tens of thousands of members; while among the members of the Alliance, it has increased and encouraged the desire for knowledge and reading. It has influenced the <pb facs="5423968_6_0378.jpg" n="6"/>masses outside the Alliance to a similar degree; for though not members of the Alliance, they learn to love and to serve Poland through Dziennik Zwiazkowy. In this respect, then, the services of Dziennik Zwiazkowy as an educator, as a source of information, and as a director of public opinion have been invaluable.</p>
   <p>The best evidence of Dziennik Zwiazkowy's growth during the past ten years is its paid circulation of 50,000. It has over 200,000 readers. It is, therefore, the most widely read Polish daily paper in America, and at the present moment is the greatest Polish daily paper in the world; for while there were in pre-war Poland newspapers that had circulations larger than ours and even, as with Gazeta Grudziacka (Grudziadz Gazette), twice as large, they still were not as widespread as Dziennik Zwiazkowy, nor could they compete with it as far as publishing costs are concerned.</p>
   <p>Dziennik Zwiazkowy is also the only Polish paper in America that maintains permanent correspondents in Europe, thanks to whom it has been able to <pb facs="5423968_6_0379.jpg" n="7"/>keep the Poles here in touch with Poland in spite of the war that is raging in Europe; all of the other Polish papers in America have profited by this. By developing and improving from year to year, Dziennik Zwiazkowy has had a beneficial effect on the standards of Polish journalism in America, for the other newspapers strive to equal it at least for purposes of competition.</p>
   <p>Honor and recognition are due to those who created Dziennik Zwiazkowy and to those who helped to develop it. Today, after ten years, Dziennik Zwiazkowy is an institution so strong that it is not only existing and developing by its own strength, but, in addition, it shows substantial profits at the end of each year. These will help it maintain itself in the future, even when the Polish element here begins a general exodus to a free Poland, leaving only the younger generations which have already become a part of American society. Among the latter Dziennik Zwiazkowy will keep awake the Polish spirit, it will serve as an educator and as their connection with the land of their forefathers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
