<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-09-15">Sept. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Notice to the Commanders of the Polish Falcons of America on Military Laws</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-09-15">Sept. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">NOTICE TO THE COMMANDERS OF THE POLISH FALCONS OF AMERICA ON MILITARY LAWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to section 241 of the Military Laws, if the body of men calling themselves the Polish Falcons of America constitutes an independent military organization which was in existence on the 23rd, day of April, 1883, it is now lawful for them to associate themselves together as a military company or organization; they may also parade in public with firearms. On the other hand, if they are merely incorporated under membership corporate laws for purely athletic purpose, they are not considered under the military laws as a military company, nor have they the right to parade in public with firearms.</p>
   <p>Section 1484 of the Penal Laws of this states provides as follows: Any person wearing any uniform or designation of rank similar to those in use by the National Guard, issued or authorized under the provisions of the said law, is guilty of a misdemeanor.</p>
   <p>The above statute should be posted on the bulletin board in all the Polish Falcon meeting halls. The statute will bear out the legality of conducting <pb facs="5423968_6_1168.jpg" n="2"/>uniformed parades and marches which were attacked by some as illegal military meetings and at times looked upon as a clandestine preparation to overthrow the government. However, they forget that the Polish Falcons were organized as an athletic organization, and not a military one. In years that went by it was upon the suggestion of the United States Army that they adopted some of the National Guard tactics and military exercises and training. It is well to remember that the Polish Falcons, as a military unit, in any emergency are subject to be called to military service for the protection of this country.</p>
   <p>Therefore it would be advisable to invite foreign groups, and particularly the Anglo-Saxons to attend sessions and meetings and convince themselves that the wrecking of the organizations of Polish Falcons, which the chauvinists are comtemplating, would be a greater loss than any gain the latter may conceive.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
