<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-09">Jan. 9, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Our Contest</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Continuation from January 8, 1892, issue is missing)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0746</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0746.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-09">Jan. 9, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CONTEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Continuation from January 8, 1892, issue is missing)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every author, if he so desires, may have his name kept a secret until the contest is over, providing he places his name in a separate envelope with the same number, or pseudonym, that appears on the article. These envelopes will be opened after the judges' decisions have been reached.</p>
   <p>The "jury" is not going to consider the length of the article as much as the contents. The manuscripts that are going to be sent in will be judged for timeliness and accuracy. Items falling into the following categories will be accepted for consideration: value to our society, building of new hope for our immigrants, and for our people abroad. Interesting poems, verses, and short stories will be next in line for consideration. Following this, will be articles about happenings, travel, holiday celebration, and society news. Articles from other newspapers and magazines will not be considered.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0747.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A word about the selection of the judges who are to pick out the various material for acceptance and merit. It is customary before a literary contest is launched to select authorities from the various fields of literature to act as judges. These members of the "jury" cannot take part in the competition, which is readily understood. If we were to follow this example, and if we were to select judges for this "jury" from the noted Polish-American novelists, teachers of literature, poets, feature writers, and editors, of which there are not many, we would have to exclude those from whom we are especially anticipating contributions. In this respect, we would be endangering our purpose rather than bettering it.</p>
   <p>We must resort to other means in choosing a "jury" of this kind. The "Dziennik Chicagoski" has definite aims to reach. It has a bright outlook on the betterment of our people. Certain steps are going to be taken to better these goals. We support such noble ideas becuase we feel that we are a part of them. We fight for them and keep the doors open for improvement. The Polish Publication Association also lends a hand in this direction.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0748.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This organization is partly comprised of educated men, i.e., university trained, partly of outstanding personages, and finally those of true patriotic citizenship of this country, who probably do not possess great literary ability, but are true Poles who possess common sense. Towards this source, the editors of this paper turn for its judges to determine the value of the manuscripts sent for the contest. Those will be excluded from this group that desire to enter this field of competition. Those writers who wish to compete, and also express a desire to be on the judges staff will be considered on the condition that they relinquish the right of accepting the prize money in case one of their articles is chosen.</p>
   <p>No work will be accepted before the fifteenth of this month, or after the same date in November. If within this specified time, less than thirty six manuscripts are received for this contest, then the time limit will be extended on official notice. This extra time will be allowed until the required number shall be reached.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0749.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This contest is held primarily for our "American Knights" of the pen to stimulate interest in the literary field. We do not want the prospective contestants to believe that the awards are going to be lucrative, nor do we want them to think that they are going to get world-wide recognition. We do not wish the prize money to be the primary bait. We do believe that the principal incentive will be the love for our people, to serve them, if only through the means of the pen which, as a result, may serve as a stimulus to awaken them from their dormant stage.</p>
   <p>Secondly, we do hope that the prize money will awaken the writers to do some outstanding work. These awards are going to be presented just before the Christmas holidays. What could be better than a prize for literary effort at Christmas time? Those that have a regular income from this particular branch have an opportunity to earn some extra money. We are going to make an effort to use the future work of the winners, and from time to time publish their work on a larger scale. Also, we will try to find an outlet for them in other papers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
