<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-04">Dec. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to Our Countrymen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1242</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1242.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-04">Dec. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO OUR COUNTRYMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Dear sisters and brothers:</p>
   <p>"As you no doubt have already learned from the papers the Poles in Avendale, under the auspices of the Avendale Civic Club and the Falcons, have succeeded in obtaining a Polish name for the park now being constructed between North Avers, Schubert, Harding, and Diversey Streets. This park has received the name of Thaddeus Kosciusko. In spite of the fact that this park will be supported primarily by taxes paid by citizens of Polish ancestry, a minority group of people of other nationalities wanted to give it some other name--any name, as long as it was not Polish. Thanks to the solidarity of the Poles and to the support of a majority of the park commissioners, they were unsuccessful and the park received a Polish name.</p>
   <p>"The need arose for the construction of a building on this ten-acre park plot. After they lost one fight, the enemies of the Poles concentrated all <pb facs="5423968_6_1243.jpg" n="2"/>their efforts in order to prevent the construction of this building. They said, "The Poles do not need it." They wanted to leave us a vacant field and protested against the erection of a building to the governor of the state, though the funds were to be raised by numerous Polish clubs.</p>
   <p>"Nevertheless we have succeeded--the building is under construction and on Sunday December 13, through the efforts of the Polish Civic Club, the laying of the corner stone will take place. This building will include free halls for meetings and national celebrations, and most important, it will have a large gymnasium for the children, as well as a library, baths, etc. At present our children, unfortunately, must gather in halls next to saloons, because they have no other place.</p>
   <p>"Therefore we appeal to the groups of the Polish National Alliance, the groups of the Roman Catholic Union, the Society of Poles in America, the Polish Women's Alliance, the Falcons, the Singers, the Young People's Alliance, <pb facs="5423968_6_1244.jpg" n="3"/>the Alliance of Polish Military Societies, the Young People's Confederation, and the Scouts--all societies in general--to take part in the parade on December 13. We want to show strangers by our numbers that we know how to honor the memory of our heroes.</p>
   <p>"The societies which wish to take part in the parade are asked kindly to inform the parade marshall, A. J. Plocinski, 2907 North Ridgeway Avenue, in advance. The details of the program and the meeting place will be announced in the papers next week.</p>
   <p>"We must emphasize here that we were unable to issue this invitation to the Poles earlier, for the reason that the prospects of building the pavilion were uncertain, because of the subversive activities of other nationalities and their attorneys.</p>
   <p>"Believing that you compatriots will not deny us your participation, we remain</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1245.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>"M. Koterski, A. Plocinski, F. T. Wolowski,</p>
   <p>T. Skorupa, A. Meyer, F. Grabowski,</p>
   <p>M. Brod, S. Milewski, J. P. Koskiewicz.</p>
   <p>"Members of the Committee"</p>
   <p>The last issue of the local American weekly The Northwestern News stated that fourteen clubs are going to try to obtain a court injunction to stop the construction of the pavilion at Kosciusko Park. They have already,through their attorneys, appealed to Governor Dunne, and this matter is to come up at the next session in Springfield. The entire paper reeks of hakatism [Translator's note; A Prussian society inimical to the Poles called H. K..T. from the initials of its founders: Hanseman, Kenneman, and Tiedeman. Its purpose was systematically to destroy the Polish element in the Duchy of Poznan by purchasing land from the Poles, confiscating estates, etc.] However, before <pb facs="5423968_6_1246.jpg" n="5"/>this matter reaches the courts the pavilion will already be up and roofed. The work is going ahead at full speed--regardless of the weather. Just as in the case of the name of the park, our enemies will not succeed.</p>
   <p>According to the agreement, the contractors are to have all the work completed by May 3, 1915, the anniversary of the announcement of the constitution in Poland. We should add here that the masonry work is being done by the contractor J. Reczynski, and the iron work by Graczykoweki of Holy Trinity Parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
