<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-20">Sept. 20, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Zgoda under the Editorship of F. Jablonski</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0640</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0640.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-20">Sept. 20, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">ZGODA UNDER THE EDITORSHIP OF F. JABLONSKI</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have just received F. Jablonski's first issue of Zgoda [official organ of the Polish National Alliance]. Its change for the better, which, as a matter of fact, we foresaw, is striking.</p>
   <p>Zgoda now appears in a new form; it contains much more general news and its language and style are as different from that used by Nicki as heaven is from earth. Mr.Jablonski modestly admits that the first few issues will not be of "great literary value". In truth, errors can be found in this first issue, but the literary Value". In truth, errors can be found in this first issue, but the general level of Zgoda has been raised immeasurably. It is now characterized by peaceableness and moderation; the trouble-making and scandalous articles so common under the former editor have disappeared.</p>
   <p>In an introductory article, Mr. Jablonski expresses his views with dignity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0641.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He states that he wishes to direct the paper honestly and patriotically, in the fullest sense of the words, that he will try to conduct the Alliance's organ in such a way that it will serve to some extent as a school for those who had no educational opportunities in their youth. He asserts that he will make no attempts to discredit any Polish organization, for "their existence is justified by the very fact that they exist; they all tend, in their various ways, toward one goal--the resurrection of Poland." Although he promises to champion the workingmen's cause, he will, at the same time, warn the workers against trouble-makers. Finally, he writes as follows:</p>
   <p>"I will be a party to no quarrels, and if I am forced to conduct polemics in defense of my organization, I will do so with dignity, never exceeding the bounds of decency. Furthermore, I will take care to avoid personal matters; my pen shall never spread scandal. I hope to create, not to destroy."</p>
   <p>We willingly admit that his intentions are very good and that this policy is <pb facs="5423968_6_0642.jpg" n="3"/>honest. This policy ought to be put into practice, and the new Zgoda should abide by it forever. We sincerely hope this will be so.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
