<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-11-15">Nov. 15, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">New Books for You</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0135</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0135.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-11-15">Nov. 15, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">NEW BOOKS FOR YOU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many new and valuable books were received this last week by the Pulaski Park Branch of the Chicago Public Library. In addition to its famous Polish collection, the Pulaski branch will now include Russian, Bohemian, German, and French titles. Gogol, Tolstoy, Turgieniev, Gorki, Checkow, and Buchon are representative of its Russian authors; Reuter and Wasserman of its German; Loti, Zola, Hugo de Maupassant, Fabre, France, and Chateaubriand of its French; and there are some good translations of Bohemian by Rolland and Milne. In addition to these, a number of fine English books have arrived. The branch has also received the second of its Dreiser collection, which is ultimately to include his greatest work The American Tragedy, a novel which is so descriptive of the present era, and which took Dreiser ten years to write. It is excellently writen and presents, among other problems, the struggle of youth for adjustment to life, and the effect of that constant struggle on individual crime.</p>
   <p>Willa Cather's book, Death Comes to the Archbishop, and Glenway Wescott's Grandmothers, are also included. The fact that Miss Cather writes deftly and <pb facs="5423968_6_0136.jpg" n="2"/>intelligently, and that Grandmothers won a prize this year, makes these titles significant. The branch always likes to order the best and newest without neglecting its standard collection. Among the new additions to its standard works are Checkov's The Shooting Party and Spencer's Synthetic Philosophy. One cannot pretend to be a student of literature unless he has read the stirring life documents of Checkov; neither can he say that he knows philosophy unless he has a knowledge of the first principles of Spencer's attitude, because it is essential for everyone who aspires to live his life to the fullest, to develop some philosophy of living. The branch has an excellent philosophy department in the making.</p>
   <p>For a long time, readers have had access to Will Durant's Story of Philosophy and many other authoritative books on the subject. Now they may have Bertrand Russell's little book What I Believe. This is a particularly timely purchase inasmuch as Mr. Russell was in Chicago last week, lecturing to thousands of people. Not only those who had the joy of hearing and seeing him, but also those who were not so fortunate will want to have his works, now. In this volume he reveals himself very intimately. What I Believe contains the essence of a great man's philosophy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0137.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Avail yourself of this splendid opportunity that is yours, and take home these books and read them. The Pulaski branch librarians are Polish and are always delighted to have you come in, if only to brouse around. These are your books.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
