<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-03-01">Mar. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Correction and an Explanation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-03-01">Mar. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A CORRECTION AND AN EXPLANATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A veritable stench-bomb appeared in the Polish newspaper Dziennik Ludowy in its issue of February 26, 1915. It made its appearance in an article, entitled "The Record of Anthony Karabasz, Three Times Convicted of Theft".</p>
   <p>An excerpt from the record of the criminal court at Bygdoszcz, in Poland, is presented in the article in question. It shows that a court decree was issued on November 30, 1891, against Anthony Karabasz, who was thereby sentenced to a year at hard labor for theft committed on a church alms box at Szubina, Poland, on March 31, 1891.</p>
   <p>The court record from which the above facts are obtained states that the convicted person performed the functions of organist, acting as substitute for Louis Samola, who had become ill in the Easter holidays, and that the father <pb facs="5423968_6_0461.jpg" n="2"/>of the convicted person, Michael Karabasz, had requested the keys to the church and had them upon his person. For this and for other thefts by him committed the aforesaid Karabasz was punished by jail sentences on several occasions and had been obliged to serve the full terms to which he was sentenced.</p>
   <p>And now relative to the stench of this bomb. A naive and inexperienced person not well acquainted with Mr. Anthony Karabasz, the censor of the Polish National Alliance, would be under the erroneous impression (and that is exactly what the editors of the Dziennik Ludowy desired) that he is the thief whom Dziennik Ludowy describes. No self-respecting person could allow this to go unchallenged.</p>
   <p>There is an old Polish maxim that states that a lie has short legs, and it will not go far. It can be applied to this particular instance.</p>
   <p>Council Number Thirty-eight of the Polish National Alliance, of Pittsburgh <pb facs="5423968_6_0462.jpg" n="3"/>was the first to nominate Mr. Anthony Karabasz for the office of censor of the Polish National Alliance. Through this Council's efforts Mr. Karabasz was elected to that distinguished position. But is there only one person in the world who has the name of Anthony Karabasz? The answer to that is no.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anthony Karabasz, who was elected censor of the Polish National Alliance, is well known to all members of the Alliance, among whom there are many who knew him well in Europe. The censor of the Polish National Alliance was born in Szubina, Poland, on January 27, 1869. His father was John Andrew Karabasz (not Michael, as stated by the Dziennik Ludowy), a farmer of Szubina. His mother was Mary Karabasz, nee Kowalski. This same Anthony Karabasz attended a teacher's college at Kcynia and completed the course in August, 1887 (whereas the thief Anthony had been incarcerated since March 21, 1887).</p>
   <p>After completing the course in the teacher's college he taught in the national school at Welnau from 1887 to 1891. Having lost this position, on February 19, <pb facs="5423968_6_0463.jpg" n="4"/>1892, he came to Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, and was a teacher at Natrone (whereas the thief Anthony Karabasz was sentenced in October, 1892, in Szubina, Poland). Mr. Anthony Karabasz later became a pharmacist in Pittsburgh, and he has remained in that business up to the present time.</p>
   <p>That is the biography of Mr. Anthony Karabasz, the censor of the Polish National Alliance. It might be worth while to mention here that there were four Karabasz families residing in Szubina, Poland, and strange as it may seem, none of them was related to any of the others. Perhaps there was an Anthony Karabasz who was a common thief, but it was not Anthony son of John Andrew but Anthony son of Michael, as the Dziennik Ludowy itself proves.</p>
   <p>The absolutely disgusting character of these stories published by the "Red Messiah's" organ is herewith exposed, and Council Number Thirty-eight of the Polish National Alliance cannot find words strong enough adequately to condemn slanders and liars of this type.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0464.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>R. S. Abczynski</p>
   <p>A. Mystkowski</p>
   <p>F. Wiernicki</p>
   <p>Resolutions Committee</p>
   <p>Walter Borkowski, president of the Council</p>
   <p>Julian Gayda, recording secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
