<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-09-04">Sept. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Newspapermen of America Hold Convention in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">Association of Newspapermen Organized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-09-04">Sept. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH NEWSPAPERMEN OF AMERICA HOLD CONVENTION IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">Association of Newspapermen Organized</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As had been previously announced in the Polish press, a convention of Polish newspapermen of America was held on September 2 and 3 at the Polish Press Club, 2138 Pierce Avenue. The convention was, to a certain extent, a preliminary to a general convention of Polish journalists of America. Naturally, in addition to matters pertaining strictly to organization of the professional [Polish] journalists in America, the lack of which has been greatly felt, the subject of discussion was the historic moment now being experienced by our homeland and by the whole world.</p>
   <p>It can safely be said here that the convention was successful in every respect, primarily because of the fact that Polish newspapers in cities very far from Chicago had sent their representatives to attend, and this of course, was no simple matter. We shall not give a detailed report of the proceedings <pb facs="5423968_6_0433.jpg" n="2"/>here, since such a report, prepared by the secretary of the convention, will appear in tomorrow's issue. We shall limit ourselves, therefore, to a general account of the convention's course and of the discussions that took place.</p>
   <p>The following newspapers were represented by their editors and publishers, as listed:</p>
   <p>Detroit, Michigan: Rekord Codzienny [Daily Record], L. Koscinski, publisher and Wusza, editor.</p>
   <p>New York: Tygodnik Polski [The Polish Weekly], L. Wazeter, editor and publisher.</p>
   <p>Cleveland, Ohio: Polonia W. Ameryce [American Polonia], [J.] Zielinski, editor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0434.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>South Bend, Indiana: Goniel Polski [The Polish Runner], Kalczynski, editor and publisher.</p>
   <p>South Chicago: Polonia, F. Bloch, editor.</p>
   <p>Stevens Point, Wisconsin: Gwiazoa Polarna [The North Star] and Rolnik [The Farmer], Szaroleta, editor and publisher.</p>
   <p>Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania: Sokol Polski [The Polish Falcon], Dr. T. Starzynski.</p>
   <p>Chicago: Dziennik Zwiazkowy: [S.] Orpiszewski, [J.] Przyprawa, [I.] Osostowicz, [S.] Lewental, Skwarczynski, and [V.] Fronczak; Dziennik Chicagoski: Editor V. Papara; Dziennik Narodowy: Editors [J.] Chrzanowski, [H.] Lokanski, [E.] Kolakowski, and Medwecki; Cepy [Flail]: [N.] Zlotnicki; Glos Polek [Polish Women's Voice] Mrs. S. Laudyn-Chrzanowski, editor; Narod Polski, [Polish Nation]: F. S. Barc, editor: Nowy Swiat [New World]: John Wedda; Kumoszka; [Gossip]: E. Kolakowski. Altogether, there were representatives <pb facs="5423968_6_0435.jpg" n="4"/>of seventeen publications, eight from Chicago and nine from out of town.</p>
   <p>After the convention had been opened by Orpiszewski, chairman of the pre-convention committee, by request of the President of the Polish Press Club, the gathering proceeded to elect its officers. (Convention opened at 10:20 in the morning, Sunday, September 2.)</p>
   <p>John J. Chrzanowski, editor-in-chief of Dziennik Narodowy of Chicago and president of the Polish Press Club, was elected chairman, and V. Papara, associate editor of Dziennik Chicagoski, was chosen as secretary. Leon Wazeter, publisher and editor of the New York Tygodnik Polski was elected vice-chairman. The chairman then named press, resolutions, and motions committees, after which the secretary read numerous telegrams and letters from well-wishers. Before adjournment for lunch, representatives of Polish organizations who had been invited to attend the convention were asked to speak. Among those present were: Casimir Zychlinski, president of the <pb facs="5423968_6_0436.jpg" n="5"/>Polish National Alliance; Peter Rostenkowski, president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union; T. M. Helinski, president of the Polish Central Relief Committee, and its secretary, H. Setmajer, who is also secretary of the [Polish] National Department; and Mrs. Anna Neuman, president of the Polish Women's Alliance. In addition to these, there were many other guests.</p>
   <p>At two o'clock, following lunch which was served at the Press Club, the convention was reopened. Editor Przyprawa [Dziennik Zwiazkowy] read a paper entitled "The National Department and the Press". The paper was written with an evident thorough understanding of the subject, and was given careful attention by the audience. A lengthy discussion followed this reading.</p>
   <p>A few motions were then read, formulated by the press committee, which was to have presented to the gathering a plan for organizing the Polish journalists of America. The motions on this subject were read and explained by S. Lewental. A motion was finally passed that the Polish journalists and publishers in <pb facs="5423968_6_0437.jpg" n="6"/>America form an organization to be called the "Association of Polish Newspapermen of America". Further discussion on this matter brought out the question of a constitution and statutes for this association, as well as the question of putting the project into effect. A committee ad hoc was chosen, consisting of Chrzanowski, Przyprawa, Papara, Koscinski [of Detroit], and Wazeter [of New York]. At six o'clock in the evening, the convention was adjourned, to meet again on the following day. Availing themselves of the hospitality of the Polish people of Chicago who had offered the use of their automobiles, the delegates went for a drive through the boulevards and parks of the city, visiting also the monument of Kosciusko in Humboldt Park. It should be added here that the entire convention had been invited to attend the concert given by the Chopin Choir at the Polish Roman Catholic Union Hall. The delegates availed themselves of this invitation. After hearing a few numbers splendidly rendered by Polish Choral groups from this part of the city, they returned to the Polish Press Club headquarters, where a few hours were spent in pleasant conversation on professional matters, political affairs, and <pb facs="5423968_6_0438.jpg" n="7"/>topics of a general nature.</p>
   <p>Second Day's Session</p>
   <p>The second day's session was attended by Waclaw Gasiorowski [Polish author], Polish delegate from Paris, and by Gutowski, delegate from Kiev.</p>
   <p>To open the session, a paper on the subject of the war was presented by Lokanski, and Medwecki then read a paper entitled, "The Adoption of Polish Orphans". Both of the guests from Europe were introduced before noon and each spoke to the gathering, indicating that he would speak at greater length during the afternoon session. The afternoon session opened at two o'clock.</p>
   <p>The first address was that of Waclaw Gasiorowski, who explained the reasons why he had been sent to America to visit the Poles here. In an address that lasted more than an hour, the speaker described recent events in Poland, the <pb facs="5423968_6_0439.jpg" n="8"/>position of the Allied governments in respect to the Polish cause, the recent decree of the president of France, and so on.</p>
   <p>The other very interesting address was that of Gutowski, delegate from Poland, who gave a clear picture of political conditions in Europe from a Polish standpoint. Both of the speakers were received and rewarded with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>Following these addresses, papers were read by Zielinski of Cleveland entitled, "An Army," and by Setmajer entitled, "Re-emigration".</p>
   <p>Finally, a discussion was opened on such matters of extreme importance as present conditions in Poland and the relation of the Polish element in America to Polish questions, as well as its duties to Poland. A number of decisions were made, which need not be mentioned here since they will <pb facs="5423968_6_0440.jpg" n="9"/>appear in the official report by the secretary of the convention. In conclusion, telegrams were sent to President Wilson, to the President of France, and to Governor Lowden of Illinois. Following the reading of the resolution, which appears in its entirety elsewhere in this issue of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, the convention was adjourned at eleven o'clock in the evening.</p>
   <p>It should be added here that it was decided to hold the next general convention of Polish newspapermen of America in Detroit, Michigan, on Thanksgiving Day.</p>
   <p>The second day's session of the convention was also attended by the Philaret Chorus which, under the direction of its capable conductor, Professor Rybowiak, sang two numbers. The performance did much to add to the pleasure of the occasion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
