<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-07-28">July 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Polish National Alliance Summer Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0974</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0974.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-07-28">July 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE SUMMER SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Educational Dept. of the Polish National Alliance is meeting with great success. Polish women belonging to this department are doing great work. The growth and the development of the summer schools maintained by that department is very rapid. About 200 Polish children attend these schools. Polish mothers, realizing the benefits derived from these schools, send their children there.</p>
   <p>The summer school is open six weeks. Three hours are devoted each afternoon to lessons, with fifteen minutes for recess. There are children's and adult's sections. In the children's sections boys and girls are taught how to read and write the Polish language, and in the adult's sections Polish history, literature, and geography are taught.</p>
   <p>It is gratifying to observe the great interest the children are taking in these studies. The children attend these schools regularly and punctually. They learn the language of their fathers, and acquire knowledge of their literature and culture from a native <pb facs="5423968_6_0975.jpg" n="2"/>teacher who is not <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. The children <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> wonderfully.</p>
   <p>The teacher in there <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> method which they think is best.</p>
   <p>The purpose of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> not only to teach Polish, but also to develop individuality and good citizenship. At the last meeting, the teachers decided to establish<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> contact with the pupils and to study their characters. The children will then feel that the teacher are their friends who love them and wish them well.</p>
   <p>At that meeting they <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the very important question of a new Polish reader for children. Most parents do not send their children to summer schools, for they think that the children should be <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> any study during vacation time. This is partly true, but not so in this case. Children attending public schools do not study Polish and therefore they should attend summer schools. It is also better for the child to attend schools than to run around. Such schools should be established in every community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
