<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-11">Aug. 11, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">New Polish Daily Published</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0590</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0590.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-11">Aug. 11, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">NEW POLISH DAILY PUBLISHED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This afternoon the Dziennik Polski (Polish Daily) made its first appearance and will continue to be published daily. The manager of this new paper is M. Kaczmarek, and Nicodemus C. Zlotnicki is the editor. The platform of this newspaper is truth, progress and toleration.</p>
   <p>There are a number of technical errors on the pages of this first issue but these will be corrected in later issues. The whole make-up of this first edition is not very good. A picture of Sigmund Milkowski also graces the front page.</p>
   <p>This newspaper, published in the name of truth and tolerance, if it follows out the meaning of these words, can do a great deal of good, and we would welcome this paper with open arms but for one thing.</p>
   <p>The Dziennik Polski seems to be avoiding the truth in its very first issue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0591.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It claims that the dedication of the cornerstone under the independent church in St. Hedwig Parish will be made by the "bishop" from Cleveland and it calls this building a "Roman Catholic Church." Both statements are untrue. This building has nothing in common with the Roman Catholic Church. And the Roman Catholic bishop of Cleveland, the Most Reverend Horstman, is energetically combatting the schismatics in his diocese, and it seems most unlikely that he would support this same faction in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We make allowance for these errors and hope that they will be corrected by the Dziennik Polski in the very near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
