<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-11">Dec. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Popular Lectures</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1049</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1049.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-11">Dec. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">POPULAR LECTURES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday a series of popular lectures sponsored by the committee on lectures of the Department of Education of the Polish National Alliance was begun. Lectures were given in two districts.</p>
   <p>At the Alliance building, in spite of the inclement weather, a considerable number of people gathered at about four in the afternoon. The lecture hall was completely filled. The audience represented an interested group.</p>
   <p>Professor Thomas Siemiradzki made the opening address, vigorously illustrating the need for strengthening our minds with constant additions of new stores of knowledge. The audience received the professor's address with enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Stanley Jakiel gave a lecture on Miczkiewicz, presenting an outline of his creative work, with especial emphasis on his "Ode to Youth"--this <pb facs="5423968_6_1050.jpg" n="2"/>splendid blossoming of the prophet's poetic genius--analyzing it line by line and explaining the beautiful and lofty thoughts contained in the "Appeal". The lecture was excellent and brought the speaker tremendous applause of gratitude.</p>
   <p>At the parish hall at St. Casimirs, Twenty-second and Whipple Streets, Professor R. Piatkowski delivered a lecture yesterday at 7 P. M. He spoke about Miczkiewicz. Besides outlining the life and activities of this national prophet, the lecturer analyzed in detail one of A. Miczkiewicz's best works, Conrad Wollenrod. Many people attended and their conduct was truly gratifying. Reverend Rector K. Furman, who is an ardent supporter of these lectures, was also present.</p>
   <p>Next Sunday the lectures will be continued. At 3 P. M. there will be a lecture at the Alliance building, and at 7 P. M. at St. Casimir's parish. The committee will see to it that the subjects are of the greatest interest. The lectures will be illustrated with slides. The subject of the lectures will be announced later. The committee expects the public to continue to support its efforts as it did yesterday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
