<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-08">Nov. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Zgoda and Dziennik Zwiazkowy under Separate Editors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0482</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0482.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-08">Nov. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ZGODA AND DZIENNIK ZWIAZKOWY UNDER SEPARATE EDITORS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The central administration of the Polish National Alliance, in accordance with the recommendation of the nineteenth convention at St. Louis, Mo., through its committee on the press, has separated the editorship of the weekly Zgoda from that of the daily Dziennik Zwiazkowy. From now on the weekly Zgoda, as the official organ of the Polish National Alliance, will be controlled by the editor in chief, elected at the convention. He will devote all his efforts and knowledge to this organ; Dziennik Zwiazkowy, on the other hand, will have its separate editor in chief appointed by the administration, who will devote all his time to the daily paper. The substance of the articles, remarks, etc. will be different in the weekly, Zgoda, from that of the daily, but the national spirit of the work for the alliance will be identical in both publications.</p>
   <p>This cannot, and will not, be otherwise. Both publications are issued by the people of the alliance in defense of their mutual interests: to fasten the <pb facs="5423968_6_0483.jpg" n="2"/>national ideology among the masses of our immigrants, and to serve our beloved mother country faithfully. Seperating the editorships was necessitated by the fact that one editor in chief, even though he were the most capable and indefatigable worker, could not manage all of the work. Work in the alliance publications increases daily, and the demands of the readers grow constantly more exacting; and he who reads Dziennik Zwiazkowy is justified in demanding that different scientific and informative material should appear in the weekly, Zgoda, than that which already appeared the week before in the "daily".</p>
   <p>Therefore, for the present, both publications, the daily and the weekly, although they may seem to follow different channels will always have the same aim. Our old friend Zgoda who has grown grey-haired in the struggle for the unity and welfare of the alliance, will fill the position of heavy artillery in the army of the alliance, while the daily will play the part of light cavalry, trying to get everywhere, discover the enemy's movements everyehere, <pb facs="5423968_6_0484.jpg" n="3"/>and, if necessary, give battle. Only by these means can the alliance benefit, since it will be defended on two sides--it will have fighters for its good cause. The press today is a power with which everyone reckons, and one cannot imagine a nation, faction, party, religious order or any other type of organization which would not have a publication for the defense of its interests and the fostering of its aims. The alliance today has really three publications, the men's weekly Zgoda, the women's weekly Zgoda and the daily Dziennik Zwiazkowy. It can, therefore, successfully foster its ideals, and step forward in defense of its own interests. Let us hope that the publications of the alliance will honorably discharge their lofty, but difficult and serious, duties.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
