<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 47,
<date when="1900-11-22">Nov. 22, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Kosciuszko Monument</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1293</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1293.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 47,
<date when="1900-11-22">Nov. 22, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">KOSCIUSZKO MONUMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How long will the committee in charge of building the Kosciuszko monument keep us Polish people in suspense, will you give us an answer?</p>
   <p>This is not the first time that this question is asked. Many groups and organizations are getting sick and tired of waiting to hear how the committee is progressing on this great undertaking. Leading this argument against the committee is the Polish Courier, which will not stop until some answer is given. Did the committee fall asleep?</p>
   <p>But this cannot be true, because people see the members of this committee walking in our streets, eating in restaurants, drinking and talking about every other thing of importance but not a word is said about the monument.</p>
   <p>A few years back Zgoda did the same thing the Courier is doing now. We have waited a year and a half for their answer, but the Courier does not intend to be as lenient.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1294.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Central Committee promised to look into this matter because of the protests of the Polish National Alliance and of the Courier, but not a word has been heard since this promise was made four weeks ago.</p>
   <p>At the beginning of this great movement the Central Committee was given full authority to use the money as they best saw fit, which means that no one can see their records or files except the state auditor.</p>
   <p>Above all, if the committee worked in earnest, as they promised, the funds needed for this monument would have been in the bank long ago, but this shows that they have lost interest in this movement and are lazy.</p>
   <p>Lack of cooperation is what is hindering our progress. Mr. Baraczowi is one example. He collected money for this monument and instead of turning it over to the Committee, he kept it for his own use. This amounted to about $1,200. Another fault of the Committee is having the plans drawn for a monument half the original size, paying to this firm $4.500. Who has <pb facs="5423968_6_1295.jpg" n="3"/>supervised this wonderful piece of work?</p>
   <p>The people are greatly in favor of having the Polish National Alliance take over this work and capital, and see that it is put on a working basis and not as a profit-sharing bank as the present committee is doing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
