<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Figures Speak Loudest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0370</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0370.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FIGURES SPEAK LOUDEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I greet the tenth anniversary of Dziennik Zwiazkowy with real pleasure, for I have always seen and still see in it a powerful instrument in our organizational work. A diplomat once said that, if there were not already a nation of Poles, such a nation would have to be created. The same applies to Dziennik Zwiazkowy--if there were no Dziennik, we would have to create one. Fortunately, our predecessors in office and practically the entire organization reasoned as we do, and, as a result, Dziennik Zwiazkowy is today celebrating the tenth anniversary, not only of its existence but of its fruitful work for the organization of which it has become the official organ.</p>
   <p>Since I move about in a world of figures, I like to present my arguments in figures also. I can do so now.</p>
   <p>I have no intention of presenting a mathematical statement on Dziennik <pb facs="5423968_6_0371.jpg" n="2"/>Zwiazkowy's worth, but a few figures that speak for themselves will not be out of the way. In the year 1907, that is, at the time our organization established its daily newspaper, the assets of the Polish National Alliance totalled $469,233.23. Today, after ten years of Dzeinnik Zwiazkowy's active and energetic aid in organizational work, the assets of the Polish National Alliance total $3,827,220.43. Ten years ago, our organization had $53,638 members; today, its membership is 126,946. In numbers, then, we expanded almost threefold; in assets, almost eightfold.</p>
   <p>Naturally, it is understood that such promising growth in numbers and wealth is not due solely to Dziennik Zwiazkowy. Far from it. In any case, however, our daily newspaper has become a powerful instrument in encouraging some to join our ranks and others to remain in them. Perhaps, in these critical times, the Alliance would not have many members if they were not constantly reminded, through the columns of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, not only of their duties but of the benefits that can be derived from membership in our organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0372.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thus, I wish Dziennik Zwiazkowy the greatest possible development, for the greater and the more influential it becomes the greater and more influential the Polish National Alliance will be among the Poles in America.</p>
   <p>Joseph Magdziarz,</p>
   <p>treasurer of the Polish National Alliance</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
