<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-08-18">Aug. 18, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">A Chronicle of Poles in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Memorial Book of 1891 One Hundred Years after the Proclamation of the Constitution of the Third of May 1871</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0895</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0895.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-08-18">Aug. 18, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">A CHRONICLE OF POLES IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Memorial Book of 1891 One Hundred Years After the Proclamation of the Constitution of the Third of May 1871</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I am going to publish a Polish memorial book entitled "A Chronicle of Poles in America," (Kronika Polska w Ameryce) in honor of the memorable anniversary of the Constitution of May 3, 1871, and as a proof of our existence here in exile.</p>
   <p>This book will give an account of all Polish celebrations in America, a list of speeches and speakers, also a detailed description of all Polish settlements in America, with a list containing the names of the inhabitants and the name and location of the sections from which they come.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, this book will also show how many members there are in each family. In other words, it will give correct information of the number of <pb facs="5423968_6_0896.jpg" n="2"/>Poles living in America at present.</p>
   <p>Each settlement will be mentioned separately, and a brief record of it will be shown. It will tell when and by whom the settlement was founded. It will also reveal the first Polish settlers who built the first church and school. It will give the name of the first pastor and his successors.</p>
   <p>I already have the most important material, and desire to have all available information as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>Every true and well-thinking Pole will admit that this book will be a permanent record of Polish activities,of the spiritual and material progress of the Poles on American soil, and at the same time, it is a public protest against the slanders of our enemies who deny our good qualities and our right to make a livelihood.</p>
   <p>It will be a permanent record, I repeat, for the voice of the newspapers <pb facs="5423968_6_0897.jpg" n="3"/>will soon die out and be forgotten, but such a book will be handed down as an inheritance from parents to children, from generation to generation for many years, and will be sent to the libraries in Washington where it will last for centuries. Besides, this book will be a beginning and a foundation of the Polish history of Poles in exile after the partition of Poland.</p>
   <p>Finally, this book being of a larger size than a regular photographic album, printed on good paper, beautifully illustrated, and in durable binding, will be an ornament in your home.</p>
   <p>The clergy, editors of newspapers, presidents and secretaries of organizations, and all societies are asked to give their kind co-operation and support to this publication in their vicinities. They are asked to send in data of their neighborhood, or to recommend a worthy citizen, a good writer, who would undertake this work. Kindly have him communicate with <pb facs="5423968_6_0898.jpg" n="4"/>me, and I will be glad to give further instructions.</p>
   <p>The sooner I receive the particulars, the quicker the work will be finished.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, I wish to inform the public that in order to prevent any one from reprinting the book, or a possible competition, I have registered it in the proper office of the United States, a country so favorable toward the Poles. I also wish to announce that the book will be published by subscriptions, either cash or in four convenient payments, for which special canvassers will be engaged.</p>
   <p>Further details will be announced later. At present, I am waiting for the result of my appeal.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>I. Wendzinski</p>
   <p>488 Mitchell Street,</p>
   <p>Milwaukee, Wisconsin</p>
   <p>Aug. 1, 1891.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
