<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-20">May 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Funeral of the Late Stanislaus Szwajkart</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-20">May 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FUNERAL OF THE LATE STANISLAUS SZWAJKART</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The funeral of Stanislaus Szwajkart, late editor in chief of Dziennik Chicagoski, on which he had worked for more than a quarter of a century, was held on Saturday, May 18. The funeral was held from the home of the deceased at 2747 Ballou Street to St. Hyacinth's Church in Avondale. After Requiem Mass had been celebrated by the Reverend John Zdechlik, pastor of the church, the body was taken to the Polish-Bohemian St. Adalbert cemetery. The body was interred in the Szwajkart family lot.</p>
   <p>The funeral was impressive but unpretentious, for in accordance with the deceased's wishes, there were no flowers or wreaths. Present at the funeral were the family of the deceased, many of his friends, and representatives of the press and of the organizations and committees in which Szwajkart had been active. The organizations represented were: The Polish National Department, the Polish Central Relief Committee, the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, <pb facs="5423968_6_0335.jpg" n="2"/>the Polish Alma Mater, Dziennik Zwiazkowy, Dziennik Chicagoski, Dziennik Narodowy, the office of the clerk of the Municipal court, [A. I.] Danisch and many others.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance was represented by Casimir Zychlinski, president; J. Magdiarz, treasurer; Mrs. M. Milewski and Mrs. M. Sakowski, directors. Dziennik Zwiazkowy was represented by A. Lokanski, S. Orpiszewski, F. Szczerbowski, and K. Grabowski. The Polish Army Recruiting Center II was represented by ten recruiting officers and volunteers of the Polish Army.</p>
   <p>A great many Polish priests participated in the funeral ceremonies, and Archbishop Mundelein was also among those present in church. More than seventy automobiles formed the funeral cortege.</p>
   <p>Eulogies were delivered at the cemetery by the Reverends W. Zapala and F. Gordon, and by N. L. Piotrowski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
