<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-23">Mar. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[New Polish Magazine]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0842</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0842.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-23">Mar. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[NEW POLISH MAGAZINE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As the readers of Dziennik Chicagoski know, there has existed for some time a desire to publish in America a monthly magazine in English dedicated to Polish interests. Such a publication would be designed to acquaint the American people with Polish art, literature, civilization, and so on. A magazine of this kind--Art and Freedom--will soon make its appearance.</p>
   <p>Various Polish names have been mentioned in connection with the prospective publication, but for the time being, Mr. Sigmund Slupski has charge of the matter. Mr. Slupski was formerly editor of The Pole in America (Polak W Ameryce) and later of the Philadelphia Patriot (Patryota). The first issue of Art and Freedom will probably appear in June. Its editorial offices are located in the Davy Block Building at 207 W. Madison Street.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, before the first issue appears, Mr. Slupski is circulating, as a sort of prospectus, an article in Polish which will be found in Art and Freedom. The article is entitled "Copernicus and Columbus." We have had the <pb facs="5423968_6_0843.jpg" n="2"/>opportunity of seeing the first copy of this brochure which has just come off the press, and we admit that, from the standpoint of typography, it is well presented. The print is plain, clear-cut; the paper is of high quality. It contains in all about forty illustrations. We have not yet had the opportunity to review the work from a literary point of view, but we concede that the choice of illustrations seems commendable. We find no such illustrations embellishing the works of our investigators of Copernicus in Poland. We find in the brochure copies of a number of portraits of Copernicus, among which is one that was supposed to have been painted by himself; drawings depicting members of his family; pictures of all the monuments that have been erected in his memory, and finally, reproductions of paintings by such masters as Matejko, Siemiradzki ("Apotheosis of Copernicus"), Gerson, Lesser, Sypniewski, and others, representing our great countryman in various stages of his life. This capital collection of illustrations gives the brochure an added value and should prove highly interesting to Americans.</p>
   <p>Mr. Slupski's brochure, arranged to resemble the first copy of Art and Freedom, contains two additional features, namely, a large portrait of Paderewski <pb facs="5423968_6_0844.jpg" n="3"/>and a prospectus.</p>
   <p>From the latter we discover that the first issue of Art and Freedom will contain--besides the article on Copernicus--the following articles: "Slavonic Beginnings," "Religious Persecutions of the Russian Government," "Sketches From Russia," etc. One of its special attractions will be a composition by Paderewski, written especially for Art and Freedom, entitled "Columbus Jubilee Hymn."</p>
   <p>We wish the publishers success in their undertaking and eagerly await the first issue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
