<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-17">Dec. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">On Returning to Poland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0951</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0951.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-17">Dec. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ON RETURNING TO POLAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>You gentlemen have invited your readers to take part in a discussion of your editorial in one of the issues of Dziennik Zwiazkowy on the subject of what our duties toward the homeland are.</p>
   <p>You are doing well, gentlemen, in opening your columns to the general public for a thorough discussion of matters concerning the entire nation. This will lead the general public to become acquainted with a wider range of problems and to study them more deeply.</p>
   <p>There is not much that one can add to your article, much less contradict that which was expressed in it.</p>
   <p>Everyone knows very well that Poland will not need lawyers, doctors, and notaries, but will need industrialists, technicians, mechanics, and artisans, or people with just strong hands to guide the plow.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0952.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Poland has an overproduction of intellectuals, whom we shall call "impractical intellectuals," with decidedly bureaucratic tendencies. On the other hand, Poland lacks skilled mechanics and all sorts of artisans of the type of American "tradesmen." This state of affairs has been brought about by many causes, chief among them being the inherited, noble disdain of commerce and trades. People in Poland still speak with contempt of certain trades--for instance, that of the cobbler. The old adages, "Drunk as a cobbler" and "Silly as a cobbler's last," clearly indicate the disrepute in which this trade is held. In Poland training in crafts is unnecessary; the schools teach their pupils only to dream of a gold collar, stars, and a sword, not to seek a trade and work for the country in industry, commerce, or craft.</p>
   <p>For this reason our democracy is beneath criticism. For this reason there is a countless number of rungs on our social ladder, and people on a higher rung look down with contempt on those below. Every nation has its social ladder. We have one here in America. Everyone will notice the difference between Rockefeller and one of his laborers, but this is a material difference; personal dignity is the same for all here. That is why those who go back to Poland from <pb facs="5423968_6_0953.jpg" n="3"/>America, with American ideas of democracy and social structure, are so welcome over there and are such gallant workers in all the people's organizations in the homeland.</p>
   <p>But let us return to the subject of training our young men in crafts. If we were to undertake the training of young men in crafts, trades, and business,for Poland, it is my opinion that we should place greater emphasis on the young men coming into the country, rather than on those born here, because one can say with certainty that from among those born here only a negligible percentage could be expected to return to Poland. On the other hand, the young immigrants live in the thought of returning and do not relinquish this idea, even though they try to become or already are citizens of this country.</p>
   <p>We should guide these young men into the proper channels and help them with advice and services. We should create proper trade and business schools for them, point out the best American schools in these lines, and endow already existing Polish institutions. This would be a noble undertaking for the co-operative work <pb facs="5423968_6_0954.jpg" n="4"/>of our organizations. This would indeed be action, not empty words--action which would give abundant returns in the future.</p>
   <p>More and more of our intelligent young men are beginning to seek vocational training in correspondence schools. Occasionally a few will go through Chicago's Coyne National Trade School. Hundreds could be found who would like to learn; but some of them lack funds, others do not know English sufficiently well to be able to understand the lectures, to some the difficulty of finding employment in Chicago forms the obstacle, and still others cannot manage for numerous other reasons. These young people waste their lives in stuffy factories, frequently doing work beyond their strength, and thus increase the ranks of the sickly and the so-called "young old-men."</p>
   <p>Could we not establish our own Polish trade and business school, or at least arrange appropriate courses from time to time? We have so many influential and fine people in Chicago who advocate the idea of real work for the people and could do something about this if they wanted to.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0955.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Two years ago a League of Self-help was formed in Chicago which was to conduct such practical courses, but now for some reason one does not hear about it; perhaps it no longer exists because of lack of support on our part. I have written to this League several times but have received no reply. I wonder if Engineer Galezowski's Vocational School in Cleveland, Ohio, has met the same fate. It is too bad because we need such schools very, very badly.</p>
   <p>(Signed) S. Zaklikiewicz</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
