<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-06-06">June 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">New Sokol Group Organized in Town of Lake</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-06-06">June 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">NEW SOKOL GROUP ORGANIZED IN TOWN OF LAKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(The following article was received by our staff for publication.)</p>
   <p>The far distance of Town of Lake from the nucleus of Polish life on the Northwest Side has rather obscured the activity of the Polish group in this community. Activity in this section was small and gradual in its development. It was not until recent years that it began to be noticed. During a score of years several patriotic exercises were staged, lectures were arranged for every second Sunday at University Hall, and the younger generation, not wishing to be surpassed by its elders, held a meeting last Sunday, June 2, and organized a sokol group. The founders are M. Checinski, S. Jankowski, J. Zalewski, S. Szmidt, and S. Stubiak. Plans were laid sometime in advance and when arrangements were completed a meeting for June 2 was announced. The Polish youth responded, the idea was accepted and forty joined.</p>
   <p>Casimir Zychlinski, commander of the Polish Sokols Alliance, was present at <pb facs="5423968_6_1198.jpg" n="2"/>the gathering. He made a convincing talk that a group of this kind is not mere play, but a place in which serious work is conducted under stipulated conditions.</p>
   <p>Mr. Szmidt, who took the stand, urged the new members to have respect for their superiors. This was followed by a proposal from C. Zurawski to add the slogan "One for All and All for One" to the one that has already been accepted, "With Body for the Fatherland and with Sword for the Enemy".</p>
   <p>An election of officers brought the following results: J. Zaleski, president; S. Szmidt, vice-president; H. Checinski, recording secretary; C. Zurawski, financial secretary; and J. Pawelkiewicz, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The results of the meeting indicate a promising future for this organization.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held on Friday, June 7, at the University Settlement <pb facs="5423968_6_1199.jpg" n="3"/>hall. All Poles are invited to attend, for many important matters will be discussed.</p>
   <p>M. Checinski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
