<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 13,
<date when="1919-03-26">March 26, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Gazeta Handlowa, the Monthly Gazette of Trade and Commerce Address on a Very Important Matter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0804</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0804.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 13,
<date when="1919-03-26">March 26, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GAZETA HANDLOWA, THE MONTHLY GAZETTE OF TRADE AND COMMERCE ADDRESS ON A VERY IMPORTANT MATTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear reader:</p>
   <p>The joy that embraces every Polish soul has no bounds. That for which we have yearned for one hundred years, we possess. We already have our own government, our own land, our own garden beds, those wonderful fields gilded with wheat, silvered with rye, for which our poet Mickiewicz always pined for so deeply in his writings, are already ours! Our property once and for all!</p>
   <p>Brother Poles! Let us demonstrate to the world that, having our own land, our own government, we can rebuild Poland from its ruins and work ourselves up to such heights like our friend, the American Republic.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0805.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We will rebuild a powerful Poland, support its welfare on a concrete foundation; as a building is only then lasting if it will rest on concrete, made up of stone, sand and cement. Likewise the building of our nation will only then become lasting as soon as we support it on commerce, trade and agriculture, on which solely perfectly developing governments earn their livelihood.</p>
   <p>It does not matter if any one of us leave for Poland or remain here. The knowledge of trade among Poles in America, and the art of circulating money in the aim of continuous fair profits will place us high in the eyes of American and Polish society.</p>
   <p>He who will learn trade and commerce perfectly and leaves for Poland, there he will have an open field for everything; the one remaining here acquiring a sufficient knowledge of trade and commerce will make a fortune. Now is the only opportunity for us Poles to make money and not be dependent on others.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0806.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In this particular aim, we are publishing a much needed periodical, giving out advice and pointers to mechanics, farmers, laborers and businessmen in which it will contain the following departments.</p>
   <p>1. Trade, Commerce and Agriculture</p>
   <p>2. News about trade, industry, farming, and labor in the old country.</p>
   <p>3. The art of preparing the soil and the breeding of livestock.</p>
   <p>4. Information about labor conditions in America and the old country.</p>
   <p>5. The rights of the workingman in America.</p>
   <p>6. Relationship between employer and employee.</p>
   <p>7. The value of money in trade circulation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0807.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>8. American laws and citizen papers.</p>
   <p>9. What interest and profit money ought to bring and where to place it.</p>
   <p>10. The sale and purchase of real estate.</p>
   <p>11. What a worker leaving for the old country should know and must know. (Information about leaving America for the old country according to the regulations of the American government; further, when and the cheapest way to go to Poland).</p>
   <p>12. A new method of learning English.</p>
   <p>13. Legal protection.</p>
   <p>From the above you can see that the Gazette of Trade and Commerce, a periodical of exceptional value to everyone, will be an accomplished advisor in daily matters and will save you more than once from losses and exploitation by others.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0808.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It costs only $1 a year in advance. He who pays $2 will receive this gazette for two years at the same price.</p>
   <p>Address: The Gazette of Trade and Commerce Publishing Co., Suite 1207, 155 N. Clark St., Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
