<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-08-08">Aug. 8, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Ameryka</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0776</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0776.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-08-08">Aug. 8, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">AMERYKA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of our readers has asked us to comment on the statement, made recently in St. Louis by the editor of Ameryka, to the effect that "Ameryka is the best Polish newspaper in this country". The reader asks if it is true, as claimed, that Ameryka aids in the intellectual development of its readers, that it publishes only the truth, that it is entirely patriotic, and that other newspapers are supported by millionaires for the purpose of oppressing the poor people and keeping them in ignorance. He asks us also to verify the allegation that Ameryka is a socialist journal.</p>
   <p>That Ameryka is a socialist journal is quite true, and we are certain that the editor will admit the fact himself. Not long ago, this journal published a series of articles written from a viewpoint of extreme socialism, a viewpoint rightly considered dangerous by people of deep religious convictions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0777.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That the journal in question publishes fables and clumsy falsehoods which no one can believe, can be proven by an article which appeared in Ameryka recently, and to which we replied in our paper. In that article, there was a false statement concerning a publishing company which publishes a daily newspaper, a large weekly on Sundays, and many books. The article claimed that this company employs in its printing establishment only orphans from the orphan asylum, and keeps them under the supervision of a person who "does not know how to hold a stick in his hand" and who works every day, including Sunday, till 11 P.M., at a salary of eight or ten dollars a week.</p>
   <p>That Ameryka is not a Polish patriotic newspaper but rather Russian in its sympathies can be substantiated by the fact that, not long ago, Ameryka offered its readers portraits of the czar and czarina of Russia as a premium for a subscription to a certain Russian newspaper. This indicates very clearly to what extent this journal is "the most intelligent and the best".</p>
   <p>Furthermore, Ameryka has no respect for our laws, for it sends indecent stories <pb facs="5423968_6_0778.jpg" n="3"/>through the United States mail, in direct violation of the law. For a long time after laws had been passed forbidding lottery advertisements in the press, Ameryka continued to publish such advertisements, until the law finally intervened and put a stop to it.</p>
   <p>It is evident that Ameryka has no respect either for the laws of the United States or the feelings of the Poles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
