<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-03">Dec. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Oldest and the Newest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0313</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0313.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-03">Dec. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLDEST AND THE NEWEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The daily recently founded in Chicago, which out of its own conceit endeavors to hide intellectual deficiency and which treats all warnings, advice, and censorship of other Polish daily papers in Chicago in a comical manner, made an unusual discovery and revelation in a recent number. It contended that one of the oldest Polish daily papers in Chicago pads the date on the news received from abroad, virtually making dispatches that are three weeks old carry a present date line.</p>
   <p>It is very gratifying to know that there is such a sentinel in the field of Polish journalism. Much nerve-racking time must be spent to find this discrepancy in the date line of foreign dispatches. Such precautionary measures may be well and good but it presumably casts its attack on one <pb facs="5423968_6_0314.jpg" n="2"/>particular paper. A publication that is in its infancy has many points to learn about the trade. This infant of the press has overlooked the fact that the father of the Polish dailies has always given a date line to all foreign dispatches. But apparently that is its method of attack on this particular paper; at the same time it overlooks the stories of the yellow journals.</p>
   <p>If this daily paper can understand we will try to explain the treatment of news bulletins from abroad. The date that appears on news from Poland is not unethical because the date line signifies when the news was received by that particular paper.</p>
   <p>What would this bellicose paper say to the fact that the Herald and Examiner printed news from London dated December 1, which bore news of what happened in Persia - not three weeks ago but seven?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0315.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If this belligerent daily is so concerned with the ethics of the press it should not let this fact go by without sending the Examiner a sharp reprimand for its gross error.</p>
   <p>We are sorry to devote so much space to this incident; however, we anticipate that these few words will enlighten the dark corners and narrow mind of this infant of the press.</p>
   <p>In the future, if any person connected with this daily paper is confronted with a problem or misunderstands some point of journalism let him call at our office and one of our "older" editors will be glad to enlighten him.</p>
   <p>K. W.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
