<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1929-01-16">January 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Archbishop Cieplak Society Organizes Sports Branch</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1929-01-16">January 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">ARCHBISHOP CIEPLAK SOCIETY ORGANIZES SPORTS BRANCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Another Polish social and athletic club has stepped into the limelight. A new body, organized by members of the Archbishop Cieplak Society No. 800 of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union has thrown its gloves into the arena. They will be known as the Cieplak Social and Athletic Club, with headquarters at the Holy Trinity High School Gymnasium, Division and Cleaver Streets.</p>
   <p>Next Tuesday, January 22, the new Club will hold its first regular meeting at seven-thirty o'clock, on the second floor of the Trinity High School Building. The meeting will be held under the guidance of the officers of the Cieplak Society, including Louis A.Zulowinski, Z. Stefanowicz, Sr. Secretary; Joseph Wiewiora, Vice Pres. The Club, however, will elect its own officers who will take the reins after next Tuesday.</p>
   <p>The new Club has arranged an extensive calendar of activities; which, with the calibre of its members should be extended to the highest rung in the Polish Roman Catholic Union. The activities on its program are bowling, baseball, basket ball and social entertainments.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1139.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Z. Stefanowicz Sr., who is a mat and ring enthusiast, is looking into the future, hopeful that this manly art will find a place on the new club calendar.</p>
   <p>The foremost feature of the new Club is that both young men and young women are privileged to join. Heretofore, only those who were members of the Archbishop Cieplak Society were eligible; the secretary will gladly inform all those interested as to their elegibility.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
