<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 31,
<date when="1936-08-03">Aug. 3, 1936</date><title level="a">Polonia the South Chicago Polish Weekly</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0299</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0299.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 31,
<date when="1936-08-03">Aug. 3, 1936</date><title level="a">POLONIA THE SOUTH CHICAGO POLISH WEEKLY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polonia was founded in 1906 by Father Frank Wojtalewicz, pastor of the Immaculate Conception parish, located at 87th street and Commercial avenue.</p>
   <p>In 1916 Father Wojtalewicz sold Polonia to the Urbanek Brothers, who since that time operate a printing establishment known as the Polonis Publishing Company.</p>
   <p>Polonia, although small, contributed from the first, and still contributes, very valuable instructive and enlightening articles on citizenship, patriotism and other subjects. It supplies its readers with news from America, Poland and every part of the globe. It always stood for democracy and human rights. It upheld and still upholds the American tradition and custom.</p>
   <p>Judging by the editorial articles on citizenship, patriotism and democracy it is more patrictic than some of the so-called hundred-per-cent papers printed in the English language.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0300.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Reprint form Polonia, vol. XVIII, No. 18, May 1, 1924.</p>
   <p>AMERICA WHAT DOES IT MEAN TO YOU</p>
   <p>American means everything to us today, even more than ever before. Learn the language of America, adopt the simple friendly customs of the typical, true American, inform ourselves of her laws, obey them and take part actively and intelligently in improving them through the power of the ballot in our hands. If we refuse to listen to extremists of any kind, and with thrift, industry and definite aims walk upon the high middle ground of sanity,consideration and service, if we will give value received and expect the same in return; and if we will defend America at all times and before all people as the land of these opportunities; if we will be true-blue Americans ourselves, America will <pb facs="5423968_6_0301.jpg" n="3"/>return to us a full measure, heaped up, and pressed down and overflowing with life's riches.</p>
   <p>Let our object be our country, our whole country, and nothing but our country. All of which leads to solving the difficulties of reconstruction and its attendant question of work and time. Time is what we want most, and what, alas, we use worst. And with time and work lies the destiny of America.</p>
   <p>Be willing to make any sacrifice for the furtherance of the ideals of this great country. America is giving you everything, prosperity, opportunity-(how many of our great men of today have fought their way up from obscurity and poverty.)</p>
   <p>America offers educational advantages, freedom, such as is enjoyed in no other country in the world.</p>
   <p>All America asks of you is only that you will continue to be as true and loyal in these trying times of reconstruction as you were during the war, that you will support her as faithfully and unselfishly as you have in the past.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0302.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Americanism is a mighty social current, a gulf stream in the ocean of humanity. Men may attempt to divert it they may even sail upon it roughly for their own selfish purposes, but none can stop it flowing; and everywhere it touches there is given off to the blessing of mankind a great life-giving warmth carried down from the source of our national beginning, the warmth of hearts that care for each other and are willing to help anywhere, any time that there is an opportunity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
