<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1929-02-12">Feb. 12, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Roman Catholic Union Sports Commission Holds First Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1929-02-12">Feb. 12, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION SPORTS COMMISSION HOLDS FIRST MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the momentous decisions of the last Polish Roman Catholic Union (P. R. C. U.) convention at Buffalo, N. Y., was the establishment of a commission of sports and youth; a move that gave heart to the youth in the ranks of this greatest of Polish and Catholic organizations in the world. The move immediately conveyed to the Polish Youth that the present administration of the Union holds the welfare of its youth uppermost in its thought.</p>
   <p>Yesterday that commission met in the executive offices of the Polish Roman Catholic Union for its first regular meeting. And the momentous question of youth has at last gained the spotlight and the forefront.</p>
   <p>As the first session of the meeting of the committee, held in the forenoon, Mr. John J. Olejniczak, president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, presided; and after a few hearty words, submitted a plan, on which he asked the commission recently appointed by him to deliberate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1137.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first move of the new committee was the elections of offices. Mr. J. Rostenkowski, son of Peter Rostenkowski, former treasurer and ex-president of the P. R. C. U., was named president of the commission; while Mrs. A. Wlodarski of the Town of Lake was named secretary. Other members of the commission, who met yesterday at the summons of President Olejniczak, are Miss Stephanie Zarembs, of Buffalo, N. Y.; Miss Lew, of Chicago; Miss Stempien, of Buffalo, N. Y.; Stanley U. Kappa, Washington D. C.; Mr. Chelminak, South Bend Indiana and Mr. Kaliszewski, Chicago. The afternoon session was confined to discussing the plan of eleven paragraphs submitted by Mr. Olejniczak. The commission will submit its full findings and deliberations to the board of directors of the Polish Roman Catholic Union at a meeting today in the executive offices.</p>
   <p>What lent impetus to the work of the commission of youth and sports, was the fact that a fund of more than $13.000 will be available for the needs of that commission to carry out the plans of the president, formulated at the convention and approved by the different bodies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
