<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-06-19">June 19, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Dziennik Chicagoski Six Months Old</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0784</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0784.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-06-19">June 19, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">DZIENNIK CHICAGOSKI SIX MONTHS OLD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago, a half year passed since the first issue of Dziennik Chicagoski was delivered into the hands of the reading public.</p>
   <p>Time has convinced us that a Polish daily newspaper is necessary in Chicago, that it is supported by the public, and that it will be necessary to enlarge its size in the next half year. This necessity is felt already, but at present this is an impossibility, and it would be unjustifiable to demand that a newspaper increase its expenses after a half year's existence, when the income is still small, for the paper sells for less than a penny, on the basis of yearly subscription.</p>
   <p>Our journal is too small for fulfilling the desires of most of our readers satisfactorily. In the last six months we tried to find what are the wishes <pb facs="5423968_6_0785.jpg" n="2"/>and needs of our readers, and have endeavored to adjust ourselves to them. Our difficulty lies in selecting and rejecting the material for publication, of which we have a great number, and this is very embarrassing.</p>
   <p>In order to satisfy most of our readers, we decided to arrange our articles and publish some of them every day, besides the telegrams and local news. This will be continued until the size of our paper increases which will enable us to change our plan.</p>
   <p>In the future, news from Poland obtained from European papers will be published on Mondays and Thursdays. Articles on American politics will be published on Tuesdays. On Wednesdays, we will publish articles concerning Poles and their affairs in America. On Fridays, articles on science and literature will be published, and on Saturdays excerpts from Polish journals edited in America, and other material, such as correspondence, etc.</p>
   <p>This system will be adopted next week. However, it will be necessary to <pb facs="5423968_6_0786.jpg" n="3"/>deviate from this course occasionally, and devote the entire issue to some cause or important incidents. We are introducing this program for the purpose of determining whether or not our readers are in favor of it. As stated before, we will be glad to receive correspondence from our readers and comply with their wishes and requests, if possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
