<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-11-26">Nov. 26, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Citizens Honor Notre Dame U. Student's at Palmer House</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-11-26">Nov. 26, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH CITIZENS HONOR NOTRE DAME U. STUDENT'S AT PALMER HOUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polish students of the University of Notre Dame, and members of the Notre Dame football squad, with Coach Knute Rockne and a group of professors will be guests at a banquet to be given at the Palmer House, under the auspices of a group of distinguished Polish citizens of Chicago. The banquet will specifically honor John Niemic and John Poliski who are Polish boys, and members of the Notre Dame football squad. They will receive tokens that will mark the occasion and remind them that their work is appreciated and admired by their fellow countrymen.</p>
   <p>The committee in charge of the dinner apprises us that this fete was decided upon at a meeting of the prominent Poles who are represented in the committee of arrangements. Their chief aim is to make known to American citizenry, that a great number of the students attending the universities are Polish-American; to spur Polish youth to higher ideals in the pursuit of their studies, and finally, to interest our youth by this public manifestation, to such an extent that the number of Polish students in the universities be greatly increased. Appearing on the roster of the University of Notre Dame are the names of sons of many prominent Poles in Chicago, who will be guests at tomorrow's banquet.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
