<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-02-04">Feb. 4, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">New Sokol Organized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-02-04">Feb. 4, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">NEW SOKOL ORGANIZED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new gymnastic society was organized on the northwest side of Chicago Sunday, January 31, called "Sokol Society." The aim of this new organization is to give its members a thorough physical training. Contests will also be held.</p>
   <p>It is a well-known fact that a definite routine of exercise is beneficial to the body and the mind. It keeps the body physically fit, and the mind clear and agile.</p>
   <p>The aim of this society is also to train Polish youth for competition in tournaments, in gymnastics, and awaken within them the love for their native people and their native tongue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1217.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This organization is divided into two classes: Active embers and supporting members. The difference between the two is that the former must attend classes twice a week for instruction, besides attending a regular meeting. The latter attends only the meetings.</p>
   <p>Children of members and non-members will be taken in and given special training. At the present time, however, boys only will be enrolled.</p>
   <p>All Polish people interested and familiar with this particular kind of training, and have children whom they would like have given physical instruction are invited to attend a special meeting Sunday February 7, The meeting will take place at Anthony Greenwald's hall, 668 Holt Avenue, at 7 P.M. Plans of this organization will be discussed. Those desiring to become members, or wish to enroll their children will gladly be accepted. New members will be registered free of charge at the present time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
