<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1890-12-16">Dec. 16, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A Letter to Dzienrik Chicagoski</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_0791</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0791.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1890-12-16">Dec. 16, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A LETTER TO DZIENRIK CHICAGOSKI</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Instead of a regular daily talk, we will share with our readers today a communication which we have just received.</p>
   <p>We do this with a great pleasure, because it has strengthened our confidence in and hopes of a good future. Here is the communication from a kind reader who signs himself "A Silesian."</p>
   <p>"Dear Editors:</p>
   <p>"I do not know whether my writing will please you, but I do know that I write what I feel; it comes straight from my heart.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_0792.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"In the first place, I am very glad that we Poles have at last a daily paper. You could not think of a better Christmas present for this year. Every decent Pole rejoices with his whole heart that he will be able to read the latest news in his native tongue. 'Daily paper' also indicates that the Poles are progressing and growing in number and power. I feel that Dziennik Chicagoski will help us immensely. Polish business will improve; Polish people will know what is going on; Polish workingmen will know more about employment and find it sooner; and politics will be enlivened to the advantage of Polish interests. Other nationalities, especially Americans, will have a respect for us and take us under consideration, for they will discover that we are strong. Such a newspaper will also help us in our everyday life. There will be reports of meetings and other activities, and every person will know what takes place at these meetings, even, if he or she cannot attend them on account of business. It would also be nice if the paper would inform us about weddings <pb facs="5423968_6_0793.jpg" n="3"/>and other social activities, because the citizens are also interested in them. I know that the editors must have thought about these things, but I must write about them because such is my nature that I must reveal what lies in my heart. I warn you not to pay any attention to criticism, for there are always people who condemn everything, no matter how good it is. I will also whisper into your ear that a habitual critic is usually, if you please, a very ignorant person.</p>
   <p>"If the Lord will permit me, and if you desire, I will write about, our undertakings and other matters in which the Poles are interested.</p>
   <p>I am enclosing a one-year subscription for myself, a six-month one for my neighbor Paul, and a one-month one for my neighbor John. The addresses <pb facs="5423968_6_0794.jpg" n="4"/>are written on the paper in which the money is wrapped. I am closing my letter with the old time Polish 'God Bless You.'"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
