<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 89,
<date when="1922-04-15">April 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Baseball League - Last Call to Managers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 89,
<date when="1922-04-15">April 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH BASEBALL LEAGUE - LAST CALL TO MANAGERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Polish Baseball League will be held next Tuesday, April 18th, at 8 P. M. in the office of the Polish Alma Mater, on the second floor of the Dziennik Chicagoski Building, 1455 W. Division St.</p>
   <p>All managers and their assistants should come to this meeting because this is the last meeting at which they can sign up for the league.</p>
   <p>We are informed that there are certain difficulties in regard to the true understanding of things. Therefore, those who wish to have anything explained to them are requested to come to the next meeting. We also invite those managers who have not yet been to a meeting. This is a matter of which many have no comprehension, how a league is organized. The Rev. Thomas Smyk from the St. Hedwig's Orphanage at Niles, Ill., himself did not know until he attended a meeting and found out how a league is organized. Because of that, therefore, not reflecting long upon the subject, as an active sportsman, he spoke a few words and these words <pb facs="5423968_6_1165.jpg" n="2"/>meant very much. He said that it is true that Polish sportsmen went to work and that the league is organized according to regulation requirements and in regards to games everything is correct according to the by-laws.</p>
   <p>All managers or their assistants should attend this meeting, so they can find out how the matter stands. This will be the last meeting, in which the players will be chosen for the opening game of the Polish league, in which one or two players from each club will take part. Each player will represent his club in the baseball league. This will be the first time in which the leaders will be sportsmen, experienced in this field. So, help us make this league one of the best and strongest leagues in the state of Illinois, the only Polish league in existence in the United States. We repeat once more: Come to the meeting and sign up in the strictly Polish Baseball League!</p>
   <p>Next Tuesday is your last opportunity!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1166.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The season of the league's activities is to open on the last Sunday in April or the first Sunday in May.</p>
   <p>All letters, checks or money orders should be sent to the cashier of the Polish League, Mr. Frank L. Arendtt, 1455 W. Division St.</p>
   <p>Administration of the Polish Baseball League.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
