<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. 17, No. 241,
<date when="1906-10-19">Oct. 19, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Do Not Over-Indulge in Sports</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_6_1179</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_6_1179.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. 17, No. 241,
<date when="1906-10-19">Oct. 19, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">DO NOT OVER-INDULGE IN SPORTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In recent time the love of sports has become quite extensive. If only this inclination to indulge in this form of exercise does not prove injurious by over-indulgence. Already in England, the mother of sports and, after her, in France, voices of caution are being heard. In those lyceums and schools, which might be called athletic schools and arenas, the accomplishments or results do not offset the harm done to the human organism. The report of mutilated bodies are increasing greatly in number every year as the result of sport matches. For the growing youth, excessive activity in sports is harmful; it can create chronic disorders, lameness, digression, etc. After foot races we saw a youth about 12 to 15 years old collapse breathlessly, causing signs of asthma, expansion of the heart, also afflicting the lungs.</p>
   <p>A Parisian doctor, Dr. Potain, has taken the pulse beat of participants in a so-called "football" game, showing that they had a fever reaching 39 Reamur points. A London physician, Elliot, claims that one out of five players contracts a chronic ailment. Dr. Redfield goes so far as to say that "football" <pb facs="5423968_6_1180.jpg" n="2"/>is more murderous than war. It has claimed more dead and injured in England than the total of ill-fated mariners in Mikada during the war in 1905. The list of "murderous" sports are listed as follows: "football" the worst of them all, boxing, gymnastics, baseball, swimming, and lawn-tennis. So for the sake of your health it is not enough to love sports, but you must learn to indulge in them physiologically. In many cases, instead of aiding your health through sports, you usually cause yourself physical injury.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
