<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1892-02-26">Feb. 26, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Hebrew Performances at the Metropolitan Theatre</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1892-02-26">Feb. 26, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">HEBREW PERFORMANCES AT THE METROPOLITAN THEATRE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An opera entitled "King Solomon" enlisted a large and appreciative audience at the Metropolitan Theatre last Sunday evening, Feb. 21. The house was crowded to its utmost capacity.</p>
   <p>Madam Tanzman sang the part of Sulamitha and much amazed and bewildered the audience with her fine, cultivated and thrilling voice; her finale in the trio at the end of the third act almost made the windows rattle, and the proprietors, Rubenstein and Rose took the hint by engaging carpenters and plasters to enlarge the theatre and build a new large stage. All the encores of that evening were received by her and her husband, Mr. Tanzman, the latter in the part of Shulam, proving his foremost ability as a first-class comedian, the like of which has seldom if ever been seen in Chicago Hebrew theatres. Mr. and Mrs. Tanzman have just arrived from San Francisco where Mr. Tanzman has managed his own company for three months in the Orpheum Theatre and is now in Chicago on a special engagement by Messrs. Rubenstein and Rose.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1729.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Rotenstein in the part of "King Solomon" was wise enough to acquit himself acceptably; has has a fine baritone voice and was greatly applauded. Mr. Gold as the "Ashmedai" almost scared the audience with his demonlike acting, being always perfect in his parts.</p>
   <p>The rest of the cast was fair. "King Horodus" rendered by this company on Feb. 19 was equally well attended. Mr. and Mrs. Tanzman were recalled several times before the curtain. Mr. Gold in the part of "King Horodus" has well assumed the wild nature and jealous disposition of the ancient king, and in all appearances his acting resembled that of the Moor Othelo. Mr. Gold is a character actor of unquestioned ability. Mr. Silberman, the originator of Hebrew theatres in the United States, the first manager and best tenor singer among the Hebrew professionals, arrived here in a special engagement with the Metropolitan Theatre and his first debut in Chicago will be tonight in "Joseph and his Brethren," where Mr. Silberman will enact the part of Joseph, and Madam Tanzman the part of the youngest brother Benjamin. Rubenstein and Rose, the proprietors are praiseworthy for endeavoring to employ in their house first-class professionals, and the professionals alone are to blame for calling that an opera, while in fact it is an operetta.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
