<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-10-16">October 16, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Attorney Grossberg Is Being Boomed for Judge</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0299</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0299.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-10-16">October 16, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">ATTORNEY GROSSBERG IS BEING BOOMED FOR JUDGE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Due to President Taft's appointment of Judge Julian W. Mack as Judge of the Commerce Court, the Circuit Court of Cook County lost the only Jewish judge in a court of this nature.</p>
   <p>A movement, therefore, is on foot among the Jews in Chicago to work out plans to have another Jewish jurist appointed or elected in place of Judge Mack. With this object in view a committee was organized of the following prominent Jewish citizens: Abraham S. Roe, James Rosenthal, Benjamin Schiff, Issac Lurie, Harry M. Fisher.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0300.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This committee sent out a lot of letters and called a mass meeting of prominent Jewish citizens. The mass meeting was held, last night, in the office of Harry M. Fisher, 3247 Douglas Blvd. There were thirty-six of the most outstanding Jewish citizens, at that mass meeting, representing the West Side and they unanimously endorsed the lawyer, J. G. Grossberg as judge of the Circuit Court of Cook County, to take the place of Judge Mack.</p>
   <p>The Committee has organized itself into a political club for the sole purpose of formulating plans, ways and means to have this attorney, J. G. Grossberg, elected judge of the Circuit Court of Cook County at the next spring election.</p>
   <p>The officers of the club are as follows: Senator Solokof, chairman; A. Z. Roe, treasurer; A. Edelman, secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0301.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The committee of Ways and Means, has the following: Harry M. Fisher, Max Goodman, Samuel Rosenblatt, Jas. Rosenthal.</p>
   <p>Among the thirty-six, who were at the meeting were D. L. Halpern, Dr. B. Bregstone, Phillip P. Bregstone, Dr. J. Gartenstein.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
