<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-14">Apr. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">An Injustice to Dr. Hirsch</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0514</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0514.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-14">Apr. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AN INJUSTICE TO DR. HIRSCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the hideous qualities possessed by human beings is the quality of seeking honor or recognition at another's expense. "Honored through disgrace of one's neighbor" was condemned by Jewish sages thousands of years ago.</p>
   <p>The members of Sinai Temple Congregation seemed to possess this quality when they accused Dr. Hirsch of disloyalty to the United States. Such an action has no other purpose than to advertise their own patriotism before the world. They think that they will be heard more easily if they can point out some one whose patriotism is not what it should be. Choosing Dr. Hirsch as their victim, they were certain of attaining their aim. As a prominent Jew, they naturally knew that attention would be focused upon Dr. Hirsch when the finger of accusation was pointed at him. This in itself would be sufficient for the world to conclude that they are <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0515.jpg" n="2"/>patriots of the first rank. Such an action could have no other purpose. Even if it were taken for granted that at heart Dr. Hirsch is somewhat sympathetic to Germany--a thing which is understandable in a man who has German blood relations and who was educated in German schools--yet he did not do anything to deserve the accusation of disloyalty to the American Flag.</p>
   <p>Several weeks ago we had an opportunity to say a few harsh words about Dr. Hirsch. He has committed the same injustice to other as is now being committed against him. In a widely heralded and publicized interview given to the Chicago Herald, he pointed out, among other things, that the patriotism of American Zionists is open to question, whereas his school children sing patriotic songs and the American Flag flies from the roof of his temple. This was not worthy of a men of Dr. Hirsch's caliber and we expressed our opinion about it. Perhaps the heartache, undergone now by Dr. Hirsch, has <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0516.jpg" n="3"/>been meted out "measure for measure" as just retribution. Nevertheless, this cannot be the justification of those who parade their own patriotism in order to hurt him. A patriotism which seeks such demonstrations is invalid. The true patriot does his duty and invites others to do likewise, without trying to find fault with his fellow men. After all a person should be judged by his actions and not by his thoughts. And when a person buys Liberty Bonds and induces others to buy them, without uttering a single word which might cast the slightest suspicion upon his actions, no one has the right to accuse such a person of disloyalty.</p>
   <p>Those who are circulating the petition to force Dr. Hirsch to resign from Sinai Temple because of "disloyalty" to the United States are committing a double injustice: to Dr. Hirsch personally and to Jewry generally. After all, it must not be forgotten that he represents a great class of Jews, and if such suspicions should spread, they would cast a shadow upon all Jews. The fact that Jews themselves have brought forth such accusations will not minimize that shadow.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0517.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We have a right to look upon Dr. Hirsch as an adversary who doesn't always seem to be in the right. Through some jest or witticism he will often hurt others more than is called for. Yet this does not prevent us from stating that the attack upon him by members of his own congregation is not seemly or justifiable.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
