<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-05">Sept. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Candidates for Illinois Legislature</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. A. Lebenson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-05">Sept. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH CANDIDATES FOR ILLINOIS LEGISLATURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. A. Lebenson</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last election for the Illinois [State] Legislature, one Jewish senator and five Jewish representatives were elected. The senator, Corporation Counsel Samuel A. Ettelson, has two more years of office because he represents an unusual district, the third. This year the election of senators will be held in the even districts only. The five representatives were Dr. George Lipshultz of the Second District, Isaac S. Rothschild of the Fifth District, Jacob W. Epstein of the Seventeenth District, Solomon F. Roderick, of the Nineteenth District and Benjamin M. Mitchell of the Twenty-First District. Dr. Lipshultz, Mr. Epstein and Mr. Mitchell were elected as Democrats, and Mr. Roderick and Mr. Rothschild as Republicans. Three of these Jewish representatives--Dr. Lipshultz, Mr. Epstein and Mr. Roderick--are running for renomination.</p>
   <p>We can say, to the credit of these Jewish representatives, that each one of them made good in office. The Legislative Voters League, whose task it is to <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0177.jpg" n="2"/>give an impartial survey of each lawmaker in the Assembly, compliments the Jewish lawmakers.</p>
   <p>The first on the list is Dr. George A. Lipshultz. About him the League says: "He worked hard for good laws, especially for a law to abolish capital punishment." Considering that this is Dr. Lipshultz's first term in the Legislature, that is, [he is considered] a "greenhorn" in lawmaking, this report is highly complimentary.</p>
   <p>About Jacob W. Epstein, representative of the Seventeenth Senatorial District, the League says the following:</p>
   <p>"He ends his first term with a very good record. He has the ability to develop into a very good member." It would be no more than right that the Jewish public should help the young Jewish man to become "developed" by seeing that he is nominated and elected.</p>
   <p>About Solomon F. Roderick, representative of the Nineteenth Senatorial District, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0178.jpg" n="3"/>the League says: "He ended his term with a good record; he was active on the floor and in various committees, and at times he revealed wonderful independence of character." Such lawmakers are very necessary in the Legislature.</p>
   <p>Benjamin M. Mitchell completes his eighth term. The League claims that his last term was the best. He proposed and worked for good constructive laws. If good work entitles a person to membership in the lawmaking body, Mr. Mitchell is entitled to support from every Jewish citizen.</p>
   <p>In the place of Mr. Rothschild, of the Fifth District, a young Jewish lawyer, Mr. Sidney Lyon, is running for this office. He is active in Jewish philanthropic affairs and is well recommended.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
