<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-11-02">November 2, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Adolph J. Sabbath Insulted as a Jew</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0305</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0305.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-11-02">November 2, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">ADOLPH J. SABBATH INSULTED AS A JEW</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Anthony Michalek, who was once defeated, is again the candidate for Congressman from the Fifth District, on the Republican ticket opposing Mr. Adolph J. Sabbath, Democratic candidate for Congress.</p>
   <p>The Republican Party has issued the second leaflet in which they insulted Mr. Sabbath, calling him:- "Jew," "Snake," and are asking the voters not to vote for Mr. Sabbath. We know that this infamous procedure of obtaining votes will not appeal to the Jewish people. It will also not appeal to the decent Bohemians, whom Mr. Michalek is trying to convince that he must represent in Congress, where he landed four years ago by accident.</p>
   <p>Jews of the Fifth Congressional District, should unite their forces and vote solidly for Congressman Sabbath. In doing this, they will express their protest against the disgraceful dealings of Mr. Anthony Michalek, who so shamefully insulted Mr. Sabbath as a Jew.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0306.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Anthony Michalek, as stated above, is running on the Republican ticket. It is the duty of all Jewish voters, regardless of their party affiliation, to vote for Congressman Adolph J. Sabbath.</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabbath's name is the 39th in the Democratic column. Jewish voters of the Fifth District, it does not matter which party you belong to. When you vote, just place an X opposite the name of Mr. Sabbath, and show Mr. Michalek that the Jewish name is not as cheap in America as he thinks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
