<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-30">Oct. 30, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Woodrow Wilson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-30">Oct. 30, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WOODROW WILSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Wilson has recently made a speech that will draw the attention not only of America but of all Europe.</p>
   <p>This occurred at the Southern Commercial Congress, touching upon that most important question of American foreign policies.</p>
   <p>The President spoke of conditions in the South and Central American Republics, pointing out that Russia is to blame for much of the conflicting conditions existing there at the present time.</p>
   <p>The European speculators come to the American republics get various concessions, invest capital in enterprises, seeking thereby to secure huge profits regardless of the welfare of the natives. They are not concerned <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0134.jpg" n="2"/>in the conditions of the land, the form of government or the government itself. It matters little to them what the existing circumstances might be. They seek only a strong government that can guarantee returns for their taxes and duties even if that government be the worst kind of despot, oppressing the people to the utmost.</p>
   <p>The attitude of the United States toward these republics is entirely different. This country is sufficiently large and powerful and does not need to undertake any territorial robbery. We do not seek new possessions. Instead we foster high ambitions to develop in all other republics a form of government such as we enjoy in our high ideals of freedom and democracy. Let every republic be independent.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0135.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That was the essence of Wilson's speech. It will, without a doubt, make a good impression in all America. It will be realized that the United States does not seek to absorb the small republics, but wishes, instead, only to place these countries on a higher, freer, and happier level. America seeks only commercial ties and friendly cultural influences.</p>
   <p>A confirmation of the President's words can be seen in the stand taken by the United States government in the Mexican entanglement. While the European nations have given recognition to the bloody rule of Huerta, giving moral support to this despot in return for his help in cutting coupons for their incomes, yet the United States had the moral courage to oppose him.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0136.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Europe, too, shall have to conform with the higher moral principles embodied in American political dealings. Europe has as an example the American refusal of the Japanese loan in which the Americans did not wish to establish their government as a tax collector for a financial syndicate.</p>
   <p>And now, even more than ever, will the European countries have to take into account the policies of the United States regarding the small American republics. On this continent the United States is in its home, therefore, European powers will have to consider the moral principles as set forth by the Washington administrators in their policies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
