<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-15">Apr. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Mayor Dever's Keren Hayesod Proclamation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-15">Apr. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">MAYOR DEVER'S KEREN HAYESOD PROCLAMATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Honorable William E. Dever, Mayor of Chicago, has issued the following proclamation to our good citizens of this great prosperous city:</p>
   <p>"The Holy Land, the cradle of civilization, is now being rebuilt by the Jews with the consent of the Nations of the earth and with the full approval of our own Government. When rebuilt, it will be the Homeland for all the oppressed, downtrodden members of the Jewish race and will be the final solution of the century-old Jewish problem in Europe.</p>
   <p>"Since the Holy Land has been laid waste by the Romans and the Jewish people exiled from its ancestral home, it has witnessed some of the greatest events in human history, such as the rise of Islam, the Crusades, the appearance of Napoleon on the streets of Jaffa, but now it witnesses the greatest of all <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0143.jpg" n="2"/>historical events--the return of a large part of the Jewish people to their ancestral homeland, after centuries of exile.</p>
   <p>"Providence willed it that millions of Jews find freedom and happiness in our beloved America and form the greatest and most powerful Jewish community in the world there, and Providence willed it that of all the Jewish groups in the world, the American Jewish group alone emerge from the great World War unweakened and unimpaired, and be financially in a position to build the Holy Land for the persecuted and downtrodden Jewish people in various parts of Europe, oppressed for centuries as a result of prejudice and malice.</p>
   <p>"The Jewish citizens of our beloved city have decided to build a large agricultural colony in the Holy Land to be named Chicago, to perpetuate the name of our own great and prosperous city as an expression of gratitude for the great opportunities the city of Chicago has given them. The Jews of other great American cities will no doubt shortly do the same thing and within a reasonable period of time the Holy Land will be covered by a net of agricultural <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0144.jpg" n="3"/>colonies bearing the names of American cities in which millions of Jews have found liberty and prosperity. Our Jewish fellow citizens in Chicago are on the verge of inaugurating a drive for $300,000 for the Palestine Foundation Fund, the financial agency under which the Holy Land is being rebuilt by the Jewish pioneers from all parts of Europe.</p>
   <p>"I consider the rebuilding of Palestine by the Jewish people and for the Jewish people a great humanitarian enterprise, worthy of the support of every citizen of this great Republic.</p>
   <p>"I consider the undertaking of our Jewish fellow citizens in Chicago, to name a large agricultural colony in our Holy Land Chicago, a praiseworthy ambition and an expression of heartfelt gratitude to this great city and I, therefore, call upon our fellow citizens to view this laudable enterprise with sympathy and lend it their support.</p>
   <p>"The work of reconstruction of the Holy Land is making rapid strides. Since <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0145.jpg" n="4"/>the conclusion of the war, 40,000 Jewish pioneers from all parts of Europe have immigrated into Palestine and have settled there as agricultural laborers. They are drying up swamps, planting forests, building roads, bridges, houses, schools, and houses of worship, and are turning a wilderness into an Eden. The Holy Land, cradle of all great religions, will soon raise from its ashes and be again what it has been at the time of the great prophets--a land flowing with milk and honey.</p>
   <p>"It would be a matter of great satisfaction to the citizens of this great, prosperous and progressive city to know that we have been instrumental in rebuilding the Holy Land and that we have been helpful in solving the century-old problem that has perplexed humanity since time immemorial. Let each of us help in this great human and humanitarian enterprise and thus strengthen and continue the great philanthropic traditions of this great and beloved city of ours. When the Holy Land will be rebuilt, and will again serve the highest purpose of the human race and will be again the fountain and wellspring of the spirit, our children and children's children will have the happy consciousness that their <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0146.jpg" n="5"/>fathers and grandfathers have done their share in erecting this great structure.</p>
   <p>William E. Dever."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
