<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-22">Sept. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Men as Teachers in the Evening Classes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1032</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1032.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-22">Sept. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">MEN AS TEACHERS IN THE EVENING CLASSES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That a woman is a very capable and appropriate teacher of children has been convincingly demonstrated by many tests. A woman has a better understanding of the character, disposition, and caprices of a child, and has the emotional warmth that a child needs. This makes her both capable and suitable as a teacher in elementary schools. In countries of a high degree of culture like Germany, England, and America, most of the teachers in the elementary schools are women.</p>
   <p>For adult students, a woman, as a teacher, is no longer suitable, because more rigid discipline, more experience, and more profound knowledge are required. And, instead of a woman, a man occupies the professorial chair in the institutions of higher learning.</p>
   <p>It pays institutions of higher education to engage men as instructors not <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1033.jpg" n="2"/>only because they have a more profound knowledge of the various subjects, but also from a practical and ethical point of view. Thus, the engagement of men instructors in the institutions of higher learning has become the fashion.</p>
   <p>In our country, especially in the larger cities where most of the immigrants settle, an educational problem arises regarding the teaching of English to adults. In the evening classes in English, which are arranged by the Board of Education of our city for adult immigrants, as well as in the citizenship classes which prepare the immigrants to pass the naturalization examinations, women are engaged as teachers.</p>
   <p>Very often this is not satisfactory. We have heard complaints many times that the courses are not conducted as they should be, that they are conducted as children's courses, and that the students do not respect their teachers. This question which should have been considered long ago, was recently taken <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1034.jpg" n="3"/>up by the management committee of the public schools.</p>
   <p>This question was taken up not because women are incompetent to teach in the elementary schools for children, but because men are much more suitable as instructors in elementary courses for adults.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harry A. Lipsky, chairman of the committee on school arrangements for adults, introduced this question at a session which was held recently, and all the members, who participated in the discussion, realized the practicability of his plan and unanimously agreed to it. Mr. Lipsky's resolution to the Board of Education reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, There are some men instructors who are able to teach the courses in English and citizenship for adult immigrants, in night schools, and it seems very advisable that these subjects should be taught by men, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, There are many men with teaching experience who are engaged in <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1035.jpg" n="4"/>other professions and could be induced to accept teaching positions in evening classes; therefore be it</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That the superintendent of schools shall recommend an examination for teachers of English and citizenship in the evening classes for men candidates, and that the qualifications of teachers who are eligible for the examinations, shall be the same as is required of teachers in the elementary schools, and that the time when the examinations are to take place shall be determined by the superintendent of schools."</p>
   <p>It is obvious that Mr. Lipsky's plan is a very practical one, particularly the point on engaging men as instructors in the citizenship courses. This is not because women are not good citizens of the United States, nor because they might interpret the Constitution incorrectly, but because the question of women's suffrage has not been completely settled in America. Certain grievances that suffragettes have, would be discussed and commented upon, and would have an undesirable influence upon immigrants who should be given <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1036.jpg" n="5"/>instruction in American citizenship with more enthusiasm and less criticism. Aside from this, one of the chief arguments of the suffragettes, especially the women teachers, has been that immigrants can become citizens. They look contemptuously upon the immigrant men who can become citizens in five years, even though they are a foreign element, whereas native-born women are deprived of their citizenship.</p>
   <p>Although a major part of the question of women suffrage has already been solved in Illinois, nevertheless, until it is entirely solved, it would be preferable to have men engaged for these courses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
