<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1882-07-21">July 21, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">Some Plain Truths</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0945</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0945.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1882-07-21">July 21, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">SOME PLAIN TRUTHS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We must freely admit that we have not yet attained to that eminence which is true of other metropolises, on this Continent. It cannot be averred that they do not possess the wealth. On the contrary, we count now among us who are not only millionaires while a considerable number are financially well to do, and as a business class stand pre-eminently high. But the Israelites of Chicago lack influence, notwithstanding their social and political relations are as nil. There are several causes assigned for this anomalous condition. One or more Jewish wiseaires have in the earlier days of Chicago conceived the Utopian idea that races and religious sects have no business to exist on this American Continent. In other words, the Jewish type and character was to be transmuted into an American citizen in all spheres of life. However, much of this state of being is desirable, yet so long as there are other religious denominations neither the history, nor the Jewish people can be lost sight of; on the contrary we would stand out in bold relief, as may be evidenced in our everyday life.</p>
   <p>As Jews or Israelites, our Chicago representative men seldom confer with each other.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0946.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They are ever wanting as a body when a great public measure is to be fostered and encouraged. Another and the most potent reason is, that the most affluent Israelites of Chicago lacks that intelligence and education which might convince them of such public undertakings, whereby they might attain a renown for public spintedness, and to say nothing of their parsimonious disposition and money harding qualifications. There are however, among our middle class Israelites very many whose magnanimity appear like shining stars, if we compare the sums donated in behalf of the Russian Refugees with those of the Jewish millionaires of Chicago......It were about time that our Chicago Jews began to realize their insignificant. They should, of right become philanthropist and public benefactors. We have yet to record a single instance where one of our rich Jews has ever endowed a public institution to the amount of even one dollar.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
