<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The American Jewish Year Book</title>, 5673,
<date when="1913-10-01">September 12, 1912 to October 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Edited by Herbert Friedenwald Appointments, Honors, and Elections June 1, 1911, to June 30, 1912 Chicago, Illinois</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0188</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0188.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The American Jewish Year Book</title>, 5673,
<date when="1913-10-01">September 12, 1912 to October 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Edited by Herbert Friedenwald APPOINTMENTS, HONORS, AND ELECTIONS JUNE 1, 1911, TO JUNE 30, 1912 CHICAGO, ILLINOIS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Amberg, N. Samuel., appointed member of the Research Staff of the Otto S. A. Sprague Memorial Institute, Chicago, April, 1912, (p. 274)</p>
   <p>Bergstone, Philip P., Appointed Assistant Judge, Probate Court, January, 1911. (p. 275)</p>
   <p>Deueker, Saul., appointed member Hotchkiss Committee, investigating conditions at Illinois Industrial School for girls, and other institutions, September, 1911 (p. 276)</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0189.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Friedman, Herbert F., appointed Counsel for Civil Service Commission, July, 1911. (p. 277)</p>
   <p>Klafter, David S., appointed by Mayor, member of Commission to Conserve Residential Portion of Chicago, December, 1911, (p. 279)</p>
   <p>Kraus, Adolph., appointed by Mayor of Chicago, delegate to Lakes-to-the-Gulf Deep Waterway,Association Convention, October, 1911. (p. 280)</p>
   <p>Lipsky, Harry A., appointed by Mayor, member City School Board, July, 1911. (p. 281)</p>
   <p>Mack, Julian W., Judge, Chicago, Illinois, reappointed for five years to Commerce Court, February, 1912. (p. 281)</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0190.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Michelson, Albert A., Chicago, Illinois, receives honorary degree from (Christiana) Oslo University, Sweden, September,1911, (p. 282)</p>
   <p>Pam, Hugo, Chicago, Illinois, elected Judge of Superior Court, November, 1911 (p. 283.)</p>
   <p>Pfaelzer, David M., appointed by Mayor, member City School Board, July,1911; appointed by Mayor, delegate to Lake-to-the-Gulf Deep Waterway Association Convention, October, 1911. (p. 283)</p>
   <p>Rappaport, Julius, appointed by Mayor, member Special Park Commission, February, 1912. (p. 283)</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0191.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Rosenblatt, S. J., appointed by Mayor, member Special Parks Commission, December, 1911. (p. 283)</p>
   <p>Rosenwald, Julius, elected Trustee University of Chicago, May, 1912. (p. 283)</p>
   <p>Sabath, Adolph, J., appointed by Mayor of Chicago, delegate to Lakes-to- the-Gulf Deep Waterway Association Convention, October, 1911 (p. 284)</p>
   <p>Schanfarber, Tobias, Chicago, Illinois, appointed by Governor, delegate from Illinois to National Civic Federation, at Washington, March 5-8-, February, 1912 (p. 284)</p>
   <p>Solomon, Mrs. Henry, Chicago, Illinois, appointed on Commission to Investigate Workings of Juvenile Court, August, 1911 (p. 285).</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0192.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Stole, Joseph, Chicago, Illinois, appointed by Governor, delegate to American Prisons Association Convention, Omaha, Nebraska, October, 1911; officiates as Chaplain to Republican National Convention, June 19, 1912. (p. 285).</p>
   <p>Weisskopf, M. A., appointed by Mayor, member School Board on the Bridewell, July, 1911 (p. 287)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
