<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-09">May 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Health Promotion Week Begins Tomorrow in the Jewish Neighborhoods</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-09">May 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">HEALTH PROMOTION WEEK BEGINS TOMORROW IN THE JEWISH NEIGHBORHOODS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Setting aside a week for health promotion is a very good and worthy action. It would naturally be better if each man and woman would take this into consideration everyday in the year, for nothing makes man so happy and content as good health.</p>
   <p>Health is the best blessing man can receive. If he cares for himself, he has health, which is really everything. Without it we have nothing, so what would avail us millions if we could not enjoy them.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the Health Department set aside the week from the eleventh to the seventeenth of May as Health Week. A huge program is being prepared for this week.</p>
   <p>Health Commissioner Robertson, as we know, appointed Dr. Jacob A. Goodman, of Twelfth Street and Homan Avenue, as chief of the division of the Jewish Districts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1119.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On behalf of the Health Commissioner, Dr. Goodman appeals to all rabbis, requesting that this Saturday they speak in their synagogues about Health Promotion Week.</p>
   <p>This Health Promotion Week will be devoted to the cleaning of streets, alleys, and homes. The city government will see to it that the alleys and back yards are made as clean as possible. But it will be up to the housewife to keep her home clean.</p>
   <p>Once one becomes accustomed to cleanliness, it becomes hard to break the habit, and one feels like a new person, strong and healthy.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, should home cleanliness be neglected, one exposes himself not only to illness but also to the danger of diseases.</p>
   <p>"Dirt and filth are the worse enemies of mankind. They foster all kinds of diseases. We must, therefore, eradicate them from our abodes, streets, and alleys," said Dr. Goodman. We can do this very simply by keeping ourselves, our children, and our homes clean.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1120.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Officially Health Week commences Sunday, but, I believe that the rabbis should begin the campaign Saturday by devoting a part of their sermon to the question of health and the necessity of keeping oneself, home, alleys, and back yards clean."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
