<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-12-08">Dec. 8, 1877</date>, 5:1.
<title level="a">The Greenebaum Banks Proceedings in Court</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-12-08">Dec. 8, 1877</date>, 5:1.
<title level="a">THE GREENEBAUM BANKS PROCEEDINGS IN COURT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The casual visitor at the German Savings Bank yesterday morning would probably have noticed the rather protracted absence of its President, Mr. Greenebaum, but, unless he happened to be in a somewhat inquisitive frame of mind, would not have remarked upon it as a thing to excite wonder or surprise. But there are other people under the sun besides casual visitors, and a reporter with even an ordinarily well trained nose for news, reminding himself of the rumors prevalent for a few days back that Mr. Greenebaum's troubles had not ended with the suspension of the German National, but would probably be supplemented by trouble in the savings bank, put this and that together, and before long discovered that the President's withdrawal from that famous back room did indeed mean something. If the casual visitor alluded to had passed along the hall in the City Building, opposite Judge Moore's court room, a few minutes before 12 o'clock, he would have seen the aforesaid bank President, looking somewhat worried, and holding hurried conversations with Mr. John Woodbridge, the lawyer, and a young gentleman by the name of Simeon Strauss, an employe of the bank, who has charge of the mortgage business, and who writes attorney-at-law after his name.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1525.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The trio were evidently waiting for something, and it did not take the ubiquitous reporter long to ascertain in what direction the wind blew. At just 2 o'clock, he learned, Mr. Woodbridge would appear before Judge Moore, remind him of an appointment for that hour, and proceed to ask that a Receiver be appointed for the German Savings Bank, his request being backed up by certain representations concocted in due legal form by a certain Herman G. Berls and Frederika Berls, depositors in the aforesaid institution. Further inquiry elicited the information that the bank people, aware that they would have a hard road to travel if they persevered in keeping the institution open, would make no opposition to the bill, but would quietly let the matter take its course. Notice of the move on the part of the two depositors had been communicated to them at about 10 o'clock, and the interim had been spent in interviews between Mr. Greenebaum and the lawyers, in the course of which he had come to this decision. By the time the reporter had posted himself on the preliminaries, the hands of the watches and clocks in the City-Hall which manifested any proper regard for regularity indicated that the hour of 12 had arrived, and a few minutes later the three incessant talkers aforesaid, joined by several others who represented depositors and who had been informed as to what was going on, presented themselves before Judge Moore, and the court proceedings in the case of the German Savings Bank began.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
