<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1895-03-23">March 23, 1895</date>. pp.81-82.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0330</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0330.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1895-03-23">March 23, 1895</date>. pp.81-82.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Robert R. Jampolis, the Democratic nominee for Judge of the Circuit Court, has made the study and practice of law his life-work. Although regarded as one of the younger members of the bar, he has been actively engaged in the profession for nearly 18 years.</p>
   <p>Admitted to the bar in 1877, Mr. Jampolis at once started a general practice, which he conducted for 8 years. In 1885 when Judge Julius S. Grinnell was elevated to State's Attorney, he appointed Mr. Jampolis to the position of Assistant State's Attorney. Judge Grinnell's successor in the State's Attorney office, Joel M. Longenecker, honored Mr. Jampolis by a re-appointment. In his capacity he was engaged in the prosecution of many important cases, and as legal adviser of the grand jury, he conducted the investigation of from 25,000 to 30,000 criminal cases.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jampolis is a thorough Chicagoan and has lived in this city since a few weeks after his birth in 1855. He entered the Union College of Law, from which he graduated with honors in 1877. Mr. Jampolis was the youngest, but one, in his class and had just become 21 when he began to practice. Mr. Jampolis has been a prominent member of Zion Congregation for years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
