<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-31">Jan. 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Newly Formed Companies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-31">Jan. 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">NEWLY FORMED COMPANIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Paetz and Company, 5542 Broadway, which will handle theater business, has been organized by Charles and Louis Levin, and M. Paetz. Capital is $50,000.</p>
   <p>The Alaska Sheepskin Clothing Manufacturing Company, 713 West Roosevelt Road, has been organized. Capital is $20,000.</p>
   <p>Siegel Brothers, 227 West Van Buren Street, clothing manufacturers, has been organized by Abe, Jerome, and Milton Siegel. Capital is $125,000.</p>
   <p>Sheridan Brampton Building Company, 140 North Dearborn Street, which will purchase and operate buildings, has been organized by Harry Solomon, Morris B. Risman, and Irving Zevin. Capital is $470,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1290.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Imperial Producing Company, State and Lake Building, a booking agency, has been organized by Sam Tishman, Albert Sabath, and Henry Shapiro. Capital is over $5,000.</p>
   <p>Jones and Berger Company, 3139 Roosevelt Road, dealing in auto and radio accessories, has been organized by Louis Berger, Israel Benjamin, and Julius Jones. Capital is $5,000.</p>
   <p>Natoma Sales Corporation, 167 West Chicago Avenue, dealing in food products, has been organized by Henry Apfelbaum, T. Sarazon, and Nathan Goldberg. Capital is $10,000.</p>
   <p>Humboldt Credit Company, 2706 West Division Street, which will handle general merchandise, has been organized by Samuel Weinshenker, Morris Rose, and Daniel Wolf. Capital is $7,500.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1291.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Pure Knitting Mills, 2007 South California Avenue, which will manufacture and trade in woolen and knit goods, has been organized by Herman Newberger, Meyer Weiner, and Emma Weslen. Capital is $60,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
