<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
wk. of <date when="1892-04-16">Apr. 16, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[Mode Wineman Esteemed as Piano Teacher]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1724</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1724.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
wk. of <date when="1892-04-16">Apr. 16, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[MODE WINEMAN ESTEEMED AS PIANO TEACHER]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is to Mr. Eddy, the world famous organist, who was his preceptor for so many years, that Mr. Mode Wineman owes much of his great success. Being a favorite pupil, Mr. Eddy took especial care to develop his musical gifts. Mr. and Mrs. Wineman, parents of Mode, were among the prominent early settlers of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wineman's eminent success as a teacher of the pianoforte, places him in an enviable position in the profession for a young man twenty-seven years of age. The friendship and regard of great artists for him is evident from the tokens of esteem on the walls of his studio. Notably among them is a large and excellent photograph of Paderowski, with his autograph inscription.</p>
   <p>While abroad last summer, Mr. Wineman was the recipient of considerable social attention from artists. In London, Madame Antoinette Sterling, the renowned contralto, gave a dinner for him to meet London's musical and literary celebrities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1725.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Frederick Boscovits, the Chopin player, who has the distinction of having been a pupil of Chopin, and who later was such a favorite guest of the late King Alphonso of Spain, also arranged a dinner for Mr. Wineman. While in Halle, the birthplace of Handel, the composer, one of the heirs of the Handel estate presented Mr. Wineman with two volumes of Handel's biography and also a diagram sketch of the house in which Handel was born, accompanied by many interesting notes net generally known.</p>
   <p>Joseph C. Budge, organist of the ancient Cathederal of Chester, and brother of Dr. Budge, organist of Westminster Abbey, presented Mr. Wineman with an autograph copy of "Rudel" a dramatic Cantata, having its first production at the Musical Festival of Chester, at the of Mr. Wineman's visit there.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wineman's literary ability is of a high order and of much originality. A few weeks ago, he received a commission to write a musical sketch for one of the foremost monthly magazines of this country, but the demands upon his services are so great that only limited time can be given to literature and musical criticisms of which Mr. Wineman is a recognized authority.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
