<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1926-06-26">June 26, 1926</date>, Vol. 71, P.737.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0689</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0689.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1926-06-26">June 26, 1926</date>, Vol. 71, P.737.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Home Club, for working mothers with children, will be opened to view next Sunday. Located at 6617 S. Racine Ave., this new building is the result of many years work on the part of the Home Club, Northern Branch, and the Cooperators.</p>
   <p>According to Mr. James E. Greenebaum, president of the organization, the principle of the institution is to keep mother and children together. From each weekly salary, the mother contributes something towards the support of her family. The part that she is unable to pay is taken from the funds of the club. After her children have reached a certain age, she is given assistance in establishing a home of her own. Among those who are officers of the organization are Mrs. Herbert Hart, Mrs. E. G. Foreman Jr., Mrs. Lester Wellman and Mrs. Henry Wursberg.</p>
   <p>The Home Club it well situated with plenty of light and air and each family with a room for itself, which promotes the spirit of home. The fact is stressed that the charity is a home and not an institution. It has been endorsed by the Jewish Charities of Chicago. After months of research on their part, surveying the welfare problem in Chicago, it was found that the Home Club filled a very important need.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
