<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1886-08-13">August 13, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">Hon. Chas. H. Schwab Mayor Ad Interim of the City of Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1886-08-13">August 13, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">HON. CHAS. H. SCHWAB MAYOR AD INTERIM OF THE CITY OF CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was not a little surprise to the citizens of Chicago, that the office of City Comptroller was tendered to Hon. Chas. H. Schwab, of the firm of Selz, Schwab and Co., wholesale boot and shoe manufacturers. It was with some reluctance that Mr. Schwab entertained such a proposition, but through the solicitation of many personal friends and leading business men of the city, he consented to accept the appointment and promised the mayor that he would for a short period (until October 1), supervise the city finances. He forthwith assumed the office of comptroller, a position second only to that of Mayor of the City of Chicago. Even on the first day of his incumbency, Mr. Schwab's exceptional sagacity was demonstrated by the fact that he discovered a clerical error, amounting to $5,000.</p>
   <p>We have known this gentleman for many years, as a conscientious Democrat. As the present incumbent of the office of comptroller, he will reflect high credit upon the City of Chicago. It is not improbable that his party may nominate him for Mayor of Chicago, since he possess all the sterling qualities of a highly honorable business man, combined with great administrative <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0335.jpg" n="2"/>ability. He is fully identified with the interests of the city and his cosmopolitan proclivities render him generally popular.</p>
   <p>The Israelites of Chicago may well be proud of the distinction and honor conferred upon Mr. Chas. H. Schwab.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
