<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-27">Aug. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Cook County Fair in Maywood</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1074</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1074.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-27">Aug. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE COOK COUNTY FAIR IN MAYWOOD</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There will be a big fair in Maywood--the Cook County and Chicago fair--from Saturday, August 26, to Monday, September 4. Five thousand farmers who live in Cook County will exhibit their products at the fair. You are citizens and residents of this county, as well as Jews. You enjoy the many products produced on the farms near Chicago; you should know more about them. Jewish public affairs should not demand your exclusive interest. It would be news not only to the Jews, but also the the non-Jews, if they were told that Cook County is the greatest and most varied agricultural district in America. The residents of Chicago very rarely think about that part of the county which provides them with a considerable amount of food, and which ships various farm products to other parts of the country.</p>
   <p>You should certainly want to know the role that Cook County plays in providing you with comforts, and with the food you eat. You can find out all about it if <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1075.jpg" n="2"/>you attend the Chicago-Cook County fair. Let as many Jews as possible go and see the fair; let them buy whatever they need and whatever they like. We will thus gain favor in the eyes of the farmer. In order to stimulate your desire to visit the fair, we will tell you a few facts about farming in Cook County so that you can be proud of your neighbors of the field.</p>
   <p>Cook County produces ninety per cent of all the onion seed that is used in America--two million bushels annually.</p>
   <p>The greatest winter-gardens of flowers and vegetables are found in Cook County.</p>
   <p>Cook County's truck gardens annually bring in more money to the farmers than the total of all the taxes in many states.</p>
   <p>Cook County has the greatest number of cattle that are free from tuberculosis.</p>
   <p>Cook County cultivates sugar beets and is one of the most important districts <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1076.jpg" n="3"/>in the country manufacturing articles to satisfy the sweet tooth of America.</p>
   <p>There are in Cook County 5,000 farms, valued at one hundred million dollars. On these farms there are 43,000 goats and sheep, 42,000 cattle, and 16,000 horses. There are 50,000 pigs--but, very likely, this would not interest you. These farms annually produce two million bushels of oats, one and one-half million bushels of corn, and one-half million bushels of wheat. Many Cook County wheat fields produced an average of fifty bushels per acre this year.</p>
   <p>The residents of Cook County should know each other. The problems of the farmers are our problems. The Chicago-Cook County fair in Maywood will give us an opportunity to become acquainted with the farmer. Take your family to the fair in your automobile, or go there on the streetcar. While it is true that we earn our living in Chicago, we are, nevertheless, fed by the farmers of Cook County.</p>
   <p>Chicago is:</p>
   <p>The commercial crossroads of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1077.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The financial center of the West.</p>
   <p>The heart of the great waterway system of the United States.</p>
   <p>The world's greatest lumber market.</p>
   <p>The world's greatest wheat market.</p>
   <p>The world's greatest cattle market.</p>
   <p>The world's greatest food center.</p>
   <p>Chicago is the world's greatest center for manufacturing furniture, clothing, electric and gas apparatus, dry goods, general merchandise, machinery, jewelry, musical instruments, automobiles, railway cars, iron and steel products, paints and varnish, building materials, and leather.</p>
   <p>More agricultural machinery is produced in Chicago than in any other place [in the world].</p>
   <p>Chicago is the world's greatest transportation center. Thirty railroads enter <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1078.jpg" n="5"/>Chicago. There are fourteen hundred miles of belt lines here--a third of the mileage of the longest railroad in the United States. There are three hundred and fifty freight stations; one hundred railroad yards. Twenty-five hundred package freight cars leave Chicago daily. Thirteen hundred thirty-nine passenger trains, carrying one hundred ninety-two thousand people, arrive and leave daily. A train arrives every minute.</p>
   <p>Chicago has:</p>
   <p>The greatest retail stores in the world.</p>
   <p>A population of nearly three million people.</p>
   <p>Two hundred and sixteen libraries.</p>
   <p>One hundred and one miles of water front.</p>
   <p>The greatest marble building in the world--Field</p>
   <p>Museum of Natural History.</p>
   <p>Chicago is the healthiest city in the world.</p>
   <p>It is greatest convention center.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1079.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Chicago has more playgrounds than any other city. There are seventy municipal playgrounds and forty-five playgrounds in the parks.</p>
   <p>It has the greatest park system in the world: fourteen large parks and one hundred ninety-three small parks, many of which have swimming pools.</p>
   <p>It is the world's greatest summer resort.</p>
   <p>It has twelve bathing beaches.</p>
   <p>It has twenty thousand acres of forest preserves.</p>
   <p>It has the largest zoological garden in the West.</p>
   <p>Chicago is the greatest of the young cities of the world.</p>
   <p>Chicago has the greatest municipal pier, which cost five million dollars--it is a place for rest and pleasure and is also the home of the Pageant of Progress--a second world's fair.</p>
   <p>Be proud of your home, Chicago, and of Cook County. It is true that you earn <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1080.jpg" n="7"/>your living and enjoy yourself in Chicago, but you are fed by the farms which surround Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
