<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-06-26">June 26, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Ku-Klux Klan and the Democratic Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0211</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0211.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-06-26">June 26, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE KU-KLUX KLAN AND THE DEMOCRATIC CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The resolution against the Ku-Klux Klan is one of the most important issues at the Democratic convention.</p>
   <p>A similar resolution was submitted to the Republican convention, but it handled it in such a manner that it came out unnoticed. Although it was easy for the Republican politicians to divert the attention of the convention from this resolution, this will not be possible to the politicians of the Democratic party.</p>
   <p>At the Democratic party convention, the anti-Klan resolution, being proposed in connection with the candidate for president, is not merely a question of program but a piece of politics between rival candidates for nomination.</p>
   <p>Alfred Smith and his followers insist that an anti-Klan resolution should <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0212.jpg" n="2"/>be adopted at this convention, while McAdoo and his followers demand that the convention should ignore the Klan-question just as was done at the Republican convention.</p>
   <p>Smith is in favor of the anti-Klan-resolution because the Klan is against him; first because he is a Catholic; and secondly because he opposed it when he was governor.</p>
   <p>McAdoo has the support of the Klan; it publicly supports his candidacy. A resolution against the Klan would be against McAdoo's friends and supporters.</p>
   <p>It is easy to understand that the anti-Klan resolution, at the convention of the Democratic party, is above all a question of political nomination between Smith and McAdoo, a question not depending entirely on the candidates but which is up for decision to the politicians of the Democratic party, who are to determine what harm or good the resolution against the Klan can do in the next election campaign.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0213.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Professional politicians, naturally, believe in the rule that the best policy in doubtful questions is to say nothing. The Democratic politicians will, therefore, do their utmost to avoid this issue entirely. The question is whether they will succeed.</p>
   <p>It is because of this that the anti-Klan resolution draws particular attention. It is possible that it will develop into a battle among the delegates of the Democratic convention; it is also possible that the best choice will be made as a result of this issue about the anti-Klan resolution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
