<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-24">Feb. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Citizens Do Your Duty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0285</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0285.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-24">Feb. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CITIZENS DO YOUR DUTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today is the day on which every citizen, man or woman, should vote in the primaries. It is the duty of every citizen to take a little time to go to his polling place and cast his vote for the most qualified and capable candidate in his ward. This is particularly the duty of all those Jewish citizens who are strongly inclined to neglect their political obligations. This year, however, every political leader hopes that the Jewish citizens will understand that by their neglect during the primaries, persons are nominated quite frequently who are far from being qualified to represent the Jewish interests in the City Council.</p>
   <p>It is at election time that one must decide who are the best candidates. It stands to reason that no one is to be blamed but the citizens who evade their duties at the primaries. If everyone would be present and not rely upon others to do the nominations, such things would not occur, because the primaries proper were instituted to give the citizens not only an <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0286.jpg" n="2"/>opportunity to vote but also to nominate the candidates, thus precluding the possibility of favoritism on the part of the bosses. The responsibility for the nomination of the candidates in the various wards rests upon the citizen himself.</p>
   <p>At these primaries there is a new element, the women citizens. And these women, who have manifested intense resoluteness on registration day, will surely again today show that they understand the tasks of citizenship.</p>
   <p>It is also expected that the votes of the women will play a very important role; that they will be the power which will decide the nomination of most candidates. It is especially important that the Jewish women show that they are not the last; that even though they are not as politically active as the American women, they are more aware of their political task than others.</p>
   <p>They can only show it in one way, by participating in the primaries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
