<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-09">June 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Jew Is No Slacker</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-09">June 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEW IS NO SLACKER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A paragraph of severe calumny and very bad taste slipped into the original book of instructions for the medical advisory boards that are affiliated with the draft. The paragraph, to the great shame of its author, reads as follows: "The foreign born, particularly the Jews, are more inclined than are the native born to seek exemption from the army on the excuse of diverse ailments."</p>
   <p>When this original book of instructions appeared, it came like a storm out of a clear sky. This insinuation was so repulsive that not only Jews, but liberal Christians as well, began to protest. It appeared as though some hidden power in this country was trying to create dissatisfaction, and effect breaches between the diverse nationalities, as was the case in the old despotic Russia and in present-day Germany. When the protests began, Provost Marshal Crowder openly stated that although the book of instructions was published under his supervision, he has no idea of how that particular paragraph was smuggled in.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0466.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Were such a remark made in one of the half-civilized countries of Europe of today, it would not be at all surprising. But it is incomprehensible that such a thing should occur in America. However, this disgraceful stain on the Jewish escutcheon has now been removed. In the present book of instructions, that particular paragraph has been omitted by order of the President and the Secretary of War.</p>
   <p>And now let us see if there could possibly be the slightest suspicion that foreign-born Jews desire to evade military service on the grounds of illness to a greater extent than foreign-born non-Jews.</p>
   <p>In the last issue of the North American Review there appears an article on this subject by Mr. Louis P. Brown.</p>
   <p>"It cannot be proved," says the author of this article," that the foreign-born and native Jews as a whole are less loyal to their country than their non-Jewish compatriots.(On the other hand, according to the Bureau of Jewish <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0467.jpg" n="3"/>Statistics, we find that the Jews, who constitute barely three per cent of our total population, compose four per cent of our army.) Then what do these anti-Jewish condemnations really indicate? How is it that even in some official circles the Jew is considered a 'slacker'? The condemnation of the rabble can be wholly attributed to ignorance. But how can we explain the fact that intelligent officials believe such slander?"</p>
   <p>It appears that in some cases such a thing (evading service) does occur among Jews, but it also occurs among non-Jews. The Jewish examples seem to be emphasized more, not because they occur more frequently than others, but rather because Jews are of a more sensitive nature. And because they are more sensitive, they make a deeper impression upon those with whom they come in contact. That evidently is why the impression remains that only the Jew seeks to evade military service. Officials who are connected with the draft board state that there are some Jews in the country at this time (fortunately very few) who will make every attempt to evade military service. They would enmesh themselves in a tangle of lies, they would sell their souls and cripple their bodies rather <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0468.jpg" n="4"/>than serve in the army. They are "slackers", of course, but they are courageous and impressive. Of course these "slackers" are not Americans nor are they American-reared. They can be designated as un-Americanized Jews.</p>
   <p>The un-Americanized Jew who lives in this country is not however an integral part of it. Naturally, he is a newly arrived immigrant. What this un-Americanized Jew thinks of war can be told briefly. He thinks that war is the most abominable thing in the world; he hates war. Therefore he will seldom volunteer. He would rather attempt to evade service, and would even consider such evasion to his honor. Many of these un-Americanized Jews do not fear this war because it is a war. Those that come from Russia are terrified by the draft. It reminds them of the Russian military service with all its terror and misery. They recall how they were torn away from their homes, from their dearest and most beloved ones, and cast among brutal and bestial Cossacks. That is the reason why many of these un-Americanized Jews fear the draft so much--it seems to them that it is a reversion to the Russian mode of living.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0469.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>When the Jew becomes Americanized, however, he then becomes entirely different. Then he understands that the Constitution of the United States gives all citizens of the country equal rights, and that this country affords every inhabitant equal opportunity. Then he who originally was a "slacker" is among the first to volunteer, and on the field of battle he is the renowned hero.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
