<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-20">Aug. 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Why the Price of Milk Has Increased</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1435</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1435.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-20">Aug. 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE PRICE OF MILK HAS INCREASED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Friday, Jews living on the West Side and Northwest Side received an announcement informing them that both the United and the Western dairy companies had increased the price of milk. Consumers will now pay one cent more for each quart of milk.</p>
   <p>When businessmen conduct their business in a conscientious manner, and fulfill honorably their obligations to their patrons and to the public, it is the public's duty to support such businessmen. This principle is more applicable to the milk business than to any other business, because the state of health and the nourishment of the people, and especially of children, depend upon milk. Naturally, milk dealers have a greater responsibility than, let us say, clothing or shoe salesmen. Only people with honest business principles can fully understand the difference. The users of dairy products know, or should know, that milk must be sold by reliable dealers, and that they, the <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1436.jpg" n="2"/>customers, must co-operate in every way possible with both milk dealers and milk producers in order to afford them the opportunity to produce finer, purer, and more wholesome milk.</p>
   <p>This preface was given in order to clarify the reason why the prices of milk were increased by the two largest Jewish dairy firms--the United Dairy Company, 835-839 South Hermitage Avenue, and the Western Dairy Company, 1443-1459 Edgemont Avenue.</p>
   <p>The customers unquestionably have a right to ask these two questions: Why was the price of milk raised? Why haven't these two Jewish firms raised the price of milk before? We shall endeavor to answer.</p>
   <p>As human beings who wear clothes, buy food, etc., you must have observed that in recent years the prices of many commodities have been increased. Business intercourse is built on economic law--on scientific calculations. If the price of one product is raised, the prices of other products are directly or <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1437.jpg" n="3"/>indirectly affected.....Some dealers and producers raise the prices of certain articles, not because they suddenly wish to do so, but because they are compelled to do so by factors over which they have no control.</p>
   <p>This situation has now developed in the milk business. In the month of March, the farmers demanded from milk dealers a higher price for raw milk, arguing that it now costs them more for feed and for the maintenance of the farm than it has in the past. This means that the farmers are forced to raise the price of milk or be confronted with serious difficulties in maintaining their farms and cattle, difficulties which might jeopardize the health of milk consumers. After many negotiations, in which the Government participated, the farmers' demand was granted and the price of raw milk was raised, In addition, drivers of milk wagons, plant employees, and those who deliver the other products necessary in the production of milk have all demanded, and received, wage increases.</p>
   <p>Thus milk dealers were forced to raise the price of milk one cent. Otherwise <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1438.jpg" n="4"/>they would either have to go out of business or decrease the cost of production and delivery. The last alternative would mean an inferior grade of milk, and consequently the risking of the health and even the lives of children and grown-ups alike. Thus, if you examine this matter, you, as rational and fair-minded people, must arrive at the conclusion that milk dealers are not to blame. They have not raised the prices of their own volition, for the sake of making more profits, but have been forced to do so.</p>
   <p>The United Dairy, as well as the Western Dairy, as Jewish companies with honest business principles, as companies which have distinguished themselves by their devotion and loyalty to their business, have spared neither money nor labor in establishing the most modern and sanitary plants, in order to produce the finest, healthiest, and most wholesome dairy products. These two Jewish companies have tried in every way possible to avoid an increase in the price of milk. Other companies raised their price long ago. Not wanting to jeopardize their profits, they made no serious effort to prevent the increase <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1439.jpg" n="5"/>in price. However, as we have said, the United Dairy and the Western Dairy wanted to avoid placing this extra burden upon their customers, and, since they paid more for raw milk, for production, and for delivery, they lost money every day for several weeks. But how long can one operate a business on a losing basis?.....The crucial moment came at last, and these companies were forced either to close their plants or to reduce expenses, and the latter alternative would mean lowering the quality of their milk. This the two Jewish companies would not do under any circumstances.</p>
   <p>Since their customers are for the most part intelligent and fair-minded, the companies are convinced that their customers will certainly understand that it is better to pay one cent more than to risk their own, as well as their children's, health. Surely they will not jeopardize their health because of one penny.</p>
   <p>Knowing that the United Dairy and the Western Dairy are not the first and only <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1440.jpg" n="6"/>ones to raise prices, and taking into consideration the great sacrifices the Jewish dairies have made in an effort to avoid an increase in price, the tens of thousands of Jewish customers will surely realize what duty and responsibility they must shoulder in co-operating in the production of pure and wholesome milk. They will gladly sacrifice the trifle of one cent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
