<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-29">Mar. 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Miss Jane Addams and the Frank Case</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1037</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1037.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-29">Mar. 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MISS JANE ADDAMS AND THE FRANK CASE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Miss Jane Addams, the famous Chicago social worker, sent a letter to a teacher of women suffragettes, in which she urges all women of Atlanta to protest the sentence imposed upon Leo M. Frank, and to request in his behalf a new trial at which the whole matter of the killing of little Mary Fagen should be clarified.</p>
   <p>The famous Miss Addams also states that it is contrary to human feeling and human intelligence to keep a person enwrapped in the shadow of death, without knowing positively whether he is actually guilty of a crime. As long as there is a doubt as Frank's guilt, we face the possibility of taking an innocent man to his premature death.</p>
   <p>Miss Addams's letter has had a desirable effect. The women of Atlanta and of the entire country started a vigorous movement the object of which is to obtain a new trial for Frank. Everywhere there is manifested a warm sympathy <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1038.jpg" n="2"/>toward Frank, who has already been convicted of murder by a jury.</p>
   <p>That this movement and sympathy are very characteristic can be seen by the fact that they evolved after the court had already determined the fate of the accused. Notwithstanding the fact that Frank had already been branded as a murderer, the people instead of forsaking him began to demand justice and truth. This phenomenon itself shows that we are living in an age when we can no longer crush justice or lead the people blindly. In spite of the verdict of a jury, the nation wants to know definitely whether or not the accused actually committed the crime.</p>
   <p>Yet, we must acknowledge that the fact that women showed a keener interest in this movement than men, is an unfavorable circumstance. In the case of Frank, the men have just as much, if not more, interest than the women, because not only were the jurors, judges, and the accused men, but the public opinion of justice rested on the opinion of men.</p>
   <p>Should there ever come a moment when we need to decide the guilt or innocence of such an intricate, involved matter as the Frank case, the men ought to be <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1039.jpg" n="3"/>the first and most active to do it, because the vast experience the men have gained in jurisprudence will enable them to untangle the mysterious clew and bring everything to light.</p>
   <p>It is therefore necessary that at the same time the women demand a new trial for Frank the men should do likewise in order to establish truth and justice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
