<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Sentinel</title>,
Volumes 15-16; Week of <date when="1914-09-04">September 4, 1914</date>. Page 23.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1206</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1206.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Sentinel</title>,
Volumes 15-16; Week of <date when="1914-09-04">September 4, 1914</date>. Page 23.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judge Philip P. Bregstone is a candidate for judge of the Municipal Court. His life story is one of achievement from obscurity to prominence. At the age of twenty, he arrived in this country. After a short stay in New York, he came to Chicago in August 1887, and has remained here since.</p>
   <p>Judge Bregstone became associate editor of the Jewish Courier. He continued in that post for a year until he gained a knowledge of the English language. He then began to contribute articles to the German and English magazines and became a special writer for the Sunday editions of the Chicago newspapers on Russian and Jewish life. In 1894, he was a member of the editorial staff of the, Inter Ocean and in 1895, he matriculated at the Lake Forest University for the study of law.</p>
   <p>Judge Bregstone was admitted to the bar in 1897. As assistant city prosecutor, he was assigned to the most cosmopolitan court inthe city, the Maxwell police court. After rendering invaluable services for four years, his ability was recognized by Mayor Dunne, who promoted him to the position of assistant city attorney. Mr. Bregstone is active in all communal affairs and matters pertaining to Jewish problems. He has devoted his time and services gratis as attorney for the bureau of personal service.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
