<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1917-12-01">December 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">How Judge Fisher Carries on His Campaign</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1917-12-01">December 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">HOW JUDGE FISHER CARRIES ON HIS CAMPAIGN</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(EDITORIAL)</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judge Harry Fisher, noted leader of the closed Maimonides Hospital, is already preparing for his next campaign. There is certainly nothing wrong about this, but it is wrong of the orthodox synagogues to transform their Houses of God into political halls. They, the leaders of the orthodox synagogues, evince in this, that they do not think in serious terms of their Judaism. First of all, they are all "business men" and the fate of their political bosses stands higher to them than their God and Torah (Law).</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, if the pious Jews are pleased, that their synagogues should be utilized for politics, and that all sorts of politicians should be advertized at the Holy Ark, it is their concern. An orthodox synagogue, in America, is not a public institution, but a private enterprise of a certain organization. Therefore no one may say anything about the synagogue being not considered as a House of God, but a political meeting hall. It is a terrible disappointment to those good and pious people to learn that their synagogue is a voting place; that their rabbi is more of a politician than an erudite man.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0256.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This judge, also, does not conduct himself as was expected of him. According to his "fame" earned at the Maimonides Hospital, and his association with certain "social workers," he should be a bit more careful of his false accusation against the Socialists. A young man, as he is, should have a higher ambition than the cheap career of a ward politician.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
