<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-04-25">April 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Peace! Peace! an Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0666</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0666.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-04-25">April 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">PEACE! PEACE! AN EDITORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Next week we shall hear the word, Peace, resound in many Chicago halls, in the churches, and in the press, for the Second National Peace Conference is to be held in Chicago, the beginning of next month. Elaborate preparations have been made by citizens who are interested in bringing peace on earth, and good-will amongst men. They want to make these meetings as impressive and pompous as possible.</p>
   <p>Governor Deneen will receive the delegates to the Peace Conference in the name of the state, and Mayor Busse will greet them in the name of the city. Every peace-living, progressive, and intelligent citizen is expected to be there in order to make the conference a huge success.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0667.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to make the Peace Conference more impressive, special peace meetings haven been arranged in the public schools, where well-known speakers and educators will talk to the youth about the values of peace, and will acquaint the boys and girls with the aims of that conference.</p>
   <p>It is, therefore, necessary to let our readers know, in advance, about that important event. Any of our readers who understand English, and are not working on those days, must avail themselves of the opportunity, to be present at the peace Conference. It will be a noble expression of peace loving people. The Congress, itself, will be an altruistic phenomenon that is not often experienced in a world of race hatred, where one nation tries to subdue the other nation by might rather than right.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0668.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We live now in a world of extreme envy and economic rivalry and greed, and the slightest provocation is hardly necessary to plunge the European nations into a general war.</p>
   <p>At such time of stress, let us hear the voices of Peace! Peace! echo and re-echo throughout Chicago. Let's hear the voices who believe that right is might, and who also hope that civilized humanity will soon shake off the spell of hatred towards one another, and will come to the realization that war, cruelty, and blood-shed is not necessary among the organized nations of the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0669.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>For the Jews, such a Peace Congress has a double significance. In the first place, the Jewish sentiment for peace is the main issue at the conference, for it was our great prophet Isaiah, who expressed the Jewish sentiment in such noble words as, "One nation will no more raise a sword against the other, and no more will warfare be taught amongst them."</p>
   <p>These words will be discussed at the Congress. They will be interpreted, and paraphrased in many different ways, but the main idea is the same. In the second place, the Jewish people can only hope to exist as a nation when right will be might, and the rights of every people to exist as a nationality would be recognized as in the United States, where the rights of an individual is an immutable law.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
