<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-09">June 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Can We Expect Peace Soon?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-09">June 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CAN WE EXPECT PEACE SOON?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When a whole country is thrown into as gigantic a war as America is at present fighting against the German autocracy, it is always best for the average citizen, who is unfamiliar with diplomatic intrigues and political labyrinths to take stock for himself. As a single small link in the mighty chain called the American people, how long must he gird his loins and ever be ready, in any undertaking, to aid in bringing the war to a victorious end (for his country)?</p>
   <p>In a world war, such as the present one, we find an insatiable power-seeking group seeking to place under its yoke all the free nations that stand in its path[as it moves] toward world domination. At such a time, it is not enough that we send soldiers to fight for and seal our liberty with their blood,while we sit back with folded arms. The body of the nation is passing through a period of high fever, and every limb, be it directly affected or <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0461.jpg" n="2"/>not, must add its power of resistance to the whole, otherwise the body of the sick one is in grave danger. So it is with our country. All industries, all institutions, all movements, all thoughts, all people, must dedicate their utmost vigor--must make the necessary sacrifice so that our country and our allies may be successful; so that they may establish for future generations a glorious heritage--justice between nation and nation. We shall be able to attain this goal only through an honorable peace.</p>
   <p>There is no greater authority on American war policy and program, next to President Wilson himself, than the Secretary of State. He has the power to conduct our foreign affairs and to determine our foreign-relations policy. During the ceremony at which Columbia University conferred the honorary degree of LL. D. upon our Secretary of State, Robert Lansing, and our kinsman, the British Ambassador, Earl Reading, Mr. Lansing said:</p>
   <p>"Let us not look backwards at the military objectives where we were defeated in this great "Gog and Magog" war [war of annihilation], which we could not <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0462.jpg" n="3"/>escape. We are fighting against an old, established, well-organized army across the sea--we are facing a "war-chest" that for two generations has devoted itself entirely to preparations for war. We dare not look back upon our criminal mistakes--our eyes must only be directed forward. Our whole organization, as a national unit, must be pressed into service so that we will not be defeated in our forthcoming plans.</p>
   <p>"The Prussian proposals for such peace plans as will strengthen the power of the German government and perpetuate its reign, are base and treacherous. They may be compared to our own critics and faultfinders apropos our government's war-program.</p>
   <p>"Prussia sought war, sinful, criminal war; she planned to spread herself all over the world and to control the European forces of land and sea. Now America says, 'Let her [Prussia] have war, and war, and war,until she is fed up [with war]. And henceforth, she will shiver and tremble at the mere mention of the word 'war'. Force is the only antidote for force. Force is the only <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0463.jpg" n="4"/>way to end the Prussian bloodthirstiness. Force is the only thing that the Prussians believe in and respect."</p>
   <p>From this speech of Secretary Lansing, upon such an important occasion, we can understand what the German peace proposals are likely to be. The clever and knavish diplomacy which they [the Germans] now dealt the conquered provinces of the Russian Republic, where they have instituted a new type of government "made in Germany"; their seditious acts in Mexico against America, where they have spent millions for propaganda; their attempts to instigate a revolution in Ireland; and dozens of other acts indicate that Germany is attempting to create a continuous state of political upheaval and chaos; from all these things we can understand that America will not give in to a "German" peace, even though Germany offers to return Belgium, Serbia, and everything which she robbed from France.</p>
   <p>This is the task that America now has. And the whole American nation will <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0464.jpg" n="5"/>help to accomplish it with the aid which our army can render and with the great possibilities rendered by our natural resources and financial strength.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
