<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929">1929</date>.
<title level="a">[Vocational Guidance]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0679</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0679.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929">1929</date>.
<title level="a">[VOCATIONAL GUIDANCE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This bring me again to another problem with which I have been grappling for quite a number of years. Twenty-seven years of experience with thousands of young men and young women who have undertaken vocations and professions for which they were wholly unfit, has brought me to the conclusion that in the interest of the individual, and more so in the interest of the community, as a whole, the time has come when, in connection with the Institute, a psychological clinic or bureau be established for the purpose of making a careful scientific observation of those with whom we come in contact and who will in a great many cases fall into the same pit of the misfit as have the others in years gone by.</p>
   <p>Harvard University, some twenty odd years ago, made a very distinct contribution in recognizing this problem and has established a department known as Vocational Guidance and Direction. This department has interested itself, not only in the professions, but also has gone into the problem of industry and commerce from the same point of view.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0680.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is a psychological and sociological truism that when one follows a vocation or a profession for which he has a distinct liking or aptitude and has all the necessary qualifications that go into the making up of a successful person in such a profession or vocation, that the individual concerned will be happy and successful, all things being equal. The psychologists and sociologists recognize only too truly the converse of this near axiom.</p>
   <p>Since the Harvard experience, there have been sporadic attempts in this important direction, but they were only sporadic. An example is the appointment of a dean of men and a dean of women in practically every college and university in the country. Primarily, the function of such a dean is to give vocational and professional direction to students at the college who may come for such advice. In order to show the futility of this situation, I might cite the following example: The University of Illinois has approximately 9,000 students. One dean of men is charged with the responsibility of looking after the welfare of the young men of the University of Illinois. This includes their pranks, their misdemeanors, and their scholastic rating. One need not go into detail to show <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0681.jpg" n="3"/>how utterly impossible it is for one man to take the interest that is necessary for proper and direction, especially if that interest and guidance is ultimately to help the young person to make up his mind definitely as to what he is going to do as a member of society when he leaves the institution. Vocational and professional direction should begin with the child as soon as it enters its formal educational program, in order that some day we may be able to look forward to an army of growing youth in America who will be happier and who will intelligently fall into their proper nook as members of society. This however, is a dream that may take many years to reach a state of fruition, and for that reason private organizations who have sufficient wisdom and the inclination to experiment along these lines and to make a contribution to the field at large must establish this kind of a psychological bureau for vocational and professional direction.</p>
   <p>In all of its departments, the Institute contemplates touching directly in the neighborhood of from 2,000 to 3,500 young people between the ages of 15 and 19, a very important period in the life of our youth when <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0682.jpg" n="4"/>they must more or less definitely make up their minds as to what their future responsibility in life is to be. My experience has been, especially in connection with the Institute for the past 15 years, that many of the young men and young women who have come under my direction and under the direction of the Institute through our Educational Department, that many, if not most of them, who attend our schools, feel that they are doing so with the object in view of entering either the fields of medicine, law, engineering, dentistry or pharmacy. To be sure, many have actually undertaken to follow their respective ambitions without much direction and without much guidance, with the result that too many have joined the already over-crowded fields of medicine, law, dentistry, and engineering, of the type who are wholly unfit to measure up to the necessary requirements of personality and scholarship for the successful development of these respective fields. Many of these, if this proposed bureau had been in operation years ago, would have been advised to go into business in one form or another, either as bookkeepers, clerks, stenographers, etc. There is no question that in the instance of those who have <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0683.jpg" n="5"/>made a colossal failure of their ambitions, they would have been very much happier if they had gone into business. I personally, have been responsible in the last fifteen years in discouraging more young men from going into the professions because I was conscious of the futility of the ambitions of a great many of them, than were any one, or groups of persons in this city, to my knowledge. It is my hope that such a bureau may be established at the earliest possible time. It is my further hope that someone in the community may be found who recognizes the tremendous constructive value of such a piece of work and who will finance it to the extent of $15,000 a year for a period of five years.</p>
   <p>The personnel of such a bureau would include a well-trained and experienced physician and psychologist who would give full time, an assistant who would give part time, a stenographer who would assist in the keeping of careful records in the instance of each person who comes for aid to the bureau for the necessary appliances, for examination purposes, and other miscellaneous requirements.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0684.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>I feel certain that at the end of five years there will be a body of information and experience which would lead the Institute in the direction in the form of a book which would clearly designate the importance of the field of work, and the Institute, indirectly, would have made a contribution to what is possibly the most important piece of experimental work in the direction of a better and a more wholesome development in the field of vocational selection.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
