<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title><bibl><title>Forward</title>,
    <date when="1932-02-16">Feb. 16, 1932</date>.
    <title level="a">Judge Cardozo, A Jew, Nominated to Supreme Court; Quick Confirmation by Senate Expected</title></bibl></title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0091</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
            <date when="1932-02-16">Feb. 16, 1932</date>.
            <title level="a">Judge Cardozo, A Jew, Nominated to Supreme Court; Quick Confirmation by Senate Expected</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
  <p>President Hoover nominated today Judge Benjamin N. Cardozo, a Jew, of New York, as a member of the United States Supreme Court, in place of Justice Oliver Wendel Holmes, who resigned several weeks ago due to ill health and advanced age.</p>
  <p>The president at once sent the nomination of Cardozo to the Senate for confirmation.</p>
  <p>Cardozo was supported by the United States Senators from New York and many progressive Senators, like Borah, Borris, and La Follette, etc., as well asnumerous organizations throughout the country.</p>
  <p>Before nominating Cardozo to the High Tribunal, Hoover conferred with Senator Watson, Republican Leader in the Senate, and other Republican leaders.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0091.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Cardozo is a Democrat, is the Chief Justice of the New York State Court of Appeals (The Supreme Court of the state), and is one of the most liberal and most famous lawyers in the country.</p>
   <p>Immediately upon the resignation of Justice Holmes, Cardozo's name was mentioned as a worthy successor to the venerable liberal Justice. For a while it looked as though Hoover would not nominate Cardozo, the latter being considered as too liberal.</p>
   <p>The former Justice Holmes expressed great satisfaction upon learning of Cardozo's nomination by President Hoover.</p>
   <p>Cardozo is a Portuguese Jew, a descendant of an old aristocratic family who came to America before the time of the Revolution against England.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0092.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He was born in New York sixty-three years ago and received a good education. He is a graduate of five universities, Columbia, Yale, New York, Michigan, and Harvard.</p>
   <p>Among lawyers, he is recongized as one of the greatest authorities on law. For five generations the Cardozo family has belonged to the Portuguese Synagogue in New York. An uncle of his, the Reverend Lyons, was a cantor in the Portuguese Synagogue sixty years ago, and a cousin of his was a trustee of Columbia University during the time of the American Revolution.</p>
   <p>Cardozo is the second Jew to be nominated to the United States Supreme Court. The first was Justice Brandeis, who was nominated to the High Tribunal by President Wilson, who had to fight very hard for the Senate's confirmation. Brandeis was opposed for being a liberal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0093.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>No opposition is contemplated against Cardozo by the Senate, whose confirmation is expected shortly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
