<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-12-08">Dec. 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Action Wanted</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0884</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0884.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-12-08">Dec. 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ACTION WANTED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Life does not stand still. It throbs and shifts and varies. Each change brings new conditions, creates new circumstances, gives birth to new desires and new demands.</p>
   <p>Today we have heard three variations concerning these new conditions and circumstances and their results. But of the three not even one presented a necessary logical solution on the subject discussed.</p>
   <p>Dr. Elliott, of Harvard University, in his lecture traced the changes that occurred in our local economic life over a period of seventy years, showing its resulting effects. Craftsmanship gave place to the factory system, which jeopardizes the existence of the nation. It has made life difficult, sapping the strength of man both physically and mentally.</p>
   <p>Young orthodox Rockefeller, in his Cleveland church, presented chastisement in his Godfearing sermon. Afterwards, just outside the church, he <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0885.jpg" n="2"/>addressed a large crowd, saying: If the sun would shine forever, people would feel happy.</p>
   <p>A clerk from a Chicago Court stated that during the last week, when everywhere everything was at its darkest, the number of incoming cases increased greatly.</p>
   <p>All three indicated that there was something wrong in our lives, yet failed to mention any line of action for its remedy.</p>
   <p>Well, of the ordinary court clerk we cannot expect more. He noticed a specific phenomenon and presented it. Of the pious Mr. Rockefeller there is also very little we may expect. He believes in hearty prayers to heaven so the sun will shine.</p>
   <p>But the learned Dr. Elliott should have had more to say on the subject than merely pointing out developments.</p>
   <p>To mourn the present and look back longingly on the waning yesterday is no solution. The factory system is here to stay. It is an advancement <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0886.jpg" n="3"/>in our development and not a setback. We shall not again return to the old methods. What is necessary is that man should not be sacrificed on the altar of the new methods of life.</p>
   <p>In this case no philosophical sighs or pious Rockefeller sermons are of any avail. It necessitates practical action. The motto of the day being: Action Wanted! It is definitely necessary that the millions of people sweating in the factories be adjusted under better circumstances to new-developing methods. Life must be so regulated that man may grow and develop physically and mentally and not that he sink or perish.</p>
   <p>It is not enough to simply prevent the hovering of the fog over the streets, or that the sun shines in the heavens. We need the sun to shine in the streets, in the factories, in all the homes and corners of life. These are the logical endings for the given facts which to be realized demand action.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
