<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-07">Apr. 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Jews Are Buying Liberty Bonds</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-07">Apr. 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">JEWS ARE BUYING LIBERTY BONDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jews of Chicago are buying Liberty Bonds of the Third American Liberty Loan as Jews. This was noted yesterday in the first day of the campaign. Wherever Jews bought Liberty Bonds, they demanded that the words, "Jewish Section", should be written upon the applications. This of course does credit to Americans Jews, and will be continued for the duration of the campaign. The banks in the Jewish neighborhoods provided themselves with stamps marked "Jewish Section". When a Jew comes to a bank where there is no such stamp, he should demand that the clerk write in "Jewish Section" in long hand.</p>
   <p>At the Covenant Club where a Liberty Loan Station has been established, the campaign was opened yesterday noon with a luncheon, at which Professor Baker and the well-known Jewish banker, Moses E. Greenebaum, were the main speakers <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0566.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Greenbaum strongly emphasized the necessity for Jews to buy Liberty Bonds as Jews. In this campaign the entire Jewish community of Chicago is united, and committees have been appointed in all neighborhoods, where Liberty Bonds will be sold.</p>
   <p>The present loan will be quickly subscribed, for the American Nation was never so enthusiastic about the war as it is now. The Jews, together with the great masses of non-Jews, will do their utmost to buy Liberty Bonds. First because the investment in itself is the finest in the world, bringing 4 1/4% interest; second, because it supports our Army and Navy, which has long been active on the European front to conquer the foe of free countries and little nations--the hated and despised Prussian Junkerdom.</p>
   <p>After the conclusion of the speeches at the Covenant Club, the attending guests subscribed at once for Liberty Bonds to the sum of $50,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0567.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Z. B. Komaiko speaks in behalf of Liberty Bonds at all performances of Leon Blank's Haymarket Theatre. He will also speak there today at both presentations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
