<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-16">Mar. 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to the West Side Aldermen</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1128</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1128.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-16">Mar. 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO THE WEST SIDE ALDERMEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This evening the City Council will again deal with the matter of forbidding smoking in street cars. Last Monday, when this ordinance was brought forth, the majority of West Side aldermen opposed this restriction, and it was therefore sent back to the Judiciary Committee, in order to undergo certain changes. This evening, it will be decided upon in the City Council whether to do away entirely with smoking in street cars or to permit smoking on the front platform, as is now the rule.</p>
   <p>We understand full well the motive of the West Side aldermen for not acting hastily in forbidding smoking in street cars. These aldermen represent a class of people who are hard workers, mostly poor wage earners, who have neither the time nor the means to smoke all day. In the morning, while still chewing their last morsel of breakfast, they run hurriedly in order <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1129.jpg" n="2"/>to catch a street car, lest they arrive late at work. And the street car is the only place where they can smoke their pipes, cigars or cigarettes. In the factory, or wherever they may be working, they are not permitted to smoke during working hours. So they can hardly wait until six o'clock, when they dash off for their street cars, on which they refresh themselves by lighting up something to smoke. To protect this personal liberty of the workers, their representatives [the aldermen] have sought to arbitrate and even sent back the ordinance for bidding smoking in street cars to the Judiciary Committee.</p>
   <p>But now, when this law shall once again be acted upon, may the West Side aldermen take into consideration the motorman, who is also no more than a poor worker and who suffers severely from the smokers' cravings. They should be very thoughtful of the motorman, who continuously drives the car and thereby strains his five senses so as to avoid accidents. He cannot, under any circumstances, do his work as it should be done, when surrounded by people</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
