<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-06-22">June 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The United Hebrew Trades in a United Front on the Political Field</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0060</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0060.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-06-22">June 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNITED HEBREW TRADES IN A UNITED FRONT ON THE POLITICAL FIELD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very important question is to be discussed at the central body of the Jewish unions in Chicago. At the last meeting of the United Hebrew Trades, it was determined that at the next meeting, which will take place, this Sunday, the question how to establish a united political front of all the Jewish progressive trade unions will be discussed. This is the most important question that the Jewish unions ever have had come before them.</p>
   <p>The time is here when the unions must interest themselves with political action on the ground of a class struggle, at least, with their economic activities. Some unions always, may have been socialistic and always interested, but it is necessary that all unions should be interested. Every intelligent organized worker knows what is now taking place in this country, that organized capitalists with the aid of the Government, and the Courts, are undermining the foundation of the unions and taking <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0061.jpg" n="2"/>away the rights of the organized workers, who have won through years of struggle against the temple of capital. The unions are being robbed of their human, citizen, and worker's rights, due to political power being in the hands of those who possess economical power. Those possessing political strength are united in a solid front against the organized workers.</p>
   <p>The Legislature, Congress and the Courts are working hand in hand, to take away from organized workers the improved conditions they have so long struggled for. Through various so-called laws, never actually enacted, and by voiding laws that were enacted by Congress, these capitalists succeed in suppressing the workers, and depriving them of their freedom, at every move.</p>
   <p>What can the workers do in such a case? The answer is: A united political front on the ground of class struggle to gain political power for the workers. The organized worker must unite, in order to have a voice, and be able to use their influence in the law-making bodies, city, state, and <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0062.jpg" n="3"/>Federal.</p>
   <p>If the organized workers want to protect their economic conditions, retain the remaining freedom and rights, and to get back what has been taken away from them, by the bosses through their political power, they must follow the example of the capitalists. The Citizens Committee, the Open Shop, the Chamber of Commerce, the Employers Association, the Civic Federations, the Union League Club, all these organized capitalist organizations are united on the same basis; they all have faith in political action as the best remedy to protect their interests against the class interests of the organized worker. It is therefore time for the Jewish organized workers to unite, and use the best and only remedy that adds strength to the class that use political power, and to start a strong political campaign through which the workers of Chicago will gain political power enough to place them in a class, as true strugglers for the interests of all workers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
