<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1919-01">Dec. 1918-Jan. 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[Needs of the Jewish Community]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0791</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0791.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1919-01">Dec. 1918-Jan. 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[NEEDS OF THE JEWISH COMMUNITY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The districts into which our former neighbors have moved are approximately three and a half to five miles from the Institute respectively; One is the great Lawndale district with an approximate Jewish population of 100,000. The other is the North West Side, with an approximate Jewish population of 75,000. These districts have grown, particularly the Lawndale district, in so rapid a fashion that it was most difficult to keep up with its growth, in that section of the city as well as on the North West Side. But particularly in the Lawndale district, there is practically no facility provided for the expression of the people who live there. There is no Institution to meet the perfectly natural demand of an outlet for the residents along social, recreational and intellectual lines.</p>
   <p>Outside of a number of Talmud Torahs that have been established to meet the purely religious needs of the community, the children have no avenue of self-expression sufficient for their purpose. The young men and the young women are likewise placed in an embarrassing position and have to <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0792.jpg" n="2"/>find avenues of recreation and social contacts which very often lead into dangerous channels. These are no theories. The statements which I have made are based upon facts; facts that unfortunately stare us in the face and cause us to be ashamed of our neglect.</p>
   <p>In the Juvenile Court, the Boys Court, and other socialized courts in our city, it was formerly the pride of the Jew to be able to state that as far as he was concerned these courts might never have been today. He finds himself in a position of having to bend the head in shame and to face daily, upon visitation in these same courts, the call from the daily docket of the Golsteins and the Bernsteins in much larger numbers than is at all necessary, and all, in my opinion, because the community was near-sighted and negligent and did not provide the necessary social machinery to give these boys who today are 18, 20, and 25 years of age the chance, ten years ago, to function as normal children should, so that they consequently found their own methods of social contact, with these consequent results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
