<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1894-04-27">April 27, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">An Original Enterprise</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1489</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1489.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1894-04-27">April 27, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">AN ORIGINAL ENTERPRISE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Competition in business is responsible for many strange enterprises. The subject of this article, Mr. Solms Marcus, is the father of one of the strangest of these. At 161 Fifth avenue is a five-story building, unpretentious, but marked by the signs of uninterrupted activity. This is the home of the Apollo Custom Pants manufacturers.</p>
   <p>The Apollo Custom Pants manufacturers commenced only eight years ago the making exclusively of custom made pants, and the sale price of them is $4 each pair, no more, no less. Every pair of pants is made to the exact measurement of the customer. The business grew rapidly under this idea, the establishment being the only one of this kind in the United States.</p>
   <p>Mr. Marcus was born in Berlin, Prussia, in 1847. He came to this country when a boy of seven years, with his father, who located at Milwaukee, Wis. At his thirteenth year he left home to shift for himself, making Chicago his future home. When twenty-two years old, he was married and in 1871, the great fire consumed his possessions. Later he became the superintendent <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1490.jpg" n="2"/>of the manufacturing department of Hart Bros., extensive wholesale clothiers and manufacturers of furnishing goods in Chicago, for a continuous service of fourteen years. Mr. Marcus left that firm for the purpose of giving his entire attention to the business of the Apollo Custom Pants manufactures.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
