<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1919-01">January, 1919</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0788</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0788.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1919-01">January, 1919</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Child Welfare.</p>
   <p>Late last spring, I brought to your attention the calling made by the United States Government through its Child Bureau and different Social Agencies of America to help save 100,000 babies of the 300,000 that die every year, and whose deaths are avoidable. Illinois had a quota assigned to it of 5,625. This quota was subdivided again throughout the entire state, and naturally Chicago had the largest share. The various agencies of Chicago volunteered their facilities and cooperation, and in the same spirit, the Institute offered its cooperation.</p>
   <p>Our Bureau was open fron 1 P.M. to 5 P.M. daily, with the exception of Saturday and Sunday, the first day being June 15. During this time, infants and babies under six were weighed and measured and otherwise examined as to their general physical well being. The station was in charge of our trained nurse, who devoted her time between the Infant Welfare Station and the grounds.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0789.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A volunteer registrar was assigned each afternoon to assist the nurse in making out duplicate records, one for the Government and a copy which remained with us. Any child that was underweight or under measure or did not pass the general inspection was reported for medical and other attention to the General Child Welfare Bureau and the Volunteer Nurses Association.</p>
   <p>In connection with the Bureau, an Infant Welfare Exhibit was in constant progress. Some sixty charts in Yiddish and in English graphically illustrating the step by step development of child welfare from prenatal times until it passes its youthful period were described the mothers who visited the Bureau. Those who were unable to read and appreciate the English charts had the opportunity of reading and studying and observing the charts in Yiddish placed next to the English ones. We hope to continue this educational work throughout the entire year, and to send our exhibit, which is probably the only one in the city, especially the Yiddish charts, to the different settlements and schools in our immediate vicinity. Over 500 babies have been given individual attention, and <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0790.jpg" n="3"/>we hope that before the year is over, we may be able to report having examined and looked after the interest and welfare of a thousand babies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
