<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-26">May 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Wheel of Life</title><title level="a" type="sub">From Reader to Reader</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-26">May 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE WHEEL OF LIFE</title><title level="a" type="sub">From Reader to Reader</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Dear Editor:</p>
   <p>As constant readers of your worthy newspaper, we hope that you will publish our letter and also say a few words to our daughter whom we mention herein. I talked this matter over with my wife and she agreed that I should write to you.</p>
   <p>"We are middle-aged people, close to fifty. We have six children all of whom are quite prudent, especially the three oldest ones, two boys and a girl. Thanks to them, I am in business now for myself and making a fairly nice living.</p>
   <p>"We came to America in 1905, shortly after the bloody pogroms spread throughout Russia immediately after the publication of the manifesto of October 17 by the Czar.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0491.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>we decided then and there to leave forever that cursed land where Jewish blood is shed so freely and to emigrate to America where the Jew emjoys equality of freedom with the Gentile.</p>
   <p>"My children grew up as true Americans and as such are body and soul for America. When this country was forced into the war, the two oldest boys enlisted immediately and both left in the same week last February for camp.</p>
   <p>"My oldest daughter, who is 22 years old, is now about to enlist in the Red Cross and is eager to leave in a few weeks with a unit for France. We pleaded with her, 'As a Jewish girl, why don't you enlist, instead, in the Red Shield of David?' She replies that she would rather risk her life for the whole of humanity than just for Jews alone. Besides, she claims that there are many Jews on the battlefields of France. She argues that in times of stress no distinction should be made--Jew or Gentile, a human's life must be saved.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0492.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"We therefore appeal to you to say a few words to her, that for a Jewish girl the Shield of David is better fitted to enlist in than the 'Cross'. We are anxious to show her your reply.</p>
   <p>With many thanks,</p>
   <p>The Parents."</p>
   <p>Reply: We cannot dissuade their daughter from enlisting in the Red Cross. It is possible that if they had given their daughter a real Jewish education, she would have herself been attracted to the Shield of David.</p>
   <p>But they need not be bitter about it. They need not fear the "red cross", because the Red Cross is one of the most noble and mose useful institutions which the world possesses. It helps enormously in time of misfortune, even in peace time, and especially in war.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
