<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-10-31">Oct. 31, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">"What Is Happening in the Unions in Chicago,"</title><title level="a" type="sub">by M. Zeskind</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0715</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0715.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-10-31">Oct. 31, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">"WHAT IS HAPPENING IN THE UNIONS IN CHICAGO,"</title><title level="a" type="sub">by M. Zeskind</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Wright, the business agent of the Capmakers' Union, Local 5, reported conditions in the trade are not as they should be.</p>
   <p>Lately a number of small non-union shops opened in various quarters of the city, thereby causing some of the bigger bosses to fight against the union.</p>
   <p>The local determined to combat the open shops and will carry on a strong organization campaign to do away with the open shops which are detrimental to the organized cap makers. The organized workers can be a great help to the capmakers in their efforts to organize the non-union cap makers, simply by being careful when buying caps for themselves or their children that the union label is in every cap. There is no work attached and it does not cost the buyer of the cap any more for the union label.</p>
   <pb n="2"/>
   <p>It is just a matter of being in earnest and feeling that you are a union worker or sympathizer of unionism.</p>
   <p>Delegate Weinstein of carpenters' local 504 reported that his local donated $200 towards the house of Debs. Comrade Henry, the manager of the House of Debs Association, addressed members, explaining the necessity of building a labor temple in the name of Debs.</p>
   <p>Delegate Goldfarb of the Jewish Waiters Union claims that the union people have many ways of helping union waiters to be employed in restaurants, by seeing that the waiters wear a union button, and insist that you be served by union waiters.</p>
   <p>The thousands of retail clerks working in the various stores in three vicinities of the city, Northwest, Douglas Park, and West Side, will now hear very often of the Retail Clerks Union Local 195. This local started 
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0716.jpg" n="3"/>
   a campaign to organize the thousands of men and women working in the cloak, shoe, furnishing and clothing stores. Delegate Cooper of this local has suggested to the executive of the United Hebrew Trades that the organizer should join as a member of the organizing committee of local 195 and help in the work of carrying on the organizing campaign. The United Hebrew Trades granted this demand and instructed the executive to do all in their power to help local 195 in their work.</p>
   <p>The question of establishing an educational bureau to educate the workers through the unions, was discussed at the United Hebrew Trades for a long time.</p>
   <p>At the last meeting Miss F. Cohen, vice-president of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union and vice president of the Workmen's Education Committee, gave an interesting lecture on workers' education and the delegates unanimously determined to recommend all the affiliated locals to uphold the United Hebrew Trades or organizing a joint educational committee, with one member of each local in the committee. This committee <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0717.jpg" n="4"/>will work out a plan for conducting the educational work.</p>
   <p>A letter will be sent to each union regarding this decision, and it is hoped that all the unions will support this important work.</p>
   <p>Wednesday night the first labor school in Chicago was established by a great union.</p>
   <p>The first step was taken in the office of the Joint Board by the shop chairmen, chairladies, and members of all the executive boards, in the presence of Miss Fannie Cohen, vice-president of the International; Professor Paul H. Douglas, of the University of Chicago; and Professor Arthur V. Cudenhauser.</p>
   <p>Comrade Bialis, manager of the Joint Board, introduced Miss Cohen as <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0718.jpg" n="5"/>chairman of the evening. She discussed the importance of educating the union members and submitted a program to be used in educating the members of the unions. The program is as follows:</p>
   <p>Course No. 1. Work in Modern Capitalist Society, by Dr. Paul Douglas.</p>
   <p>Course No. 2. Current Economic and Labor Problems, by Prof. H. A. Millis.</p>
   <p>Course No. 3. Social Psyhology, by Professor Kornhauser.</p>
   <p>Course No. 4. Social Interpretation of English Literature.</p>
   <p>Course No. 5. Historical Problems in the Aims of the American Trade Union Movement, by Allen B. Farbsberg.</p>
   <p>Course No. 6. Speakers' class in parliamentary rules.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0719.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Course No. 7. The English language.</p>
   <p>Course No. 8. Health and hygiene.</p>
   <p>Course No. 9. Physical exercises; Social meetings.</p>
   <p>After Miss Cohen presented the program. Professor Douglas delivered a short lecture on the course that he will give the members. He pointed out that the workers need education to understand their part in modern industrial society, and the means for overcoming the wage system. He said that the workers have three methods they must use to accomplish their aim: the trade unions, the cooperative movement, and the political labor party.</p>
   <p>Through these three methods the workers can improve their conditions and attain a degree of influence and power in modern economic society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0720.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Professor Kornhauser explained the meaning of social psychology and showed that people do not realize why they think the way they do. He stated that people, conservatives as well as radicals, fool themselves when they lay the blame of certain conditions on human nature.</p>
   <p>The professor affirmed that social psychology is a new science and is not sufficient developed to give the people to understand that the nature of mankind is not inflexible and constant. It can be changed when the factors affecting mankind are clearly understood.</p>
   <p>These professors will give courses to the members of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
