<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-05-24">May 24, 1917</date><title level="a">Loeb Reveals Conspiracy against School Board</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-05-24">May 24, 1917</date><title level="a">LOEB REVEALS CONSPIRACY AGAINST SCHOOL BOARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jacob Loeb, president of the Board of Education, caused a great sensation yesterday by his special message, at an extraordinary meeting of the Board of Education, in which he revealed the ignominious acts of the city administration against the School Board. Mr. Loeb showed in his message how the Mayor's advisor, Fred Lundin, had commanded and forced Mr. Thompson to break his word to the Impartial League of Prominent Citizens and execute the order from the ward committeemen.</p>
   <p>Mr. Loeb's message will go down as a historical document. It is permeated with the spirit of a fighting soul which can no longer bear the outrages committed by the mayor against the Board of Education. Loeb detected a great danger hanging over the public schools and how unclean politicians seek to undermine the most sacred and most beautiful of all public institutions, the school. And therefore he decided to remain silent no longer, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0361.jpg" n="2"/>but to step out in an open fight against the Mayor and his counselors, revealing their acts to the world and fighting until he will free the schools from politics.</p>
   <p>Following the enumeration of one fact after another, and one direct charge after another against Mayor Thompson and Fred Lundin, he said, "I am also tired, but remember, I will not commit suicide or resign from office, on the contrarty, I will retain my position, and will fight until I triumph."</p>
   <p>The large body present at the meeting readily understood who Mr. Loeb aimed at, and a thunderous applause was heard. When Loeb concluded his message, he was greeted heartily. The Board pledged its assistance and promised to cooperate with him in the fight against the Mayor and Fred Lundin. Only two school trustees did not vote to support Pres. Loeb. The others have fallen in line with him to combat the clique of politicians who want to exploit and corrupt the entire school system.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0362.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, Mr. Loeb was not merely satisfied with examining the undermining work of the Mayor and Fred Lundin, but he also proposed a step whereby to eradicate the corrupt plans of the City administration. He therefore proposed, in concluding his message, that the Rules Committee should be increased by four new members and to render it a body able to create new rules for the Board of Education, so that it can function under the Otis Law.</p>
   <p>The Board accepted his proposal and he immediately appointed four new members to the School Board Rules Committee, which will introduce new rules at the new meeting, under which the present board will be able to reorganize in harmony with the new law and then carry on its work.</p>
   <p>In other words, this means that the Board determined not to heed the Mayor but maintain power, the Board is certain that it will get support from the City Council, who will not confirm the nine members appointed by the Mayor to the Board.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0363.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The conflict between Mr. Loeb and Mayor Thompson arose from the question as to who should be appointed to the Board and for how long a term. Mr. Loeb argued with the Mayor for a fw weeks, urging him not to pay any attention to Fred Lundin and to keep his word to the Impartial League.</p>
   <p>The league has no other interest but that of checking on the qualifications of the persons whom the Mayor recommends as members of the Board of Education. The Mayor promised the League to do this, but Fred Lundin is more important than the Mayor's promise.</p>
   <p>All Fred Lundin wants is to have "his men" on the Board. "His men" are such persons as will vote as he, Lundin, orders, and not as their conscience dictates. He has therefore, accepted the recommendation of politicians instead of that of impartial, reliable men who care for nothing but the interests of the schools. Lundin knows that an educated and intelligent man will not carry out the command of a low politician, and therefore, he mustered a list of such men as will follow orders and vote as they are commanded.</p>
   <pb n="5"/>
   <p>Mr. Loeb had seriously looked into the matters for the past few weeks and had alone taken up the fight against this. He held many meetings with the Mayor, Fred Lundin, the Health Commissioner, and Dr. John Dill Robertson, and they promised to act honestly, but they deceived him.</p>
   <p>They did not keep their promise. They did not however, fool Jacob M. Loeb; they only fooled themselves. Mr. Loeb proved that all those who thought that he had closed an alliance with the Mayor were badly mistaken. The Mayor and Fred Lundin, who thought that Mr. Loeb had become their partner, were disappointed.</p>
   <p>As long as Mr. Loeb saw that everything was run honestly he stood with the City Administration, but no sooner did he learn that the City Administration deviated from the honest path, that he broke his diplomatic relations with the City Hall bosses and declared open war.</p>
   <p>Mr. Loeb is a strong advocate of the preparedness idea and had, therefore, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0364.jpg" n="6"/> prepared an adequate supply of ammunition for his war against the City Hall.</p>
   <p>The most formidable blow aimed at him was a letter, addressed to him from Mayor Thompson, stating that he must drive out from the Board of Education Atty. Shanon, Secty. Larson, Husender, and others because they won't follow orders from Fred Lundin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
