<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-25">Mar. 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Candidate of a United Party</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0100</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0100.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-25">Mar. 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE CANDIDATE OF A UNITED PARTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The two candidates for Mayor, Postmaster Lueder and Judge Dever, are busy preparing their final messages to the people of Chicago. Both candidates are more or less known to the people; Dever is better known than Lueder. Both have a good name and both have the confidence of the people as far as honesty and decency are concerned. Under normal conditions, it would be difficult for the people of Chicago to choose between them, but under the present circumstances, we believe that the voters of Chicago will have an easy choice.</p>
   <p>The people of Chicago will choose the candidate who has experience in local political life and who knows everything that goes on in the City Hall. The voters of Chicago rejected Thompson, not because he is a dishonest man, but because he did not have any experience in City Hall affairs when he took <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0101.jpg" n="2"/>over the city government. Because he was inexperienced, he had to depend upon people who were not always trustworthy, and upon politicians who left him in the lurch. Only in this light can be understood the many scandals which occurred during the past eight years, and which contributed so much to the mistrust of the Thompson administration. If the present mayor had had experience in City Hall affairs when he took over the city administration eight years ago, the various things that occurred, would not have taken place, and the present administration in the City Hall would enjoy a better reputation.</p>
   <p>We may conclude, therefore, that experience is the essential qualification of a mayor, and Mr. Lueder has had no experience. He is a very fine man, a highly respectable man, and an able man. But if he were elected mayor, the same thing would happen under his administration as happened under the Thompson administration. It would not be the mayor who would administer all the important city affairs, but rather a group of politicians who would lead Mr. Lueder by the nose, as they led Mayor Thompson by the nose.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0102.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On the other hand, Judge Dever is a man with vast experience in local politics. He was an alderman for ten years. He knows everything that takes place in the City Council. He knows the aldermen; he knows their strengths and their week-nesses, their sympathies and their prejudices, their ambitions and habits, and, therefore, he will not permit anyone to lead him by the nose. He will not act as the politicians wish; his own judgment and his own conscience will dictate his policy. His opponents themselves admit that he is a discreet man with a sound judgment of men and affairs; it stands to reason, therefore, that he is the man of the hour because what the city administration needs now is a man of independent judgment and opinion. Both candidates are honest and discreet men, but Judge Dever has vast experience in City Hall matters and Mr. Lueder has not. Hence, we believe that it will not be difficult for the people of Chicago to make their choice.</p>
   <p>It is also worth mentioning that whereas Postmaster Lueder is the candidate of only one faction of the Republican party, Judge Dever is the candidate of the whole Democratic party, and that means a lot politically and morally. The <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0103.jpg" n="4"/>whole Democratic party of Chicago accepts the moral and political responsibility for the future city administration, whereas if Lueder were elected, and made the same mistakes that Thompson made, certain factions of the Republican party would repudiate him, and the same political chaos would ensue as now prevails.</p>
   <p>It is also obvious that a Republican mayor will not be able to clean out the City Hall as thoroughly as a Democratic mayor because the latter will not have to take any risks with the party or any group. Certain changes must take place in the City Hall--radical changes. Only a new man can make these changes, and Judge Dever is the man because he is not obligated to anybody in the City Hall. The Chicago voters are familiar with this fact and that is why we believe that the next mayor of Chicago will be Dever.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
