<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-05-24">May 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Loeb's Great Service</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0123</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0123.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-05-24">May 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">MR. LOEB'S GREAT SERVICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As president of the Chicago Board of Education, Mr. Loeb last Tuesday raised a corner of the curtain, which keeps the political machinery of Chicago out of sight from the "untrustworthy" and gave the people the opportunity to get an idea of how the machine is run. Mr. Loeb, with unparalleled clearness, furnished evidence that the City Administration has now centered its attention upon the Chicago public school system, with the object of turning it into another cog in the political machine.</p>
   <p>The political slogan in America is: "To the Victor belong the Spoils". This cannot be classed as the noblest slogan of America, but the political parties have always clung faithfully to it, to the detriment of America's political life. In the last quarter of a century important reforms were made to restrain the influence of this tradition and give attention to honesty in office, regardless of party politics. Civil Service has been introduced in several branches of government, and political leaders are from time to time forced, through public opinion, to deviate from the noxious tradition that the victor <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0124.jpg" n="2"/>is entitled to the plunder, and leave institutions in the hands of competent servants, regardless of their political convictions or political disbeliefs.</p>
   <p>Noxious traditions are like harmful diseases that are hereditary and cannot be easily annihilated. The politicians of the old school cannot forget their antiquated methods. It is easily understood why such a politician, as Lundin, Mayor Thompson's right-hand man, should seek to widen his authority over every institution belonging to the City of Chicago. Something similar to this occurred a few years ago with the City Tuberculosis Sanitarium, when the action of the Administration struck the death knell to Dr. Sach's career and, indirectly, to his life.</p>
   <p>Now the same attempt is being made with the Chicago public school system. No one charges the Chicago Board of Education, as is, with incompetency, or dishonesty, or accuses it of not fulfilling its duties as it should. But the City Administration doubts whether all members of the Board, and all their employees, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0125.jpg" n="3"/>are firmly with the administration of the city. Well, Mr. Lundin is in doubt whether they will vote, when the time comes, "as they should".</p>
   <p>Against this Mr. Loeb protested with all his vigor, and in the protest are backing him all the right-thinking citizens of Chicago, excepting those who are interested, together with the administration, in the "Political Spoils".</p>
   <p>To tens of thousands of citizens in Chicago the public school is a sanctuary. No other city institution affects the life of every family so deeply as does the public school system. The City Administration's attempt to subordinate the public school system to pure political objectives, is not only harmful to the schools but also poor politics. The citizenry of Chicago will reject such malicious action.</p>
   <p>It makes no difference whether the persons whom the administration seeks to put into office are good or bad, but if their appointments, as Mr. Loeb shows, are <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0126.jpg" n="4"/>made with the intention that they should vote as they are ordered to, it is then ample reason why the City Council should not confirm the new appointments.</p>
   <p>Mr. Loeb is worthy of recognition for the timely warning that he issued against the danger that suspends over the public schools, and the City Council will also become worthy if it takes this warning to heart and protects the public school from every political onslaught.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
