<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title/>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0866</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
                    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0866.jpg" n="2"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We can readily understand that an honest conscientious, and respectable person will not prefer to be a scab, because a person having a family will not debase himself to such depths as to despoil a peaceful worker of his livelihood. Thus the army of scabs are recruited from among the lowest strata of humanity, from such as have abandoned every moral and human sentiment, and are wont to commit any sort of crime. This was actually pointed out by the representative, who said that just as soon as the strike-breakers, consisting of criminal elements, were chosen, they became organized and procured weapons, becoming not only dangerous to the strikers but also detrimental to society at large.</p>
   <p>And the representative presents facts from the two bloody and disorderly protracted strikes of the coal miners of Colorado and the Copper miners in Michigan, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0867.jpg" n="3"/>where, in every instance, the law had been broken because of the unconstitutional activities of the strike-breakers.</p>
   <p>When we learn that there exists in America manifold scab agencies which shelter, feed, and even give money to such persons as do nothing but wait until a strike breaks out somewhere, we can truly understand the danger of the strike-breaking element.</p>
   <p>This simply implies that a group of man are nurtured and paid to commit moral crimes because they protect the interests of wealthy companies. Now, when a few strike investigations have been made by the government, some representatives are convinced that scabs are a menace.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0868.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>One need not be a prophet to foresee that the bill against strike-breakers, regardless of how advantageous it may be, will not pass through Congress, because on the side of the strike-breaking agencies stands the powerful Employers' Association, and we know too well their influence on Congress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
