<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title><bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>, <date when="1931-03-30">Mar. 30, 1931</date></bibl></title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0677</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item><item>I D 2 b</item><item>I D 2 c</item><item>III B 2</item><item>II D 1</item><item>II D 3</item><item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div><div type="citation"><bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>, <date when="1931-03-30">Mar. 30, 1931</date></bibl></div>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0677.jpg" n="2"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The importance and usefulness of this department is not appreciated by many members. Some members have not paid sufficient attention to this institution which could have been made the largest of its kind in this country.</p>
   <p>What is the aim of the medical department of the Workmen's Circle? Why was a medical department established in New York? why have 600 members of the Workmen's Circle in Chicago organized themselves and are anxious to establish a co-operative medical department? They did it because they understood the full value of co-operative medical aid. They know that by united efforts "worlds can be built," and all can benefit more easily. Considering these facts, every member of the Workmen's Circle should have joined the medical department. However, only 600 out of the 2,000 members did join, and the rest refused to do so. We think that the other members failed to join the medical department because the Chicago Workmen's Circle did not properly stress the importance of health problems. That is one reason. Another reason is that the members <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0678.jpg" n="3"/>were not taught the relationship of health to our daily life.</p>
   <p>The members of the Workmen's Circle should recognize the great importance of a medical department, especially at a time when a large number of the members are unemployed and a good many others are reduced to poverty.</p>
   <p>Let us imagine the deplorable conditions of the Workmen's Circle members who were severely stricken by the depression! So many need a doctor and a hospital, but they do not have the opportunity to secure free medical aid. What a tragedy for such families! What anguish for a mother who knows that her sick child absolutely must have a doctor, yet is unable to pay for the services of a physician!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
