<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-22">Mar. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Abolish the Grand Jury</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0834</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0834.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-22">Mar. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ABOLISH THE GRAND JURY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the April elections, the voters will have to decide as to whether or not the system of the grand jury should be abolished. Hitherto, the law provides that the state's attorney cannot bring charges against a person involved in a crime without the approval of a grand jury after weighing all evidence privately and without any interference on the part of the accused, the prosecution or the defense.</p>
   <p>Since long ago many jurists have wanted to abolish the grand jury. They claim that we can get along just as well without it. Others, however, maintain that if it weren't for the grand jury, the state's attorney could accuse all his enemies of different crimes. The state's attorney would then always be victorious, as he sides with the state's machine that stands the costly trials, whereas the accused must defend himself at his own expense. This will enable the <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0835.jpg" n="2"/>state's attorney and his friends to cause their foes a great deal of trouble.</p>
   <p>Truthfully, however, the state's attorney can now do the same even with the grand jury in existence. Why does the grand jury now heed the advice of the State's attorney? Rather seldom do jurists occupy the jury bench. The majority on the jury are ordinary citizens who rely upon the state's attorney as the representative of the people, assuming that he works for the interest of society and knows what he does.</p>
   <p>The opponents of the grand jury reason that if this ancient institution is not advantageous, why should it obstruct progress? At a meeting of Chicago's business men, Chief Justice Olson discussed this question at length, and showed why the Chicago judges would be able to render better services without the grand jury. As the case is now, a judge of the Municipal Court sends the trial of a criminal to another court, notwithstanding that he reviewed the case and is capable of rendering a just decision.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0836.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Without the grand jury," contends Chief Justice Olson, "the Municipal Court will be in a position to devote its time to the long waiting list of thieves, stick-up men, incendiaries, etc, and, in coordination with the Criminal Court, both can rid Chicago of the many crimes which have made it famous in all parts of the world."</p>
   <p>On the other hand, those who do not want to have the grand jury abolished are not so convincing and logical in their arguments as is Chief Justice Olson. Their only claim is that the state's attorney will be endowed with more power to do evil. But need the state of Illinois always have such state's attorneys as should be suspected of committing evils? Why shouldn't we seriously consider the proposal of having the State act not only as the prosecution but also as the defense? This will eliminate suspicion against State justice. If the grand jury is unsalable and if there is the slightest suspicion that the state's attorney can do evil in behalf of society, this should be stopped in a direct manner and not in a round about way by preserving the mould which is neither sacred nor advantageous.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
