<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-12">Nov. 12, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Warning</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0887</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0887.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-12">Nov. 12, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A WARNING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several days ago our own well-known Jacob Schiff spoke on a very important topic.</p>
   <p>He spoke to the members of New York's Chamber of Commerce on the question of "Finance Reform" which is at present the point of order in Congress.</p>
   <p>His speech echoed as a warning. He warned the heads of American finance that their opposition to the planned reforms may lead to much harm throughout the entire country. He added that, besides individual interests, there are also collective interests, and the individual must at times sacrifice his own interests for those of the groups.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0888.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Schiff's stand on this question of finance reforms adds much esteem to his name. It proves that besides being a financier he is also a statesman with a broad understanding of present day problems.</p>
   <p>America today is not the same as it was a hundred or fifty years ago. The monetary system of those times is no longer suitable to the present situation, and therefore, the need of reforms in a system that puts the entire control of the country's finances into the hands of a few magnates.</p>
   <p>To what such a system may lead is clear even to the common workman.</p>
   <p>It was seen quite clearly, in fact one could almost put his finger on it, during the Roosevelt administration. He stepped on the toes of the big trust magnates, so to speak, and they were called to the carpet not only by President Roosevelt but by the entire population of the republic.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0889.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Morgan and his friends pressed an electric button in his office, its ring resounded throughout the entire country. Factories began to close, banks crashed, the entire country flew into convulsions so that we were not far from a national crisis.</p>
   <p>Roosevelt remonstrated, he gnashed his teeth, and in the end he, chosen by the people as the head of a national government, had to come to terms with the uncrowned kings of Wall Street and do their bidding.</p>
   <p>The proposed bill of finance reform does not go so far as to take away all the powers of Wall Street. It has in view just certain limitations, certain definite methods against such further occurrences.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0890.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Schiff sees that these changes are of all the people, and he is willing to set aside his personal interests for those of the country, demanding the same of everyone else. Thus, he is giving them due warning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
