<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1893-03-26">Mar. 26, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Hebrews Declare for Reform</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1893-03-26">Mar. 26, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">HEBREWS DECLARE FOR REFORM</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Away down on Jefferson Street, in the neighborhood of Twelfth, there is a large Hebrew settlement. The claim has often been made that Harrison possessed great strength in this particular locality. Evidence to the contrary was a crowded meeting held last night in Metropolitan Hall, corner of Jefferson and O'Brien Streets, under the auspices of the Hebrew Club of the Seventh Ward.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order at 8 o'clock by M. Goldman. B. Horwich was elected Chairman, and J. Barnes acted as Secretary. Among the speakers who addressed the meeting were S. C. Eastman, I. F. Patterson, James A. McShane, the people's candidate for City Attorney. J. L. Monaghan, candidate for West Town Assessor, and Rev. Dr. Emil G. Hirsch and the citizens candidate for mayor, Samuel W. Allerton.</p>
   <p>None of the speakers was more warmly received than Mr. Allerton whose terse presentation of facts and convincing argument commanded an enthusiastic response from the larger audience. "All those who will vote for Mr. Allerton," said Chairman Horwich at the close of Mr. Allerton's speech, "will please rise." There was an instant and unanimous movement by the audience and as <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0053.jpg" n="2"/>they rose to their feet some one proposed "three cheers for Allerton." The cheers were given and the citizens candidate for mayor was assured that in that section of Chicago at least the Hebrews were with him.</p>
   <p>Before the meeting came to an end Chairman Horwich read the following telegram from a member of their own race, who is well known in this city: Santa Barbara, Cal., March 25, To J. W. Allerton, Chicago, Ill. Just learned of your nomination. Accept my heartiest congratualtions. Having been the best of friends for thirty years, I know you will fill the office with honor as demonstrated by your past career. With best wishes. Nelson Morris.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
