<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-11-09">November 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Hearty and Long Remembered Evening</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1577</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1577.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-11-09">November 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A HEARTY AND LONG REMEMBERED EVENING</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second evening of art by the Labor Culture League, Tuesday, October 31, in the Place Theater, turned out to be a greater success than the first one, as the tickets were sold out long before the evening of entertainment approached. The first evening, the audience suffered, because the program lasted too long. The Culture League prevented that error this time, and chose their talents carefully, with the exception of one number.</p>
   <p>These evenings have established a desire among the Jewish people for more concerts. They create friends, and give a good deal of prestige to the Culture League. The program began with Miss Eugene Shapiro in a piano composition by Paul Lempkoff, the musical director of the Labor Culture League. The rest of the performers were all so good that we do not know whom to speak of first. The talented soprano, Miss Lillian Sindahl, inspired the audience with her singing and graceful bearing on the stage. Victor Young, the violinist, who recently completed a coast to coast tour, touched the <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1578.jpg" n="2"/>hearts of his listeners with his playing and the audience regretted that the time was limited and Mr. Young had to leave the stage. Mr. Young was accompanied by his sister, Miss Helen Young. Ely Gennenholz appeared twice. The first part of the program he impersonated Morris Schwartz in a scene wherein he buys a play, and in the second part he presented a few recitations that had the audience in stitches. The public proved itself to be close friends to the Culture League.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the League, Comrade Louis Schaffer, related to the audience the work of the League and appealed to them to join the League. Since that evening many of the audience have joined. The League has arranged a performance of the famous English play, The Hairy Ape, for the twentieth of this month. The League also arranged a lecture by the star of the play, Mr. Louis Wohlheim. We hope that our Jewish workers will be present at both the lecture and the performance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
