<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-28">Feb. 28, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Importance of Brandeis</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0268.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-28">Feb. 28, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE IMPORTANCE OF BRANDEIS</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The investigation which is going on at present in the United States Senate, on the question of Mr. Louis D. Brandeis' eligibility, to be seated in the Supreme Court, brings certain ideas and an educational problem before our nation. We must ask the question: What would our country know about the principles and ideals that Mr. Brandeis introduced without this investigation? Of course, very little. We heard that Mr. Brandeis was a prominent attorney in Boston, who investigated the question of retaining the natural resources of Alaska for our nation instead of turning them over to the rich corporations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0269.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We also know that for the interstate railroad commission, he represented the interests of the shippers. Most of us know and the press also knows that he presented many cases in the Supreme Court where the 8-hour law for women workers came up for trial, and that he was instrumental in the arbitration between the Cloak Makers' Union and the manufacturers. But these are only a very small part of what Mr. Brandeis has accomplished. Of his ideals, his principles, and his entire spiritual make up, the general public knows but very little. It is no wonder that the public at large does not know why President Wilson saw fit to appoint Mr. Brandeis as a Judge of the Supreme Court of the United States. The average citizen, who is accustomed to look at all political matters with suspicion, will without a doubt think that the appointment of Mr. Brandeis certainly came through a political "pull."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0270.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now comes the Senate investigation and much information is released....It is shown that wherever Mr. Brandeis appeared as an attorney in important cases concerning the vital interest of the public, he never shirked his duty, but took up the part of the masses in general. You may disagree with his socialistic and economic convictions, and with his opinion in reference to fighting the trusts, but his whole career as an attorney demonstrates that he does not cherish the letter of the law as much as the spirit of law, and does not regard law as highly as he does justice, which should serve as the basis of law. These views the big interests of high finance cannot possibly be satisfied with, and a great opposition is being carried on by these interests against the confirmation of the nomination of Mr. Brandeis by the United States Senate. We are not sure that Mr. Brandeis himself would fret if his nomination were not confirmed, but the opposition against him, as it appears in the investigation, is very enlightening to the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
