<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-10">May 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">To Cultivate Jewish Music</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-10">May 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">TO CULTIVATE JEWISH MUSIC</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The appearance of the three world famous cantors, Rosenblatt, Hershman and Kwatin, at a concert held recently under the auspices of two local booking agents, was a striking demonstration of the development of Jewish liturgical music in modern times. The concert also testified to the fact that our masses love Jewish music, for at least five thousand people, mostly of the masses of the Jewish population, have attended that concert and have left the large Medinah Temple more than satisfied with what they have been offered by the three artists.</p>
   <p>It is our contention that such concerts have not only a cultural value from a musical point of view, but they also have a Jewish educational value. The Jewish masses who attend such concerts are not necessarily Orthodox Jews. The majority of them, we suppose, are non-Orthodox. They very seldom attend <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1573.jpg" n="2"/>synagogue services and are very little in touch with Jewish religious life, and one of the reasons why they are still attached to Judaism is because of their intense love for liturgical music. The most radical Jew of Eastern European origin still falls for a Jewish liturgical melody sung by a great cantor. Jewish liturgical music has an indescribable fascination for the average Jew. It sends a thrill into his soul and causes him to remember everything that is sacred in our life, our yearnings for Palestine redeemed, our veneration for our martyrs, our pious prayers, our deep feelings for our suffering people everywhere, etc. The cultivation of Jewish music, therefore, has more than an artistic significance. It has a great educational and therefore also a great political significance, and the community would do well to pay some attention to this phase of Jewish education. We cannot compel our masses to attend synagogue services, but we can bring them into concert halls where they will hear Jewish music, and therefore the cultivation of Jewish music should be one of the activities of the community. Jewish musical societies should be encouraged, Jewish choirs should be organized not only for purely synagogue purposes but for the purpose of cultivating Jewish music and bringing <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1574.jpg" n="3"/>it to the masses. Each and every synagogue should try its utmost to engage a good cantor. There is something to the contention of the presidents of the Orthodox synagogues that a good cantor is a greater attraction to the worshipers than a good rabbi. They duty of the cantor should not be to perform the services only, but he should make it his business to cultivate Jewish music within his circle of activity by organizing choirs and by doing everything possible to foster and cultivate Jewish music among the congregants. As long as a Jew finds pleasure in listening to Jewish liturgical music, he is a Jew, and when he no more enjoys the rendering of a great cantor, he has ceased to be a Jew emotionally, and as a rule he has ceased to be a Jew altogether. The reaction to Jewish music is the best test of one's Jewish emotions, and we therefore believe that a community should do everything it can to encourage Jewish music and to fill the Jewish street with Jewish melodies. If there should ever be established a real Jewish center in the Lawndale district, one of its main activities must be the cultivating of Jewish music. It may not be possible to make every Jewish boy a Hebrew scholar, but it is possible to make every Jewish boy love Jewish music and through Jewish music <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1575.jpg" n="4"/>develop his Jewish emotions and Jewish sentiments. The boys and girls attending the Talmud Torahs [Hebrew schools] may in the future forget all their Hebrew, their Bible, and their Jewish history, etc., but they will never forget the Jewish melodies. For this reason cultivation of Jewish music is of paramount importance to the Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
