<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-05">Apr. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Science in War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-05">Apr. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">SCIENCE IN WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In London, a noted scientist, Dr. William Osler, recently found it necessary to defend "science" before a group of educated people. As a scientist, he apparently felt that the role of science in the present war is misunderstood and should be defended. He admitted that the terrible massacres in Europe can only be effected with the aid of the inventions of scientific inventions: submarines, flying machines, gigantic zeppelins, poisonous gases, hand grenades, new artillery, and powerful explosives, as well as many other weapons.</p>
   <p>"But," said Dr. Osler, "science has also evinced unprecedented ability to save human lives, even in time of war. The new ambulances, the remedies for blood poisoning, surgery, the modern hospitals, the swiftness with which wounds are treated--all these should be placed to the credit of science."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0628.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It seems to us that the defense is rather weak. When science seeks to restore a small portion of that which it has helped to destroy, it does not deserve gratitude. But this is not the question. Science is neither to be blamed nor to be defended. This would be like seeking a defense for the axe, with which wood is chopped, when the woodchopper becomes murderous and kills someone with it. Mankind, which alone of living creatures has cultivated the intellect, is not in need of a defense, but that part of humanity which is destroying morals, creating war, and killing men, is to blame. Science is neutral. It depends upon the moral condition of the people who use it whether it shall become a blessing or a curse to mankind.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
