<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-07-04">July 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Fourth of July</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0969</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0969.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-07-04">July 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE FOURTH OF JULY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To-day is the Fourth of July, the day when the people of the United States of America celebrate, with national pride and joy the day of their independence, brought about one hundred and forty-eight years ago after the long struggle for freedom of the American colonies against England.</p>
   <p>Since that time the thirteen colonies, with a population of about seven million, have developed into a gigantic and mighty world power of forty-eight states, with a population of 110 million people.</p>
   <p>Becoming a free and independent nation, the United States, the then created Republic of 1776 in the western hemisphere, promised to be the land of true freedom and democracy. Since that historical day, the United States began to grow and develop in power and prestige, and along with this gigantic growth of wealth and power, grew the desire and ambition of the people of <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0970.jpg" n="2"/>this young developing nation to teach the world the true meaning of freedom and democracy.</p>
   <p>America came triumphant out of the Civil War between the North and the South, the war that put an end to Negro slavery, the black mark of infamy that until then had prevailed on America's proud, democratic Republic.</p>
   <p>But the ambition of those people, impressed with the ideals of 1776, to serve as an example of freedom and democracy for the old world, even after this brilliant period of the Civil War, did not materialize. Among certain groups of American citizens, in which freedom-loving people can be found, it was noticed that a change was gradually taking place. After an investigation, it was learned that Europe did not wish to be taught democracy, by America, but that on the contrary, it was she who expected to teach it to America. European observers acquainted with our institutions have, with very little inspiration, responded in this regard. In truth, if the people of Europe are bold enough to think they can preach morals to America, it is because of the political bosses, the rulers of capital, and the many other <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0971.jpg" n="3"/>social and political evils found in America. They point out America's ever-increasing growth of poverty, sickness, sin, and crime as evils developed during America's growth in wealth and power. They mention especially the rapid growth of the slums in large cities, and the army of unemployed; the premature death of children, the gigantic spread of diseases, the tens of thousands of people disabled and crippled by fast-growing industries, the growth of prostitution, and the bitter struggle between capital and labor.</p>
   <p>No, the true ideals of 1776 never materialized. Our democracy, created with such earnest splendor and magnificence, started to decry long, long ago. The World War gave it a terrific death blow on the head, and to day, the day when the United States celebrates its birth of freedom, it would be well to take a clear, historical inventory of what became of America's freedom and democracy, and of what is awaiting us in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
