<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-22">Feb. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Justice</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0858</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0858.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-22">Feb. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">JUSTICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two men were arrested on conviction that they had stolen bread and locked up in a dark cell behind iron bars, as common criminals.</p>
   <p>These two bread thieves were brought into a South Side Court. They had confessed that they stole the bread because they were out of work for several weeks and there was no work to be had. Feeling the pangs of hunger and seeing that there was no other way that would bring them relief, they determined, against their own will, to steal bread.</p>
   <p>Tears came to the eyes of the judge upon hearing the story of these unfortunate men. He then handed them fifty cents and told them to eat a good meal and them look for work. He also said, "It is surprising that you have not held up a railroad."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0859.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This fact shows that unemployment very often drives honest people to commit crimes against their own will especially when nothing is done to ease the tribulations of the unemployed.</p>
   <p>Unemployment is no accident in our society. We know that nearly 27 per cent of the workers are unemployed at all times, and that society is indifferent toward the problem.</p>
   <p>However, this particular instance proves to us that unemployment forces people to become habitual criminals. It so happened, in this fortunate case, that the judge understood the plight of the poor unemployed and discharged them. But what if they would not have been discharged? If these two men would have been sentenced to a few months imprisonment, nobody would have hired them after their release, for who would want to hire anyone with a prison record?</p>
   <p>What would be left for them to do? They could have no other alternative <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0860.jpg" n="3"/>than to make thievery their profession. And as a result these two innocent workers would have become two regular criminals and bitter foes of society.</p>
   <p>Therefore, this phase of the problem is an important one from the viewpoint of justice. The judge's discharging them and speaking friendly to them, giving them money for a meal, will certainly have a good effect upon them. They will realize that one should not lose hope nor confidence in looking forward to better times.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
