<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title><bibl><title>Forward</title>, <date when="1924-08-02">Aug. 2, 1924</date></bibl></title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0338</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
</div><div type="citation"><bibl><title>Forward</title>, <date when="1924-08-02">Aug. 2, 1924</date></bibl></div>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0338.jpg" n="2"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When Thompson's administration was replaced by another with a good religious and God-fearing mayor at the head, they tried to persuade the public that Chicago would be an example of the new administration's work to make this a clean and respectable city.</p>
   <p>And it did not take long. The police, under their new chief, started a clean-up campaign all over the city. First of all they began with the saloons. Licenses were taken away from every saloon and coffee house and the places closed. Restaurants that were within a shade of suspicion in regard to serving liquor, were raided by the police. The patrol wagons were busy day and night; the police searched for "sinners;" even the "innocent" beauty-parlors, where people would go for a manicure or a face massage, were bothered. The new "saintly" administration wanted to protect our citizens, from even the least thought of sin entering their minds. The motto was to make Chicago an ideal city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0339.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And now, after a year's "clearing," it is learned that Chicago is the same "open town" it was in the good old times under the Thompson's administration. Now the attention of the police is called to the open gambling houses with which the South Side is flooded, where the bosses of the under-world feel as though they were the city officals. When the police was asked about this state of affairs, their chief gave an answer which is worth listening to.</p>
   <p>His answer regarding open gambling is just plain. He shifts the blame onto the Chicago courts, and a few of the judges whose names he mentions. He shows that the police are absolutely helpless because the gambling house are protected by the courts. Some of the filthiest gambling houses are protected by injunctions granted by Judge Sullivan, the same judge who <pb n="4"/><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/><pb facs="5423972_4_1_0340.jpg" n="5"/>also found many deadly weapons, such as guns, revolvers, knives, daggers and black-jacks.</p>
   <p>Judge Samuel Trude, of the Municipal Court, pigeon-holed the case. On top of all that, we had to appear in court on a charge of violating the injunction granted to this gambling house by Judge Sullivan. This is the answer to the gambling question."</p>
   <p>What we have just quoted is only a short extract of the statement made by the Chicago Chief of Police. The Chief reveals facts which show how the entire under-world is protected by the courts. He shows, for instance, that when the gambling houses are not protected by injunctions, their trials are dragged for so long that they are forgotten.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0341.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Even though the "sensation" the newspapers have made out of the open gambling houses in Chicago is not a surprise, the answer given by Chief Collins should interest all of us. The public should know that the same judge who protects the bosses with his injunctions in case of a strike, helps the gambling houses, and the entire under-world with the same weapon, giving them a free hand to operate their business.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
