<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title/>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0358</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
                    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0358.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>market. The poor man, - stated Alderman Pick - no longer has any chance in the Maxwell St. market. He must first pay a certain sum before he is permitted to sell his merchandise. The law states that every merchant should have the right to utilize 10 linear feet of space and that all stands must be removed between 6:00 P.M. and 7:00 A.M.</p>
   <p>"But today the market is not conducted along such lines. The stands are controlled by the collectors of the politicians. I can prove this by showing checks and affadavits. Wooden booths and sheds have been raised standing partly on the sidewalk and partly on the street and they are rented for large sums of money. Wagons have remained standing so long on the paid for spaces that their wheels have sunk into the asphalt. The system of paying graft has been so well organized, he further stated, that those who refused to pay were driven out of the market. Over 100,000 persons, he further stated, buy and sell on Sundays. They come from all parts of the city. At least a million dollars per week business is carried on and the city receives no more than $14.00 per permit.</p>
   <p>Sam Lebedinsky of 700 Maxwell St., whose store is on Union St., gave testimony to the effect that the door of his store is blocked by a stand and that his customers must enter through a rear entry. The market master allows this, he said.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0359.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Committee decided to work out new regulations for the market. The entire fuss which has been raised against the Maxwell St. market however, is recognizable as merely a means to create a sentiment against Jewish businessmen. The Maxwell St. market is one of the oldest markets in Chicago. It is a famous place, and people from all over the city, come to purchase bargains. Because of the great turnover, it pays the merchant to sell his merchandise cheaper and with a smaller profit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
