<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-27">Feb. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[What Is Wrong with the Professional Men?]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-27">Feb. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[WHAT IS WRONG WITH THE PROFESSIONAL MEN?]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are several hundred Jewish physicians and lawyers in Chicago, and all of them make a fine living, yet we very seldom hear that our professional people, the representatives of the professions, as a group, are doing anything in the field of Jewish philanthropic work, for Jewish institutions, for relief, for Zionism, and so on. Of course, in all Jewish organizations there are to be found a certain number of professionals, doctors, lawyers, and so on, but as a professional group, they don't do anything and they do not answer any appeal.</p>
   <p>By the grace of God, we have begun to build a Hebrew University in Palestine. It would seem logical that the first ones to become interested in that undertaking should be the Jewish university men: doctors, lawyers, chemists, dentists, pharmacists, engineers, and so on. The Jewish professionals in <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1179.jpg" n="2"/>New York have done something for the Hebrew University: they have raised one hundred thousand dollars, they have promised to raise a few hundred thousand dollars more, and, anyway, they are becoming active in the movement.</p>
   <p>The situation in Chicago is entirely different. The Jewish professionals, as a group, are neither heard of nor are they seen. They are not interested in the Hebrew University in Palestine, nor are they active in any other Jewish cultural movement.</p>
   <p>I am curious to know who is responsible for this miserable condition. Is it the fault of the leading personalities among the Jewish professional men in Chicago? Is it a lack of interest? Is it a spirit of indifference? It is high time that our doctors and lawyers began to discuss this question openly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
