<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-13">July 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Career of the Deceased Mr. Harris Dick, as Businessman, Jew, and Humanitarian</title><title level="a" type="sub">[one column-eighth of page, picture of Mr. Dick]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1384</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1384.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-13">July 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE CAREER OF THE DECEASED MR. HARRIS DICK, AS BUSINESSMAN, JEW, AND HUMANITARIAN</title><title level="a" type="sub"> [one column-eighth of page, picture of Mr. Dick]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Wednesday, July 9, 1919, Mr. Harris Dick, founder and president of the Western Dairy Company, died. He has done much for Chicago Jewry as a man of great self-respect, with a soul and a Jewish conscience. He devoted many years to the building of a business concern which brought health to hundreds of men, women, and children.</p>
   <p>Like all immigrant Jews he found himself a stranger in a strange country on his arrival twenty-six years ago. The Jewish community in Chicago was too small at the time to be able to render aid or service to the newcomers. Mr. Dick's motto was "to earn money by his own hands". Possessing natural courage, energy, and a rare patience, working at everything and anything to earn his livelihood, he found nothing too base nor too hard to undertake.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1385.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Later he opened the H. Dick Milk Store on Fourteenth Street. At that time, there were no large Jewish-operated dairy companies. Those that existed at the time were small and were housed in filthy, dark damp basements. Mr. Dick, as a far-seeing man, saw clearly his duty to the Jews of Chicago and performed it all.</p>
   <p>In 1907 he organized the present Western Dairy Company, installing the most modern machinery of the time. Jews were now able to secure milk, butter, and cream, produced under the most sanitary conditions. This was then a revolutionary step in the dairy business. More and more Jews patronized his company.</p>
   <p>He was the first Jew to use modern methods to produce milk, cream, and butter for Chicago's Jews under sanitary conditions. He was also the first Jew to pasteurize milk; the first to bring the dairy business into the field of Jewish employment.</p>
   <p>Mr. Dick did not stop at this; he <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>
<pb facs="5423972_4_1_1386.jpg" n="3"/><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></p>
   <p><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/><pb facs="5423972_4_1_1387.jpg" n="4"/>the Congregation Anshe Wilna Hagar'a, devoting much time and energy to its maintenance. He leaves three daughters Anna, Ida, <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>mie and two sons Morris and Samuel.</p>
   <p>Mr. Dick is dead, but his accomplishments, his character as a businessman, Jew, and humanitarian will remain in the memory of Chicago Jews for generations to come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
