<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1898-08-27">August 27, 1898</date>. p.28.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1239</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1239.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1898-08-27">August 27, 1898</date>. p.28.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judge Philip Stein, who has been renominated for judge of the Superior Court, was born in Russia in 1844. He came to America at the age of ten. Later he studied common law and was admittedto the Illinois Bar in 1868.</p>
   <p>Mr. Stein never held any public office until his election as judge of the Superior Court in 1892. He delivered the address at the laying of the corner-stone of the Chicago Turgemeinde, and has been the president of that society. In 1870-71, he was associated with Mr. Adolph Moses under the firm name of Moses and Stein.</p>
   <p>Judge Stein was one of the organizers of the Standard Club in 1869. He was one of the founders of the West Chicago Club in 1882 and president for the first eight years of its existence. He has been a member of the B'nai B'rith for over thirty years and of the Free Sons of Israel for twenty-five years and occupies prominent positions in both. He has been presiding officer of two of <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1240.jpg" n="2"/>the general conventions of the Free Sons, and one of the B. B.</p>
   <p>In 1893, as judge of the Superior Court, he issued the injunction which prevented the World's Fair Commissioners from closing the Fair on Sundays. The result of Judge Stein's action was that the Fair was kept open every day of the week until its final closing.</p>
   <p>Mr. Stein's record as a judge is exceptionally high. Particular attention may be called to the fact (rendered doubly important because of the clogged condition of the court docket) that he has instituted certain changes in the practice and proceedings at trials which have saved a vast amount of time and thus expedited cases to such an extent that in his court, a suit could be tried and disposed of within three months after it was commenced.</p>
   <p>These changes are three in number (1) an examination by the court instead of <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1241.jpg" n="3"/>the attorneys of the jurors called to try a case, as to their competency and qualifications (2) a limitation of the time during which counsel are to address the jury (3) no argument on questions as to the advisability of evidence, unless the court expresses the desire to hear from counsel. Especially to our business men it is of great importance to have litigation disposed of in a short time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
