<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-10">Apr. 10, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">High Rents and Real-Estate Specualtions</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. Grinblau</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-10">Apr. 10, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">HIGH RENTS AND REAL-ESTATE SPECUALTIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. Grinblau</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is an old story that is being repeated every year at about this time of the year. I refer to the plague of high rent. The Chicago landlords begin their yearly drive of skinning their unfortunate tenants, who are completely helpless because the law is on the side of the landlords, who have the unlimited right to charge as much rent as they want to, with nobody to say anything to the contrary.</p>
   <p>The feeble attempt made a few years [ago] to control the wolfish appetite of the real-estate speculators came to nought thanks to the barrels of gold which the landlords spent where it would do most good and thanks to our local reactionary press, which raised a hue and cry against the law as legislation savoring of Bolshevism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0708.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The tenants have thus remained helpless, a flock of sheep ready to be sheared continually by the landlords. How long can it go on like this? How long will the patience of the great majority of the population that is so shamefully exploited last? An end to these conditions must come sometime. The tenants will not be then satisfied with the feeble remedies which the reactionary press condemned so strongly. The tenants will then demand and pass a law which will put an end, once and for all, to the exploiting power of conscienceless landlords.</p>
   <p>The true cause of the continual raise in rents is to be found in the multiplicity of real-estate sharks. Some people buy and sell real estate for speculative purposes, to make a few thousand dollars on a "property" that is being continually transferred. Some houses are transferred a few times during a year. Every buyer is entitled to a profit and during a year the value of the property increases by a large amount--the profits of the speculators, which is being shouldered by the poor tenants in the form of higher rent.</p>
   <p>It is the conscienceless speculators who cause the high rents. The landlords <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0709.jpg" n="3"/>who buy real estate for investment purposes are compelled to step into line.</p>
   <p>A reaction against the real-estate speculators is unavoidable and the later it will come the more a drastic form will it assume.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
