<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-08">Sept. 8, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Miller Answers Northup</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-08">Sept. 8, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">MILLER ANSWERS NORTHUP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, City Prosecutor Harry B. Miller, one of the Republican candidates for the nomination for State's Attorney, sharply rebuked his opponent, John Northup. Mr. Miller pointed out that his record in helping Mayor Thompson maintain law and order brought him recognition from many civic organizations. He turned to his opponent with the following questions:</p>
   <p>Out of justice to the citizens of Cook County, I ask you, Mr. Northup, if it is not true that after I started a trial against the proprietors of the disreputable Cadalac Cafe, you urged Judge Olson, your political supporter, to continue the case, and that I was then forced to ask the mayor to revoke the license of this cafe and to padlock it. Is it not true that after I filed, in behalf of the city, a case against this cafe, Judge Olson continued the case until after the primaries?</p>
   <p>In connection with this, I ask you, Mr. Northup, if it is not a fact that <pb n="2"/>whereas my office prosecuted the owners of houses of prostitution and suspicious hotels, you got a large sum of money to protect them? Will you make public the names of the men who run houses of ill-repute and the amount of money they paid you? Is it also not a fact that all of your clients were tried?</p>
   <p>I would also like to ask you, Mr. Northup, if it is not true that whereas I, as City Prosecutor, have prosecuted criminals, you took money from these criminals and defended them in the Criminal Court? Amoong these criminals there were many policemen whom you defended as being honest persons, while they were charged with crimes.</p>
   <p>That the taxpayers and the citizens of Cook County may know your stand on the punishment of criminals, I ask that you make public the amount of money you have received from corrupt policemen. I also wish to ask you whether it is <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0262.jpg" n="3"/>not true that you are using this money for your campaign.</p>
   <p>In conclusion I wish to ask you, Mr. Northup, whether it is not a fact that you have reached an understanding with Charles Deneen to do what he did as State's Attorney, in the event that you are elected to that office, i.e., that you will accept fees which morally belong to the school children of this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
