<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-06-04">June 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Day of Registration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0672</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0672.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-06-04">June 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE DAY OF REGISTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tomorrow is the day set aside by Congress on which all American citizens, from 21 to 30 years of age, are requested to register for preparation to service in the army, if it shall be necessary. This will be the day when the echo of the World War, from which America had until now abstained, begins to invade millions of families in the peaceful United States, reminding us that we are a part of the civilized world, which is engaged in a bloody war, seeking new forms of social orders, and that we cannot completely remain distant to this war.</p>
   <p>Until now, the war had very little effect on us. It contributed mostly to the high cost of living and made a sensation on the finances of the country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0673.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Tomorrow's registration is the first step to bring the World War nearer to us, and to make us think more seriously about what is now taking place in the world.</p>
   <p>It is not necessary for us to remind the Jewish youth that they should not neglect the duty imposed upon them on that day. The bill adopted by Congress is intended for everybody, without any exceptions, and our youth are imbued with enough spirit of American Democracy, and are intelligent enough to understand that no land can enjoy freedom, equality and peace without, at times, defending these gifts of God with its blood. More words of encouragement and optimism, evolving from present conditions, cannot be superfluous.</p>
   <p>The war has endured three years, and from what we hear of European events, we must conclude that it cannot continue for a lengthy time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0674.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In all war stricken countries peace without plunder or contributions is spoken of widely and freely, which proves that all countries are willing to "negotiate". The entrance of America into war contributed much to this, because the powers of Central Europers are beginning to understand the necessity of bringing about peace.</p>
   <p>It will take at least five or six months before an American army of the newly registered could be prepared for the European front. By that time peace might be achieved. But we must not forget that a colossal registration cannot fail to make the proper impression on the powers of Central Europe, and at the same time let them know that the United States is in earnest. Such an impression may save peace.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0675.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>America cast her lot with the Allies, and we are for America. America stands for peace without plunder or contributions, and we are for such a peace. Therefore, we too, are for a powerful registration tomorrow, because the larger the registration the nearer will we draw toward peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
