<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-09">July 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Are the Children to Blame?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0778</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0778.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-09">July 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ARE THE CHILDREN TO BLAME?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How often do you read the Bible? If you do not read it for religious purposes, then read it for literary pleasure. Hundreds of beautifully wonderful stories are found between Genesis and Deuteronomy; love stories, as the story of Ruth, the travel stories of Jacob and his children, stories of heroism such as David's fight with Goliath, or of wars and battlefields, unless the last-mentioned have become tedious reading as a result of the last four years. [Translator's note: This refers to World War.]</p>
   <p>There is only one type of story that is not found in the Bible. The Bible contains no comic tales, no humorous whimsies. Nothing written for the sake of ridicule has remained in any literature as a work of actual value. People do not devote their deepest thoughts to writing merely in jest. Those who read nothing but comic or ridiculing material learn very little from it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0779.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Let us recall the story of Judah and Tamar. Judah's sons died young without leaving any heirs. Only Tamar, his daughter-in-law, remained. She was first the wife of Judah's elder son who died leaving no offspring. Tamar then married the younger son, as was the custom in that ancient Hebrew era. But he too died leaving her childless.</p>
   <p>Tamar was grief stricken and full of despair. Disappointed in her hopes of becoming a mother she left for the market place. When Judah met her there he thought she was a prostitute.</p>
   <p>This happened just before Moten Torah (the giving of the Torah). No rigid rules of social morals as yet existed. Old Judah did not wish his family to become extinct, to leave no heir. Thus he took his former daughter-in-law [as wife]. Thus too did the tribe of Judah beget the progeny from which there came King David and the founders of the Jewish Kingdom.</p>
   <p>We are far removed now from the acts of those ancient times. Yet the moral lesson of this beautiful Biblical story came to our mind when we read of the <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0780.jpg" n="3"/>actions of the city administration of Newark, New Jersey.</p>
   <p>At the expense of the city of Newark a home has been established for unwed mothers, under the supervision of the mayor and under the management of the Board of Health.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the Home is not to punish the unfortunate but to make a place for them where, at least for six months, mother and child may receive the necessary love and protection which lead to the path of adjustment. The mother is not considered an outcast. When her parents oust her the Home becomes her guardian, and when she is in a position to leave, she receives enough aid to carry on under honest and adjusted circumstances within the community.</p>
   <p>Founders of the Home in Newark agree that it is the duty of the state to care for those who are morally unfortunate as well as for those who are ill or poor.</p>
   <p>Two hundred such cases occur in the city during the year. On the average, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0781.jpg" n="4"/>these mothers range from eighteen to twenty-two years of age. If the work of the Home is carried on successfully, it will mean that four hundred potentially good citizens are saved from shame and moral degradation.</p>
   <p>In all America there are over one hundred and fifty thousand such cases, and only recently has one city been found which recognizes its duty to establish a home, a rescue station for unfortunate human souls. It is a serious problem for the thinking part of mankind.</p>
   <p>No matter what we think of the unwed mother--and the story of Tamar teaches us not to condemn the fallen woman--there can be no two opinions regarding the innocent children who are born under these unfortunate circumstances.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
