<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-10-04">Oct. 4, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">[Twenty-Thousand Childred Are Starving in the Schools]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0927</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0927.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-10-04">Oct. 4, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">[TWENTY-THOUSAND CHILDRED ARE STARVING IN THE SCHOOLS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The report of Superintendent, William L. Bogan shows that among the Chicago school children, 15,000 are hungry and 5,000 are virtually starving to death.</p>
   <p>Great Movement for Speedy Relief.</p>
   <p>Five-thousand children go to school without breakfast, and fifteen-thousand others are on a hunger diet, is the report which was brought into the school board by Superintendent, William L. Bogan, after a careful and thorough investigation, which lasted a whole year.</p>
   <p>One year ago a trustee, Mr. Mathew Spiegel had brought in a resolution to the school board, that an investigation be made of the children attending the schools of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The resolution was accepted and Mr. Bogan received orders from the school-board to make an investigation. However, no one, at that time, knew how outrageously acute the situation really was, although Mr. Spiegel, who is known as the father of this movement had then pointed out that the situation was <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0928.jpg" n="2"/>extremely grave, and that something must be done immediately.</p>
   <p>A Question of Law.</p>
   <p>Last year, when Mr. Spiegel had brought in this resolution about the investigation, many of the trustees on the Board of Education maintained that this procedure would not bring practical results. According to law, the Board has no right to spend money, in order to feed the children, and the work is, therefore, a waste of time. Mr. Spiegel, however, had attacked this attitude by saying that until such time as the legal justification is established, the destitute children can not remain in such a condition, and that there is a definite need for establishing the truth.</p>
   <p>The investigation has been made and the report has created a sensation everywhere. No one, however, could imagine that twenty-thousand children are actually starving. The attorney of the Board of Education, still maintains that money that he gets for building purposes, should not be used to feed the children, but individuals and institutions will, no doubt, take the matter in hand.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0929.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Bogan and the persons he appointed to investigate the matter, did not base their findings upon rumors and have investigated every case separately. The report, therefore, is very lengthy and not even a fraction of it can be brought to light. It was impossible to read the entire report at the meeting, therefore each trustee received a typed copy. Some of the details were recorded, so that citizens of Chicago could have an idea of this most terrifying situation.</p>
   <p>The report shows a colossal number of cases in the Ghetto and other districts of Chicago. The adults go to bed, without having eaten lunch or dinner, in order that their children could, at least, have a dry piece of bread for breakfast, before going the school.</p>
   <p>The report states that the martyrdom of mothers in the poor districts is so Wide-spread, that they do not consider it martydom. The report tells of children found rummaging in the garbage cans of the alleys, gathering filthy and rotten food in order to continue their pitiful existence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0930.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Bogan and his assistant had found a great number of women, who though they are working, are barely earning $2.50 a week and on this miserable pittance, they support four or five children. Thus, one need not stretch his imagination too far to see how well these children can be fed. They have also discovered many homes, where the bread winner was unemployed for over a year, the mother is sick and the children are virtually starving.</p>
   <p>The report, briefly, is placing society on trial, for tolerating this undescribable misery. This situation is directly responsible for the wide spread crime and juvenile delinquency.</p>
   <p>Masses of Jewish Children Involved.</p>
   <p>The report was so lengthy that it required a full week merely to look through it.</p>
   <p>All Chicago schools and the number of starving children who attend these</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0931.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>schools were enumerated. In this, the West Side took the most prominent place. The following schools, attended by Jewish children are listed in this report:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Pasteur School</cell>
     <cell>200 children</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Washburn School</cell>
     <cell>203 children</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Ewing School</cell>
     <cell>100 children</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Smith School</cell>
     <cell>49 children</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Tilden School</cell>
     <cell>35 children</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Rogers School</cell>
     <cell>41 children</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Drummond School</cell>
     <cell>30 children</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Montefiore School</cell>
     <cell>25 children</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Kosciusko School</cell>
     <cell>50 children</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Many other schools besides these, which are located on the North-West Side, and are attended by Jewish children were listed.</p>
   <p>Plans of Action.</p>
   <p>In order to feed an army of starving children (school), $30,000 would be required. It would then be possible to furnish kitchens at the schools, so that the starving children could have a hot meal once a day, which they do not see in their homes, for years. In view of the fact, that the school board has no right to do this alone, it will be up to philanthropic people, to see that this <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0932.jpg" n="6"/>of this horrible report. Mayor Busse stated that the city council will, no doubt take this matter up, but until this is done, an intensive movement should be on the way, in order to bring this to the attention of the public. As a private citizen, he promised assistance. He offered the first contribution toward the needed sum of $30,000. He also expressed his intention of contacting his friends and acquaintances for funds.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
