<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-15">Mar. 15, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-15">Mar. 15, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That the Chicago "World's Greatest Newspaper," The Chicago Tribune, deemed it necessary, for political reasons, to pretend to believe in the confessions of a knavish fellow, whom an impartial jury refused to believe even in an instance which could leave no doubt, can be readily understood by all. The Tribune picked up this man's confession and created a sensation about the purchases on land transacted by the Board of Education.</p>
   <p>Everything is permissible in wartime and in politics. The Tribune has used the same weapons that other politicians use in their struggle for political existence.</p>
   <p>It isn't new to hear from a political rostrum how one politician "reveals" things about his opponent which have never existed. Truth is evaded at a political festival. Accusations are framed and evidence is fabricated in a political war.</p>
   <p>It is said that even decent politicians are not so clean. But, in the first <pb n="2"/> place, there is very little decency among politicians. Second, politicians measure decency with a different rule from what ordinary people do, and whatever appears indecent to the average layman is very decent to a politician.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Tribune, whose ambition is to publish the World's greatest newspaper, is also meddling with politics. And this time it is on the other side of the fence. The Tribune, as we all know, is Republican, reactionary Republican, except in the last campaign when ex-President Taft refused to dance the political tango in accordance with the tune it [The Tribune] played. The Tribune was then forced to oppose him and line up with Theodore Roosevelt, thus becoming progressive until after the presidential election. After the election, not knowing who would gain the upper hand in the Republican party, the Tribune became impartial, i.e., half Republican and half progressive. But the Tribune is at all times a bitter opponent of the Democratic Party.</p>
   <p>Incidentally, the State of Illinois, Cook County, and the city of Chicago <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0369.jpg" n="3"/>are now governed by Democrats. And still worse, Chicago the city in which the "World's Greatest Newspaper" should really be influential, where it should be adhered to if it had any power, is administered by a fraction of the Democratic party, against whom the Tribune is more embittered than any other political opponent.</p>
   <p>Those who are somewhat posted in Chicago politics, know that there exists an old feud between the Tribune and the Harrison family, and from every indication, it still will have to do some tall fighting against the Harrison administration in Chicago. It stands to reason that the Tribune's opposition to the Harrison family could not prevent the old Carter H. Harrison from being elected mayor for five terms. This proves that the Tribune is probably the "World's Greatest Newspaper," but when it comes to a political battle the broad masses can interpret the political-dyed news and the made-to-order editorials, which aren't taken seriously.</p>
   <p>A newspaper can only have an effect on the masses, especially on election day, if it is honest, impartial, and not one-sided. The large masses are not so <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0370.jpg" n="4"/>blind as mudslingers would have us believe. Even if the Tribune is the "World's Greatest Newspaper" it is rather little in proportion to Chicago's population, especially when it assumes the role of a moral preacher venting chastisement and reprimanding the Democratic party, the Democratic city, county, and state administration. It is the advice of a friend that sinks deeply into the heart; the enemy's advice goes into one ear and out through the other.</p>
   <p>It is therefore very natural for the Tribune to devote its front page and print in large letters the admissions of a scamp whom an impartial jury declined to believe and whose testimony concerned a dead man unable to disprove it.</p>
   <p>But, from the Tribune's standpoint, as long as the admission could cast a shadow on the city administration, it was deserving of front-page space; as long as the admission could cast some suspicion on the people who are responsible for the success of the Democratic party, the Tribune took to it as flies take to molasses. Upon investigation, however, Chicago's noted businessmen proved that everything written by the Tribune was a lie, which should have occupied some corner on the 13th page in fine print. Partiality in politics leads to the adoption of the <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0371.jpg" n="5"/>Jesuitical maxim that "the end justifies the means." The Tribune is no exception to this.</p>
   <p>But if we can understand the tactics of the "World's Greatest Newspaper," we cannot conceive of the traditions of our so-called great Jews. We cannot agree with the Hirschs, the Hirschbergs, the Schoenfarbers, and the Levys who follow the Tribune's footsteps when they act nonsensically in politics.</p>
   <p>[At this point the writer reproaches the rabbis for taking a hand in politics and for agreeing with the attitude the Tribune has taken in this case. The writer concluded by saying that "this exposes the pettiness of our so-called great men."]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
