<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-26">Jan. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Most Organizations Support Paul Rottenberg for Alderman in the Twenty-Fourth Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0224</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0224.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-26">Jan. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">MOST ORGANIZATIONS SUPPORT PAUL ROTTENBERG FOR ALDERMAN IN THE TWENTY-FOURTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Twenty-fourth Ward is one of the new wards, which has been formed out of various sections of older wards. It has no alderman at present. Ninety per cent of its inhabitants are Jewish. It is the only ward in Chicago which can truly be called a Jewish ward, and is the most beautiful, so to speak, "Jewish Ghetto" in America. The greatest and most significant institutions of the Orthodox Jews of Chicago can be found there. Most of our synagogues are there. Hitherto, the ward has had no Jewish representative in the City Council and it is high time that it should.</p>
   <p>Most organizations and prominent Jews have sought and finally found the most suitable man for the office of alderman. They believe that Attorney Paul Rottenberg is the man. They have made a good selection. Paul Rottenberg is one of the most popular, courageous, and energetic Jews in the ward. He is also a good speaker; he is tactful and he has a sense of justice. He is well <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0225.jpg" n="2"/>acquainted with the needs of that ward. He has been a resident there for a number of years. The interests of the Jews of that ward are well known to him, and he will know what has to be done if he is elected to the City Council.</p>
   <p>The primary elections are still far distant but the campaign for Mr. Rottenberg is in full swing. Young and old have joined the campaign to work for him. Men and women of all parties, lodges, vereins, unions, and synagogues have endorsed his candidacy. Rottenberg has always been friendly toward everyone who turned to him for help. His influence in city and county government has always been great. Mr. Rottenberg is also very sympathetic toward Jewish refugees and unfortunate Jews abroad.</p>
   <p>Among his supporters there are both Republicans and Democrats. Mr. Rottenberg is running on the nonpartisan ticket, although he is a Republican and Republican Committeeman of his Ward.</p>
   <p>Everyone is of the opinion that Mr. Rottenberg, when elected, will represent his office with honor to himself, his ward and the whole community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
