<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-10-13">Oct. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Critical Hour</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-10-13">Oct. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE CRITICAL HOUR</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The critical hour of the War has arrived.</p>
   <p>The four-year-old struggle between light and darkness, between freedom and oppression, nears its conclusion. The hearts are beating, brains are impatient, and souls are aroused at the sight of this fifth and last act of the horrible bloody drama. We will soon witness the great peace act of this historical tragedy, which will seal the fate of the future generation, bring victory for freedom, victory for all oppressed and persecuted nations, victory for this country of liberty, and victory for the Jewish people.</p>
   <p>The heroism of a group, nation or race, is shown not only in the struggle alone, but also in the patience of carrying the struggle through, in the strength of holding out till the last moment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0442.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If the nations who are fighting for liberty and democracy do not have the strength to hold out, or if they fail to show the heroism of patient waiting and hope, then the entire bloody combat will have been useless, and all the sacrifices which were made upon the altar of freedom, the best and most influential forces of humanity, billions of gold and the martyrdom of entire nations, will have been of no avail.</p>
   <p>Now, in this critical moment of the universe, in this fateful hour, when the lot of mankind is being decided, it is the duty of every American citizen, of every American Jew to make the greatest sacrifices, sacrifices of blood and gold, in order to secure the victory of freedom.</p>
   <p>With a victorious America, the ideas of freedom and justice will also be victorious, and the black forces in world's history will be licked. Anti-Semitism and the pogrom beast will be conquered everywhere, and the ideals of redemption for us and for all other oppressed and persecuted nations will become a reality.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0443.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Help America to victory! Help the Jewish people to victory!</p>
   <p>This war is not only America's war, it is also the Jewish people's war. If America wins the war, the Jewish people will also win it--Jews will enjoy freedom throughout the world and a national home in Palestine.</p>
   <p>If America wins, every Jew throughout the world wins--he will have won a new status in life, the respect and esteem which he deserves as the son of an ancient people with great classical traditions.</p>
   <p>In helping America to win--and win fast--we are not only doing our duty as citizens, not only expressing our appreciation to the country which accepted us when we were running away from the enemy, and which has given us freedom and a thousand opportunities to develop our strength, but we are also helping ourselves as Jews; we help the Jewish people to obtain their old homeland and become a nation equal to other nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0444.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>America now needs the assistance of every citizen.</p>
   <p>The moment has also arrived for us Jews in America to prove that we love America, that we are thankful to America, that we love our own people, and wish to make them free and happy.</p>
   <p>We are now facing the greatest test in our history.</p>
   <p>Will we withstand this test? Will we come to the aid of the American Government, and by so doing help the Jewish people in Europe and Asia with our last drop of blood and our last penny? Will we turn out to be the great generation in a great moment? Will we give America everything it pleads for?</p>
   <p>To attain a quick and secure victory, America must have man power and money.</p>
   <p>We have given it as much man power as it required. Are our dollars dearer to us than our sons and brothers whom we gave to America?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0445.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Many of us have given to America our only son--should we not also give our last and only dollar?</p>
   <p>Is the dollar dearer to us than our blood?</p>
   <p>Mr. Jew! You, who gave your son to America, how many dollars have you invested in Liberty bonds? And you Mr. Jacob, who did not give any son to America, how much have you invested in Liberty bonds?</p>
   <p>Your hand on your heart--the real truth.</p>
   <p>Jews! We are facing a terrific test.</p>
   <p>If you so desire, we can withstand that test.</p>
   <p>Pawn your pillows and buy Liberty bonds.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
