<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-07-03">July 3, 1912</date><title level="a">Woodrow Wilson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0991</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0991.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-07-03">July 3, 1912</date><title level="a">WOODROW WILSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After eight days of arduous work, the Democratic National Convention finally nominated Prof. Woodrow Wilson as the Democratic candidate for president of the United States.</p>
   <p>Woodrow Wilson is an old candidate for the presidential office, since he was elected as Governor by the Republican state, New Jersey. He was considered as "Presidential Timber", but he was never looked upon as the highest sort of candidate. He was always one of the sort that could do in time of need.</p>
   <p>The reason for this is that Woodrow Wilson, although he calls himself a Democrat, is practically no Democrat at all; his strength is not acclaimed for his activity in the Democratic Party, but on the contrary, from his inactiveness.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0992.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As professor of history and economy since 1885, he never mingled in any practical politics, and, therefore, he never participated in any battles that occurred in the Democratic Party for the last sixteen years. He voted the straight Democratic Ticket as did other millions of democrats. He could neither be exposed by the conservatives nor the progressives, and it is therefore, very easy to unite with him.</p>
   <p>This took place in New Jersey when the Democrats wanted a candidate for governor and the same thing occurred at the Democratic Convention now. Speaking in general, Woodrow Wilson is rather a neutral candidate. Nothing could be said about him pro or con.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0993.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From the Jewish standpoint Woodrow Wilson is a relentless chauvinist, a strong opponent of immigration, believes that America was created for the nobility whose great, great grandparents came to America hundreds of years ago, hates the "foreigners" who come here to confiscate the country from the "people", and is the opposite of the noble, calm, good hearted, true Democratic William Howard Taft. Wilson will not be able to contend with the problems of, at least, the Jews and other nationalities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
