<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Inter Ocean</title>,
<date when="1880-02-12">February 12, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Greenebaum's Bank</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1512</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1512.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Inter Ocean</title>,
<date when="1880-02-12">February 12, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">GREENEBAUM'S BANK</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Washington, February 11. - The Committee on Banking and Currency today heard Congressman Price read the report of the sub-committee which went to Chicago to investigate Greenebaum's Bank. The report was adopted and Mr. Price was authorized to present it to the House, which he did. Following is the full text: Mr. Price begins with quoting the resolution of the House under which the committee was organized, and says: In compliance with which resolution, a sub-committee, consisting of Messrs. Buckner, Lounsberry, and Price, visited Chicago on the 16th day of October, 1879. Mr. Edmund Jassen appeared as attorney for petitioners, at whose instance the investigation was asked for. James M. Flower, receiver of the German National Bank, and Henry Greenebaum, who was president of the bank before and at the time of the failure, was, also present. The committee remained in session for several days examining witnesses in reference to all matters complained of, and also in examining the books of the bank, in which examination the committee was assisted by an expert accountant. The testimony of all witnesses demonstrated very conclusively that great irregularity <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1513.jpg" n="2"/>had been practiced in conducting the affairs of the bank and that the manner of keeping the books had been of such character as to make it very difficult for even an expert accountant to ascertain the nature of the transactions. These irregularities were so numerous and so great as to impress the minds of the committee with suspicion that possibly they were intentional. The language of one of the witnesses who was introduced as an expert bookkeeper, is: "I think they have been kept in a very loose manner, and in making the examination we have found many entries of a blank character." Again, this witness says, "Only a party familiar with the books could trace many of the entries." Again he says, "As a rule the entries are of such a blind character that it is with great difficulty that anything could be traced to its true origin." Your committee also finds that good assets were used after the failure of the bank to pay preferred creditors, which was clearly in violation of the law. So far as the acts of the Comptroller of the Currency and of receiver are concerned, the letters put in evidence and the testimony of witnesses on the stand, indicate a disposition on the part of these officers to protect the rights of stockholders and creditors of the bank. Possibly a little more vigilance and energy might have been exercised to a good purpose, and in the opinion of your committee, a fair <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1514.jpg" n="3"/>construction of the law would have authorized and justified these officers in adopting more stringent measures toward the directors and managing officers of the bank, for the testimony discloses the fact that transfers were made on books of the bank by which good assets were issued to pay Preferred Creditors of the Bank.</p>
   <p>Such transfers are clearly under the law not only voidable, but absolutely void. At the time of the failure of the bank in December, 1877, its affairs, as appear from the testimony, were put into the hands of a managing committee, consisting of Henry Greenebaum, the president, with the vice-president and cashier of the bank, and this committee had entire control of its affairs until December, 1878, and during all of this year, as appears from the testimony, Henry Greenebaum was really the managing man, and controlled the assets of the bank, and it was during this time that the assets of the bank shrunk from what he said was eighty or ninety per cent of its par value to nearly nothing. In one instance, the testimony of Mr. Flower is, that the bank lost $20,000, and that Henry Greenebaum got the money. The <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1515.jpg" n="4"/>over-drafts of persons doing business with the bank were allowed to run up sometimes to nearly $100,000, for which there was no security, and in addition to this, memorandums on slips of paper by Henry Greenebaum, amounting to nearly $15,000, were counted as cash.</p>
   <p>The whole secret of the trouble with the German National Bank of Chicago, has arisen from the fact that the directors, whose sworn duty it was to watch over and guard the interests of the stockholders and creditors of the bank, utterly failed to attend to their duty, but have allowed one or two men to manage its affairs and handle its funds as they saw proper, and if the creditors of a national bank have not the right of action at common law, or in equity, against the board of directors, who by wrong action or neglect of duty cause loss to the stockholders or creditors, then the law should be so changed as to give that remedy as in evidence there was gross negligence on the part of those whose sworn duty it was to see that the bank was conducted according to law, if, indeed, it did not amount to Criminal Wrong.</p>
   <p>Your committee calls attention to the fact that on the 6th of December, 1877, the books of the bank did not show any over-drafts, while a balance sheet or statement of the affairs of the bank, on the same day showed an over- <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1516.jpg" n="5"/>draft of $92,032. The grounds for asking this investigation by Congress, as disclosed by the petition presented to the House, presupposed mismanagement if not criminal management of the affairs of the bank by some of its officers, as well as a charge of failure on the part of the Comptroller of the Currency to initiate a criminal prosecution of the alleged delinquents, and an indisposition on the part of the receiver to do his duty in the premises. It appears that when application was made to the Comptroller embodying charges against the officers of the bank, that he promptly referred the matter to the Solicitor of the Treasury, and that he, with the assent of the Attorney General, directed the United State's Attorney for the Northern District of Illinois to lay the matter before the Grand Jury, but at the time this order was made there was no Grand Jury session, and shortly thereafter the attorney for the government resigned his position and a successor had been appointed but a short time before the committee met in Chicago. No preliminary examination of the charges against the bank officers had been made, nor had any arrests been made with a view to such preliminary examination, but your committee has learned that, since the investigation, these charges against the late president have been presented to the first Grand Jury impaneled after the order of the Solicitor <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1517.jpg" n="6"/>of the Treasury was received, and that an indictment has been found, and the officer thus indicted has been held to bail, and his case will be ready for trial at the next term of court.</p>
   <p>Your committee reaffirms that the leading and principal cause of the failure of this bank is found in the fact that the directors utterly failed in their duty to watch over the affairs of the bank.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
