<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1925-01-15">January 15, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Coolidge Changes His Cabinett Secretaries</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0956</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0956.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1925-01-15">January 15, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">COOLIDGE CHANGES HIS CABINETT SECRETARIES</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Different reasons are being given for the resignation of Secretary of State, Mr. Hughes, but the newspapers in Washington admit that they, do not know definitely. Something happened behind the curtains, which is being hidden. Only a few weeks ago, it was officially declared in the name of the president, that his new term, which begins March 4th, all cabinet secretaries will remain in their position, with the exception of Secretary of Labor Davis. The declaration stressed the denial of rumors, that the three secretaries, Hughes, Mellan, and Hoover, will drop out; in other words, the President assured the public that Hughes will remain in office. And suddenly, without the least warning, the news appeared that Hughes had resigned, and that the President had appointed someone else in his place.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0957.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Why was it done so suddenly? And why was the President in such a hurry to appoint another one, and why did not the President consult anybody about these affairs?? (1) The resignation of Hughes, and (2) the appointment of his successor Kellogg. The newspapers in Washington announced, that the news was as suprising to the important Republican officials as it was to the average citizen. Why were these events hidden behind a well of deep mystery? If the reason has a party character, it is not important to us; what is the different to us who, or which clique will have control over the Republican machine in the next four years? But it is possible, that the cause is political.</p>
   <p>This is of great importance. Hughes was most responsible fox American was too stubbornness in the question about Russia. Hughes fixed the policy of America concerning the debts, which the allies owe to us.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0958.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Hughes stated the viewpoint of America towards Mexico, and also towards the Southern Republics and towards Central America. It is possible that Coolidge decided to change the policy of his Administration in one or more of all foreign affairs. And as long as Hughes would remain in office it would be impossible for Coolidge to do it.</p>
   <p>The appointment of Ambassador Kellogg to replace Hughes does not throw any light on the situation. Nothing is known of Kellogg, he is not in machine politics, and he has no position in questions of policies in foreign politics. The fact, that the president appointed such a man to fill that most important office shows that Coolidge has decided to control that particular office himself. But it is not clear as to why he wants to control this office?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0959.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>During the period that Kellogg was Ambassador to England, he distinguished himself by his silence, no one knows what opinions he has concerning the important foreign matters. He is of the same caliber as Coolidge, he is silent, and the reason for his silent, is, perhaps, the same he has no convictions; he waits until someone else will decide for him.</p>
   <p>There is only one consolation in this affair: it is almost possible, that through this change, the power of Senator Borah in foreign questions, will be increased. Borah is now Chairman of the Benate Committee of Foreign Relations. He has liberal views on many of the important questions, especially in relation to the recognition of Russia. It can be expected that Senator Borah will get along better with Kellogg than with a Hughes.</p>
   <pb n="5"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0960.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>A Washington report stated that when representatives of the state became aware of this, they protested to the President. Coolidge answered that he would not heed their opinion. He declared that he will appoint his Cabinet secretaries, and that no one can advise him, in this matter. This attitude is against the regulations of machine politics.</p>
   <p>According to the rules, the President is obligated to consult the Senators and the Congressmen. Coolidge broke the rules, because he has declared to all, that his party is in Washington, and that he has decided to keep the party machine in his hands. It was demonstrated as self leadership.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
