<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Chicago Hebrew Institute</title>
      <date when="1918-01">January 1918</date>
      <title level="a">Observer War Service Activities</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0819</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0819.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Hebrew Institute</title>
     <date when="1918-01">January 1918</date>
     <title level="a">Observer War Service Activities</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There ishardly an agency operating in this country that has not developed on its curriculum a well defined emergency war time program along the lines suggested by bodies like the AMERICAN INSTITUTE OF SOCIAL SERVICE, THE NATIONAL CONFERENCE OF SOCIAL WORK, THE RED CROSS, THE WAR DEPARTMENT COMMISSION ON TRAINING CAMP ACTIVITIES, THE ADMINISTRATION, authorities having to do with important problems in connection with war industries, the amount of insurance and family allotments for soldiers and sailors--and measures in prospect for the treatment of soldiers who return disabled, Some do more, others do less. Each of them, however, are functioning to the best of their capacity--many of them working under special curcumstances, because of the increased cost in operation, in contrast to the decrease in income. But there, too, the idea is always foremost to develop a war-time program which shall be definitely constructive in character and in every way of service to the nation.</p>
   <p>In co-operation with the Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society of America, which was responsible for the developing of a system whereby the relatives in <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0820.jpg" n="2"/>America (who have since the war had no word from their relatives in Russia), were placed in communication with their loved ones across the waters, we have distributed 2129 letters out of a total of 3954 received. This mail contained letters not from Jewish relatives abroad to their relatives in this country, but from non-Jews as well. A total of 1338 letters of non-Jews by means of co-operating with the Immigrant Protective League were distributed. Over 1800 letters were not claimed--this, in spite of the many published lists in our local Jewish papers, particularly the Daily Jewish Courier, which co-operated most unselfishly in this important matter.</p>
   <p>The duty which is imposed upon the member of the Service Club, and one which is probably of greatest service, is the visiting of the boys'home and becoming a friend of the members of the home. There are quite a number of mothers, who if it were not for the service which the members of the Club intend to give, would probably not hear from their boys. Many of the Mothers are unable to <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0821.jpg" n="3"/>read the letters which the boys write in English, and a great many of the boys would not understand the letters which their Mothers write in Yiddish--and thus the problem, which these girls will solve by acting as the happy medium. The visit to the home on the part of the girl member will undoubtedly prove a comfort to the Mother of the family. She will read the letter received from the boy--she will write letters for the boy's Mother--see that they are properly addressed and attend to their sending and thus keep the "Home Fires Burning" and "Hold the Home Lines".</p>
   <p>The patriotic object of the Club is to co-operate with other possible agencies in the community which have direct bearing on serving the soldier. Because of the very large number of boys who have left for service directly from the Institute, the girls feel that their duty lies closest to those, and thus not until all of our boys are cared for will others be considered. For the service they render is a personal service, and the donating of things at large does not carry with it the personal touch.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0822.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Among their meeting, they knit and saw, and now accumulated a considerable stock of finished products in spite of the many pieces which have already been sent away. An interesting auxiliary of the War Service Club is the "Orthodox Old People's Home, Women's Department". A group of old ladies, the youngest 65 and the oldest 90, are busy knitting socks from wool that is supplied them by the Service Club. The finished products they turn over to the Service Club as their contribution.</p>
   <p>They are proud of being members of the Organization and wear, with much importance, the Service Club button, which is worn by the members of the Club.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
