<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title><bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>, <date when="1931-03-06">Mar. 6, 1931</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1541</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet Archive by the University of
     Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>,
      <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus
      Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.b"/>

   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
</div><div type="citation">
 <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>, <date when="1931-03-06">Mar. 6, 1931</date></bibl>
</div>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1541.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The music critics have proclaimed him the foremost guest soloist of the Chicago Symphony
    Orchestra. They praised him highly for his playing of the Stocke Concerto, considered one of the
    most difficult musical compositions. Through this appearance the young violinist has already
    gained recognition and it will be easy for him to climb the ladder of success. Yet, all this was
    not such a big surprise to those, who have heard him play. This happened a short while ago, when
    he appeared together with the famous Italian tenor, Gigli.</p>
   <p>To appear in the same concert with the world famous Gigli would be an ordeal for any artist,
    but in spite of that, Rosenstein was greatly applauded on that evening. The music critics
    proclaimed him a violin prodigy. They also stated that if he had come from abroad the music
    world would have given him recognition at once, but being a Chicago boy it would take somewhat
    longer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1542.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Although young Rosenstein has made such a brilliant start in life, he earns his living as a
    messenger boy. He is employed by the Chicago Daily News. He is very modest and contented with
    the kind of work he is doing at present, for he is certain that it will not take very long until
    he'll reach real success.</p>
   <p>The writer visited the home of the Rosensteins at 2918 W. Roosevelt Rd. It is not a musical
    family. David Rosenstein, Joseph's father, is a tailor by trade, and belongs to local 144,
    Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union. He is employed by Alfred Decker &amp; Cohn and makes an
    honest moderate living for his family. He came to Chicago many years ago from a little town in
    Galicia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1543.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mrs. Rosenstein is simple, kind-hearted and sociable. She typifies the true Yiddishe Mame. Her
    face becomes radiant when one mentions her Joseph's name. Besides a married sister there is a
    younger sister and a younger brother, Emanuel, who is studying to play the piano.</p>
   <p>When Joseph was eight years old, while walking with his father, he saw a man who carried a
    cello. Little Joseph admired the instrument and urged his dad to buy him one like it. The next
    day Mr. Rosenstein purchased a violin for his son. Two years later his father arranged lessons
    for him with the celebrated violin teacher, Herman Pidler. Although Mr. Pidler was by that time
    old and deaf he was nevertheless still popular, especially on the West Side.</p>
   <p>When little Joseph played for the first time for Mr. Pidler, the latter laughed because
    Joseph's first teacher had trained him to hold the bow the wrong way. It was Mr. Pidler who
    recognized Joe's talent.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1544.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The young Rosenstein won a six years' scholarship at the Conservatory of Music of which Mr.
    Ramon B. Gurwin was president. Mr. Gurwin is very proud of Joseph, and Joe is very fond of and
    grateful to his teacher.</p>
   <p>Rosenstein is not only adept in music, but also in his other studies. While attending Marshall
    High School, he won a scholarship for the private Parker High School. At Parker he was
    considered one of the best students.</p>
   <p>His hobby at present is the reading of philosophic books. He is familiar with the philosophic
    works of Aristotle,Schopenhauer, Kant and Spinoza.</p>
   <p>His favorite hero in history is the Jewish statesman, Disraeli. He loves to read about him.
    But all the philosophic works and the heroes vanish as a fog when he takes his fiddle and begins
    to play.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1545.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>He sees before him visions and beautiful tones are filling the air. They tell fascinating
    tales. They paint master pieces and awaken dreams and hope in the hearts of his listeners.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
