<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-18">May 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Meditations of the Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0723</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0723.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-18">May 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">MEDITATIONS OF THE DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>While the packers, the clothing manufacturers, and various other industries of the country, including even the steel mills, long the most backward in its policy to labor, have [made wage] increases to their employees, in recognition of the upward trend of living costs, we read that the Wisconsin legislature, reputed to be the most progressive state assembly in the United States, has passed a bill which virtually repudiates some of the pension rights of Wisconsin public school teachers. We do not know all the provisions of the pension allotments granted teachers in the state of Wisconsin, and it may be possible that such modifications in the existing laws as were made were to the interests of the majority of teachers as well as to the public, but at any rate, we wish to say that we have never read in any newspaper in the last year any increase in salaries granted teachers. The surface and elevated transportation employees of the city of Chicago plan to enforce their demands by a strike. The threat of a strike in other industries has resulted in an increase of wages in those industries, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0724.jpg" n="2"/>but teachers may not strike. The odium that would attach to a cessation of their work would brand the teachers themselves and put them in an unfavorable light, but while their right to strike is denied, by their own organizations as by the municipality generally, should not their right to an increase in salary also be considered? The teachers of America are, on the whole, the poorest paid of all professions, and are far below many trades in income. Someday America will awaken to the rights of its teachers and the best needs of its children that receive instruction from them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
