<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-09-20">September 20, 1930</date>, Vol. 80, p.183.
<title level="a">Rabbi and Doctor</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1141</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1141.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-09-20">September 20, 1930</date>, Vol. 80, p.183.
<title level="a">RABBI AND DOCTOR</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great rabbis of old among whom were many artisans and craftsmen, declared that the Torah must not be made an instrument with which to earn a livelihood. Dr. Albert B. Yudelson, a student of Talmudic lore, conscientiously abided by this Talmudic injunction. When he came to Chicago in 1902, to assume the ritual leadership of the South Side Hebrew Congregation, he matriculated soon after as a medical student in the medical department of the Northwestern University. Dr. Yudelson was born in Suvalk, August 2, 1872. His father, Yehudah Leib and his mother, Hanna (Strashun) Yudelson, occupied prominent places among the Maskilim of the city and their home was a mecca for the Jewish intellectuals of the neighborhood. The famous Chaim Zelig Smolensky, editor of the 'H magid, was among the frequent visitors at their home. Albert attended Cheder up to the age of eleven and then entered the Yeshivah. Parallel with those studies ran his preparations for the gymnasium, for which he was instructed by private tutors. After Bar Mitzvah he continued his studies in the Yeshivah as well as those in the gymnasium, with a view to become, eventually, a govern, ment rabbi in compliance with the wishes of his father. To him and his mother, the idea of being a government rabbi was obnoxious. At the age of twenty-one, he came to the United States with his parents, brothers and sisters. The family <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1142.jpg" n="2"/>made their home in Troy, N. Y. There Yudelson became the principal of the Hebrew Free School, a position which he occupied for four years, during which time he studied English and its literature. In '96, he accepted a like position in the Patterson Hebrew School, Patterson, N. Y. His next move was to the city of New York. He entered the New York State University, where he remained until 1900, when he accepted a call to become director of the Jewish Educational Society of Brooklyn. In 1901, he passed the Regent's examination and was awarded the degree of A. B. His public activities began with his coming to Chicago. Dr. Yudelson was admitted to the practice of medicine in 1906, but continued his work in the rabbinate until 1910. These four years he spent, when not engaged in his duties as rabbi, in research work in Neuro-Pathology. He returned to Europe for a short sojourn during which he took post-graduate work in nervous and mental diseases. Immediately after he resigned from the rabbinate he devoted his entire time to the practice of medicine, specializing in neuro-psychopathic cases. Dr. Yudelson holds a professorship in the medical branch of Northwestern University; he is attending neurologist at Wesley Memorial Hospital and at Cook County Hospital.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
