<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title><date when="1919-04-26">April 26, 1919</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1396</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1396.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title><date when="1919-04-26">April 26, 1919</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish Bakery Proprietors were the first to sign the new agreement with the Baker's International. Sixty-two Jewish bakers have signed the agreement with the Jewish Union Local 237, for better working conditions and less night work. The pay is higher than many other Bakery Union Member in Chicago receives.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Bakery Union not only won day work, but it also succeeded in securing a 7 hour day instead of an 8 hour day, when electricity is being used for weighing and measuring purposes. The first Bakery Unions to sign the agreement for day work and the 7 hour day were, Jacobs Wisnievsky, Mossberg, and Kaplan. In the gentile bakeries, where German-Americans are working the Master Employer's Association refuses to compromise, a strike will be declared tomorrow in all bakeries, but Jewish ones. The gentile employers are stating in full page advertisements, that they are willing to settle with <!-- 5423972_4_1_1397 omitted, duplicate of 5423972_4_1_1398 --><pb facs="5423972_4_1_1398.jpg" n="2"/>the workers, but that day labor will result in the public's being unable to secure fresh bread.</p>
   <p>Comrade Homan of the Baker's and Confectioner's Union issued a statement which disproved the statements of the Association. He proves that it will be an easy matter to introduce day labor in the shops and that it will cause no inconvenience to the public. The workers would greatly benefit by working no later than 11 p. m. each night instead of spending the entire night in the various shops.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
