<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-12-11">Dec. 11, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">[Butchers Protest Judge Fisher's Decision]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-12-11">Dec. 11, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">[BUTCHERS PROTEST JUDGE FISHER'S DECISION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish butchers of Chicago are very nice people, but men should be men, men of character and pride. When a man gives his word, he should keep it. But when a man gives his word and fails to live up to it, he is not a man but a fraud.</p>
   <p>The Jewish butchers of Chicago had a dispute with the slaughterers. They wanted to compel the slaughterers to pluck the poultry that they kill. The slaughterers argued that they were slaughterers, not pluckers, and absolutely refused to do any plucking. So the arguments waxed between the two parties. After a long, drawn-out argument, both parties agreed to turn over the entire case to Judge Harry Fisher and to abide by his decision. Judge Fisher held a few hearings, thoroughly considered the case, and finally rendered a decision that the slaughterers should not do any plucking.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1349.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Everything should be lovely and rosy now, but it is not. The butchers have a complaint against Judge Fisher: his decision is not fair.</p>
   <p>This attitude on the part of the butchers is not very commendable. Once they have chosen Judge Fisher as their arbiter, and declared that they would depend upon him and would accept his verdict, they have no right to complain now. Men should not act that way. A real man must be a "good loser," must be a sport. If he has lost fairly, he must accept the loss cheerfully and make the best of it.</p>
   <p>I can understand the butchers not being enthusiastic about Judge Fisher's decision because the decision is not in their favor. But I cannot understand at all how they can be such poor sports and how they can complain against Judge Fisher. If the butchers want to know how the public reacted to the judge's decision, I can tell them that it met with unanimous approval and with shouts of "bravo". To protest now against the decision of a man upon whom they agreed to depend, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1350.jpg" n="3"/>means to make fools of themselves. The butchers should not be fools. This privilege belongs to the old-fashioned cantors.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: I have taken some liberties with certain parts of the text, as Dr. Melamed employs a highly idiomatic Yiddish, the translation of which into English would not make any sense.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
