<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1915-03">March, 1915</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1915-03">March, 1915</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Peace Movement Among Children.</p>
   <p>A week after the 28th day of July, 1914, the day which will be remembered for many years to come, as the beginning of the greatest war every known in the history of mankind, marks the organization of a society of children at the Chicago Hebrew Institute, the members of which pledge as follow:</p>
   <p>I pledge myself to follow the call of peace, to promote peace at home, at school, in work or play, or wherever life's path may lead me: to influence other children to follow in peaceful ways, to strive always towards the goal of peace, and to earnestly believe in the fulfillment of the prophecy of Isaiah, "And they shall beat their sword into plough-shares, their spears into pruning knives, nations shall not life up sword against nation, and they shall not learn any more war." A unique situation in this instance, for it was the spontaneous result of a large group of <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0651.jpg" n="2"/>girls, who were at this particular time studying Isaiah, and had only, as if it were on that very day, been discussing the remarkable foresight of the greatest of Hebrew prophets - Jewish girls - girls at the Institute - members of the Post Biblical History Class.</p>
   <p>The children of the Peace Society are recruited from the various classes conducted at the Institute. Each teacher or leader of these children's activities, is in turn the guide of the peace movement in his or her class. We now have approximately 450 children in ten Sabbath School classes. 294 children in seven of the children's classes in the Gymnasium, 100 children in three Hebrew classes. 35 children in two sewing classes, 35 children in the Piano School, and a few hundred children in our <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. Among the clubs which have adopted the peace principle, as well as the peace pledge, and have turned their activity practically over to the peace idea are: Rosebuds, Institute Girls' Club, Junior Social Club, The Peaceful Strivers, Morris Colts, Young Maccabees, and Shoshanath Zion. The last club expects to give an entertainment on March 7, the proceeds of which will go to the Peace Fund.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0652.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following are some of the special Peace Clubs that have been conducted for the past five months: The P. Club, the E. Club, the A. Club, the C. Club, and the E. Club. The reader will notice that the capital letters of the five clubs spell the work "Peace." the first four are girls' clubs and the last one is a boys' club.</p>
   <p>Besides the work that is done at the Institute, the following schools have been communicated with, and have been asked to cooperate in this city-wide movement: South Side Orphan Home, Orthodox Jewish Home for Aged, Montifiore Temple, Marion Place Talmud <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, Sabbath School Rodfe Zedek, Temple Sholom, Temple Or Chodosh, Temple Judea, Zion Temple, Hebrew School of the Hungarian Congregation, Temple Isaiah, Kehilath Anshe Maariv, Maxwell Settlement, Montifiore Talmud, Lincoln and Taylor Streets Talmud Torah, O'Have Sholom Sabbath School, Hungarian Congregation Sabbath School,Deborah Congregation Sabbath School, Anshe Kenesseth Israel, Marks Nathan Jewish Orphan Home, National Radical School</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
