<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-05-19">May 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Living Orpahns</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Moses Levin, principal of a Talmud Torah</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0899</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0899.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-05-19">May 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">LIVING ORPAHNS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Moses Levin, principal of a Talmud Torah</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We tremble when we hear the word "orphan." We become shocked upon learning that this or that child was left parentless. The compassion for the orphan among us (Jews) is very great; it is so greatly developed that we are ready, at any time, to do everything possible, or even impossible, in order to alleviate the orphan's afflictions, to soothe the pain he feels through his bereavement.</p>
   <p>We built a Marks Nathan Orphanage costing over one hundred thousand dollars; we provide the orphans with clothing, shelter, and education, e. g., Hebrew, music, and manual training. We seek for the orphan, the best father that money can buy. We make a rumpus when we think that something in being neglected in the Marks Nathan Home. We are always <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0900.jpg" n="2"/>ready to fight for the orphan. In other words, we exert every effort to see that the orphan lacks nothing.</p>
   <p>However, we fail to conceive the idea that there are children having parents, so-called, who are much more unfortunate than those having no parents, and these children we many call "living orphans."</p>
   <p>Yes, many children have parents and still are orphans. The parents do absolutely nothing for the spiritual development of their children. How many thousands of Jewish homes will we find in Chicago where parents take very little or no interest in the moral or spiritual condition of their children? How many thousands of Jewish families are there among us who permit children to lie about the streets until 10 o'clock at night?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0901.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The street is the unfortunate place for these children. They pay strict attention to what other children do and among them are bad children who become leaders and in a short time they teach others ugly and profane words and vile acts. They also teach one another to steal, at first a piece of candy from a sow case, later something of more value, until they start picking locks, and consequently organize themselves into a gang of stick-up boys.</p>
   <p>And we see gangs of small Jewish boys - an organized group with a leader at the head - armed clubs, iron, and stones. One gang conducts war against another. These gangs of small children go out pirate chases. They capture small children, apparently as a joke, but they go through their pockets and take away their belongings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0902.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It isn't sheer fantasy. It happened that a mother sent the (Hebrew school) tuition fee with her child, and he entered the school crying and explaining that a group of youngsters held him up on the way and took away his money.</p>
   <p>Small children play dice for money. They gamble on the side walks for many hours after school until late at night. It would be very good if they were out doors playing harmless games, if they were under the supervision of an organizer. But since they do not have this, and since therefore they prowl about the streets freely, it would be far better to send them to Hebrew school where their time would be occupied.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0903.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The children attending the Talmud Torah of private schools are not exposed to the street influence, but their number is so small in comparison with the number of Jewish children dwelling in Chicago.</p>
   <p>There are approximately 1,800 children enrolled in all the Chicago Talmud Torahs; five to six hundred children attend private Hebrew schools, and if we account for the two hundred children taking lessons privately we still do not reach the three thousand mark. This is the number of children in the city of Chicago, where 100, 000 Jewish families reside, who receive a Jewish education. The remaining thousands of children, who do not study Hebrew know very little or nothing of Judaism, and the majority of these children lie about and are brought up in the streets.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0904.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>When visiting the public schools, we see that from eighty to eighty-five per cent of the Jewish children are registered in the schools of the various districts of the city. But the question confronting us is: do these children study Hebrew? In one school, where 1,300 are registered, there are 260 non-Jewish and 1,040 Jewish children attending, which could fill up two Talmud Torahs like the Woller Street Talmud Torah. Where do these children receive their instruction in Jewish studies? Where are these Jewish children?</p>
   <p>You will see them on the side walks and streets. You will see them wandering from one corner to another. They have their gangs and their captains. In order to be occupied they start fights. They even commit such acts as would eventually lead them to become vagrants, and suddenly the father finds out that his son is charged with theft and picking locks, and he can hardly believe it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0905.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Every European father understood his duties in rearing his child. He sent him to Hebrew school; paid tuition for him. He sacrificed his life to raise his child as a Jew, as a respectable man of good manners.</p>
   <p>In his leisure time the father shared his company with the son. On the Sabbath and on holidays the father would examine the child's studies. He took interest in the child's conduct in the home, the synagogue, and the street. At each opportunity the parents taught the child how to conduct himself in society, when to speak and what to speak. On the other hand, the child always looked up to his father and obeyed him. There was always a strong spiritual relationship between father and son. The former would always influence the latter.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0906.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The Jewish child in America knows no authority, no guide. The father works long hours and has no time for that which we call children's education in the higher sense of the word.</p>
   <p>(Continued).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
