<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-05-20">May 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Living Orphans</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Moses Levin, principal of a Talmud Torah</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0894</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0894.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-05-20">May 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">LIVING ORPHANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Moses Levin, principal of a Talmud Torah</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How does the American father react towards his son? The father very seldom sees his son. He leaves early in the morning and when he comes home from work the child is either sleeping or out on the street. Neither Sabbath nor holidays exist. He is always on the hustle, bustle, harnessed down to his work just as the ox to its cart.</p>
   <p>And the poor mothers, who are enslaved, who have enough work to do in the house by preparing food and taking care of the babies, are highly pleased when the older children go out on the street to fulfill their hearts' desire.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0895.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This is how the Jewish family appears - like a ship without a rudder and the Jewish child - a living orphan. The only remedy for such children is - as was mentioned - to have them occupied in order to keep them away from the streets, by giving them a Jewish religious and moral education. To attain this, a beautiful school with modern instruction is needed. We are also in need of more teachers.</p>
   <p>The Jewish teacher in America has a twofold mission to fulfill:</p>
   <p>1. To teach Hebrew.</p>
   <p>2. He should take the place of the child's father as a guardian, friend, and authority to whom obedience, love, and respect should be shown. In other words the Jewish teacher should be the father of this living orphan.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0896.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Hebrew school should supersede the home training. It is the only place where this child - the living orphan - acquires his knowledge of Hebrew. It is also the only place where he gets his religious and moral training, where he must get that which he lacks at home.</p>
   <p>And because our future depends upon the Jewish education given to our children we ought to register more children for Jewish studies. The more students we shall have in the Talmud Torah (the greater number of soldiers, the better the Jewish army the fewer Jewish names will be bound in the Juvenile Court records.</p>
   <p>The Talmud Torahs, which we have, cannot accommodate the number of registered students. There is no seating capacity for all these children whose parents want and demand that they be given a Jewish education.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0897.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Observe closely: Poor parents register their children in Talmud Torahs to acquire a Jewish education and they are rejected due to a scarcity of seats.</p>
   <p>Do you know that we already have 621 students in the Waller Street Talmud Torah? Seventy-two (72) students in one class room! And it is merely the first week of the semester.</p>
   <p>We are more concerned with the orphan who is parentless than with the living orphan.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0898.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>By refusing to accept Jewish children in the Talmud Torah, we drive them out on the streets. We expose them to dissoluteness, and perhaps the result is that these turned-down children become thieves and it is also possible that with such conduct we turn them over to the missionaries who will certainly accept them with open arms.</p>
   <p>If a few Jewish children are sent to Pontiac, then we begin a rumpus by crying that the Jewish name is being ridiculed and disgraced! Please, worthy rabbis, wealthy Jews, welfare workers, the Chicago Jewish community, stop to think a while. You are evidently responsible for their presence there.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
