<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-10-25">October 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Where Is Our Jewish Musical Genius?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1673</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1673.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-10-25">October 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">WHERE IS OUR JEWISH MUSICAL GENIUS?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is said that Jews are a musical race. The people who think of our Jewish virtues, never forget to remind us of our Meyerbeers, Mendelschn, Rubinsteins, and so forth. Although, they were not entirely what one could call "ours", nevertheless, they were descendants of our Jewish race, and the world is satisfied to give us credit for them as part of our share in musical genius. We think ourselves are proud and often boast of our great Jewish cantors. It is a known fact that the Jew loves to hear a good cantor, or a cantor of whom Chayim, Yosel, or Berel said, "He is good." In itself, this shows that the Jew is greatly interested in song, and music which makes life sweet and worth while. It develops and elevates the spirit of the Jew. When you discuss the culture of a nation, the first thing that comes up is the development and advancement of it's music.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1674.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have in Chicago a population of over 150,000. When it comes to charity, of course the Jews are at the head of the list, considering their comparatively small number in a city like Chicago. Now when it comes to culture, the Jews can furnish their share of cultured men; they also have their share in turning out great business men, but when it comes to music, we must ask the question where are our Jewish musical artists?</p>
   <p>We all know that many of our Jewish parents of Chicago are making great sacrifices to give their children a musical training. Many of them are overburdening themselves financially for the cause. The first thing a Jewish mother does, when she possibly can afford it, is to have a piano, even if she has to buy it on the installment plan. We believe that in comparison with other nationalities there is a greater percentage of Jewish boys in Chicago, who take violin lessons.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1675.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>According to their eagerness for singing, we are certain that the Jews of Chicago can furnish their share of good voices, but the question of instrumental music is still unanswered. Where are our Jewish musicians and why do we not hear of them?</p>
   <p>Very often, at Jewish homes or entertainments, you find a Jewish girl who play the piano or violin very well. She also sings well-just enough to entertain a small ordinary audience, but that is not enough. So we are convinced that among our Jewish population, there is musical talent hidden to supply the music loving Jews of Chicago with lots of good music.</p>
   <p>What Chicago Jews lack is an organization of musical talent. The talent needs to be brought into the open, so that the Jews will be in position to show their genius in the line of music.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1676.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We believe that it would be very easy to organize a choral society on the West Side, with hundreds of good voices and we are sure that the Jews in Chicago will be exceedingly proud of the new undertaking.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
