<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-09-06">Sept. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">American Justice</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0576</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0576.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-09-06">Sept. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN JUSTICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A convention opened yesterday in Minneapolis where the voice of Americans will be raised regarding the position that President Wilson and his administration have taken in the present World War.</p>
   <p>This will not be the voice of a small group with special interests, that has been so often heard recently, but of the broad masses of American organized workers and all their policies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0577.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This is the convention of the American Federation of Labor, the American Alliance for Labor and Democracy and that prominent subdivision of the American Socialist Party which refused to further the interests of Germany, in America, through the Socialist Party.</p>
   <p>The huge laboring masses which constitute at least 75 per cent of America's population, will, through their elected delegates, declare their position on war, and the policy of President Wilson, and all doubts that have until now been expressed, in reference to the attitude of the labor masses regarding the war, will be solved.</p>
   <p>This convention is very timely. The entry of America into the World War demands unity and the undivided will of the entire American nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0578.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Every false note, every word that is uttered to discourage, and to divide the ideas of America, can no more than serve American enemies. It is necessary once for all, to know on which side the labor masses stand, who furnish both the people and the ammunition for the war....</p>
   <p>Since this convention will have to analyze the policy of President Wilson and his position as to the rights of small nations to live free and undisturbed, on their own ground, and regarding the rights of nations that have lost their independence, it is also expected there will be discussion of the problem of the Jewish nation, which seeks to regain its home on its historic ground. There will be representatives of the radical and liberal elements of America, who believe in the sacred right of people of all nations to live their own lives, and determine their own faith, undisturbed by other more powerful and greedy people and nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0579.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Such representatives at the convention will have to realize the logic and justice of the Jewish demands for the immigration to Palestine, their old home, in order to institute their own Jewish way of living and a legal, assured and publicly acknowledged home.</p>
   <p>Imbued with the American spirit of fair play, justice and good will to all nations, this convention will ultimately consider the question of what will be fair to the Jewish people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
