<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-11">June 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To Thy Brother Thou Shalt Not Charge Interest</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-11">June 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO THY BROTHER THOU SHALT NOT CHARGE INTEREST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the fifteenth of this month, Chicago will collect the sum of three quarters of a million dollars from the Federal Government as interest on the bonds of the Third Liberty Loan. Jews should not make use of the interest on these Liberty bonds for their personal needs. Every Jew should at this time uphold the spirit of the Bible, which forbids the taking of interest from a brother. There can be no more beautiful symbol of excellent patriotism and personal effort toward helping to win the war than for every Jew to take the money that he will receive next week as profit on his loan to Government and to reinvest it in smaller Government bonds--as war-saving stamps that also pay interest. The small sum that every (Jewish) bondholder of the Second Liberty Loan will reinvest for government use is insignificant in comparison to the great mass recognition and honor which the Jews of America will receive as a result of such a step.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0458.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As long as the war goes on, our army has to be supported by every cent that can be spared. So don't put the interest money in your pockets; buy war-savings stamps with it. You can obtain them from mail carriers, in the post office, and in every bank.</p>
   <p>If this movement were started by Chicago Jews and should it spread among the Jews in all parts of America, the sum collected would be a considerable contribution toward helping America win the war.</p>
   <p>The great Jewish sages and savants in all generations observed the principle of not making their knowledge of the Scriptures a Kardom Lahapor Bo [an instrument for their own end]. Thus should the American Jews act now in relation to their duty toward the land that has given them equal rights and opportunities to a degree never before equalled by any other country in history.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0459.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Their [the Jews'] responsibility is as great as that of the government. They should support the government because it is their government, and because it is now fighting for the RIGHT. The profits from this money [interest from the bonds] should be set aside for the same purpose as was the principal--that is, it should be given to the country for war supplies.</p>
   <p>It has been a long time since the Jews have had such a wonderful opportunity to acquaint the world with altruistic spirit of our Scriptures us exemplified by the law: "To thy brother thou shalt not charge interest".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
