<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-05-20">May 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Open Pacifist School in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0386</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0386.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-05-20">May 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">OPEN PACIFIST SCHOOL IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Women Delegates of twenty-two Nations Will Speak against War.</p>
   <p>A pacifist school was opened in Chicago, yesterday for the purpose of showing the horrors of war and preaching international peace.</p>
   <p>These peace classes are to be held in the Fine Arts Building, at the University of Chicago, under the supervision of Prof. Ferdinand Shevill. For two weeks the women delegates, representing the twenty-two nations of the Women's International League for Peace and Liberty, who held a convention in Washington, will act as instructors and will also explain the movement.</p>
   <p>The general subject is, "The Human Factor in Internationalism."</p>
   <p>Explanations regarding this subject are now being given in the studio hall of the Fine Arts Building by Dr. Aleta Jacobs, founder of the birth control <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0387.jpg" n="2"/>movement; Dr. Ethel Williams, one of the English delegates; Madam E. Joseph, the first woman journalist of Turkey, and Dr. N. Surofsova, of Ukrania, chief of the Ukranian peasant group.</p>
   <p>Professor Shevill; professor of history at the University of Chicago, and author of a book, The Political History of Modern Europe, gave a lecture yesterday on the historical development of internationalism. "The peace problem" he said, "is really a problem of better social and international relationship, and as such it must be explained from the historical standpoint from its inception. As a historian, I shall attempt to prove that history, from 'its' inception, has been developed on the lines of internationalism."</p>
   <p>A meeting for peace was also held yesterday in Mandel Hall, under the chairmanship of Miss Jane Addams, president of the Women's International-Peace League.</p>
   <p>The main speaker was Lady Lidia Gustava Heimann, vice-president of the League, who claims that it requires more courage to fight for peace than in war. Over a thousand people were present at this meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
