<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-12-08">December 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Masses Build a Beautiful Nursery in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Siegel</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0711</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0711.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-12-08">December 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH MASSES BUILD A BEAUTIFUL NURSERY IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Siegel</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The grand opening of the Douglas park Day and Night Nursery will be celebrated tomorrow and it is a celebration in which the majority of Jews in Chicago must participate. The Douglas park Day and Night Nursery is one of the two institutions that was built in the Jewish centers by the masses themselves. Neither is supported by the organized charities, and that alone is a sufficient reason why the masses must support these two institutions, where lonely and impoverished orphans are raised and educated.</p>
   <p>Both institutions, the Douglas park Nursery and the Daughters of Zion Nursery, on the Northwest Side, were practically founded at the same time and both ought to seek new homes in a few years, due to inadequate room.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0712.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That proves how necessary such institutions are. The Douglas Park Nursery was founded five years ago, during the flu epidemic. Fortunately, a small group of men and women fully understood the horrors of the epidemic, which left many children homeless and parentless. They immediately held a meeting in the Herzl High School, where the foundation for the first Jewish nursery on the West Side was laid.</p>
   <p>At that meeting three thousand and five-hundred dollars ($3,500) were appropriated, and the house at 1300 Independence Boulevard was purchased. The nursery was opened shortly afterwards.</p>
   <p>When the nursery was operating, the social elements of society saw how urgent such an orphanage is and how much work must be embodied in it to make the home modern, large, and successful.</p>
   <p>The nursery that opened was as a drop of water in a bucket, in <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0713.jpg" n="3"/>comparison to the number of children that remained without homes. Therefore, work of enlarging the home soon started in order to provide permanent home for orphans and a part-time home for the children whose parents are obligated to provide a livelihood.</p>
   <p>There was a time when poor unfortunate mothers and fathers were compelled to place their children in gentile homes, and the children were brought up in a gentile atmosphere. A great problem arose.</p>
   <p>Socially conscious Jews began considering a large home. A new fund had to be raised. In addition to this, the expenses grew steadily and the tasks of the directors became intensified. This problem was solved. Thanks to the tireless work of the directors. Today the Nursery is in a new home, in a large home with all conveniences, with a play ground on the corner of Albany and 15th Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0714.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And tomorrow, Sunday, the grand opening of the new home will be celebrated. And it need not be mentioned that on this occasion the masses must participate and resolve to continue the work.</p>
   <p>The happiest man today is the president, Mr. George B. Sacks, under whose management all these great things were accomplished. The fruit of this work, in this case is the building that is dedicated as a monument for many generations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
