<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1895-06-22">June 22, 1895</date>. pp 285-286.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1243</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1243.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1895-06-22">June 22, 1895</date>. pp 285-286.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Few people know that the Young Men's Hebrew Charity Association has added another stone to its monument of fame by assisting in the foundation of an institution whose object is not only the giving of charity, but involves the broader principle of instruction.</p>
   <p>The need of practical teaching in Obstretics has been felt in this city for years but efforts to supply the material for the purpose have been but slightly successful. More than half of the doctors graduated every spring from our colleges have never had charge of an obstretical case and a great many have not even seen one.</p>
   <p>It is to the credit of our people that the movement here was started among them. Through the efforts of Dr. Joseph De Lee, numerous people were interested in the work, but the first real help came from the Y. M. H. C. A., which after an earnest plea by their president, Henry X. Strauss, appropriated $200 for the foundation of a maternity dispensary. Several voluntary subscriptions were added to this and soon enough money was raised to make a beginning. A site in the center of the most densely populated district of the city was chosen.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1244.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Dispensary is non-sectarian, although the books show that 2/3 of the cases treated are Jews.</p>
   <p>The following are members of the institution, or have helped the Dispensary in many ways - Mrs. Levy Mayer, Mrs. F. Mandel, N. R. Cahn, Leo A. Loeb, S. W. Strauss, Oscar Foreman, L. B. Kuppenheimer and Norman Florsheim.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
