<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-07-08">July 8, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1063</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1063.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-07-08">July 8, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a great error to think that women are capable only of raising children and taking care of a house. The best illustration of this error is the Jewish women of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Several and even hundreds of Jewish women carry on business alone, work in shops, and canvass from door to door. They are the only bread winners of the entire family. One must naturally possess a great deal of energy and courage to carry all this through, but the Jewish women show that they have more than is needed, and these types of Jewish women are, without a doubt, the most clever in Jewish life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1064.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>True that this is an unfortunate phenomenon of our life, because women are more than capable, suitable, and obligated to raise children, run a house, and so forth. And it is also true that when they neglect to take care of the home, it's very bad. But what shall the Jewish women, whose fate compels them to carry on such life, do? You may rest assure that they do not engage in other activities for the sake of pleasure or happiness. Want, privation, and hunger drives them to do other things than housekeeping. Many are employed in other work because their husbands are handicapped and earn too little.</p>
   <p>Upon visiting Jefferson Street, Maxwell Street, and many other streets you will witness how women run stands of fruit, clothing, fish, and other products, and several manage complete stores. In other localities you can meet Jewish women running candy stores, groceries, butcher shops, cleaning and dyeing stores and so forth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1065.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At times, the strength of our Jewish women is to be marvelled at. They endure heat, cold, rain, snow, winds, from early morning until late at night on the street or in poorly ventilated stores.</p>
   <p>The tragedy of such families can not be over estimated. The children are not brought up as properly as they should be. Food is never dished out in proper time or proper manner.</p>
   <p>Walking through the West Side, one can observe dressmaking signs in the windows. These are practically all family women who are compelled to make dresses in order to help along the family budget.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1066.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Many Jewish women can also be found canvassing from house to house. Most of these women are widows, or divorcees, or who have unemployed, or sick husbands.</p>
   <p>A great number of Jewish women can be found in the tailoring shops working together with the opposite sex. Most of the women are unskilled and, therefore, are employed in the sweatshops where they work long hours with little pay.</p>
   <p>Speaking in general, we should not feel ashame of our Jewish women.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
