<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-13">Mar. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Smoking in Cars</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-13">Mar. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">SMOKING IN CARS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Smoking is a habit which has become second nature to a large portion of humanity, which is too weak to free itself from it. In the past 400 years, since the Indians of America instilled their white oppressors with the desire to smoke, statesmen, kings, and the clergy have attempted to eradicate this double "destroyer" of human labor and human health. The campaign against smoking was carried on in vain. The boycott by the Church, the scourge by the government, and the arguments by science did not help.</p>
   <p>According to official statistics, in 1912 the world produced 2,626,000,000 pounds of tobacco. In the same year the United <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1131.jpg" n="2"/>States alone consumed 962,855,000 pounds of tobacco, which amounted to $104,063,000. An average of $200,000,000 are spent annually for smoking, of which more than one fourth is spent in the prodigal United States.</p>
   <p>Thus, smoking belongs to the evils from which mankind will not free itself so soon, despite of the fact that it pays such a high price in money and in health for the delight to inhale the smoke of nicotine, the poison which tobacco contains. But when those who smoke begin to infect the air in which people, who find no pleasure in becoming intoxicated with alcohol, opium or nicotine, need live; when such smokers force these people to inhale the poison of nicotine, just because they accidently come in contact with each other, then it steps out of the limits of an innocent habit and into the class of a guilty crime.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1132.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Even the better class of men, who have already acquired the knowledge of asking permission or even suppressing their desire for nicotine in presence of women, have no respect for their fellow men of the same sex, let alone those who turn a meeting or a lecture into torture for the vast number of men and women who suffer from the infectious smoke of tabacco.</p>
   <p>The claim that they are being robbed of their personal liberty is full of hypocrisy, when the nicotine addicts protest against the proposal which forbids smoking on the platform of street cars.</p>
   <p>Sacred should be regarded the liberty of each individual in society, but when the personal liberty of one is the oppression of someone else, then there is no longer any liberty. May the nicotine users <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1133.jpg" n="4"/>continue to enjoy the odor of their tobacco, but let them not impose that odor upon those to whom it is a pest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
