<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-06-21">June 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">School Board and Politics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-06-21">June 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL BOARD AND POLITICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The incident which took place in the Chicago Board of Education during the past few days could provide a humorist with a great deal of material were it not that it so seriously affects the education of thousands of children. The act of sending a policeman to depose the president of the Board of Education and put a successor in his place is original and quite interesting. It is also characteristic of the political conceptions prevailing now in the administration of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Why did Mayor Thompson accelerate the deposal of Mr. Loeb? If the appointment of new members and a new president was within the confines of law, why didn't Mr. Loeb surrender his desk to his successor? And if, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0258.jpg" n="2"/>on the other hand, improper action was employed, then this haste and the use of a policeman only intensified the unlawfulness.</p>
   <p>Two motives are clear in Mayor Thompson's action; namely, the desire to manipulate the Board of Education for the fortification of the political machine in the City Hall, and the desire to take revenge on Mr. Loeb for denouncing politics in the educational system of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Loeb has the satisfaction of predicting correctly. That Democratic aldermen supported a Republican city mayor in carrying out his obstinacies, in order to surrender the school system into the hands of his "good friends," was not merely accidental. This can readily be understood by all. The accusation was openly made in the city council that an unclean political deal had taken place. This is a shameful reflection on the administration, and still worse on the Chicago schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0259.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A little consolation lies in the fact that Mr. Loeb still remains as a member of the School Board. With Mayor Thompson's friends in the majority, his term on the Board of Education will not be any too pleasant. We trust that he will have the courage to remain on guard and keep us posted on events taking place behind the scenes of the Chicago Board of Education.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
