<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-03-07">March 7, 1892</date><title level="a">The Hungarians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1493</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1493.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III A (Hungarian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-03-07">March 7, 1892</date><title level="a">THE HUNGARIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hungarians play an important part of the cosmopolitan combination of Chicago's population. There are about 6,000 Hungarians in Chicago....</p>
   <p>A Hungarian settlement or colony was unable to maintain itself, because the immigrants became rapidly acclimatized. Therefore, the national characteristics of beautiful Hungaria can rarely be noticed in public life. Although the Hungarian immigration can be traced since approximately forty years ago, the sign-posts, however, for the tracing have been chiefly single individuals. Among the first Hungarians arriving in Chicago was Anton Herzog, who tried to find his fortune here forty years ago. Herzog died a few years ago. Benjamin Grossman, likewise, was one of the first Hungarian settlers. He established a furniture business, but became a real estate agent later. He succeeded very well, and when he died recently, he left a huge fortune behind. The so-called Grossman block on State Street, opposite the Palmer House, belonged to him.....</p>
   <p>Only after the Civil War was Hungarian immigration noticeable. Among the new-comers of that time we find Kiss, Ringer, Rubovitz. Leopold Schoenefeld had arrived here ten years earlier.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1494.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Hungarians organized their first society in 1873. It was called Deak Ferencz, in honor of the famous Hungarian statesman. E. Rubovitz was the founder of the society, and its purpose was to find employment and shelter for the Hungarian immigrants. The activities of the men directing the affairs were energetic, as well as beneficial.</p>
   <p>In the course of time a number of social clubs were formed among the Hungarians, and one of them still attracts the attentions of the public whenever it gives dramatic performances in the North Side Turnhalle.</p>
   <p>The Hungarians achieved special distinction in the manufacture of coats. The firms of Beifeld and Co., and L. Heilprie and Co., which dominate the markets of coats, are widely known.</p>
   <p>Quite a few citizens of Hungarian nationality have achieved fame in public and business life. M. Beifeld came to Chicago in 1864, and in 1871 he established his own business, which was destroyed by the Chicago fire. However, he opened a larger coat-factory in 1876, and in partnership with his brother developed this branch to a very high degree. Philip Ringer, who came to Chicago in 1867, has become famous, and his book-bindery is recognized as one of the most excellent of its kind. E. Rubovitz and Co. is also a well-known firm dealing in stationery and office supplies. This business was founded in 1867 and is still a going concern.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1495.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Other eminent citizens of Hungarian nationality are F. Kiss, T. Rubowitz, Rabbi E. B. M. Browne, L. Schoenfield, Dr. A. Loew, Dr. E. Sincere, architect, Jules De Horvath, journalist, Max Polechek, M. Cornhauser, Count Serenyz, Dr. L. Ottofy, St. Black, and others.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian painter and photographer, S. Krausz, became very famous recently by his brilliant Street Types of Chicago, and the opera-tenor, Johan Wass, is likewise highly esteemed by the public.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
