<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title/>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0756</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
                    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0756.jpg" n="2"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>that he would be sure of a comfortably filled small hall and in case the small room were overfilled, the embarassment would be one of riches only.</p>
   <p>Which means to say-if we understand the situation and the personalities concerned that as the speaker for the Federated Press group Mr. Sinclair could speak to possibly 250 or 300 persons. As an invited guest of the University Mr. Sinclair would have had an audience of twelve hundred or more. Of course the open air might have been resorted to in case the small audience chamber proved too small, but in that event the rules and regulations governing the use of open spaces on the grounds of the University might have been invoked to embarrass the speaker. But be that as it may--we are interested only in suggesting to the readers the following facts for their calm, unbiased consideration--</p>
   <p>1. The auspices--a liberal or "radical" organization.</p>
   <p>2. The speaker--Upton Sinclair.</p>
   <p>3. The Hall, a small one--too small when a larger one was available--which might have been too large.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0757.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>4. The University--where there should be free speech and academic freedom, but where several members of the faculty have been relieved of their duties as instructors of the youth of the land because of supposed non-conformity to certain standards of conservatism and "sanity".</p>
   <p>[Editor's note: This article is in English originally. It has not been edited in the usual manner.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
