<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-09">Apr. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Farmers' Revolution</title><title level="a" type="sub">By I. Duo</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0809</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0809.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-09">Apr. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE FARMERS' REVOLUTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">By I. Duo</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the farmers declared a strike last week demanding higher prices for their products, Chicago began to feel a milk scarcity. Thousands of farmers are struggling heroically against the armed sheriffs. As the farmers seek to effect a complete paralysis in the milk industry, those who are not familiar with the history of the farmer consider this action spontaneous and accidental. They cannot understand where the farmer gained the courage for such a revolt.</p>
   <p>The truth is however, that the present farmers' revolt is no accidental phenomenon, but has its roots in economic conditions. This may be an indication that the American labor movement stands before a new epoch in its development and that the present uprising may affect the economic life of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0810.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the past ten years there has been a movement to organize all American farmers into unions similar to the established trade-union pattern. Many such attempts have been made although in most states, the farmers are organized into various types of organizations. This plan is unsuccessful only because the farmer is loath to throw off his petty-bourgeois psychology. He does not understand that, at a certain point, his interests converge with those of the industrial worker.</p>
   <p>Recently however, a revolution has been taking place in the mind of the farmer. He is reaching the conclusion that the consumer and the producer have the same struggle to fight against those who take advantage of both. Above all, the farmer has finally become aware of the economic situation.</p>
   <p>He has realized that the industrial worker through organization gains higher wages, while the farmer, who must buy, from time to time, improved and more expensive equipment, receives the same prices for his products. He can't <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0811.jpg" n="3"/>figure out why the worker pays more for farm products, due to the railroad tariff, while the farmer receives less for his products. These, and other factors, made him realize that if he were organized with the workers, their combined strength could force the national legislature to effect economic reforms.</p>
   <p>Last November the farmers' organizations held their national convention in Chicago. Representatives of the Federation of Labor from four states were present. There the cornerstone for an alliance between farmers and workers was laid; plans were considered for the inauguration of a national co-operative movement to attain solidarity between the urban and rural community.</p>
   <p>The organized workers rejoiced at the news, since such a movement will make it possible to buy directly from the farmer, which will benefit him, and will also stimulate the farmer to demand union-made goods. Thus the <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0812.jpg" n="4"/>entire labor movement will profit. At that time the American Federation of Labor, inspired by the convention, appointed a ways and means committee to make definite plans to unite both groups and call another convention. The Federation is aware that the organized farmers can strengthen the power of the organized workers, so that together they can struggle for their own interests.</p>
   <p>As we can see, the recent strike which the farmers won, was not an accident, but arose from their dissatisfaction with the dealers who refused to meet their demands. When Chicago needed milk, everyone realized that the farmer played a highly important role in city life, and that he was entitled to recognition.</p>
   <p>Although the farmers are already organized in groups similar to labor unions, in most cases they are not officially affiliated with the American Federation of Labor. The fact remains that the organized workers support <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0813.jpg" n="5"/>the farmers' movement and are ready to help it. The Chicago Federation of Labor aided the strikers and has participated in all their activities.</p>
   <p>The farmers' revolution indicates the rise of a new epoch in the American labor movement. It is safe to say that we are standing now on the eve of important events in the economic life of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
