<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-05-23">May 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Why Is America Fighting</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0585</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0585.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-05-23">May 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WHY IS AMERICA FIGHTING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a fact that not until Congress adopted the resolution that the United States declare war against Germany, and Pres. Wilson had clarified in a brilliant manner our dispute with Germany, did any one understand clearly why the nations of Europe were slaughtering one another. America cleared the issue, and it now lips open before everyone, that the struggle for life and death emerges from two principles; viz., that or self-government by the people and that of a government by a divine ruler, who is not obligated to account for his acts to his people, but to God, by whose grace he governs.</p>
   <p>On one side stand all democratic nations, Republican &amp; Constitutional, where freedom of the people is guaranteed by laws which the people themselves make and where the legislative power and the question of war and peace depend <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0586.jpg" n="2"/>entirely on their will.</p>
   <p>On the other side stand the autocratic powers, under which the people have not as yet won their inalienable right to govern themselves, and where the question of war and peace is not decided by the people, but by their rulers.</p>
   <p>For example, Germany has declared a part of Poland independent under German rule. Should, however, Poland decide to become a republic, she can't, because of being under Germany's Germany's authority. Kaiser Wilhelm will not permit another republic near the eastern border because he is already contending with one at the western one.</p>
   <p>Germany has the power to make Lithuania a principality. Should Lithuania desire to become a republic, or create her own for of self-government, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0587.jpg" n="3"/>would she be able to do it as long as she remains under the rule of Germany?</p>
   <p>Germany is connected with Austria, Turkey, Hungary, and Bulgaria, and properly speaking she is the sole authority over all these countries. She destroyed Serbia, Rumania, Montenegro, Belgium, and the wealthiest provinces of northern France, and all these combined will become one powerful empire which will be in a position to impose its power upon the world, changing the forms of democratic countries, and destroying their democratic institutions.</p>
   <p>Germany does not recognize the principle that any race has a right to govern itself as it pleases and according to its own manner. Contending</p>
   <pb n="4"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0588.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>order to protect the Monroe Doctrine?</p>
   <p>Thus, we see that the United States entered the war, not for the sake of fighting, but as an urgent need. America fights for a democratic cause and her own democratic institutions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
