<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-05">June 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Hospital Unit Committee Is Organized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0477</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0477.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-05">June 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">HOSPITAL UNIT COMMITTEE IS ORGANIZED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fifty rabbis, representatives of synagogues, and a number of prominent men organized at a meeting yesterday evening at the Hebrew Institute a permanent Jewish Hospital Unit committee, and at the same time formulated plans for a big campaign to raise a large sum of money for a hospital unit for our boys on the battlefields. As is known, the campaign to establish a hospital unit in the name of Chicago's Orthodox Jewry was begun last Thursday, the day of public fasting and prayer. A sum of five thousand dollars was collected on that day, and now the plans call for an additional twenty thousand dollars which will enable us in a grand and patriotic manner to aid our government in its great and noble relief work for our soldiers and sailors.</p>
   <p>Eloquent and impressive speeches were made by Congressman Adolph J. Sabath, Judge Harry M. Fisher, and many others. They pointed to the necessity of being of greater service to our government and our country in every possible way. "There is no limit to how much one can do. We must work and accomplish more than in ordinary times. It is war, and everyone must help the government to conquer the German, for when we will win--and win we must--the small and <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0478.jpg" n="2"/>large nations of the world will also gain their liberty and freedom, including the Jews among them," said Congressman Sabath.</p>
   <p>"As Americans, Jews have done their part, but not enough as Jews," said Judge Fisher. "We must perform our duty to our country, not only as Americans, but as Jews as well; so that a future historian will record that when America--the best country in the world for Jews--was drawn into the great war to save the freedom of the world, the Jews proved how much they valued the friendship and freedom given them by this country, and performed their duty fully."</p>
   <p>After the speeches the meeting discussed plans for beginning the campaign and what to do with the money collected--whether to buy only ambulances or an entire hospital unit. It was decided to turn this matter over to the executive committee for decision.</p>
   <p>The following officers were elected: Nathan D. Kaplan, chairman; Rabbi Saul Silber, treasurer; and Dr. George H. Elk, secretary. The next meeting will be held next Monday. The "drive" will begin soon, and last until July 4.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
