<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-10-27">October 27, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Workers' Ghetto</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0922</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0922.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-10-27">October 27, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORKERS' GHETTO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the workers' world, all is quiet and peaceful. It is the calm and quiet of people who undertake to do more than their strength permits. The organized workers realize that they have undertaken a tremendous task, when the American Federation of Labor openly declared itself much in favor of the Democratic Party. The unorganized workers know, that the defeat of organized labor will also affect them. The workers know, through bitter experience, that they are last to benefit from a victory, and first to suffer in a defeat, resulting from War between Capital and Labor. The uncertainty as to the outcome of this war, throws workers into inactivity--they are merely waiting.</p>
   <p>The very important event of this week which the workers should pause and consider, is the voting at the Cleveland of a three-cent carfare.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0923.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Every one knows about the struggle between Tom Johnson and the Surface Car Companies, which he has carried on for the last seven years.</p>
   <p>The fight is against the reduction of the price of fares, from five cents to three cents. Mr. Johnson was leading this war in the name of the people and the workers. They were merely informed, that the car companies rob them of two cents each day of the week, when they ride the Street cars. The workers have enlisted in this fight with Mr. Johnson and he has won. As soon as the war was over, and it was attempted to convert theory into practice, it was discovered that the system is not workable. The workers demanded more privileges. They were victorious and they wanted to reap the benefits.</p>
   <p>This resulted in strikes, bloodshed and so forth. The three-cent fare was not profitable. It was necessary to reduce the number of cars and stop issuing transfers. It was very uncomfortable for those, who had to use the cars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0924.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The workers have decided that something has to be done about it. They decided that they would rather pay five cents fare, in order to be comfortable, and to enable their brothers to get higher wages.</p>
   <p>The moral of this is that, some theories are fine so long as they remain as such, but the minute they are put into practice they are a flat failure. Also that it is unwise to depend upon professional schemers. The workers are not so dumb as toallow themselves to be led by any Autocrat or Demogogue.</p>
   <p>The American workers are Progressive but not radical. They know that Rome was not built in a day. They believe in Evolution.....not Revolution. They are aware of the extent of their strength, and can admit that they erred.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
