<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-05-30">May 30, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Decoration Day</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By Leopold Deutelbaum</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0952</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0952.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-05-30">May 30, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">DECORATION DAY</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By Leopold Deutelbaum</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In this blessed republic - founded on the principle of equal right for every faith and creed and an equal chance for every man who lives beneath its flag - it must be our sacred duty to awaken in the hearts of the young and to stimulate and inspire in the hearts of the mature that love of country which is based on intelligent understanding of its achievements and possibilities and an honest enthusiasm for the heroic figures of its history. And our national holidays have been wisely ordained, at different intervals, so that in patriotic celebration there may be brought home to the public mind, the splendid traditions of American history, and the marvelous achievements that in a few hundred years have produced a nation which in dignity, power, and influence takes rank with the great nations of the earth.</p>
   <p>February 12 and 22, are the birthdays of the two noblest figures in the history of our country: Washington, the founder, and Lincoln, the preserver, of this country. Washington, with his wise, foresighted "Farewell Address," Lincoln, with his gentle spirit, his martyr death and his tender words, "With malice towards none, with charity for all."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0953.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>July 4,is the anniversary of the singing of the Declaration of Independence, that declaration which has been fraught with more momentous consequence to humanity than other document in the world's history since the charter of English liberty won from King John at Runnymede.</p>
   <p>The Thanksgiving Day celebration is peculiar in that its original observance dates back to the earliest Colonial history of America; to the time when the forces and influences that have shaped American destiny were first forming and developing; while its observance now includes within its scope the grateful recollection of all the victories of mind and heart, of all the triumphs of industry and skill, and all the exploits of valor and courage that have made of American history one long story of glorious achievement, from Plymouth Rock and the Mayflower to Santiago and Manila.</p>
   <p>On Decoration Day we deck, with love and sorrow, the graves of the defenders of the Union and of those others who fought with equal valor for the lost cause, united in death no more indissolubly than their living descendants are united in purpose, thought, and hope.</p>
   <p>The Confederate women first began decorating the graves of their dead with flowers, and did not pass by the Union graves near their late foes. This <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0954.jpg" n="3"/>touched the heart of the nation as nothing else could have done, and enmity melted away and the observance of the day has become universe.</p>
   <p>We do not meet on this Memorial Day to weep for the dead, as we did while wounds were yet fresh. Time has healed the scars of war, and we can calmly contemplate the great lesson of patriotic devotion, and rejoice that the nation to which we belong produced men noble enough to die for that which they valued so much. Neither do we care to say anything of human slavery, the institution that died and was buried with the Confederacy. Let the dead past bury its dead. But, we are here to foster patriotism, in view of the most tremendous sacrifice ever willingly made by a people on the altar of nationality. That the sacrifices of the Civil War deserve this rank will appear from the fact that they were made - in the main - by volunteers. We were not fighting directly to defend our altars and our fires; we were not driven to arms to repel an invading foe; we were not hurried to the field by king and noble; but in the first flush of manhood we offered ourselves to preserve unimpaired the unity, the purity, the glory of our nation. And when the struggle was over, there were no state trials, no prisons and scaffolds, as is customary in the European countries, and the republic, though bleeding at every pore, said to the conquered enemy, "Come and share fully with us all the blessings of our <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0955.jpg" n="4"/>preserved institutions." And thus won a second victory greater than the first. Let us pray today that our beloved flag, which is the protector of human freedom and the rights of all men, may exist forever. May our flag, with all its stars, ever shine forth undimmed and untrammeled in its beauty. Learn to love that flag, and by good useful acts live for it, so that others after you may enjoy its protection and be ready, if necessary, to die for it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
