<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-05">Nov. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Young Chicago Jewish Girl to Sing with the Opera</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-05">Nov. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG CHICAGO JEWISH GIRL TO SING WITH THE OPERA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a result of the marked interest of the Chicago public and several prominent Jewish families, as well as a number of successful appearances in New York and throughout the South and Middle West, Frances Papette, a young mezzo-soprano from Chicago's own studios, was brought to the attention of Mr. Herbert Johnson, business director of the Chicago Opera Association. He heard her sing, and, recognizing at once her great talent and promise as an operatic artist, engaged her for the coming season. She will make here debut at the Auditorium late in November, and will be heard during the season in a number of prominent roles.</p>
   <p>Frances Papette was born in a small town, Coloma, Wisconsin; she is of humble French and Russian-Jewish parentage, and, at an early age, began to show unusual musical talent. At four she played by ear, and would often sit at the piano for hours picking out tunes, while her two-year-old brother worked <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1603.jpg" n="2"/>the pedals. When she was six, her mother, recognizing her ability, obtained a teacher [for her] from a neighboring town. The child attracted the attention of many travelers who passed through the town and gave her money for playing for them. They advised her parents to take her to a larger center where better musical advantages could be secured. When she was twelve years old, her mother brought her to Chicago where her studies were continued.</p>
   <p>At fifteen, she was an accomplished pianist, and expected to make this branch of music her life profession. But a few years later her magnificent voice was discovered; since that time, she has been stydying with the most noted local teachers and has applied herself with unswerving devotion annd diligence. She is an accomplished pianist and a talented linguist, and her beautiful voice, together with her youth and magnetic personality, have for several years been the subject of much attention in the concert field. She is one of the youngest members of the present company--she is only twenty-four--and her debut is expected to be one of the events of the season.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
