<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-07-11">July 11, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Women's League Midwest Branch Honors Mrs. Philip Klafter at its Closing Meeting of the Season</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1003</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1003.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-07-11">July 11, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN'S LEAGUE MIDWEST BRANCH HONORS MRS. PHILIP KLAFTER AT ITS CLOSING MEETING OF THE SEASON</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. Philip Klafter, chairman of membership, and delegate to the National Convention held in Atlantic City during the month of May, was the guest of honor at the luncheon and closing meeting of the Women's League, held at Brauer's Cafe, on Wednesday noon, June 29. Over seventy members and friends were present at the affair. Rabbi N. Blechman of Houston, Texas, who with Mrs. Blechman was visiting Chicago and was present at the luncheon, praised the ladies for their fine attendance and marvelled at the display of enthusiasm at this meeting. Mrs. Klafter, imbued with enthusiasm for the activities of the league, gave a very interesting and inspiring talk on the nature of its work.</p>
   <p>The latest publication of the Women's League, entitled "The Three Pillas," which is a guide-book for Jewish women, describing the Jewish home ceremonies and Jewish home life and their meaning, was announced, and several copies were sold at the meeting. Copies of the publication can be secured at the United <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1004.jpg" n="2"/>Synagogue headquarters, 53 W. Jackson Boulevard, Chicago. It is a valuable addition to the libraries of all Jewish women.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
