<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1916-06-30">June 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Opening of a New Jewish Institution in Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1916-06-30">June 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">OPENING OF A NEW JEWISH INSTITUTION IN CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To morrow Saturday, July 1, will see the opening of the Jewish People's bank at 1200 W. 12th Street. The opening of this bank is of great importance to Chicago Jews. It will be a real Jewish institution that will honestly serve the Jewish interests of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Realizing the necessity of sending money to Russia during the present war condition, the Jewish People's Bank has made direct contact with the main Government bank of Russia and has established a new telegraph system whereby money can be sent by telegraph direct to all cities, towns, and villages in three days at only a trifle more than the ordinary method of sending by mail.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1444.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Jewish People's Bank has also made arrangements with German and Austrian banks, and are now in a position to send money under a full guarantee that it will be turned over to the exact person. It will also issue receipts signed by the person to whom the money is sent.</p>
   <p>The Jewish People's Bank has also worked out a plan whereby they will be able to bring passengers from the war countries with out hardships, and at the lowest prices.</p>
   <p>The most important of the departments in this bank is the foreign free service bureau. Today the condition of our families and relatives in the war countries are getting worse from day to day, and thousands of Jews are being driven from one town to another with no possibility of letting their relatives in this country know of their whereabouts! Therefore, the Jewish People's Bank have spared neither time nor money and have made the necessary arrangements, with all the relief societies in Germany, Russia, and Austria, and will thereby be able to help the Jews in America who are trying to locate their lost relatives.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1445.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This department will be under the supervision of a man of ability and speaking many foreign languages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
