<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-24">Feb. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Bezalel Exhibition</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1531</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1531.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-24">Feb. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">BEZALEL EXHIBITION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In ancient times when the Jew dwelt in his own land, he was known throughout the world as a pursuer of culture and science. He contributed the original Jewish literature and the original Jewish art. There are still many relics found in the old ruins of Palestine, such as artistic carvings in stone and other decorative work, which show the most wonderful artistic skill. But in the last 2,000 years of Jewish life in the Ghettos in the different countries of Diaspora, Jewish hands have lost their skill and the eyes lost their vision for beauty.</p>
   <p>The Jews have been robbed of their artistic skill and their art has been used to enrich the skill of other countries. Enemies of the Jews state, that there is no such thing as original Jewish art and skill, and that the Jew is only a pseudo artist.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1532.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But in the Jewish new life which is developing anew in Palestine in the last few years, a movement has begun to revive Jewish art and to regain a name for the Jew, as a promoter of the original Jewish art. The instigator of this movement is the Bezalel School in Palestine, which has undertaken to revive the Jew's technique and the artistic skill, in which he excelled above all those countries, which persecuted him. So, now is the opportune time for the Jew to create something again in his old home. It is remarkable to note the success of the Bezalel School in the short time of its existence. The Jew has begun to produce and show his artistic work. The goods are found in markets in all European countries, and tourists who visit Palestine are buying the Bezalel-made goods for gifts to their friends.</p>
   <p>The Bezalel School boasts of the Hebrew language which is being taught in its classes. Another thing, which the school is proud of is the brotherly love which exists among the students.</p>
   <!--5423972_4_1_1534 omitted, duplicate of 5423972_4_1_1533-->
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1533.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These students come from our city of Chicago from other large cities in the United States, and in fact from all parts of the world, to the Bezalel School which is called a melting pot. This institution in Jerusalem well deserves all credit from all classes of Jews throughout the world.</p>
   <p>The Bezalel Society in Chicago, was founded for the sole purpose of creating a market in America for Bezalel-made goods. Not long ago several thousands dollars worth of merchandise was received in Chicago, from the Bezalel School which is now exhibited at the Hebrew Institute, 1258 Taylor Street. Every Jew here in Chicago, who is interested in Jewish art and the Jewish ancient home is cordially invited to come to the Hebrew Institute to see what our brethren in the Holy Land have accomplished, in regaining our former prestige in the world.</p>
   <p>D.P.Polak.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
