<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-19">Sept. 19, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Run on the Banks</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Spivak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0804</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0804.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-19">Sept. 19, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUN ON THE BANKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Spivak</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a result of the deplorable bankruptcies recently of three private banks on the West Side, some depositors in other banks have grown wary, and have withdrawn their savings, even though their bankers may have reputations for irreproachable honesty.</p>
   <p>Someone probably joked about Mr. Schiff's bank, at Twelfth and Halsted Streets, and the joke actually assumed a somewhat serious character, culminating in a small run on the bank.</p>
   <p>This, however, does not reflect any discredit on those depositors who save their earnings regularly in this bank, which conducts its business so honestly and conservatively that all deposits are secure.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0805.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Those who were responsible for spreading a false rumor about this safe and sound Schiff and Company bank, causing uninformed depositors to withdraw their savings, committed a horrible crime; it is like yelling "fire" in a crowded theater where there is no fire, and causing a panic among the frantic audience.</p>
   <p>The anxiety of some depositors ended when, as was to be expected, each of them was paid in full. This alone indicates that a state bank like Schiff and Company, and some others, can stand the acid test when they are put to it. And the depositors may, as they have until now, rest assured that their money is safe.</p>
   <p>The lack of confidence on the part of [some] depositors in state banks began when the Lorimer-Munday Bank crashed, notwithstanding the fact that it was under state supervision. But, first, we should realize that that was an exceptional case, and, second, that after this sad incident, there still remained <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0806.jpg" n="3"/>enough money and valuable real-estate papers for the receiver, Mr. B. Horwich, to pay the depositors a large percentage. The lack of confidence on the part of some depositors, such as those who started a run on Schiff's Bank yesterday, also arises from ignorance.</p>
   <p>Private banks find it difficult to place themselves under state control because they do not have the required two hundred thousand dollars in capital.</p>
   <p>A movement, therefore, has begun to have the state determine the amount of capital required in accordance with the amount of business the bank does, and to increase its capital steadily in proportion to the increase of business. This would enable a private bank, with a capital of thirty or forty thousand dollars, to be placed under the control of the state.</p>
   <p>If the state supervised the smaller banks, many bankruptcies would be avoided <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0807.jpg" n="4"/>because the state would act like a sovereign, forever demanding an accounting, and in the event that bankers were incompetent or dishonest, the state would intercede, and would tell the bankers how to run their business, or else, would take the business out of their hands before the depositors lost their property.</p>
   <p>But a sound bank such as Schiff and Company, which is under the supervision of the state, and which has the required capital and a surplus of $250,000, and assets of $2,600,000, is certainly safe, and depositors have nothing to fear.</p>
   <p>Several depositors lost their interest from July 1 to the present date by withdrawing their money. They also lost a day's wages when they stood in line all day to withdraw their deposits instead of going to work.</p>
   <p>The main thing is to have confidence in the bank with which one transacts business, and this confidence can only exist when the banks carry on their business <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0808.jpg" n="5"/>honestly, and when the reputations of the bankers are good. This can be said of Schiff's Bank. Therefore, there is no reason why some depositors should become excited and want to withdraw their deposits, especially when they can withdraw their money at any time without any notice, notwithstanding the fact that the banks have a legal right to demand of their depositors a sixty-day notice before they draw any money. Let us have less excitement and more deliberation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
