<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-26">Mar. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">"Majority Rules" in Theory and Practice</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_0401</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0401.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-26">Mar. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">"MAJORITY RULES" IN THEORY AND PRACTICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the cardinal principles of democracy is the [principle of] rule by the majority--"majority rules". The parliaments and congresses of democratic countries should represent the majority of the people and should express their will in the legislature, to which the minority must yield. This principle, like many other great principles, exists, however, in theory only. In practice, however, it is just the reverse. In no country, regardless of how democratic it may be, does the majority actually rule; it is rather the minority which rules, and the majority acquiesces.</p>
   <p>The English ex-Premier Lloyd George points out in his latest article that Parliament, which decided in 1914 that England should enter the World War, represented only one-sixth of the English population and less than one-third <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0402.jpg" n="2"/>of the adults of England. The representatives of one-sixth of the population, in this way, imposed their will upon the other five-sixths, and without the approval of the large majority, the minority dragged the country into one of the most horrible and destructive wars that England has ever experienced. We can go still further and say that the representatives of the people in Parliament, who took upon themselves the great responsibility of the war, did not actually represent even one-sixth of the population. A large number of this minority would have opposed the war, had the question been submitted to them. The "representatives" of this minority did not, however, submit the question to them, and, therefore, they actually represented only a handful of the English citizenry. The majority were forced, by that handful, or by the representatives of that handful, to sacrifice their blood and lives without having the opportunity to express an opinion on the matter.</p>
   <p>Yet England serves as a model for democratic countries! How much less were <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0403.jpg" n="3"/>the masses represented by the French government in 1914, which assumed the responsibility of a war that nearly cost the existence of France?</p>
   <p>The same holds true with the other democratic countries where rule by the majority exists in theory. Who can now say that Congress, which decided in 1917 that America should enter the war, actually represented the will of the majority of the American people who had, shortly before the declaration of war, re-elected Wilson on the strength of the campaign issue: "He kept us out of war"?</p>
   <p>This great difference between the theory and practice of rule by the majority is the best argument in favor of the movement for a referendum on war--a movement which is being ruthlessly attacked by the reactionaries and militarists in all countries, who advance the argument that the "representatives of the people," representing the majority in parliament and in the government, must also have the right to declare war. If not, <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0404.jpg" n="4"/>it would mean an end to the "representative" form of government.</p>
   <p>That this argument is illogical, is proven by no less an authority than ex-Premier Lloyd George, who cannot, under any circumstances, be suspected of ultraradicalism, especially when we remember the role that he himself played in the [last] war, and his chauvinistic speeches which were so thunderously applauded by the reactionaries and militarists both here [America] and in England. Naturally, Lloyd George makes this "discovery" [that the English government dragged the country into war without the people's consent] now, when he is no longer at the helm of the government. This, however, merely strengthens the argument in favor of a war referendum.</p>
   <p>Let us suppose that in all the countries which were dragged into the world blood bath, there had been a law providing for a war referendum. Can we doubt for a moment that the war would have been impossible had the broad masses, who had to bear the brunt of war, been able to speak their minds <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0405.jpg" n="5"/>freely on this vital question?</p>
   <p>Wars would be impossible if the principle of rule by the majority existed not merely in theory, but also in practice. This, however, can never be completely realized.</p>
   <p>The government must always be administered by a small number of people, who may even be elected by a majority, and yet not represent the will of the majority on certain vital issues, especially on the question of war. The only guarantee, therefore, is a referendum--a direct inquiry as to whether the nation wants war. It can hardly be doubted that the broad masses of people, regardless of how backward they may be, would ever vote for war, unless there were danger of an attack by an enemy.</p>
   <p>A war referendum means that the power of declaring war shall be taken away from a handful of politicians and be given over directly to the <pb facs="5423972_4_1_0406.jpg" n="6"/>people themselves. This is the only effective means to avoid war. It also means the exercising of the principle of rule by the majority in actuality, to the extent that it can be exercised under the existing conditions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
