<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-20">Jan. 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">This Is Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Zeitigen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_4_1_1097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-20">Jan. 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THIS IS CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Zeitigen</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: Zeitigen means a spectator. Obviously, this is a pen name.]</p>
   <p>A resident of a big city sometimes asks himself this question: When was it better to live--in the old days, before the modern machines, automobiles, telephones, steam heat, radio, and other improvements and inventions appeared, or now when we have all these? What is the final result of this progress? Is it easier or more difficult to live? One often thinks about these questions. There are many opinions with regard to them, but we will not consider these opinions at the present time.</p>
   <p>We want to throw some light upon facts and figures regarding life in Chicago <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1098.jpg" n="2"/>during the past fifty years. The entire material is taken from an official report which the Chicago Health Department issued this week. Let us see what the facts tell us. But, first of all, let us make a few general comments about our city.</p>
   <p>It is very likely that you know that Chicago, one of the largest cities in the world, is not yet one-hundred-years old. Chicago did not exist a hundred years ago. At the place where Chicago is now located, there stood the old Fort Dearborn, which had a few hundred inhabitants.</p>
   <p>Chicago is eighty-seven years old. Today it is the second largest city in America, with a population of nearly three million people. According to the figures of March, 1923, its population, last winter, was 2,833,000 people. The first city in America, New York, had a population of 5,839,000, while Philadelphia, the third city, had 1,894,000, and Detroit, the fourth, 1,019,000. The following cities had a population of less than a million:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1099.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Cleveland, St. Louis, Baltimore, Boston, and so on.</p>
   <p>Chicago would have been a sorry sight, if it had had to depend for its growth upon a natural increase in population. The first figures on Chicago tell us that in 1840, eighty-four years ago, the city had 4,479 inhabitants. It was indeed a tiny city. Who knows how many hundreds of years would have passed till this tiny city reached a population of three million people.</p>
   <p>Since the natural growth of the population is only some ten thousand a year even now, when the population is nearly three million, one can assume that when Chicago had a population of four thousand, its natural growth was only about a hundred per year. The term "natural increase" means the excess of births over deaths during any given year. For instance: In 1922 there were born in Chicago 56,724 children, but 31,700 people died, a net gain in population for the city of 25,024.</p>
   <p>It is true that the birth rate was higher twenty-five years ago than it is <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1100.jpg" n="4"/>today. There were twenty-eight births twenty-five years ago for every one thousand people, but the rate for 1922 is only twenty per thousand. This means that twenty-four thousand more children would have been born in Chicago in 1922 if the birth rate in 1922 had been the same as it was twenty-five years ago. However, one must not jump to the conclusion that the natural increase in population was higher then than now because the birth rate was higher then than now. One must not forget that if the birth rate was higher, so was the mortality rate; in fact, it was incomparably higher.</p>
   <p>Taking everything into consideration, we must admit that Chicago would not have grown very much if it had had to depend for its growth upon a natural increase in population. Chicago grew only because a stream of people came here from somewhere else, generally from other parts of the country, as other cities in this country also grew very rapidly, one must ascribe the phenomenal growth of Chicago to the stream of immigration. Chicago <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1101.jpg" n="5"/>is really a city of immigrants. Seventy-two per cent of Chicago's inhabitants are either immigrants or children of immigrants.</p>
   <p>A little later we will discuss the fact that the moral standard existing among the immigrants is higher than among the native-born Americans. For the present, let us return to the first question we asked at the beginning of this article: When was the best time to live, then or now? Facts are the best answer. Let us consider the life span of a Chicago resident then and now. One lives longer under favorable conditions than under unfavorable ones. In 1875, that is forty-nine years ago, the average life span in Chicago was sixteen years, two months, and twelve days. Of course, there were people who lived much longer, but when we add their lives and the lives of those who died at an early age, or in infancy, we get an average life for a Chicago resident then of slightly over sixteen years. The average life span of a Chicago resident today is forty-one years, one month, and twenty-five days, which means nearly three times as long as it was forty-nine <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1102.jpg" n="6"/>years ago.</p>
   <p>The answer to this problem lies in the mortality figures for children. Fifty years ago, the mortality among children under eight years of age was eight times what it is today. The mortality rate for children then was eight children per every thousand inhabitants, while now it is only one per thousand. The same conditions are true in regard to the mortality among children from one to four years of age.</p>
   <p>Here is an interesting fact. Statistics tell us that more males are born in Chicago than females, but more males die. In 1922 two thousand more males were born than females, but three thousand more males died than females. The final figures show that the number of men decreased and that women live longer than men.</p>
   <p>Not only has mortality among children decreased, but mortality due to <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1103.jpg" n="7"/>other diseases, such as typhoid, scarlet fever, tuberculosis has also decreased. Fifty years ago, the mortality rate from typhoid was eight deaths per every thousand inhabitants in Chicago, but the figures show that during the last ten years, the mortality rate has been decreased to only one per thousand. The mortality figures for scarlet fever and diphtheria tell the same story. Great progress has been made in overcoming the dreaded disease, tuberculosis. Fifty years ago, the rate of mortality in Chicago was twenty-four per ten thousand people, but during the past ten years the rate has been only twelve--one-half of the former rate. But--everything would be all right were it not for the word "but".</p>
   <p>When we speak of the development of medical science, we must always point out its progress and improvement. However, there are diseases against which medical science has not fought, and toward which its attitude is the same today as it was fifty years ago. These diseases present a terrible picture today. They prove to us that man's life expectancy is <pb facs="5423972_4_1_1104.jpg" n="8"/>greatly diminished if medical science does not come to his aid. For instance: The mortality rate heart disease is now twenty per every ten thousand, while fifty years ago it was only three per ten thousand. This means that nearly seven times as many people die from heart disease today as fifty years ago.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: This article was presumably concluded on another page, which is missing from this volume. Hence, no translation.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
