<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
     Jones, John T., “<title level="a">Religious Music and Its Influence</title>,” <title>Yr Ymdrechdydd</title> (Monthly), 
	<date when="1894-08-16">August 16, 1894</date>.
	</bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>03512_0004</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-welsh"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-welsh #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-welsh #code-III.C"/>
  </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2013-04-19">Initial TEI transcription by Brenna Lee.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="03512_0004.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>WELSH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     Jones, John T., “<title level="a">Religious Music and Its Influence</title>,” <title>Yr Ymdrechdydd</title> (Monthly), 
	<date when="1894-08-16">August 16, 1894</date>.
	</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Religious music is found in many forms. For instance, the great oratorio writers, Handel, Hayden, Beethoven, Mendelssohn, Parry and others, interest the upper class of people, that have had a degree of musical education that is above the average. I believe the best music for the consecrated Christian is the gospel tune that has life and is more simple, and which carries with it the message of the cross.</p>
   <p>Music and life are very closely related. Music has an influence that cannot be expressed in words. Spiritual music and worship go together. Music that has been composed and arranged by some consecrated person is wonderfully effective and gives the sweetest experience. My idea in writing this, is to encourage our young people to give more attention to religious music, because it will be most important in dispelling the darkness when it comes.</p>
   <p>The protestant church has been falling down on this very important feature, but with indications here and there we see that it has not entirely disappeared from Israel. For this reason, the redeemed of the Lord will come from far <pb facs="03512_0005.jpg" n="2"/>with Zion’s Hymns. When our churches and church organizations will appreciate Zion’s music, they will see the beautiful Zion is not so now, but once in a while a flash of the beautiful, even in this day, is heard and felt through the influence of music that has been composed and sung by consecrated people, and its influence stretches farther than we can imagine. These are the reasons for what I have said.</p>
   <p>In Sasiwn, Caernarvon, 1884, I will never forget the Rev. Owen Thomas encouraging congregational singing, and he inferred that some day it may take the place of preaching, - they had sung these words.</p>
   <p>The Hill of Calvary will never leave my memory, and the above story is only one of the many to prove the influence of consecrated music on the nations of the world. The worshipful congregational singing is so important that I would like to write more about it, hoping to influence our American young people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
