<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
    <title>Chicago Record</title>.
	<date when="1894-02-12">Feb. 12, 1894</date>.
	<title level="a">Modern Church Open Without Creed or Pastor</title>
	</bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>03512_0033</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-welsh"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-welsh #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-welsh #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-welsh #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2013-04-22">Initial TEI transcription by Brenna Lee.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="03512_0033.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>WELSH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
    <title>Chicago Record</title>.
	<date when="1894-02-12">Feb. 12, 1894</date>.
	<title level="a">MODERN CHURCH OPEN WITHOUT CREED OR PASTOR</title>
	</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5 – The modern church was launched yesterday afternoon at Bricklayers’ Hall. The meeting was announced for three o’clock but a number of persons, including the Rev. Jenkin Lloyd Jones, who was to deliver the address, arrived fifteen to twenty minutes before that time. They found the doors locked and Janitor Collier announced that no one had made arrangements for the hall, and that some on would have to be responsible for the rent before he would open the doors. The Rev. Mr. Jones, in the absence of the committee, volunteered, ad this difficulty was overcome. It was explained that the engaging of the hall had been left to a committee of two and that both gentlemen had been called out of the city.</p>
   <p>While the hall was filling up, L. T. O’Brien went over to the Moody Institute and secured the services of a double male quartet to lead the singing. These gentlemen supposed they were going to attend a revival meeting, and were considerably put out when they learned the character of the work; however, they remained during the service and led the singing.</p>
   <pb facs="03512_0034.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There was some disappointment because a larger turnout of the working people was expected. In explanation of the absence of the laborites, Mr. O’Brien said that a number of meetings were being held about the city that had been previously advertised, and which could not be postponed. He said that in the future arrangements would be made so that these meetings should not conflict with those of the Church.</p>
   <p>The Rev. Mr. Jones read Christ’s sermon on the mount and a portion of the 26th Chapter of Matthew, giving the closing scenes in the life of the Savior.</p>
   <p>Plan Of The New Church</p>
   <p>After prayer and a song, Mr. O’Brien addressed the audience. He said it was the intention in founding the modern church to erect a building which would contain in its basement bath-rooms, a gymnasium and a bowling alley. The main floor would be fitted up as a reading a writing room, the tables would be provided for games, etc. On the upper floor would be the auditorium. There would be no pastor, and no collection, and the seats would be free. Meetings would be held each Sunday, and the workers would be give the opportunity of listening to men of all thought. For the present the meetings would be held in Brick <pb facs="03512_0035.jpg" n="3"/>Layer’s Hall and would alternate with the Trade and Labor assembly, which meets the first and third Sundays of each month. Two weeks hence there will be a discussion between the Rev. Mr. Burch, secretary of the Ministers’ Association, and William C. Pomeroy. It has not yet been decided whether the discussion shall take place in Brick Layers’ Hall or Centenary Church.</p>
   <p>Mr. O’Brien then introduced the Rev. Mr. Jones as the speaker of the day, who took his text from the fortieth verse of the twenty-sixth chapter of Matthew: “What would ye not watch with me one hour?” He said these words were the cry of a soul for sympathy, the groan of the heart for companionship. This cry of the great Teacher in the garden was the wail of the centuries, and was the most fundamental thought of man, the highest privilege of religion to gratify. If he should be the subject of this afternoon’s thought into one word it would be sympathy.</p>
   <p>Great And Prophetic Interest</p>
   <p>The movement to establish a modern church carried with it great and prophetic interest. It indicated that the God of the Old and New Testament still lived. The church should be established on the root of sympathy. In it all prejudices <pb facs="03512_0036.jpg" n="4"/>should be buried. The road to sympathy was the near dear, holy road of service. The modern church should be the church of the good Samaritan – the good Samaritan brought down to the nineteenth century. The church that did not do anything in this world was not a modern church – not even an antiquity. It was a nuisance and a stumbling block, and should be put out of the way. It brought religion into disrepute.</p>
   <p>The speaker said the possibilities of the new church were almost beyong the power of description. It would make the millionaire and the beggar equal, who have an equal need of God. To fail in such an undertaking, he said, was a greater glory than to succeed with a less worthy object. In conclusion, he said: “Build on honesty, build on helpfulness, and then you build on the everlasting foundation which prophets and saints have laid in all ages.”</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
