<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
    <title>Chicago Evening Post</title>,
	<date when="1929-03-16">March 16, 1929</date>
	<title level="a">Biography of A. J. Llewellyn, Vice-President and Manager of the Sherwood Music School</title>
	</bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>03512_0064</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-welsh"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-welsh #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2013-04-22">Initial TEI transcription by Brenna Lee.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="03512_0064.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>WELSH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
    <title>Chicago Evening Post</title>,
	<date when="1929-03-16">March 16, 1929</date>
	<title level="a">BIOGRAPHY OF A. J. LLEWELLYN, VICE-PRESIDENT AND MANAGER OF THE SHERWOOD MUSIC SCHOOL</title>
	</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Born at Rhoos near Cardiff in 1865. Leaving Wales he came to Canada and stayed for a short time. Coming to the United States, he graduated from Brown University, Providence, Rhode Island, and in 1898 he entered the publishing business in Chicago. Later he became connected with the Sherwood Music School, and upon the death of Mr. Sherwood in 1911, took over the complete management of the school with the assistance and cooperation of his wife, Mrs. E. A. Llewellyn who has been Mr. Sherwood’s pupil.</p>
   <p>In 1913, Mr. Llewellyn organized an extension department at the school. The object of this department was to make it possible for serious students in country towns to obtain the essentials of a conservatory education in music, and to earn credentials without the expense and inconvenience of leaving home. This was accomplished by affiliating qualified and established teachers in outside communities and enrolling pupils in a course of study paralleling that <pb facs="03512_0065.jpg" n="2"/>given by the main school in Chicago, the studies conducted by an affiliated teacher. This course of study was in printed text form, and embraced theory lessons and annotated exercises, studies and compositions. The course was divided into eight grades, and led to a diploma. Those who wished to go further with their music and work for advanced credentials at the main school, could lay a thorough foundation at home upon which to build when they went away. While those who did not wish to go further, had acquired a good music education at home.</p>
   <p>The school has now over 1,000 affiliated teachers, with some 30,000 pupils enrolled, and working for credits. This extension plan is unique, and there is nothing like it in connection with any other school.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
