<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Albanian Journal</title>,
<date when="1922-12-06">Dec. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Albania's Independence Celebrated in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418477_0111</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-albanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-albanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-albanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418477_0111.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ALBANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Albanian Journal</title>,
<date when="1922-12-06">Dec. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE ALBANIA'S INDEPENDENCE CELEBRATED IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Prof. Elmer E. Jones tells Albanians of Educational Needs and Future Development of Shkiperia (Albania).</p>
   <p>MORE SCHOOLS FOR THE COUNTRY</p>
   <p>p. 1.- It was a glorious time when the natives of Albania now residing in Chicago, Argo, Ill., and Milwaukee, Wis., heard Prof. Elmer E. Jones, director of the School of Education of the Northwestern University of Evanston, Illinois, relate to them about his trip to Albania.</p>
   <p>The Albanians assembled to celebrate the Tenth Anniversary of the Independence of Albania, and to express their loyalty to the American flag for the privilege they enjoy under it in shaping the destiny of their country. The Albanians believe that while the races of mankind are represented by their own distinct languages, the nations and governments of the world are symbolized <pb facs="5418477_0112.jpg" n="2"/>by the flags. The Albanian flag is highly esteemed by the Albanians, and at all patriotic meetings the flag of Albania and The Stars and Stripes lend their grandeur to the occasion.</p>
   <p>A committee had been appointed to invite Prof. Jones who had been on a trip to Albania recently for the purpose of investigating the educational needs of that country. Dr. Francis La Piana presided at the meeting.</p>
   <p>Prof. Jones was greeted by the Albanians as the first American who went to see what Albania is like and brought a complete report of the present conditions and future possibilities of the Balkan countries. During his lecture he brought Albania to Chicago for the Albanians who listened attentively to his experiences in going from town to town on mule's back, by carriage and automobile; how the people in Albania welcomed him and the hospitality shown him during his trip through the land of the Shkipetars (Albanians). The possibilities regarding the education of their countrymen and the development of the natural resources made the audience see the realization of the Albanian national aspirations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418477_0113.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Prof Jones spoke for two hours. He related how his friends in Evanston advised him to carry a gun with him because they thought Albania was a lawless country full of bandits, but since he was going for a peaceful purpose he decided not to carry the gun and that he felt perfectly safe without it among the supposed bandits. He spoke of Albania as a law-abiding country with an effective government, but greatly in need of educational facilities. He commented on the eagerness of the people for learning and their interest in the establishment of schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
