<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-18">June 18, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">To the Societies Connected with the Polish Roman Catholic Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-18">June 18, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE SOCIETIES CONNECTED WITH THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Brothers:</p>
   <p>At the last convention of the Polish Roman Catholic Union of the United States of North America, under the guidance of the Sacred Heart of Jesus, held at Philadelphia in September, 1897, it was agreed that the administration should apply for a charter that will enable the organization to do business not only in the State of Illinois but in the entire United States, according to the prevailing laws.</p>
   <p>This matter was brought before Chicago's well-known firm of Sullivan and Company, and after eight months of investigation the following opinion was given:</p>
   <p>"The Polish Roman Catholic Union may at any time get a charter that will enable it to do business throughout the country as soon as it adopts certain changes required by law."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0232.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The administration of the Union may, in the name of the organization, approve of these changes. However, the changes are very important. At a regular meeting of the officers it was decided that such changes should be taken up at a general meeting.</p>
   <p>At the same time another more important matter presses for urgent attention, which can only be acted upon before the representatives of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. This other matter was brought about by the prevailing hard times.</p>
   <p>Certain societies are sending delegates to the Polish Roman Catholic Union Headquarters with the complaint that their groups are no longer in a position to pay the assessment on a one-thousand-dollar death benefit, and that as a consequence they will have to drop this unless some relief is found, or a change is made.</p>
   <p>A demand has been made for a regular five-hundred-dollar policy; [if this is established], those who desire to subscribe for a one-thousand-dollar benefit must take <pb facs="5423968_7_0233.jpg" n="3"/>out two and pay a double assessment. In this way the treasury can be fortified, and smaller claims can be paid, although one member would [apparently] be paying assessments for two or three, since he can die only once. Such matters can be discussed only at a convention.</p>
   <p>Since the honor and good of the Polish Roman Catholic Union is at stake, and since we are bound to obey the laws of the country, therefore, I, the undersigned, under the powers bestowed upon me by the constitution, call a special convention to be held on July 28 in Chicago.</p>
   <p>In order to save expense for the smaller societies, votes may be sent by proxy. For the same reason the convention is being held in Chicago, for it will eliminate travelling expenses for the officers of the organization, which would have to be taken out of the treasury. Even the large societies may be represented by one delegate, who may cast as many votes as are due to his group.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0234.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>An appeal is therefore made to all societies belonging to the Polish Roman Catholic Union to take up this matter in their meetings and to appoint delegates to represent them at the convention. The names of the delegates should immediately be sent to the secretary general, Mr. F. Wleklinski, 742-746 North Ashland Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Signed: Clement J. Belinski, president,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois, June 1, 1897</p>
   <p>Reverend P. Gutowski, spiritual trustee,</p>
   <p>Detroit, Michigan, June 3, 1897</p>
   <p>Francis Wleklinski, secretary,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois, June 5, 1897</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
