<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-16">Feb. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Emigrants and Poland</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1144</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1144.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-16">Feb. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH EMIGRANTS AND POLAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We know from the recent history of Poland after its partition that whenever catastrophes and the oppression of aggressors have afflicted our native land, the Polish emigrants have become active in foreign countries. When the aggressors' force gained control after breaking by brutal strength our attempts to liberate Poland, strangling free thought by the use of the iron fist and crushing and demoralizing the nation's spirit, the Polish emigrants assumed the responsibility for sustaining and maintaining our national identity. But blind fate has decreed that the tempest of war should descend upon Poland, destroying her completely and scattering her children all over the world. But, as always, the Polish emigrants must preserve the ideals of the nation and save the people themselves from destitution.</p>
   <p>These several thousand dollars that we have thus far collected for relief for our native land are insignificant. They are nothing in comparison with the <pb facs="5423968_7_1145.jpg" n="2"/>number and the financial condition of the Polish immigrants in America and the vast poverty of our beloved compatriots in Europe. This is only a beginning. If every Pole in America gave at least one dollar a month to this noble cause, we should already have millions. But, as is usually the case, real Polish patriots give what they can, and other soulless degenerates, unworthy to be called Poles, give nothing. We appeal, therefore, untiringly and will not cease to call:</p>
   <p>"Deny yourselves useless luxuries, do not squander your money on harmful pleasures, and give for our native land! It is your obligation before God and the nation."</p>
   <p>Before the war many of our people sent their hard-earned money to their families in Poland; war makes this practice impossible. However, the statements of banks and savings accounts show that in recent times the deposits have increased considerably, and that the careful save their money diligently. Many also are making preparations to return to Poland. Do we all do this? Do <pb facs="5423968_7_1146.jpg" n="3"/>many of us, unable to send money to Europe, spend it needlessly instead of taking it to a bank? It might be worth while to give this serious consideration. Revelry, parties, and weddings are pleasant things but very expensive in America because they consume money rapidly. Native-born Americans can afford to do such things because they are in their own country, which will not let them perish when they fall into misery. But we are strangers here, and our own country is in dire need. Money is our only support; let us therefore respect it and save it, even if we are called misers. Let us revel when our native land becomes free.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
