<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-17">Mar. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Society for the Protection of Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0852</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0852.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-17">Mar. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SOCIETY FOR THE PROTECTION OF WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p/>
   <p>We have received the following communication:</p>
   <p>"Many times in the past voices have been raised deploring the lack of an institution to extend moral protection to Polish immigrant women.</p>
   <p>"There is probably not a single Pole, man or woman, who has not felt the need of organizing a purely humanitarian and nonpolitical society to aid all Polish women, regardless of creed, and thus save them from moral decay. There are many girls who descent to the lowest rung of immorality only because they have no one to whom they can turn for advice or protection.</p>
   <p>"It seems that in cases of this type we Poles are the only ones who don't have in court any representative to defend our women, who are forced to expose before the public forum matters most painful to their honor and good name.</p>
   <p>"So far we have done nothing to prevent situations that bring dishonor to Polish <pb facs="5423968_7_0853.jpg" n="2"/>women.</p>
   <p>"Motivated by this concern, a group of Polish women has organized the Society for the Protection of Polish Women, the main purpose of which is to extend moral protection and legal help to Polish girls and women lacking such protection.</p>
   <p>"The necessary steps have already been taken in order to secure a charter for this institution. A conference at which we will explain our aims will be held with Mr. Verden, who represents the state government at Springfield, on Monday, March 19, at 7:30 P. M., at the Polish Press Club.</p>
   <p>Jadwiga [Harriet] Smulski</p>
   <p>Florence Mazur</p>
   <p>Anna Klarkowski</p>
   <p>Pelagia [Belle] Janiszewski</p>
   <p>Helen Setmajer"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
