<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1919-01-04">Jan. 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">John F. Smulski, President of the Polish National Council, on His Activities in Washington, D. C</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0969</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0969.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1919-01-04">Jan. 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN F. SMULSKI, PRESIDENT OF THE POLISH NATIONAL COUNCIL, ON HIS ACTIVITIES IN WASHINGTON, D. C</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Besides the duties entrusted to me by the Polish Conference in Detroit after the departure of Mr. I. Paderewski, an additional task was laid on me, that of representation of the Polish relief case in Washington.</p>
   <p>Because of the importance of many issues in this cause I left for Washington on December 8th 1918 and remained there until December 22nd. During my visit there I had conferences with the Secretary of State Mr. Phillips; the Secretary of War, Mr. Baker; the director of the Red Cross, Mr. Walling; the chief of the Food Administration Bureau, Mr. Walcott, and with the representatives of the Jews in America.</p>
   <p>Mr. Phillips was of the opinion that I, being an American citizen, cannot represent Poland. I then suggested that Mr. Paderewski is offically recognized as a representative, and I should be considered only as a temporary representative during his absence. Mr. Phillips agreed and heeded my point of view willingly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0970.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In regard to the issuing of Polish passports, I suggested that, though Poland was officially still considered to be partitioned between Russia, Germany and Austria, the words "subject of Russia, Germany and Austria" should be omitted in passports issued henceforth. Mr. Phillips is of the opinion that this question will be definitely decided after the official recognition of Poland as an independent state.</p>
   <p>On Wednesday, December 18th, I had a conference with the Secretary of War, Mr. Baker, in regard to obtaining the aid of the War Department for the Polish army. I explained to Mr. Baker Poland's difficult situation. Poland is surrounded from the West by German troops and from the East by bands of Germans, who were Russian war prisoners, but were tried and put under the leadership of bolsheviks. I explained to what extent Poland was devastated by these enemies. I reminded Mr. Baker of the fact that Mr. Paderewski foreseeing these plunders had requested the Secretary of State and the War Department to permit releasing from the American army all those Poles who are not citizens of the United States, and to allow to recruit them for the Polish army.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0971.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Secretary of War pointed out the great difficulty brought about by the act of the armistice. If soldiers recruited in America would be used in war against Russia or another country, then the United States would be responsible for indemnity. Mr. Baker then promised to talk this matter over with Mr. Polk, Secretary of State.</p>
   <p>I had another conference with Mr. Walling, director of the Red Cross, and found him very sympathetic with the Polish cause. He explained to me that all relief cases should be presented to the director of the Food Administration, Mr. Hoover, to whom he directed me. After a long conference with Mr. Walcott he conferred with Mr. Polk and Mr. Phillips, and as a result of these conferences he sent the following cablegrams to Mr. Hoover and Mr. House:</p>
   <p>"Mr. Hoover, American Embassy, Paris, via State Department.</p>
   <p>Most distressing reports reaching officers of Polish organizations regarding <pb facs="5423968_7_0972.jpg" n="4"/>conditions in Poland since armistice, great destitution, immediate need of food, clothing and medical supplies. Smulski of Chicago and other leading Poles much distressed over absence reference Polish relief. Catastrophe too vast for private relief; should be governmental undertaking. Polish organizations representing four million American Poles eager to help with clothing, provisions and private funds. How soon can entrance into Poland be effected for supplies? Strong feeling here, situation so depressed that, unless immediately relieved, most serious consequences must follow. Think it important you cable promptly as possible to relieve minds of Poles in this country, giving them hope of constructive relief program in definite terms as possible.</p>
   <p>Walcott"</p>
   <p>On December 26th Mr. Walcott advised me of the satisfactory answer from Mr. Hoover who is sending to Poland Mr. V. Kellog and Mr. H. Gibson to investigate the situation. Likewise Mr. Walcott advised me that twenty tons of milk will be sent from Switzerland to Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
