<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-03-01">Mar. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Contributions for War Victims</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-03-01">Mar. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CONTRIBUTIONS FOR WAR VICTIMS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Contributions for war victims, for the new Poland devastated by German soldiers, flow in copiously, thanks to the harmonious work of our national organizations. Information reaches the Dziennik Zwiazkowy from the Polish National Council that the total has already attained the amount of forty-five thousand dollars. To the members of the Polish National Alliance this news should serve as an incentive for more concerted efforts. After all, the Alliance has always considered itself the leader among our people. Let it, therefore, also lead now in this noble work. Let it not allow other organizations to surpass it and thus prove to others that it is worthy of leadership. The members of the Polish National Alliance are, therefore, urged to act with new and redoubled energy. The service which we are rendering to our native land cannot be denied by any one at present, nor will it be forgotten by history.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1138.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At this time the Dziennik Zwiazkowy is compelled to bring up a very tender and unpleasant subject, a matter which threatens Polish-American immigrants with disgrace. Information reaches us from various sources that some loose and disorderly committees are being formed which collect funds supposedly for the relief of Poland and keep the money for themselves under various pretexts. In view of the fact that the Polish Central Relief Committee is headed by members of all the Polish organizations, ecclesiastical, conservative, and progressive, [unauthorized activities] have no reason for their existence, and consequently all local committees should connect their activities with this main committee. Otherwise they create the suspicion that their intentions are not honorable and do not deserve confidence. After all, it is solely for this reason that the Polish organizations have combined, namely, to remove all doubt, suspicion, and party friction and to push ahead the work for the aid of our native land. Let those, therefore, who have not as yet combined their efforts to bring relief to our war-torn Poland [with those of the main committee], and who have a sincere desire to help, heed these few words of advice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
