<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-07">Dec. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Pulaski Hall to Be Officially Opened January 1, 1893</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Letter)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0038</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0038.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-07">Dec. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">PULASKI HALL TO BE OFFICIALLY OPENED JANUARY 1, 1893</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Letter)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear friends! After several months of laborious work, the Pulaski Hall Building Society has finally completed its task. The society invites the Polish people to attend the opening ceremonies of the Hall, 796-800 South Ashland Avenue, on January 1, 1893, at 2:00 P. M.</p>
   <p>To us Poles the opening of this building, bearing the name of our immortal hero of two countries [Poland and America], Casimir Pulaski, will be proof of our spirit, our progress and our unity in the presence of other nationalities, especially the American people. This event will be conclusive proof that the Polish people in America have not forgotten their heroes, who lost their lives fighting for the freedom of the people. It will also be further evidence that the Polish people, who have been forced to leave their native land and adopt a new one, want, and know how, to erect monuments to those who defended freedom with the might of the Polish sword. Because of this, the undersigned hope <pb facs="5423968_7_0039.jpg" n="2"/>that the Polish people will accept this invitation and attend the gala dedication services New Year's Day.</p>
   <p>Casimir Zychlinski, president;</p>
   <p>W. Mankowski, secretary;</p>
   <p>Francis Smietanka, Bernard L. Majewski, Joseph Napieralski, Adam Blaszczynski, Joseph Rozanski, John Czaja, Francis Marcinkowski, Anthony Polenz, administration</p>
   <p>P. S. The Polish societies which intend to take part in the ceremonies are requested to notify the secretary, W. Mankowski, 688 Van Horn Street, not later than December 20, in order that tickets may be issued to them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
