<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 30,
<date when="1915-07-28">July 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Consecration of The'guardian Angel'shelter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 30,
<date when="1915-07-28">July 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CONSECRATION OF THE'GUARDIAN ANGEL'SHELTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every appearance of social work in our society deserves the greatest praise. It proves indeed that we are pushing ourselves forward beyond the sphere of the necessities of home, that we are stepping into a field of work into which we are directed by our duties of Christian love. There has been very little of this sort of endeavor among our society until now because the financial indigence of our emigration seemed to have prevented us from carrying out this duty of ours.</p>
   <p>Did our financial conditions undergo a change in this regard, or has the dawn of a long awaited moment arrived when the stronger in spirit and feeling will fulfill our duty and give a helping hand to the weaker and poorer? We do not intend going into this, but nevertheless we state the fact that a great deed has been accomplished when the Home for Girls was opened under the auspices of the Holy Guardian Angel, at the corner of Gross Avenue and 46th Street, Chicago. This home was consecrated with great celebration on July 5. The consecration was performed in the absence of the Rev. Bishop, by Rev. F. M. Wojtalewicz, accompanied by the following priests: Reverends L. Grudzinski, F. Karabasz, S. Cholewinski, J. Grzesinski, S. Nawrocki, F. Rusch, A. Jung, B. Czajkowski, T. Langfort, and J. Gawrych.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0138.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the consecration a solemn high mass was said in the new chapel of the institution by the Rev. S. Nawrocki, the first outstanding benefactor of the first shelter for girls in Chicago. This new Polish outpost is a quite stately building, built upon spacious grounds with burnt brick. It is composed of three floors and a basement, accommodating easily 300 Polish girls, two beautiful chapels, dining room, kitchen, work room, sleeping rooms and the office of the institution. The Associated Polish Charitable Societies have their headquarters here, at the head of which stands the worthy and energetic priest Rev. Thomas Bona.</p>
   <p>There has been established there a suitable headquarters for girls, that branch of our society which is exposed to all kinds of exploitation, but up until now were left without any protection and care to the destiny of fortune or misfortune. The institution costs, together with the land, about $70,000, and undoubtedly brings honor upon those who were instrumental in its establishment.</p>
   <p>In a separate part of this building is a nursery for small children whose mothers are forced to go to work during the day. There is also an absolutely free health clinic for the poor Polish people of this city. Upon viewing this magnificent accomplishment, so useful, involuntarily the question forces itself upon one's lips: To whom are the Poles obligated for this beautiful monument of Christian mercy? Who is putting out the money for all of this?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0139.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Here are our Polish priests, the pastors of local parishes: Rev. S. Cholewinski, Pastor of St. Joseph's Church; Rev. L. Grudzinski, Pastor of St. of God Church, and F. J. Krabasz, Pastor of Sacred Heart Church.</p>
   <p>Honor to you, benefactors! May God bless you for this; let your example find as many emulators as possible among our emigration! let it be a stimulus, encouragement and example to others who up to this time looked at this indifferently and were slow with help and offerings for a charitable cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
