<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-12">Dec. 12, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Welfare Bazaar Opens</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0907</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0907.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-12">Dec. 12, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH WELFARE BAZAAR OPENS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, a Christmas welfare bazaar was opened at the Union hall for the widows and orphans of Upper Silesia. The affair is sponsored by district two of the Polish Sokols' Alliance of America. The sponsors were gratified by the large public attendance.</p>
   <p>The festivities were officially opened by Mr. Cieslik, secretary of the organization. Mr. Skibicki, president of Polish Sokols' Alliance, and Mr. Dolbinski, financial secretary, addressed the public. After the introductory speeches, the entertainment program was started.</p>
   <p>The first number on the program was a drill presented by the young boys and girls of the Sokol. This was followed by the singing of the well-known Chopin Choir. Four members of the Sokol danced the mazurka. Another group gave a demonstration on bars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0908.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Captain Hauke-Grzesika, Dr. Mikolajczyk, and Mr. Konieczny, members of the Upper Silesia delegation, gave short talks about the dire needs of their people. Each presented a part of the historical events leading to the rising in Silesia, and pointed out that although the Polish people of this section were oppressed by the Germans, they did not forget that they were Poles. According to them, when the time arose to defend themselves, they willingly went to the side of Poland.</p>
   <p>A collection was made after the speeches. It brought $218.03. The group Promien, of the Polish National Alliance, added ten dollars to the contributions.</p>
   <p>An orchestra added variety to the program with many Polish numbers. It also played during the drills staged by the Sokol members.</p>
   <p>This bazaar will continue for eight days. Persons who purchase christmas gifts at this bazaar will also make up that part of the donors who will wipe away the tears of many unfortunate people in Upper Silesia. The bazaar committee will continue to make this affair as gay and entertaining as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
