<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-23">Oct. 23, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Silver Anniversary of Group 91 of the Polish National Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0217</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0217.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-23">Oct. 23, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">SILVER ANNIVERSARY OF GROUP 91 OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polonia Society, Group 91 of the Polish National Alliance, formally celebrated the twenty-fifth anniversary of its existence on October 22, 1910. The celebrating group of the society, as well as representatives of other associations, met before the home of Mr. Romanowicz and marched to the strains of band music to Walsh's Hall, where appropriate commemoration exercises were held.</p>
   <p>Mr. D. Ekowski, the founder of the society, greeted the guests with cordial words. Then Mr. Joseph Piatkiewicz opened the celebration with brief but welcome words and called the Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance, as well as presidents of societies, to come up on the stage. There were numerous guests. The many societies occupied places at the nearby tables, in honor of the group that was celebrating. Mr. Philip Ksycki, vice-president of the Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance, presided over <pb facs="5423968_7_0218.jpg" n="2"/>the exercises, while the position of secretary was ably filled by Mr. S. Orpiszewski. The celebrated Chopin Choir appeared twice and sang several songs beautifully. Auspicious orations, pertinent to the occasion, were delivered by Mr. M. B. Steczynski, president of the Polish National Alliance, and Professor Romuald Piatkowski, whom the audience rewarded with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>Miss S. Kapelanska rendered her declamation in excellent fashion. After this, the presidents and delegates of various societies presented the group with numerous gifts. These consisted of money and other articles, such as a silver wreath, a mallet inlaid with silver, (to be used by the president of the group), several gold medals commemorating the occasion, and other equally auspicious gifts. Everyone who made a presentation spoke briefly but with sincerity to the group celebrating so rare a festivity.</p>
   <p>Finally, the chairman of the exercises, Mr. Ksycki, thanked all those present for their participation. For the finale, the Polish national anthem, <pb facs="5423968_7_0219.jpg" n="3"/>"God Save Poland", was sung by all, accompanied by the melodious strains of the popular orchestra under the baton of Mr. Przybylski. This concluded the exercises. There followed immediately a dance, which lasted until late at night.</p>
   <p>The celebrating society prepared an excellent commemorative program, in which a detailed report of the groups was presented. This was read in its totality by Mr. Ekowski, the founder of the society.</p>
   <p>The group numbers sixty-four members. During its existence a sum of $3,890.35 has been paid out from the society for sick and death benefits. Moreover, the association has made contributions for national purposes to the amount of $505.91. The society has made payments for the Polish Seminary at Detroit, maintained the national treasury at Rappersville, and purchased two banners, one Polish and one American, at a cost of $350. The present financial condition of the society shows that it has $224.32 and all necessary equipment.</p>
   <p>The present administration is composed of the following members:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0220.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Joseph Piatkiewicz, president; Theophil Cybarth, vice-president; Joseph Malkowski, treasurer; Joseph Graczyk, financial secretary; and Dionisius Ekowski, recording secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
