<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-04">Dec. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">"Dollar Christmas Fund"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1210</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1210.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-04">Dec. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">"DOLLAR CHRISTMAS FUND"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's mail brought us an appeal from an American society in New York which has recently been organized under the name of "Dollar Christmas Fund." Its purpose is to collect millions of dollars for the poor people of Belgium. In the name of almost two million Belgians who were forced to leave their country and are now wandering about Holland, England, and France, this society appeals to the merciful and kind hearts of the American people. It asks for contributions for those who will have to spend Christmas, the pleasantest holiday of all, away from their native land, perhaps in inadequate tents or ditches--cold, badly clad, and hungry.</p>
   <p>The tragedy of this small nation--which was once a magnificent and wealthy country but today has only its king, its government and a small piece of land left--has shaken the entire world to its depths. This destitution has found <pb facs="5423968_7_1211.jpg" n="2"/>a particular response in America.</p>
   <p>"The need is so great and the situation of this nation is so tragic," says the above-mentioned appeal of the "Dollar Christmas Fund," "that no sacrifices, no contributions, will be adequate. They will be able only to dry a tear and bring a little light to the poor Belgian families now abandoned by their providers.</p>
   <p>"Even if you have contributed to some other fund you cannot resist this appeal; you will contribute a dollar or more to the Christmas fund which will be sent from America and which must be worthy of the name of this nation. If you stop to consider that millions of people are dying of hunger, that children are constantly asking for bread, that homeless women press to their breasts infants who are shivering with cold, that old men have no place to go, you will not avoid making a generous contribution but will make it at once....."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1212.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And they will contribute, because Americans do not ask by what right a certain society collects funds to help the poor when there are already dozens of other such societies in existence. Americans will not use their press to undermine the people's confidence in this or that relief committee. They will not attack those collecting because of jealousy, or accuse them of robbery or of dissipating the funds; but, knowing the need and having kind hearts, they will trust these "self-appointed" committees, as we call them, which are created on the initiative of individuals and are not approved by special meetings or conventions of hundreds of delegates.</p>
   <p>And what about us? Why, among all the nations, is it the Polish nation which today suffers the greatest tragedy in history? There are almost two million Belgians wandering about on foreign soil. About four times as many people of our nation have met the same, or possibly a worse, fate.</p>
   <p>The Belgian nation has already found protectors throughout the entire world. Contributions come to them from England, France, Canada, and America. Even</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1213.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Australia has hurried to Belgium's aid. Who knows about our poverty? Who knows the tragedy of the situation in which our brothers, fathers, and mothers, in the homeland find themselves--besides possibly ourselves? Have the Americans formed any societies for the purpose of bringing aid to Poland? Have they, with the exception of a few individuals, answered the appeal sent out by the Polish Central Relief Committee with even a small contribution?</p>
   <p>A few of the local papers have mentioned the need of aiding Poland--even describing this as a duty--but nothing else has been done, because we ourselves do not know how to take advantage of sympathies, and, in quarreling about who should dictate the politics of leadership, we forget the most important duty which we should perform over here.</p>
   <p>In general we do not understand Americans, nor they us. We do not want to knock on the doors of their generosity, and they themselves will not fling open the doors to their great generosity for us. If we wanted to, and knew how to do it, we could organize similar "Dollar Christmas Funds" for ourselves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1214.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>By describing to the Americans the horrible devastation and destruction on Polish soil--on which battles have been fought since the very beginning of the war--we should enlist their sympathy and, what follows, their generosity.</p>
   <p>Maybe we do not need this! Perhaps we ourselves are so generous that we can already send a sizeable fund as a Christmas present to our children, sisters, brothers, mothers, and fathers. Knowing the poverty and destitution of millions of our closest relatives--because surely there is not a Pole in America who has not heard about it--we hurry with aid. We give all of our surplus; we have already succeeded in collecting about $100,000, together with that which we contributed for similar purposes in 1912.</p>
   <p>For almost four million Polish emigres this is quite a bit; it is all of two and one-half cents per capita....</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1215.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"Hard times," whispers the merchant or the wealthier industrialist, and he will not go to the mass meeting or celebration because a collection will be taken up there.</p>
   <p>"No work," whispers the wealthier landlord of the shopkeeper, and he closes his pocket when a collector approaches him to ask for a modest contribution for the homeland.</p>
   <p>"Poverty in general," we all complain, unmindful of the fact that over there they look upon us as millionaires, and justly so in contrast to their poverty. We are satisfied with the nickels which we toss into the collector's plate.</p>
   <p>There are those who not only do not contribute anything, but even make fun of those who collect and contribute. They suspect the collectors or their leaders of theft and assert that Poland deserves nothing from them because she will give then nothing in return.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1216.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Therefore it is not surprising that our brothers and sisters will not have a merry Christmas this year, that no one will come to their aid, that the star of Bethlehem, which brings "peace to men of good will," will not shine for them, because foreign "Dollar Christmas Funds" do not exist for us, and we ourselves do not consider it our duty to aid the homeland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
