<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-05-30">May 30, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Hunger and Destitution</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1556</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1556.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-05-30">May 30, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">HUNGER AND DESTITUTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On February 7, 1891, under the title "Hunger and Destitution," we published an article in which we called the attention of our countrymen to the fact that among the Poles there are many families and individuals who need help, help that the County Welfare Bureau is unable to give in an adequate manner. We pointed out at the time that other national groups had their own benevolent institutions and that since the Poles had not done anything along this line, despite the growing need among their poor, it was high time that they consider the matter.</p>
   <p>In the article in question we also told our readers that the Poles had considered the necessity of establishing an institution of this kind but <pb facs="5423968_7_1557.jpg" n="2"/>never had succeeded in arriving to a definite understanding. We concluded with the remark that we hoped that the Poles who had taken this matter up on several occasions, as well as others who were willing to support it, would in the very near future get together for the purpose of deciding on this urgent necessity, dictated by our heart, our conscience, and our honor. In fact, we predicted that it was not going to be long before we could be able to announce in our paper the formation of a committee to begin the work. And our prediction came through as expected, for now we learn that this idea is beginning to take shape.</p>
   <p>County Commissioner Victor Bardonski, our well-known countryman, is the reviver of the idea. As a county commissioner, Mr. Bardonski is in a position to estimate the extent to which the County Welfare Bureau can help.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1558.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He is, moreover, aware of the fact that many of our countrymen need Polish assistance because the county Bureau cannot tend to all their needs.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bardonski will hold a conference next week, the exact date to be announced later, to which will be invited all those who are interested in this important undertaking. At this meeting, ways and means of forming a welfare committee will be discussed.</p>
   <p>This is such an important matter that we are releasing this information ahead of time. Influential and practical Poles should take this matter under consideration. Up to now, no one has any idea of how to tackle this problem so that it is necessary to concentrate on the matter, lest the whole project go to pieces.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1559.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Our paper is willing to co-operate with those desiring to make any suggestions in this direction. Perhaps the solution to this problem lies in these suggestions, since they may furnish a clue to the realization of the plan.</p>
   <p>In our opinion valuable information could be obtained from German, Irish, and other institutions. Poles connected with members of these institutions should inquire from them how their institutions are managed. The members of these organizations are qualified through experiences to point out the benefits and faults of these institutions and as a result they can give valuable information. Not only because of their benevolent character, but also because of the load taken off their shoulders, these institutions will be more than willing to give the information required.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1560.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The success of the new institution will depend, of course, on the generosity of its founders and members.</p>
   <p>Contributions may be made in cash or in goods, such as food, coal, etc. Cash donations will be sent directly to the treasurer's office, which will dispose of them in accordance with the decision of members. Signed pledges intended to Maintain a fixed income that will enable the management to issue regular orders to those who need help, will also be accepted. Not only those who are willing to support the institution financially, but also those who wish to support it morally, should be welcomed as members. Sound advice, as well as any other activity in behalf of the institution will be credited as financial help. It is for this reason that no one who is able to help should shirk this patriotic duty.</p>
   <p>The foregoing suggestions are provisional and general; their purpose being <pb facs="5423968_7_1561.jpg" n="6"/>to create a desire towards the consideration of this matter. Should our suggestions give rise to a controversy, so much the better. After all, opposition is better than indifference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
