<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-10-23">Oct. 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to Mothers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1239</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1239.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-10-23">Oct. 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO MOTHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As is already known it has been suggested in this country, which feels the consequences of the terrible European tragedy the least, that the children of fortunate and wealthy parents give Christmas presents to the children of the war areas. The parents of those children are dying of starvation, are absolutely destitute, and cannot even provide enough food for their little ones, much less give them little presents on this day which is so dear to us and is awaited with such eagerness by all of us.</p>
   <p>This idea, suggested by a group of philanthropic people, has been applauded everywhere. Mothers already have begun to tell their children to save the pennies their parents give them, in order to be able to send Christmas presents to children their own age who have lost their fathers in the war and whose mothers are starving.</p>
   <p>Our people here, who certainly realize that the present war is being fought <pb facs="5423968_7_1240.jpg" n="2"/>primarily on our Polish soil, should take up this idea. The war has brought terrible destitution to hundreds of thousands of families, deprived them of their homes, and cast them on the mercy of strangers. It has made wanderers and beggars of them. We have already read so much about the horrible crimes committed by the Germans in our land, that surely no one needs to be convinced that our nation has experienced the greatest wrongs and abuse.</p>
   <p>No one will hear our protest because we do not have the backing of ministers at the courts of neutral nations which might want to take up this matter for us. The only protest we can make before the world at present is to contribute all we can to help our starving brothers and sisters and our tiny brothers who are crying for a drop of milk, who no doubt turn their sad eyes toward us, believing that only from us can encouragement and comfort come to them.</p>
   <p>We give wherever we can. Our contributions, though just begun, are steadily increasing. It is time that our mothers begin inculcating in their children <pb facs="5423968_7_1241.jpg" n="3"/>the idea that they should follow the example of children of other nationalities and save their pennies, so that every Polish child in America can send a Christmas present to a child his own age who is hungry and homeless.</p>
   <p>Polish mothers, begin tomorrow to teach your children how to save! Tell them that over there in Europe thousands upon thousands of Polish children--their brothers and sisters--will not be able to look forward to a good dinner and presents on Christmas Day. Explain to them the terrible predicament in which these children find themselves. Awaken in them the desire to save and help the children of the most unfortunate nation in the world.</p>
   <p>A way will be found to send these gifts. If the Americans send them, we, too, can send them in care of relief committees which have been organized in all Polish cities. This is not our greatest concern. Our greatest concern is to have Polish mothers take this appeal to heart and begin at once to persuade their children to be generous to the poor little children who now do not have a roof over their heads or probably even have a spoonful of warm food.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1242.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Therefore to work, Polish mothers, and your deed manifested in your children will be the best protest against Prussian barbarism: it will be a living protest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
