<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. I, No. 4,
<date when="1920-01-28">Jan. 28, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A Great Massmeeting at the Hole of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0955</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0955.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. I, No. 4,
<date when="1920-01-28">Jan. 28, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT MASSMEETING AT THE HOLE OF THE POLISH ROMAN-CATHOLIC UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There was a great Polish massmeeting at the hall of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, located at Augusta and Milwaukee Avenue, on the 20th day of January, 1920, sponsored by Mr. Z. Stefanowicz, the editor of Narod Polski.</p>
   <p>At that meeting the following Polish leaders and great orators spoke: (1) Father Adamski, a Polish prelate, the patron of the Cooperative Association of the province of Posen and Silesia, in Poland. (2) Mr. K. Karpinski, the head manager of the Cooperative Bank of Poland. (3) Lieutenant George Lekszycki, head of the Foreign Department in General Haller's army.</p>
   <p>The meeting was a great success. The hall was filled with the public to its capacity; even the aisles were occupied.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0956.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. N. L. Piotrowski, president of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, was the first speaker. He started the program by introducing the representatives of the Cooperative Bank of Poland, which was founded by the late Prelate Rev. Wawrzyniak. Those cooperative associations fought for the economic independence of the Polish people in the province of Posen.</p>
   <p>The Rev. Prelate Adamski, began his speech by a remark that perhaps we doubt that our offers which we have contributed towards Poland have reached its proper destination; that perhaps it would seem to us that those donations get lost somewhere on the way to Poland, and those who need it most receive very little or nothing.</p>
   <p>"You here in America," he said," do not realize what a great service you have rendered for our nation by your generosity. I saw with my own eyes how donations contributed by the American Poles have saved people from starvation; how clothing sent by you covered the poor people and protected them from cold, giving them encouragement by strengthening their falling spirits and urging them to go on with their work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0957.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"It would be necessary for you to see for yourselves if you wished to know the value of the help rendered by your organizations towards our country.</p>
   <p>"And the fate of the Fatherland, of those Polish people was terrible. In the first place things were horrible in Galicia. There, in that land, formerly called Galicia and now Malo-Polska (Little Poland), rich in black soil and minerals, the people were more loyal to the House of Habsburg than it was worth. Quite often you could hear the expression among the people that the Austrian emperor was "our emperor." During the war time, not only did they enlist in the army but also formed legions from the remnants of those left behind, which took an oath of fealty to "Our Emperor," who was under the command of German "Willie." Loyal were Malo-Polanie (Poland Minor) but what reward have they received from the Austrian government? More than half of the Austrian disabled soldiers live at present in Poland Minor (Galicia). What does that mean? It means that our Polish regiments from Poland Minor were forced to fight the fiercest battles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0958.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"How many of these poor fellows lost their lives we do not know because the poor Austrian system has no records.</p>
   <p>"But that is not all. Mr. Dlugosz, the Polish envoy, showed an authorized Austrian statement that 60,000 of Polish civilian population were hanged by the Austrian army.</p>
   <p>"If someone informed an Austrian officer that there was a spy in the village, the officer issued an order to massacre the whole village. They slew everyone, men, women and children, in order to destroy the evidence of the terrible crime. Germans and Hungarians enjoyed the massacres in particular."</p>
   <p>A Polish officer, who served formerly in the Austrian army, told the prelate that when he received the order to exterminate every human being in the village, he almost lost his senses.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0959.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>At his feet the innocent men, women and children writhed in terrible agonies, sentenced to death by the Austrians.</p>
   <p>There! The vile German spirit took a revenge on our nation! There! The Austrians ordered by Germans, have been destroying our nation!</p>
   <p>The Austrians did not defend Poland Minor (Galicia) against the Russians because they were under the German command, were ordered not to do so; consequently that part of Poland was open to invasion and was easy prey for the Russians.</p>
   <p>Today that country which was once rich, is in a dire poverty. Whole localities are depopulated. All you can see are cripples, cripples and cripples. Today that country must be fed by other sections of Poland.</p>
   <p>In one locality, where Rev. Prelate Adamski had sent a car of flour, the expressmen were told that they were too late for all the children had died. They were told to deliver the flour to another locality where <pb facs="5423968_7_0960.jpg" n="6"/>there still lived a few children. The five-year-old children who could walk at the age of two do not walk any more for they are too weak; in reality they have forgotten how to walk.</p>
   <p>That is the reward received by Poland Minor for her loyalty. There is no home without a dead member, no family without a casualty. Life in America is heaven as compared to the life over there.</p>
   <p>The conditions in Russian Poland were a little better. The Muscovite (Russian) who was a drunkard and a grafter, did not take all the young Poles into the army for he pretended to be our friend, but when he saw that Germans are after his skin, then he gave an Asiatic, savage, barbaric order to burn and destroy everything in the Polish territory; the population was ordered to go to Mother Russia (deep Russia).</p>
   <p>The sky became red from the reflections of burning villages, and the roads leading towards the East were filled with refugees.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0961.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The Russian hordes have burned and plundered many Polish villages, but they could not accomplish their work of destruction, for the Germans were at their heels.</p>
   <p>Instead of the Russians, the Germans and the Austrians were the masters of the situation. They told the Polish inhabitants that there was famine and the Poles must starve first.</p>
   <p>The Germans sent their soldiers through Poland to rob what was left and they plundered the Polish cities and villages. In the province of Posen the Germans duplicated the Austrians in Poland Minor. The German government confiscated everything for the German army and the German population. There was sickness and starvation every where. Then your shipments of gifts from America started to arrive in Poland, wiping the tears of our brothers, giving us encouragement.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
