<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-22">Dec. 22, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">In the Polish Roman Catholic Union Former General Secretary of the Union, Mr. F. Krolik, Presents Explanation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0157</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0157.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-22">Dec. 22, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION Former General Secretary of the Union, Mr. F. Krolik, Presents Explanation</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union!</p>
   <p>From the time of the discovery of Mr. Ostrowski's malfeasance [as an officer of] the Polish Roman Catholic Union, repeated charges have been directed against me by the present administration, which I do not understand or admit. The members of the organization who have repeatedly honored me and trusted me by electing me to the office of general secretary could demand of me only that I keep the books in order. Did I not do that? Could any one, in the course of my tenure of office charge me with entering willingly and knowingly one false item on the records of the Polish Roman Catholic Union? Can experts and public accountants from Springfield or the present administration or Mr. S. Adamkiewicz charge me with any such transgression?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0158.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I solemnly declare and give assurance upon my word of honor that every entry made by me is honest, and I take full responsibility for each and every item.</p>
   <p>The supposition that Mr. Szopinski and I must have known of the malfeasance of Mr. Ostrowski is false.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ostrowski, the treasurer of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, was also treasurer of other business associations and enterprises. In conducting the construction of some thirty churches he had sufficient credit to obtain cash when it was necessary at a given time.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ostrowski, as he himself stated, besides erecting thirty churches also built about five hundred buildings, and his turnover in the period of his tenure of office exceeded two and a half million dollars. Hence, in accordance with his needs, he could transfer money from one account to another, Whenever I or Mr. Szopinski asked him about the cash, he could always give an <pb facs="5423968_7_0159.jpg" n="3"/>accounting. To conventions he took certified checks, and proved himself solvent.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ostrowski undertook too many enterprises, and I suppose that he made his bids for [building] contracts too low. Be that as it may, neither I nor Mr. Szopinski talked him into any enterprises. Moreover, we never dreamed that he would use the funds of the Union to promote his personal interests.</p>
   <p>Then, again, Mr. Ostrowski at no time gave money either to me or to Mr. Szopinski for safekeeping. Consequently, only those could take money from him whom he had trusted outside the organization.</p>
   <p>What is more, Mr. Ostrowski cannot show a single check which might dishonestly have been passed to him twice for payment. He is not so foolish that he would not have called attention to this. Even if he had said nothing of it previously, he certainly would say it today, and he would present the checks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0160.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If Mr. Ostrowski claims that he never counted the daily receipts, that is a false statement, for he was very exacting when it came to taking in money. When we closed the daily financial reports, he was always present, and he counted every penny of it and took the money with him. The only reason for his antagonism to me and Mr. Szopinski was that we demanded that he deposit the money daily in the bank in the organization's name. He made every possible attempt to squirm out of this. When he discovered recently that Mr. Szopinski was secretly checking him, he became definitely antagonistic and combined with our enemies to prevent our re-election. If we were partners in the malfeasance, it would be natural to expect that he would be hand in glove with us.</p>
   <p>Why, then, does not Mr. Ostrowski himself speak up? Why is this left to Mr. Adamkiewicz and the former treasurer's friends of the new administration? If Mr. Ostrowski could say that "such and such funds were taken from me by Mr. Krolik, and so much and so much by Mr. Szopinski," that would be very pleasing to his protectors and would help him greatly in his defense. But <pb facs="5423968_7_0161.jpg" n="5"/>he cannot say that because it is not true, and at no time was there any suspicion of such a thing.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ostrowski never was nor could have been either my victim or Mr. Szopinski's. His present position resulted from reversals in his building enterprises. If he had been successful this year in closing at least one good contract and in obtaining a considerable deposit on it, this catastrophe would never have occurred. But, as I understand the conditions in the Polish Roman Catholic Union, this catastrophe could not have involved more than a few thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>If there was actually a defalcation of the huge sum of ninety thousand dollars, then this was due exclusively to Mr. Adamkiewicz and his friends in the new administration. In their fight against me and Mr. Szopinski they have forgotten completely about watching and checking Mr. Ostrowski.</p>
   <p>They have conducted themselves in exactly the same way as did Mr. Roszkowiak.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0162.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>This gentlemen, in his statement made to the Polish newspaper, Dziennik Narodowy, asserts that being a member of the revision committee, he had searched hopelessly for Attorney Belinski, and that he waited for us and for others. But it is strange that he did not approach Mr. Ostrowski and did not say to him:</p>
   <p>"I refuse to sign the report until you make an accounting of the money according to the last [of those] statements [which are] always printed in the official organ of the Polish Roman Catholic Union."</p>
   <p>It is far more convenient for Mr. Roszkowiak to tell fairy tales now as to why he did not examine the treasury. He did not need anybody [or anything] to help him do this except Mr. Ostrowski and the recent financial statement printed in the Dziennik Narodowy.</p>
   <p>It is equally convenient for Mr. Adamkiewicz and for others to present Mr. Ostrowski as an unfortunate victim and falsely to blame me and Mr. Szopinski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0163.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>By so doing they attempt to free themselves of the charges of criminal negligence and scandalous mismanagement of the organization's funds. They have brought about these conditions in their administration.</p>
   <p>In order to inspire confidence in others, they say that I was an ordinary laborer and without proper education for the position which I held. Strange, very strange indeed, that only after my ten years of work as secretary of the Polish Roman Catholic Union and after five conventions the present administration has discovered this and has announced to the whole world in a very noisy manner that I was an inadequate person for the office of secretary, an ordinary laborer without the least education! The highly experienced professional dignitaries of the present Polish Roman Catholic Union base their assertion upon the fact that after coming from my native land to America I worked in a lumberyard as a common laborer.</p>
   <p>Yes, I have worked, as all others have who have come here fresh from Europe. I have worked hard for my living, and for a period of several months I was <pb facs="5423968_7_0164.jpg" n="8"/>an ordinary laborer, an employee of the Ritz Lumber Company; but I have never been ashamed of this work, nor am I ashamed of it now, for it was honest and honorable labor. Nevertheless this charge is no proof whatsoever that I arrived in this country without the slightest education of any type. The best proof of this is perhaps the fact that the firm for which I worked as an ordinary laborer, despite the fact that I had not mastered the language of this country, promoted me after four years of hard labor to the position of bookkeeper, a position which I held for four years. After this I was a foreman in the employ of this company for a full year, until the time when St. Stanislaus Kostka's Parish appointed me its secretary, and these duties I performed for more than six years to the general satisfaction of the reverend pastor as well as that of all the parishioners, who have from time to time honored me with their complete trust.</p>
   <p>At the same time I was appointed to the very important position of secretary of the St. Joseph Savings and Loan Association, and in this association more than three hundred thousand dollars passed through my hands annually. This <pb facs="5423968_7_0165.jpg" n="9"/>position was held by me for more than twenty years, and to the best of my knowledge [I filled it] to the general satisfaction of the members of the administration and of the official examiners in Springfield.</p>
   <p>Ten years ago the convention of the Polish Roman Catholic Union for the first time honored me with the position of general secretary. From that time on I have served in that capacity to the best of my ability, having at heart only the welfare of the organization. At the same time Mr. Szopinski, who later became the president of the organization, was appointed on the financial committee, which completely reorganized the Union, brought order into it, and worked out a new assessment table. This table placed the declining organization again on a firm basis.</p>
   <p>The subsequent conventions serve as the best proof that my work was well and capably done. This is further attested by the examining committees appointed at the conventions as well as by the Insurance Department's examiners sent from Springfield by the State government. These two examining groups have <pb facs="5423968_7_0166.jpg" n="10"/>for the last ten years always expressed themselves in commendation of my work.</p>
   <p>As secretary I have worked hard and deligently for several years without any one's assistance. It was not until recently that with the consent of the convention the administration of the organization gave me an assistant in the person of my daughter, a capable bookkeeper. Her salary for a very long time did not exceed twenty-five dollars a quarter.</p>
   <p>Any impartial person may go to the office of the organization and see how I have keep the books. After so doing I am certain that such a person will not accuse me of lack of education and ability to perform my duties as secretary. The best proof of that is the income that has come into the organization as a result of my labor and Mr. Szopinski's throughout ten years.</p>
   <p>The manner in which the present administration keeps books is best seen in the fact that on November 12, 1910, the president, according to the Polish newspaper, <pb facs="5423968_7_0167.jpg" n="11"/>Dziennik Chicagoski, reported the assets of the Polish Roman Catholic Union as $666,708.85, whereas in the official report it was shown almost simultaneously that they were only $631,986.53. The difference of $34,722.52 in the two figures is no trifle. Moreover, how many times was the present general secretary obliged to change the announced balance, making deductions of several thousand dollars, for the benefit of the treasurer?</p>
   <p>Equally false are the charges that I, in collaboration with Mr. Szopinski, endeavored to destroy the organization's documents immediately after the convention. This accusation has no foundation and is nothing but a falsehood. Every sane man will acknowledge that neither the former president of the Union nor I would be so naive as not to know the consequences of such an act.</p>
   <p>False also are the accusations of the present noisemakers in the Polish Roman Catholic Union, who claim that I have paid exorbitant sums for printing material to a firm in which Mr. Szopinski has an interest. They announce, for example, that for printing the constitution I paid ten cents a copy, <pb facs="5423968_7_0168.jpg" n="12"/>whereas the officials of the present administration pay only three and a half cents.</p>
   <p>This is nothing more than a base lie and an attempt to confuse the members of the organization. In my term of office, on February 6, 1906, Mr. Szopinski's printing concern charged the organization ninety dollars for printing four thousand copies of the constitution, or 2 ¼ cents a copy. In the year of 1907 Mr. Szopinski's firm printed five thousand copies for $120, 2 1/5 cents a copy. Receipt books for members, bound in cloth, were printed by the same firm at 4 ½ cents a copy. When it was decided to open new sets of books in the numerous branch groups of the Union, a special committee of the directors was delegated to request estimates on these books of other printing companies. No firm, however, gave so low a price as that of Mr. Szopinski. Naturally, his company received the contract to print these books. It was the same with other printed matter. Why, then, cast calumnies and spread lies about exorbitant prices for printing material for the Union?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0169.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>One more word of the alleged extortions of Mr. Szopinski's firm. It had, in fact, a clause in its contract that the Polish Roman Catholic Union was to pay it for correcting addresses. Despite this clause the organization for eight years did not pay a cent for this work. The firm further had it stipulated in the contract that it was to be allowed to print at least sixteen columns of advertisements per week, but it never took advantage of this privilege and did not print on an average more than eight columns per week.</p>
   <p>Mr. Szopinski and I have never taken a cent for making numerous installations in the groups of the organization and for various other personal expenses. All these expenses were met by us, although in the first years of Mr. Szopinski's term of office he received a salary of only two hundred dollars a year.</p>
   <p>That is the way in which Mr. Szopinski and I have abused our Polish Roman Catholic Union and extorted money from it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0170.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>I am convinced that the members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, who have always honored me with their trust, will arrive at the conviction that I was at all times their faithful servant and was ever sincere in my endeavors to promote the Union's interests.</p>
   <p>Fraternally yours,</p>
   <p>Thomas Krolik</p>
   <p>Former general secretary of the</p>
   <p>Polish Roman Catholic Union</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
