<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-07">Jan. 7, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Benefit Ball for Polish Welfare Association Planned</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone--one column--eighth of a page, profile of August Kowalski, treasurer] [Half-tone-one column-eighth of a page, profile of Mrs. C. L. Grabbot]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0105</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0105.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-07">Jan. 7, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">BENEFIT BALL FOR POLISH WELFARE ASSOCIATION PLANNED</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone--one column--eighth of a page, profile of August Kowalski, treasurer] [Half-tone-one column-eighth of a page, profile of Mrs. C. L. Grabbot]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our life is a combination of happy and sad moments, peace and storms, cloudy and sunny days.....</p>
   <p>Following these steps our Polonia is making an effort to remedy the sad and needy circumstances of life in a more pleasant and diplomatic way.</p>
   <p>In this city of ours it is concerned about the tens of thousands of under privileged Polish children and youths, many of whom get their training in the streets without guidance.</p>
   <p>Because of this, not one or two, but hundreds, and at times thousands, of our youth stray from the path of righteousness to pursue the road of evil; as a <pb facs="5423968_7_0106.jpg" n="2"/>result, they find themselves before the juvenile tribunal.</p>
   <p>It is at that crucial moment that the Polish Welfare Association steps forward like a guardian angel before the face of justice, to protect our youth from the bad effects of law transgression.</p>
   <p>After all this youth is innocent. Such transgressors have had very little training to distinguish good from bad, and when they break a law it is because of the bare necessity of satisfying a necessary and natural want, or because of ignorance. The punishment of such children by incarceration in detention homes means only a training for professional lawbreakers.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the Polish Welfare Association takes the place of the home which is negligent in taking care of the children.</p>
   <p>This work is unusually noble and the more funds are gathered the better will be the care extended to our neglected and abandoned boys and girls, [who are left to their fate.]</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0107.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Because of the nature of this work we are certain that all the Polish men and women will greatly support the Polish Welfare Association ball on Wednesday, January 18, at the Stevens Hotel, 8.30 P. M.</p>
   <p>At this ball one can easily find entertainment to his heart's content and mix with people from whom much can be learned. Mrs. Mary Paczynzka, who is at the head of this organization, is president; Anna Chrzanowska acts as secretary; August Kowalski, treasurer of the Northwestern Bank, largest Polish bank, is treasurer. Mrs. Pearl Dyniewicz is chairwoman of the entertainment committee, while Mrs. C. L. Grabbot is chairwoman of the ball. The following will act as assistants: Mmes. H. Bieszke, F. Brandt, M. J. Peska, J. Kowalska, secretary.</p>
   <p>Vocal music will be part of the entertainment. Sylvester Klosowski's orchestra will play for the dancers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
