<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. I, No. 15,
<date when="1897-04-09">April 9, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">[Appeal for Hospital]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0458</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0458.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. I, No. 15,
<date when="1897-04-09">April 9, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">[APPEAL FOR HOSPITAL]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Monday, the 19th of this month, the day after Easter, at 7:30 P. M. at St. Stanislaus Church Hall a great concert will be given for the benefit of the Polish hospital, which for three years has been serving the poor people.</p>
   <p>First rate artists of our city are offering their services. Mrs. Paula Bredermann, a concert singer of Munich Conservatory, Mr. Ernest Wendt, whose Polish mother has inspired him with love for her countrymen, is the first violinist with the famous Thomas Orchestra. Amateurs will perform on the piano, violin and violincello under the direction of Mr. Rudolph Modrzejewski, son of our famous artist. Polish Organizations are offering their singing choirs. For two years there has been no benefit performance for our hospital. Several hundred persons of both sexes have found help and tender care at the hospital and the number of free patients is steadily growing because of hard times.</p>
   <p>Besides the sacrifices of the organizers of the hospital, the Sisters of Nazareth and the disinterested services of best doctors, the Polish hospital posseses no resources and depends only on the contributions of the public for its growth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0459.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We appeal to this charitable feeling of the people from every neighborhood to reserve the first evening after lent and help this worthy cause, showing the gratitude to the splendid artists who are giving free their time and talent.</p>
   <p>We hope all officials of various Polish societies will strongly urge their members to support this concert. There is no one but who either have had or may have a member of his family in our hospital.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
