<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-18">Feb. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Case of Mr. Stanley Mermel</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0147</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0147.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-18">Feb. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE CASE OF MR. STANLEY MERMEL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two Chicago Polish newspapers, Dziennik Chicagoski and Dziennik Ludowy, in their editions of February 17, 1915, published a statement forwarded to them by Mr. Stanley Mermel, whose resignation was requested and received by the board of directors of the Polish National Alliance. Mr. Mermel had formerly acted in the capacity of vice-president of the organization. In his public statement Mr. Mermel, in a sly manner, before judgment could be passed at a certain meeting on his unbecoming behavior, attempted to cast aspersions on the whole central administration of the Polish National Alliance. He attempted to accuse every one of the knavery which he himself has practiced for several months. He finally resigned, taking with him, at 7 A.M., secretly and illegally, as one of the directors correctly remarked, important documents belonging to the organization.</p>
   <p>Before this newspaper, the Dziennik Zwiazkowy, discusses the case of Mr. Mermel more thoroughly, it wishes to make an immediate reply [to Mr. Mermel's letter], <pb facs="5423968_7_0148.jpg" n="2"/>a reply which will explain why Mr. Mermel was not punished, and why he fled from the headquarters of the Polish National Alliance before his term had expired. He even lacked the courage to be present at the meeting of the central administration of the Polish National Alliance at which his actions were to be judged. The best document [in evidence] is the sworn testimony of Mr. J. Borkowski and Dr. W. Bochenek, members of the Committee on National Defense. In their testimony against Mr. Mermel they let it be known that he has exposed all the secrets and confidential matters of the Polish National Alliance to the worst enemies of the Alliance. This document, which has been in the hands of Mr. K. Olszowy for the last few weeks, was to have been taken under advisement at the board of directors' meeting. It was to have exposed Mr. Mermel as a traitor to the Polish National Alliance, which it did, and which it is considered to have done in the reports of the central administration of the Polish National Alliance. Another column of today's issue of the Dziennik Zwiazkowy contains the sworn statement of the aforesaid Mr. J. Borkowski and Dr. W. Bochenek.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0149.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And a man like this, to whom many other unsavory dealings are attributed, has the audacity today to say that he is acting for the welfare of the Polish National Alliance, announcing to the whole world his resignation from the position that he has shamefully abused! Let the members of the Polish National Alliance judge for themselves and be convinced that every cad shields himself behind the name and the good reputation of the Polish National Alliance when he is about to be exposed for his knavery and degraded activities! So much for today. This matter will receive further consideration in the very near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
