<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-23">Apr. 23, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Pleasant Strangers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0335</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0335.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 c (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I L (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-23">Apr. 23, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">PLEASANT STRANGERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Seven months ago, a Jewish welfare organization was organized for the purpose of helping Jewish persons who have come to Chicago, to establish themselves. The city's richest and most influential Jews became supporters of this benevolent society. Headquarters were established at 154 West Lake Street as temporary quarters for the newcomers. Here assistance of every kind was given. Thousands of Jewish people received sustenance for a few days, and then were sent out West where various kinds of employment were offered them. Some of them, in fact, fifteen per cent, declined to be sent out, because they refused to sacrifice themselves to farming, consequently, they remained and continued to receive free board.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0336.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Finally, the patience of the welfare society was exhausted. The idlers were informed by the officials that unless they found work, they would be forced out. And when they did not heed this warning, they were put out, for room had to be made for the incoming strangers.</p>
   <p>Those that were compelled to leave, returned again and insisted upon being permitted to stay at the shelter. When they were refused, a demonstration was started. These reached such proportions that Mr. Loeb, president of the organization, and Mr. Goldstein, director of the employment bureau, were compelled to call the police for help. As the police arrived on the scene, the demonstrators began to break the doors down. Mr. Loeb pointed out a person by the name of Alper as the chief instigator. He was arrested. But Alper was released by the intervention and pleading of his parents.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0337.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Although the police succeeded in dispersing the mob, they soon returned. The police were called anew. This time Captain Kennedy came to investigate. In the meantime, hundreds of persons gathered. The police had to disperse them before they could confront the rioting Jews. They were informed by the police that they could not be readmitted to the shelter. The Jews began to cry, yell, and scream. All claimed vociferously that they were unable to work because of sickness. This was to no avail. At the end, they had to leave. Many found shelter at the police station.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
