<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-26">Aug. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish to Stage Benefit Fair for Holy Family Orphanage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0703</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0703.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-26">Aug. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH TO STAGE BENEFIT FAIR FOR HOLY FAMILY ORPHANAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Through the efforts of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish a fair will be held at the school hall for the benefit of Holy Family Orphanage. A number of leading citizens of the parish gathered at a meeting yesterday and prepared plans for this event.</p>
   <p>The fair is to run for two weeks beginning September 21, except on Fridays and Wednesdays. Single admission will be ten cents and a ticket for the duration of the fair (12 admissions) will cost fifty cents.</p>
   <p>Committees were chosen for making the plans. On the financial committee the following were chosen: A W. Rudnicki, president and treasurer; B. Klarkowski, secretary; Messrs. Lamczyk and Tomaszewski.</p>
   <p>The management committee will be as follows: W. Jedrzejek, president; <pb facs="5423968_7_0704.jpg" n="2"/>T. Krolik, secretary; F. Wleklinski, J. Mucha and P. Ratkowski.</p>
   <p>Operators of the various concessions will be: F. Nuncek, F. Okon, T. Majewski, Golubski, Klugiewicz, A. Ogurek, Cinau, Drzonek, J. Robakowski, J. Steltman, Dolinski, Petlak, F. Zagrzebski, J. Tomaszewski, Kikulski, Wieckowski and J. Rudnicki.</p>
   <p>The buffets will be operated by F. Okon, J. Kortas (both as cashiers), J. Gorzynski, J. Kwasigroch, J. Palubski, Dudek, P. Smeja, Szczodrowski and Bohart.</p>
   <p>T. Ostrowski, J. Maca, Kolodziejski and F. Murkowski will have charge of the sale of tickets. Tickets will be received by Smorowski, John Klinger, Jacob Klinger and Polcyn.</p>
   <p>The management committee will make efforts to book an orchestra for the event.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0705.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As can be seen, the citizens of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish are willingly supporting this affair by offering to contribute their services. Undoubtedly a large number of contributions will also be made, especially by businessmen.</p>
   <p>Polish businessmen will meet on Friday, August 30, to discuss the matter, and we believe there will be enthusiastic response.</p>
   <p>An event of this kind, for the support of unfortunate Polish orphans, is worthy of encouragement and assistance by all Poles of Chicago. It concerns not only the orphans of this parish but also the orphans of all Polish parishes in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
