<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-07-08">July 8, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of Polish Home of Freedom in Brighton Park Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0804</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0804.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-07-08">July 8, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF POLISH HOME OF FREEDOM IN BRIGHTON PARK CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, July 3, 1927, the Polish settlement in Brighton Park celebrated the dedication of its own Polish Liberty Home,which is located at 46th and Mozart Sts. A delightful program was staged by the Polish Dramatic Club, "Ognisko." The dedication was preceded by a solemn religious service in the Five Holy Martyrs' church, where representatives of local church societies from this parish participated and Rev. Francis Czarny, assistant to the pastor, was a celebrant of the Holy Mass. Rev. Francis Czarny arrived at the Polish Home of Freedom, where the sponsors of the new institute were gathered, at exactly 3 o'clock in the afternoon. Immediately following the solemn rites of the dedication of our new Polish Home of Freedom, the Rev. Francis Czarny delivered an address expressly suited to this impressive occasion.</p>
   <p>Rev. Francis Czarny explained to the vast audiance of celebrants, the great importance of such a home, and encouraged all to employ every effort toward the good of the community. The Rev. Czarny was rewarded with enthusiastic applause for his effective speech.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0805.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After this Mr. K. J. Karaskiewicz, president of the committee representing Allied societies sponsoring the Polish Home of Freedom in Brighton Park, thanked the Rev. Czarny, in the name of the committee, for his encouragement; and after a brief introduction formally opened the program by appointing Mr. W. Koztowski chairman, and Mr. Anthony Guzdek, a member of the dramatic club "Ognisko," secretary.</p>
   <p>The orchestra played the Star Spangled Banner, then Mr. W. Kozlowski, the chairman and also one of the founders of the Polish Home of Freedom in Brighton Park, related. in a long speech, the history of the Polish Home of Freedom of that neighborhood; stressing the difficulties encountered in the erection of an edifice of this size because of the lack of funds.</p>
   <p>The speaker is hopeful that in a few years, this home will be replaced with a large brick building which will be the pride of the Polish settlement in Brighton Park. The program was continued with musical selections, vocal and instrumental. Many choirs participated in the celebration. Among the many prominent people of Chicago, who attended was Mr. B. Hartnett, alderman of the 12th Ward. The celebration was a tremendous success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
