<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous - "<title level="a">Information from Polish Welfare Association of Chicago</title>", <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. II, No. 7,
<date when="1924-03">March 1924</date>, p. 5.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0876</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0876.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous - "<title level="a">Information from Polish Welfare Association of Chicago</title>", <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. II, No. 7,
<date when="1924-03">March 1924</date>, p. 5.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last officers' meeting of the Chicago Society, some one inquired as to what the present status was of the Polish Welfare Association.</p>
   <p>Since the Chicago Society gave the first impetus to the idea of organizing such an Association, and since it materially contributed to its support, the inquiry is proper and justified. Hence prompt information in reply thereto is gladly offered here.</p>
   <p>When the Association was organized some two years ago, its main object was to establish a central office in the downtown district with a paid corps of workers. It was therefore necessary to gather a fund of several thousand dollars for this purpose. To do this, it has taken considerable time. Furthermore, many circumstances and conditions arose from time to time which occasioned an unavoidable delay in the opening of such a bureau. However, despite constant discouragement the officers clung tenaciously to their object, undaunted in spirit and hope, until the proposed object was achieved.</p>
   <p>Last June, happily, things took a turn for the better. A definite plan and basis for operation was agreed upon, and sufficient funds were obtained to operate for at least one year. Accordingly, on November 15 of last year, quarters were opened at 308 N.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0877.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Michigan Blvd. with Mrs. T. Sakowska, creditably known among the Poles of Chicago for her many voluntary efforts in social and welfare service, as Superintendent, and Miss Zajaczkowska as Stenographer. The building in which we are housed contains the offices of sixteen American social and welfare agencies, such as the United States Charities, Infant Welfare, etc., and since our opening we have handled a number of juvenile and adult delinquent cases, as well as a number of general welfare cases of some importance.</p>
   <p>Several articles have appeared in the Polish Press concerning our opening and "doings". We have, however, refrained from writing or talking too much about the Association, lest we do injury to a firm and intelligent establishment of the Association. We do not wish to claim or promise too much at the start.</p>
   <p>By working quietly, cautiously, and effectively we hope to win the confidence of the English and Polish public, and hope thereby to have the results achieved speak for us. A stable and reliable foundation for a permanent existence will thus be laid.</p>
   <p>Financial support is necessary, but this we plan to secure by building up a reputation <pb facs="5423968_7_0878.jpg" n="3"/>for unbiased, impartial, honest, sincere, intelligent, prompt, reliable, constructive, and effective social service. To this end we aim to co-operate with the already existing agencies wherever and whenever possible; handle cases which other organizations do not provide for; and in cases handled by other, where some injustice has been done, help to rectify same.</p>
   <p>From our brief period of functioning, we have found that we are meeting a dire need, greater than we really can adequately cope with. So far the results are rather promising. If we but exercise patience and continue to support the Association morally and financially, the Association will become an indispensable agency in our Polish community, and its good service will become common knowledge.</p>
   <p>"By our good work the public shall know us."</p>
   <p>T.J. Szmergalski, Sec'y.,</p>
   <p>Polish Welfare Association of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
