<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-11-18">Nov. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Anniversary Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-11-18">Nov. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The society Star of Victory, Group 46 of the Polish Women's Alliance, celebrated its tenth anniversary on November 15, at J. Slowacki Hall. The celebration was a great success. The committee composed of Mrs. B. Malkiewicz, Mrs. M. Hojnacki, Mrs. A. Jankowski, Mrs. M. Szymanski, Mrs. S. Bosek, Mrs. F. Pawlak, and Mrs. L. Bradel showed that it knew how to work. Proof of this was in evidence last Sunday. The stage of Slowacki Hall had been turned into a magnificent garden of fresh flowers and palms. The program opened with a short and concise address by the president of the society, Mrs. K. Kwiatkowski, who invited the founders of the Star of Victory, Mrs. E. Budzinski, Mrs. E. Gurniak and Mrs. A. Wolgemuth, to come up on the stage. She also invited Mrs. A. Neuman, president of the Polish Women's Alliance, to be chairman of the program.</p>
   <p>Program of the Celebration</p>
   <p>(1) Music by Mr. W. Lagocki's orchestra.</p>
   <p>(2) Song by the singing and dramatic society, Wisla.</p>
   <p>(3) Report of the financial secretary, Mrs. W. Jankowski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0151.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(4) Address by Miss M. Baranowski.</p>
   <p>(5) Piano solo by Miss A. Hojnacki.</p>
   <p>(6) Vocal solo by Miss H. Jurkowski.</p>
   <p>(7) Address by Mrs. L. Wolowski, treasurer of the Polish Women's Alliance.</p>
   <p>(8) Song by the ladies' choir of Wisla.</p>
   <p>(9) Music by the orchestra.</p>
   <p>The speeches and musical numbers were applauded enthusiastically. In a word, the celebration was a success.</p>
   <p>After the program our ladies adjourned to the dining room where tables were ready, elaborately set for the so-called "coffee."</p>
   <p>The only unpleasantness for both the committee and the society Star of Victory was the fact that many members of the society ignored this celebration by not attending it. From the sister group, number 15 of this district, only six members attended, and this group has almost two hundred members. No celebration <pb facs="5423968_7_0152.jpg" n="3"/>can take place without misunderstanding and without our well-known "I".</p>
   <p>The report of the financial secretary disclosed the fact that the society Star of Victory has over 150 members and possesses over $1,000.</p>
   <p>Throughout its entire existence this society has taken active part in all national endeavors.</p>
   <p>The officers of this society are: Mrs. K. Kwiatkowski, president; Mrs. M. Hojnacki, first vice-president; Mrs. Dzierzawski, second vice-president; Mrs. L. Bradel, general secretary; Mrs W. Jankowski, financial secretary; Mrs. A. Gorski, treasurer; Mrs. W. Wutkowski, Mrs. M. Ciaciuch, and Mrs. A. Wagner of the advisory board.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
