<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-16">Mar. 16, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Help from the Poles of Chicago Acknowledged by Reverend Sebastyanski of Nebraska</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1392</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1392.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-16">Mar. 16, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">HELP FROM THE POLES OF CHICAGO ACKNOWLEDGED BY REVEREND SEBASTYANSKI OF NEBRASKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As has already been reported, $292 of the fund collected in Chicago during the past few weeks by Peter Kiolbassa for the destitute Poles of Nebraska has been sent to Reverend W. Sebastyanski, S. J., at Posen, Nebraska. Yesterday, Mr. Kiolbassa received a letter of acknowledgment from Reverend Sebastyanski which read as follows:</p>
   <p>"March 12, 1895.</p>
   <p>"'The undersigned attests that he has received from Peter Kiolbassa the sum of $292, which was immediately turned over to the Posen Parish committee.</p>
   <p>"'Reverend W. Sebastyanski, S. J.</p>
   <p>"'We have received the sum of $292 from Reverend Sebastyanski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1393.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"'Michael Mudloff, treasurer,</p>
   <p>"'Joseph Majejski, commissioner.'</p>
   <p>"My Dear Mr. Kiolbassa: In addition to enclosing the requested acknowledgment of the receipt of the sum of $292 which you, Mr. Kiolbassa, had sent to the poor Poles of the Posen Parish, and which was turned over to the parish committee, I wish to thank you personally from the bottom of my heart for your brotherly benevolence. I offer you my thanks, just as every countryman of yours who has been aided by your support thanks you. God bless you!</p>
   <p>"The money received was used for the purchase and distribution of the following products: 200 bushels of corn for sowing (at sixty cents a bushel), $120; 234 bushels of wheat for sowing (at sixty cents a bushel), $140; 100 bushels of oats for sowing (three dollars added), $35. The corn was divided (five or six bushels to a farmer) among thirty-five farmers; the wheat among fifteen farmers, about fifteen bushels to each; and the oats among seven farmers, <pb facs="5423968_7_1394.jpg" n="3"/>who received about fifteen bushels each.</p>
   <p>"If God wills it, I will celebrate a special Mass for the intention of all the kind donors whose names we have on record. At this Mass, those who have received assistance will offer a prayer of thanks to the kind Polish people of Chicago, and God will also be asked, through the intercession of St. Joseph, for further support in this day of great need.</p>
   <p>"Once again, God bless you!</p>
   <p>"In the name of the grateful parishioners, I remain,</p>
   <p>"Your obedient servant in Christ,</p>
   <p>"Reverend W. Sebastyanski, S. J."</p>
   <p>As is evidenced by this letter, the initial sum that has been sent to Nebraska <pb facs="5423968_7_1395.jpg" n="4"/>has only given partial relief to our unfortunate compatriots. More help and contributions are needed. Yesterday, Mr. Kiolbassa sent a second check for $220, drawn on the Milwaukee Avenue State Bank, to Reverend Sebastyanski. This brings the total that has been sent to our fellow countrymen in Nebraska to $512.</p>
   <p>More contributions, however, are necessary....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
