<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-12">Apr. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Seventh Semiannual Convention of the Central Polish Relief Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1048</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1048.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-12">Apr. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SEVENTH SEMIANNUAL CONVENTION OF THE CENTRAL POLISH RELIEF COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The seventh Semiannual Convention of the Central Polish Relief Committee closed yesterday. Due to the formation of the National Department the activities of the Committee have been reduced to relief work exclusively.</p>
   <p>There were many delegates at the convention. In addition to those listed yesterday there were: [Translators note: The names of those who were not Chicagoans are omitted in translation]....Mrs. M. Sakowski, Mrs. S. Jozwiak, F. Porzuczek, J. S. Zawilinski, secretary general of the Polish National Alliance, Z. Ulanowski, Mrs. Laudyn-Chrzanowski, M. Osuch, J. S. Konopa, and others.</p>
   <p>REPORTS OF THE OFFICERS</p>
   <p>Dr. F. F. Fronczak, second president of the Central Polish Relief Committee, was chairman of the convention, and Mr. H. Setmajer, secretary of the Central <pb facs="5423968_7_1049.jpg" n="2"/>Polish Relief Committee, acted as secretary.</p>
   <p>The convention accepted the reports of the officers and of the auditing commission, which examined all the financial books of the Relief Committee and reported that it found them in perfect order.</p>
   <p>The reports of the officers revealed that the generosity of our people was not decreasing, but, due to the formation of all sorts of provincial committees, these contributions were scattered, as the president and the secretary in their separate reports emphasized. The convention expressed the opinion of the general public by passing a motion that an effort be made to centralize the relief activities of the Central Polish Relief Committee. The officers of the Committee then made their reports.</p>
   <p>REPORT OF PRESIDENT T. M. HELINSKI</p>
   <p>"From the moment of the organization of the National Department the activities <pb facs="5423968_7_1050.jpg" n="3"/>of the Central Polish Relief Committee have been confined to the raising of funds for the purpose of bringing help to our brothers and sisters in Poland and in other countries to which they were forced to flee by horrors unheard of in the history of war.</p>
   <p>"Unfortunately the funds collected were not and are not sufficient to bring even partial relief to the poverty which has struck the greater part of the Polish nation as the result of the brutal actions of our three oppressors. The Executive Committee did everything in its power to collect the necessary funds, but it frequently met with indifference on the part of the people, even among the Poles, not to mention other nationalities supposedly friendly to the Poles.</p>
   <p>"This can be attributed, it seems, in the first place to the fact that the truly desperate conditions of the Polish country destroyed by this terrible war is too little known; because it is impossible to believe that our Polish people here in America, who are living in luxury in comparison with our brothers and sisters in Poland, could be indifferent in the face of the constant appeals made by <pb facs="5423968_7_1051.jpg" n="4"/>our Committee and by the Polish press. It is now our most important duty to rescue our brothers and sisters from death by starvation, because obviously our enemies, confident of their victory, want as few Poles as possible to survive on Polish soil.</p>
   <p>"A detailed report of the activities of the Central Polish Relief Committee since the last annual convention, as well as an itemized account of the income and disbursements, will be made to you by the secretary, treasurer, and the auditing commission.</p>
   <p>"I am not going to name the societies or individuals who distinguished themselves by their zeal in collecting funds. Let the knowledge that they have done their duty, and the prayers of the most unfortunate of those victims whom they have aided, be their most appropriate reward.</p>
   <p>"The work of the Central Polish Relief Committee has frequently been criticized by both friends and opponents. Since people in general are too inclined toward <pb facs="5423968_7_1052.jpg" n="5"/>criticism, the Executive Department willingly answered the various accusations and reproaches when these were made in good faith, or answered with facts, criticism which was intended to strengthen the activity of the Central Polish Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>"Arguments with opponents would be pointless because the collecting of money for our starving brothers and sisters would only meet with opposition from such Poles; for instead of having hearts they must have pieces of ice in their breasts.</p>
   <p>"The Executive Department is convinced that our Polish people here in America still do not sufficiently realize that only through united effort can we attain our goal, that in the struggle for our national existence and the inalienable rights of our nation, we should always and everywhere follow the motto: 'One for all, and all for one.' The effort to save a part of our people from death by starvation is surely a struggle for the existence of our entire nation.</p>
   <p>"The Executive Department is also convinced that we have little influence <pb facs="5423968_7_1053.jpg" n="6"/>and importance in this country, in spite of the fact that there are almost four million of us here. That which people of other nationalities and the government of the United States have done for our cause, we owe only to the sacrifice and indefatigable work of individuals.</p>
   <p>"When it comes to contributing, to sacrificing one's self for important matters, to carrying out tedious tasks, we always see practically the same willing individuals. Therefore, much hard work is still needed in order to make our people realize their duty toward the homeland. Much explaining and convincing is still needed to make the people realize that every Pole, man and woman, should contribute, if only the most modest amount, to the relief of our poverty-stricken and suffering brothers and sisters, victims of the war.</p>
   <p>"We still have the fault that, no matter what activity we undertake, we always seem to scatter our forces. Everyone wants everyone else to know immediately what this or that particular individual has done. Therefore, we lack the system and the freedom of movement which are so essential to the attainment of <pb facs="5423968_7_1054.jpg" n="7"/>successful results.</p>
   <p>"The Central Polish Relief Committee, in placing itself at the head of this relief activity, expected that all organizations, societies, unions, and even individuals would subject themselves to its orders and control. After all, this activity demands united effort, systematic collection of funds for a noble and sacred cause, where no one should be interested in publicity, but in the fulfillment of his sacred duty. Therefore it is necessary that the Central Polish Relief Committee as a whole always work at its undertakings in complete harmony, in order to set an example for all Polish people to follow.</p>
   <p>"Such united and harmonious work is absolutely necessary, because the poverty in our homeland is terrible, and we should exert all our efforts in order not to disappoint those who have placed their confidence in us.</p>
   <p>"In conclusion may I be permitted to express the hope that during this moment when the fate of our homeland is in the balance, the Semiannual Convention of <pb facs="5423968_7_1055.jpg" n="8"/>the Central Polish Relief Committee will come up to expectations and solve this problem, and will not disappoint the confidence which the Polish people have placed in it."</p>
   <p>REPORT OF THE SECRETARY</p>
   <p>The report of Secretary H. Setmajer is divided into two sections, administrative and financial. For the moment we are attaching the financial report, leaving the administrative report for tomorrow. [Translator's note: Here follows a long itemized report, the sum total of which is as follows:]</p>
   <p>Financial Statement</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Relief Fund Receipts</cell>
     <cell>$26,500.60</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Operating capital</cell>
     <cell>2,355.04</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash on hand March 1</cell>
     <cell>$28,855.64</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1056.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>[MONTHLY REPORT]</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Carried over from the operating</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>capital as of August 31, 1916</cell>
     <cell>$2,799.79</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Income as of April 1, 1917</cell>
     <cell>3,033,05</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$5,832.84</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Disbursements</cell>
     <cell>3,477.80</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$2,355.04</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>(Signed) K. Zychlinski, president,</p>
   <p>John S. Rybicki,</p>
   <p>Anna Neuman.</p>
   <p>REPORT OF THE AUDITING COMMISSION</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Rybicki presented the report of the auditing commission showing that the report of this commission was in complete harmony with the reports of the <pb facs="5423968_7_1057.jpg" n="10"/>treasurer, Mr. J. Magdziarz, and of the secretary. We will publish the complete report in another section.</p>
   <p>Mr. H. Setmajer read a report in the name of the re-emigration committee, showing that this matter should create greater interest among our emigres.</p>
   <p>Because the National Department will hold its meeting in a closed session, and because there will be several matters with which the members of the Central Polish Relief Committee should become acquainted, the secretary will read several excerpts from the report, relating particularly to finances, about which the readers will learn later from the report of the National Department.</p>
   <p>NEW BUSINESS</p>
   <p>The committees, called upon to make their reports, were not quite ready; therefore, the chairman took up new business. Various delegates took the floor explaining or making certain motions which the committee on motions will <pb facs="5423968_7_1058.jpg" n="11"/>present in its report. The important matter is to consolidate the activities of the Central Polish Relief Committee, to encourage the emigres who as a result of having previously been exposed to the agitation of the opponents of this work, frequently failed to respond to the needs and appeals coming from the homeland, as one would have expected. Nevertheless we cannot be reproached for being ungenerous with our efforts to help those suffering hunger and pain in the homeland.</p>
   <p>Open discussions were held until 12:30 P. M. when Reverend W. Zapala made a motion to increase the number of the members of the committee on motions, because of a very important communique which had just arrived from [Ignace J.] Paderewski, which had to be discussed and settled at once.</p>
   <p>The president appointed the following additional members to the committee on motions: J. F. Smulski, T. Jasiorkowski, Dr. Drobinski, Reverend T. Bona.</p>
   <p>A motion was then made and carried that the session be adjourned until 1:30 P. M., <pb facs="5423968_7_1059.jpg" n="12"/>when the committees would be ready to make their reports.</p>
   <p>AFTERNOON SESSION</p>
   <p>Chairman F. F. Fronczak opened the afternoon session at 2 P. M., calling on Secretary Setmajer to read the report of the Motion Committee, which was as follows:</p>
   <p>1. To try again to consolidate the relief activities of the Central Polish Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>2. To develop the press and organizational activities further by means of an appropriate number of agitators and by enlisting greater help from the press.</p>
   <p>3. That the Press Bureau of the National Department should send articles and communiques to the Polish papers in the United States for <pb facs="5423968_7_1060.jpg" n="13"/>publication.</p>
   <p>4. That the treasury centers remain and continue their work as heretofore, but that they make a report of all moneys sent out.</p>
   <p>5. That a request be sent to all the local committees to join and co-operate with the Central Polish Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>6. That financial reports be sent to all organizations, parishes and members of the Central Polish Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>7. That the reports of the secretary, treasurer, and financial commission be accepted.</p>
   <p>Those present at the meeting passed all the motions in the order in which they were made.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1061.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>Mr. H. Lokanski then read the following resolution of the Semiannual Convention of the Central Polish Relief Committee, in the name of the committee on resolutions:</p>
   <p>RESOLUTION OF THE SEVENTH SEMIANNUAL CONVENTION OF THE CENTRAL POLISH RELIEF COMMITTEE</p>
   <p>"In the midst of the titanic upheavals of the world today, new hope of happiness for humanity and of freedom for the nations which have been trampled upon by brutal feet is beginning to dawn. The Poles, most unjustly oppressed for centuries and most cruelly punished only because they wanted to uphold the banner of democracy and the rights of man, with tremendous emotion see in the flames of the world set afire by the war, The Stars and Stripes of the United States. In view of the fact that this flag is also the herald of our freedom, and of the great glory of the descendents of Washington's great country, we, the representatives of alliances of Polish immigrants in America, united in the Central Polish Relief Committee, at our convention held at Chicago, Illinois, <pb facs="5423968_7_1062.jpg" n="15"/>on April 11, 1917, express, as citizens of these United States, our unswerving loyalty to the President and to the Government of this Republic fighting for the rights of man, and our readiness to accept the burdens falling upon us as a result of this war.</p>
   <p>"As Poles, however, we urgently request that the President not only allow us to fulfill our duties toward this country as citizens, but also consider us a belligerent and allow us to fight shoulder to shoulder with the American Army as allies, granting us permission and help to raise an additional Polish Kosciusko Army, which could enter Poland and bring to the most unfortunate of nations freedom and independence, as a gift from the hands of the United States and its Allies; an army which would also spread the glory, generosity, and dignity of the United States throughout all the Slavic lands.</p>
   <p>"In the unshakable belief that the Government of the United States, seeking the freedom of nations, will accept our offer, and will look upon us as a nation which has never yielded its right to independence, we appeal to all Polish <pb facs="5423968_7_1063.jpg" n="16"/>organizations, alliances, and societies, which so far have remained outside of our organization, to join the Central Polish Relief Committee for the purpose of upholding our joint honor as a million-strong branch of the Polish nation, in order to give proof of our unity. We ask them to join either as individuals or as treasury centers, because at so critical a time as the present, in which the fate of our entire nation is held in the balance, only united effort can save us.</p>
   <p>"In the name of Poland, condemned by the merciless exigencies of war to death from starvation, we ask the Poles in America to double their generous efforts to save our brothers, sisters, fathers, and mothers in the homeland, since Poland can exist only so long as Polish people exist. Let future generations not condemn us for not helping when we could have helped those who died for us and our children.</p>
   <p>"For the efforts made so far we extend our sincerest gratitude to the organizations and societies centered in the Central Polish Relief Committee, <pb facs="5423968_7_1064.jpg" n="17"/>and to those noble sons of America who, either with money or friendly words in the press, or on the public rostrums, advocated Poland's existence or wanted to help her; God reward them or their children for it.</p>
   <p>"We express our deepest respect to President Wilson for his memorable stand on the Polish question in his address of January 22,1917, and we believe that the powerful Republic of the United States, having already become our champion, will support at the peace conference our just claims for war compensation for our country, which has been turned into a land of graves, ruins, and ashes, for the tears and horrible tortures suffered by millions of Polish people, who suffered although they committed no transgressions, and who in the past had always done good to others or had nothing but good intentions.</p>
   <p>"To those who, confused by the rapidly changing events, are afraid, and who continue to have attitudes which are not in harmony with the spirit of Poland and its traditions, we extend our hand in fraternal affection that, in the name of the good of the entire nation, in which there should not now be any <pb facs="5423968_7_1065.jpg" n="18"/>people standing apart, they will seize this hand and go along with us. Strong with the power of unity, and joined together by the mottoes of our forefathers, we will then build not a sectional, but a great, united, free and independent Polish republic.</p>
   <p>"Reverend Stanley Sobieniowski,</p>
   <p>"Stephen J. Napieralski,</p>
   <p>"Honorata B. Wolowski,</p>
   <p>"Joseph W. Stryiak,</p>
   <p>"Francis Zawadzki,</p>
   <p>"Henry Lokanski."</p>
   <p>The members at the meeting accepted this resolution by a rising vote.</p>
   <p>A motion was made to translate this resolution into English, and the committee on motions will see that this is done.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1066.jpg" n="19"/>
   <p>The session of the Central Polish Relief Committee was adjourned because the closed meeting of the National Department was to be held in the same hall.</p>
   <p>The convention was closed with the singing of "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
