<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vo1. XVIII,
<date when="1914-03-25">March 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Orphans in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Administrative Report in Regard to Polish Orphans to the Alliance of Guardians for Polish Orphans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vo1. XVIII,
<date when="1914-03-25">March 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ORPHANS IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Administrative Report in Regard to Polish Orphans To the Alliance of Guardians for Polish Orphans</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Summary'</p>
   <p>At annual meeting of Guardians for Polish Orphans, held on last Thursday of the month of February, at Chicago, Ill., a fairly good attendance of representatives attended the meeting, who understood the necessity of guarding homeless orphans in Chicago of which there is a big number.</p>
   <p>This cause is supported by all major Polish organizations. All those organizations are working heartily and mutually for the benefit of Polish orphans and for this cause only they intend to forget their parties and differences.</p>
   <p>After one year of time has elapsed on work for this institution at Norwood Park, Chicago, we have collected over $3,000, which was reported previously.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0588.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After all this is not enough. At present the administration of this alliance is working on a plan which if brought to life, not only will regulate the normal functions, but also will help to achieve other fruit bearing necessities.</p>
   <p>This plan will enable us to expend our activities among merchants and industrialists. Knowing that not every one of us could spare his time freely, we have created honorary memberships.</p>
   <p>For the payment of one dollar annually every Polish man and woman, feeling the necessity of Polish Guardianship for Polish Orphans, will become an honorary member in the Alliance. With this mutual understanding we will create warm lodgings, clothing, and enlightenment for Polish orphans. By this we hope that all Polish citizens and merchants will become honorary members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
