<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 2,
<date when="1919-01-08">Jan. 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal of the Administrave Council of the Polish National Department</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0964</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10&#9;"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0964.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10	</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 2,
<date when="1919-01-08">Jan. 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL OF THE ADMINISTRAVE COUNCIL OF THE POLISH NATIONAL DEPARTMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Countrymen: As a result of efforts undertaken by the National Department, the United States Food Administration has agreed to give up food stored on ships in New York, amounting to $7,000, to save Poland from a hunger disaster.</p>
   <p>The Food Administration does not have, however, the necessary funds so valuable to Poland, and requests from the National Department the laying down of two million dollars during a time when, on the funds being collected, there are gravitating important obligations contracted in the presence of the American Red Cross in exchange for the help to the families of our soldiers in view of the Polish army, the preparation for the approaching congressional deliberations, and the activities for uniting Polish lands, for which cause Ignace J. Paderewski has already left and is acting in this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0965.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Food for Poland is the first and most important necessity and we must benefit from the offer of the Food Administration. A telegram in this matter from Mr. Walcott is as follows:</p>
   <p>Washington, D. C., Dec. 31, 1918</p>
   <p>John F. Smulski, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>We must commence the relief of Poland in a broad practical way. We must insure Hoover's enthusiastic support in Europe by strong concentrated action. We have a seven-thousand-ton ship ready in New York, but no funds. This first shipload will cost approximately two million dollars according to Hoover's table requirement for foodstuffs. You must meet me in Washington, Friday, to get relief started. Situation critical. No time can be lost.</p>
   <p>F. C. Walcott.</p>
   <p>After receiving this telegram the administrative council of the National Department resolved to continue without delay toward putting through this matter, and for this mission the president of the council left on Wednesday <pb facs="5423968_7_0966.jpg" n="3"/>, New Year's Day, for New York.</p>
   <p>Simultaneously, the council decreed to make an appeal to the entire emigration for immediate help. This is a matter which should be the test of love for our Fatherland. If we do not assure food for Poland, we will give her up as prey to the Germans and bolsheviks and will destroy the so heavily fought out foundations of our independent national welfare.</p>
   <p>We implore speed!</p>
   <p>We appeal to our organizations, to the clergy, to the parishes, to the national and merchant associations: Help immediately!</p>
   <p>He who stands at the head of any union, parish or society, let him call together his brothers, his parishioners, his colleagues and let him endeavor to get immediate gifts for the ten million dollar fund.</p>
   <p>Poland is in the greatest danger and if we do not help ourselves, no <pb facs="5423968_7_0967.jpg" n="4"/>one else will help us.</p>
   <p>We remind everyone that there will yet be necessary, in a very short while, shipments of more food to Poland and apparently more million dollar funds for the purpose.</p>
   <p>You owe it, then, to endeavor to help collect as soon as possible the ten million dollars for this cause and that without delay.</p>
   <p>Let us save the Fatherland!</p>
   <p>In the name of the National Department. (Signed) John F. Smulski, president of the Administrative Council; Dr. Adam Szwajkart, Secretary; N. L. Piotrowski, treasurer and director for collecting the ten million dollar fund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
