<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-30">Sept. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter to All Polish Organizations, Civic Committees, Societies, and Clubs Collecting Funds for the Polish National Cause</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0974</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0974.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-30">Sept. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER TO ALL POLISH ORGANIZATIONS, CIVIC COMMITTEES, SOCIETIES, AND CLUBS COLLECTING FUNDS FOR THE POLISH NATIONAL CAUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Beginning on October 1, 1918, the Polish National Department will issue credentials to all organizations, civic committees, clubs, and societies, wishing to collect funds for the Polish cause. The Polish National Department will also register in its records all groups that receive the aforesaid credentials. All groups of that kind that wish to participate in collecting such funds are urged to come for their credentials immediately. Only one group in one parish or circuit can receive such credentials, and in any place in which several exist they must come to a mutual understanding and unite in one group before making application for credentials.</p>
   <p>Groups in applying for their credentials should also list the names and addresses <pb facs="5423968_7_0975.jpg" n="2"/>of those who will collect such funds in their particular territory. These individuals will also be recorded by the Polish National Department, and each one will receive an identification card with his or her name, the seal of the Polish National Department, and the signatures of the president and the secretary of the Committee and of the local pastor.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Department has ordered special identification cards and stamps to certify to the amount donated by each contributor. In that way it is hoped that a uniform system of recording contributions and collecting funds can be established. Until the time when these identification cards and stamps are prepared and sent out, all collections made thus far are to be certified in the usual way. The collector should not fail to mention, however, that the receipt given to the donor will later be exchanged for stamps.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Department has on hand prepared speeches appropriate for the occassion. These can be obtained upon request by those interested. A self-<pb facs="5423968_7_0976.jpg" n="3"/>addressed stamped enevelope should be inclosed, together with a request for such prepared speeches. The purpose of this last request is to defray mailing expense and to save time in addressing enevelopes. Address all communications to:</p>
   <p>The Polish National Department</p>
   <p>1309 North Ashland Avenue</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
