<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-18">Dec. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Patriotic Organization Gives Entertainment for the Benefit of the Poor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-18">Dec. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH PATRIOTIC ORGANIZATION GIVES ENTERTAINMENT FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE POOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Patriotic Organization held an entertainment last night, Sunday, December 17, in the school hall on Bradley Street. The program, prepared hurriedly and at the last moment, pleased the audience immensely. A great crowd assembled and all numbers on the program were tumultuously applauded.</p>
   <p>Mr. Peter Ligman opened the night's program by calling on Mr. John Arkuszewski to act as chairman and Mr. Ignace Kowalski as secretary.</p>
   <p>The first number, an overture, "Tancreda," by the Polish West Side Music Band directed by Mr. Hensl, was rendered in a truly artistic manner. The members of this band offered their services for the benefit of the poor without remuneration and thereby deserve praise not only as good musicians but also as dutiful citizens.</p>
   <p>After two songs beautifully rendered by the Polish Male Choir of St. Cecilia, Mr. S. Zahajkiewicz spoke clearly and earnestly. He reminded the audience of the <pb facs="5423968_7_1457.jpg" n="2"/>first entertainment given by the Patriotic Organization and gave a summary of its activities. He then urged all Poles to co-operate for the good of the fatherland. He warned against nihilistic agitators and then fervently exhorted the audience assembled to action, to work, to fight for our religion and our country. He concluded with a four-line verse from the Polish poem "Odyniec":</p>
   <p>"Know ye well and judge yourselves,</p>
   <p>He who wishes to be a faithful son of Poland</p>
   <p>Must seek light and strength from heaven,</p>
   <p>A mother in the native land and honor</p>
   <p>father in God." (Translator's note: a free translation of the verse).</p>
   <p>Mr. Zahajkiewicz's speech was so beautiful that it is worth while to give it at length and quote some of the passages. On account of lack of space, we shall do so tomorrow.</p>
   <p>The Polish Young Ladies' Choir then sang a medley beautifully, after which the <pb facs="5423968_7_1458.jpg" n="3"/>St. Stanislaus Turners gave a wonderful exhibition of gymnastics and were rewarded with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>Then Reverend Eugene Siedlaczek read an interesting and very educational treatise as to how those possessing more education, morals, and finances can help to elevate others less gifted with knowledge, morals, or material resources. The theme, as we see, is very important and intriguing. We cannot do justice to it in our short report, so, with the author's permission, we will review it more thoroughly and cite a few of the most important passages in the near future in the Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch sang a solo, as usual, magnificently.</p>
   <p>"Polish Flowers," a medley of Polish melodies played by the orchestra, evoked the wildest enthusiasm and tremendous applause. The singing by the Ladies' Choir of St. Cecilia was likewise applauded.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1459.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Adam Szwajkart recited a poem entitled "Before The Court," and Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch and Mr. Andrew J. Kwasigroch sang a duet which was also applauded tumultuously.</p>
   <p>Next came exercises by the Turner Society No. 2 on the bars and rings that astonished everybody. Directed by their brave instructor, the turners did marvelous stunts. During their entire exercises, the applause was deafening. This was really the most wonderful number on the program.</p>
   <p>Due to the late hour, Reverend Vincent Barzynski was not able to speak at great length, but he briefly thanked the audience for a good deed well done.</p>
   <p>The proceeds will undoubtedly be quite large and the poor will benefit by it greatly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
