<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-02-21">Feb. 21, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">The Alliance of Polish Catholic Youth</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-02-21">Feb. 21, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">THE ALLIANCE OF POLISH CATHOLIC YOUTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The delegates representing the four Polish youth societies belonging to the Polish Roman Catholic Union held their second meeting last Sunday. The four societies represented were the Polish Patriotic Educational Youth Society, the St. Casimir's Society, the St. Stanislaus Cadets [Society], and the Youth Society of the Patriotic Organization, from St. John Cantius parish.</p>
   <p>Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek presided at the meeting, and Francis P. Danisch acted as secretary.</p>
   <p>Besides the delegates, there were also present Mr. Clement Bielinski and Mr. Boleslaus Klarkowski, representatives of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bielinski delivered a short address, in which he urged the delegates to <pb facs="5423968_7_0298.jpg" n="2"/>persevere in the good work that had been started. He gave a short history of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, pointing out the great hardships encountered by this organization during its early days. The speaker, who is experienced in organizational matters, gave the delegates some good advice, which may help the Alliance of Polish Catholic Youth in its development.</p>
   <p>Subsequently, the constitution of the new organization was discussed. It was agreed that the official name of the organization would be Alliance of Polish Catholic Youth in the United States of North America. The emblem of the organization, to be worn by its members, consists of a pin representing a Polish eagle on a crimson field.</p>
   <p>The aims of the Alliance of Polish Catholic Youth have already been announced. At this meeting, however, it was decided that, at the death of a member, the Alliance of Polish Catholic Youth would pay a regular death benefit of $250, <pb facs="5423968_7_0299.jpg" n="3"/>plus $75 for funeral expenses.</p>
   <p>The question of monthly dues was then taken up by Klarkowski, Bielinski, Wieckowski, Danisch, Napieralski, Chabowski, Jarzembowski, and Paszkiewicz. After a long discussion it was agreed that the monthly dues would be ten cents for the first six months, during which time no death benefit would be paid. After the first six months the payment of dues will be discontinued, and the death benefit fund will be obtained by assessing each member equally in order to raise the sum of two hundred and fifty dollars.</p>
   <p>The initiation fee will be ten cents.</p>
   <p>The Alliance of Polish Catholic Youth will try to arrange with the Polish Roman Catholic Union for a free transfer card, so that members reaching the age of thirty years may have their death benefits transferred to the Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0300.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It was also decided that the Constitutional Committee should prepare the constitution of the organization as soon as possible, and that this constitution should be published in the Polish press, together with an appeal to all Polish youth societies.</p>
   <p>The Constitutional Committee will meet next Sunday at the Polish hall on Bradley Street, and any youth society desiring to join the Alliance of Polish Catholic Youth is welcome to offer its suggestions.</p>
   <p>Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek closed the meeting with a prayer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
