<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-19">Mar. 19, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Report of the Polish Roman Catholic Union for the Second Quarter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-19">Mar. 19, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION FOR THE SECOND QUARTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Those who have been spreading scandal about the Polish Roman Catholic Union under the protection of the Sacred Heart of Jesus, and who have so often sung hymns of sorrow for this old and brave organization, can now be assured that, in spite of their intrigues and withdrawals, the Union improves each day.</p>
   <p>Let them only glance at the report published by the administration of the Polish Roman Catholic Union for the second quarter after the convention, in the Wiara I Ojczyzna (Faith and Fatherland).</p>
   <p>This quarter includes the time from December 1, 1895, to March 1, 1896.</p>
   <p>On December 1, 1895, the assets amounted to $1,698.50. During the quarter, the sum of $23,131.66 was received, making the total $24,830.16.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0257.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The expenditures during this quarter amounted to $20,993.93.</p>
   <p>On March 1, 1896, the net balance in the treasury was $3,836.23.</p>
   <p>Hence, during the quarter the cash assets of the organization were increased by over two thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>During the quarter the sum of $12,600 was paid out to widows as death benefits, and $6,600 to widowers. The total paid out was $19,200. In other words, the sum of almost twenty thousand dollars was paid out in forty-three death benefits.</p>
   <p>So much about the financial condition of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, which is improving every day.</p>
   <p>Now a few words about the number of members:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0258.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We note from the report, that the Polish Roman Catholic Union gained five new societies during the last quarter--four of them from Pennsylvania and one from Chicago.</p>
   <p>The membership statistics are as follows:</p>
   <p>On December 1, 1895, the membership was 7,960. New members during the quarter were 365. Members suspended were 240. The membership on March 1, 1895 was 8,085. In other words, the membership of the Union was increased by 125.</p>
   <p>These figures speak for themselves. The death benefits have been paid. The assets are increasing. The membership is gaining. The books are kept in the best possible manner, as is testified by the auditing committee.</p>
   <p>It is perfectly proper, therefore, that the trustees should publish the following statement:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0259.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"......We are convinced that the Polish Roman Catholic Union is financially and morally stronger now than ever before, despite the disaffection of the brothers from Milwaukee Avenue. Neither their withdrawals, nor any intrigues or plots of the papers inimical to us, were able to stem the growth and success of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. It was mainly due to the conscientiousness of the officers of this organization, and to the energy and eagerness of President Clemens J. Bielinski, that the Polish Roman Catholic Union has weathered the storm and is growing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
