<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-04">Feb. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Formation of Civic Clubs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0811</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0811.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-04">Feb. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FORMATION OF CIVIC CLUBS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very important meeting took place on January 31, 1915, at the Casimir Pulaski Civic Club in Holy Trinity Parish Hall. The purpose of this meeting was to unite all Polish clubs of all parishes, where such exist, by creating a central body of the delegates. The following clubs were represented at this meeting: Casimir Pulaski Club of Holy Trinity Parish and vicinity, Messrs. Peter Nawrot, W. Wieczorowski, M. Wojciechowski, and Adalbert J. Danisch; Thaddeus Kosciusko Club from St. Stanislaus Kostka's Parish and vicinity, Mr. Stanley Zywicki; Sobieski Club from Holy Innocence Parish and vicinity, Messrs. John Imbierski and W. Skdczylas; King Casimir The Great Club from St. Helen's Parish and vicinity, Mr. W. Schmatloch, King Walter Jagello Club from Cragin, Messrs. Frank Michola and Thomas Bandur; Casimir Pulaski Club from the South Side of Chicago, Mr. John Piergalski; Thaddeus Kosciusko Club from St. Venceslaus Parish and vicinity, Messrs. A. Kirstein, Walter Palewski, and S. Wojalewicz.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0812.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The congregated delegates unanimously consented to have the idea coming from the Casimir Pulaski Club in Holy Trinity Parish go into effect in the shortest time possible. Immediate steps were, therefore, taken in that direction. A temporary chairman, in the person of Mr. Adalbert Danisch, was selected, and Mr. A. Kerstein was chosen as temporary secretary.</p>
   <p>After a brief but enthusiastic discussion of propositions presented by the committee which called the meeting, it was decided unanimously to call a meeting for this purpose within two weeks, that is, on Sunday, February 14, 1915. The meeting will take place in the hall where the Thaddeus Kosciusko Club of St. Stanislaus Kostka's Parish conducts its civic affairs. It is anticipated, and sincerely desired, that all clubs which were not present at the meeting of January 31 will not fail to send their representatives but will unite in such a worthy work.</p>
   <p>Adalbert J. Danisch, President pro tempore</p>
   <p>A. Kerstein, Secretary pro tempore</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
