<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-25">Mar. 25, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Poles Offer Assistance to Needy Greek-Catholics Abroad</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-25">Mar. 25, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO POLES OFFER ASSISTANCE TO NEEDY GREEK-CATHOLICS ABROAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Over one hundred dollars has been contributed by Chicago Poles toward a fund to help the unfortunate Polish Greek Catholics in the province of Orenburg, which is under control of the Tsar. Poles in other cities have joined this drive, and twenty-five dollars came from Milwaukee. Donations from Pittsburg, Winona, and other cities were also received. At the present time one hundred and sixty-two dollars has been contributed.</p>
   <p>One hundred and fifty dollars (350 guldens) has been sent to Rt. Rev. Chotkowski at Cracow. Some doubt has been expressed whether any of this money will reach the famine stricken in the Province of Orenburg.</p>
   <p>Because of very poor crops, not to mention the unbearable demands of the Russian government upon religious groups, this section of the country has suffered severely, and consequently, a plea has been made to the followers <pb facs="5423968_7_1523.jpg" n="2"/>of the faith in America, a plea that has been heeded by some of these groups. W. Smulski, editor of the Catholic Gazette, 565 Noble Street, is sponsoring the drive.</p>
   <p>The work to raise the funds is being carried out in a quiet and orderly manner. The methods used are not like those of some millionaires in America, who amidst pomp announce that they have taken the interest of the famine stricken Russians at heart and have sent them foodstuffs. Their generosity is heralded by the press all over the world.</p>
   <p>This drive, however, is being carried out by various prominent people and sympathizers of the faith. No great sums are asked; only a mere ten cents. These donations in all probability will do more good and reach more needy persons than the larger ones, because they will go directly to the ones in need.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
