<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-11-19">Nov. 19, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Hospital Benevolent Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0437</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0437.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-11-19">Nov. 19, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH HOSPITAL BENEVOLENT SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second meeting of the Polish Hospital Benevolent Society was held at the Holy Family of Nazareth Home on Sunday, November 14, The reading of the constitution was postponed until the next meeting in December, because Reverend Gieburowski, who had been entrusted with its compilation, had been unable to complete the work on time due to his extra duties during the mission at Saint Stanislaus Kostka Church. However, the priest was on hand to tell of the duties of this new organization, and he urged all members to spread word of the society's purposes throughout all Polish parishes of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The following women have joined the ranks of this spirited group:</p>
   <p>[Countess] Helen Chlapowska, [Mme. Modjeska], Felicia Modrzejewska, Anne Klarkowska, Anne Korzeniowska, M. H. Lebkowska, H. Xelowska, Helen Stobiecka, Magdalene Machek, Genevieve Zolkowska, Michalina Makarska, Leokadya Ciszewska, Theodore Piotrowska, Theresa Piotrowska, Rosalie Ostrowska, Antoinette Sergot, Agatha Gajewska, <pb facs="5423968_7_0438.jpg" n="2"/>Mary Schultz, and H. Wojnicka.</p>
   <p>Also, Catherine Rozmarynowska, J. Orzechowska, Juliana Szultz, Anne Wejna, Mary Mayen, Anastasia Rehbein, Catherine Rehbein, Marianne Rehbein, Anne Wisniewska, Frances Wisniewska, Veronica Chrapkowska, Bridget Kucharska, Frances Krolik, Apolania Walkowiak, Elisabeth Wierzba, Agnes Szazak, Catherine Ciscewska, Teofila Sniegocka, and Francis Smolinska.</p>
   <p>All new members pledged to get new recruits from among their circles and to have them attend the next meeting to be held on the second Sunday of December, that is December 12, at 2 P.M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
