<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-04-09">Apr. 9, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">A Letter of Thanks from Nebraska for Contributions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1375</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1375.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-04-09">Apr. 9, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">A LETTER OF THANKS FROM NEBRASKA FOR CONTRIBUTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Peter Kiolbassa received the following letter yesterday:</p>
   <p>"Posen-Farwell, Nebraska</p>
   <p>April 6, 1895</p>
   <p>"My dear Mr. Kiolbassa:</p>
   <p>"The undersigned wishes to acknowledge the receipt of $435 from you on April 5, and with your permission I have distributed it as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>"1. To the Poles in Elba (Howard County, Nebraska),</cell>
     <cell>$100.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"2. To the Poles in Chojnicach (Howard and Sherman counties),</cell>
     <cell>$167.50.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"3. To the Poles in Posen (Howard and Sherman counties),</cell>
     <cell>$167.50.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1376.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Total distributed, $435.</p>
   <p>"Although I say that I acknowledge receipt of this money, I cannot thank you enough, because only God can reward those who have so generously contributed toward the succor of our destitute Poles in Nebraska.</p>
   <p>"In the name of our Polish colonies in Posen, Chojnicach and Elba, I wish to extend thanks to the brothers Edward and John Reszke: May you sing long with God, and with your happy Polish hearts sing and comfort the Polish spirit in the world at large, and sing out the early freedom of our country! (sic)</p>
   <p>"Sincere thanks are sent to you, our renowned Miss Mira Heller! you are accustomed to applause and flowers, but a long distance separates us, and then, too, we have had no flowers for the past two years--they have become sere in the fields of Nebraska. Yet you have been able to dry some of our tears of <pb facs="5423968_7_1377.jpg" n="3"/>misfortune. Our tears of gratitude to you will never dry!</p>
   <p>"Thanks are offered to the kind Polish clergy and parishioners of Chicago. It is pleasant to know that you have not forgotten the one who took part in your missions, especially at St. Stanislaus Kostka, St. Adalbert, St. Mary of Perpetual Help, and St. Michael Archangel parishes.</p>
   <p>"And to you, Mr. Kiolbassa, thanks are extended for your sacrifice of time and efforts in making these contributions for our poor in Nebraska possible.</p>
   <p>"Yesterday I celebrated a mass and besought God for health and blessing for you [Mr. Kiolbassa] and all the kind donors.</p>
   <p>"Familiar with your kind heart, I wish to make one more request: please send me photographs of the Reszke brothers and Miss Heller, so that my parishioners <pb facs="5423968_7_1378.jpg" n="4"/>can see their kind benefactors through this medium.</p>
   <p>"Once more I repeat, God bless you all, kind and generous donors!</p>
   <p>"May God favor and protect the Polish people of Chicago!</p>
   <p>Your servant in Christ,</p>
   <p>Reverend W. Sebastyanski, S. J.</p>
   <p>pastor of Posen and Polish missionary"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
