<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-07">Dec. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Polish National Alliance Calendar for the Year 1911</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0206</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0206.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-07">Dec. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE CALENDAR FOR THE YEAR 1911</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second consecutive calendar of the Polish National Alliance has already been printed. It is a beautifully printed book of nearly two hundred pages, containing much priceless information. The character of the calendar for the year 1911 is more informational than literary, although there is no lack of the literary element. The index shows the book to contain more than two hundred articles, each of which might be described as long or short statistical and educational comment. This book is very interesting and very useful. The information contained in it has permanent value, and hence everyone is urged to obtain it.</p>
   <p>In the literary section the reader will note a detailed enumeration, based upon official figures, of the number of Poles in the world and where they live. Then there is an interesting article on the first Polish National Congress at <pb facs="5423968_7_0207.jpg" n="2"/>Washington, written by Dr. K. Zurawski.</p>
   <p>Following this, there is an excellent article on the Polish Falcons organization, containing a history of the origin of the Falcon movement in Poland.</p>
   <p>The calendar then makes extensive mention of some of the great sons and daughters of the Polish nation. Thus we see particular attention given to such outstanding figures as Mmes. Orzeskowa and Konopnicka, as well as the great composer pianist Chopin. Extensive is the section dedicated to women. Such articles as "Polish Womanhood of the Past," "What Is The Goal Of The Womens' Movement," "Woman Suffrage," and "Home Management" are worthy of the attention of every woman organized under the banner of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>It is impossible to enumerate here all the articles contained in the calendar. We mention here only a well-written article on "Constitutions," to which is added a verbatim translation of the Constitution of the United States.</p>
   <p>Relative to educational information, of which there is an immeasurable amount, <pb facs="5423968_7_0208.jpg" n="3"/>we recommend primarily the one entitled "The History of Poland in a Thousand Words." It is worthwhile to learn it word for word. Then there is a brief description of all the nations of the world a section on trade, commerce and agriculture, a table of weights and coins, general information concerning astronomy and geometry, dietetics in figures, that is, an educative enumeration of the quality and the quantity of food necessary for man to maintain life and strength, a list of a hundred chemical compounds used most frequently in agriculture and commerce, and many other sections too numerous to mention.</p>
   <p>Of the Polish National Alliance there is less written in the calendar of 1911 than in that of the preceding year. This subject was treated very extensively in last year's book and the material presented there possesses the same value today.</p>
   <p>Instead, particular attention is called to the table representing the growth of the Polish National Alliance. This summary shows that the organization, on <pb facs="5423968_7_0209.jpg" n="4"/>November 1, 1910, numbered 70,195 members, and had an estate of over $1,000,000. From the beginning of the Alliance's existence to November 1, 1910, 6,278 members died, and the organization has paid their families $3,658,000 in death benefits. This is an excellent amount to be amassed by a handful of Polish people for so lofty a purpose as aiding widows and orphans in the greatest misfortune. Let these empty-heads who, for inexplicable reasons, scoff at the Alliance insurance take note and pause over these three million dollars.</p>
   <p>But our Alliance brethren did not deposit their hard-earned money for insurance purposes only. The Polish National Alliance has paid out $248,472 for welfare and educational purposes. In view of the fact that this organization began to support these projects regularly in 1899, the whole sum of a quarter of a million dollars annually has been allotted to this purpose in a period of eleven years. Thus it is evident what well-organized people can accomplish with but a few cents per month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0210.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Particulary worthy of notice is the recent rapid growth of the assets of the Alliance. In the year 1890, that is, ten years after the founding of the Polish National Alliance, the organization had a total capital of $1,444. In 1900 it already had $100,000; in 1910, over a $1,000,000. The rate of increase has been particularly great in the past three years, after the adoption of a graduated scale of assessments. For the year 1908, there was a flow of $200,000 into the organization; and in 1910, nearly $300,000.</p>
   <p>Let no one think that a large capital is unnecessary to an organization as great as the Polish National Alliance. This capital is an assurance of death benefits, that is, proof that people can safely insure themselves in the Alliance. No catastrophe, no unforeseen increase in mortality in one year will make an organization totter which knows how to amass a reserve during normal times and to administer it adequately.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
