<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 20,
<date when="1915-05-19">May 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Singing Contest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1125</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1125.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 20,
<date when="1915-05-19">May 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">SINGING CONTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our societies in Chicago have received an announcement from the head office of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, urging them to take an active part in an international singing contest which will take place June 13th instant. The net profits are to go for the cause of the war victims in Poland. The imploring hands of the oppressed Fatherland, going at the present time through an unheard of fate among civilized people, like hands in misfortune, are stretching in our direction. The groan of our poor mother reaches us with the breath of the oceanic wind and fills us with its terror from head to foot. She cries! She is grieving over the destruction of her children, over the mass murders which are being perpetrated by satraps in the present international war!</p>
   <p>Which one of us does not understand accurately this war, so terrible in its effects? The whole world is looking with amazement and aversion upon this slaughter, but without council or unwilling, does not care <pb facs="5423968_7_1126.jpg" n="2"/>to get mixed up to end these bloody bouts. It looks therefore like a long drawn out war, where without question the Polish nation will be most harmed. And these harms will be irreparable, financially will run into millions, and never will be recompensed by the people.</p>
   <p>For this reason we must act, the more because the freedom of all activity is our participation.</p>
   <p>Coming from this supposition the "Chor Filaretow," (Filaret Choir), resolved to collect funds on a large scale and transmit such to our suffering countrymen touched by the horrors of war. These funds can be acquired by staging an international singing contest, which will take place on June 13 at Riverview Park. Eighteen nationalities living in Chicago and surrounding territory will participate. Because of this we expect that a colossal participation will be taken by all the Poles in America and Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1127.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>All the Polish organizations in our city are cooperating with the Filaret Choir. The officers of all these organizations have resolved to restrain their groups from giving any picnics or other forms of entertainment on this day, and we, from ourselves, once more renew our plea and plead that not one brother or sister of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union should be missing, that we should all collectively participate.</p>
   <p>The officers of the Union ask that the members bring as many tickets as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
