<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-05">May 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A Letter of Thanks (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-05">May 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A LETTER OF THANKS (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On May 3, a letter was received from Rev. Dr. Chotkowski, guardian of the Polish-Russian Catholics, expressing thanks for the first contributions. It reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Rt. Rev. Fr. Constatine Domagalski</p>
   <p>Editor of Wiara I Ojczyzna</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1514.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>My dear Rt. Rev. Fr. Domagalski:</p>
   <p>"Your generous and timely letter, that included a check for one hundred and fifty dollars, has been received. The check has been redeemed at the bank of Blau and Epstein, in Krakow. This money, donated by kindly Polish people in America and collected by W. Smulski for the aid of exiled Catholics on the Orenberg province, has been Gods answer to my prayers. Words cannot express my appreciation. I can only say thank you and God bless you, generous Father. These words express the feelings of the unfortunate exiles, who have been flung upon the barren fields of Orenberg because of their religious beliefs. They are outstanding examples of martyrs who have not bowed to the spreading growth of godless-ness of the present century.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1515.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"At one time, they protected the flag of Christianity in the field of battle against the barbarism of the East. Today, although the Western boundaries have been broken by this barbarism, our people are showing the world how to be faithful and loyal to the principles of the church. This money, that has spanned the great Alantic ocean and which will be sent past the rugged Ural mountains to our exiles, will be ample reward for their persecutions. This Christian deed definitely shows that there still flows a kindly feeling for our brothers and our neighbors.</p>
   <p>"May God repay you, kind friends, for your gracious generosity! When I send this money to your exiled brothers I will inform them from whom it came. Their prayers have been truly answered. God never forgets his children!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1516.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Please accept my sincere, humble thanks.</p>
   <p>Rev. Dr. Chotkowski</p>
   <p>Krakow, April 18, 1892."</p>
   <p>Let this beautiful and tender letter from Rev. Dr. Chotkowski be a symbol of thanks for the contributions received and a plea for further donations We are knocking upon the portals of the large parishes of Detroit, Buffalo, Pittsburgh, St. Paul, and Minneapolis for help. Every penny will be gladly welcomed, for each penny may wipe a sad tear away from the eyes of our unfortunate brothers. Every cent will be marked in the book of life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1517.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Four series of checks have thus far been sent to the kind priest in Krakow. Besides this, many priests and private individuals have sent personal checks direct to Krakow. The letter received from Rev. Dr. Chotkowski is the first of its kind.</p>
   <p>The figures below show in what amounts checks have been sent to Europe. The money came from various parts of the country. For once the antagonistic Polish papers, including the Zgoda, forgot their differences and solicited and contributed toward this cause.</p>
   <p>The Gazeth Katolicka (Catholic Gazette) and Wiara I Ojczyzna, official representatives of the drive, under the direction of Father Domagalski, have sent the following sums to Rev. Dr. Chotkowski:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1518.jpg" n="6"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1. March 24,</cell>
     <cell>$150</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2. April 7,</cell>
     <cell>300</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>3. April 15,</cell>
     <cell>300</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>4. April 27,</cell>
     <cell>300</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Polish Gazette,</cell>
     <cell>300</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Niedziela (Sunday), of Detroit</cell>
     <cell>50</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1519.jpg" n="7"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Wiarus,</cell>
     <cell>$50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Polish Courier, of Milwaukee,</cell>
     <cell>40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Fr. H. Gulski, of Milwaukee,</cell>
     <cell>102</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Father Gorski,</cell>
     <cell>151</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>St. Bruno's Society, of Milwaukee,</cell>
     <cell>38</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Father Grabowski, of La Salle,</cell>
     <cell>80</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Committee of The Catholic Gazette and Wiara I Ojczyzna,</cell>
     <cell>100</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$1,911 (sic).</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1520.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the total amount of money that has been donated by our kind people in America and sent to Krakow to aid the poor Polish-Russian Catholics. These generous contributions are further proof of our love for our countrymen and our religion. They definitely prove the generosity of our people. They also show that the Polish people take interest and spread benevolence whenever they see a need for it. The Polish people have always been willing to share their last morsel and their last penny for just causes. This laudable gesture truly shows the noble character of our people. We have the fondest hopes that our people, as these gifts show, will never veer from the path of just patriotism and religion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
