<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. Jos. Trygar</title>, district Commander of the Polish Army Veterans Association, 1239 N. Wood St., Chicago, Ill., by Thos. Nowacki,
<date when="1937-05-06">May 6, 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0781</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0781.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. Jos. Trygar</title>, district Commander of the Polish Army Veterans Association, 1239 N. Wood St., Chicago, Ill., by Thos. Nowacki,
<date when="1937-05-06">May 6, 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This Association was organized in 1920, after the soldiers returned from Europe. The members of the Association are former volunteers of the Polish army recruited in the United States among the Poles who were born either in "Austrian" or "German" Poland and as the so-called alien enemies, were barred from enlistment in the U. S. army.</p>
   <p>There are 1,200 veterans belonging to the Association in Chicago, grouped in fourteen posts. The Chicago district of the Polish Army Veterans Association owns a large building, located at 1239 N. Wood St. worth about $25,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0782.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The principal aim of the Association is to help the sick and aged Polish veterans who either on account of injuries suffered in the war or because of old age are not able to support themselves.</p>
   <p>Since 1929 there have been twenty five invalid veterans staying in the Polish army veterans' home, getting room and board clothing and medical attention. One third of the veterans have been there since 1929.</p>
   <p>Ten of which are between the ages of forty and sixty-five years. In order to raise funds the Association gives balls, entertainments and picnics, besides income from renting rooms for the meetings of different Polish clubs and associations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0783.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The children of Polish veterans are organized in junior departments by each post, where they are trained in patriotic spirit. This training is similar to one given the children by boy and girl scout organizations. The children are also taught the Polish and American dances, reciting of poetry they listen to lectures on topics that are of interest to their growing minds. In short, an effort is being made to give the children good moral and physical training and provide an opportunity for their self-expression and the development of their latent talents and abilities so that they may become good citizens and contribute something from the old Polish culture to the American melting pot. The Association takes part in civic and patriotic activities.</p>
   <p>The commander of the Chicago district is Mr. Joseph Trygar.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
