<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-12">Jan. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Relief Activities at St. Innocent's Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-12">Jan. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH RELIEF ACTIVITIES AT ST. INNOCENT'S PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our countrymen from the village of Jadowniki Mokre, County of Dabrowo, Galicia, impelled by a sense of duty toward their unfortunate brothers and sisters in the homeland, who are victims of the terrible war, met last Sunday, January 7, at Mr. Pudlo's hall, 1431 West Huron Street, in order to discuss how best to appeal to the generosity of all the Polish immigrants from this district for relief funds. There are about three hundred people from this district in Chicago alone. The idea is to concentrate the relief action among them, so that no one from their group will be passed up. This program presents certain difficulties, because not all of the people live in the same district. Nevertheless, those who attended the last meeting are determind to overcome this obstacle and will do everything in their power to have all the people from Jadowniki scattered throughout various districts, parishes, and even those from neighboring towns, come to their next meeting, which will be held in two weeks at the same place. For this purpose committees were appointed and a temporary administrative committee was elected as follows: Joseph Pajak, president;</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1081.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>F. Wilkosz, vice-president; W. Gibsz, financial secretary; F. Urban, recording secretary; W. Kozlowski, treasurer. Agitational committee: J. Tyrcha, S. Wilkosz, and W. Zalesny. Others present besides those already mentioned were Joseph Zalesny, John Tyrcha, John Biesiada, Andrew Partyka, and John Aniol.</p>
   <p>M. Idzikowski, T. Wojciechowski, S. Kolczak, and others who were at the hall earlier in order to attend a meeting of the Relief Society of the People of Miechowicze, spoke encouragingly to those gathered. This latter society, which has been in existence for over a year and can show favorable results of its work, offered five dollars to start the treasury of the new society. Others made individual contributions to the relief fund in the amount of $23.50, which made the total $28.50. [Translator's note: Here follows a list of the contributors and the amounts contributed].</p>
   <p>In two weeks, i. e., on Sunday, January 21, the people of, Jadowniki expect to collect a sum many times larger if everyone comes to the meeting at the above-named hall, 1431 West Huron Street, at 3 P. M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
