<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-13">Nov. 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A Hospital for Poles</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Submitted)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0546</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0546.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-13">Nov. 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A HOSPITAL FOR POLES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Submitted)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The splendid Polish Day has passed, the Lwow Exposition looms brightly in the near future; although slowly, contributions for the Kosciusko Monument are flowing in.</p>
   <p>This is all very useful, noble, and necessary. Let us support these things with all our strength--but let us not forget about other needs equally important, or perhaps even more so. I refer to the matter of a Polish hospital in Chicago, which we have needed for a long time. At one time, the Polish doctors discussed this question in Dziennik[Chicagoski]; since then nothing has been heard about it. At last, on Saturday, I read a small item on the plans of the Sisters of the Holy Family of Nazareth. I commend them most heartily--and I hope for their realization. A Polish hospital is certainly a very great necessity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0547.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I will cite the following incident which occurred to me, as an illustration:</p>
   <p>While I visited a sick friend in St. Elizabeth's Hospital on Sunday, I noticed a boy, about six years old, to whom the attending Sister was saying something in English. One of the patients told me that the boy was Polish, so I walked over to his bed. The child, his head bound, his face pale and eyes sunken, was sitting up and asking for something. The nurse, leaning over him with all the tenderness of a guardian angel, endeavored to understand what the child wanted, but not knowing the language she was helpless. The child became impatient and began to cry; he was suffering, evidently. I asked the Sister in German what the trouble was. She told me that the child was suffering from some sort of insanity. Then I asked the boy in Polish: "What do you want, my child?" "Water," he answered, "water," and stretched out his arms to me.</p>
   <p>My countrymen! At this moment, I would like to see at that bedside all 120,000 of you Poles who live in Chicago! There is not one of you who would <pb facs="5423968_7_0548.jpg" n="3"/>not be moved at the sight of the little fellow, his arms outstretched, his weak voice calling: "Water, water." The child was suffering from thirst for perhaps as much as half an hour, while the Sister, who would do anything to relieve him, could not understand what he wanted and thought that he was suffering from some kind of insanity.</p>
   <p>A few minutes later, the boy's mother came into the room, and I learned that there are five small children in his family, that the father works hard at bone sorting, and that the boy himself had been ill for a year and a half. The parents did what they could for the boy and now, when death is but a matter of time, they placed him in the hospital. Why? Because there is no Polish hospital! How can one place a child in an institution where no one can understand what he needs and what he is suffering?</p>
   <p>I have submitted an account of this incident to give the public an example, one that occurs daily, of why a Polish hospital is vitally necessary. I would hold it against myself had I remained silent. In addition to this, I <pb facs="5423968_7_0549.jpg" n="4"/>have seen similar incidents at the Alexian Brothers Hospital, where, last February, three Poles who understood neither German nor English, lay. They suffered much, and treatment could hardly be expected to bring successful results.</p>
   <p>I repeat: We need a Polish hospital, especially a Polish hospital for women and children. Since the erection of a hospital entails great expense, the plan proposed by the Sisters of the Holy Family of Nazareth should be supported as a beginning; the idea should be spread, so that the projected hospital will be able to serve not only Polish women but children also.</p>
   <p>P. Ligman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
