<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-23">Jan. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">On the Eve of the Double Tag Day for Poland</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-23">Jan. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE EVE OF THE DOUBLE TAG DAY FOR POLAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Day, promoted by the Polish Central Relief Committee, will do its share. Even if the expected sum of a million dollars is not collected on that day, nevertheless a great interest in Poland's cause has been aroused in nearly all the cities of the United States. This in itself is a great accomplishment of this noble and praiseworthy project of the Polish Central Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>In our own city of Chicago work was begun in earnest as soon as the news was heard of the public tagging for two days. People of other nationalities became more interested in Polish matters when the City Council, headed by Mayor Harrison, proclaimed this Polish Day, calling upon all to contribute and donate for the cause. Interest in the tag day was thus aroused in all residents of this city. The newspapers of other nationalities have adopted a very friendly attitude toward this undertaking. In view of all this, success should be <pb facs="5423968_7_1160.jpg" n="2"/>assured.</p>
   <p>Word reaches us from other cities that the idea of conducting a tag day in other municipalities, modelled on that to be held in Chicago, has met with new sympathy among the residents. There is on hand a copy of a letter of the Relief Committee of Grand Rapids, Michigan. This letter was printed in English and addressed to people of other nationalities. It contains a long list of particulars on the present condition of Poland, and it urges the people of Grand Rapids to make contributions for Poland's cause, a country "that lies helpless between the warring nations, trampled by the horses of Austrian, German, and Russian armies, a land of which the residents have innocently found themselves in the very midst of the horrible hell which all Europe is today."</p>
   <p>"Let us be mindful", the letter further states, "of the debt that we owe to Kosciusko and Pulaski. What can you do for the Motherland of these two famous heroes, for the wives, mothers, and children of this nation?" We <pb facs="5423968_7_1161.jpg" n="3"/>might add that all the English newspapers in Grand Rapids have printed this letter, ardently promoting the cause. The banks, moreover, have willingly consented to accept in their establishments all contributions and have created special accounts for that purpose.</p>
   <p>That is the situation in the West. But what about the East? And again we have on hand a letter of the Polish-American Relief Committee of Boston, Massachussetts. This committee is headed by Mr. Curtis Guild, a millionaire. Names of the most prominent Poles are also found on the committee, for example, Mrs. Antoinette Szumowska-Adamowska, Mr. J. Romaszkiewicz, and Mr. J. Adamowski. This letter of the Bostonian Committee also appeals to Americans to accord substantial aid to the unfortunate people of Poland.</p>
   <p>"The general sympathy", states the letter, "for the entirely innocent residents of little Belgium has attracted the attention of the whole civilized world. For a while it has distracted attention from another and even more unfortunate <pb facs="5423968_7_1162.jpg" n="4"/>nation, a country in which the most vicious battles are being conducted.</p>
   <p>"That is Poland. All eyewitnesses and newspaper correspondents are agreed on one thing, namely, that Poland is completely devastated and ruined, and its people have nothing to eat. Although it is divided among three powers, it cannot escape any one's attention today that the people from the Baltic to the Carpathian Mountains, who have suffered most from the war, are the residents of a formerly magnificent Polish kingdom. Can we be so inhuman as to refuse shelter to the homeless? Shall we fail to feed the hungry? Shall we not clothe the naked?"</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the letter our compatriots in Boston mention that the contributions of all will be forwarded to Warsaw, where the General Polish Relief Committee, with Messrs. Henry Sienkiewicz and Ignace Paderewski at its head, will take care of the distribution.</p>
   <p>And in truth our Poles in Boston were not disappointed in their expectations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1163.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Inspired by a spirit of great enthusiasm, they were moved by the spirit of prophecy when they foresaw that the two best-known Poles in the entire world would undertake to bring aid to our brethren and sisters in Poland.</p>
   <p>The latest reports from Switzerland received by the Polish Central Relief Committee in Chicago inform us that a General Polish Relief Committee has been established in Lausanne, with Henry Sienkiewicz and Ignace Paderewski at its head. What is more, this Committee, recently organized in neutral territory, in Switzerland, is composed of thirty-six members, representing all parts of Poland, including three Polish delegates from the United States. The Central Polish Relief Committee in Chicago has appointed the Right Reverend Bishop Paul Rhode, Mr. A. Karabasz, censor of the Polish National Alliance, and Mr. John F. Smulski, treasurer of the Polish Central Relief Committee, as the three delegates.</p>
   <p>And so a rather burdensome and important question has been solved, namely, to <pb facs="5423968_7_1164.jpg" n="6"/>whom our hard-earned money shall be sent, and how to distribute it among the poor and the destitute. The Polish Central Relief Committees in Chicago was uneasy on that point, not knowing in whose care to send the already collected fifteen thousand dollars. The mail and all other communication with Warsaw has been suspended.</p>
   <p>Today this question appears clarified. We will send immediately all the money collected by the Polish Central Relief Committee directly to the Polish General Relief Committee in Switzerland. Those who stand at the head of the General Committee, Henry Sienkiewicz and Ignace Paderewski, people who enjoy respect among all nations, give us the best assurance that the funds will be distributed by them according to needs.</p>
   <p>The most important thing is that this generosity, which has of late commenced to bear such noble fruit, shall not cease. It is essential that our willingness to promote the good work shall not die out with the termination of the Polish Day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
