<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 120,
<date when="1922-05-23">May 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Free Dental Clinic</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 120,
<date when="1922-05-23">May 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FREE DENTAL CLINIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The local Association of Polish Dentists for a long time has felt the need of a free dental clinic. Such a clinic would prove a great benefit during this present economic adjustment.</p>
   <p>In every community there is a certain number of people who, because of their financial status, find indispensable professional aid beyond their reach. Nearly every dispensary gives free, or for a minimum charge, certain services, even in "good times." The present period, however, is an economic recession and free dispensary for local communities is imperative, but work has been limited to that of a surgical nature.</p>
   <p>The association has acquired several hospitals where dental surgery will be given free of charge. Persons interested are invited to refer to any Polish dentist who is a member of the association (very few Polish dentists <pb facs="5423968_7_0408.jpg" n="2"/>are not members), or direct to the secretary, Dr. S. Gorny, 1858 S. Ashland Avenue.</p>
   <p>Until further notice the clinic will be open Wednesday evenings. The association has done everything in its power in the effort to establish a general dental clinic, but found it necessary to abandon the idea until a desirable location, plus other necessities, are available. Thousands of children in public schools are examined and given dental care, either in clinics or in private dental offices.</p>
   <p>Does society actually lack the essential requirements for establishing a much needed clinic for Polish children?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
