<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-12">Feb. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Reverend Sebastynski Appeals to Peter Kiolbassa for Help</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-12">Feb. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">REVEREND SEBASTYNSKI APPEALS TO PETER KIOLBASSA FOR HELP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Peter Kiolbassa recently received a letter from Reverend W. Sebastynski, S. J., pastor of St. Anthony Church, Posen-Farwell, Nebraska, making an appeal for help. Since the letter concerns all Poles, it has been turned over to Dziennik Chicagoski for publication.</p>
   <p>The letter is as follows:</p>
   <p>"February 6, 1895</p>
   <p>"Dear Mr. Kiolbassa:</p>
   <p>"As you know, the barren harvests of the past two years in Nebraska, especially in the western part, have brought poverty and hunger to the farmers.</p>
   <p>"The Poles in Howard and Sherman counties have been hit the hardest. During <pb facs="5423968_7_1417.jpg" n="2"/>the past four weeks I visited every home in my parish. I offered encouragement to the best of my ability, but I found too much poverty--too much for one person to handle. There are about forty families without any means of existence, about eighty farmers are without seed for the spring planting, and the winter is severe.</p>
   <p>"It is true that help is coming from the East, but this assistance is being distributed from Lincoln, Nebraska, by a central relief committee. This parent organization in turn redistributes its aid to the small towns and villages through local relief committees. These committees are in charge of Masons and members of the A. P. A. [American Protective Association, which was anti-Catholic]. What is worse, they are operated by women of these two factions. It is no wonder that these committees have taken advantage of this charitable work and turned it into a business venture for their organizations. This is being carried out in two ways:</p>
   <p>"1. Clothing and food are being distributed only among the Masons and <pb facs="5423968_7_1418.jpg" n="3"/>A. P. A. 's, and what is left over is passed on to the others--provided there is anything left over.</p>
   <p>"2. What is worse, these factions publish factional stories and announcements, stating that this or that shipment of goods has arrived from X or Y, through the courtesy of the Methodists, the Baptists or the German Lutherans of Chicago, etc. At the same time they charge that the Catholic church is the only one of all the denominations that has not offered succor to the needy.</p>
   <p>"It is an evident fact that the relief action on the part of the Poles has not been made known. Therefore, in my opinion, it is high time that some assistance be given to the destitute Poles. Because I am familiar with your good heart, Mr. Kiolbassa, I appeal to you for help.</p>
   <p>"I have already written to a few places asking for aid for my parish in Posen. And now, after a consultation with the priests of this diocese, we must ask for aid for the entire two counties of Sherman and Howard, but this assistance must come from Catholics for distribution by the relief committee, <pb facs="5423968_7_1419.jpg" n="4"/>St. Paul, Nebraska.</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir! Become a father to our stricken people. In your own way, as you know best, request for us as much as you can get, in food, clothing, coal, etc., if only one or two carloads. Have them sent by way of the Burlington Railroad to St. Paul, Nebraska, addressed to The Howard County Relief Committee, care of Howard County Clerk. The shipment should be designated as follows: 'For Howard and Sherman Counties, from Polish Catholics of Chicago,' or words to that effect.</p>
   <p>"I beseech you in the name of God and the poor suffering brothers to arrange some kind of plan which will bring us aid. In the name of God and the Blessed Mother!</p>
   <p>Yours faithfully in Christ,</p>
   <p>Reverend W. Sebastynski, S. J.</p>
   <p>Pastor, St. Anthony Church</p>
   <p>Posen-Farwell, Nebraska"</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1420.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>To this letter Peter Kiolbassa adds the following:</p>
   <p>"Dear Friends:</p>
   <p>"I appeal to Dziennik Chicagoski to publish this letter written by Reverend Sebastynski, K. J., renowned and beloved missionary of Nebraska. Poverty and hunger are tormenting our Polish brothers in Howard and Sherman counties of Nebraska. As the letter indicates, there is no one to take care of the dire needs of these people.</p>
   <p>"I have the sincerest hope that in the hearts of the Polish people in Chicago and vicinity the spirit of brotherly love has not faded, that many will be found, especially among the businessmen, who will help these destitute Poles.</p>
   <p>"It would be a great help if the Poles of Chicago would call a meeting, create a committee and make plans to collect various kinds of goods, whether food or clothing, for the aid of the poor Polish people. This is my proposal <pb facs="5423968_7_1421.jpg" n="6"/>to the Poles of Chicago.</p>
   <p>"I also appeal to all the Polish newspapers to take enthusiastic interest in this matter; for who will come to the assistance of these poor Polish people if not we Poles of Chicago? Our greatest duty is to lend a hand to our brothers.</p>
   <p>Peter Kiolbassa"</p>
   <p>Nothing further will be added to these noble words of Mr. Kiolbassa. It might be said that a meeting of Polish representative individuals of Chicago this week would be an ultimate stepping stone to the assistance of the unfortunate Poles of Nebraska.</p>
   <p>Let us act! Remember, he who acts first gives twice as much.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
