<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 44,
<date when="1915-11-03">Nov. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Union Fire Insurance Company</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 44,
<date when="1915-11-03">Nov. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH UNION FIRE INSURANCE COMPANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are able to announce that one point of the resolution of the 34th convention of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union is already realized. This point concerns the organizing of a Polish fire insurance company.</p>
   <p>Under the above name a Polish company has already been organized with a subscribed capital of one million dollars. The price of each share has been set at $10 par, therefore making it possible for everyone to participate in this Polish company. The company will be incorporated under the laws of the State of Illinois. Supplementary to each share there will be paid $10 toward a surplus fund and expenses.</p>
   <p>This is a company with a right to operate all over the United States and when we consider that four million Poles have already long ago yearned for a company of their own, then we will see that success is assured.</p>
   <p>So then, we have a right to be happy, that for once the Poles are beginning to care for their "skin" and are thinking about themselves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0383.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As far as we know the whole matter is being treated in a business way, and the funds of the company will be controlled by trustees, and therefore responsible people and under bond as required by the law.</p>
   <p>We have found out that the president of the company will be Mr. J. F. Jozwiak, whom the Poles in America know well and they also know that whatever his hand touches is successful. We all know him and wish him success. The two other trustees are Dr. F. E. Fronsczak of Buffalo, N. Y., one of the most popular Poles in America, and Mr. F. A. Kwasigroch, postal official from Chicago.</p>
   <p>Next week we will give more information. Today we wish success and congratulate them, that they were able to realize the idea of His Excellency the late Bishop Kozlowski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
