<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-21">Dec. 21, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Deficit in the Treasury of the Polish Roman Catholic Union</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0171</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0171.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-21">Dec. 21, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">DEFICIT IN THE TREASURY OF THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Everyone has heard, undoubtedly, of the deficit existing in the treasury of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. Rumors have been current for some time that something is amiss in that organization, but heretofore the matter also ended in rumors. It was not until the newly elected president of the Union, Mr. Stanley Adamkiewicz, suspended Mr. T. Osrowski, the treasurer of the organization, and reported his action to the newspapers, that the truth of these rumors became officially established. Various particulars, the testimony of many people, interviews by reporters, conjectures and complaints have poured out as if from the horn of plenty. On the day following the suspension of the treasurer an extensive report, emanating from a committee selected at a meeting of the organization's administration, appeared in the newspapers. In this <pb facs="5423968_7_0172.jpg" n="2"/>report the committee asserted that $81,000 was missing from the treasury of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. The committee also reported that the former treasurer of the organization, Mr. T. Ostrowski, had assigned his entire private estate to the Union. Moreover, in the same report the committee accuses the former administration, namely, the former president and the former general secretary, saying that they knew of the existence of this shortage at the time of the last convention in Cleveland, and still they concealed it from the delegates.</p>
   <p>In reply to this communication an extended statement by the former president of the Union appeared in the daily newspapers. In this reply he attempts to shift the blame from himself to the new administration. The former president quotes the very words of the treasurer himself to show that at the time of the Cleveland convention the shortage did not exceed $40,000. Therefore, if the shortage has now reached $81,000, or perhaps more, it is clear that the new administration was not without fault in failing to discover the deficit and in not making certain that it would <pb facs="5423968_7_0173.jpg" n="3"/>not increase.</p>
   <p>The chaplains of the Polish Roman Catholic Union were also drawn into the discussion, namely, the present chaplain, the Reverend Father Gronkowski, and the former chaplain, the Reverend Father Wojtalewicz. Two distinct parties appeared--that of the old administration and that of the new--which mutually accuse each other and give various items of information against each other to the daily newspapers.</p>
   <p>It is difficult absolutely to distinguish truth from exaggeration in the mass of material presented by some of the newspapers. They write, for example, that the shortage is far greater than the committee admitted; they mention $100,000 and more. They also state and write that the private estate of the former treasurer, Mr. T. Ostrowski, is not only insufficient to cover the entire deficit but will not even offset an appreciable share of the amount missing.</p>
   <p>The controversy has already attained huge proportions. With polemical <pb facs="5423968_7_0174.jpg" n="4"/>zeal people cast various charges at one another, some of them very grave, and the accused reply in kind. Only the courts or a convention extraordinary could solve the whole matter and assign to every one his share of guilt, penalty and responsibility.</p>
   <p>It is a very important fact, and it has been irrefutably confirmed, that the shortage did not arise all at once but has existed for some time and has gradually increased. When it began, and with what initial amount the newspapers do not certainly know. But the interested persons are agreed that a marked shortage already existed at the time of the last convention of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, and that the former officials were aware of this and yet kept it secret from the delegates. After the convention the shortage steadily increased. The new administration did not take the matter up until it had been in office a year and two months.</p>
   <p>It is difficult to imagine that other officials of the Union's <pb facs="5423968_7_0175.jpg" n="5"/>administration besides the president and the secretary did not know of the existence of a shortage for so many years, including the priests who form part of the administration. This greatly increases the guilt of the old and the new administrations.</p>
   <p>This conjecture is verified by the present chaplain of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, the Reverend Father Gronkowski, who in an extended communication forwarded to the Polish newspaper Dziennik Zwiazkowy expresses himself in a very ambiguous manner. The reverend chaplain considers it bad policy that some of the officials of the present administration of the Union are members of the committee selected by the administration to ascertain the extent of the shortage.</p>
   <p>We consider the position which the Reverend Father Gronkowski takes in this matter to be absolutely correct. As long as the matter necessitated the appointment of a committee by the administration to give an authoritative opinion, it was proper to appoint on this committee reliable <pb facs="5423968_7_0176.jpg" n="6"/>members of the Union belonging neither to the old nor to the new administration and hence, impartial. People of that kind would inspire more confidence in the public.</p>
   <p>Every deficit in the treasury of an organization is a sad matter. It exposes the organization to harmful aftereffects. But of the two possible forms of shortage that of which there is now talk is unquestionably the worse.</p>
   <p>A sudden shortage, caused by a single act of malfeasance on the part of the treasurer, would be a thing greatly compromising and embarrassing to an organization. But a deficit lasting for several years, increasing constantly, and carefully concealed puts the management of the organization in a far worse position. Throughout the entire period of its failure to comply with the law this organization enjoyed a good reputation and received new members into its fold. The officials should not be permitted to hide <pb facs="5423968_7_0177.jpg" n="7"/>the truth from the members for years and at the time of enrolling new members give them the impression that everything is in the best of order.</p>
   <p>The very words of the reverend chaplain himself indicate the high degree of disorder which has existed. He proves on the basis of the testimony of the former treasurer that this official, in a way the most important in the entire organization, has for the last ten years failed to keep a daily record of the amount of money and the kind of money that has come into his hands. This, after all, is nothing less than criminal negligence! By so conducting a business it is possible not only to endanger the financial condition [of an enterprise] but even to ruin it.</p>
   <p>But, we ask, what were the other officials doing in the course of the ten years of the treasurer's failure to keep a record of the income? Did it never occur to them that it is improper to conduct financial affairs in that manner? After all, they must have known in what way the treasurer kept his books because that was their first duty. What did <pb facs="5423968_7_0178.jpg" n="8"/>the finance committees do at the conventions of the Polish Roman Catholic Union?</p>
   <p>It is not the intention of the Dziennik Zwiazkowy to pronounce judgment here over the officials of the Union. Let the people who have trusted them be the judges.</p>
   <p>We only wish to call the attention of members of the Polish National Alliance to the benefit and the security to be derived of the system employed in our organization. Here the people themselves govern; they themselves know and investigate the ways and means of conducting the business. They have at all times access to all books and accounts and receive detailed and truthful reports.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
