<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-19">Aug. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">Society of St. Michael Archangel in Chicago, Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0314</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0314.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-19">Aug. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Society of St. Michael Archangel In Chicago, Illinois</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The society [of St. Michael Archangel] was organized on September 14, 1888. The founders of the Society were John Chemma, John Szostakowski, John Kaminski, and many others who to this day are members of the organization.</p>
   <p>The object of this society is mutual aid in the form of sick and accident benefits; care of the widows and orphans of the deceased members. At the time the society was organized its other purpose in view was the foundation of a new Polish Catholic Parish, and this was indeed realized on the third birthday of the organization. This parish was established in South Chicago, Illinois in the so-called Warsaw district. The members were mainly instrumental in this accomplishment.</p>
   <p>The church and school which are now under construction and on the verge of <pb facs="5423968_7_0315.jpg" n="2"/>completion, were named after St. Michael Archangel, patron of the Society. The pastor, Reverend Adolph Nowicki, who is popular [and] well liked, is revered by the parishioners.</p>
   <p>This is strictly a church society; it does not belong to any other greater organization. The sick benefit is six dollars a week. In the event of death, the family of the deceased member is paid fifty dollars for burial expenses and a two-hundred-dollar death benefit.</p>
   <p>Harmony and unity prevail within the Society, and the administration makes every effort to maintain this atmosphere with good order.</p>
   <p>The current year's administration is as follows: John Szostakowski, president (this being his fourth year); Michael Trafas, vice-president; Michael Godzinski, recording secretary, Francis Swiadek, financial secretary; John Wozniak, treasurer; Walter Przybylinski and Anthony Niewolski, chairmen.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0316.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The control board consists of John Kaminski, Martin Pawelczyk, and John Stolarski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
