<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-14">Dec. 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Kosciuszko Monument Model Contest to Be Announced in Lwow</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-14">Dec. 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">KOSCIUSZKO MONUMENT MODEL CONTEST TO BE ANNOUNCED IN LWOW</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Plans for the Kosciuszko Monument Model Contest, sponsored by the Kosciuszko Monument Fund Committee, have advanced another step toward realization. Dr. E. H. Dunikowski, who was appointed by the Committee to represent it in Europe, has finally returned to his native land. He arranged to have the Lwow Fine Arts Society announce the contest, and called a meeting of leading Polish artists. At the close of the conference it was decided that the awards stipulated by the Committee of Chicago were too low. Dr. Dunikowski sent the results of the deliberations to Chicago.</p>
   <p>The proposal of increasing awards was discussed Monday evening, December 12, by the Kosciuszko Monument Fund Committee. The Committee, realizing that the Lwow Fine Arts Society is an outstanding institution of its kind and a good judge of the standards of awards, agreed to increase the prizes as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0036.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>First prize</cell>
     <cell>1000 Austrian Crowns</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Second prize</cell>
     <cell>750 Austrian Crowns</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Third prize</cell>
     <cell>500 Austrian Crowns</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>[Translator's note: An Austrian Crown was equivalent to a little over 42 cents in American money.]</p>
   <p>The sum necessary for these awards amounts to $950, which sum was sent out to Lwow yesterday. The contest will be announced by the Lwow Fine Arts Society upon receipt of this money.</p>
   <p>The prize-winning models will be on exhibit on Polish-occupied territory and in Chicago. From them the Kosciuszko Monument Fund Committee will choose the one to be erected as a memorial in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The project is developing according to plans. What is most necessary at present is more contributions. With good support the monument should be erected in a short while. Its completion will stand as a symbol of our patriotic feeling and work on American soil.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
