<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-08-23">Aug. 23, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Employment Bureaus, a Working Man's Nemesis</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0861</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0861.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-08-23">Aug. 23, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">EMPLOYMENT BUREAUS, A WORKING MAN'S NEMESIS</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many of the so - called employment bureaus are really a working man's nemesis. Their sole objective and purpose is not to help, but to exploit the workers. According to state laws such bureaus or agencies shall, upon failure to furnish employment for the applicant, return the fee collected for that purpose. In many cases the agents in charge of these offices disregard these regulations, and shamelessly deceive and cheat applicants by charging higher fees than allowed by the law; in addition to this they fail to furnish employment for the money collected from their applicants.</p>
   <p>This city has many of these so-called agencies, a few of them are in our Polish settlements. This matter should be thoroughly investigated by the city administration, and if violators are found, the offending agencies or bureaus should be closed, and the unscrupulous agents sentenced to jail. From the numerous complaints brought forth, it appears that the employment agents accept fees ranging from $5.00 to $12.00 and then not only fail to find jobs, but also refuse to refund the money collected. Some of these agents have been found to be in conspiracy with the foremen and supervisors of factories who hire the applicants, retaining them for a few days, or for a week at most; then, without reason discharging them, only to <pb facs="5423968_7_0862.jpg" n="2"/>replace them with another victim and finally the profits are divided with the agents. Other employment agencies virtually sell the workers into slavery in far off places where there is hardly a possibility of escape from the unbearable working conditions and pitiable wages offered.</p>
   <p>It is, therefore, the duty of the various immigrant protective association and charitable institutions to look into this matter and curb the violations perpetrated by these so - called employment agencies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
