<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-27">Apr. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">One Thousand Dollars for Polish Relief</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-27">Apr. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ONE THOUSAND DOLLARS FOR POLISH RELIEF</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The patriotic Polish district of Town of Lake again reminds other Chicago districts of its existence, and sets an example of how one should work for the Polish cause.</p>
   <p>Recently Mr. J. Magdziarz, treasurer of the Polish National Alliance, received a $1,000 contribution for the war victims in Poland from the board of directors of the J. Slowacki Library, together with the following letter:</p>
   <p>"Chicago, Illinois, April 24, 1917.</p>
   <p>"The Independence Department</p>
   <p>of the Polish National Alliance,</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Magdziarz.</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir: We are herewith sending you, as treasurer of the Independence <pb facs="5423968_7_1042.jpg" n="2"/>Department of the Polish National Alliance, the sum of one thousand dollars, representing the net proceeds of the bazaar and concert arranged by societies which are members of the V. Slowacki Library of Town of Lake. This money is to be used for the relief of war victims in Poland.</p>
   <p>"We stipulate that this one thousand dollars is to be used only for the war victims in Poland and not for any other purpose. We expect the National Department of the Polish National Alliance to conform to this condition.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>D. Hojnacki, president.</p>
   <p>[Mrs.] W. Deplewski, treasurer.</p>
   <p>M. Gacki, secretary,</p>
   <p>4826 Marshfield Avenue."</p>
   <p>On acknowledging this splendid gift, for which he thanks the Poles of Town of Lake <pb facs="5423968_7_1043.jpg" n="3"/>in behalf of the National Department of the Polish National Alliance, the treasurer wishes to call to the attention of the donors that up to the present the National Department has collected $170,000.02 for Polish relief, not one penny of which has been used for any other purpose. The money has been sent to the General Relief Committee in Switzerland.</p>
   <p>Even the administrative costs and the costs of sending this money to Europe have been defrayed with other funds of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Therefore, all contributions for Polish relief have reached their destination, as the records of the General Relief Committee at Switzerland clearly show. These records indicate specifically where and to whom the committee has sent the money it has received.</p>
   <p>Therefore, let the Alliance brethren rest assured that no one will touch these sacred funds for other purposes, and let them continue to make their generous contributions, so that we can save as many people as possible from starvation at <pb facs="5423968_7_1044.jpg" n="4"/>a time when we already have the assurance that our homeland will be free, united, and independent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
