<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-02">Mar. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">War Assessment Passed by Polish National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-02">Mar. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WAR ASSESSMENT PASSED BY POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In another column of this paper, the members of the Polish National Alliance will find an official notice from J. S. Zawilinski, secretary of the Polish National Alliance, concerning the referendum submitted to the Alliance groups on the question of a war assessment, which will amount to two cents per hundred dollars of insurance. The result of the referendum was two to one for the assessment. The assessment was absolutely necessary, since the additional funds must be raised in one way or another.</p>
   <p>The members of the Alliance, as intelligent people who are concerned with the welfare of their organization, understood immediately that the existence and future of the Alliance were involved, that this was not merely a whim of the <pb facs="5423968_7_0369.jpg" n="2"/>censor, or of the Central Administration, or of the Advisory Board; it was not groundless alarm but absolute necessity that forced the Alliance officials to take this step.</p>
   <p>It is well known to all of us that many of our members are of draft age. Some of them are already in the American army, and others will be called in the near future. Others, again, have enlisted in the Polish army, thus fulfilling their duty to our dear motherland, Poland. To deprive them of the death benefit because they went to fight for the rights and freedom of nations, for the safety and integrity of the United States--which the Teutons threatened, hoping to place the Prussian heel on our necks too--or because they went to help Poland win its unity and freedom, would be wrong both morally and legally. How would our alliance appear in the eyes of Americans and of the American government if it would dare do such a thing? To leave the treasury as it was, however, would be courting financial ruin and the final collapse of our organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0370.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>War is no joke, for where shells are bursting, rifles cracking, swords and bayonets ringing, more than one young life from among our brave Alliance members may be snuffed out; more than one may return crippled for life, making it necessary to pay him his death benefit--all of which will draw considerable sums from the Alliance treasury. In order to meet its obligations and at the same time avoid financial ruin, a special war assessment is necessary to meet this eventuality. After all, it is better for us to pay two cents more per hundred dollars of insurance today than to expose the treasury to collapse and suffer for it ourselves in the future.</p>
   <p>Finally, a war assessment has been voted, or is being voted by other organizations, even those larger than the Alliance, for they know what awaits them unless they safeguard themselves beforehand. In this case, no Alliance member should complain, for it is being done for the good of every member--to safeguard his life insurance policy for his heirs.</p>
   <p>From the first of March, then, the war assessment will go into effect for <pb facs="5423968_7_0371.jpg" n="4"/>every member of the Polish National Alliance, and it should be paid with the idea that it is safeguarding the families of our boys, should they fall in battle or should they return crippled and in need of aid. God grant that as few as possible of our boys be killed, or crippled, but we all know that the enemy does not shoot peas or turnips, but bullets, grenades, bombs, and other death-dealing missiles. We over here are not risking our lives and health; we can talk politics safely and mark up the map of Europe as we please, while they mark the map of Europe with bayonets and with blood, their own as well as that of the enemy. It is not difficult, then, for us to pay a few pennies per month extra for the death benefit of those who are fighting and dying for our integrity and our future while we ourselves are exposed to no danger.</p>
   <p>The referendum concerning the acceptance of new members of draft age for insurance not higher than five hundred dollars instead of a thousand, passed by a large majority--and justifiably. More than one such person failed to <pb facs="5423968_7_0372.jpg" n="5"/>join the Alliance or any other organization, and even made trifling remarks about them. Now, feeling that he may be taken into the army, such a person would like to insure his life to the greatest possible sum, so that in case of misfortune his family will receive a death benefit. The Alliance will not close its doors to such people, but will accept them on equal terms with other members; on the other hand, however, it cannot take too great a risk, for in paying out larger sums, perhaps even the war assessment would not be sufficient. When they return from the war alive and well, they can then raise their insurance to as much as a thousand dollars. At present, however, the Alliance cannot take the risk.</p>
   <p>In forthcoming issues of Zgoda, we will publish a report showing how each individual group voted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
