<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-09-26">Sept. 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Court Action Undertaken by the Polish Roman Catholic Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-09-26">Sept. 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE COURT ACTION UNDERTAKEN BY THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new decree was issued recently by Mr. Humphrey, master of chancery, in the court action undertaken by the Polish Roman Catholic Union. The suit was filed some time ago against Messrs. Szopinski and Krolik, former officials of that organization. They are charged with embezzlement of the organization's funds.</p>
   <p>As members of the Union know the misappropriations amounted to some ninety thousand dollars. Mr. N. L. Piotrowski, former attorney of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, succeeded in recovering about fifty thousand dollars from the estate of the former treasurer, the late Mr. Ostrowski. Since Mr. Ostrowski, the former treasurer, did not have a larger estate, Mr. Piotrowski, wishing to regain the entire amount of the defalcations, brought legal action against Messrs. Leon Szopinski, former president, and Thomas Krolik, former secretary of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0132.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was shown by the examination of records and the investigation of checks that both these officials had received various amounts of money from the former treasurer in the course of eight years. The aggregate sum thus obtained was said to be approximately fifty thousand dollars. These amounts were not entered in the records, and neither Mr. Szopinski nor Mr. Krolik has given any explanation thus far concerning the purpose for which they received these sums or the use which they made of the money. In addition to this as the second point of the charge, Attorney Piotrowski held that both these former officials of the Polish Roman Catholic Union are responsible to the organization for the defalcations. They not only failed in the fulfillment of their duty according to the rules prescribed by the constitution, but they have also, for a period of eight years, concealed the true status of the Union's treasury and presented false reports at the organization's conventions.</p>
   <p>After lengthy and bitter court proceedings, in which the defense attorneys frequently attempted to throw the case out of court, on technical grounds, the matter was finally referred to the master in chancery. After several sessions, <pb facs="5423968_7_0133.jpg" n="3"/>the depositions of numerous witnesses, and the examination of huge volumes of records and documents, the chancery issued a decree in May, 1915, declaring that Mr. Szopinski owes to the Polish Roman Catholic Union the sum of $15,849.30, and that Mr. Krolik owes $10,642.47. The master in chancery held them liable only for the amount of the money which they had obtained from the Polish Roman Catholic Union and could not account for as used for organization purposes.</p>
   <p>The master in chancery, failed to take into consideration Mr. Piotrowski's second charge; namely, that the accused had failed in the fulfillment of their obligations and had concealed the true financial status of the organization. The chancery did, however, recommend that the court settle that question.</p>
   <p>When Judge Foell was prepared to listen to the arguments and to issue his decree, the defense requested the court again to refer the case to the master in chancery. The reason for this was that new witnesses have been found who can <pb facs="5423968_7_0134.jpg" n="4"/>prove that the money in question was spent for organization purposes. The court allowed the petition and returned the matter to the master in chancery for further consideration. This matter was in progress for nearly the whole summer of the year preceding this. More than fifty witnesses were heard, and numerous checks and documents were examined. The accused by the testimony of these witnesses and by these documents attempted to prove that the money received by them was used for the Union's purposes. According to the recent decree of the master in chancery Mr. Szopinski accounted for various sums amounting in all to 6,760.30 and considered this accounting sufficient. Mr. Krolik succeeded in accounting for only two sums; the total of these two was $1,402.30.</p>
   <p>And so, according to the new decree, if the statute of limitations, submitted by the accused as their defense, should be found valid [in this case], Mr. Szopinski will have to pay to the Polish Roman Catholic Union the sum of $11,684, and Mr. Krolik will have to pay $9,240.09, a total of $20,929.09 [sic].</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0135.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The master in chancery's report will be presented to the judge, before whom the arguments will be heard concerning the legal points. Following this a decree will be issued.</p>
   <p>Attorney Piotrowski, asked for his opinion on the new order of the master in chancery, replied:</p>
   <p>"I should be pleased if the two defendants would give an adequate explanation of the funds which they received from the organization. Neither one of them has offered to give any explanation before the time of the court hearing. In my opinion the presentation of the statute of limitations is not the proper defense in this instance, and I expect that the judge will recognize my arguments on that point as well founded.</p>
   <p>"The defendants, in my opinion, should be held liable not only for the money which they received of the Polish Roman Catholic Union and did not use for organization purposes, but also for all funds of which by their negligence the organization was defrauded. By such negligence they failed to fulfill the <pb facs="5423968_7_0136.jpg" n="6"/>obligations constitutionally imposed upon them as officials, especially when they concealed the true financial status of the Polish Roman Catholic Union."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
