<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-03">Dec. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Remember Upper Silesia</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0945</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0945.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-03">Dec. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">LET US REMEMBER UPPER SILESIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We wish to remind you, you dear readers and friends, about the problem facing Upper Silesia.</p>
   <p>You know that the Silesia Insurrectionists' Alliance delegation is here in Chicago. It is conducting a drive to raise funds for its unfortunate widows and orphans who number about twenty thousand in Upper Silesia. The Germans do not wish to give any aid. They would rather see these poverty-stricken people wiped out by famine just like the Slovanians of old. At the present time these poor souls are threatened with the coming of a severe winter - an unwanted plague to the destitute. This is one of the main reasons why help should be given to this group from Silesia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0946.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Much anguish can be averted if aid reaches them as soon as possible. A helping hand to them is a helping hand to Poland!</p>
   <p>There is nothing to complain about this visiting group. The delegation from Upper Silesia has been cordially received by our people in Chicago. Many of them have offered unsolicited assistance. Party differences have been dropped, for all realize the importance of the work of this welfare committee. Help is being offered because our people realize the important part the people of Upper Silesia have played in having this land restored to Poland. It was their undying desire to be a part of Poland that brought about victory despite the many intrigues. Neither the false plebiscites, nor the Jewish-Anglo-German instigations could dampen the desire of these people who forced the issue to have the laws of Poland <pb facs="5423968_7_0947.jpg" n="3"/>recognized. By this resolution Poland has gained - this is only one-third of the Silesia territory - a parcel of land that possesses two-thirds of the economic riches of that region.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the aftermath of this issue brought three thousand widows, nearly fifteen thousand orphans, and about one thousand families into the hands of the Polish government. Many of them came from parts situated beyond the river Oder. As a grim consequence of all this, the Silesia delegation has been founded and has taken upon itself the responsibility of looking after these destitute people. In return for this help a solemn promise has been given that they will not stop their efforts until all the unfortunate souls are rehabilitated, until all the people of that region are instilled with the spirit of Polish patriotism, and until all of the land is recovered for Poland. This is certainly possible and entirely probable, for at some opportune time when the political issue is favorable the people may <pb facs="5423968_7_0948.jpg" n="4"/>declare themselves to be a part of Poland, not of Germany. No force will be able to deter the people from their wishes, no force will be able to keep them bound to the German shackles, no one will know how or wish to restrain, or deflower the freedom of these awakened but peaceful people.</p>
   <p>Therefore, let us support the Silesians! We can see that our work is not completed here, that the affair is not closed yet. If only this work could be finished for the benefit of the future. The only way to make this possible is to show the people of Silesia that Poland wants them, loves them, and remembers them. In return the people will strive eagerly to draw themselves into the arms of Poland. At this time there is no better opportunity than the present to offer aid to these destitute widows and orphans. The Insurrectionists' Alliance has sent the best representatives to our city. These men have given us their word of honor that the goods and money collected <pb facs="5423968_7_0949.jpg" n="5"/>will be accounted for and used in the most efficient way possible. Some of the prominent persons who vouch for the purpose of the drive are: Lieutenant Konieczny, commissioner of the Silesian plebiscite, Commander Hauke-Grzesik, chief of the delegation, who was the leader of the Silesian insurrection, and Dr. A. Mikolajczyk, although he does not hail from Silesia but from Little Poland, he has taken an important hand in the affair. The delegation has received the finest recommendation ever possible to attain from all the parties, political factions, government and church officials, and many prominent men of Poland. One of these prominent supporters is none other than the ever popular General Haller, protector of Warsaw during the Bolshevik encounter. General Haller was one of the first to favor this plan when his advice was sought about the possibilities of this delegation. He was the one who recommended them to come to America where many Polish people have founded their homes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0950.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Let us not wait until we are approached for contributions; let us not stint in our generosity; let us not deny the success of this purpose which the honorable General has become personally interested in. Let this example of General Haller spur us on in this direction; let us show them that we care and remember the poor people of Upper Silesia.</p>
   <p>Silesian nights are being held in our Polish neighborhoods of Chicago. Do not hesitate to attend them, but go there willingly and do not begrudge a donation. Bear in mind that this is for a very important cause, remember that the future of the remainder of Silesia, which two-thirds still belong to Germany,depends on the outcome of, this drive. Let our thoughts and our activity join together with patriotic tendencies toward the fatherland, which - as we are informed - does not want to give up what has been won in Upper Silesia and if for the present it must accept the Silesian <pb facs="5423968_7_0951.jpg" n="7"/>decision, it can plan for the future and promise to get the remainder of this territory. In another part of this issue we have published an answer from the National Silesian Organization, in Warsaw, whose president S. Belza also asks American Poles to support their cause. Read this beautiful letter and let it convince you.</p>
   <p>Give contributions for the Upper Silesian cause!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
