<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-05">Dec. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">An Upper Silesian Night Given at Town of Lake</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0938</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0938.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-05">Dec. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">AN UPPER SILESIAN NIGHT GIVEN AT TOWN OF LAKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An Upper Silesian Night, sponsored by the Julius Slowacki Library, was held last night at J. Slowacki's Hall, Paulina and 48th Streets. To this was added the celebration of the November Insurrection. D. Chojnacki, president of the library, opened the gala program. The chairman, W. Wrzesinski, gave a speech of welcome and introduction. A chorus group composed of the Lutnia, Filomeni, Druzyna, and Orleta choirs, under the direction of B. J. Zalewski, rendered a number of Polish songs that thrilled the capacity audience. Then the latter choir, which is made up of the younger Polish generation, sang "Jestem Sobie Polak Maly" (I Am A Small Pole).</p>
   <p>Miss Bordin, a vivacious schoolgirl, gave an impressive recitation of Poland, "Piekna Jest Ojczyzna Nasza" (Beautiful Is Our Motherland). She was followed by Captain Grzesika-Hauke, Chief of the Upper Silesia delegation, who gave a short sketch of the historical events that led to the uprising. Dr. A. Mikolajczyk was the second member of the delegation to take the stand. In his speech <pb facs="5423968_7_0939.jpg" n="2"/>of appeal, he begged the audience not to forget the destitute children and widows who are innocent victims of the insurrection.</p>
   <p>The songs of our own talented nightingale, Miss Jeannette Korolewicz-Wajdowa, were the highlights of the entire program. This gifted songbird sang a number of martial airs.</p>
   <p>The president of Group 39 of the Polish National Alliance, R. Kowaleski, gave an interesting talk on the spirit of helping, after which Miss L. Metler gave a declamation "Those Who Fought for Freedom." The remainder of the program was filled by the songs of the chorus, the speech on the pitiful conditions prevailing in Silesia by Louis Konieczny, and the showing of battle scenes of the insurrection with a commentary by Dr. Mikolajczyk. This pictorial review of the fight in Silesia impressed the entire audience. Nothing like it has ever been presented before. The ragged, the homeless, and the dying masses, all passed in review as the Polish doctor explained the conditions that had <pb facs="5423968_7_0940.jpg" n="3"/>brought about these appalling scenes.</p>
   <p>After the showing of the pictures, the entire assembly sang the Polish National anthem. The proceeds of the program and the collection brought over eight hundred dollars for the Silesian cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
