<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 1,
<date when="1916-01-05">Jan. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Telegram of Thanks to President Wilson for His Part in the Cause of Polish Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 1,
<date when="1916-01-05">Jan. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">TELEGRAM OF THANKS TO PRESIDENT WILSON FOR HIS PART IN THE CAUSE OF POLISH DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Below we give the full text of a telegram to President Wilson, which was sent out by the administrations of all Polish organizations, in the name of same, thanking him for his part in the cause of Polish Day.</p>
   <p>Honorable Woodrow Wilson</p>
   <p>President of the United States</p>
   <p>Washington, D. C.</p>
   <p>The undersigned duly elected representatives of organizations comprising a membership of over half a million of American citizens, have learned with gratification of the introduction by the Hon. John W. Kern, United States Senator from Indiana, ably seconded by the Hon. Harry Lane, United States Senator from Oregon, and of the unanimous passage by the United <pb facs="5423968_7_1119.jpg" n="2"/>States Senate, of a resolution calling attention to the situation in Poland and suggesting that the President of the United States designate a day during the holidays, on which contributions should be made for the relief of the sufferers in that country.</p>
   <p>We further learn with profound satisfaction of the prompt action of the President of the United States in is suing a proclamation designating January 1st, 1916, as the day upon which the people of the United States may make contributions to be transmitted to the American Red Cross at Washington.</p>
   <p>The organizations which we represent have, since the beginning of the war, exerted their utmost efforts for the raising of funds and extension of relief to the sufferers abroad. While it has been our earnest desire <pb facs="5423968_7_1120.jpg" n="3"/>to do the greatest share of this relief work, we gratefully welcome the humanitarian resolution of the United States Senate, and its instant approval by the President.</p>
   <p>Opportunity being afforded by the adoption of this resolution and the issuance of the proclamation, we deem it our duty to bring to the American people a realization of the magnitude of the calamity which has befallen this liberty-loving, innocently suffering, yet patient, nation. Its country has been made the scene of the most sanguinary and destructive conflict of all times; cities, towns and villages have been leveled to the ground; more than twenty-five million population consisting not only of Poles, but also their kin, the Lithuanians, Ruthenians and White Ruthenians have been made homeless. In this conflict they have been forced to make contributions in blood and treasure far greater than any other nation. Poland's babies, below <pb facs="5423968_7_1121.jpg" n="4"/>the age of eight years, have ceased to exist, her men have been slaughtered, serving in rival armies; the remaining old men, women and children, are now dying of starvation and exposure. All this, not of her making, not due to any declaration of war on her part but forced upon her without the approval or consent of her people.</p>
   <p>The generosity of the American nation in this instance shall not be misplaced. The Polish nation will survive even this, the greatest of all disasters and trials. From this baptism of blood, fire and pestilence, there will emerge a nation sanctified by misfortune and purified by suffering which will find ways and means in the future, not far distant, to give substantial expression of gratitude for the assistance rendered by the people of the United States throughout in this hour of greatest distress.</p>
   <p>We rejoice that the great humanitarian institution, the American Red Cross Society which has added so much to the glory of the United States throughout the world, by prompt and substantial relief in times of <pb facs="5423968_7_1122.jpg" n="5"/>distress and misfortune, has been selected as the recipient of these contributions. We most respectfully express our hope and desire that the General Committee for the Relief of Polish Victims, which has its headquarters at Vevey-Lausanne, Switzerland, of which Henryk Sienkiewicz and Ignace Paderewski are presidents, which is recognized by the vast majority of the Polish nation as their only national institution existing at the present time, will his instance, be invited to participate in the distribution of relief.</p>
   <p>We are authorized to transmit to you, Mr. President, our profound thanks and to assure you of the gratitude of the millions of sufferers across the sea, of the blessings of mothers of babies yet unborn, and of mothers of babies, whose innocent, starved little bodies, have filled a million graves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1123.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>And we, who cannot help but feel more keenly the great misfortune which has befallen our brethren on the other side, and who are a part of United States of America, believing that we express the sentiments of four millions of our co-residents here, take this means of expressing to you, Mr. President, our profound gratitude and deep appreciation of your prompt and generous conduct.</p>
   <p>Most respectfully,</p>
   <p>Polish National Alliance</p>
   <p>K. Zychlinski, President; J. S. Zawilinski, Secretary.</p>
   <p>Polish Roman-Catholic Union</p>
   <p>Peter Rostenkowski, President; J. S. Konopa, Secretary</p>
   <p>Polish Women's Alliance</p>
   <p>Anna Neuman, President; Emily Napieralski, Secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1124.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Polish Falcons Alliance</p>
   <p>Dr. Starzynski, President; T. Smulski, Secretary.</p>
   <p>Polish Alma Mater</p>
   <p>Julian J. Nejman, President; M. Brohocki, Secretary.</p>
   <p>Polish Union of America</p>
   <p>Dr. R. Tenerowicz, President; J. Dembiec, Secretary.</p>
   <p>Polish National Council</p>
   <p>S. Adamkiewicz, President.</p>
   <p>Polish Central Relief Committee</p>
   <p>T. M. Helinski, President; S. Osada, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
