<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-10-17">Oct. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal of the Poles to the People of the United States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1243</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1243.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-10-17">Oct. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL OF THE POLES TO THE PEOPLE OF THE UNITED STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are all living today in dread and terror as we listen to the news from the lands plunged in war. We must admit that, even in our wildest fantasies, until recently we could not have imagined such a hell as Europe is today for her unfortunate inhabitants.</p>
   <p>Poland, torn between Prussia, Austria, and Russia, with her twenty-five million Polish people--the most unfortunate of all in Europe--finds herself in the worst hell.</p>
   <p>This land, from almost the first moment of the outbreak of the war, has been the theater of war for the million-strong enemy armies, the destructive waves of which have already passed over the same territory many times. Where once there were populated cities and blossoming hamlets gleaming in the sun, now there are ruins, smoldering fires, and ashes, in which lie the corpses of women, old men, and children who died of starvation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1244.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The world knows a great deal about the horrors of war within Belgian territory. Entire columns in the American press are filled with descriptions of the destruction raging there. Nothing is written about what has happened and is happening in Poland. The press is not allowed to describe this theater of war.</p>
   <p>The world knows that Kalisz was burned by the Prussians and Jaroslaw by the Austrians, but it knows nothing about the thousands of blossoming hamlets which have been burned down to the ground. It does not know that the armies have taken all of the horses from this agricultural country, that they have slaughtered all of the cattle for meat for the soldiers, so that now there is not a drop of milk for hundreds of thousands of Polish children and infants.</p>
   <p>All of the produce of the land is rotting in the fields because the war came before the harvest was finished. A million Polish farm hands were called away to bear Prussian and Austrian guns and murder their own brothers who had been forced <pb facs="5423968_7_1245.jpg" n="3"/>into the Russian ranks.</p>
   <p>The Frenchman, the Englishman, the Belgian, and even the German have at least this consolation in the war, that they are defending their own countries. The Pole is the most unfortunate of all because in the Austrian army, as well as the Prussian and the Russian, he is fighting for the benefit of the country which has been oppressing him for a century and a half and every few moments he is committing fratricide.</p>
   <p>Those who dared protest against these commands--criminal from the Polish point of view--were soon silenced. The rest were terrorized by seeing the corpses of thousands who had complained.</p>
   <p>Armies pass from one end of this land to the other. Who knows how much longer they will continue to trample it. Such destitution is coming over the land as other fortunate nations cannot even imagine.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1246.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>France and Belgium, though trampled by German boots, are rich countries: they have their own governments and powerful friends who have already come with immediate help to alleviate their destitution. Only Poland is abandoned by all. Every government in this land is an enemy; and the most painful defeat in all Galicia was inflicted on the Polish people by the government which was the least unfriendly of all, the Austrian Government, because it not only took away the men but also took away the cattle and paid for them with "script" which, now that Russia has occupied this territory, has no value.</p>
   <p>The letters which are beginning to come to the three million Poles in America are filled with such despair that they tear one's heart. All Polish families in America have both close and distant relatives engulfed by the war and hurled into absolute destitution and hunger. We have already organized relief work. Every Pole is giving and will give as much as he can possibly afford; we will give up everything we can in order to rescue our brethren. Their destitution, however, <pb facs="5423968_7_1247.jpg" n="5"/>is so boundless that our help will be like a drop in the sea of this misfortune.</p>
   <p>At this time, which is so inexpressibly difficult for us--a time when everyone has abandoned unfortunate Poland--we United States citizens of Polish ancestry always loyal to our adopted country, have organized the Polish Central Relief Committee. We appeal to our fellow citizens, and to all the people of the prosperous, fortunate, and free United States. We beg for help.</p>
   <p>Our ancestors, Kosciusko, Pulaski, and many others, shed their blood for the freedom of this country. Poland, the "knight of the nations," hurried to battle wherever in the world a war was being fought for liberty. Now, the people of this unfortunate land, crushed by war, are dying without anyone coming to their aid.</p>
   <p>Surely the hearts of the noble people of the United States cannot remain indifferent to the terrible fate of our brothers over there in Europe! We believe that the people of this fortunate country, deeply moved by our voice, <pb facs="5423968_7_1248.jpg" n="6"/>will not deny help to our nation caught in the vortex of war, but will help us dig it out of the ruins and ashes.</p>
   <p>Help! Aid! Do not tolerate or permit the destruction of such a noble nation!</p>
   <p>God, who guides the fates of all nations, will repay you for this a hundredfold.</p>
   <p>We acknowledge all contributions in our publication, Free Poland, which is the herald of the Polish cause in this country.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Polish Central Relief Committee</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
