<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-11-13">Nov. 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Organization Meeting of the Polish Social Workers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-11-13">Nov. 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZATION MEETING OF THE POLISH SOCIAL WORKERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are in Chicago every thirty Polish welfare workers employed in the Bureau of Immigration, in the United Charities, in the Juvenile Court in hospitals etc. Feeling that their work among Polish people will be more efficient if they will be organized, they called a meeting at the assembly hall of the School of Civics and Philanthropy, 110 N. Michigan Ave., on Sunday, November 9th. The following workers were present: Mrs. Evans, from the Social department of the Crane Co.; Misses Fabrycki, and Matuszewski, nurses of the County Hospital; Mr.Chmielewski, from the Department of Health; E. Napieralska, vice-president of the Advisory Committee of the United Charities; Miss J. Rzeszotarski, of the Northwestern University Settlement; H. Zegar, School inspector; J. Franciszek, W. Jablonski, L. Kamassa, M. Netzel and E. Skorupa, from the Infant Welfare Society; A. Jablonska, H. Olszewska, J. Maliszewska, Paszkiewicz, Pawlak, A. Schultz, Sleszynski, Zielinski and Zegar, from the United Charities; Mrs. Zakatis and W. Reszkowski, probate officers; Rev. Spetz, T. Szmergalski, and J. Skibinski. Rev. Spetz was elected chairman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1296.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After a short introductory speech he called on Mr. Szmergalski who explained in detail the purpose of the meeting and the importance of its work. He said that organized social workers will be able to give better and more efficient service to needy Polish people among whom they are working.</p>
   <p>After prolonged discussion the new officers were elected: Rev. A Spetz, president, and J. Skibinski, secretary. The next meeting was voted to take place on November 23rd, at the Eckardt Park pavilion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
