<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-11-04">Nov. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Poorest of the Poor--A Word about Polish Orphans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-11-04">Nov. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE POOREST OF THE POOR--A WORD ABOUT POLISH ORPHANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The general attention of the Polish people is now turned toward the bloody historic drama which is being enacted in our homeland. Our thoughts turn in this direction; our hearts beat faster in the hope of a better future.</p>
   <p>The war and the hopes of the Poles connected with it absorb our strength and thought, but in spite of everything else we should not forget our needs here among the immigrants.</p>
   <p>There are many of these needs, and among the first is the care of the poorest of the poor. These are the Polish orphans who ask our help, our tender care, which is to take the place of that of their own parents.</p>
   <p>In beautiful surroundings, outside the city of Chicago, at a place called Niles, beyond the resting place of the dead, on a strip of level land stands the Polish Orphanage--which houses more than four hundred Polish orphans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0580.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These new buildings are now under construction in order to meet the demands and to receive the poor Polish orphans constantly seeking admission. This work is being carried out by Polish contractors. Our Polish parishes are financing it.</p>
   <p>In order to help this Christian cause, Polish societies have organized the Polish Orphans' Welfare Society, which for almost two years has been increasing its activity among the Chicago Poles, thanks to the sincere support of the Polish press and the gratuitous work of the officers of this society.</p>
   <p>The following organizations sponsor this society: Polish National Alliance, Polish Roman Catholic Union, Polish Women's Alliance, Circuit 2 of the Alliance of Polish Falcons, Catholic Order of Foresters.</p>
   <p>All these organizations, through their representatives, are engaged in collecting the necessary funds. Thanks to this work many thousands of <pb facs="5423968_7_0581.jpg" n="3"/>dollars have come into the treasury of the Polish orphans.</p>
   <p>There are many ways of collecting this fund, such as tags on Memorial Day, balls, excursions, subscription lists, etc.</p>
   <p>A few months ago appeals for help were sent out to all of the more influential Poles. A list of honorary supporting members was made. Unfortunately this appeal was a disappointment, because not even a hundred people replied and made a contribution. We did not demand very much, only a dollar from our people. Unfortunately less than a hundred dollars was collected by this means. The postage itself on the circulars cost more. It is sad but true that our people are not yet sufficiently interested in one of the most important of our social welfare institutions.</p>
   <p>The[Polish Orphans']Welfare Society, nevertheless, continues in the hope that the number of its supporters will increase--that the help which is so <pb facs="5423968_7_0582.jpg" n="4"/>badly needed will be forthcoming.</p>
   <p>All contributions will be announced in the press.</p>
   <p>At present the Polish Orphans' Welfare Society announces to the public that on November 11 it will arrange a social evening at the large hall of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. The entire proceeds will go to the cause for which it is working gratuitously.</p>
   <p>In order to interest more of our Poles in this social evening, several hundred invitations, together with tickets, have been sent out, and two hundred of our most influential Polish people have been invited to be honorary patrons.</p>
   <p>Money for the tickets and replies to the invitations are slowly beginning to come in. We hope that no one will deny the Polish orphans his support.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0583.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The social evening promises to be interesting; the committee is working with a will in order to make it a success and to make it really the attraction of the season.</p>
   <p>We will announce further details tomorrow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
