<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-21">Dec. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Hospital in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0542</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0542.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-21">Dec. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH HOSPITAL IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The project of organizing a Polish Hospital in Chicago--first contemplated about two years ago by a group of Polish doctors and now revived by the Sisters of Nazareth, as is evident from the article published yesterday, Wednesday, December 20, in our paper--is coming closer to realization. Of course, it is quite a distance from that. Many troublesome matters stand in the way, but the object is so worthy and important and our young people have shown so much life lately, that we do not doubt that it will eventually be completed.</p>
   <p>We have time and again argued the necessity of and the benefits to be derived from such a Polish hospital. It is useless to repeat our arguments, which no doubt are well known to all. Here we wish to point out to the Poles of Chicago their duty in respect to the efforts being made by these good women. With tenacity of purpose and individual sacrifices (the Sisters of Nazareth are offering space for the hospital in their own Home), they will bring this <pb facs="5423968_7_0543.jpg" n="2"/>charitable project to a successful conclusion. But they should be able to call on the support of our whole Polish community. The project will benefit all of us, therefore we should all help along the good cause. We have many burdens; many projects have been started which await completion; times are hard, that is all true. Still we haven't the right to shy at sacrifices for this purpose. Hard times will not last forever. The number of poor people will diminish. Work begun will be completed. And then, perhaps even today, all those who are able to do so should consider it their duty to help this project for humanity and the relief of suffering. This Polish hospital will become a reality, built from the widow's mite and other small offerings donated by everybody, and then it will bring us great benefits.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
