<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-10">Dec. 10, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal of the Polish National Committee to the Polish-American Citizens</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Letter)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0909</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0909.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-10">Dec. 10, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL OF THE POLISH NATIONAL COMMITTEE TO THE POLISH-AMERICAN CITIZENS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Letter)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fellow-Countrymen! For over ten months we have not turned to you with public problems. There were many reasons for this--one of the most important being that Poland, after passing her crisis, had entered a period of reconstruction and, as a result, did not need help, especially from her emigrants, as she did during the years of the War.</p>
   <p>However, now that the country is back to normal and relations have been established, great signs of want are beginning to be uncovered that give rise to a problem the solution of which requires the assistance of the Poles in America. Because of this, many pleas for aid are reaching our shores from across the sea. Appeals for contributions for educational and social purposes have been pouring in.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0910.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These pleas uncover the gravity of the situation, which is, in fact, so grave that it has become a problem to the Poles the world over. During the past year, the Poles living out of Poland, especially those in the United States, have been vitally concerned about this and have tackled this problem with great enthusiasm and sincere idealism. The problem which touched their hearts the most was the one of the unfortunate orphans.</p>
   <p>We have actually torn away four hundred motherless children from the Siberian wastes where they were being Russianized. These children were brought to this country, where they found refuge in our institutions. Now that there is no obstacle to prevent their return to Poland, work must be started to make this possible.</p>
   <p>We must send these children back to Poland, purchase a large plot of ground, build a home for them, and set aside a fund that will give them a start. This <pb facs="5423968_7_0911.jpg" n="3"/>plan, once under way, could be easily taken over by the Polish government and society. In this way, the problem of these Siberian orphans would be solved. When this is realized, then we can say that we have ended our work honorably.</p>
   <p>In order to do this, large funds are required, not only for the repatriation of these homeless children, but for many other national, educational, and economic needs, including a defense fund for Poland. We cannot remain deaf to these needs.</p>
   <p>Years ago we gave more frequently and ten times as much. Let us give now; less--because we are poorer now--but let us not forget to give.</p>
   <p>Let us give with the same heartfelt feeling that characterized the immigrants before the freedom of Poland, when they lived only with the thought of their motherland in their minds.</p>
   <p>Let us make our contributions with sincerity, from the heart; let us make them as large as we can afford.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0912.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Let us all do our share and not shun our duty. Our support will enable the Polish National Committee to be successful in its Christmas campaign, which will start the fifteenth of this month.</p>
   <p>The Administrative Council of the Polish National Committee:</p>
   <p>John F. Smulski, president</p>
   <p>K. Zychlinski, vice-president</p>
   <p>Dr. B. L. Smykowski, vice-president</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Szwajkart, secretary</p>
   <p>N. L. Piotrowski, treasurer</p>
   <p>F. B. Celichowski</p>
   <p>Anna Neuman</p>
   <p>R. Piatkowski</p>
   <p>Francis Piekarski</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Pitass</p>
   <p>J. F. Sawicki</p>
   <p>Reverend L. Grudzinski</p>
   <p>S. T. Zwierzchowski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
