<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-18">Mar. 18, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Opera Star to Take Part in Benefit Concert for the Poles of Nebraska</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1387</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1387.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-18">Mar. 18, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH OPERA STAR TO TAKE PART IN BENEFIT CONCERT FOR THE POLES OF NEBRASKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are very pleased to announce pleasant news to our readers today.</p>
   <p>The well-known Polish opera star, Miss Mira Heller, of Lwow, who is appearing with a company of French-Italian opera singers at the Auditorium in Chicago, has consented to appear at a benefit concert staged by the Poles of Chicago.</p>
   <p>This arrangement was effected by one of the Polish benevolent societies planning the concert. The concert will take place on Sunday, March 24. The proceeds will be divided between the destitute Poles of Nebraska and the Polish Hospital of Chicago.</p>
   <p>A special committee has been chosen to make all the plans, and all indications show that this is being done speedily and energetically.</p>
   <p>The committee is made up of the following:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1388.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Countess Lubienska, Judge M. A. La Buy, Peter Kiolbassa, Mr. Leszczynski, J. F. Smulski, S. Szwajkart, M. Drzemala, C. Budkiewicz, Count Komorowski, S. Zahajkiewicz, H. Nagiel, Dr. Czupka, and S. Barczewski.</p>
   <p>Further particulars, namely, price of admission, program, etc., will be given later.</p>
   <p>Perhaps it will be possible to have other talented Polish individuals appear on the program.</p>
   <p>This evening at half past seven the special committee will hold a meeting, and all members are invited to attend.</p>
   <p>In every respect this is interesting and pleasant news. Sincere thanks should be extended to the talented Polish star for her willingness to take part in this benefit concert.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Although this is an announcement of a future event, <pb facs="5423968_7_1389.jpg" n="3"/>plans, representative individuals, and the reason for the concert are given. The committee, etc., are not listed.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
