<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-09">Dec. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Drive Sponsored by the Polish National Committee Attracts Attention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0920</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0920.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-09">Dec. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">DRIVE SPONSORED BY THE POLISH NATIONAL COMMITTEE ATTRACTS ATTENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p/>
   <p>News of the proposed thirty-day campaign to raise a quarter million dollars, sponsored by the Polish National Committee, has been spread throughout every Polish locality in the United States and has received great attention.</p>
   <p>Some of the Polish communities in America have already sent in news of their plans to support the drive. Welfare committees that have experience in this kind of work have been holding meetings and mapping out plans.</p>
   <p>One of the first and post enthusiastic responses came from our patriotic organizations. Their replies have shown great interest in the campaign.</p>
   <p>In localities where the patriotic committees had ceased to function, new life has been instilled as a result of this drive. Letters from the office <pb facs="5423968_7_0921.jpg" n="2"/>of the Secretary of the campaign reveal that many dormant patriotic societies have come to life and are functioning better than ever.</p>
   <p>These early enthusiastic responses reveal that this drive will be a total success. The final steps for returning the orphans who were brought to this country and placed in orphan asylumns, to their native Poland, where they will be raised to become upright citizens, have been undertaken.</p>
   <p>Activity at the headquarters of the Polish National Committee can be compared to a beehive. Instructions, plans, buttons, placards and many other preparations are being made and sent out by the Committee. These promising early replies have acted as an added incentive to get the campaign under way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
