<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-17">Sept. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Roman Catholic Union and Aid to Poland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0979</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0979.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-17">Sept. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION AND AID TO POLAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last plenary meeting, held on Tuesday, September 10, 1918, the central administration of the Polish Roman Catholic Union decided unanimously to issue to all its members the following appeal relative to amassing a ten million dollar relief fund for war-torn Poland!</p>
   <p>Members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union:</p>
   <p>Two weeks ago there was held, in Detroit, a historical convention of the Polish people in America, at which it was unanimously decided to amass, in the shortest time possible, ten million dollars for the starving people in our motherland, for the needs of the Polish army, and for the liberation of Poland from her present state of servitude.</p>
   <p>This sum is neither in excess of our ability nor is it in the realm of <pb facs="5423968_7_0980.jpg" n="2"/>impossibility to raise, when one considers that there are over four million Poles in America, and that we are living in a time of unusual events. It must be remembered that we are living in a time when the fate of Europe and America, as well as that of Poland, is now upon the scales of history, at a time when the United States has placed everything it possesses, the lives of its citizens and all its material resources, in this great battle with the autocratic and diabolically proud Prussian forces, that democracy and the liberation of free nations now under the brutal military heel of the aggressive Germans, and hence the liberation of Poland, might be realized and brought to a successful conclusion.</p>
   <p>In view of events of such great importance, can we Poles truthfully say to ourselves that we have conscientiously performed our duty in the same measure as those who left for the battlefields, sacrificing upon the altar of liberty that which is most dear to man--his life? Consequently, we who have remained at home must exert ourselves financially and fulfill our duty to the very <pb facs="5423968_7_0981.jpg" n="3"/>end in the same proportion.</p>
   <p>The payment of a voluntary national assessment is the duty of every right thinking Pole. This duty should be considered as a sacrifice. These contributions should be given not from an individual's surplus funds. It should be as an expression of real exertion, with a self denial of certain luxuries.</p>
   <p>The Polish Roman Catholic Union is true to its motto and traditions. In its desire to bring assistance to war-devastated Poland, the organization, through its representatives, decided to impose a twenty-five cent tax on each member. The money so collected is to aid the sufferers of our motherland. This momentuous decision was arrived at during the last convention of the organization. In view of the fact that the need is immediate and cannot be delayed, therefore, it is urgently requested that, instead of this monthly assessment of twenty-five cents, the members make a voluntary <pb facs="5423968_7_0982.jpg" n="4"/>single annual payment of not less than three dollars. This does not mean, however, that those who are in a position to pay five, ten, twenty-five, one hundred or more dollars should limit themselves to only three dollars. On the contrary, let everyone give according to his or her means. We should not adopt the attitude of giving only that which is in excess to our need. This contribution should be one of real exertion and self-denial of certain luxuries and pleasures. True, in this more than one hundred thousand membership of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, there will be some to whom a contribution of three dollars per year will be difficult--although this number is comparatively small. People who are really poor will be excused from such assessment if they themselves declare that conditions do not permit them to make such sacrifices. We do, however, believe that the Polish Roman Catholic Union, as a whole, will not be satisfied with the payment of three dollars per year only, but will willingly give more than that. Many will give five, ten,one hundred dollars and more. It is for our motherland, a homeland resurrecting from its grave of oppression and devastation, a land of our ancestors calling to the true sons of Poland to give it aid and <pb facs="5423968_7_0983.jpg" n="5"/>assistance in her moment of dire need. Those who have Liberty bonds and wish to donate them toward the Polish cause may do so in lieu of money.</p>
   <p>The central administration of the Polish Roman Catholic Union requests that individual societies which are affiliated with that organization and which have a proper fund on hand, make a contribution out of such funds.</p>
   <p>The names of members, as well as individual societies, and the sums contributed by them will be announced in the official organ of the organization, the Narod Polski. In addition to that, their names will be inscribed in a special list, which will be given to the Polish National Museum, where it will be kept in eternal commemoration.</p>
   <p>Those who, in spite of their economic well-being and considerable income, attempt to avoid the payment of their share of the assessment, or endeavor to evade the issue by a payment of a small amount or who, in their intent <pb facs="5423968_7_0984.jpg" n="6"/>to cover their miserliness and ill will, grumble and, by making false statements, harm the cause, commit thereby an unpardonable national trangression. People of that type should never be permitted to hold any high or honorable public office, and they should be characterized as dissenters.</p>
   <p>Trusting that this appeal will find its way into the hearts of the good-thinking members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, we wish to remain,</p>
   <p>Fraternally yours,</p>
   <p>Reverend B. Celichowski, chaplain.</p>
   <p>Reverend F. M. Wojtalewicz, vice-chaplain.</p>
   <p>N. L. Piotrowski, president.</p>
   <p>Dr. B. L. Smykowski, vice-president.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Agnes Klawitter, vice-president.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0985.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Ignace Wroblewski, financial secretary.</p>
   <p>Leon Zamorski, treasurer.</p>
   <p>In order to set a good example for others and, at the same time, fulfill their obligations, the members of the central administration of the Polish Roman Catholic Union made the following contributions to the Polish Aid Fund:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>N. L. Piotrowski</cell>
     <cell>$500.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Reverend B. Celichowski</cell>
     <cell>200.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Reverend B. L. Smykowski</cell>
     <cell>100.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mrs. A. Klawitter</cell>
     <cell>100.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>John Zielinski</cell>
     <cell>100.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>L. Zamorski</cell>
     <cell>50.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>J. Czekala</cell>
     <cell>50.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>J. Pionke (Former Director)</cell>
     <cell>50.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0986.jpg" n="8"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>B. Golaszewski</cell>
     <cell>$ 25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>P. Jurczak</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>J. Janowiak</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>A. Kosko</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>S. Lachajczak</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>F. Lojkiewicz</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>W. Skoczylas</cell>
     <cell>15.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mrs. M. Turalska</cell>
     <cell>15.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mrs. K. Karpinska</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mrs. K. Chamska</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mrs. T. Twarogowska</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mrs. A. Jozwiakowska</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>M. Chubinski</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>A. Blaskow</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>S. Stefanowicz</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>F. Nejman</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>I. Wroblewski</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
