<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-05">Jan. 5, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Hospital of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0517</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0517.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-05">Jan. 5, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH HOSPITAL OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the present time when the New Year has just begun, when stock of last year's activity has not been completed, I wish to recall to the mind of our Polish society of Chicago the Polish Hospital, which was organized by the Sisters of Nazareth about a year ago. I am not going to bring to light the needs and usefulness of this institution. Everyone of us is familiar and aware of its advantages.</p>
   <p>When this hospital was organized, the general Polish public not only gave it recognition and support, but also did not spare any material assistance, and willingly hurried to give it aid.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, this ardent support for so noble a cause soon cooled. Today the Polish people have practically forgotten that the Polish Hospital exists, that it needs our help. It is very simple to play upon our feelings. As soon as someone makes known someone's misfortunes and needs, generous gifts and <pb facs="5423968_7_0518.jpg" n="2"/>contributions come from everywhere to give succor to the stricken. But alas, we are not systematic with our donations.</p>
   <p>We burst forth like an ignited match, which quickly gives a bright glow and as quickly burns out, only to let our fire quickly pass away. This is the picture of our generosity. It is simple for us to create something on the spur of the moment, but it is difficult for us to continue to support this new creation. In this respect we can compare our nature with that of a woman who cries easily because of sentimental reasons, but cannot continue to cherish this sentiment for long, that is, to retain the first impression and noble impulse to the end.</p>
   <p>We virtually pass from one thing to another with unbelievable levity. Today we abandon for new things the things we ardently supported yesterday, only to drop them on the morrow for newer ones.</p>
   <p>This holds true for our Polish Hospital. Our support is gradually cooling.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0519.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And yet this institution has accomplished a great good. During the short existence of this hospital, fifty-five persons were under its care, twenty-eight of whom were cared for free of charge. At the present time there are ten patients. Every doctor on the hospital's staff is at their disposal. The hospital is conducted under the best order and is scrupulously clean. The Nazareth Sisters do not spare any trouble or work, and are devoutly attached to their duties of caring for the sick. The ailing not only find tender care during their sickness but also moral support, something that at times is of greater value. Each patient hears sweet words of solace and courage which cannot be found in other hospitals.</p>
   <p>Honor and recognition is due a hundredfold to these worthy caretakers. But recognition is not their only due; active support, material aid from the general Polish public is also necessary.</p>
   <p>It is the purpose of this article to remind the Polish people. It is hoped that this reminder will strike at the appropriate time. The New Year has just started.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0520.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Only recently we have distributed gifts during Christmas. Is it justifiable to forget during this distribution the exceptional work of the Polish Hospital? No! On the contrary, it is believed that the Polish people will recall to themselves their duty during this New Year. They will come to realize their laxity, and once again they will not stint on their aid to the hospital. Let us be merciful and the Lord will reward us a hundredfold for our every contribution given in the name of mercy. Above all, let our more prosperous countrymen not forget this Polish institution. Let all our Polish societies offer donations, even if it is only a few dollars. No one will become poor because of this kindness, and at the same time these offerings will be of great help and the purpose of the hospital will be fulfilled.</p>
   <p>Let masses of people come to the assistance of this worthy institution, but not those that always carry the burdens of beneficence; let the masses be constant in their support.</p>
   <p>Could not a few pennies go toward the support of the Polish Hospital along with <pb facs="5423968_7_0521.jpg" n="5"/>the large offerings and collections for other causes? Only through constant support will this institution be able to fulfill its intended purposes and strive for better and bigger accomplishments in the future.</p>
   <p>"Let us be merciful and we will attain mercy" (sic). The Polish Hospital has been erected under such a concept, and in case of need requires our mercy.</p>
   <p>B. Klarkowski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
