<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-14">Dec. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Roman Catholic Union</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0196</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0196.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-14">Dec. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Public notice is hereby given to all readers of the Dziennik Zwiazkowy and to members of the Polish National Alliance that, in regard to the deficit found in the Polish Roman Catholic Union, this newspaper will present only well-established facts. It is not the wish of this paper to be accused of ill will toward another Polish organization. The only facts that will be printed are those that have been clearly proved. Personal comments will be withheld until the entire matter has been clarified and settled. This newspaper wishes harm to no one. Although ill will was found to exist on various occasions on the part of those who were at the head of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, there is no desire for vengeance or ill will in our hearts. On the contrary, the Polish National Alliance wishes that the Polish Roman Catholic Union may be able to lift itself out of the difficulty it now is in.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0197.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The thing of utmost importance is not the individuals standing at the head and managing the funds of the organization so carelessly. We are, however, concerned about the tens of thousands of our people who were insured with the Union and placed all their hopes in it. They are the ones whom we pity. No harm should befall them. Decency demands that even when fighting our opponents we should use noble weapons; hence, conclusions should not be arrived at before all the facts are investigated. This matter has received a great deal of notoriety and therefore it will probably be clarified completely and the guilty ones punished. The Dziennik Zwiazkowy, therefore, waits and requests everyone to be patient. The truth will out at some time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
