<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 33,
<date when="1914-08-19">Aug. 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Fable and Not a Fable</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0384</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0384.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 33,
<date when="1914-08-19">Aug. 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">FABLE AND NOT A FABLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Three travelers were walking through a forest during the night and the night was very dark. They glanced over the heavens to see if at least one star is shining for them but they did not see any.</p>
   <p>One of them noticed a light and ran toward it with such haste that he even did not watch out where he was. Those were firebugs hovering over a swamp. He fell into the swamp and was lost forever.</p>
   <p>The second traveler again noticed a light in another direction. He ran as fast as he could and reached it, and these were wolves, who tore him apart.</p>
   <p>The third one went another way and came upon a plain. Here he espied in a certain home a light. When he came up to it, there he was willingly received, given a chair, warm supper and a comfortable rest, where he felt fortunate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0385.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To these three travelers one can compare us Poles living in America.</p>
   <p>The first one who fell in the swamp, that is, the one who allowed himself to be "insured" in a certain company and was deceived.</p>
   <p>The second one who got himself among the wolves, he is the one who got himself into the hands of fraudulent agents, who go from house to house writing people up into some sort of organization, and when they get a member and his money, then they disappear without a trace.</p>
   <p>The third who came up to the real light, that is, the one who wrote himself up in the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, where he was not disappointed because in that organization he found real protection and help.</p>
   <p>The Union numbers over 80,000 members, grouped in 850 societies, and in their treasury they have close to one and a half million dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
