<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-07">Mar. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Constitution Adopted by the Polish Welfare Association Put into Effect</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0341</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0341.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-07">Mar. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">CONSTITUTION ADOPTED BY THE POLISH WELFARE ASSOCIATION PUT INTO EFFECT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The delayed meeting of the Polish Welfare Association was held yesterday afternoon at the Polish school hall at Bradley Street near Noble. The board of directors formally accepted the constitution that was formulated some time ago, and officially proclaimed its adoption. All the amendments will be carried out to the letter. A general announcement will be made to the public by means of circulars. The handbills will also inform the people of the purpose of the welfare organization.</p>
   <p>On the twentieth of this month a public meeting will be held at which a general reading of the constitution will be given. A second meeting of this kind will be held on March 27, and a third on April 3. The purpose of these meetings is to get a general acceptance of the constitution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0342.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Beginning today, the financial secretary has official right to accept donations and gifts. The secretary's office hours will be made known to the public tomorrow. Offerings by mail and in person will be greatly welcomed.</p>
   <p>The people are warned to be on the lookout for agents who pose as representatives of the Polish Welfare Association. They are impostors. As yet no one has been appointed to canvass the homes for contributions. The police should be notified if any attempts to collect money are made. A general notice will be given when solicitors from the welfare office will be put out into the field.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
