<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-19">Jan. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago City Council Comes to Poland's Aid</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-19">Jan. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO CITY COUNCIL COMES TO POLAND'S AID</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Alderman Stanley H. Kunz, together with Aldermen C. F. Petkoski, John Szymkowski, and Stanley Walkowiak, has presented the following resolution before the City Council at its meeting on Monday, January 18, 1915:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The European war from its very beginning is being waged in part upon the territories of a former Polish nation, which territories are divided among three nations, Germany, Austria, and Russia, all of them conducting war against each other; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The flower of the Polish youth is the most innocent and the most burdened victim of the war, thrown against their will in the fighting columns so that one kills the other and their wives and children, and all unable to bear arms are destined to starvation and their homes burned and property confiscated; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Thousands will have to die of cold and hunger before aid comes to <pb facs="5423968_7_1169.jpg" n="2"/>so many victims of the war from noncombatant nations; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, human instinct itself demands that the citizenry of the city of Chicago, regardless of faith and nationality, come forth with a generous assistance for those suffering so terribly; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, All Polish organizations in the city of Chicago, with the Polish National Alliance at their head, in accordance to the City Council's decree, will, on the days of January 23 and 24 of 1915, conduct a tag day throughout the entire city of Chicago, the City Council, therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolves, That the Mayor of the City, together with all members of the Council, issue a proclamation to all citizens and businessmen to support this undertaking generously, hurrying to the support of the unfortunate Poland.</p>
   <p>"Be it further resolved that the Mayor of the City appoint a special committee of prominent citizens to collect contributions from large firms and <pb facs="5423968_7_1170.jpg" n="3"/>corporations for assistance to war victims in Poland."</p>
   <p>The Hon. C. Harrison, Mayor of Chicago, presented the resolution for immediate consideration and obtained wide support for it. After a strong plea by Alderman Kunz, the City Council adopted the resolution unanimously.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
