<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-02-16">Feb. 16, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Welfare Association's Membership Continues to Swell</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-02-16">Feb. 16, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH WELFARE ASSOCIATION'S MEMBERSHIP CONTINUES TO SWELL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Welfare Association, officially organized last Sunday to aid poverty stricken Poles, has finally completed a program to be followed during the present year. A committee of twenty-one directors has been elected to execute the resolutions adopted at a meeting held Sunday after-noon at the New Polish hall. The board of directors have already chosen the assistants to aid them in their work. Out of the large crowd that came, sixty people joined the welfare organization.</p>
   <p>The organization of this society is an important step forward. The execution of the adopted resolutions did not end with the first few meetings; therefore, it is necessary to continue these gatherings over a period of time. The problem of alleviating the critical situation of our poor will be discussed at future sessions, when solutions will be offered.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1541.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Sunday's meeting has placed this organization on a good footing. The road for its success looks very bright.</p>
   <p>Important resolutions passed at the gathering are as follows:</p>
   <p>1. The name of the society shall be:</p>
   <p>Polish Welfare Association No. 1 of Chicago, Illinois, located at St. Stanislaus Kostki's parish.... The organization will be placed under the guidance of St. John.</p>
   <p>2. The aim of the society will be to practice Christian kindness among the unfortunate, especially our own people in the vicinity of St. Stanilaus Kostki's parish. The activities of the association may be extended to other Polish parishes and neighborhoods in Chicago by the organization of groups sanctioned by the central board. Polish societies in the city can do their share by following the example of this organization, that is, they can name a committee to enroll members at a dollar per person. Members may pay a dollar every quarter, or four dollars for the whole year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1542.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Those not wishing to belong to this welfare association, or those not having the means to pay, are urged to contribute as much as they can afford. Money, food, and clothing will be welcome at all times.</p>
   <p>The Intelligence Bureau is working on plans to find employment for the able-bodied needy. As soon as this department completes its study of the needs of the poor, it will be ready to offer assistance. The time will be announced.</p>
   <p>By the aid of ballots, Father Vincent Barzynski was elected president; Victor Bardonski, first vice-president; Thomas Krolik, second vice-president and financial secretary; Stanislaus Szwajkart, secretary; Jacob Mucha, cashier; Paul Ratkowski, visiting case worker; and Wladislaus Nowaczewski, guardian.</p>
   <p>The next meeting of directors will be held February 24 at 8 P.M. at the parish hall. The question of a permanent place for the financial office will be decided.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1543.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>At the present time, the twenty-one members at the board of directors do their work without pay.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
