<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-21">Jan. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Mayor Harrison's Proclamation Summons People to Contribute--Appointment of Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-21">Jan. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">MAYOR HARRISON'S PROCLAMATION SUMMONS PEOPLE TO CONTRIBUTE--APPOINTMENT OF COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Mayor of Chicago, Carter Harrison, issued the expected proclamation on January 20, 1915, to all the people of Chicago. In it he urges every one to make contributions on the tag days on behalf of our war-afflicted people in Poland. The Mayor's proclamation is as follows:</p>
   <p>"Among those suffering because of the European war, which destroys nations and thousands of people, no one suffers greater misery and needs more aid than the Poles who remain under the control of the main warring countries, that is, Germany, Russia, and Austria. The flower of the Polish nation constitutes the first lines of the armies of these combating powers. Polish families are doomed to starvation and are exposed to all the horrors of war. Thousands <pb facs="5423968_7_1166.jpg" n="2"/>perish of starvation and lack of shelter. A plea to help these unfortunate people comes to us residents of Chicago. The Polish National Alliance has undertaken to conduct tag days on January 23 and 24 for the benefit of [the Poles in Europe].</p>
   <p>"I therefore, Carter H. Harrison, Mayor of the City of Chicago, by the power granted me by a resolution of the City Council appeal to the citizens of Chicago to contribute to the creation and the augmentation of a fund in behalf of this worthy nation. I hereby nominate a committee composed of citizens of Chicago, which committee shall occupy itself with the collection of funds during the tag days."</p>
   <p>The committe nominated by the Mayor:</p>
   <p>The Right Reverend Bishop Paul Rhode, the Reverend Fathers Francis Gordon, Casimer Gronkowski, Stanley Cholewinski, Joseph S. Pajowski, Florian M. Chodniewicz, <pb facs="5423968_7_1167.jpg" n="3"/>W. Zapala, A. T. Jung, C. F. Slominski, Casimer Sztuczko, Francis Wojtalewicz, C. I. Gronkowski, Albert Furman, S. Nawrocki, John Szczypta, S. Swierczek, F. Lange, M. Kotecki, John Obyrtacz, A. Nawrocki, Stanley Siatka, Francis Ostrowski, F. J. Karabasz, L. Grudzinski, F. Scieszka, Raymond Kowalewski, John Zwierzchowski, Leon Zuchala, and J. S. Pajkowski, Alderman Stanley Kunz, Messrs. Vincent Zwiefka, Z. H. Kadow, John F. Smulski, Francis P. Danisch, Frank Koraleski, Julius Smietanka, John Czekala, Francis Rydewski, John Konopa, N. L. Piotrowski, Dr. Adam Szwajkart, Peter Rostenkowski, C. Zychlinski, the Honorable Edmund K. Jarecki, Stanley Kielczynski, Stanley Glomski, Julius Rosenwald, Charles R. Crane, Edward P. Butler, and Charles G. Dawes, Mmes. Anna Neuman, Rose Kwasigroch, and Agnes Nehring, and Miss Emilie Napieralski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
