<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXII, No. 13,
<date when="1918-03-27">March 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Weekly Chronicle News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0995</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0995.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXII, No. 13,
<date when="1918-03-27">March 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WEEKLY CHRONICLE NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Probably no nation is ailing as much from lack of systematic work as we Poles. By us everything is done in jerks, under the first impression. We take the first one that we can drag in and commit to him social or national work. No one asks him where he comes from, who he is, of what extraction, or what is his past. It is sufficient if he is smooth, knows how to kiss tiny hands, and carries himself with somewhat lordly manners.</p>
   <p>Therefore, with a certain kind of pride we may note in the Chronicle the fact that the Polish clergy in Chicago has taken into their hands a certain amount of work for the Polish army and has resolved to combine the strength of Polish women in that direction.</p>
   <p>Here is what we read in the resolutions adopted at the meeting of Polish pastors in Chicago:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0996.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Local women and young ladies as well as all women welfare societies were to be placed under the direction of the Central 'Helen Paderewski' Association. The school girls, will for a half day each week, make stockings, jackets and scarfs for soldiers in the Polish army and besides that all the school children will donate money into the hands of the respectful Sister Teachers for the hungry orphaned Polish children in Switzerland.</p>
   <p>"Rev. Pastor Gronkowski has been selected as the head director of the entire movement, who will remain in constant understanding with the Central Bureau of Mrs. Paderewski in New York, and the shelter located in St. Adelbert's parish, under the direction of Rev. Gronkowski, as a central location, to which the products of the women and the money from the children from all parishes will be forwarded."</p>
   <p>This entire activity is found under the direction of the selected <pb facs="5423968_7_0997.jpg" n="3"/>commission, which is composed of Rev. Casimir Gronkowski, Rev. Francis Wojtalewicz, and Rev. Edward W. Kowalewski.</p>
   <p>We believe that work started in such a way will bring forth fruit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
