<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-14">Jan. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">For Proper Representation of Poland in Foreign Countries</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0888</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0888.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-14">Jan. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FOR PROPER REPRESENTATION OF POLAND IN FOREIGN COUNTRIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In yesterday's editorial we discussed the question of Polish official diplomatic representation abroad. Today we wish to touch briefly on the subject of the other type of Polish representation abroad, namely, the various delegations, deputations, commissions, and committees sent from Poland to foreign countries. We admit that we do not know much about the various Polish delegations traveling in Europe. It is true that we read much about them in Polish newspapers as well as in other journals, and we hear a great deal of favorable and unfavorable comment about them; still we prefer not to express our opinion of them because it is beyond the sphere of our immediate interests, and frankly, we are not thoroughly familiar with them. But we do know the delegations sent from Poland to America, and we have a perfect right to discuss them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0889.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There has been a veritable deluge or Polish delegations to America from the very first moments of the Polish government's existence. Political, economic, party, educational, and God knows what other kinds of representation, delegation, commission, a never-ending swarm here among us. Frankly, we affirm that there are absolutely too many of them. The new Polish secretary of the treasury, Mr. Michalski, is in our opinion perfectly right, according to news received from the old country, in refusing on principle to finance these delegates and emissaries; he should put them under strict control and curb them most effectively. There is not the least doubt that Poland's reputation and interests would gain if only properly selected and authorized delegates were sent here on really important business.</p>
   <p>And meanwhile what has been taking place for more than two years? Literally there is not a week in the whole blessed year but that some guest arrives here from Poland! For God's sake please understand us clearly! We are not inhospitable. We give the heartiest support, personally and in our newspaper, <pb facs="5423968_7_0890.jpg" n="3"/>to all the causes presented to us by these emissaries which we consider deserving. We co-operate intensely, more than any other Polish paper in Chicago. The best proof of it may be found in our columns of these many years and in our own unselfish,disinterested, self-imposed labors. Actually, an immense number of articles, appeals for the support of such causes, originate in our editorial offices. From our offices they are sent to other Polish papers which have a well-earned reputation for not writing much about these matters, but at least they may publish an article sent to them already written. And so we do not spare labor, support, or even money. Our main consideration is principles and the method of their application. Our community grumbles ever so much louder and complains of being imposed upon by various collection campaigns. And the truth is that it has been milked on all sides for the last half dozen years. It is being milked by our local people and by the emissaries from Poland. Patiently we keep on contributing, believing that it is for Poland. Venerable and noble is this faith, deserving the highest recognition by our native land.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0891.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Please consider this, and after consideration you will admit the truth of it: delegates of all sorts have been coming to us and are still coming, representing not the government of our native land but various private interests, cliques, and even political parties of suspicious or even decidedly undesirable character. Let us mention only the recent visit of socialistic noisemakers and the cable which happened to fall into our hands, sent to our local red barkers for the Socialist party in Poland, asking them to send money for their socialistic campaign there--in other words, for a decidedly destructive type of work with all its possible consequences, known already by past experiences, and for their flirtations with Bolsheviks and Jews and the promotion of a pro-German political orientation. For this, then, the funds were going to be sent from America; for such dirty work money was going to be wheedled from our credulous countrymen in the name of patriotism and our native land!</p>
   <p>And do you remember the "traveling delegates" of all sorts at the time of the Polish Loan campaign? A miscellaneous assortment of litterateurs, <pb facs="5423968_7_0892.jpg" n="5"/>deputies, experts, simpletons, cranks, and musical comedy characters came [to visit] us; Americans made fun of them. Their lack of orientation, their narrow viewpoint, their selfishness, and their greed brought shame upon us, for every one of them was trying to feather his own nest. And for all this travelling about, this "patriotic tourism", our community had to pay. We know that the travelling and living expenses, and even the pensions of these delegates were paid by the National Council, and from what? From funds collected for starving people in our native land and for the strengthening of their patriotism and morale. And how much of the money collected for the Polish Loan was used for these delegations and their travelling about the country? We have learned from unimpeachable sources about the expense accounts submitted by Polish patrioteers for publicity work and speeches made in the loan campaign; we know about the "modest" expenses of the official representatives of the Polish republic in connection with the Polish Loan campaign [representatives] who received salaries from the Polish government, and whose principal and only duty was to help make the Polish Loan <pb facs="5423968_7_0893.jpg" n="6"/>campaign the greatest success possible. We even know of delegates who were receiving salaries and travelling expenses from several sources at the same time, and who while acting in their official capacity as agents of the Polish government were really devoting most of their time to their private business deals.</p>
   <p>And today is it really different? Not at all! Only recently we received the news that another "aristocratic" delegation is getting ready to leave or perhaps has left already for our shores--of course, again in search of the Golden Fleece. The names of the delegates do not inspire faith and confidence; they rather suggest and recommend extreme caution. This deputation has earned a bad name by its activities in Poland, concerning which we are well informed. It has to do with the distribution of food and clothing sent to Poland from America--our gifts, well we remember! The distribution of these gifts degenerated into a hopeless pseudophilanthropic mess reeking with intrigue, disorder, favoritism, and waste of public wealth. Today the same people, <pb facs="5423968_7_0894.jpg" n="7"/>known for their harmful work over there, are flocking to us for new dollars in the happy anticipation of collecting millions. Well, we shall see! Times have changed, and the people have "got worse". Yes, they have got worse, or we should rather say that they have become wiser because the delegates from Poland, the kind that we are writing about, have taught us a lesson.</p>
   <p>One more example. We all remember the appearance in our Polish-American colony in the latter part of last year of some kind of "educational mission", which made an appearance, made a little noise, collected all it could, and finally vanished. It developed that it was a "mission" of ordinary crooks who raked in money "scientifically", "Educating" us not to give anything to such people in the future. The newspapers of Warsaw gave urgent and strong warning in regard to this incident, even making formal representations to the Polish government and asking how it was possible for such scum, individuals with a shady past, to secure official letters of introduction and recommendation to America. In another place in this paper we are reprinting this inquiry <pb facs="5423968_7_0895.jpg" n="8"/>from one of the Warsaw newspapers. This, of course, is nothing new, since even some other Polish papers in Chicago have been writing about it. But we have kept this information in our desk drawer until the time came for us to use it in today's discussion.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, it is a proved fact that Polish authorities give letters of recommendation and authorization too indiscriminately to individuals going abroad. We ourselves have seen letters of recommendation from important Polish government officials in the possession of "educational" emissaries and "aristocratic" cheaters. Well, all these official papers will not move us in the future. Our attitude will be one of cold criticism and caution founded only too well on our past experience.</p>
   <p>Before we end, let us summarize in a few words our stand and our viewpoint. We are in favor of the greatest generosity for our native land, but we <pb facs="5423968_7_0896.jpg" n="9"/>demand co-ordination and systematization of collection and control of the distribution and the use of funds. Regulation and control should be in the hands of the Polish government and should be applied through its qualified and designated official and civic bodies. This rule must be enforced whether anybody likes it or not if our contributions are to be used for moral and useful ends. Otherwise our community will see the light sooner or later--it does not matter when, but it will learn--and then it will put a stop to being fleeced. Poland should endeavor to have a better, more competent representation abroad--both permanent representation and occasional or temporary representation. Diplomatic posts should be given to men who are thoroughly qualified for their various diplomatic assignments. No figure-heads or characters from comic opera should be sent as diplomats; they must be men who at least have some elementary diplomatic qualifications and will not disgrace the Polish government. We firmly believe, as we said at the beginning of this article, that an early improvement in this respect will inevitably ensue with the better functioning of governmental machinery.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0897.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>And the results cannot help bringing the greatest benefit to Poland and rejoicing to the generous and warmhearted American colony of Poles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
