<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-17">Apr. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To the Polish Immigrants in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1045</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1045.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-17">Apr. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE POLISH IMMIGRANTS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Countrymen! Woodrow Wilson, President of the United States, following the humanitarian duty of helping the millions of innocent victims of the present war, regardless of their national or political affiliations, has set aside April 21 for the purpose of collecting contributions throughout the nation for the relief of the war victims of Ruthenia.</p>
   <p>Poland, Ruthenia, and Lithuania, which have shared for centuries the same fate, have today become the victims of the war that has been raging in Europe for the third successive year.</p>
   <p>The Poles, true to their traditions--although without doubt the most seriously affected by the war--hasten to the rescue and generously help all those nations which suffer along with them.</p>
   <p>Polish relief organizations--first among them the General Relief Committee in <pb facs="5423968_7_1046.jpg" n="2"/>Vevey, Switzerland--in distributing relief funds, food, and clothing on Polish soil do not differentiate between Poles, Lithuanians, Ruthenians, or Jews, but give relief to all equally, in the belief that humanitarian action recognizes no national or political barriers but only the call of the unfortunate people in need of help.</p>
   <p>The Executive Department of the Central Polish Relief Committee in America hereby appeals to your hearts, fellow countrymen, and asks you to contribute as generously as you can to aid our brother Ruthenians on April 21--the day set aside for this purpose by President Wilson. Let the community of our misfortunes and the phantom of death from starvation that threatens both the Poles and the Ruthenians erase all tribal differences and arouse in our hearts the noble desire of mutual rescue.</p>
   <p>All larger contributions, in addition to collections during tag day, will be publicly acknowledged by the Executive Department of the Central Polish <pb facs="5423968_7_1047.jpg" n="3"/>Relief Committee, which will send them to the Ruthenian Committee.</p>
   <p>Executive Department of the Central Polish Relief Committee:</p>
   <p>T. M. Helinski, president</p>
   <p>H. Setmajer, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
