<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-06">Feb. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Stockholders of Great Lakes Insurance Company Hold Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-06">Feb. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">STOCKHOLDERS OF GREAT LAKES INSURANCE COMPANY HOLD MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Monday evening, a stockholders' meeting of the Polish insurance firm, Great Lakes Insurance Company, formerly Polonia Fire Insurance Company, was held at the Polish Roman Catholic Union Hall. More than three hundred stockholders were present, a number of whom came from as far as the state of Pennsylvania. The directors of the corporation were also present at the meeting.</p>
   <p>At the opening of the meeting, the president of the corporation, N. L. Piotrowski, gave an extensive report on the organization of the corporation and explained the reasons for which this meeting was called. On a motion by Doctor Pietrzykowski, the president's report was unanimously accepted, and the gathering thanked the president for his efforts by rising. Speeches were also made by John Smulski, treasurer of the corporation, and by underwriter A. C. Mack. It was unanimously decided to change the corporation's <pb facs="5423968_7_0374.jpg" n="2"/>name to "Great Lakes Insurance Company", to raise the corporation's capital and surplus to $600,000, and to increase the number of directors from nine to fifteen.</p>
   <p>The Company already has its charter and its license and is engaged in conducting insurance transactions. Fortunately, A. C. Mack was secured as an agent for the firm. He is a capable man with more than twenty years' experience in the insurance field. His ability and his wide connections are a guarantee of the Company's success.</p>
   <p>President Piotrowski, upon being asked the reason for the change in the Company's name, explained in the following manner:</p>
   <p>"At present, public sentiment in America is against anything foreign. Everyone can understand that the chief purpose of our Corporation is material gain, and while we expect support from the Polish people, we expect also to do business with Americans. Profit from others is just <pb facs="5423968_7_0375.jpg" n="3"/>as welcome as profit from Poles. It will be to our credit if we succeed in gaining the confidence of Americans and win their support of our Company. We know from experience that no Polish enterprise based on patriotism was ever successful. A stockholder who invests his money does so primarily for profit. We are convinced that in conducting this enterprise in a purely business sense, we will even receive greater support from the Poles themselves, for, after all, business is business and patriotism is patriotism. All this considered, our directors decided that it is in the best interests of the corporation and its stockholders to give the firm an American name.</p>
   <p>"There was never an insurance company in the United States that had at the time of its organization such promise of success, especially in times such as these. We are under state supervision and are members of the Board of Underwriters. The administration and the board of directors consist of well-known and highly respected members of our community and of experienced businessmen. Premiums are the same as those of other companies and we pay <pb facs="5423968_7_0376.jpg" n="4"/>the same commissions. We have reached agreements with other well-established companies for the purpose of business exchanges and "re-insurance", by virtue of which our Company will incur the minimum of risk. The Great Lakes Insurance Company will be to American Polonia what the Northwestern Trust and Savings Bank has been and is to Chicago's Polonia."</p>
   <p>President Piotrowski also added that until such time as the company will be prospering and doing a good business, he declines to accept any salary for his services.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
