<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-10-12">Oct. 12, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Hospital Benevolent Society Founded</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-10-12">Oct. 12, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH HOSPITAL BENEVOLENT SOCIETY FOUNDED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Hospital Benevolent Society was organized by a group of women from the Saint Hedwig Society of Saint Stanislaus Kostka Parish on October 10 at the Home of the Sisters of Nazareth. The main purpose of this society is to look after the needs of the Polish Hospital. One of the first steps taken in this direction was an assessment of ten cents per month on all members. This money will be turned over for the support of the hospital. The success of this, of course, lies upon a large membership.</p>
   <p>In return for this generosity, the Polish Hospital is going to offer prayer and Masses for the benefactors, and each member of the society is going to have certain privileges, as free quarters during illness. In this respect both will be gaining a great deal in service.</p>
   <p>An election of officers has been held and Mrs. John F. Smulska was chosen president; Mrs. Leokadia Hoffman, secretary; and Mrs. Jedrzejek, treasurer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0445.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Monthly dues are to be paid on every second Sunday of the month. A committee has been appointed to work on a constitution, which is to be read at the meeting to be held in November.</p>
   <p>The following have joined the new organization: Eugenia Smulska, Francis Nowaczewska, Josephine Jedrzejek, Bronislawa Barzynska, Leokadia Hoffman, Eve Pstrag, Pauline Fuhl, Marian Swierza, Antoinette Matysek, Constantine Solinska, Veronica Kosmieja, Anastasia Lamczyk, Mathilda Embiorska, Elizabeth Przybysz, Mary Borowiak, Francis Smolinska, Helen Halin, Roumalda Wilkoszewska, Catherine Kobrzynska, Eve Tatera, Ladislawa Chudzinska, and Sophia Lubienska.</p>
   <p>A sincere invitation is extended to all Polish women interested in giving the Polish Hospital a hand. Names of all new members will be announced in the Polish papers.</p>
   <p>It is anticipated that the pastors of all Polish parishes will give their <pb facs="5423968_7_0446.jpg" n="3"/>wholehearted support to this new society and urge their parishioners to join. All presidents of Polish women's societies of Chicago are requested to mention this at the next meetings of their societies and to urge their members to join. This is a noble cause and those who join it will derive benefits. Those desiring to become members are requested to get in touch with any of the above-mentioned members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
