<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-07-28">July 28, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Poles Too Highly Assessed by Unscrupulous Appraisers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0856</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0856.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-07-28">July 28, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">POLES TOO HIGHLY ASSESSED BY UNSCRUPULOUS APPRAISERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We often read in the local American press of protests being raised by various industrial and business firms against too high a valuation of their properties and, consequently, of too high a tax assessment. In almost every such case the authorities acknowledge the validity of the protests and reduce the taxes. This is particularly true when those involved are big firms or wealthy individuals who are well informed on ways of handling such a situation. But the owner of a small piece of property, especially if he is an immigrant who cannot speak the English language well, pays even the most unjustly imposed taxes on his property first, and then complains because he had to pay so much. Had he known how to go about it, he could have protested, and could have had his taxes reduced. The Polish property owners of wards Four and Five, in the community of Bridgeport, do not allow themselves to be treated so unjustly. Of great help to them in that respect is their Citizens' Club, which protects them from unjust taxes.</p>
   <p>This club, as we are informed by its secretary, Mr. K. J. Karpinski of <pb facs="5423968_7_0857.jpg" n="2"/>1058 West 32nd Street, decided that every citizen belonging to the club, and afflicted with too large a tax bill should bring his bill to Mr. F. Pruszynski, 946 West 33rd Street, at which address is located the main office of the club. The executive committee will go with such bills to the assessors and will question them. The time in which to deliver the protests is very short, however, and therefore they should immediately be turned in at this office.</p>
   <p>It would be advisable to organize such clubs in other Polish settlements, in order to take care of such matters as this and to protect the interests of the citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
