<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-02-26">Feb. 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Right to Aid War Sufferers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-02-26">Feb. 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE RIGHT TO AID WAR SUFFERERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>American public opinion should insist upon our right to come to the relief of the wretched Polish war sufferers. The conditions in that country are heart rending.</p>
   <p>While the Belgian people are clothed and fed by American charity, with the active aid of the German provisional government, the Polish people are dying by the thousands of sheer hunger. There are more than 4,000,000 men, women and children who are suffering from hunger, cold and exposure at the very moment you are reading these words.</p>
   <p>When the Russian armies were being driven from Poland, the savage Cossacks were ordered to lay waste the whole country, and they performed <pb facs="5423968_7_1108.jpg" n="2"/>their inhuman task with cruel thoroughness. The villages were destroyed, the crops were destroyed, the horses and cattle were destroyed, the farm implements were destroyed, and the poor people were driven like herded animals along the roads or compelled to flee into the woods and swamps. The devastation and cruelties committed by the savage Russian soldiers, under the orders of the Grand Duke Nicholas, and the personal direction of Russian officers, are unparalleled in the history of all the world's tragedies.</p>
   <p>These inoffensive, helpless creatures are literally starving to death. Thousands of their kin in this country and other thousands of Americans, not their kin, are willing and anxious to send to the poor starving Poles the same help we have extended to the poor Belgians. But the British government refuses to let clothing and food go through the sea blockade to alleviate the awful sufferings of the Polish people. The British government will not even permit Red Cross supplies, for the use of <pb facs="5423968_7_1109.jpg" n="3"/>surgeons and nurses in the hospitals, to go through the blockade. The German government has offered to pay in gold for two shiploads of wheat to be taken to Poland by American commissioners and distributed by American agents to the starving Polish women and children, but Mr. Asquith, on behalf of the British government, has just refused to permit this relief to be sent. The excuse for this inhuman refusal to let Americans feed these poor Polish sufferers, as we have been feeding Belgian sufferers, is that the food supplies would relieve Germany of the task of feeding this starving population, and so leave Germans with more food at home. We doubt if anything to equal the cold-blooded inhumanity of this action has ever stained the governmental policy of any nation calling itself Christian and civilized.</p>
   <p>The German people are forced to conserve their own food supplies, in order to get through from harvest to harvest. They are feeding 1,500,000 prisoners of war among them nearly 200,000 British captives. The German <pb facs="5423968_7_1110.jpg" n="4"/>government cannot feed these 3,000,000 suffering Polish people, deliberately reduced to starvation by England's ally, Russia, and Mr. Asquith knows that these people must perish unless American charity is permitted to succor them.</p>
   <p>Then why are these miserable ones refused aid and left to suffer and die? Why? Because they are Jews! It is the deliberate plan of the cruel Russian autocracy to let these people perish because they are Jews.</p>
   <p>Besides this, the British government is naturally anxious to conceal as much as possible from the neutral world, the real truth about the horrid and wholesale barbarism and cruelties of its half-civilized ally. A detailed account of the awful atrocities committed by the Russian soldiery, if given to America by American Red Cross agents and American charity commissioners at work in Poland, would excite a great revulsion of feeling in this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1111.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It is high time that all American newspapers told this truth. It is high time that American public opinion was brought to bear upon Mr. Asquith's government, to compel recognition of American right to succor these starving millions in Poland, whose sufferings are a hundred times more severe than any endured by the Belgians whom we have succored.</p>
   <p>The fact that these miserable ones are Jews will not lessen the sympathy of Christian Americans; Jew or Gentile, they are human beings, men and women like ourselves, children and babies like our own little ones, and our souls rebel against the thought that they should be left to perish in their agonies when we are so ready and so able to provide them with the means of life.</p>
   <p>The American press, the American people, and the American government should insist upon the right of Americans to take medicine, clothing, <pb facs="5423968_7_1112.jpg" n="6"/>and food to the suffering, starving and perishing millions of inoffensive non-combatants in Poland.</p>
   <p>International law holds that food for non-combatants is exempt from seizure as contraband and the law of humanity demands that we send food to these poor Polish victims without any regard for illegal and highhanded orders to the contrary, whether from London, Petrograd, Berlin or any other capital.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
