<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-12">Apr. 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Contributions for the Kosciuszko Monument and the Russian Catholics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0065</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0065.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-12">Apr. 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONTRIBUTIONS FOR THE KOSCIUSZKO MONUMENT AND THE RUSSIAN CATHOLICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The measure of goodness or usefulness of any project, or any kind of future welfare work, depends upon the contributions from the people.</p>
   <p>Not clamor with its noisy, but empty patriotic phrases, not the puffing advertisements of the press confirms the goodness, or the welfare of any project, but letters of the contributors and the quotas deposited for this purpose.</p>
   <p>Two major causes have for sometime occupied the attention of the people: The project of building a monument to Thaddeus Kosciuszko in Chicago, and <pb facs="5423968_7_0066.jpg" n="2"/>the collection of funds for the starving Russian Poles, who for their religious beliefs, have been exiled on the snowbound Siberian frontiers.</p>
   <p>Although the proposal of building a monument of our beloved hero was the creation of a young Polish poet, who has a tendency towards anarchism and atheism, it was discovered that it was not his overflowing patriotism that prompted him in this direction, but pure business. He conceived this plan in order to promote the sale of his tainted poetical works for the cause of the monument, half of the net contributions to be applied to future poetical creations. A group of Polish citizens of Chicago, without political affiliations, formulated a committee to promote the plan, and made a public appeal for contributions to this patriotic cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0067.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Two months have elapsed since subscriptions were opened in national organs and single donations accepted.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, in spite of the flow of turgid articles of patriotism, in spite of the reprimanding of those individuals who have responded negatively to this noble cause, and suggested another plan, in spite of the staunch support of the daily press, etc., only eight hundred dollars has been collected in the two months.</p>
   <p>Several Polish editors took up the plea of the Russian Relief Society to help the poverty-stricken Russians. This plea was spread throughout the many Polish papers of America through the influence of this small group.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0068.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A movement was created to inform all of the Polish people that the aim of this plea was primarily for the assistance of the poor Polish exiles, who have been thrown upon the Siberian steppes by the same Tsar who has, and still is trying to stamp out the flow of Polish blood on his domain.</p>
   <p>The appeal was short and to the point. Only the warm respect for fellowman was sounded in all the Polish Catholic periodicals [Polak W. Americe (The Pole in America) did not publish this appeal, nor is it collecting any offerings.] This simple approach bore unexpected results. The generous hearts of our people were greatly touched. Donations began to flow into the offices of the Catholic periodicals, and are continuing to increase in number. Two series of two hundred dollars each were already dispatched to <pb facs="5423968_7_0069.jpg" n="5"/>Father Doctor Chotkowski. A third series is well underway. This amount, plus the three hundred dollars collected by the Milwaukee Courier and Wiarus of Winona, Wisconsin, and other Catholic periodicals, adds to a total sum of fifteen hundred dollars. Twice as much was collected for the poverty-stricken Russian Poles than for the Kosciuszko monument.</p>
   <p>Is further proof necessary? The above figures speak for themselves. The monument fund is for a noble cause. It honors the memory of the dead. Alms for those exiled in Siberia is a far nobler cause, for our starving people are brought back to life, and their tears of misfortune are wiped away. Our people have recognized this fact. And from the far flung corners of America, contributions are flowing to the offices of the Catholic Gazette <pb facs="5423968_7_0070.jpg" n="6"/>in Chicago. Everyone admits this simple truth: that a shirt is closer to the flesh than a coat, that it is far nobler to rescue the dying from death than to honor the dead, who have already become immortal by their deeds, by erecting bronze statues.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
