<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-04">Jan. 4, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Special Social to Be Held Tonight for Invalids</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0404</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0404.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-04">Jan. 4, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">SPECIAL SOCIAL TO BE HELD TONIGHT FOR INVALIDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A special social has been arranged by the Ladies' Legion of the George Washington Post #1, Polish-American Veterans Alliance, and will be presented tonight at the Speedway Hospital, Maywood, Illinois. This social is actually a program of variety entertainment, and will be presented for the benefit of the invalids and the sick of the soldiers' hospital.</p>
   <p>The following people will take part in the entertainment tonight: Ladies' Halka Choir; Victor Mika, popular personality among the veterans; Mrs. Antoinette Zebrowska-Perlowska, well-known violin artist; Miss Mary Gruszczynska, noted songstress; Eugene Lukaszkiewicz, Edward Rosczewski, and Miss Victoria Rosczewska, dance artists from the school of Lauretta Boris; Florence Paluszek and Anatolja Jarmulowicz, duet singers; Carol Gorecki, Loretta Pendzinska, Florence and Edmund Paluszek will present a clog dance; Alice Sikora, doll dance; Loretta Pendzinska, modern dance; acrobatic stunts <pb facs="5423968_7_0405.jpg" n="2"/>will be given by Carol Gorecki, Edmund Paluszek, and others.</p>
   <p>The participants are requested to meet at the Union Hall, Milwaukee Avenue and Augusta Street, at 6:15 P.M. They will leave by automobiles at 6:30 P.M. for the hospital. The Ladies' Legion requests everyone to be punctual.</p>
   <p>The committee is sending out an appeal to all vehicle owners to donate their services and take the entertainers to the Speedway Hospital. These who wish to offer their cars should communicate with J. P. Kolbrzynski, telephone Brunswick 4741, or J. Korczak, telephone Humboldt 5887.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
