<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-14">Dec. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Reply of the Committee Selected from the Administration of the Polish Roman Catholic Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0198</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0198.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-14">Dec. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">REPLY OF THE COMMITTEE SELECTED FROM THE ADMINISTRATION OF THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The newspapers have by now undoubtedly informed the members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union of the shortage of funds and the mismanagement of the treasury of the organization. The committee chosen to investigate the matter will, for the time being, refrain from issuing an exhaustive report, since it is not as yet thoroughly prepared for this. It does, however, feel obligated to give a general but truthful account of this unpleasant affair.</p>
   <p>The present administration took over the deficit in the treasury and the muddled bookkeeping of the former officials, without even suspecting the former treasurer of a shortage. It relied upon the reports made by the finance committees, and their acceptance by several past conventions. Later, however, despite the fact that the last convention, in Cleveland, rejected a motion to <pb facs="5423968_7_0199.jpg" n="2"/>hire professional accountants to examine the books, the present administration ordered the books checked over by professional and responsible accountants, on the basis of its own experience. As a result of the audit the present administration became acquainted with the actual financial condition of the organization.</p>
   <p>A shortage of approximately eighty-four thousand dollars was actually found. The administration immediately summoned Mr. Ostrowski, the treasurer, to explain himself. The treasurer expressed surprise when he was informed of the true condition of things. He had never even suspected such a great difference between his figures and those of the accountants. When asked what he intended to do about this, he announced that he would willingly cover this shortage with his own money, even if it were to cost him his last cent.</p>
   <p>The committee announces with great pleasure that Mr. Ostrowski immediately transferred his entire estate, as well as his wife's to the Polish Roman <pb facs="5423968_7_0200.jpg" n="3"/>Catholic Union. Besides this guarantee, the administration has the treasurer's surety bond of forty thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>In view of all that, the undersigned have an undaunted faith that the treasury of the Polish Roman Catholic Union will suffer no loss. They also observe that the president of the organization, on the basis of power rightfully bestowed on him, has temporarily held the activities of the treasurer in abeyance until the entire matter is completely settled.</p>
   <p>The administration, at a meeting held recently, empowered the committee to follow this matter to its conclusion. Further developments will be made known to all members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>We trust that the discovery of the shortage, as well as the ordering of a systematic and professional accounting in order to protect the organization's finances according to banking regulations--which the <pb facs="5423968_7_0201.jpg" n="4"/>present administration has already introduced--will prove to be the best guarantees to the members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union and will awaken our Polish people's faith in the organization.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Stanley Adamkiewicz, President</p>
   <p>Right Reverend Paul P. Rhode, Honorary Chaplain</p>
   <p>Reverend J. B. Obyrtacz, Vice Chaplain</p>
   <p>J. Czekala,</p>
   <p>J. Zamorski</p>
   <p>J. Szczepanski, Directors</p>
   <p>N. L. Piotrowski, Attorney for the Polish Roman Catholic Union</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
