<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-12">Feb. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">New Plans to Refinance Pulaski Hall in St. Adalbert Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0828</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0828.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-12">Feb. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">NEW PLANS TO REFINANCE PULASKI HALL IN ST. ADALBERT PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following letter was received by Dziennik Chicagoski for publication:</p>
   <p>"At the annual meeting of the Pulaski Hall Building Society, held on January 8 at Pulaski Hall, the following motion was carried:</p>
   <p>"In order to lift the heavy debt of the Hall, especially by making payment to private individuals, it was decided to create a second division of shareholders who are to make weekly payments of from fifty cents to one dollar or more, according to their circumstances.</p>
   <p>"Everyone signing up on the shareholders' books of the Pulaski Hall Building Society will receive a book bearing the official seal of the Society; this book will contain every payment made, and as a guarantee of this investment a share of stock will be given for each ten dollars paid. The money received in this manner cannot be assigned for any other purpose than payment for private debts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0829.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the event that a large number of persons subscribe to this plan, the loan from the bank will easily be paid.</p>
   <p>"All money paid in on this new shareholders' plan will be placed under a guarantee, and the payee will be able to withdraw his money, with the accrued interest on his investment, at any time.</p>
   <p>"A committee of thirty was chosen to publicize this proposal among the Poles of Chicago, especially in the neighborhood of St. Adalbert Parish. Those appointed to the committee are: A. Stefanowicz, J. Napieralski, A. Gorecki, J. Jereczek, J. Chmielinski, F. Marcinkowski, Albert Jenczyk, F. Koch, B. L. Maciejewski, W. Jawrocki, J. Kruczkowski, J. Bylinski, F. Wleklinski, J. Bednorz, M. Gieldzinski, J. Mielcarek, Joseph Lemon, C. Brukwicki, W. Urbanski, J. Nowak, P. Benna, J. Hoppe, S. Waligorski, F. Golaszewski, A. Blaszczynski, B. Markiewicz, W. Kopicki, F. Kaminski, S. Nawrocki, and J. Cichowicz.</p>
   <p>"The weekly payments will be accepted by the financial secretary, J. Mielcarek, <pb facs="5423968_7_0830.jpg" n="3"/>assisted by A. Stefanowicz and W. Urbanski, at the meeting of the directors, which will be held every Friday evening between 7 and 8 o'clock at Pulaski Hall, 800 South Ashland Avenue. The first payments will be accepted February 1.</p>
   <p>"Let us all support this plan, fellow citizens! Make weekly deposits of your savings, and in this way the foundations of Pulaski Hall will remain as a monument to Polish life. In this way a certain sum of money will be saved which can be withdrawn on request. An especial appeal is made to Polish youth, for not a few young men squander a dollar or more each week. Let these young, men invest at least fifty cents weekly in the Polish hall, and in time they will have tidy sums which will be of great advantage to them in later years. Let us turn over our savings, penny by penny and dollar by dollar--and in a short time the debt will be paid, and the income from the hall will then be divided among the shareholders.</p>
   <p>"Those desiring further information about this savings plan are invited to attend any of the directors' meetings held each Friday evening at Pulaski Hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0831.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"A hope is expressed that these words will not pass without an echo, but will awaken many to active participation, primarily those who have not hitherto been interested in this matter.</p>
   <p>"Alas! if the present indifference continues, then we will shortly be shorn of our pride in the Polish hall; the present small handfull of shareholders will not be able to carry the burden long, and bankruptcy will be a reality. It should be the duty of every Pole in St. Adalbert Parish to support this refinancing drive,thereby making failure impossible.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Pulaski Hall Building Society,</p>
   <p>John Nowak, secretary 722 West 18th Street</p>
   <p>"P. S. All local letters requesting information will be gladly received."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
