<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-04">Apr. 4, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Welfare Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0338</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0338.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-04">Apr. 4, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH WELFARE ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The initial steps of the recently formed Polish Welfare Association have come to an end. Verily, a laborious task. Yesterday, for the third and last time, the constitution of the Association was read. The original constitution has been accepted with a few minor changes.</p>
   <p>We will try to inform the people from time to time about the aims and purposes of this organization, although its activities have been well covered before. This noble society will begin to show its worth within a short time. The constitution, as has been revised and accepted, will appear in this paper next week.</p>
   <p>Regular work of this welfare society was curtailed because of the various debates relative to articles of the constitution. However, some worthy <pb facs="5423968_7_0339.jpg" n="2"/>work has already been performed. Besides giving assistance to several persons, the Association discovered a few cases where people were trying to get aid under false pretenses. The system of interview and investigation has showed its effectiveness.</p>
   <p>The next regular meeting of the members of the association will be held on the first Sunday of May instead of in April. The April meeting was postponed to give way to complete all the work which has accumulated from the past sessions, which were held every Sunday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
