<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-04">Nov. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">In Defense of Our Unfortunates</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0854</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0854.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-04">Nov. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">IN DEFENSE OF OUR UNFORTUNATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every Friday the police bring many people to the Detention Home at Wood and Polk Streets (back of the County Hospital) on the charge of mental deficiency; there are Poles among them. Some of these people are freed as soon as the authorities ascertain that the charges are groundless, that the supposed attack of insanity was the result of worry or an overindulgence in liquor. Many, however, are mistakenly sent to Dunning as insane, only because the person arrested as insane could not explain his case to the judge in coherent English.</p>
   <p>This is the usual fate awaiting the Poles, as one of the officers of this court informs us. It happens because we do not have anyone there to present the matter clearly to the judge, to show that mere circumstance has brought these unfortunate people there.</p>
   <p>Other nationalities, like the Czechs, Germans, Jews, and others, have organized committees whose special function is to defend these unfortunates.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0855.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When one of their nationality is arrested as insane, members of the committee investigate the case, and after ascertaining that the charge is unjust, present proof to the judge, who usually frees the person under arrest. This is what other nationalities do in defense of their unfortunate people.</p>
   <p>We, in this respect, are far behind them. Therefore, it is logical to assume that many of our brethren are innocently detained in the insane asylum at Dunning, only because no one came to their defense. Even Judge Owens of the Detention Home is of this opinion, and frequently asks why the Poles do not form an organization similar to those of the Czechs, Germans, Jews, and others. This is a very important matter and worthy of consideration. Perhaps among our well-known and influential citizens some people could be found who would undertake the forming of such an organization, or perhaps our ladies, known for the kindness of their hearts, can best solve this problem.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
