<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-02-18">Feb. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">John F. Smulski Says "Poland to Be Fed"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-02-18">Feb. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN F. SMULSKI SAYS "POLAND TO BE FED"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>England seems to have caused some embarrassment by refusing to play the role of cruelty toward Poland which Germany and pro-German Americans had marked out for her.</p>
   <p>Germany conquered Poland and still holds Poland. Germany drained Poland dry. Yet Germany and pro-Germans set out now to put upon England the responsibility for the starvation which Germany caused.</p>
   <p>All that England did was to hint that it might be well for Germany, before forcing onto others the job of feeding her conquered province, to give back to that province the food of which she had stripped it in contravention of the laws of nations and of humanity.</p>
   <p>That hint England disdains to follow up. Now, apparently, she waives the <pb facs="5423968_7_1114.jpg" n="2"/>"rations" demand, as it was called, and says that she will let food go into Poland, upon the absolute guarantee that Germany and Austria will stop draining food from Poland. Without this guarantee, feeding Poland, of course, would be pouring supplies into a bottomless pit.</p>
   <p>Mr. John F. Smulski, who has so ably led the victorious fight for his starving people, believes that the guarantee will be given and that food can soon begin to go into Poland. We hope so. But the amount of organization work to be done before a system can be established is overwhelming.</p>
   <p>The first thing to do is to get enough ships to send from America the food that will go to Poland; that job, we believe, is within the province of the American Government. Indeed we regret that our Government did not move, as it was requested by the Polish-Americans to do, to bring about the concession which England has voluntarily made.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1115.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On the matter of ships,Congressman Loud has introduced into the House of Representatives a bill providing that, for the period of one year, one-fourth of our naval colliers and transports be devoted to carrying to Europe food for Polish relief.</p>
   <p>If the naval experts believe that such a move is safe, the Loud Bill should be passed at once. Every day, every hour counts when men, women and children are dying of starvation by the hundreds and thousands. If we can do it, we should have the ships ready to carry the food the very hour that Germany and Austria give their guarantee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
