<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-08-18">Aug. 18, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Roman Catholic Union and the Coming Convention</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0291</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0291.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-08-18">Aug. 18, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION AND THE COMING CONVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention of the Polish Roman Catholic Union in America will be opened Tuesday, August 14, in Cleveland.</p>
   <p>The Polish Roman Catholic Union in America is a very large Catholic and national institution. It has almost ten thousand members; it supports hundreds of orphans and widows and unites the large masses of the Polish people in America into one great family. Therefore we ought to wish this institution success at its convention and in the future.</p>
   <p>The statement for the fiscal year of 1893-1894, which will be distributed at the convention in Cleveland, shows that the institution is in very good <pb facs="5423968_7_0292.jpg" n="2"/>condition.</p>
   <p>Right after the Chicago convention the organization had 9,250 members, and at the present moment it has 9,270.</p>
   <p>The income for the last fiscal year (1893-1894) was $81,705.39, and the expenditures were $81,461.77. The cash balance is $5,269.72.</p>
   <p>The unpaid dues of the societies are only $2,529.95.</p>
   <p>The income for the last fiscal year was as follows: assessments, $79,178.14; monthly dues, $1,696.00; initiation fees, $440.50; net income from Wiara I. Ojczyzna [the organ of the Union], $265.75; interest on assets, $120.00.</p>
   <p>The expense column shows the following items: death benefits to eighty-two widowers, $24,350.00; to eighty-four widows, $49,900.00; total death benefits, <pb facs="5423968_7_0293.jpg" n="3"/>$74,250.00; Wiara I Ojczyzna, $5,018.65; Polish Immigration Home, $300.00; and Polish Pavilion at Lwow, $300.00. The rest is administration and office expenses.</p>
   <p>The assessments were $9.90 per member.</p>
   <p>The special statement for Wiara I Ojczyzna for the last eleven months shows subscriptions, $5,073.58; advertisements, $711.85; expenses, $5,253.92; net profit, $531.51. According to the agreement with the Polish Publishing Company the organization receives half the profit, or $265.75.</p>
   <p>So much for the figures. From this statement, the following deductions may be made. Despite the separatist movements in various cities, such as Detroit and Bay City, Michigan, the number of the members was not diminished. The dues and assessments do not exceed ten dollars a year per member, which is comparatively low. The indebtedness of the societies for unpaid dues is very small. The administrative expenses, including salaries paid, do not exceed fifteen hundred <pb facs="5423968_7_0294.jpg" n="4"/>dollars a year; that is, they are not too high. The reserve capital draws interest.</p>
   <p>The organ [Wiara I Ojczyzna] of the Polish Roman Catholic Union instead of showing a deficit, as is generally the case in such organizations, yields a profit.</p>
   <p>Finally, in the last year our institution assisted 166 Polish families by paying death benefits.</p>
   <p>It may be said with confidence that these results are highly satisfactory. They prove that, thanks to the good management of the administration, there are order and economy in the institution; in short, that it is a financial success. The donations to the Polish Immigration Home and to the Polish Pavilion at Lwow testify that the Union is also interested in Polish affairs.</p>
   <p>The foregoing facts indicate that the future of this institution is assured, <pb facs="5423968_7_0295.jpg" n="5"/>and that the next convention cannot be anything but a success.</p>
   <p>That there are good and bad people everywhere is a fact, and it is also true that in the Polish Roman Catholic Union there is a handful of Poles who during the whole year tried to sow dissension in this organization by means of a newspaper published in Winona, Minnesota. However, their intrigues are shattered against [the wall of] facts and figures.</p>
   <p>The convention may make some changes in the structure of the Union. Wiara I Ojczyzna, organ of the organization, has published a series of suggestions on that subject. Some members propose that the conventions shall be held less rarely; others desire that the administration shall be centralized in one locality; a certain group desires to make changes in the death-benefit system; and so on. We shall see how these matters are decided at the convention.</p>
   <p>We believe that the convention will be guided by common sense and justice, and <pb facs="5423968_7_0296.jpg" n="6"/>that it will not make any radical changes in the present system which might undermine and weaken the stability of the Polish Roman Catholic Union and cause misunderstandings. We believe that it will consider the interests of all Polish settlements, and that every settlement will be fairly treated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
