<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-13">Aug. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1288</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1288.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-13">Aug. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Brothers and Sisters! Drawing near on the clock of history is the hour of retribution for the crimes against generations of our nation, for the murder of defenseless mothers and sisters, innocent children,and ailing old folks, for the tortures and rackings [we have suffered], for the torture chambers and underground dungeons in which thousands of the best sons and daughters of our country have met and continue to meet death. Today, when the great powers in the continent of Europe have entered into a battle to the death, we, dear Brothers and Sisters, the descendants of a great and noble nation, must not stand on the side lines with our arms folded in inactivity!</p>
   <p>May the dazzling charm of freedom which flows from the Star-Spangled Banner of the United States upon our immigrants, open our eyes to the wrongs and martyrdom of our nation; may this charm arouse in our hearts an ardent desire <pb facs="5423968_7_1289.jpg" n="2"/>to see our trampled and calumniated homeland enjoy the same freedom that we enjoy here in the American nation!</p>
   <p>May the well-being and the happiness which flow from the wise laws of the Constitution of the United States upon the workers' cottages and the merchants' houses awaken in us the desire to win such well-being and freedom for our homeland.....</p>
   <p>May greediness, conceit, and miserliness keep far away from us; may our hearts and our pockets open to the needs of the homeland. May the one cry of retribution take possession of all of us united in brotherly love: The hour of retribution is drawing near. To action, Brothers in the Alliance! To action, Sisters in the Alliance!</p>
   <p>Dear Brothers and Sisters! The Polish National Alliance--which, as its very <pb facs="5423968_7_1290.jpg" n="3"/>name indicates, is an organization strictly nationalistic--cannot serve any party or side but must follow the road markers which its founders left it as a heritage; that is, it must serve us as a whole, it must serve the immigrants and the homeland.</p>
   <p>At every occasion the Polish National Alliance has built golden bridges, in order to bind with the golden thread of brotherly love the sides poisoned by party antagonisms and return them to the service of the homeland, but, unfortunately, party chauvinism above the general welfare of the nation has spoiled and continues to spoil the noble work of the Polish National Alliance. We, nevertheless, not discouraged by oppositions, will persevere on this road to the very end, because thus Christian ethics, tolerance, and love for the homeland command us!</p>
   <p>We have worked and we will not stop working at resurrecting brotherly love and love for the homeland in the souls of our blundering countrymen in order <pb facs="5423968_7_1291.jpg" n="4"/>to return them to the bosom of the Polish nation. We have given proof of noble conduct: when we were persecuted, we remained silent; when we were insulted and showered with the worst kind of epithets, we did not reply but awaited patiently for the moment of reflection and conversion of our persecutors and this moment has arrived.</p>
   <p>This is not the time, at such an important moment, to enter into discussions with our ardent political-minded countrymen of various views, because the present moment demands only one thing of every true Pole and every true Polish woman--action!</p>
   <p>To action, then, dear Brothers and Sisters!</p>
   <p>Leave the red of punishment for the guilty ones to history, leave revenge to God, leave big politics to our brothers in the homeland, for the path <pb facs="5423968_7_1292.jpg" n="5"/>which our nation takes in Europe is the path the Polish National Alliance will follow. For the purpose of this work, the directors of the Polish National Alliance have created the Department of Independence. As soon as this appeal reaches you let the choice of the people, the officers of branches and groups of the Alliance, call a meeting at once. At this meeting they are to form a district committee for each branch and a subcommittee for each group. Collect funds in all possible ways and send them to the treasurer of the Polish National Alliance. You may rest assured that the contributions collected by you will be paid only to such a body as the Polish nation will create and recognize as its chief authority.</p>
   <p>Love and regards.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Executive Committee,</p>
   <p>K. Zychlinski,</p>
   <p>President of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>John S. Zawilinski,</p>
   <p>Secretary-General of the Polish National</p>
   <p>Alliance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1293.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>N. B. We are enclosing herewith instruction blanks for the collectors, which we ask the officers of the committees kindly to fill out, writing in the name of the collector,and having the chairman of each committee place his signature beside that of the secretary-general of the Polish National Alliance. We will send you receipt books and other information in a few days. For collectors of the Independence Fund we ask you kindly to select the members--men or women-best qualified for this important and noble work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
