<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-13">Dec. 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">For the Poor (Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_1463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-13">Dec. 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE POOR (Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Depression, misery, destitution, hunger--these terrible words are heard oftener and oftener. Everybody wants and tries to help the poor suffering unfortunates, yet if we ourselves do not possess much, it is impossible for us to divide the little that we contribute either widely or effectively.</p>
   <p>Aren't we all importuned five to ten times a day for help by the poor beggars walking the streets? We give, but in the end our patience and our pockets are exhausted, and frequently the sincere contributor is placed in the embarrassing position of refusing help.</p>
   <p>Having been placed in this unenviable position a few times, I began considering the situation and whether there could be found a method to correct this, and I have come to the conclusion, which I am submitting to the attention of the public, <pb facs="5423968_7_1464.jpg" n="2"/>especially, the Polish businessmen.</p>
   <p>Contributions for the poor are coming in slowly, not because we lack a generous heart--because we have time and again done our share--but because we lack a definite system for making contributions. Many of us cannot afford to give more than a dollar and would feel ashamed to give less; others haven't the time to go hunting for members of the committee or delay from day to day bringing in their contributions to the proper place; and there are some who wait until some collector calls.</p>
   <p>Our Polish Charitable Society, in existence a few years already, is working hard and has already done a lot of good, but it is poor itself, because with only one hundred or two hundred regular paying members, the income is limited and very meager.</p>
   <p>The Polish Charitable Society should have at its disposal certain funds regularly contributed, to be able to perform its mission. It is our duty to see <pb facs="5423968_7_1465.jpg" n="3"/>to that, and we can do this by a little good will and our well-known generosity.</p>
   <p>For this purpose, I am proposing the inauguration of the following system:</p>
   <p>The Polish Charitable Society to distribute one hundred tin boxes in saloons, meat markets, grocery stores, drugstores, etc. The proprietors thereof, the merchants, to keep their boxes prominently displayed, and if they don't want to irritate their customers, let them follow my example.</p>
   <p>For several days I have had in my store a small tin box into which each evening I deposit pennies for the relief of the poor. I decided to contribute only one per cent of my gross sales. That means, if the sale amounts to ten dollars, I deposits ten cents; if it is eighteen dollars, then I deposit eighteen cents. With sales of ten to twenty dollars daily, it would mean from three to six dollars a month put aside. If we strike an average of five dollars a month from one box, then one hundred boxes will bring five hundred dollars a month for the disposition of the Polish Charitable Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_1466.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Such a sum could be used to bring relief to many, clothe many a frozen body, feed many hungry people, and dry many a tear.</p>
   <p>Such a system presents an additional advantage, because such contributions will not be too oppressive, lighter indeed than a one-time donation, which may prove to be inadequate, because it is given only once. Furthermore, such a system creates a sort of moral contest, because every store proprietor will endeavor to have his box more filled than his neighbor's.</p>
   <p>Then, according to a routine, an authorized collector, chosen by the Polish Charitable Society, will collect the money and deposit it with the proper persons.</p>
   <p>For the sake of order, the Society will publicly announce the condition of the treasury and amounts received from the various merchants.</p>
   <p>Remember, these pennies will grow into such proportions that a similar amount <pb facs="5423968_7_1467.jpg" n="5"/>could not be collected either by private collectors or by means of public appeals.</p>
   <p>If, besides these merchants, who will morally agree to such a tax, others in private life display such a collection box in which they would deposit their pennies themselves, or in which their guests at a birthday or other party could deposit their winnings after playing sixty-six or some other game, then the goal will be reached and we will feel happy and satisfied over a duty well done; we will triumph morally and will step on the head of the awful monster known as poverty.</p>
   <p>Adam Szwajkart.</p>
   <p>(We personally recommend the idea submitted in this article by Mr. Adam Szwajkart as being timely and practical. We judge there are no obstacles to prevent putting it into action. The practicability of the idea is very apparent. The Polish Charitable Society will no doubt consider it at once and put <pb facs="5423968_7_1468.jpg" n="6"/>it into operation without delay. Editor)</p>
   <p>*Such boxes can be ordered from a factory, with a proper inscription and a key for the collector.</p>
   <p>**If the Polish Charitable Society decides to accept this proposition, then I suggest that they mail cards to all, asking them if they would be willing to display such a box. These cards, when returned would furnish the collectors with a list of firms and private people to call on.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
