<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-02-08">Feb. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Polish Welfare Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0847</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0847.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-02-08">Feb. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE POLISH WELFARE ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday noon a meeting of the recently organized and steadily growing organization, the Polish Welfare Association, was held in the downtown offices of Attorney Smietanka. This organization will be ready to begin its work of aiding and protecting juvenile delinquents in a few days. More than a score of prominent Poles attended the meeting; among them was the Reverend Theodor Czastka, pastor of Holy Rosary Church in North Chicago. Former Judge Edmund K. Jarecki presided. The secretary of the society read the report of the meeting of the board of directors,which was also held in the same office last Friday.</p>
   <p>Summary</p>
   <p>Here follows a list of the directors who were present or absent at that meeting.</p>
   <p>(Translation Resumed)</p>
   <p>The following officers were elected: Edmund K. Jarecki, president, Albert F. Soska, vice-president, Theodor Szmergalski, secretary, and August J. Kowalski, treasurer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0848.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Names of members of the following committees are given: advisory committee, thirty-nine names; legal committee, nine names.</p>
   <p>(Translation Resumed)</p>
   <p>After completion of the reading of the report it was accepted in full. Three applications for the position of superintendent were given to the committee, which is composed of Messrs. Albert F. Soska, Joseph A. Lasecki, and Marion Kudlick. It was decided to begin work immediately and to see to it that a place shall be rented for the office of the Polish Welfare Association and opened to the public as soon as possible. But how soon this will be done depends in large measure on the nobility and the generosity of our fellow countrymen in rendering financial help. The purpose of this society is the protection and aid of adolescent boys and girls who are brought into court for violation of the law and who lack sufficient legal assistance. The Association will try to protect these boys and to lead them from crooked ways to the straight path of life. We have felt the need for such an organization for a long time. And so now let <pb facs="5423968_7_0849.jpg" n="3"/>us go to work--to action! The most important requirement for starting and continuing this action is funds, for without them nothing can be accomplished. We therefore count on the support of our Polish organizations, businessmen, doctors, lawyers, dentists, etc., because only with their help can our organization be effective and successful.</p>
   <p>The first Pole to make a contribution for our work was Mr. John F. Smulski.</p>
   <p>Who will be next?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
