<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-12">Jan. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Triumph of the Society Sons of Freedom, Group 694, Polish National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Report by M. Turbak]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_7_0128</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0128.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-12">Jan. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TRIUMPH OF THE SOCIETY SONS OF FREEDOM, GROUP 694, POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Report by M. Turbak]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On January 6, the auditing commission completed its work and prepared a very commendatory report on the fruitful work of the Sons of Freedom, and acknowledged as honest, conscientious, and harmonious, the work of the entire administration [for 1917]. It is no small triumph to gather five hundred sons of Poland to the Polish National Alliance standard--it is a great deed, a dream that even the boldest did not believe would materialize. Yet, it is now an accomplished fact. No wonder, then, that every member is filled with joy; it is in itself a stimulus to further effort.</p>
   <p>We have confidence in our hearts and hope shines on our horizon, but we are not resting on our laurels; we continue to increase our efforts.....For we cannot sleep now, we cannot hesitate in our organizational work; the greater <pb facs="5423968_7_0129.jpg" n="2"/>the glory, the greater our joy, but our duties and responsibilities increase also. Today, we are a large group, and it is easier to recruit members, easier to convince those who are as yet unattached. To action, then!</p>
   <p>The growth of our society and the state of its treasury for the year 1917 are revealed in the following data:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Number of members at the close of the year 1916</cell>
     <cell>398.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Number of members at the close of 1917</cell>
     <cell>501.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Funds in treasury at the conclusion of 1916</cell>
     <cell>$4,440.95.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Funds in treasury at the conclusion of 1917</cell>
     <cell>$5,090.48.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>These figures speak for themselves on whether a society can become stronger or more firmly established, and whether a member can expect aid when necessary. Do not delay, then, countrymen, but join as soon as possible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_7_0130.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The next annual meeting will be held on January 12 in the hall on the corner of Wade and Crittenden Streets. The new administration will be installed at this meeting, after which there will be a great many pleasant surprises. The administration for the year 1918 consists of the following: M. Turbak, president; J. Madaj, vice-president; A. Guzik, recording secretary; J. Czekaj, financial secretary; S. Wojcik and K. Kowalczyk, auditing committee; and J. Zajdel, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
