<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-23">Mar. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Vital Question for the German Element</title><title level="a" type="sub">All Factions Unite</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-23">Mar. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A VITAL QUESTION FOR THE GERMAN ELEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">All Factions Unite</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Convinced, that the struggle for the mayor's office of Chicago will not only affect Robert M. Sweitzer's political career, but will also demonstrate German unity to the country as a whole, the German elements of the Democratic party got busy to start an effective campaign among the Germans of the city on behalf of the Democratic candidate for mayor. It was the first session of the new German association which was formed by combining the German following of Robert M. Sweitzer and Carter H. Harrison. The session was conducted in harmony, and led to a further strengthening of the association which was established during the primaries in Robert M. Sweitzers' interest. The followers of Mayor Harrison were granted the same recognition and consideration as the members of the original organization, thus making the combination an entirely new outfit. The first activity of the alliance will be a great German mass meeting scheduled for March 31 in the Lincoln Turner Hall. Sheriff John E. Traeger will be chairman.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1318.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Vital Question for German Element</p>
   <p>Henry W. Huttman, former member of the school board, explained convincingly that the present mayoralty campaign was not merely a political struggle, but a matter of honor for the German element. The great applause which he received was proof that his audience was thoroughly in accord with him. "Not only the German [-American] newspapers, but also the Anglo-American press in the East consider the present fight for the office of mayor a struggle of the German element as well."</p>
   <p>Anglo-American newspapers in Boston, Baltimore, Philadelphia and New York look upon Robert Sweitzer as a purely German candidate, and regard his nomination and victory over Carter Harrison a result of the newly established unity among an awakening German public. Sweitzer's victory is to a large extent credited to the Germans, who wanted to prove their political power to their American fellow citizens. Sweitzer's election would be regarded a victory for the German element of Chicago, his defeat a defeat for them. If he should beaten, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1319.jpg" n="3"/>the German element all over the country would feel the consequences. German Republicans are of the same opinion, and are willing to forget their party affiliation in order to help Sweitzer, because he is the German candidate. If we could make the Germans here understand how very important Sweitzer's election would be for the German element in general, ninety or maybe even ninety-five per cent of all German votes could be secured for our candidate.</p>
   <p>Paul O. Doederlein spoke in similar fashion, and added that the Germans were honor bound to unite and vote for the German candidate en bloc, in order to show the German-haters in this country that the German element must be reckoned with.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
