<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-03-02">Mar. 2, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Blaine, Sherman and Grant</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0973</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0973.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-03-02">Mar. 2, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">BLAINE, SHERMAN AND GRANT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of the three[potential presidential nominees], Blaine, Grant and Sherman, the one most unpopular with the German Republicans is Elaine, as far as we can judge. While here is an almost complete unanimity[among the Germans] for Washburne; and almost sixty per cent of the German Republicans would vote for Grant, in case he were nominated; and while Sherman could count on an equal support; the number of votes that Blaine could command from the German element, combined with all his other Republican votes, would not amount to more than forty per cent. The other day, when we inquired among the local German Republicans, which of the three candidates they would give preference, if Washburne were out of the running, the unanimous reply was: "Then, Grant!" And we agree: Between Grant and Blaine, we take Grant any time; furthermore, between Blaine and Sherman, it would be 'Sherman for us. But that does not mean at all that for the present we are ready to give up the one candidate <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0974.jpg" n="2"/>which the Germans would like better than all the other three combined, namely Washburne.</p>
   <p>Blaine represents to the Germans—whether with justification or not—that Yankee spirit[Yankeetum]so essentially hostile to everything German. He is the representative of the hateful and contemptible attitude toward the foreign-born of the Nation; the representative of those crackpot ideas, which have made the name of his home state, Maine, the object of disgust, resentment and scorn for all Germans. That malicious antagonism shown toward Mr. Schurz during an affair in which the latter was perfectly within his rights (forest protection within Federal territory), they[the Germans] considered as the combined result of unworthy demagogism and malicious treachery against the "alien" advisor of the President. The miserable conduct during the recent election campaign in Maine (the favorable result of which only gross ignorance and falsification could attribute to Blaine; whereas, in reality it was General Chamberlain's doings, exclusively) makes them[the Germans]more convinced than ever that, in case he[Blaine]should <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0975.jpg" n="3"/>really be elected President (but which is far from being certain) he would not be the man capable of preventing the recurrence on a greater scale of the Garcelon coup d'etat.</p>
   <p>All that the friends of Blaine can say to recommend him is that he has a "magnetic personality" , in other words, smooth oratory. That may fool Americans, to idiom rhetoric talent is tantamount to wisdom, personal energy, and all kinds of statesmanlike virtues; but the Germans are not the least bit impressed by it. They are not easily intoxicated by mere speeches. On the contrary, a brilliant oratory makes them rather suspicious, unless it is accompanied by proofs of efficiency, reliability of character, good judgment, and ability to assume leadership.</p>
   <p>However that may be, the fact remains that of all the candidates, Blaine's name finds the least response among the Germans, and that the boom being drummed up for him does not make the slightest impression on the German element. His adherents and followers cannot ignore this fact. Without a <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0976.jpg" n="4"/>doubt, his sponsors also include those English-speaking Americans whose true and innermost feelings toward the Germans can be summarized with the words: "Damn the Dutch". They would rather be defeated with Blaine than be victorious with Washburne or Grant; however, they probably will not comprise the majority of his following. The others who sincerely follow the Blaine boom, under the delusion that he would make the "strongest candidate", had better be warned in time, for once Blaine is nominated and his weakness then becomes obvious, it would do them no good to be sorry.</p>
   <p>As matters stand, Washburne would most certainly be elected, if the National Convention would nominate him. Grant's election, though not at all assured, would seem probable. Sherman could perhaps be elected; but Blaine would quite certainly be defeated, unless the Democrats make a huge blunder in nominating their own candidate. Blaine's defeat in the final election would not be considered as a special misfortune by the German Republicans. They would consider his elevation to standard-bearer of the Republican party as definite proof that this party had nothing but contempt for the wishes and desires of the Germans[German Republicans], and that it had assigned them <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0977.jpg" n="5"/>the humble duty of more yes men, who have only to obey, but have no voice in the matter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
