<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-26">May 26, 1879</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1614</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1614.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5 (Jewish)</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-26">May 26, 1879</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the men nominated by the Republicans, we note Julius Rosenthal--the first instance in which a German was proposed for that judicial position since we have had elections for circuit judges in Cook County.</p>
   <p>Those who know Mr. Rosenthal as a citizen or in his professional life, need not be told that he is one of the most conscientious, reliable, intelligent, and impartial men among Chicago's 1,180 lawyers. Considering all the candidates, there is not one who excels him in these essential qualifications, and hardly one who equals him.</p>
   <p>His definite impartiality--since he has no personal, political, or other obligations to consider--makes him a candidate for whom anyone can gladly vote, whether Republican, Democrat, or Socialist. If only three of the five Republican candidates are elected, then it is to be hoped that Mr. Rosenthal will be one of the three.</p>
   <p>In regard to Mr. Reed: He is well known as a former state's attorney, a <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1615.jpg" n="3"/>very intelligent man capable of quick discernment. As a judge, he would form a pleasing contrast to some of the "sleepy heads" we now have in office, and whose "conscientiousness," or rather, "indecision," leads them to commit serious blunders. That he understands the German language well is only a recommendation in so far as it enables him to obtain testimony from witnesses who are not well versed in English, and whose statements might lose in effectiveness if they had to face a judge who speaks only English.</p>
   <p>The fifth candidate, Ira Buell never held a public office, but has an excellent reputation among his colleagues.</p>
   <p>It is not to be expected, nor is it desirable, that every voter will be swayed by party considerations. But, one must not forget, as long as the Republican party had a majority in Cook County so that party members could have been selected for judicial positions--the Republican party, on its own accord, let the Democrats have two judges out of five, and now that the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1616.jpg" n="4"/>Democrats feel sure of having the first majority in twenty years, the latter insist on a full party ticket.</p>
   <p>It is outrageous. Every impartial person is bound to have the same opinion, and we have yet to find an intelligent, upright Democrat who does not regret the decision of the Democratic party.</p>
   <p>How much the conduct of the party fixers, who intend to degrade the judiciary by making it a part of the political machine, will affect the decision of the voters, depends on the conscience of the individual voter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
