<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-26">Jan. 26, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">"When Johnnie Comes Marching Home"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-26">Jan. 26, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">"WHEN JOHNNIE COMES MARCHING HOME"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although only a small part of our armed forces has been demobilized to date, it is already evident that the original demobilization program is not operating according to expectations. Many employers seem to be entirely oblivious of their promises to restore former employes who served in Uncle Sam's Army to the positions which these men held when they entered the service of their country. Moreover, a number of women who now occupy positions which were formerly held by soldiers and sailors, tenaciously cling to these positions, and thus prevent the returning victors from earning a livelihood.</p>
   <p>"Instead of planning festivities and dances for us," writes a discharged soldier in a Davenport, Iowa newspaper, "people should endeavor to facilitate our re-entry into civil life. Not the alluring strains of the waltz, but the shrill whistle of the factory is welcome music to our ear."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0417.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Every day we find people placing responsibility for the evident lack of employment upon the Government," remarks The Nation in its latest issue. "And it is true that the 'powers that be deserve to be critized for failing to devise a plan to care for the 3,000,000 war workers who were to be released from their martial duties, and also for displaying some indifference to the matter. However, it is also true that lack of positions has not yet proved to be a disturbing factor in the labor market."</p>
   <p>Officials of the Federal Employment Service assure us that the surplus of available man power was no greater during the current month than it was during any January of the war years. There is not the slightest indication that work will be as scarce as it was during the years 1907 and 1913, even if the returning soldiers show less inclination to reconcile themselves to an unavoidable period of waiting than they displayed on former occasions.</p>
   <p>"The Federal Employment Service," continues the Times, "was organized unwarrantably late. The incompetence of its branches in some states renders it practically useless. And the demobilization is being carried on in the same <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0418.jpg" n="3"/>unsystematic manner by the general staff of the Army and Navy, despite strong protests made by civil authorities and competent judges. Since tha ability of commerce and industry to provide work for discharged war workers is not given the least consideration, thousands of employers are permitting themselves to be governed by their own desires or by unreliable rumors when they devise plans for future operation. It is estimated that less than forty per cent of the returning soldiers accept the positions they held before entering upon their military duties; and quite a number do not return to the place where they formerly worked. Many assemble in the larger cities and make the restoration of the nation's industrial life to normal conditions difficult by eagerly competing for positions."</p>
   <p>Thousands upon thousands have been made idle through the closing of factories in which war materials were manufactured. Among these idle there are many women and boys who were employed in munition plants and shipyards, where they were paid thirty to fifty dollars for work for which eight to fourteen dollars would be paid in times of peace. And yet the returning war workers cannot <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0419.jpg" n="4"/>justly complain that they have no prospect of employment. Many industries, among them the automobile industry and the knitting industry, are making preparations for a considerable increase in operations. And the Federal Employment Service has assured work for 100,000 people through the efforts of its various branches. However, the future success of this Government bureau depends largely upon the good will and co-operation of patriotic employers. Wherever it is possible returning warriors should be placed in the positions which they held before they responded to the call to the colors.</p>
   <p>Only a few of those who are being relieved of war duty have sufficient means to remain idle for any great length of time. They are in need of a renumerative job, so that they will be able to purchase civilian clothes and defray other living expenses. And if employers will do their duty in this respect, they will be making a very important contribution to the reconstruction of our national industrial life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
