<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-07-16">July 16, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">To the Members of the German Section of the Socialist Workmen's Union in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0935</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0935.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-07-16">July 16, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE MEMBERS OF THE GERMAN SECTION OF THE SOCIALIST WORKMEN'S UNION IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to a decision of the Local Executive Committee, the general meeting of the head section, as we have already announced on various occasions in this paper, will be held at 8 P.M. Sunday, July 17, at 54 W. Lake Street. Though the present organizer, Mr. P.T. Morgan, has considered it beneath his dignity to communicate this fact officially to the German-speaking Socialists of Chicago, the meeting notwithstanding will take place. Also, all resolutions taken will have full validity, whether the Germans take part or not. The organizer and his friends and the English section favorable to a compromise with the Greenbackers, think it advantageous to their plans if the German Socialists, known to be true to their principles, remain absent from tomorrow's meeting.</p>
   <p>For this reason alone, it is the duty of every German member to be at his <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0936.jpg" n="2"/>place punctually tomorrow night to take part in the important discussions of the general meeting of the main section.</p>
   <p>The memorandum shows</p>
   <p>1. Selection of officers (which is very necessary).</p>
   <p>2. Reconsideration of the resolution which condemns the Arbeiter-Zeitung, the Vorbote and the Nye Tid, and will exclude the members Peter Peterson, and Paul Grottkau from the union.</p>
   <p>By voting on the resolutions of the compromisers, it will be shown whether the Socialists will cooperate with the Greenbackers or not.</p>
   <p>Members! For years no such important party meeting has taken place in Chicago as that of tomorrow. Therefore, all men be at your place at 8 P.M. sharp. Tomorrow it will be demonstrated within the Socialist party whether or not free speech and freedom of opinion of the Socialists who are true to <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0937.jpg" n="3"/>their principles, shall be suppressed by the American shifty politicians.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow it will be seen whether the English section has the right to bring the German and the Scandinavian party press to the point where they brought the English newspaper The Socialist, founded with German capital.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of every right-thinking member to stand by his party magazine, which has always stood for the honor and the principles of the party and which protected all members who, in the interest of Socialism, have taken up the fight with the compromisers. To do your duty to the party, you should come to the meeting tomorrow. Protest against the action of the enemies of the party press and against the joining of the aforementioned party. Germans! Show that you will not remain behind our Scandinavian and French brothers. Your honor and your interests are at stake.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
