<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1875-11-09">Nov. 9, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The Election in Chicago.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Aurora Volksfreund)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1696</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1696.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1875-11-09">Nov. 9, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE ELECTION IN CHICAGO.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Aurora Volksfreund)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The bitter fight which has taken place in Cook County for the office of county treasurer, resulted in the election of Louis Huck and in the defeat of A. C. Hesing. About sixty thousand votes were cast, from which Huck received a plurality of thirty-five hundred over Hesing. Keeley received about nine thousand votes.</p>
   <p>For two reasons the election is neither a creditable affair for the hypocrites who belong to the Law and Order Party nor for the Germans, who have shown themselves ungrateful towards A. C. Hesing and towards Chicago Germanism. This can partly be explained by the German character. The German is always ready to pull down one of his fellow citizens who is more or less outstanding, regardless of the merits of the individual. This is nothing but contemptable jealousy.</p>
   <p>In what light the Law and Order Party appears can be imagined, if one considers that its representative is a brewer, and that Keeley, who was merely used to assure the defeat of A. C. Hesing, is a liquor dealer. How does brewer and liquor dealer rhyme with law and order? Anything to beat Hesing, and it was immaterial what means were used.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1697.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Nobody can accuse us of partisanship for Mr. Hesing. He, who is acquainted with the opinions of our paper, knows that we have seldom approved the views of the Staats - Zeitung, with which Mr. Hesing is identified. During the recent campaign we have read only the Neue Freie Presse, the Tribune, and the Times and we have been converted to Mr. Hesing through their misrepresentations and lies. We would have been happy, had he been elected last Tuesday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
