<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-09-02">September 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Our Enemy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-09-02">September 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">OUR ENEMY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The primary on Wednesday, September 9th is of the greatest importance to the liberal-minded population of the State of Illinois, and therefore we call the attention of the Germans of Chicago, to one man especially, who has shown himself as an enemy of personal liberty. This is Edward D. Shurtleff as candidate for the re-election as Representative of the 8th Senatorial district on the Republican ticket. This district always has voted liberal but now, Mr. Shurtleff is endorsed by the anti-saloon league as candidate for this district. Why? His platform is local option and prohibition. A man who previously represented liberal ideas new appears as an enemy of liberalism, and will prove himself as such in the next Legislature, if he is elected. The Germans of this district are warned that under no circumstances should they vote for Shurtleff. He has friends among the farmers but they should remember that behind Shurtleff is the anti-saloon league in Fort Sheridan, Lake Forest, Waukegan and other towns of this district. For this reason, the farmers and their friends must vote against their enemy, Shurtleff in the primary election of September 9th, 1914.</p>
   <p>The candidate, friend of the people, for whom every farmer and every liberal minded person should vote is the honest and worthy James H. Vickers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1373.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He is one of the leaders for individual liberty and a candidate for re-election.</p>
   <p>Every liberal minded person and every German should vote for Vickers and only for him, which counts for three votes and would bring about Shurtleff's defeat.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
