<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-03-28">March 28, 1907</date><title level="a">To the Editor of the Abendpost</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1385</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1385.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-03-28">March 28, 1907</date><title level="a">TO THE EDITOR OF THE ABENDPOST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Referring to the present election fight, I find as an old reader, that the Abendpost has deviated from its former policy of impartiality at election time. At every opportunity they promote the election of Fred A. Busse and agitate against Mayor Dunne. They use all of Busse's speeches and the statements of Dunne against Busse mention nothing of the opponents' accusations against Mayor Dunne. I am thinking especially of the pamphlet in which Mayor Dunne is called a glutton, a libertine and a drunkard. We all know that in the Dunne administration mistakes have been made, and that the street car question was his hobby; but it should also be recognized by all liberal and radical citizens that Mayor Dunne defended personal liberty and had the right attitude on the Sunday question. We do not know yet, what we can expect from Busse on these subjects. The Republican party with its following of fanatical hypocrites and temperance women, are always pulling the chestnuts out of the fire for them. Who is Mr. Busse? The son of German parents who, already in his youthful years, by influence and <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1386.jpg" n="2"/>partisanship gained several influential positions. Who stands behind him? The influential rich Republican party with its capitalists and monopolists and their interests in steel, railways and utilities. Mr. Busse is called the representative of the Germans, but we seldom have heard his name at our festivals, nor seen him at the celebrations of the Turners' Club, the Swabian Club or the Germania Singing Society. I am only mentioning the most important clubs as being the elite of the many German associations. How can the Republican German American Central Club, with Amberg, Logemann, Hebel etc speak about our Fritz as Mayor? I have lived for twenty years in the 17th Ward of Chicago and read most of the daily press, but never have I seen it before that all English papers with the exception of one, have sponsored a German-Republican with so much ardour. I leave it to the voters to follow their own judgement.</p>
   <p>George L. Engel</p>
   <p>42 North Center Avenue</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
