<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-10-12">Oct. 12, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">Friends of the Anarchists Meet.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0712</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0712.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-10-12">Oct. 12, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">FRIENDS OF THE ANARCHISTS MEET.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Turner Society of Lake View met at Muller's Hall, yesterday, in order to listen to speeches in defense of the eight condemned anarchists, and protest against the carrying out of the death sentence. The chairman, August Moeller, opened the well attended meeting and called on H. Festram as first speaker. Mr. Festram used moderate language in expressing himself and said, that almost all the citizens with hardly any exception were against the execution of the seven so-called anarchists. Dr. Kleinadt, member of the staff of the Arbeiter Zeitung, a man possessing a good deal of humor said, that through regard of the many uniformed men in the room he could not speak as freely as he wished, but knowing the condemned men personally he must say, that the sentence passed upon them was much too severe, and that it would be nothing short of barbarism should the death sentence be carried out. Wilhelm Lange made the capitalistic press responsible for the fate which befell his friends. "Journalist" Robert Kiesling said without any hesitation, that the policemen are nothing but wage slaves, whose lives are meaningless to capitalists. The Haymarket tragedy was laid to anarchy but the fact is, that the bomb was thrown by a scoundrel whose intention was to injure the anarchists, in which he did not fail. At the end of the meeting this resolution was drawn up and approved: Considering, that the entire press influenced the so-called trial of the anarchists and though <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0713.jpg" n="2"/>without any proof of their guilt, demanded their punishment; even this demand was unjustified, and that pressure was brought upon the court. It is our opinion, that the evidence furnished at this trial does not warrant the punishment pronounced on the accused men, and it is the press which was instrumental and successful in rousing the public to prejudice, and it is the press which is responsible for this tragedy and we resolve further: to do our utmost to help the anarchists to carry on the fight against prejudice, created by capitalists and their worthy tools, who demand the death of the accused men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
