<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>Die <title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-04-24">April 24, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Strikes Railroad Service.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0263</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0263.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-04-24">April 24, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">STRIKES RAILROAD SERVICE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After being beaten in its unjust fight with the Quincy Railroad, the brotherhood of locomotive engineers and fireman seeks recourse to Congress. We can always find some demagogues who welcome any conceivable bait, if it only catches votes. From such a contingent came the proposition, clothed in apparent impartiality, whereby the railroads shall be at the mercy of their obstinate servants. Thus: Through a national law the railways shall be bound to do their public duty as common carriers and, if they fail to redeem their pledge, punishment is threatened. If a railroad company declares that conditions beyond its control, i. e., refusal of its servants (employees, we would say) to work, precludes the possibility of fulfilling its agreement, then they are compelled to subject themselves to the decision of an arbiter who will consider the questions arising between the company and the strikers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0264.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At a casual glance the suggestion does not appear bad; but if we subject it to a more thorough perusal, then we perceive it to be a decidedly one-sided affair, benefitting only the strikers, since it is taken for granted, that the employees may at anytime, under any pretext, silly excuse, or unjustified demand, bring the functioning of the railroad to a sudden end, and for such an usurpation of power which terminates transportation, the strikers will not be held responsible, but the railroads are!</p>
   <p>The railway management will not be allowed to resume service by employing other workers as substitutes for the striking element, except so far as it can be accomplished in a week, which is an impossibility in many cases. After a week the company must submit itself to a settlement by arbitration, and if it proves acceptable to men who refused to work, then they must be re-employed. The entire plan is to quote that apt English word "jug handled," which signifies that there is only one handle on it, and this one hold is to begiven to the delinquent railroad servants, the strikers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0265.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In that document only the duties of the railroad are mentioned, but nothing about its rights; which means: the workers (servants) shall only have rights, the bosses (management) are governed by duties. This is entirely wrong, from subsoil to foundation. It is the uncouth work of demagogues, which does not eliminate the danger of universal railroad strikes, to the contrary, it encourages them to the utmost. The proposition seeks to give permission to the employes to hack the railroad companies, at any time, whenever it pleases them, but the latter are prevented from retaliating. If this becomes a law, then the men may enjoy a strike whenever they feel their oats, since the worst they have to riak, is: idleness for a few weeks and bumming around, before resuming their work.</p>
   <p>If the public transportation system of the country is to be protected from deliberate interferences and delays, such as the Missouri-Pacific-strike of two years ago, the Reading and Quincy strike of this year, then strong emphasis must be given, that the railroad employees do their duty and remain on their posts until relieved, identically as the duties of the common carrier towards the public.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0266.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Locomotive engineers, fire, brake, and switchmen, station attendants and conductors must just like soldiers, or sailors, take an oath to do their duty and are to be hired under a mutual clause, which provides for a notice of dismissal (about 2 months notification), and if they leave their posts during this service period, they should be punished as deserters. This punishment should be commensurate with danger, which was brought about by the sudden flight of the deserter. It must be graduated to conform to the perils of life, property, and the amount of damage the public suffered because of the suspended service. If this desertion destroys life and property, then the conviction should be increased to provide many years of confinement in a penitentiary. This much in regard to the duties of the men who perform public services. In the closing paragraph a national, and state laws for arbitration are suggested by the editor, if the railroad cannot reach an agreement; provided that the demands of the men are reasonable and sensible. To be administered by impartial men, conversant in this branch, (experts) and lawyers. No workers representatives are mentioned, as co-members of such a board.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
