<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-12-30">Dec. 30, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A German-American Group in Favor of Charles V. Barrett</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1172</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1172.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-12-30">Dec. 30, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A GERMAN-AMERICAN GROUP IN FAVOR OF CHARLES V. BARRETT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the leadership of Herman Wollenberger and Otto Reich, citizens of German extraction have formed a group supporting the candidacy of Charles V. Barrett for the office of Mayor of Chicago.</p>
   <p>This group whose secretary is William A. Schelling, issued the following appeal in favor of their candidate:</p>
   <p>"Chicago is in need of a mayor who possesses the confidence of all groups and classes, a man of irreproachable character, an efficient businessman and a leader. Chicago needs a man in whom we have assurance that he will appoint only qualified men for the city administration; a man who possesses the confidence of the people. Chicago needs a man who is capable of restoring the good name of the city and to maintain it. Especially during the World's Fair, Chicago needs a leader of whom we all can be proud.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1173.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Charles V. Barrett is this man. He grew up on the west side of the city as the son of plain parents. Through hard work he succeeded in attending the university; today he is one of the most prominent attorneys of Chicago. He takes a special interest in fair tax adjustment. He will intercede at all times in favor of the small homeowner and the thrifty working man."</p>
   <p>"We have not forgotten that it was William Hale Thompson who protected the citizens of all nations during the war, but without the votes of the German-Americans he could not have been re-elected again."</p>
   <p>"While we did our duty, William Hale Thompson did not keep the promises he had made before his election. He did not give the city a fit administration; he appointed officials whom he knew did not possess the confidence of the people and never would be able to gain it."</p>
   <p>"Mr. Thompson knew that, at the time the citizens of the 46th ward rejected him as committeeman, his political career had ended; and therefore we are not obligated to him any longer."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1174.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"We fulfil our duty when we recommend the most efficient man for this position to the German-Americans of Chicago, namely; Chas. V. Barrett."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
