<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-09-19">Sept. 19, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">Reprinted from the Buffalo Arbeiter Zeitung.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0721</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0721.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-09-19">Sept. 19, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">Reprinted from the Buffalo Arbeiter Zeitung.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The report reached us that the sentence passed by Judge Gary upon the eight imprisoned anarchists was upheld by the supreme court of Illinois. If the execution of this sentence, as we fear, will take place, it will be an outrage which could not find an equal in the nineteenth century, and it will also be marked as the greatest judicial murder committed, since the murders of Socrates, the Nazarenes, and Giordano Bruno who died by the hands of their fellow men....</p>
   <p>We are no anarchists, nor do we sympathize with the doctrines of anarchy, but when seven men who are guilty of no other crime, but that of standing up and taking sides with the workers and the oppressed and poor, if these seven men should be hanged, because they protested the wrongs done and the fleecing of the poor, then every person with but a spark of human feeling in his breast, has to consider it his duty to declare this sentence a shameful murder.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0722.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>justice in this case."</p>
   <p>Assistant State's Attorney Furthmann shared the opinion of his colleague, but thought that Fielden and Schwab were the only ones who would deserve a milder sentence. Capt. Schaack the "Mayor of the North Side" said: "I do not believe that the Anarchists would dare to attack the county jail, but it is not impossible that an individual crazed by Most's doctrine would throw a bomb, thus creating much suffering." "Capt." Black, the attorney and friend of the anarchists said, that it was important to undertake steps to win a reprieve for the condemned men by a member of the Federal Supreme Court. "Once the reprieve is granted," he said, "the execution of the sentence would be of less concern to us, for justice will finally triumph over the fate of these men." Among the visitors at the jail, yesterday, was Georg Schilling, the well known Socialist and active member of the defense society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
