<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1915-03-28">Mar. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Sweitzer's German Ancestry</title><title level="a" type="sub">German-American Citizens' Committee Confirms it Makes Thorough Investigation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1915-03-28">Mar. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">SWEITZER'S GERMAN ANCESTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">German-American Citizens' Committee Confirms It Makes Thorough Investigation</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-American Citizen's Committee, consisting of Germans of all party affiliations, brands as malicious libel any rumors that have been circulated by certain parties, claiming that Robert M. Sweitzer, German candidate for Mayor (Democratic Party), was not really of German descent, and asks all German citizens of the city to give him their full support on April 6. The Citizens' Committee, spurred by these malicious rumors, asked a committee consisting of Messrs. H. O. Lange, Rudolf Seifert, Ernst J. Kruetgen, C. Hildebrand, and A. Benz to make an investigation. The committee has designated the charge as absolutely false and entirely unfounded. It has been ascertained that Martin Sweitzer, the father of Robert M. Sweitzer, was born in Herbolzheim, county of Emmendinger in Baden [German], that he had emigrated with his parents to America when <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1303.jpg" n="2"/>seven years of age, and that any number of trustworthy and honorable citizens can testify that the claim that Robert M. Sweitzer was Martin Sweitzer's stepson is untrue.</p>
   <p>The Committee of five made a report yesterday to the Citizens' Committee, which thereupon adopted the following resolution:</p>
   <p>Statement of the Citizens' Committee</p>
   <p>"In order to investigate the rumors disseminated by our opponents, the German-American Citizens' Committee had delegated the following gentlemen to report on the family and ancestry of Mr. Sweitzer and to settle this question once and for all: H. O. Lange, Rudolf Seifert, Ernest J. Kruetgen, C. Hildebrand and A. Benz.</p>
   <p>"During a regular session of the German-American Citizens' Committee, held <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1304.jpg" n="3"/>on March 28, this committee of five submitted the results of their investigation. In consequence thereof, the following resolutions were adopted:</p>
   <p>"WHEREAS, The German-American Citizens' Committee, a non political organization, was established to survey the political situation and to submit to citizens of German descent information regarding the candidates for the office of mayor, and</p>
   <p>"WHEREAS, our Committee has been informed that Mr. Thompson and his campaign manager have spread the story that Mr. Sweitzer is more of an Irishman than a German, and that even his father had been an Irishman, who had adopted the name of his stepfather, Martin Sweitzer, and</p>
   <p>"WHEREAS, we have to brand these claims as absolutely false and unfounded after a thorough investigation, and have been informed instead that Martin Sweitzer, father of Robert M. Sweitzer, was born in Herbolzheim, county of <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1305.jpg" n="4"/>Emmendingen in Baden and emigrated to America with his parents in 1855 when seven years old, and that many trustworthy and honorable citizens can testify that the claim that Martin Sweitzer was the stepfather of Robert M. Sweitzer was an invention without foundation; therefore</p>
   <p>"BE IT RESOLVED, that we will give this fact the most widespread publicity among our German fellow citizens; and</p>
   <p>"BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, that the German-American Citizens' Committee sharply criticize Mr. Thompson as well as his campaign manager for this disgraceful attempt to confuse and deceive the citizens of Chicago; and</p>
   <p>"BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, that we will indorse the candidacy of Mr. Robert M. Sweitzer with all our means, and will urge every German citizen of our community to vote for him on April 6 regardless of party affiliations."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
