<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-12-30">Dec. 30, 1910</date><title level="a">Strikes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0201</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0201.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-12-30">Dec. 30, 1910</date><title level="a">STRIKES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The relationship between employers and employees is unquestionably far more favorable now than it used to be. We are far ahead of the average of European nations. We may definitely assert that during the last few years we have had comparatively fewer strikes and boycotts than any other industrial country.</p>
   <p>In England, France, and Italy the workers planned general strikes, and many of their important industries have records of big and long-continued strikes and boycotts. With the exception of a few local ones, we have been comparatively free from strikes, and the idea of a general-strike seems to be considered as entirely out of order. Strikes are being considered unfavorably in the United States, and great national and general strikes seem to be out of question. In this respect we are ahead of the European nations. We have outlived the age of strikes in the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0202.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are, of course, plenty of local strikes and some of them are extensive and long-lasting, but for the most part they happen in industries, where workers have been newly organized, or where these organizations are of comparatively recent origin.</p>
   <p>The old labor unions have lost their desire to strike long ago. They depend now upon open discussions and negotiations and the results seem satisfactory. Of course, there is still considerable talk of strikes, but this is for the purpose of giving emphasis to their demands. They may "pretend" before the public that they intend to strike, but by negotiations reach an understanding and thereby give other industries a good example how it is done properly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
