<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-10-12">Oct. 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Altgeld and the Ticket</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-10-12">Oct. 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">ALTGELD AND THE TICKET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Pg. 8) The Governor endeavors to obtain a closed Democratic Phalanx for the ticket. (Phalanx, Greek: A closed battle formation, in the form of a square, with the leader in the center; the method whereby Alexander the Great conquered the then known world; an expression often used in Germany to denote solidarity. Transl.) The invitations to the banquets of the Exposition and the Columbus Club gave him a welcome opportunity to visit Chicago for a few days and, incidentally, attend to a few political matters.</p>
   <p>His opinion was solicited yesterday anent the proposed judges for the Democratic Ticket. He said,"It is the best which any party or non-partisan committee has arranged in the last 15 years. Better candidates for the judiciary could not have been selected."</p>
   <p>Governor Altgeld would like to see the entire ticket elected, and he is here to induce his supporters, who belong to the anti-Harrison faction, not to scratch a single Democratic judicial candidate. Harrison obliged the Governor by preventing Judge Gary's nomination, although the Mayor (Harrison) supported Gary's candidacy in the beginning and, as one favor begets another, Altgeld will now use his influence to promote the cause of those candidates which <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1444.jpg" n="2"/>Harrison prefers. Harrison is accused of still desiring Gary's election, a rumor of which Altgeld is fully aware of and he now intends to preclude any clandestine intrigues on Harrison's part. Altgeld's Chicago visit is tantamount to a truce between the Altgeld and Harrisonian cohorts-a stop-gap for the inner party dissension- until after the elections at least.</p>
   <p>Of course this increases the Democratic chances for victory and the benefits which might accrue to the Republicans by such party-divisions, are now nil.</p>
   <p>Of much greater moment is the irresoluteness amongst the Republican leaders; it diminishes their prospects much more than the temporary peace overtures of the various contingents in the Democratic stronghold. The Republican Kraft is barely nominated and new even members of his own rank, including the Republican Tribune, demand his abdication. The controversy will undoubtedly be thrashed out today during the session of the new County Central Committee.</p>
   <p>The Democrats, who intend to vote for Judge Gary, deny that their intentions should be construed as antagonistic towards Altgeld. Many of the Governor's <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1445.jpg" n="3"/>staunchest friends regret that they cannot follow him in an anti-Gary campaign, as they are Gary-Democrats.</p>
   <p>It appears that the election will hinge on Gary, and the Republican candidates complain already, that Gary is in the limelight, and nobody pays any attention to them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
