<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-03-15">Mar. 15, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The Begging Socialists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-03-15">Mar. 15, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THE BEGGING SOCIALISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A mass-meeting held at the Vorwaerts-Turnhall last night in honor of Mr. F. W. Fritzsche, a member of the Reichstag, was attended by more than 1,500 persons. Dr. Ernst Schmidt was appointed chairman for the evening.</p>
   <p>After welcoming the guest of honor, Schmidt said that it was a rare and happy occasion indeed that brought them together here. "It is a pleasure," he said, "to greet one of the foremost and most self-sacrificing fighters in the cause of the working people." Before introducing the distinguished speaker of the evening, Dr. Schmidt said he wished to say a word or two in connection with the death of a terrible tyrant. "As a tender-hearted human being," he said, "I am filled with pity at the thought of his dreadfully mutilated body; but, on the other hand, when I consider the bloodshed dictated during this despot's reign, during which approximately 200,000 <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0914.jpg" n="2"/>persons were accused of political crimes and either ended in the hangman's noose or in the dark mines of Siberia, I cannot join in the chorus of those who bemoan this dreadful murder. To this group all I could say is that he deserved the end that befell him. (applause). Sympathizing with tyrants has to cease .....</p>
   <p>"What medium could the Russians have employed," continued Dr. Schmidt, "to make their rights known? They could not summon Alexander before a justice of the peace.</p>
   <p>"Although I would have preferred a more natural death for Alexander, I cannot feel pity in any degree over his assassination. (applause). Therefore, to eliminate such drastic measures and to render assassinations of political characters unnecessary, we have chosen and embraced Socialism."</p>
   <p>Then he introduced Mr. Fritzsche, the guest speaker of the evening, who <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0915.jpg" n="3"/>was greeted by the assembly with a salvo of applause.</p>
   <p>The speaker pleaded for leniency if he did not express himself exactly in accord with his innermost feelings or as the audience probably expected of him, saying he didn't want to invite a five year penitentiary term for high treason or instigation to such while in foreign lands, as this would be the punishment awaiting him upon his return to Germany, were he not to watch out. Thus, I would be deprived of every opportunity to serve the cause of Socialism. "Liebknecht," he said, "was the first consideration for a tour of America. Since his prison term does not expire before May 2, the "old Swede" was the next choice."</p>
   <p>The speaker then explained the aims of the Socialist Party in Germany..... He depicted the misery of the working class there and closed by saying that the Social-Democrats of Germany are not giving up hope and would not deter from a revolution if conditions and time called for such. Mr. Fritzsche predicted a mass emigration as the result of the prevailing conditions in Germany.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
