<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-11-30">November 30, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">"Wealth and Illiteracy".</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0880</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0880.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-11-30">November 30, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">"WEALTH AND ILLITERACY".</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite the immense national wealth of America and its boast of good schools, the number of illiterates is startling. There are 4,923,451 persons past ten years of age not able to read and 6,239,958 past the age of ten years not able to write. To the last mentioned group belong 3,019,080 white persons and of these 2,255,460 are born Americans. There are 3,220,878 colored persons unable to write.</p>
   <p>These are the "blessings" which are enjoyed by the poor workers meted out by their bourgeois employers. The percentage of illiterates among the white Adult population was much smaller forty years ago. With increasing wealth of this country the slave drivers become bolder. The more power they have the more the workingman has to suffer under their oppression. The more independent the workingman becomes, the more the enslavement of women and children flourishes by employment in factories. Through increased slavery the number of persons for whom it has become impossible to learn the art of reading and writing naturally has increased too.</p>
   <p>The capitalist system of slavery is directly responsible for the state of <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0881.jpg" n="2"/>ignorance of the masses which is the next thing to barbarism. This information we gathered from the official census of the year 1880 confirming Henry George's statement to that effect, and condemning present day society. It is unquestionable that under the present system and with national wealth increasing illiteracy increases also, for the masses do not derive any benefits from this wealth but it falls into the possession of only a few parasites. Nothing of this wealth is used to free humanity of misery and want of knowledge, but for the continuation of slavery and ignorance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
