<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-05-14">May 14. 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The German Lutherans for Altgeld and the Democratic State Ticket</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-05-14">May 14. 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN LUTHERANS FOR ALTGELD AND THE DEMOCRATIC STATE TICKET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With inflexible logic the German Lutherans manifest their stand for Altgeld and the Democratic ticket in this coming election campaign, although the majority of them voted the Republican ticket two years ago. The following is a verbal quotation of their excellent manifesto:</p>
   <p>"To our Churches and Societies.</p>
   <p>At its annual meeting, the Illinois district indorsed the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>Resolved, that we demand the unconditional repeal of the present compulsory school laws.</p>
   <p>Resolved, that we support unitedly and exclusively that particular party and its respective candidate who stands for the right principels in regard to this school question, and who can furnish us the most reliable guarantees that such principles shall be maintained in the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1525.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Resolved, that the school committee investigate the situation and the platforms of both political parties in the light of these resolutions and then determine to which one of the two parties we shall give our support."</p>
   <p>After the committee complied with the request, and closely investigated party declarations as well as the situations in general it reported its findings and the decision of their consultations:</p>
   <p>Both political parties have declared themselves for the repeal of the school law. Which one of both parties will give us the positive assurance that it not only will keep its promise, but that it will stand for right principles when new laws are being passed?</p>
   <p>In the light of above facts we had to answer the question: Which party can we entrust with our worthy cause?</p>
   <p>We were compelled to say that the Republican Party can not be trusted, because of their previous action. Can we expect that they will be honest with us, since they do not think it wrong to break their promise?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1526.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Democratic Party kept its promise, defending us openly two years ago, and their present statements are in complete agreement with their previous honorable actions. If it were a case of personal advantage, or if money or property were involved, it might be excusable for the sake of certain preferences to trust again one who has broken his promise, but this school affair is a matter of Christian parents and the Christian Church; it is a matter of conscience and God's cause, and we can not risk it into untrustworthy hands. We must judge strictly in accordance with facts and act correspondingly.</p>
   <p>The committee can therefore give only the following verdict:</p>
   <p>"For the sake of our conscience in regard to the school question, we must unitedly and exclusively stand for the Democratic Party and its respective candidates, because the Democratic Party stands for the right principles in this matter and without reservation, and offers us for the preservation of such principles in the future the best security."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
