<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-02-12">Feb. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Who Is Robert M. Sweitzer?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-02-12">Feb. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">WHO IS ROBERT M. SWEITZER?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Numerous contradictory stories regarding the German lineage of our candidate for Mayor, Robert M. Sweitzer, seem to make it necessary to discuss this subject in detail and to provide the public with some biographical notes from his life and the life of his forebears.</p>
   <p>The times are too serious, the fight of the old country for its existence as a German nation is too heroic, our worldwide struggle for influence and recognition are too important for us to neglect to do our very best and utmost in behalf of Germany's honorable name by nominating and helping to elect a man who is blood of our blood.</p>
   <p>Sweitzer's grandfather Martin hailed from Herbolzheim, a district of Freiburg, in Baden; his grandmother Barbara was also a native of Baden and was born in Weil, a district of Lorrach. From Lorrach they emigrated to Chicago in 1855, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1333.jpg" n="2"/>bringing their son Martin Johann, Robert's father. Barbara died in 1908, at the age of eighty-two, in the house of her son Fritz and was buried in St. Boniface Cemetery; her husband had passed away in the seventies.</p>
   <p>As most immigrants do, our folks from Baden had to face many a bitter disappointment. In Castle Garden in New York--so the grandmother related--they got a foretaste of the easy way in which one can lose money over here. An obliging compatriot, one of the notorious tribe of "runners," persuaded the family, without trouble, to hand him their German gold currency for exchange into American money, only to depart forever. All that the poor folks had left was the railroad tickets from New York to Chicago, which the father had purchased before the robbery. The beginning, therefore, was rather difficult. But the qualities of the German character, the best traits of which have always been perseverance and diligence, manifested themselves and achieved comfortable affluence. As the grandparents managed to work them-selves up from poverty and want, they instilled into the hearts of their children a strong aversion to the life of the adventurer. The best proof <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1334.jpg" n="3"/>of this is found in Martin Johann Sweitzer, the father of Robert, Friedrich Johann Sweitzer, his uncle, and Mrs. Fritz Steif, his aunt, who can all look back on a life of honest work. The father, first an employee of McVicker's Theater and later a member of the Cotton Kemball Minstrel Company, assumed the stage name of John Roche, following an old custom of the theater. This name he has kept ever since, but naturally it was not assumed by the family. A real-estate title is also registered under the name of Martin Sweitzer, not John Roche.</p>
   <p>In 1867 Martin married Sarah Lampert, the daughter of a building carpenter of Joliet, Illinois. Two years later their son Robert was born. The house which is his birthplace can be found near Harrison and Federal Streets. His uncle Fritz, then twelve years old, was a frequent visitor and lent a helping hand to his young sister-in-law, proudly taking care of the little nephew. After a happy boyhood came the time of earnest study, in which Robert frequently received honors for excellent work in the field of commercial science. His graduation from college was noteworthy because at a <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1335.jpg" n="4"/>celebration in the former Central Music Hall he received a gold medal awarded by the McLaughlin Coffee Company, which also offered him a position. Soon afterwards we see him promoted to be assistant manager of Walker and Company, hardware dealers at Adams and Market Streets. Later on he worked in the same capacity in John V. Farwell's large wholesale house, where for twenty years he had a successful career as chief salesman. Within this period he also saw his adolescent dream come true, namely, his happy marriage to his school chum Miss Kival, whose sister had married Mark Sullivan, a brother of Roger T. Sullivan. Thus Robert became a relative of the Sullivans.</p>
   <p>Up to this time Robert had never considered a political career. It was left to the Democratic convention of 1910 to suggest Robert Sweitzer, without his knowledge or intention, for the office of county clerk, assuming correctly that so excellent a businessman could handle any job and be a credit to his party. He did not disappoint the Democratic party. The honesty and efficiency of his administration are proved by his re-election <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1336.jpg" n="5"/>as well as by the present efforts to pave his way for the attainment of the highest office which the City of Chicago has to award.</p>
   <p>Can the German element afford to stand back? Would it not be of the greatest advantage if the second largest city in the Union should see a man at the helm who combines all the good qualities of a German-American and who, in spite of his American upbringing, has always remained a good Badensian [from the province of Baden, Germany] at heart and in mind, endowed with diligence, thoroughness, and honesty? In the ancestral tree of the Sweitzers you will find no Knights; neither the sword nor the narrowmindedness of the Puritans is emblazoned on their coat-of-arms, but instead there is the shining emblem of American citizenship, together with the qualifications for the highest office: an honest heart, a diligent hand, and a clear head!</p>
   <p>The hope of the German-American Robert M. Sweitzer Club is based on the abovementioned qualifications, a hope that he may find the support of all wellmeaning, unbiased German men and women of our city.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1337.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>ROBERT M. SWEITZER for MAYOR OF CHICAGO</p>
   <p>Charles H. Kellermann, Henry P. Runkel, Reverend C. F. Weise, Theodore Kuehl, Fred C. Ewert, Louis Sala, Adolph Ester, Dr. Maximillian Herzog,</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>A. W. Huber,</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Hermann Friedl,</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Alfred Steffens,</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>H. W. Schroyer,</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Julius Schmidt,</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>William Heinemann.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>[Translator's note: Probably Club committee members.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
