<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-05-29">May 29, 1883</date><title level="a">A Large Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0856</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0856.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-05-29">May 29, 1883</date><title level="a">A LARGE MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many persons have crowded into the Vorwarts--Turnhalle last night, anxious to hear Johann most's opinion of America. At the opening of the meeting Comrades Scholz and Dusey, Secretaries for the German and English languages respectively: The chairman called on Comrade Parsons as first speaker, who addressed the audience in English giving a short sketch of the economic conditions in this country, arriving at the conclusion that the ruling classes are stubbornly denying labor to introduce reforms in a peaceful way therefore, in order to bring about better living conditions, labor has to resort to force! Dynamite is the modern Hercules. This powerful agent seems to be destined to deliver humanity from chains of wage slavery. True, there are autocrats in Russia but monsters like those we have abundantly in Chicago, Illinois and throughout the United States. He concluded with the words: Reform, reform--or bloody revolution! Following spoke comrade Johann Mosx who said: Those of the immigrants who did not expect to find in America an Eldorado. Capitalism rules this country, naturally the consequences are striking. Concentration of capital by a few (the number of whom is steadily decreasing) and the increasing poverty of the people and finally the rebellion by the laboring classes against the present "order" could be followed only by communism, which would be a natural outcome of present conditions. ... This country's wealth has increased fivefold during the last 30 years, therefore if everyone would be benefited by it, each family <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0857.jpg" n="2"/>could possess $3,000, which is surely not the case in nine tenths of the population. During this period when property ownership has increased immensely, the average wages have been decreased...</p>
   <p>The factory regulations can be compared to the disciplinary regulations of European prisons. Their laws...like anywhere else...are directed only against labor... This "beast of order" with its thirst for blood predominates in the mine districts of Illinois. Justice in America is more barbaric than anywhere else. Hanging and lashing is the rule of the day. Beggars and "Vagabonds" are called criminals and left to die of hunger in the homes for destitute, sometimes as it was brought to light just recently, to make use of the corpse, even going as far as to use the human skin in tanneries...</p>
   <p>The labor movement here as well as elsewhere was a road of thorns before the right road was found. A quantity of necessary material is at hand everywhere for the founding of a strictly revolutionary labor party. It is to be hoped that the near future will see the end of capitalism, and freedom and equality shall reign here and everywhere. "Agitate and organize" was the speaker's plea"but above everything else arm yourselves. Rebel when the proper time comes, and assure labor's triumph! Without a battle there can be no victory!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
