<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-20">Feb. 20, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Germans of 6th Ward and Better Irish Element Favor Washington Hesing.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-20">Feb. 20, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANS OF 6TH WARD AND BETTER IRISH ELEMENT FAVOR WASHINGTON HESING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-American citizens of the 6th Ward met at Germania Hall, Halsted Street, yesterday. This meeting ought to be a good reminder of the old proverb: "Never count your chickens before they are hatched!" - (verbatim: Do not figure your bill without the Inn Keeper, - but this homily is unknown here, Translator)</p>
   <p>It happens that the delegates of the 6th ward have promised the district to Harrison, but a very gratifying fact changes all this, since the well attended meeting brought a large contingent of well known, influential Irishmen who enthusiastically declared themselves for Hesing. Mr. Herman Remberg, president of the 6th Ward German-American Democratic Hesing Club, opened the meeting.</p>
   <p>Mr. William Umbach, speaking in English, called attention to the necessity of making immediate preparations for a complete Hesing ticket, listing the primary delegates, as no just or honest action can be expected from the regular Democratic committee. Mr. Umbach also emphasized that a good <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1466.jpg" n="2"/>aldermanic candidate will have considerable influence in procuring a winning ticket.</p>
   <p>General Lieb spoke in German and appealed to the crowd to take united action in behalf of the German-American mayoral candidate. Take heed of this opportunity, a chance which you never had before. It is now within your power to cleanse Chicago's political life once and for all. We are not appearing here as proud defenders of Germanity but as citizens who are aware of the deplorable conditions which engulf us and all our compatriots, Irish, Scandinavian, native born, etc., who object to this intolerable environment, and are now asked to make a concerted effort to balk the opposing force.</p>
   <p>It appears that the attitude of the various foreign elements in our national groups is a thoroughly friendly one, since nobody dissented when the president offered the following resolution, subject to a vote of acceptance.</p>
   <p>"This meeting of German-American citizens of the 6th ward resolves to give its entire support to Washington Hesing, candidate for mayor of Chicago, as we have the fullest confidence in him. He will give Chicago a better <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1467.jpg" n="3"/>administration than it ever had before.</p>
   <p>"That we will do everything within our power that his candidacy may be assured at the Democratic convention."</p>
   <p>Among those present, were noted the following prominent citizens from the ward: (46 names are published). Another meeting was arranged for next Tuesday...</p>
   <p>The 21st, 3rd, 30th, 2nd, and 22nd wards have announced Hesing meetings for tonight.... All have German-Democratic clubs....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
