<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1905-11-06">November 6, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to German-American Citizens.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1387</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1387.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1905-11-06">November 6, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO GERMAN-AMERICAN CITIZENS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tomorrow is an important day for Chicago. It is election day! For the first time the citizens have the right to elect the president for the Sanitary District of Chicago, themselves. For the first time the president will have the power to give his veto on dubious affairs in the administration. For the first time the major part of the German-American population has the opportunity to put the office of president, with a clear conscience and pride, into the hands of a worthy and experienced man of German descent, Mr. Frank Wenter.</p>
   <p>It is well known what Mr. Frank Wenter has done in his many years of service as president and trustee of the Sanitary District. His capability, experience, honesty, and his manly struggle in behalf of the rights and advantages of taxpayers against the Republican majority have found, even including the English press, universal appreciation. Mr. Frank Wenter has refuted, in a satisfactory manner, all accusations and misrepresentations of facts brought against him by the Republican party, but the English press in its blind favoritism and partiality for the rich, inexperienced candidate of twenty-five years of age, of the Republican Party, has hardly taken any notice of it. To make a short process of this injustice and to best serve the well-being of Chicago, it will <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1388.jpg" n="2"/>be absolutely necessary for the Chicago voters of German descent to cooperate and support tomorrow, with complete disregard of party views, Mr. Frank Wenter for president and trustee of the Sanitary District.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
