<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1915-04-04">Apr. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Misleading Issues</title><title level="a" type="sub">Thompson's Followers Attempt to Split up the Germans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1275</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1275.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1915-04-04">Apr. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">MISLEADING ISSUES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Thompson's Followers Attempt to Split up the Germans</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last days of the campaign, an undercurrent has been noticeable which can be traced back to the introduction, into the campaign, of the religious issue. This issue has not been openly exploited, but rather surreptitiously. Thompson's Anglo-American Masonic followers have become very active, especially in the suburban districts, and have tried to stir up sentiment against Robert M. Sweitzer by appealing directly to the voters. They have made an attempt to carry the pro-Thompson propaganda also into the circles of German Freemasons, but it is learned that they have met with scant success.</p>
   <p>Try to Split-up Germans</p>
   <p>Politicians who are familiar with the circumstances recall the statement of Thompson's campaign manager, James A. Pugh, that he would split up the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1276.jpg" n="2"/>German vote, thus preventing the German element from supporting Sweitzer en bloc [in a body]. Pugh is that noble gentleman and bosom pal of Thompson who, in September, five weeks after the war had started, offered his $50,000 motor boat "Disturber IV", the fastest boat of its kind, to the British Government for reconnaissance purposes against Germany. Political circles are of the opinion, that Pugh is exploiting the religious issue to the limit, because he and Thompson's other henchmen have come to the conclusion that this was the only way to split up the Germans, who have been united ever since the war began.</p>
   <p>German Masons Indignant</p>
   <p>Prominent German Masons are very indignant about dragging the religious issue into the campaign, for which the Masons will largely be blamed. A number of prominent members of the order are open supporters of Sweitzer. They point out that the doctrines of their organization forbid the amalgamation of religious and political issues, and that the agitation pursued by certain <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1277.jpg" n="3"/>parties contradicts the principles of the order. They also state that the German members of the order should not let themselves be misled by these false issues, but should keep the personality of the candidate in mind and the interests of the German element at heart. They [the prominent German Masons] quite frankly admit that the agitation of the Anglo-American Masons among German Masonic circles is nothing but the attempt of selfish elements to further their own ends.</p>
   <p>Warning to Germans</p>
   <p>Henry W. Huttmann, former master of the Lessing Lodge and late member of the school board, yesterday commented on this aspect of the campaign as follows: "Issues of the kind which Thompson and his men have dragged into the campaign and are trying to exploit in [German] Masonic circles, do not belong there at all. Their discussion contradicts Masonic principles. German Masons should first of all keep in mind what the election of Thompson <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1278.jpg" n="4"/>would mean for the Deutschtum [German element] of the city and of the country, and what the German Mason, so proud of his liberal-mindedness, could expect from William Hale Thompson as far as liberal movements are concerned. They should remember that William Hale Thompson and his campaign manager, James A. Pugh, offered the British Government their $50,000 motor boat, the fastest of its kind, for operations against Germany. The British Government was to use her for reconnaissance purposes. This throws a peculiar light on Thompson's alleged pro-German attitude. German Masons, furthermore, should not forget that Thompson has been indorsed by the Anti-Saloon League and similar prohibitionist organizations, which have secured his co-operation for next year, when they will try to make Chicago dry. This clearly shows that the present election campaign is regarded by these elements only as an overture to the main contest to be waged next year against liberal-mindedness. These are the problems which should guide German Masons at next Tuesday's election, not the false "issues" raised by Thompson and his Anglo-American clique."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
