<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-03-22">Mar. 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Communistic Propaganda</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-03-22">Mar. 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">COMMUNISTIC PROPAGANDA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Central Committee of the Communist party in Russia recently published a survey of the work which it has done during the past five years. The article was written by Pianitzki and approved by Glavit, the official censor of the Soviet Union, and thus received official status. It contains several paragraphs about propaganda in the United States, relates what has been accomplished thus far, and instructs agitators with reference to future activity. It is pointed out that intensive propaganda must be carried on in factories and mines, and that it must be increased to the limit when the dissatisfaction of the workers becomes evident through strikes. The Communists have designs also upon the American farmer.</p>
   <p>These instructions are of special interest in connection with the recent statement by a representative of the Soviet Union in Washington to the effect <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0457.jpg" n="2"/>that propaganda in the United States would cease. These two contradictory facts cast a doubtful light upon the honesty of the statement of the representative.</p>
   <p>However, we need not worry, for despite all Russian propaganda, international communism will not make much headway here, and a complete success of the agents of the Soviet Union may be relegated to the realm of improbability. This verdict is justified in view of the fact that communism could not gain a foothold even during the worst years of the depression. Still it is probable that constant propaganda will evoke local dissatisfaction and local disturbances, and that the American workers will always be the ones to suffer.</p>
   <p>This duplicity of the Russians should cause American workmen to think twice before permitting themselves to be made victims of communistic propaganda, for Russian communism has not yet proved that it can keep its promises. Its success in Russia is of so doubtful a nature that one must deny it the ability to make workers in foreign countries happy. Its promises are no more <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0458.jpg" n="3"/>reliable than the statement of its representative in Washington; for the excuse that the Russian Government has nothing to do with governing the Communist party is altogether too flimsy.</p>
   <p>As far as the leaders of communism are concerned, it is merely a matter of forcing their system upon the world for the purpose of gaining greater and more extensive power; the welfare of the individual worker, however, has no place in their plans. Of course, the gentlemen who reap the benefits need not suffer, and the greater the realm of communism, the greater their power. If every American workman understood the aims of communism, he would think well before casting the money which he earned by the sweat of his brow down the insatiable throat of communism. Should a conflict arise between our Government and local communists, and the agitators find it too uncomfortable here, they will follow the example given by their colleagues in Austria and vanish from the country. And the money contributed by American workers will be invested in foreign countries, and will dissappear at the same time the braggarts do. The members of the party, however, who have <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0459.jpg" n="4"/>been cheated will be left to their own devices, and will be graciously permitted to whistle for their money.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
