<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-08-25">August 25th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Protective Tariff and the Workers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-08-25">August 25th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Protective Tariff and the Workers.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Undoubtedly the workers are today better organized than ever before. The workers are closely organized in local and national unions in many industries, where ten years ago no unions existed. The number of unions is increasing and the individual unions have a larger membership than before. Their treasuries are well filled and their influence and power has steadily increased. Everywhere they are recognized as important economic factors. In most of the larger and the largest industries they control the situation to such an extent, that it becomes a necessity for workers to join the unions, and that employers are under obligation to hire union members only.</p>
   <p>One can think about the question of the "open" and "closed" shop as he pleases, but the recent crushing defeat of unionism by the Steeltrusts is rather deplorable. If there is an industry, where a strong union is necessary, it is the steel industry. There is no industry, where workers are less paid and more exploited, than this one. No other industry, on the other hand, enjoys such a high protective tariff, or in other words, in no other large industry is it made possible by means of high tariffs, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0134.jpg" n="2"/>to extract such high prices from the public, because of their being organized in trusts. Their industry is favored by nature; they gain larger profits, pay less to the workers on the average and exploit them more than any other one.</p>
   <p>They told us that protective tariffs means protection for workers. Since the idea of protection attracted attention, the defenders argued that high tariffs are essential for the protection of workers.</p>
   <p>They asserted that only high protective tariff would make it possible to keep wages on such high levels in order to assure the free American worker a high standard of living. Will the workers and the public in general again listen to the defenders of high protective tariffs? No doubt this will happen in as much as the great Colonel Theodore Roosevelt-himself will be for it. In all the seven years of his administration he never said a word against high tariffs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
