<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-02">Apr. 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1223</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1223.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-02">Apr. 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The primaries are approaching. In the gigantic arena of politics, battles are being waged, and here in Chicago the din of the conflict is even greater than in most other cities. And no wonder! For in these primaries candidates are nominated not only for Congress, but also for the state legislature and for county offices. In a city of three million inhabitants the number of aspirants for political offices is so large that the public is hardly able properly to inform itself of the record, the character, and the abilities of all the sundry candidates.</p>
   <p>Because of this bewildering profusion of candidates, there is the danger that a certain indifference and a tepid attitude may manifest themselves among those numerous voters who display but a slight interest in politics. This is easy to understand and is readily pardonable; but the voters should take enough <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1224.jpg" n="2"/>interest in the primaries so as to remember their tried and true friends on election day. Among these friends is Congressman Fred A. Britten.</p>
   <p>Mr. Britten finds himself opposed by an exceedingly energetic and active rival in his own election district, the Ninth Congressional. Both candidates are running on approximately the same platform; both pursue the same aims in national and local politics. But for the attainment of these aims, Fred Britten is undoubtedly the better fitted: He has been in Congress for the last fourteen years. All during that long period, he has had the opportunity to become thoroughly familiar with the procedures and the methods employed in Congress. But above all, he belongs on the Committee on Naval Affairs, whose vice-chairman he is. This is one of the most important and most influential offices Congress has to offer.</p>
   <p>It is at all times a good principle to re-elect Representatives who have proved their mettle in politics; and according to this principle, Fred Britten is entitled to re-election. In this connection it must not be forgotten that he has always been one of the most decisive and active opponents of Prohibition in the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1225.jpg" n="3"/>House. He is valued by John P. Hill of Baltimore, the leader of the wet wing in the House, as a zealous and influential co-operator.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
