<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-03-26">March 26, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">In Tribute to Karl Marx.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0862</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0862.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-03-26">March 26, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">IN TRIBUTE TO KARL MARX.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "Official" section of the old Chicago "National Socialist Labor Party" held a meeting yesterday at 54 West Lake Street, at which Mr. Sloan was Chairman and Mr. Kruger, Secretary. Paul Ehmann read the biography of the illustrious Karl Marx (deceased) paying tribute to the invaluable services which he rendered labor.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Julius Vahlteich, formerly a member of the Imperial German Parliament, now a member of the staff of the Chicago servile newspaper (evidently the Illinois Staat Zeitung). He spoke on the labor question in general and expressed himself in favor of political participation at elections. He also paid tribute to Karl Marx, the man of great merits. The speaker said, it is essential first to convert the great masses of workers to Socialism, before force could be resorted to. The next speaker was Mr. Dusey who said that the Star- Spangled Banner of America has fallen so low that it now resembles nothing but a dirty rag. For this remark he was reprimanded by the Chairman and Mr. Morgan. He also was denied resuming his speech.</p>
   <p>A debate ensued thereafter as to whether or not to participate at the spring elections. Morgan thought that the elections in this country are only in the interest of capital. The immense funds which stand at the disposal of the old parties, and against which labor is powerless, deprives it of its rights. Not the will of the people but the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0863.jpg" n="2"/>almighty dollar is the deciding factor in elections. Therefore it would be advisable not to consider a full ticket. A resolution in that sense was accepted. Kempke reported that the Northside Socialists nominated Christian Meier as candidate for the office of assessor of North-Towns and was indorsed by the Republicans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
