<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-03-17">Mar. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Number of Unemployed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0397</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0397.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-03-17">Mar. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE NUMBER OF UNEMPLOYED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the current plans of Administration officials in Washington are carried out, for the first time in the history of this country a census will be taken before the close of the usual decennial period. The plans are said to have been approved already by President Roosevelt, and are based chiefly upon a short report of the Scripps Foundation for Research in Population Problems, which proved, by statistics, that there has been, in the last few years, a steady deceleration in the increase in population of the United States. According to this report, on January 1 of this year the total population of this country was approximately 126,144,000, or only six tenths of one per cent more than on January 1 of last year. Only twice since 1870 has a lower per cent increase occurred during the course of a single year.</p>
   <p>The last official census was taken, of course, in 1930. But, as since that <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0398.jpg" n="2"/>time there are said to have been extensive shifts in the population of the urban and rural districts, the figures of the last census are not at all dependable, according to the census bureau of the American Statistical Association.</p>
   <p>This is especially true with respect to the number of unemployed, a subject about which no two people agree. Estimates often vary by millions. Naturally, this matter could only be settled by a new census.</p>
   <p>It is the especial task of the House Committee on the Census to determine the exact number of those now unemployed, in order to ascertain how effective the various relief measures of the Government have been up to the present time, and what further action is necessary in order to effect a change.</p>
   <p>A new census would give about one hundred and fifty thousand unemployed office workers temporary jobs, which is at least as necessary for them as for other unemployed, who can find renumerative employment at hand labor much more <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0399.jpg" n="3"/>easily, when business conditions improve, than the so-called intellectual workers.</p>
   <p>The cost of the new census is estimated at ten million dollars, a sum with which a certain amount of aid could be given to those circles [i. e., the office workers], in which the money is no less needed than elsewhere [i. e., among manual laborers].</p>
   <p>Since the census is to give especial attention to agricultural relationships, concerning which there seems to be much ignorance, we can expect light to be thrown on this subject, also, which seems very necessary, as it could point the way for future relief measures.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
