<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-07-17">July 17, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A Consequence Leads to Consequences</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0495</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0495.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-07-17">July 17, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A CONSEQUENCE LEADS TO CONSEQUENCES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From Germany come reports which indicate that the Hitler Government is rigorously pursuing its course to buttress its power. The methods employed are not of the kind to make friends for the new German rulers. Even those who until now have regarded the Hitler regime without prejudice, and who first wanted to see what Hitler would do for Germany, will find it increasingly difficult to maintain their benevolent neutrality. The Government of the Reich may be sure that there are many such benevolent neutrals whose vision has not been dimmed by any propaganda and who are not going to display the same lack of objectivity that distinguishes Hitler's avowed opponents. But just these strictly objective appraisers of the National Socialist regime must view with alarm the latest reports from Germany.</p>
   <p>In the first place, these reports, which are based on facts, are intrinsically <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0496.jpg" n="2"/>interesting. Five relatives of Philipp Scheidemann, former chancellor of the Reich, have been taken to a concentration camp as a reprisal for Scheidemann's newspaper articles, which he wrote from Prague, denouncing the Hitler regime. Furthermore, a decree has been issued, empowering the Government of the Reich to take away the rights of citizenship from Germans in foreign lands who make statements which the German Government considers detrimental to its interests. This applies especially to those Germans abroad who have, in a legal sense, remained German subjects, and only enjoy hospitality within the sovereign territority of a foreign power. The decree goes even further than that by permitting confiscation of the private property of the German found guilty, in addition to the abrogation of his citizenship.</p>
   <p>For those Germans abroad who have found a new home in a foreign country, but have not yet become naturalized citizens of that land, the cancellation of their German citizenship means more than a mere formality, because a person without a state would not know, in an emergency, to which consul he should turn for protection. The decree is of still greater consequence to Germans <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0497.jpg" n="3"/>who are visiting abroad and, who, trusting in the discretion of their listeners, make derogatory remarks about the Hitler regime. If the Government of the Reich should learn of an utterance of this kind, loss of citizenship could be effected in this case also. This practice sooner or later is bound to get the German Government into difficulties with other countries, which will probably not stand for the permanent residence of these guests within their territory. Since it cannot be assumed that the authors of this decree deliberately tried to pave the way for frictions of this sort, we can only conclude that they did not realize this potential source of arguments and conflicts.</p>
   <p>The proceedings of the Prussian Government against the relatives of Scheidemann remind us of the hostage system, which was instituted by the French and Belgians during the occupation of the Ruhr. Prominent German citizens had to ride in French and Belgian military trains, that they might either forestall bombings and sabotage or suffer together with the alien soldiers. If Scheidemann, Wels, Stampfer, Vogel, and the others cannot be reached themselves, then vengeance <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0498.jpg" n="4"/>is wreaked on their relatives, who are not at all responsible. This is contradictory to the ordinary, human sense of justice, and certainly will not make any friends for the National Socialist regime, either inside or outside of Germany. At the same time we want to express our opinion to the effect that it certainly does not speak for the patriotism of any voluntary exiles, if they propagandize against their native land while abroad. German political arguments have no place abroad, and every good German will respect and stand up for his country regardless of the party in power. Germans abroad, and other friends of Germany, would be very gratified if the Hitler regime were not so overzealous in the fight against its political enemies, or if it would not carry this campaign beyond the boundaries of the Reich. But beyond its frontiers the Reich has more reasons than one to preserve old friendships and to cultivate new ones. The present radical methods hardly seem likely to achieve this purpose. All sincere friends of Germany living abroad should regret that very much.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
