<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-16">Feb. 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Washington Hesing's Headquarters Opened.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1484</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1484.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-16">Feb. 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">WASHINGTON HESING'S HEADQUARTERS OPENED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Washington Hesing opened his headquarters yesterday in an erstwhile bank office, southwest of Dearborn and Washington Sts. The establishment is equipped with all conveniences and has been partitioned to provide a large waiting room, and private offices for Mr. Hesing, the campaign managers, the clerical force and typists. From early morning until the late evening hours the place is a modern Mecca for influential politicians and businessmen. That corner will be a busy bee-hive; the staff will labor assiduously, perhaps more so than has been customary during former pre-convention days.</p>
   <p>Hesing's chances improve consistently and such politicians as John P. Hopkins assert confidently, that his nomination will be a certainty. A branch of the Central Committee, which has been entrusted with the management of the primary election, took cognizance of the various complaints from divers wards yesterday, since there was some objection to the selection of election places and judges. The first ten wards were scanned thoroughly; the lists of the committee members were either accepted in their entirety, or partially revised to satisfy every candidate.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1485.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>First Ward: The German-American Club of the 1st Ward arranged a meeting at Zimmermann's Hall yesterday; it was well attended and 35 new members joined the ranks. The speakers, Pres. Jacob Zimmermann .... and ... eight others, were fervently favoring Hesing's nomination but aside from this, the Club had already endorsed him.</p>
   <p>15th Ward: The Young Democratic Club of the 15th Ward elected its officers last Tuesday: President Ludmil Kandlik and .... ten other officials. Its next regular session will be on Tuesday evening at their hall, California and Armitage Aves.</p>
   <p>Notes: On Monday evening, Hesing supporters in the 3rd Ward will hold a meeting, 31st St. and Indiana Ave.</p>
   <p>Fred Stoll, a well known German of the 9th Ward, is a candidate for Town Clerk of the West Side.</p>
   <p>Friday evening: A large meeting, for Germans from all wards, has been arranged at the Orpheus Hall under the auspices of the German Democratic Central Association. The issues of the spring election will be considered.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1486.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Democrats of the 24th Ward favor Hesing ... Resolutions to nominate him and work in his interests follow:</p>
   <p>"He is the friend of Cleveland, of Altgeld; we should leave no stone unturned to nominate Hesing"... One of the resolutions eulogizes Hesing's pro-Democratic publicity campaign in the following manner:... "That our Chicago Democracy should give tribute to Washington Hesing for his achievements and service to our cause, and for the support which the Illinois Staats Zeitung has given us during the last great political campaign; furthermore, that a Democratic headquarters was obtained for Chicago during the last presidential election, that Washington Hesing was the principle leader of the Democratic party during its last victory and he therefore deserves recognition accordingly." "Explanation: W. Hesing was the editor of the Staats Zeitung at that time, translator.)</p>
   <p>German Democrats of the 22nd Ward: The German-American Club of the 22nd Ward meets this evening at Ziesler's Hall, North Clark St., near North Ave., in order to make all the necessary arrangements which the preliminary work for elections entails. It is very desirable to have a large membership <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1487.jpg" n="4"/>attendance on this occasion for the general advancement of the cause.</p>
   <p>German Democrats, Lake View: The leading German Democrats from the 25th and 26th Wards (Lake View), show their ambitions by making extensive preparations for a mass meeting of German Democrats in the interests of the Hesing campaign. Location: Kuechler's Hall, Lincoln and Halsted St. The time will be announced later.</p>
   <p>The Humboldt Club of the 15th Ward: This club met yesterday and the mayoral election provided a lively topic. Thus far a definite choice for a candidate has been held in abeyance, but sentiment is decidedly in favor of Hesing. Mr. Victor Teraski has been unanimously indorsed by the Club as the representative of the 15th Ward for the City Council. Mr. Teraski is a prominent German of the ward. He is the owner of a large cigar factory at 84-88 S. Franklin St.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
