<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-01">Nov. 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">A Guest, Ernst Toller</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0510</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0510.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-01">Nov. 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">A GUEST, ERNST TOLLER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago recently had the enviable distinction of having Ernst Toller as its guest. This literary luminary was the instigator of the Munich October revolution, with its attendant council evils.</p>
   <p>Since the time when Toller ignored the council government and high-handedly put his coffee-house theories into political practice, he suffers with a certain inflation of the ego. He discovered his talent for statesmanship as he looked Moscowward. The prophet who suffered political oblivion and is of literary importance only to Alfred Kerr in Berlin, goads him on.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0511.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What then can be more natural than to seek the despised dollar in its lair and land, America? And here he expresses his revolutionary disdain for the Philistine German-American institutions, a contempt uninfluenced even by a knowledge of facts.</p>
   <p>According to Ernst Toller, we, his lamentable contemporaries, vegetate ignominiously in this country, which thus far has not been liberated by the relentlessly forward bounding spirit of Moscow.</p>
   <p>Of all the horrors! Our German theater feeds us on plays where counts marry working girls, and Kaiser Joseph personally distributes castles! In this cultural atmosphere, we are not enabled to appreciate an Ernst Toller. Our narrow-minded citizenry never heard of his drama "Hinkemann" (Limp, Man), which by the way, slumbers imperturbably in our public <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0512.jpg" n="3"/>libraries.</p>
   <p>For Toller and the higher plane of his world outlook, we are, of course irrevocably lost, and he did not hesitate to tell us that in a most emphatic manner. In his opinion, we do not accord him the proper credit which his literary and political importance deserves. And the lack of this esteem induced him to vent his violent temperament on several occasions. If facts do not contradict us, then we might say, we're hopeless!</p>
   <p>And this prompts us to ask with naive temerity, just why did Toller come over here? Was he to function as an apostle in partibus infidelium, - in the lands of infidels, - much in the manner of the prophets of the old testament, and admonish us of our sins?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0513.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Hardly! Ernst Toller discovered himself. He found that a poet and politician are a prodigious combination, that the latter's brainstorm revolutions are suitable for capitalization and exploitation, at least abroad. Whether the apostle of the Red soviet salvation will be successful also in promoting exorbitant meat prices in this domain, is still an open question. At all events, German-America can thank him for his well-meant kind instructions, and incidentally, wish him success in his apostolic mission, in which the following quotation may come handy:</p>
   <p>"As long as the coins drop into the cage, The poet will dance on the stage!"</p>
   <p>[This is a parody on the proverb which aroused such a bitter controversy during Martin Luther's time. When the money tinkles <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0514.jpg" n="5"/>in the collection box, the soul jumps from purgatory to heaven. Ernst Toller gave a lecture at the Lincoln Turner Hall, 1005 Diversey Parkway, on October 30, and at Wicker Park Hall, 2040 West North Avenue, on October 29, under the auspices of the Chicago Workers Cultural and Sport Association. He spoke on the World War and its consequences, and read his poems about the fight of the proletariat, as well as some of his other works.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
