<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-31">Mar. 31, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The City Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1623</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1623.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-31">Mar. 31, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE CITY ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In scheduling the municipal elections for the spring, and separating them from the national elections held in November, the motive was to exclude all national and state questions from local issues. The main thought was that the City elections should be limited to practical problems involving the administration of the community.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly, the object was commendable; but matters did not function in that manner. The national political parties, just as formerly, considered the municipal elections a challenge for power and "boodle". But just as formerly, city affairs were obscured, while memories of the Civil War (and happenings in Washington) came to the fore. This was shown by Harrison's speech after his return from the capitol, wherein he gave the fundamentals by which the election was to be conducted; that is, in the good old way.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1624.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Just as he extolled the sovereignty of the separate states and advocated revolting against the centralized despotism of the Republican party, so the Republican orators attacked with frenzied fervor the "Rebellocrats", "confederate generals," the slave-holding gentry, etc. Tomorrow's election was thus considered a test of strength for the presidential propects in 1880.</p>
   <p>The local Germans, however, showed little inclination to subscribe to this view in as far as the impending municipal election is concerned. The preponderant majority was aloof and critical, being interested only in reaching an opinion based on the characters of the various candidates, rather than showing concern about national political attitudes. Besides, the Germans endeavored to ascertain the opinions of the prospective officials on matters pertaining to temperance and Sunday laws. With respect to these, Wright and Harrison, mayoral candidates, expressed themselves in such a manner that the fanatical "drys" and Sunday hypocrites decided to vote for Harrison. While Wright stated irrevocably that he intends to follow the precepts of Heath, Mr. Harrison resorted to ambiguous expressions which might be <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1625.jpg" n="3"/>construed as a concurrence with the views of the zealots. And thus we are faced with the anomalous position where many a German Republican casts his vote along with the Prohibitionists and blue-law bigots in support of a Democrat, because that candidate's dubious explanations are considered more satisfactory than the direct, definite declarations of the Republican.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, tomorrow's decision will show whether Chicago is to be ruled by the allied Americans and Germans, or by the Irish, because the election of Wright would be tantamount to a continuance of the Heath administration of the preceding three years, whereas if Harrison attains office it means a reinstallation of Hibernian control and the reawakening of the sad memories associated with it. We had enough of it, more than sufficient! We don't envy the taste of anyone clamoring for a new edition!</p>
   <p>We never doubted that Mr. Harrison is a very respectable man--but likewise, we feel convinced that, if he is elected mayor, he will not be able to withstand the domineering Irish influence any better (even if he wanted to) than <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1626.jpg" n="4"/>Colvin did.</p>
   <p>It is the trite, time-worn tale about the dog and the tail; which wags? If the appendage were stronger than the canine, then the elongation of the spine would wag the animal. But, unfortunately, this part of the vertebrae does not excel in power!</p>
   <p>Whoever desires, for the sake of change, that Chicago shall be governed again by the Irish, and longs for an annual tax increase of three and one-half to five million dollars, should vote for Harrison tomorrow.</p>
   <p>However, anyone believing that such a German alliance with the decent, liberally inclined Americans, as existed under Heath, will provide for the city the most capable, honest and frugal administration, should cast his ballot for Wright.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
