<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-08-08">August 8, 1878</date><title level="a">Socialist Mass Meeting at the Marketplace</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-08-08">August 8, 1878</date><title level="a">Socialist Mass Meeting at the Marketplace</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Socialist Labor Party of Chicago called a mass meeting last night to Market Souare, to express their joy over results of the German Reichstag election, and in order to have resolutions passed regarding the founding of a daily newspaper in the English language.</p>
   <p>In front of the Vorbote's business office a stand was erected for German speakers. Mr. Paul Grottkau spoke first. He pointed to the necessity of founding an English daily paper, and tried to prove that the English capitalist press constantly suppresses facts which do not fit into its purposes. If, in Germany, a horse race takes place, if a court ball is given, if Bismarck's imperial cur (dog) is indisposed, then it prints reports filling whole columns. But when that result of the Reichstag elections are in favor of the Socialist, then, the news simply is suppressed or distorted. Formerly, it was an adage, - "He lies as it is printed". Now it should be said, "He lies as it is telegraphed."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1082.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>By this time, the North Side procession arrived, playing the tune of the Marseillaise, and it was enthusiastically cheered by the crowd that had increased to about 4500 persons.</p>
   <p>Mr. Grottkau continued to speak about the victory in Germany, and expressed his delight that the Socialists of Chicago showed interest in the fight on the other side of the ocean by being present. A Strohle, the next speaker, mentioned the success of the picnic, which was held a few months ago, producing a net profit of $3,000. This is to be used for the founding of an English daily paper, of which the first copy will be issued in two weeks.</p>
   <p>He then spoke about the attacks on William I, calling it truly ridiculous to make millions of people responsible for an assault conducted by two individuals. But that the people here and at home condemn the system of Government, is shown both by the Reichstag elections on July 30th, and by the mass meetings held here. The fall elections will also show, in Chicago, that we still condemn the happenings in the Vorwarts Turnhalle, a little over a year ago, when the authorities trampled the rights of humans under foot.</p>
   <p>There followed, Belohradsky, who spoke in Bohemian.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1083.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From the other platform the German-American, Schilling, made a speech. Organizer Morgan introduced a certain Mr. Green, who read the following telegram:</p>
   <p>To the editor of the Vorwarts in Leipzig: Ten Thousand Socialists of Chicago, assembled at the Market Place, send their brothers in Germany hearty greetings.</p>
   <p>The assembly departed in the best of order. It was estimated that around Twenty-five Hundred persons were present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
