<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1895-03-22">March 22, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Local Politics Wenter's Boom in South Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1895-03-22">March 22, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">LOCAL POLITICS WENTER'S BOOM IN SOUTH CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The candidate for Mayor, Frank Wenter, spoke yesterday in a serious, convincing,matter-of-fact manner to about 5,000 voters in the 33rd and 34th wards. In Liberty Hall he was welcomed by more than 3,000 persons and in the gymnastic hall at Grand Crossing more than 2,000 voters showed their enthusiasm for his election.</p>
   <p>Both halls were filled to their utmost capacity. Wenters declarations in favor of a municipal administration on business principles and careful consideration of civil service measures have been received with great approval, both by Republicans and Democrats. The meeting in South Chicago was preceded by a torch parade of more than 1,000 persons. It was one of the greatest political demonstrations ever effected in South Chicago. In Liberty Hall John Mc Cabe presided. Mr. Wenter spoke in English and German. He especially emphasized that if elected he would be the Mayor of the whole community and the whole town. Though he always had been a Democrat, he did not think that <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1421.jpg" n="2"/>this should interfere with his election as Mayor of Chicago, as the principle point for Chicago always would be a good administration by the City Council, and not a party question. Thousands of Republicans would vote for him, as he was no machine politician, and never had been unworthy of the confidence placed in him. Mr. John S. Cook, candidate for City Treasurer, told the meeting, among great hilarity that fifteen years ago he hunted wolves in South Chicago and today he is hunting for votes. He also spoke against machine politics. Speeches were also made by Mr. Wm. Mangler, candidate for City Clerk, Charles F. Haines, A. I. Kowalski and Frank H. White.</p>
   <p>At the meeting in Grand Crossing Bryan Tighe presided and Wenter was welcomed with great enthusiasm and his statements were generally approved. Shortly after 8 o'clock, not a seat could be had any more. Speeches were made by John S. Cooke, Charles H. Mitchel, Wm. Johnson and the candidate for alderman, John Mc Govrty and with a triple cheer to the Democratic candidates the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
