<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-08-03">Aug. 3,1880</date>.
<title level="a">(Parson's Excursion's to the Armed Organizations) Supplement to the Excursion of the Armed Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0929</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.9"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0929.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 9</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-08-03">Aug. 3,1880</date>.
<title level="a">(PARSON'S EXCURSION'S TO THE ARMED ORGANIZATIONS) Supplement to the Excursion of the Armed Organizations</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Member, A. R. Parsons, held a speech in the English language at the place of festival in which he said as follows:-</p>
   <p>"Lack of time and means make it ordinarily impossible for the workman and his family to participate in a celebration as it has been done in this one here. This was an extraordinary opportunity and it is not an ordinary picnic which has called the thousands of workman to the beautiful park. This is a brotherly celebration of men, who have the same opinions and follow the same ideas and fight for the same principles. All are opponents of the present political system as it reigns in all the United States.</p>
   <p>The underlying idea for the formation of the Armed Organization of the proletarians of Chicago has been to give battle to the present system of industry oppressing the workman and condemning him to eternal poverty as reward for his work and diligence. If sacred rights which sustain the liberty and the happiness of the people are taken away from them, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0930.jpg" n="2"/>if all peaceful means have been exhausted to induce the usurpers to return them to the proletariat to whom they rightfully belong, the last means and ways are, the last help and greatest duty of everyone to take up the arms. Worlds history has proved that only those who have been capable to defend their personal liberty who have been prepared and in the condition to force their justified demands. The Armed Organization of the workmen is the last resource to be kept in reserve if all other means and ways have failed. The vote boxes and all other careful ways to secure a Reform of the present system are under the command of the capital. The financial condition of the proletarian does not permit him to get the independence which guides him to preserve his free vote and a justified election. The rich real estate owners and manufacturers and the Kings of Monopol system control the elections by bribery, intimidation and corruption.</p>
   <p>The speaker demonstrated principally the present powerlessness of the working classes which must consequently lead to a revolution if no help will come.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0931.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Who would not employ force, if all peaceable ways have failed to get one's right? It is only power, which sustains the throne of the despot. Only power can maintain the existing systems and forms of Government. Our ancestors have already given the example in 1776, which has been followed by the Armed Organization of Chicago of the Cooperating Workmen. It is the duty of everyone to defend the right and battle the wrong. Who can deny that the present system to give the product of hard labor of the one to the other for exploitation? A system, which maintains slavery, which neither allows Masters nor slaves. The speaker continued that the workman looks for liberty of mind and soul. If the body is kept in slavery, mental blindness must follow. Therefore every proletarian whould work for the emancipation of labour. Everybody should join the glorified red flag of liberty and equality as a lifelong fighter and make a determined stand for the rights of humanity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
