<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-06-14">June 14, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">A Serious Lesson.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-06-14">June 14, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">A SERIOUS LESSON.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Local English papers estimate the number of Chicago's unemployed laborers at the present time at from 20,000 to 30,000. However, one has to take into consideration the usual American exaggeration, where a few oughts more or less is immaterial. It is not nearly so bad, not even half as bad; nevertheless, it is a fact that thousands of men are unemployed, particularly in the building trade. But why do these conditions prevail? Because Mr. "Bricklayer, Carpenter, Painter," etc., have been for the last two years busily engaged in "killing the goose, which laid the golden eggs". By their idiotic strikes they have killed the initiative of others to proceed with the construction of new buildings. By doing this they have hurt themselves, but not at all the "wretched capitalists", because those of them who had their money already invested in new buildings, will receive a considerable higher percentage of interest in rent, than they would get, if they build $25, 000, 000 worth of new homes. The others, who would have built if strikes had not scared them, have invested their money otherwise and no share of <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0260.jpg" n="2"/>However, the goose which laid the golden eggs, and which they have butchered, can not be revived. The criers and instigators, who organized labor and out of whose sayings labor received their "wisdom" are not employing labor, and have no means to force the capitalists to invest their money in new buildings.</p>
   <p>As has been repeatedly mentioned before, the strikes during the last few years originated not from necessity but from arrogance. Strikes occurred not because the condition of the workers was bad, but because they were rather too prosperous. Under the leadership of well-paid instigators and anarchistic agitators they permitted themselves the luxury of living in idleness, for they have sufficient means.</p>
   <p>But now, when men are faced with destitution, when the future looks gloomy, and unemployment stalks through the land, the instigators and agitators escape to other regions, because the stupid men who paid them so well are gone.</p>
   <p>But this is only the beginning. Until now only the building trade has suffered.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0261.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is commencing to slow down in other lines. The proposal of the Democratic Party to abolish tariffs has a paralyzing effect upon the different industries. We can already see how the imports of foreign goods are steadily increasing, and at the same time the export of our own products are continually decreasing. The result is that gold flows to Europe en masse. What will happen if the Mill's tariff amendment becomes a law?</p>
   <p>Perhaps, this would happen; workers would become sensible and modest again after they have destroyed the dignity of labor during recent years by their own mad folly. The "free-traders" aim to put American industry on a competetive basis, which means, expressed in plain terms, that American wages shall be forced down to the European level. If Mr. laborer absolutely insists upon it, then let them do it! Let them make the test! Perhaps the "wretched capitalists" will be glad, if they can hire workers at reasonable wages, who really do work, instead of agitating.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
