<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-02">Nov. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Tuesday's Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">No Citizen Should Fail to Do His Duty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1250</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1250.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-02">Nov. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TUESDAY'S ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">No Citizen Should Fail To Do His Duty</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Next Tuesday the people will have to elect one United States Senator, United States Representatives, state, county, and other officials, as well as city judges. Besides, five very important questions have to be voted on. Three ballots have to be marked, one of which contains the candidates for the city judgeships; the second one, the so-called little ballot, contains the five questions which the people have to answer. The third ballot contains the names of all the other candidates. Since the election is of the utmost importance for the nation, the state, and the county, no citizen who takes his civic responsibility seriously should fail to cast his vote.</p>
   <p>The result of the elections to the United States Congress is of greater importance to the country and to the whole world than any previous congressional election, not even excepting the one after the conclusion of the Civil War. It is the duty of the voters to put men into Congress who are willing <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1251.jpg" n="2"/>to support President Wilson's war and peace policies according to their best ability and conscience; who are not motivated by partisan politics but who will, in every respect, look after the best interests of the country.</p>
   <p>In selecting the candidates for the state, county and municipal offices, the voters should disregard party politics as much as possible. The only criteria should be honesty, capability, and experience gained in office. Men who have proved their excellence should be rewarded by re-election and retained in their offices, since they are more familiar with their duties and, therefore, of greater value to the community and taxpayers than novices who have to be broken in.</p>
   <p>In selecting the candidates for city judgeships, partisan interests should be disregarded entirely, since they have no place on the bench. Integrity, efficiency, legal education and common sense should be the only requirements for a candidate for the municipal court, which is the court of the little man.</p>
   <p>The five questions on the so-called little ballot are of especial interest this <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1252.jpg" n="3"/>year. Most important is the question whether the new traffic ordinance should be adopted. In such a complicated election as that of next Tuesday, a question like this has no place at all, to say nothing of the obvious shortcomings of the measure. It should be answered with "No".</p>
   <p>No less important is the question whether the legislature should call a constitutional convention in order to modify the obsolete basic law of the state, to adjust it to more modern standards and, above all, to make it more useful for the expected period of postwar reconstruction with its manifold new problems. This question is to be answered in the affirmative!</p>
   <p>Hardly less significant is the last question on the little ballot: whether the state should issue bonds to the amount of sixty million dollars for the purpose of constructing a good highway system. We do not have to elaborate on the fact that the state is badly in need of good highways which would be of the greatest benefit for the country as well as the city. The bonds will pay <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1253.jpg" n="4"/>interest and will be redeemed out of the automobile tax and will, therefore, not be any burden to the taxpayer. We urgently request an affirmative answer!</p>
   <p>No less urgent is the issuance of mortgages amounting to three million dollars for completion of the Michigan Boulevard project, which is sponsored by the Chicago Plan Commission and its president, Charles H. Wacker. This question should also be answered with "Yes"!</p>
   <p>The remaining question on the little ballot refers to a change in the bank law which provides greater protection for the small depositor. Here, also, a "yes" is indicated!</p>
   <p>Following an old custom, the Abendpost is submitting to its readers the names of candidates, who are, in its opinion, worthy of support, and whose election would guarantee an efficient administration of affairs in the nation, state, and county. At the same time the Abendpost is making suggestions as to how <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1254.jpg" n="5"/>the questions on the little ballot should be answered. The questions are reproduced in the same order as they appear on the ballot:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>United States Senator</cell>
     <cell>James Hamilton Lewis, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>State Treasurer</cell>
     <cell>James J. Brady, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Superintendent of Education</cell>
     <cell>Francis G. Blair, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Members of the Board of Directors of the State University (elect three)</cell>
     <cell>Cairo A. Trimble, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>John M. Herbert, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Mrs. Mary O. Gallery, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congressmen at Large (elect two)</cell>
     <cell>William E. Williams, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>William E. Mason, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>United States Representatives.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1st</cell>
     <cell>District</cell>
     <cell>Georg Mayer</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2nd</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>James R. Mann</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>3rd</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>W. W. Wilson</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>4th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>John W. Rainey</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>5th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Adolph Sabath</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>6th</cell>
     <cell>District</cell>
     <cell>James McAndrews</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>7th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Frank M. Padden</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>8th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Thomas Gallagher</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>9th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Fred A. Britten</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>10th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>Ph. J. Finnegan</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1255.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>County Offices</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>County Judge</cell>
     <cell>Thomas F. Scully, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Probate Judge</cell>
     <cell>Henry Horner, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Sheriff</cell>
     <cell>Anton J. Cermak, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>County Clerk</cell>
     <cell>Robert M. Sweitzer, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>County Treasurer</cell>
     <cell>Harry R. Gibbons, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Probate Court Clerk</cell>
     <cell>John F. Devine, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Criminal Court Clerk</cell>
     <cell>William R. Parker, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>County School Superintendent</cell>
     <cell>Edward J. Tobin, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Member of Tax Revision Board</cell>
     <cell>P. A. Nash, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Member of Tax Revision Board (substitute election)</cell>
     <cell>Charles V. Barrett, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Member of Board of Assessors (elect two)</cell>
     <cell>Charles Krutckoff, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>John A. Cervenka, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>President of Bureau of Sewers</cell>
     <cell>James M. Daily, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Member of Bureau of Sewers (elect three)</cell>
     <cell>Fred D. Breit, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Harry E. Littler, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>James M. Daily, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1256.jpg" n="7"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>President of the County Council</cell>
     <cell>Peter Reinberg, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Members of the County Council (elect ten)</cell>
     <cell>Peter Reinberg, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Albert Novak, Dem.</cell>
     <cell>Joseph Fitzgerald, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Daniel Ryan, Dem.</cell>
     <cell>Bartley Burg, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Charles Goodnow, Rep.</cell>
     <cell>John Budinger, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>George Seebacher, Rep.</cell>
     <cell>Alexander J. Johnson, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Patrick H. Moynihan, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Municipal Court Judgeships</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Municipal Court Clerk</cell>
     <cell>James A. Kearns, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Municipal Court Bailiff</cell>
     <cell>Dennis J. Egan, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Justice of the Municipal Court</cell>
     <cell>Michael F. Sullivan, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Municipal Judges (elect ten)</cell>
     <cell>John K. Prindiville, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Joseph P. Rafferty, Dem.</cell>
     <cell>Charles A. Williams, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Bernard P. Barasa, Rep.</cell>
     <cell>Stanley S. Walkowiak, Dem.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Wm. Carr Steele, Rep.</cell>
     <cell>Daniel P. Trude Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Clarence S. Piggott, Rep.</cell>
     <cell>Earl C. Hales, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Arnold Heap, Rep.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1257.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Municipal Judge (Substitute Election) Irwin R. Hazen, Rep.</p>
   <p>The Little Ballot</p>
   <p>Shall the new traction ordinance be adopted? No.</p>
   <p>Shall Bonds to the amount of $3,000,000 be spent for completion of the Michigan Boulevard Project? Yes.</p>
   <p>Shall a constitutional convention be called? Yes.</p>
   <p>Proposed change of State Banking Law. In favor.</p>
   <p>Shall bonds to the amount of $60,000,000, bearing interest, and to be redeemed out of the automobile tax, be issued for the construction of good highways? Yes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
