<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-06-10">June 10, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting Without the Masses</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0947</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0947.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-06-10">June 10, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING WITHOUT THE MASSES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Socialist mass meeting, which was hardly worthy of the name, took place last night in Aurora Turner Hall. Although it had been announced that "Barker" Kearney, Dr. Douai of New York, and Mr. Guire of Patterson would speak, the Hall was halrdly half filled, and there was no trace of enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>After Jacob Dilke had been appointed chairman and Frank Kanneberg secretary, the former announced that the main speakers were still detained at the Exposition Building of the Greenbacker Convention but would make their appearance soon. The only one of the scheduled speakers present was Paul Grottkau who, sure enough, did not fail to launch one of his usual filibuster speeches. First, he tried to tell the audience that the two main political parties were about to crumble and that the strength of the third party, which, by the way, was convened at the exposition Building to work out a platform and nominate a presidential candidate, was proof enough that the people did not have any more confidence in the present parties and demanded a change. Grottkau also commented favorably upon womens' <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0948.jpg" n="2"/>emancipation and, in conclusion, read off some statistics on labor conditions, from which he tried to prove"that the exploitation of millions by a few thousands must be combated and stopped". After a few digs at the Republican presidential candidate Garfield and the platform put up at the National Convention, the speaker concluded his remarks and yielded the floor to P. J. McGuire of St. Louis.</p>
   <p>Mr. McGuire did not sound so encouraging when he said that he was afraid a victory in the coming election campaign could hardly be expected. The capitalists had taken good care that the working class would not have the time and opportunity to agitate and fight for their rights. The speaker then attacked the plat form of the Republican party and declared that it would be a blessing for the people if both parties would die out. He advocated the founding of a new party "by the people and for the people". In conclusion he brought the audience the good tidings that the Greenback party would admit forty-four delegates of the Socialist party to the convention, but he was afraid that nothing much could be done there for the party. After offering a few disquieting phrases, the speaker <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0949.jpg" n="3"/>yielded his place to Dr. Adolf Douai of New York.</p>
   <p>This speaker did not face even half of the original audience, since the chairman had announced that a collection would be taken up to cover the expenses. The speaker, who talked half in German and half in English, referred to the election campaign twenty years ago when Abraham Lincoln was elected and the slavery problem first presented itself. He remarked that even at that time a certain statesman (Seward) had said in Congress that the ruling classes would be much better off if they would hire human labor instead of buying it. The slaves were freed allright, but the workers had remained slaves just the same; they were exploited and enslaved and had to do the bidding of the "bosses," just as the darkies had to obey their masters during the time of slavery. Now as then an upheaval--he would not call it a Civil War--had to take place as soon as possible, which, he pointed out, is the purpose and aim of the Socialist Workers' party.</p>
   <p>When Douai had repeated this speech in English,most of the audience left, and, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0950.jpg" n="4"/>since Kearney had not shown up yet and no other speakers were present, the meeting adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
