<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-05-24">May 24, 1878</date><title level="a">Attention!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1085</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1085.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-05-24">May 24, 1878</date><title level="a">ATTENTION!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some English-American newspapers have been printing lately sensational news about the growing unrest of Chicago labor elements, about secret meetings of labor leaders, and even about armed workers' units. Some papers are making it still stronger and are reporting regular, military practice of these units.</p>
   <p>We dare to say that we are pretty well informed about the present attitude of labor groups, communistic and socialistic, and know positively that none of these groups is contemplating any armed rebellion or insurrection. This does not exclude the fact that our police department stirred up by reactionary circles, is pretty well on the alert and is keeping a steady watch on our west side labor settlements, day and night.</p>
   <p>Otherwise, we are inclined to believe that strong political forces have been at work for quite a while, to pass through the State legislature new amendments which would eliminate more of our individual rights in regard to freedom of speech, assembly, rights etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1086.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At this time we consider it our duty to warn all labor organizations to keep their heads cool and not to fall for any firebrand speaker's scheme of an armed attack on our administration or government. The attempt would be a failure in its very beginning, as the masses of the nation are not enlightened enough to stand back of any revolutionary movement. Progress of mental evolution is taking its time, but gradually will prepare the human mind of all classes in the country to fight successfully for its rights and its place in the sun.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
