<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-19">Oct. 19, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">German-American Democratic Organization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1166</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1166.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-19">Oct. 19, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN DEMOCRATIC ORGANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Tuesday, there was a meeting of members in parlor K of the Bismarck Hotel, preceded by a conference of the executive committee at the headquarters of the organization. Many of the invited speakers and, of course, the candidates for the next elections, were not present, as they were busy campaigning in the county.</p>
   <p>Interesting indeed was Judge Hartigan's speech, indicating that he is well able to follow proceedings in the German language.</p>
   <p>In the business part of the meeting, some of the members emphasized the need of recommending the constituents that they vote the straight ticket, in order to avoid unnecessary scattering of votes.</p>
   <p>The most far-reaching resolution, however, was the one to have a mass meeting at the Lincoln Turner Hall on October 30th. A committee was nominated, and <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1167.jpg" n="2"/>the ladies and gentlemen present were instructed to prepare this mass meeting, to spread propaganda, to get speakers (largely, of course, German candidates), and, if at all possible, to take care of the guests with gay and moist entertainment.</p>
   <p>A number of ladies' organizations of many years' standing joined the German-American Democratic Organization at the meeting. Also the remaining men Democrats, who used to function here before, were likewise represented, and thus the last bridge to unification of all German Democrats was crossed. Unanimity, not to speak of universal enthusiasm, surcharged the whole meeting. Herr Carl Witt took over the post of recording secretary, and Herr Lorenz Schlegel took over the duties of co-organizer, which office he has actually been fulfilling.</p>
   <p>The committee for the mass meeting, on Wednesday at headquarters, was represented by eight men and four women. Entertainment will be provided by male and female choruses, and good orators will speak. Proper press releases have been given by headquarters to the local German papers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1168.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Abendpost will keep its readers informed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
