<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-23">Feb. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">More Than 400 Voters from the 5Th Ward for Hesing.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1462</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1462.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-23">Feb. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">MORE THAN 400 VOTERS FROM THE 5TH WARD FOR HESING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A sizable crowd of more than 400, of diverse national elements, Germans, Irish and Bohemians, all of them Democratic and Independent voters of the 5th Ward, - came to Liberty Hall at Union Ave. and 30th St. yesterday evening, to show their colors and assure Hesing of their support in the coming primary. Among the well-known citizens from that ward we noted: M. McCann, Senator Thiele....and 29 others.</p>
   <p>Mr. McCann, who was elected chairman, emphasized the necessity of concerted action of all genuine Democrats in the ward, to prove to Harrison's supporters, who already think they have the delegates "in the bag," <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1463.jpg" n="2"/>that there is many a slip t'wixt the cup and the lip!</p>
   <p>Mr. J. C. Richberg was the next speaker. Evidently his words made a profound and lasting impression, as he was repeatedly interrupted with prolonged applause. He gave a general outline of Carter H. Harrison's political past and dug up irrefutable evidence to show, that he does not deserve the support of the Democratic party. He then spoke about Hesing. His enthusiasm soon manifested itself and he pictured him as a man in whom all voters have the greatest confidence, regardless of their nationalistic origin. Mr. Hesing, when nominated, will be able to gather all the Democratic factions, while Harrison does not have that drawing power. If Hesing is elected, he will provide a model city administration.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1464.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. August Mette asked the assembly to select only delegates who actually share the sentiment of the voters within the 5th Ward; the conniving "ticket fixers" and their manipulations must be eliminated.</p>
   <p>Senator Thiele also made a very fiery speech; he asserted with great confidence, that the 5,000 Democrats of the 5th Ward will show once and for all, that they have no further use for a continued dictatorship by a few professional politicians. No citizen should fail to register his vote for the Hesing delegates next Monday. Messrs. John Schaefer and Thomas Cavanaugh expressed similar views. Mr. Washington Hesing's candidacy was endorsed amidst great enthusiasm. It may be safely predicted, that the 5th Ward will send a large number of Hesing delegates to the convention. The Hesing sentiment makes rapid progress in all sections.</p>
   <p>(More or less detailed news from many wards appear in the remainder of the article which cowers three columns. All districts listed favor Hesing's mayoral candidacy. Transl.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
