<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-04-15">Apr. 15, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">German Republicans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1617</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1617.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-04-15">Apr. 15, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN REPUBLICANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A number of German Republicans held a meeting last evening at No. 311 Larrabee street for the purpose of forming a German-American Republican Club of the Sixteenth Ward. Mr. George Vocke called the meeting to order, and stated that, owing to the preponderance of the German element in the ward, it would be desirable to form a ward club, at which the proceedings would be in German, because most of the Germans in the ward did not understand the English language, which was used exclusively at the general club. He thought this club should be auxiliary to the main one. Mr. John Van Danden was elected Chairman. Louis Nelke made a long oration advocating the establishment of an independent German club, one that would have nothing to do with the main club. Most of the citezens in the ward were Germans, and they should therefore have the leading club that could dictate the candidates. Mr. Hilderbrecht opposed Mr. Nelke's view, and thought if such action were taken it would only alienate the Americans, and split up the Republican vote in the ward still more than it was now. He could see no reason for forming an independent organization. If the Germans were really as strong as was claimed, they could just as well ren the main club.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1618.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Henry Spiel, John Hettinger, and a number of others made orations on the subject. It was finally decided to form a German Republican Auxilliary Club of the Sixteenth Ward.---</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
