<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-05-30">May 30, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">My Grandmother.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Mailed in)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1689</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1689.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-05-30">May 30, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">MY GRANDMOTHER.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Mailed in)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republican State Convention, while dealing out nominations, has allotted one to Cook county, that of vice-governor. In order that no one may believe the convention to be inimical to Cook County, it has given the nomination to a man who is a representative of all the political and religious aberrations, that are repulsive to a great city.</p>
   <p>Mr. Andrew Shuman is the nominee, he who as editor of the Evening Journal has raped the English language and has been a willing tool of the hypocrites and Know-Nothings. Mr. Andrew Shuman is one of the persons most repulsive to the Germans; so much more so because his name has a German appearance. But Mr. Shuman would have resented it very much had some doubted his pure blooded Yankee origin and said that in his veins was flowing the "mala sangre" of the beer loving "Dutchmen".</p>
   <p>Now of course everything is different. Mr. Andrew Shuman is a candidate and the "Dutch" votes are not to be despised. When Mr. Shuman met a German <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1690.jpg" n="2"/>journalist, he expressed his surprise to him, that an influential German should have called him a puritan and a Know-Nothing.</p>
   <p>"Why", he added triumpantly, "how could I be a puritan and Know-Nothing, since my grandparents were born in Bremen, Germany!" Thus, Mr. Andrew Shuman wants to become vice-governor through his grandmother's birth certificate. No, Mr. Shuman, not if the Germans can prevent it. We could have forgiven the Yankee Shuman his crazy "notions" but not the German Andreas Schumann.</p>
   <p>No paper has insulted the Germans more consistently than the Evening Journal under the direction of Andrew Shuman, whose grandparents were Germans. His grandmother's birth certificate will be of little use to Andrew Shuman, the hypocrite and the Know-Nothing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
