<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-05-07">May 7, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Turners Offer to Aid Ten Thousand Germans and 3,000 Bohemians Ready for Strike Duty.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0203</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0203.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4) (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-05-07">May 7, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">TURNERS OFFER TO AID TEN THOUSAND GERMANS AND 3,000 BOHEMIANS READY FOR STRIKE DUTY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten thousand members of German Turner societies have offered their services to Mayor Dunne for the purpose of maintaining order in the streets while the strike continues. The offer was made yesterday by Emil Hoechster, a leading Turner and a deputy sheriff. With him was Charles J. Vopicka, who tendered the services of 3,000 Bohemian Turners for the same character of service.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hoechster told the mayor that the Turners are men who could do effective work in preserving the peace. He declared that they are well trained and in excellent physical condition, and he offered to organize 1,000 of them at once if the mayor requested it. Mr. Vopicka also offered to organize 1,000 men at once among the Bohemians. Mayor Dunne thanked both of the representatives and said he would avail himself of their offer should the necessity arise.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0204.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"That is a good offer," the mayor said. "It does me good to receive news like that. It certainly shows that Chicago is in a position to furnish all the protection that its citizens need and that order can be preserved without troops. With our citizens volunteering to help we need outside assistance. I do not expect that I shall be obliged to call upon the Turners, but should it become necessary I am glad to be able to do so."</p>
   <p>Out of 100 employes of the city water pipe extension division who were called out by Mayor Dunne yesterday only thirty-eight were found available by Chief of Police O'Neill. Nearly all of the men were below the height needed, under weight, or could not speak the English language and were therefore not available.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0205.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Assistant Chief Schuettler declared yesterday that apparently the days of violence in the strike are over.</p>
   <p>"Everything is quiet, " he said. "Every demand for help asked by the employers is being met and every wagon is properly guarded. There are 1,200 wagons moving today under police protection. The most trouble we must look for is in the outlying districts, and it is here where the wagons will be the most heavily guarded."</p>
   <p>For harboring strike rioters and defying the police John Doornech was forced to close his saloon at 421 Twenty-sixth street yesterday upon the order of Chief O'Neill. Complaints have been made that Doornech's saloon, which is opposite of the barns of the Peabody Coal Company on Twenty-sixth st., <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0206.jpg" n="4"/>has been the resort of strike disturbers and their refuge when scattered by the police. The trouble makers are said to have gathered in front of the saloon and whenever the opportunity came they would foment riot. Upon the appearance of the police, however, the complaints declare that they would flee for protection to the saloon and Doornech would defy the police to follow them and make arrests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
