<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-10-06">Oct. 6, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">Ratification.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0746</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0746.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-10-06">Oct. 6, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">RATIFICATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A highly animated meeting of the United Labor Party was held at the Vorwarts Turner hall. T. J. Morgan the elected President made a short address saying, that in his opinion, the meeting was of much more importance than any of the past few years. The observation that labor had arrived at a point where it abandoned the old political parties and showed those parasites that it decided not to be dictated to but that it exercised its own constitutional liberty at the polling places, was a most gratifying act to me.</p>
   <p>Secretary Long then informed the meeting of the results of the convention held at Greenebaum's Hall and of the accepted platform and read the names of the nominated candidates. With a unanimous vote this meeting too accepted the platform and the candidates which were the choice of the convention. Mr. Georg Rohrbach, candidate for senator from the 11th district, was then introduced. He expressed thanks for the faith put in him, and promised to serve his fellow citizens to the best of his knowledge. Then Mr. Altpeter, the candidate for the county commissar's office stepped on the platform and was greeted with tumultuous applause. He said that he was regarded by the mail, a one penny newspaper, as the person responsible for the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0747.jpg" n="2"/>Haymarket riots. But, he said, neither he nor the Socialists were responsible for that tragedy, but the press which nursed the corruption and which described it in beautiful language. The ill doings of the capitalists and the monopolies was responsible for this outburst of human rage. He related, in a humorous way, the conditions which were prevalent in the city and county administrations as found by him and his three Scoialist colleagues when elected members to the city administration. He said, he told those people who had robbed the city treasury that if that was the high type of representatives of the parties preaching "law and order", then we would take a chance with Socialism. The never ending applause at the end of his speech forced the old veteran to re-appear and then warned the workingmen to be on their watch and nominate people for candidates who could look at a $5.00 bill with out getting excited by it. The next speaker Frank Stauber said: "When I was first elected to the city administration, astonished wealthy women looked at me from their palace windows as if they were eager to ask me, whether I was the newly elected Socialist Alderman. They must have expected to see a monster, at least. That which I and my colleagues had to say then was bitter and not easy to take, but we are almost in the same position today. As most of you know, I am not gifted with oratory talent, but I promise to do the best in my power to serve you."</p>
   <p>Following was a short address made by Charles E. Scib, the candidate for Senator. He spoke of the demands which the United Labor Party's platform contains.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
