<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title><date when="1888-04-27">April 27, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Lecture by Turner Moehle about Protective Tariffs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0700</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0700.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title><date when="1888-04-27">April 27, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">LECTURE BY TURNER MOEHLE ABOUT PROTECTIVE TARIFFS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The introduction of protective tariffs had a beneficial effect in the beginning. While industry developed originally with the help of the protective tariff and the working class had a decent standard of living there came a change by and by to the disadvantage of the public in general and to the working class in particular. So great was this change that this rich country does not seem to be able to feed sixty million people while it certainly has enough resources to provide for 1000 million comfortably.</p>
   <p>Under cover of the protective tariff there came into existence the cliques, corporations, trusts, monopolies, etc. From the standpoint of the working class the protective tariff is proferable to free trade as our wages are higher than in any other country. (?)</p>
   <p>Again from the viewpoint of humanity: to lessen the misery of mankind the protective tariff should become abolished and free trade established.</p>
   <p>The latter would help to decide the present struggle in the social province quicker <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0701.jpg" n="2"/>than any rules in the political field.</p>
   <p>While the higher wages of the American workingman would come down to the level of the European laborer he has to come to the conclusion that only a common front will enable the revolution to come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
