<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-07-12">July 12, 1935</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0118.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-07-12">July 12, 1935</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>to work. It is evident that this evil cannot be removed by laws nor will the Guffey Bill bring about a change in the situation. Nevertheless, the administration is demanding that Congress pass the Bill immediately. The fact, then, is really that the miners' union is threatening to call a general strike, in order to force the passage of the Bill.</p>
   <p>The situation is extremely precarious. If Congress can be forced by a strike threat, to pass certain legislation, then that honorable body has forfeited the right to its existence, and should confer the duty and authority of enacting laws upon the union officials. The Guffey Bill contains several provisions that are probably unconstitutional. Even the Attorney General of the United States thinks so. Despite these facts the President wants it enacted.</p>
   <p>His motives deserve credit, he wants to prevent the outbreak of a strike; but his method is questionable, to say the least. The President wrote the chairman of the Ways and Means Committee as follows:" I hope your <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0119.jpg" n="3"/>Committee will not be persuaded to vote against acceptance of this bill by objections with reference to its constitutionality, no matter how well such objections appear to be founded." That advice is good. If Congress has reasons to doubt the constitutionality of the Bill, it should not accept it before thoroughly revising it.</p>
   <p>The situation seems to be much more serious when one considers that the administration could invoke the Wagner Act to prevent the strike, since that law was passed just for that purpose. It has been passed by Congress and signed by the President. It is already in force, and there is absolutely no reason why the Government could not avert the strike through the work of a board of arbitration, as provided for in the Wagner law. There is good reason to suspect that the union is demanding that the Guffey Bill be made law because it gives their organization a wide control over the industry, and that the President has acceded to this demand. That was much too high a price to pay for having the strike postponed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
