<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-05-25">May 25, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">The Disagreeable Strangers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0726</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0726.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-05-25">May 25, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">THE DISAGREEABLE STRANGERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The prophecy of our German American newspapers ever since the beginning of the horrible communistic activities, is unfailingly coming to pass. The American people stand against and oppose the boundless immigration from Europe. By this they do not mean the immigration in general, but they object to the disagreeable, "offensive foreignism," as the Chicago Times calls it, and it goes on to explain clearly enough, what it really means, by these words: "To put into practice the criminal doctrine of the 'red flag' by Germans, Czechs, Poles, or any stranger to our shores, is offensive foreignism.</p>
   <p>"The misuse of our nationality and our flag for the furthering of the everlasting Irish row against England, is offensive foreignism.</p>
   <p>"Battling against our public school system by any of the Italian societies, is offensive foreignism.</p>
   <p>"The piratical expedition of European idlers, who think of the American political life as a business well worth while, is also offensive foreignism.</p>
   <p>"The humble devotion of our demagogues for all sorts of rascals and vagabonds, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0727.jpg" n="2"/>who for the sake of their votes, become a drain on public funds, is also offensive foreignism.</p>
   <p>"The revolting public opinion against offensive foreignism, is by no means limited to native Americans, moreover, every honest and respectable citizen of foreign extraction shares the same."</p>
   <p>This, from the Chicago Times, and we do not feel justified in replying to it in an abusive language, or in lamenting over the "disgraceful know-nothing ness," for what the Chicago Times said about the pernicious practices of a large number of immigrants during the last decade, is nothing but the truth. with the one exception, that to this class belong less than fifty percent, and it may be even less than twenty-five percent; which is still much too high. It is unnecessary for the United States to provide a milling place for the rubbish of the overly populated countries of Europe. Honest and respectable immigrants, not afraid to work, wishing to become American citizens in good faith, are always welcome; but revolutionary inclined scoundrels are certainly not.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0728.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That satan, Most, released from prison several weeks ago, is going from city to city in the East delivering his inflammatory speeches of arson and murder. Today, he will undoubtedly praise the day when "seven of the beasts of order were sent to hell" (his own words) and lament the fact, that those "noble and high-minded citizens" (candidates for the gallows) sit in prison. Too bad, that this rascal has not the courage to visit Chicago, too........ It is to be condemned that the authorities in the East don't put a stop to that vagabond's activities, especially in New York with its laws against offences of this type. Let him come to Chicago, where we would not lose anytime to deal with him as his deeds would prompt us to do; our police have not forgotten May 4, 1886 and will not for years to come. The execution of the death sentence upon the guilty persons has not taken place yet, and much doubt is expressed if it ever will........It is to be regretted that coward Most avoids coming to Chicago........and if he should try to, his comrades would not permit him to do so, for a speech similar to the one delivered at Hartford or Philadelphia would mean certain death for the condemned men.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0729.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But, on the anniversary of this abominable crime we warn our city administration to curb the anarchistic movement and render a repetition of such horrid crime impossible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
