<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-08-13">Aug. 13, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Capital, Labor and the Press</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0682</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0682.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-08-13">Aug. 13, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">CAPITAL, LABOR AND THE PRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In that bitter fight which is being waged among the capitalistic newspapers and which has to be waged to remain in that cesspool of today's degeneracy, we are certainly in the lead in this country in comparison with the rest of the world.</p>
   <p>There is no other country in existence where the press relies on such common ways and means as here, where it is up to the neck in the mud of capitalistic degeneracy.</p>
   <p>The one who does not belong to the clique or party is slandered and libeled no matter if he be the best and noblest man in the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0683.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In an even greater degree the newspapers do this to their competitors. No matter what one newspaper writes, the other will contradict the article if it does fit in with their ideas.</p>
   <p>There is a stirring up and lying, a slandering and intriguing to a degree that testifies to the unheard of corruption of our present conditions.</p>
   <p>For some time there existed hot competition among three local newspapers which ended finally in a warfare that puts everything in this line up to now in the shadow.</p>
   <p>The Daily News reduced the wages of its carriers 50 per cent and as a result some of them have naturally gone on strike which has induced the News to assume that these carrier's were bought by the Inter Ocean and Times for the purpose of doing damage to the News' business.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0684.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Although we have as much sympathy for these two papers as we have for the News, namely none, it seems to be clear enough that nobody has to be induced to strike through bribery when his salary is reduced to half.</p>
   <p>We therefore declare the statement of the Daily News to be a lie by means of which this paper wants to inflict losses on the competitive newspapers as well as on the striking carriers.</p>
   <p>To do this in a most efficient manner, this aristocratic paper printed and sent out 170,000 circulars, full of meanness against the carriers. These circulars are being mailed to all persons whose names appear in the address book and contain franked postal cards with an order blank for the News. We hope that there are not too many who will be fooled.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0685.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The American Reporter System stands unique in the whole world as far as organized meanness and vulgarity is concerned.</p>
   <p>If the person who is to be interviewed refuses categorically to answer any questions the reporter manufactures an interview himself which he must reenforce with swindle lies and big words in order to keep his job.</p>
   <p>There is only one choice for the interviewed: either he keeps quiet and allows the reporter to lie the blue off the sky, or he talks and has to tolerate that besides what he said a lot more will be added.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
