<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-04-06">April 6, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Victory of the Staats - Zeitung All Along the Line</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1533</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1533.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-04-06">April 6, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">VICTORY OF THE STAATS - ZEITUNG ALL ALONG THE LINE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The spring election resulted in an abundance of surprises. The new Australian election system has triumphantly stood the test for the second time. It proved itself to be what it was claimed to be. The citizens of Chicago were granted for the first time, the opportunity to vote according to their own convictions without being influenced by politicians, terrorists, and others.</p>
   <p>The result is that the better candidates won and that the election was a satisfactory one. The thirty-four alderman who were elected yesterday are, with few exceptions, men of honor and we may expect that the next City Council will protect the interests of the people. The election was a victory for the independent thinking citizens who, declined to be dominated by "partyism" and therefore voted for the best candidates.</p>
   <p>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung is likewise satisfied with the election results. We are principally happy over the election of our friend, E. Hoechster, and his young and brave comrade, H. Bartling. This victory with a considerable majority <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1534.jpg" n="2"/>of votes is a certain compensation for Hoechster in view of the fact that he was very viciously attacked by certain people. The only Republican who was able to rescue himself from the shipwreck was the German-American, Peter Laas. In Westtown the strength and influence of the Germans was even more outstanding. Here it was possible to elect the Republican, A. Wulf, a German, who was heartily supported by us, with a majority of nearly five thousand votes, and also the German Democrat, F. Niehoff, was elected with a majority vote of six thousand. The Staats - Zeitung recommended both candidates, and is indeed happy that the results are so favorable to its friends. However, we apprehend that the Democrats of West and Southtown will again blame the Germans for voting only for their own countrymen.</p>
   <p>For their consideration we point to the tactics of the administration and assert that these caused such results. Because as soon as the Germans realized that the Republicans were determinded to elect Dwyer regardless of what reprehensible methods they had to use, the friends of Wulf and Niehott became aroused and the overwhelming majority of votes was the brilliant result. Germans were also victorious at the local election of Lake, where both elected Democrats, Kotzenberg and O. Mueller, are our friends.</p>
   <p>Alderman Cullerton was defeated. He was a leader in the City Council for twenty-one <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1535.jpg" n="3"/>years. The Staats - Zeitung did not participate in the battle against him, although we were well acquainted with his merits and demerits. We are convinced that the citizens of the ninth Ward will know what is to their advantage. We hope that F. Rhode will prove himself worthy of his German name. The confidence extended to him by such a majority of votes must be a source of pride and satisfaction to him.</p>
   <p>More Germans than ever before will be members of the City Council. There will be twenty-one of them. The City Council will remain predominantly Democratic. Of the thirty-four aldermen remaining in office, twenty-one are Democrats and of the newly elected, there are fifteen Democrats; therefore, the City Council will consist of thirty-six Democrats and twenty-eight Republicans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
