<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-06">Feb. 6, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Change in Forms of Government</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-06">Feb. 6, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHANGE IN FORMS OF GOVERNMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anyone who has closely followed political events in foreign countries, as well as in America, will know that they are rooted in the economic conditions that developed during the course of the last half century, especially since the World War. Economic contrasts released the driving powers that finally led to the war of nations. The so-called peace pacts which were made after the close of the World War are proof of this, although they also testify to the incredible stupidity of those persons who believed that they could gain an advantage for their own business by eliminating their opponents from commercial competition, and by backing the country of their opponents into small, dependent areas. The subsequent years have proved that this conclusion was a fallacy; but even the complete collapse of world commerce, which resulted from this insane policy, apparently could not set the stubborn statesmen right--at least not all of them. Some of them, indeed, have learned that the commercial <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0466.jpg" n="2"/>nations are only one great family, and that if one of them incurs economic losses the others are also adversely affected. Still, all attempts to aid world commerce have shown little good result, because the nations were too selfish and could not agree upon a uniform policy.</p>
   <p>The Inability of statesmen to come to an understanding on questions of business has evidently grieved the nations very deeply. Of course, much time had elapsed before they recognized cause and effect, more time had elapsed before men arose who thought they knew of ways and means to dispel the gloom of the peoples, and still more time had elapsed before the nations gave these statesmen the opportunity to show what they could do. The men who came into power in this way varied greatly in regard to ability and energy. The Hungarian Regent differs in many respects from Pilsudski, the Dictator of Poland, and Alexander of Serbia is very inferior to Hitler, while Dollfuss is no match for Mussolini. All these dictators have but one thing in common: the conviction that parliaments have outlived their usefulness and have become only nuisance. This knowledge has convinced Hitler and Mussolini that the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0467.jpg" n="3"/>democratic form of government must be supplanted by another kind of government. Dollfuss is timidly following Hitler, Pilsudski and the other autocratic leaders in eastern and southern Europe would also like to fall in line, but they do not think they have sufficient power to bring about a thorough change of government. Pilsudski, it is true, has often reprimanded the Polish Parliament so severely that not even a hungry dog would have accepted a piece of bread from its members, yet he was not able to abolish it. Hitler and Mussolini are two political reformers who used, and are still using, the most radical means of completely altering their countries' form of government; for they have not yet finished their work, although the Italian is a few steps ahead of the German, because the former began his reformation a few years before the latter came into power.</p>
   <p>There can be no doubt that such revolutions also influence other nations. Any historian knows that the American Revolution, and the French Revolution which took place a few years later, had a great influence upon the development of <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0468.jpg" n="4"/>governmental systems in other countries. The same will be true of the two revolutions that are now in process in Europe. The world is subject to constant change, and the opinions of people are also under constant change. And it is an historical fact that no form of government is permanent, no matter how people may regard it. They pass through a regular cycle, one system succeeding another as soon as the former system ceases to function. And thus matters go on until the cycle is closed, and it is again the turn of the first system, which may stand the test for some time under changed conditions. Democracies, dictatorships, monarchies, despotisms, aristocracies, etc. are nothing new. As a rule there will be strong opposition to revolution. If the opposition is victorious, it is evident that the time for a change is not ripe. If the revolution is successful it is an indication that the people were tired of the old system and are willing to try another. The events in Europe must give much food for thought to every American who observes them closely.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
