<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-25">Mar. 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">What Kind of Pro-Germans Are These?</title><title level="a" type="sub">Thompson and his Campaign Manager Pugh Support British</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1315</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1315.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-25">Mar. 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT KIND OF PRO-GERMANS ARE THESE?</title><title level="a" type="sub">Thompson and his Campaign Manager Pugh Support British</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Pro-German here in Chicago when it comes to catch German votes, but otherwise tooth and nail for the British, seems to be the slogan of Republican candidate for mayor William Hale Thompson and his campaign manager James Pugh. They are doing their best right now to create good will among the German element, and for this purpose they had a button made with the inscription "Our Wilhelm for Mayor." But at the beginning of the war they did not care for the German element and their problems, as was stated yesterday at the headquarters of the Democratic candidate for mayor. Then they were one hundred per cent for the British and did not make any bones about it. Quite likely the importance of the German element in Chicago had not dawned upon them yet. To demonstrate their enthusiasm for England and her noble cause, they offered the British Government Mr. Pugh's motorboat Disturber IV, which had cost $50,000 and was said to be unusually speedy. The boat was to be used for reconnaissance trips. Besides that, they had offered the British naval reserves two thousand <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1316.jpg" n="2"/>gallons of the best quality gasoline and two barrels of high grade lubricating oil.</p>
   <p>The daily papers of Sept. 13 of last year reported this news but nobody paid any attention to it during those turbulent days. According to a report in a local English newspaper of the same date, James Pugh had been a guest in London of the well-known English yacht owner Sir Thomas Lipton, to whom he had offered his vessel Disturber IV in writing. Lipton was highly pleased and thanked Pugh for the gift; the latter was busy the next day talking with representatives of the British Government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
