<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-26">Mar. 26, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">To the German Voters of Town-Lake.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1453</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1453.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-26">Mar. 26, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE GERMAN VOTERS OF TOWN-LAKE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The nominations have been made, and a critical investigation of the candidates is undoubtedly in order. First of all, we shall give our attention to the assessor, whose duty it is to assess our property. We must pay our taxes according to his estimate and, although the Germans pay their taxes willingly, yet they demand that the assessments be fair.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it is the duty of each citizen to vote for such a candidate only who has proven in the past that he is a real man, and is well informed about conditions in Town Lake. Who are the candidates?</p>
   <p>There is Michael Mac Inerney, on the one hand, elected last fall to the state legislature chiefly by German votes. At that time he promised not to forget his German friends after the election. And how did he keep his word? Although the German is not a political job-hunter, he appreciates it, nevertheless, if one of his countrymen is called to a position of trust. Mac-Inerney not only failed to keep his promise, but he also deliberately prevented the nomination of Germans. For this reason he can not be recommended to the German voters.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1454.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On the other hand, German fellow-citizens, is a real German, who has lived in Town Lake for the last twenty-five years, and knows the needs and desires of its citizens. It should not be difficult for you to decide in favor of him, inasmuch as party affiliations are no factor in this election. This man is Conrad W. Walther; he is a self-made man in every respect. We have known him for many years, and do not hesitate to assure our fellow countrymen that he is not seeking his election for the sake of money, but that he desires to serve his countrymen and the citizens of Town Lake. He strives to become a worthy successor of Mr. Kotzenberg.</p>
   <p>German citizens, vote for our countryman, C. W. Walther! We are convinced that if elected, he will deserve the respect of the Germans, through his just assessments.</p>
   <p>German Citizens of Town Lake.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
