<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-25">June 25, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">In the Cause of Liberty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0997</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0997.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-25">June 25, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE CAUSE OF LIBERTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the September 15th speech of our Chicago, Dennis Kearney (Dr. E. Schmidt), published by us a few days ago, it was said to the armed communists:</p>
   <p>"Be persistent in your efforts and in organizational work, because some day, when exploitation becomes too unbearable, you may have to use your arms in the defence of liberty".</p>
   <p>And elsewhere:</p>
   <p>"You selected red as your color....and, if ever an attempt will be made in this country to rob you of your liberty, think of your duty, which consists in defending freedom".</p>
   <p>Just what the new Dennis Kearney thought of, when he made those blood-curdling remarks, even he may not be able to explain. Perhaps they were tangled phrases <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0998.jpg" n="2"/>of the French Revolution or the Revolution of 1848, which he saw during his "teen" age. What his audience thought of depended on the personal attitude of those present. For most of them the words meant neither more nor less than an outbreak of a long-suppressed fury, a violence which has neither direction nor distinction, and which may be summed up thus: "Hit 'em!".....</p>
   <p>"O Liberty! What things are done in thy name!" Thus sighed a brave defender of freedom when she became a victim of French tyranny and went to her execution. To that, one may add: "And what stupidity!" Particularly when one considers the nonsense which certain reformers wish to associate with the word liberty.</p>
   <p>Liberty in itself is but a negation: In the sense of absense of restriction it is practiced by ferocious animals. Human liberty does not mean that anyone may do whatever he chooses, but it signifies that a person may so conduct himself that whatever he does shall not come into conflict with the rights of other persons who, as a whole, represent society, of which each individual is a part. In <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0999.jpg" n="3"/>this sense, our national institutions and laws have been designed to protect liberty in the United States.</p>
   <p>But, obviously, Dennis Kearney I and Dennis Kearney II do not have that conception of liberty. According to their idea, liberty means that all workers who do not work on a piecework basis shall rule all other people. Communistic liberty consists of permitting all people to do what the communists want. And thus, according to their conception of liberty, it is quite proper for every worker to belong to a trade union, while those who do not belong to it may not work. The worker is "free" provided he obeys the orders of the union; if he does not comply, he then faces threats, or even violence, which disables him. In connection with that, one need only think of that infamous horde, the "Mollies" of Pennsylvania, whose crimes the communists justify on the ground that they were committed in the name of liberty.</p>
   <p>And how the communists regard liberty in Chicago can readily be explained by hundreds and thousands of our shopkeepers who were threatened with boycott if <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1000.jpg" n="4"/>they did not subscribe to the communist paper, or if they failed to vote for communistic candidates. Probably, with the exception only of the slaveholders in the South, no group in the United States has ever wielded such power over its adversaries as the communists of Chicago. Through more or less concealed threats, the communists bull dose people to become subscribers to the communist paper, and the same method is used to obtain votes for communistic candidates. To continue this procedure without restraint is the communists understanding of liberty. In the cause of liberty, which means the right to ignore the laws and freedom of others, they shall bear arms, according to Dr. "Dennis K. Schmidt," their mayoral candidate. And if the power to control workers who labor on a piecework basis is threatened, then the communists shall rally under the "banner of blood" and fight for liberty.</p>
   <p>Now, it is only a question whether the Star-Spangled Banner which represents liberty for all, shall or shall not give way to the red flag of the workers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
