<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-11-05">Nov. 5, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">The Witoh-Pot</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0663</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0663.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-11-05">Nov. 5, 1888</date>.
<title level="a"> THE WITOH-POT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The big parades of the old parties were staged with a tremendous noise last Saturday. It was a genuine Halloween spectacle. And by such crude, infantile nonsense the seriousness and importance of a national election is demonstrated!</p>
   <p>The so-called "cat's music" in use at the end of the last century in France and Germany against persons not in favor, embodied the same character as the American election demonstrations of the slave-driver parties of today.</p>
   <p>We cannot discover in that anything impressive, dignified, serious; everything is an obscenity.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0664.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And when we look at the masses, joining this swindle, and their craziness about this adolescent noise - then we involuntarily hold our heads and stop to think whether they all have gone crazy.</p>
   <p>Was there a cloud-burst of insanity which smoke-screened the mentality of thousands and thousands and made temporary lunatics out of them?</p>
   <p>This impishness with children's trumpets, cow-bells, whistles and snares, the thousand-voiced howling, crying and hollering, with the beating of drums by half grown young men and the march-music of badly arranged bands creates a noise that could make you lose your hearing.</p>
   <p>A horde of wild barbarians dancing its war on victory - dances to an accompaniment of incredible noise, will remain far behind this spectacle of American upholders of culture when they are organized for election parades.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0665.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Free citizens of the freest republic take the liberty to make fools out of themselves.</p>
   <p>Parties, depending on such means to demonstrate their "good cause" have no intrinsic value. In this great mardi gras of both old parties, a number of prominent citizens and business men participated although usually the fun of noisy street-parades is reserved for immature half-grown youths.</p>
   <p>It was noticeable that to many prominents, the duty of marching, was no pleasure. One thing the workers should learn from these parades of the slave-drivers. They should realize that they must be politically organized according to their professions. The slave-drivers too let their wage-slaves march in professional-political order.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0666.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This is the only correct method and should be kept in memory by non-political unions in order to abandon their fruitless tactics. Professionally unionized, they must stand opposed to capital, but with the full conscience of their class-position they must become active politically as closed workers' battalions in order to set aside the old form of society and achieve their economic and political independence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
