<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1891-09-02">Sept. 2, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Cabinetmakers on Strike</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0219</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <!--                    
                        <catRef target="#grp-scandinavian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    -->
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0219.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4) (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4) (Polish)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4) (Scandinavian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1891-09-02">Sept. 2, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">CABINETMAKERS ON STRIKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The organized cabinetmakers went on strike yesterday, fighting for higher wages and an 8 hour working day. According to statements of the cabinetmakers, the wages have been materially lowered during recent times, so that even the skilful and efficient workers hardly make ends meet. At certain shops the wages are supposed to have been reduced from 20 cents per hour to 7 cents and even less, and in some cases work was not available at all.</p>
   <p>To remedy this situation, the cabinetmakers called a mass-meeting yesterday at Zepf's Hall, Corner Lake and DesPlaines. At almost all the larger factories the employers had been already informed in regard to the conditions demanded, therefore the workers were ready to act, and they unanimously resolved to strike.</p>
   <p>The strikers demand an 8 hour working day, elimination of piece-work and a minimum wage of not less than 25 cents per hour. Assertions are being made, however, that an agreement about the minimum wage rate does not exist. Wages differ at the various factories and depend upon conditions and demands for workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0220.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A meeting took place last night at Greif's Hall, with large numbers of strikers present. The attitude of the owners of different shops in regard to the strikers demands was reported, and the news that some of the employers had declared their willingness to meet their demands, was received with a shout of joy.</p>
   <p>It is not, however, definitely agreed by these employers that they will pay the minimum rate of 25 cents, but they will accept a certain minimum rate, whatever the agreement will call for. The Strike Committee is holding a special meeting this morning, in which consultations will be held about the negotiations with the manufacturers. The members of the committee were rather silent about their activities so far.</p>
   <p>The cabinetmakers are organized into five unions; The German, Bohemian, Polish, Scandinavian, and the English, and have approximately 1400 members.</p>
   <p>The manufacturers have different opinions about this strike. The manufacture of furniture is one of the outstanding industries of Chicago, and it is obvious that a long strike of the skilled workers would cause an inestimable loss to them.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0221.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Furniture is sent from Chicago to all parts of the country, and at this time many orders are on hand. We do not know whether this situation has induced some of the employers to meet the demand of the strikers, or whether they consider them as just. Some of the largest manufacturers assert that it is impossible for them to pay the minimum rate and that it is unjust, to pay all workers the same wages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
