<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1933-07-16">July 16, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Government by Selected Leaders</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1933-07-16">July 16, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">GOVERNMENT BY SELECTED LEADERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When Adolf Hitler abolished the Reichstag in Germany and decided that the people should be ruled, not by parliament, but by leaders selected by himself, the world, including America, shook its head disapprovingly and talked about reaction. The same was said at the time when Mussolini established his dictatorship in Italy. In the beginning Mussolini, too, adopted stern measures and did not treat his adherents with kid gloves. But after he was firmly established in the saddle and had changed and shaped the state according to his will, he relaxed his initial severity to a considerable degree, and today, with the exception of those who actively agitate against his government, probably nobody is bothered by him. It is to be expected that the same will be true in Germany. When the Germans have recovered from that great shock which the stringent measures of the Hitler government--affecting as it does all phases of daily existence--have caused, and after they have grown accustomed to the new state, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0500.jpg" n="2"/>government will become less forceful. That may take longer than it did in Italy, because the old forms of government had become much more of a second nature to the German people than was the case in Italy.</p>
   <p>What happened in Italy and what is happening today in Germany will be termed reaction by many people. An opportunity for comparison with the time of reaction following the German wars of liberation is presented. But the analogy is by no means a good one. At that time the reaction started from above, the present one, however, originated from below. This movement does not consist of a narrow-minded opposition to progress in the realm of human society, economic life, and government methods, but rather, in a conscious and well-planned reorganization of the entire people, in its relations to the state as well as within its own social structure. And parliament in its old conception has fallen victim to this upheaval, because it no longer fits within the framework of the new form of government. In reality, it was no longer suitable for the old form; it failed miserably just at the time when it should have reached the height of its glory. The German Reichstag was composed of representatives of <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0501.jpg" n="3"/>political parties who were incapable of ruling the country, for, during a time when the people were up to the neck in economic difficulties, these members of the Reichstag dabbled in party politics and did nothing else. Keenly aware of this situation, Adolf Hitler intends to replace the political Reichstag by a Staenderat [council of the guilds, a diet], which will show a better appreciation of the economic needs of the people.</p>
   <p>Anyone who evaluates the governments of the principal countries of the world must come to the conclusion that the purely democratic principle, i.e., government by the masses or their representatives, has lost prestige in many instances. This applies not only to Italy and Germany, but also, even though not in so pronounced a way, to other countries, as, for example, England, and even the United States. How often during the last years has Congress acted in direct opposition to the will of the people, sometimes even blatantly against their best interests. A people to whom the democratic principle has become a matter of course, as it has for the American people, corrects the mistakes of its representatives when <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0502.jpg" n="4"/>it is aware of them. Right now the American people are engaged in correcting the mistake made by Congress and the legislators forty (sic) years ago when they inserted the Prohibition Amendment into the Constitution.</p>
   <p>Adjustments like that come late sometimes, but they do come. In Europe, however,--with the possible exception of England--the democratic way of life had never made as much progress as in America. In Europe democracy does not correct its faults, but perishes because of them. Therefore we should not really be astonished because the idea of a government by the people was abandoned over there when the weaknesses of the democratic form of government became too obvious. Instead of a government by the majority of the people, we now have in Germany--almost as in Italy--a government by selected leaders, selected not by the people, but rather by an oligarchy of top leaders. Obviously the theory is that it is the individual personalities of outstanding talents and achievements and not the masses nor the majorities that give a decisive character to a certain historical period. But just how much depends on the personality of a single man in a responsible position the American people have occasion to realize at the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0503.jpg" n="5"/>present time, through a simple comparison of the active energy of our President with the lethargy of his predecessor.</p>
   <p>After democracy had failed miserably in Germany, the people naturally staked their hopes on the man who had promised to reconstruct the Reich from its very foundations. Time only will tell whether or not he is the Moses who will give the German people good laws and lead them into the promised land.</p>
   <p>The idea of placing more confidence in the efficiency of individual, selected leaders, rather than in an assembly of people's representatives, is intrinsically a good one. If the sole aim had been to send none but outstanding men with political and economic foresight into the parliaments instead of third-rate politicians, the working efficiency of the parliaments would have been infinitely improved. That is probably also the reason for the miserable failure of most international conferences. You don't find any really great statesmen there who can look beyond the narrow horizon of their own nationality and appreciate what is good for humanity as a whole. Each delegation is <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0504.jpg" n="6"/>interested only in having its own petty and more or less selfish demands recognized and will withdraw with resentment whenever resistance is offered.</p>
   <p>Even the World Economic Conference would have had a much better chance for success if it had not been composed of hundreds of mediocre statesmen and economists, but had consisted of a half-dozen really great men of profound knowledge, sure judgment, and the determination to reach an agreement. If these half-dozen leading personalities had been given unlimited power by their respective nations, an agreement among them probably could have been reached sooner than expected, and the nations would have been spared much worry and anxiety about the future, and about the fact that they seem to be drawing closer and closer to a catastrophe, if one is to judge by the way things are going now. The principle of selection by a leader really has some good points. Of course it would not suit all countries and nations. The whole world couldn't be made to fit into the same framework. Nevertheless, we wouldn't be surprised if this new form of government should spread to other countries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
