<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-14">Oct. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Thirty-Hour Week</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0386</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0386.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-14">Oct. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE THIRTY-HOUR WEEK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At its annual convention, in San Francisco, the American Federation of Labor agreed, unanimously and with great enthusiasm, to the demand for a five-day and thirty-hour work week. Their president, William Green, promised the delegates of the unions that the organization would strive with all its power to attain this goal, because only in this way could unemployment be eliminated. The resolution demands that the working day be shortened and the number of working hours per week reduced without a reduction of wages. The goal is rather far away, and it will take some time to reach it. In the course of time it will come about that every person who works with his hands or brain will need to work only thirty hours a week for wages and will have the rest of the time to dispose of as he wishes. But this is still far in the future. Economic conditions are not yet ripe for it.</p>
   <p>The demand that wages not be reduced when working hours are shortened sounds very <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0387.jpg" n="2"/>fine and is easy to make; but how do they figure it will be accomplished? If the same wages are paid for a shorter work period, then, naturally, the prices of all goods will go up; for how else is the producer to get the money to pay the wages? Naturally, all consumers, including the workers, who make up the greater part of the consumers, will have to pay the higher prices. Hence it is difficult to see how this would be advantageous for the wage worker. At any rate, he would have more leisure than before. This might increase his working capacity, and probably would benefit his family life, in most cases. But the money which he earns in the shorter working time will not go as far as now, because everything will be higher in price. Unemployment will not be eliminated by this measure, out at the most will be reduced somewhat. Unemployment will not disappear until its basic causes are removed. The reduction of the working time, would at once provide bread for a part of the unemployed; but, at the same time, the increased wage costs would lead to the paralyzing of many branches of the economy, and consequently to the discharge of many workers. The actual condition of workers in general would not be affected at all.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0388.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The enthusiasm of the union delegates in San Francisco was natural and understandable; for who wouldn't be enthusiastic, if he saw prospects of having to work only thirty hours instead of forty-eight or forty, and with no reduction in wages? But there is quite a big difference between theory and practice. This really worthwhile goal can be attained only as the result of a slow development. It is not something that can be expected to happen over night, or even in the course of a year or two.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
