<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-13">Oct. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">New Methods of Organization (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0120</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0120.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-13">Oct. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">NEW METHODS OF ORGANIZATION (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Convention of the American Federation of Labor which is now taking place in San Francisco, has attracted more attention from the press this year, than it has for a long time. The reasons for this are clear. Since the beginning of the New Deal, and since the enactment of legal measures for the improvement of the economic situation, the Federation has become extraordinarily active. Often the prediction was made that under the N. R. A. the unions would slowly but surely die out because the Government had taken over most of their important functions. The leaders of organized labor have been aware of this danger. They turned the tables and have made use of the new measures to recruit more members, and have pursued this course with unswerving energy.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, only a small part of the working class belongs to the Federation. At present it has only about two and three-fourths million members. In comparison <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0121.jpg" n="2"/>with other industrial countries, this is a surprisingly small number. The Federation attained its greatest membership, immediately after the war, when its membership rose to more than four million. Since then the membership has been rapidly falling off. One of the reasons why many workers consistently avoid joining the Federation is that it does not allow its members to work side by side with unorganized labor. At present, a large building is being erected in Washington. A few days ago several hundred laborers left the structure because a handful of laborers were employed in the cellar who did not belong to a union. This regulation which, from the standpoint of the Federation seems theoretically justified, has, in practice, many disadvantages, because most of the laborers have no inclination to forego work and wages because a few other people are employed in the same building who do not belong to unions. For that reason there has been established in this country the institution known as the "closed" and "open shop," which is unknown in other countries.</p>
   <p>To remedy this bad situation, the Convention of the Federation of Labor has decided to establish so-called vertical unions. These are organizations which <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0122.jpg" n="3"/>include all the workers of a given industry. The principle of craft-unionism will not be completely given up. It is to be the regular way to organize workers, as in the past, but exceptions are to be allowed for certain industries. The Convention has ordered the immediate organization of vertical unions for a number of the largest industries; namely, for the iron, steel, automobile, aluminum, and cement industries.</p>
   <p>With this decision, the Federation has adopted an organizational principle of the I. W. W., who for some time were quite successful with their slogan: "One Big Union". Otherwise, no comparison can be made between the two organizations, because the I. W. W. was thoroughly political, and on the radical side. Its political creed was the revolution, while the Federation of Labor is politically conservative.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
