<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The New York of the West</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1610</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1610.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW YORK OF THE WEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only one thing has been lacking to make Chicago the New York of the West: It has not been a Democratic city; that is, it has not had a Democratic administration. But this deficiency has been overcome this year. The Democratic party in New York has been swept into office because of a large Irish population; and in Chicago the Democratic party has come into power through the support of the communists. These two elements [Irish population and Communists] may, or may not have different motives, but the results of their activities are the same.</p>
   <p>"It's no use talking," as the Americans say: Chicago, a former stronghold of the Republicans, is now Democratic; or, if one wants to be more accurate, Kentucky-Irish-Democratic. All the leaders of the Democratic party, including Mayor Harrison, are either from Kentucky (carpetbaggers from the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1611.jpg" n="2"/>South--a counterpart of the carpetbaggers from the North, who are so despised in the South) or are Irish.</p>
   <p>The Democratic party could never have attained leadership in Chicago had not the "Kentucky squires" had the good fortune to obtain the help of the communists, who did "nigger" [printed in English] work for them and served as "voting cattle" [term printed in English]. With their help they were able to beat the Republicans. Slaveholders and their "niggers" defeated the party which stands for liberty of the citizen (not the "bourgeois"), for equality before the law, for national unity and progress.</p>
   <p>Not all the Communists enjoy their position--vassals of the Kentucky "Slavocrats" [word coined by the Staats-Zeitung editor]. Harrison, at the time of the judicial election, followed the example of Robert Toombs, who, stood at the Bunker Hill monument twenty years ago and appealed to the "niggers" whom he had won for his party. But, in the present instance, Mr. [George] Schilling declared that the Democratic party had by no means <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1612.jpg" n="3"/>absorbed the communists. That was reassuring, but proves only that Mr. Schilling is not willing to perform "nigger" work [verbatim] for the "Kentucky gentlemen". It applies only to Schilling. The Jrottkaus [Translator's note: In other articles spelled Grottkau. Perhaps the "J" is intended for ridicule, as the Eastern Prussians pronounce the letter "G" as "J"], Lysers, and so forth, may consider the point differently. Particularly if--and it would only be customary--the communist helpers of the Democratic party are given soft jobs in the city or county courts, after which they will bid good bye to their theories and will stick to the flesh pots.</p>
   <p>But, regardless--the communists have the satisfaction of belonging to the ruling party, even if their position is lowly, and their share will probably not be withheld, because the "gentlemen from Kentucky" will need the communists again. After becoming accustomed to comfortable surroundings, they'll be reliable servants.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1613.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And that will spell "finis" to their aspirations for founding a new kind of government. The communists will become camp followers of a party in the United States which has the same standing as the Pommeranian aristocracy in Prussia. The communists will serve an American party which is definitely opposed to control of railroad monopolies and refuses to interfere in the war of "everyone against everyone," which now threatens labor; the party which has always opposed our high-wage scale, and will do nothing to protect the income of the workers; the party which plans at present to give us "watered money" with which to revive fraud and speculation; the party desirous of abolishing a protective tariff, thus placing our American workers on the same level as the starving proletarians of Europe.</p>
   <p>Service to the reactionary party--which stands for medieval servitude--that is the great success attained by the communists--world emancipators. May they enjoy it!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
