<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-12-27">December 27, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">An Ovation.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0877</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0877.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-12-27">December 27, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">AN OVATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The spacious "Vorwarts" Turn Hall last night was filled to capacity. From the earnest expression on their faces one could gather that the audience had the high ideals of the Socialists at heart.</p>
   <p>Mr. Spies opened the meeting at 8 o'clock.</p>
   <p>Dr. Ernst Schmidt was elected President and Messrs. E. Hilbert, F.A. Stauber,P. Peterson and Mrs. Neeve, Vice-Presidents. Mrs. Helen Wilmans was elected secretary. Dr. Ernst Schmidt: "I observe with great satisfaction that a large number of friends of Freedom have gathered here to honor one of the protagonists of our common cause, Johann Most. He came to us not as a visitor on a pleasure trip but as the result of his valiant fight against the despots of modern Society. For us Americans the day has not come yet to engage in a battle against existing wrongs. Change will not come through, words spoken or written, but will demand heavy sacrifices of human lives. He, who desires Peace must be prepared for a battle". Dr. Schmidt then introduced Mr. Johann Most who was enthusiastically received.</p>
   <p>Mr. George Schilling was the next speaker giving a short biography of Mr. Most in English. The conditions of the working-classes are the same here as in Europe. Persons who are worthless to Society, in other words parasites, have no right to <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0878.jpg" n="2"/>exist. To annihilate them is our duty. He devoted also a few words to Nihilism and expressed his admiration for this political group of Russians. He said that our Congress in Washington was nothing but a band of gangsters, not having an equal in the whole world. The American nation is approaching a catastrophe in the near future. Freedom at the polls is a farce as was shown in the care of the 14th ward and the decision of Judge Gardner. Johann Most remarked: The general belief in Europe and also in this country is that here no labor movement exists. This is the second of the meetings at which I have the honor to speak and I have noticed that the meetings were not only exceedingly well attended but that a thoroughly revolutionary spirit manifested itself at them. As regards America, I doubt that a revolution can be avoided. The land robberies here will create a kind of landlordism just as in England. There are laws enough, old and new, which the ruling classes can employ anytime to throttle freedom and to oppress the workers. Two battles already have been fought in this country; the first to end the foreign Tyranny, the second, to free the Negroes from slavery. I hope that the third will end with a triumph over white slavery. looking at this American flag I hope that the time will come when the stars and stripes will be replaced by a solid red, signifying brotherhood. (Stormy Applause). The spirit of revolution is predominant throughout the world. The coming revolution will differ from those of the past and greatly surprise the world. Science will replace religion, communism will replace the capitalistic sweating system; it will annihilate everything connected with the institutions of old". ( He read then a short <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0879.jpg" n="3"/>poem which he wrote in prison), (Stormy Applause). Resolution: Considering that a system of robbery and exploitation is as well established in the United States as in Europe and considering that like causes will produce like results, we declare also in the United States, any means necessary to destroy the prevailing oppression for justified.</p>
   <p>We therefore, salute Johann Most as protagonist of the social revolution which we desire and aim at.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
