<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-20">Jan. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Opportunity to Work and Immigration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0425</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0425.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-20">Jan. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">OPPORTUNITY TO WORK AND IMMIGRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The demobilization of our armies raises a question about workers, or the opportunity to work. And this question enhances the importance and urgency of the immigration question.</p>
   <p>Only a few hundred thousand of the three million workers who were withdrawn from commerce and industry to prepare for war and participate in it, have been released, and already the demand for work exceeds the supply in many quarters, and many thousands of those who have been discharged from war duties are finding it difficult to secure work. The opportunities are not numerous. Moreover, during the next six months the number of discharged soldiers, sailors, and other wartime employees will be increased by 500 per cent. This condition is causing no little apprehension. Ways and means are being considered not only to increase opportunities to work, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0426.jpg" n="2"/>but also to prevent competition between discharged members of the various war units, especially by controlling applications for help. The measures which will be taken will undoubtedly affect immigration. According to the various bills which have been prepared or are now being drawn up, immigration will be greatly restricted for at least five years, or will be cut off altogether for some years.</p>
   <p>This procedure is only natural. "Charity begins at home." As it is the duty of every father to care for the members of his family first, so it is also the duty of Uncle Sam to take care of the people of America first. If, as it is claimed, we need all the available jobs ourselves, then it is incumbent upon us to keep them for ourselves. And it is self-evident that Americans--especially American soldiers, sailors, and warworkers--are entitled to the best which the country has to offer. Thus, workers from foreign countries must be kept away from our shores as long as there is not sufficient opportunity to work to satisfy the demands of American workers. It is self-evident that immigration of foreign workmen must be prohibited <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0427.jpg" n="3"/>as long as there is the slightest danger that they will deprive American workmen of the opportunity to work.</p>
   <p>It is altogether superfluous to advance other reasons for closing our doors to foreigners. Still, some try to justify the ban on immigration by the statement that immigrants are inclined toward the violent radicalism which we call Bolshevism, and that they are responsible if our country is beset by the dangers of Bolshevism.</p>
   <p>But that is going too far. The statement is an insult to those who hold that immigration should be banned in order to serve American job-seekers first; for it permits the conclusion that their chief reason: "We want all jobs for Americans, especially for our American soldiers" (which is the only morally and economically incontestable reason), is not valid, and that they have other reasons for desiring a ban on immigration, And this suspicion is well founded.</p>
   <p>It is claimed: "Radicals are the product of autocracy....Because they had no <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0428.jpg" n="4"/>voice in matters under autocracy, they want to have all the say in our democracy." But this is true of only a very few. By far the greater number demand only what democracy has promised, or what they expected from a democracy. If they turn to radicalism it is because they have been impelled by bitter disappointment, and it matters little whether they themselves or the deficiencies of democracy have caused this disappointment. We recommend better care for the immigrant and a better application of democratic ideals and principles as a sure remedy against Bolshevism.</p>
   <p>They who advance the danger of Bolshevism as an argument for closing immigration are merely trying to cover up their Anglo-Saxon nationalism....</p>
   <p>Although thousands of discharged soldiers are looking for positions, there are still many opportunities for work. But young Americans are seeking "positions," and not just "work".</p>
   <p>The competition for jobs is stronger than ever because many girls and women <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0429.jpg" n="5"/>have done the work which had been done by boys and men, and will not relinquish their jobs. And this condition will not be improved by banning immigration. Immigrants do not take jobs, but rather create jobs. The greater the labor market, the more opportunity for industrial expansion; and the more industry expands, the more jobs there will be, jobs for Americans, jobs for soldiers, who are entitled to the best which America has to offer....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
