<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-10-13">Oct. 13, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">German Lutherans Remain Loyal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1505</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1505.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-10-13">Oct. 13, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN LUTHERANS REMAIN LOYAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Lutherans are firm and loyal not only in the city of Chicago, but also in the country towns of Illinois. Nothing can entice or seduce them to change their mind, about voting for Altgeld and other worthy Democrats on November 8th. Many of them prefer the Democratic ticket, although they were Republicans before the Edward Law became effective.</p>
   <p>The Lutherans all agree that the Democrats deserve the preference as far as the State ticket is concerned. This became very obvious at a recent meeting, where the elected delegates of the numerous German Lutheran Churches made the following practical resolutions:</p>
   <p>To organize Democratic Clubs for citizens; to promote the ones already established; to hold meetings, where the school question will be thoroughly discussed by able speakers; to give instructions, in meetings, about the proper marking of the ballot; and to appoint special committees, whose duty it will be to have the voters register in time.</p>
   <p>An outstanding member of the committee made the following remarks in the meeting:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1506.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"We must try to preserve the freedom of conscience. Although I have been a Republican for twenty-five years, I will vote in November for the Democratic Party, because it is trying to retain this liberty for us."</p>
   <p>In addition to this we have the recent announcement of the School Committee, denouncing the rumors about treason and desertion, confirming their loyal and active adherence to the manifesto of May 6th, which implies faithful support of Altgeld and the Democratic ticket in Illinois.</p>
   <p>The firmness and loyalty of the Lutherans will be an encouraging example to most Germans in the State.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
