<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-09-29">Sept. 29, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">Our Police.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0714</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0714.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-09-29">Sept. 29, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">OUR POLICE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Police Inspector Bonfield is at the present time in New York. The trip was purely a "pleasure trip". Bonfield's ideas of pleasure are very peculiar. We only have to recall to our mind the evening of May 4th, 1886 when Bonfield speaking to Mr. Simonson a traveling salesman said, that it would give him a great deal of "pleasure" if he could get a "Throng of about 1,000 of those Socialists and anarchists together, but without their damned wives and children". He wouldn't lose much time in dealing with them, and make short work of it. And Chicago didn't forget either his specially well liked amusement of 1885 either, on which occasion the street car strike afforded him that amusement. Taking all this into consideration and also the fact that Bonfield is the confidence man of the "Citizen's Association" and taking into consideration his trip east with intended stop overs at all the large Eastern cities and the mining regions of Pennsylvania and Ohio, we are tempted to join the New York Volks Zeitung in its opinion, that this dangerous capitalistic blood hound has been ordered to unite the police in a plot against freedom of speech as is the case in Bismarck's land and in the land of Francis Joseph.... At any rate, it is of utmost importance that labor keeps a watchful eye. In times past, the righteous has "received" in his sleep; but today the reverse is true..</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
