<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-02">Apr. 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago--Liberal and Good American City</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-02">Apr. 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO--LIBERAL AND GOOD AMERICAN CITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The election is over. The votes have been counted. The results are known. Thus the battle of wills, of opinions and of passions is ended. The citizens, male and female, have returned to their daily duties and to their daily preoccupations. Thus a democratic community returns to normalcy--and that Chicago is a democratic community in the fullest sense of the word is evident from the result of yesterday's election.</p>
   <p>Today, on the morning after the election, the Chicago Tribune writes: "They who feel downhearted should remember: The city will not float away, although the waters of Lake Michigan are attractive and alluring [sic]. It will remain here. It is our city. We must live in it and work in it; and as long as we continue to subsist here we must aid its progress. We hope that Mayor Thompson's second term will be more beneficial to his fellow citizens than his first term was".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0531.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The great mass of citizens will agree with the Tribune since the "Wonder of the World" has published a statement that is in complete agreement with American democratic ideas. This statement is particularly indicative of a democratic policy now that the Tribune's political platform has been so severely rebuked. The loyal followers of Mayor Thompson, and even the Mayor himself, will be pleased by this statement in the Tribune. They will gladly give their signed approval to the unaltered article--after they have first inserted the little word "even" in the final sentence, to make it read: "We hope that Mayor Thompson's second term will be even more beneficial to his fellow citizens than his first term was."</p>
   <p>The mayoral election is regarded as a personal victory for Mayor Thompson, and such a representation is entirely correct as far as party politics are concerned. Mayor Thompson won the Republican nomination in the primary election, but he did not have the support of the Republican organization in the regular election. In fact, the regular Republican party organization opposed him, partly in an open manner but mainly by <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0532.jpg" n="3"/>secret procedure. He received votes from some regular Republicans, not because of the efforts of their leaders and party workers but in spite of them. The Republican party organization fought him--fought him bitterly. Thompson is a Republican but he ran as an Independent Republican. Most of the votes of the adherents to the regular Republican organization were given to Hoyne, who ran as an Independent Democrat and who had to suffer the ignominy of being the candidate of those relentless, un-American elements which agitated race hatred.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's election was a personal victory for Mayor Thompson inasmuch as he was supported only by his own organization, was opposed by every large English newspaper of the city, and was successful--in spite of the enmity which he had incurred--in making a personal stand on the important issues of the day, thereby winning for himself the friendship and the following necessary for his re-election.</p>
   <p>And Thompson was successful; he received approximately 17,600 more <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0533.jpg" n="4"/>votes than his strongest opponent, although his opponent was backed by a very strong party organization, and despite the fact that the Mayor was attacked by the entire Chicago press and by other organizations and elements which should have supported him as their candidate. Did he win despite these facts--or because of them? Because of them! Apparently because of his enemies and the reasons for their enmity, Mayor Thompson was re-elected.</p>
   <p>Mayor Thompson provoked the opposition of the press because he would neither be dominated nor intimidated by the newspapers. He incurred the enmity of the hysterical, suspicious, big-business patriots because he would not be persuaded to join in their irreconcilable shouting, nor would he aid them in their un-American propaganda. He was suspected of disloyalty because he had the courage to respect the American ideal of liberty, and to defend the rights of freedom of assembly, freedom of speech, and freedom of thought, even during turbulent times. He polled 257,888 votes, a total of 688,361 votes. The candidate of the intolerant <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0534.jpg" n="5"/>un-American exhorters of race hatred received only 110,898 votes, and many thousands of these votes may be ascribed to his personal popularity and his well-known ability to write.</p>
   <p>This proves that the majority of our citizens want no part of intolerance and race hatred, and that they appreciate and respect courage and independence. Thus the mayoral election is even more than a personal victory for William Hale Thompson. It is a victory for liberal, progressive, strong, peaceful, genuinely democratic, American Chicago, the metropolis of the West, and the strong-heart [sic] of the nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
