<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-10-11">October 11, 1877</date><title level="a">Political Meetings</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-10-11">October 11, 1877</date><title level="a">POLITICAL MEETINGS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting of the Sixteenth Ward became almost the scene of a fist fight. Mr. Reichert formerly employed by the county stable, attempted to attack General Lieb in a speech, when General Lieb rose and declared in his defense, that he incurred Mr. Reichert's enmity when, for his drunkenness he found it necessary to discharge him....After order was restored and business matters attended to, General Lieb stepped onto the speaker's platform and made this speech:</p>
   <p>"It would be erroneous to consider me a candidate for any office, but interested as I am, in the welfare of the people, I feel it my duty to give them my help in freeing themselves of the Republican party, whose leaders were able to convert even a part of our laboring people to their way of thinking. Some years ago, when I as co-founder and leader of the "Peoples' Party" was offered an office, which was an immensely well paying position, I declined to accept it notwithstanding the fact that that very evening I had to <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1096.jpg" n="2"/>pawn my watch and chain, so I could pay my board."</p>
   <p>General Lieb then changed his speech to the Tilden campaign, but was soon interrupted by Mr. John Boning, a representative of the Socialist party, asking him whether the Democratic party is really willing and in a position to do something for the working man. General Lieb replied that the Democratic party's attitude was always friendly toward labor and asked Mr. Boning whether he was of the opinion that any salvation awaits labor from the Republican party. Mr. Boning parried this question, but expressed his doubt as to the Democratic Party's friendly attitude toward labor, to which conclusion he came by lengthy observation. Even their platform is meaningless, and promises can easily be made; but he would welcome a discussion with the opposing party on political questions. Thereupon General Lieb proposed to name a committee, which should meet a committee of the Socialist party, to confer on meetings and political questions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
