<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-04-25">April 25, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">What Will Be Expected of the Germans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1415</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1415.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-04-25">April 25, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT WILL BE EXPECTED OF THE GERMANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "Chicago Chronicle" today brings an article, addressed partly to the Democratic machine-politicians, partly to the German voters of our State. The article contains the first and asks the German citizens of Illinois to remain true to their old traditions and to give their votes for honesty and right. The "Chronicle" calculates that in the coming elections about 850,000 votes will be cast, of which about 250,000 will come from the German-Americans.</p>
   <p>The majority of the Germans are Democrats or would be Democrats on a sound money platform. With a declaration for free silver coinage, the Democratic politicians can reckon with a united German opposition. The Germans are not for a protective tariff.</p>
   <p>They are against the narrow-minded and arrogant Republican Legislation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1416.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They are against the Republican boodle in the administration; but they oppose even more energetically a dishonest money system than any other abuse of the administration. (This statement is entirely correct. Editor of Abendpost.) The Germans may have different opinions on tarif reform, they may wink an eye on the abuses of the administration, but the majority will never vote for inflation of the money and currency swindle. It is very opportune, that the Democratic newspaper calls attention to the strength of the German voters in Chicago and Illinois and indicates, that this vote can be lost to the Democratic cause, if the Democratic party accepts a silver platform. It has been proved at various times, that the German vote has turned the scale at the elections. In the year 1888, the Chronicle states, the election resulted in a Republic majority of 22,000, in 1890 the Germans on account of the school question went over to the Democratic party and the result was a majority of 34,000 for the Democrats. In 1892 the school question was still on and the Democrats were victors with 27,000 votes. There is no question that the majority of the Germans will be estranged from the Democratic party by a <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1417.jpg" n="3"/>Silver platform, and that this estrangement will take away every chance of the Democratic cause for victory. If the party in this State will commit suicide, they may follow suit with Altgeld, Hinrichsen, etc. On the other hand, however, if they declare themselves energetically against every inflation, they can count on a strong support in the coming election. It is to be hoped that the Germans will bring no disgrace to their reputation by standing as solid fighters for an honest monetary system.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
