<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-03-27">Mar. 27, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">To the Editor of the Abendpost</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1377</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1377.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-03-27">Mar. 27, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE EDITOR OF THE ABENDPOST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is gratifying to know that the subscribers of this newspaper are given a chance to express their attitude and discuss without any reservation any political topic, irrespective of their party allegiance. This is made possible through a column reserved by the Abendpost for this purpose. Thus, I avail myself of this opportunity to express my attitude in the matter of the coming election before the public. "Germans, take up the fight; and prepare to do your duty in the coming election. Do not be misled by any candidate who does not prove either by deed or simple utterance that he is a defendant of personal liberty, or something still worse whose past gives clues to the opposite.</p>
   <p>Charles C. Merriam is a son of the Prohibition State Iowa, whose family is devoted to prohibition, and helped to make the blue laws of that State.....</p>
   <p>Harrison is not exempt from making mistakes, nobody is. He may have been guilty of an occasional offense while in public service, but who can satisfy everybody? However, it is certain that Harrison is the more <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1378.jpg" n="2"/>trustworthy of the two candidates. The Germans, especially should have faith in Harrison, because he is well acquainted with the German customs, which he understands and respects. He has proven himself a practical man during his eight years as public servant. This fact reassures us of a conscientious city administration, if he is elected. Harrison will give our city that which is unquestionably necessary, namely; personal liberty."</p>
   <p>Geo. Giegold</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
