<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-10-17">Oct. 17, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Cigar Manufacturers and Cigar Makers Hold Session</title><title level="a" type="sub">Strike Settlement Probable</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0280</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0280.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-10-17">Oct. 17, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">CIGAR MANUFACTURERS AND CIGAR MAKERS HOLD SESSION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Strike Settlement Probable</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The committee appointed by the cigar makers last Wednesday met yesterday with the manufacturers' committee at the strike headquarters, 85 Dearborn Street, to effect a settlement of the strike, if possible.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the Cigar Makers' Union, Mr. Hirsch, called the meeting to order, and George Wagenfuehr, a cigar manufacturer, was named chairman of the meeting. He made a short speech, in which he expressed hope that a settlement could be reached since, after all, there were no serious difficulties involved. The cigar makers' committee was asked to state its findings and the demands of the Union.</p>
   <p>S. Goldwater declared that the Union had already stated its demands and had <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0281.jpg" n="2"/>given a price scale.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wagenfuehr replied that the manufacturers were not opposed to the price scale in general, but that the rates on cheap cigars would have to be changed. He said that the manufacturers objected to the exclusion of workers who made the cigar wrappers, since the manufacturers could not see how the men could earn more by receiving six dollars per thousand cigars without the aid of "wrappers" than the men could earn at the rate of $4.75 per thousand with the aid of "wrappers"</p>
   <p>Hirsch answered that the object of the exclusion was to provide undivided work. Most of the makers of wrappers were women who received low wages and were unable to make cigars. Self-preservation was the only motive for the measure.</p>
   <p>Mr. Goldwater then gave a lengthy speech, in which he mentioned Eastern competition and advised the manufacturers to fight it with their own capital and not with the workers' wages.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0282.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Deutsch emphasized that formerly only a few five-cent cigars were made, but that, at present, the manufacturers could not claim that there was no steady demand for the cheap grades.</p>
   <p>Hirsch spoke again. He said that cigar makers worked like machines and six dollars per thousand cigars would be only fair. Finally, he suggested that a convention of cigar makers should be held, and declared that no makers of wrappers should be employed, and that the men insisted on the six-dollar rate.</p>
   <p>After several other gentlemen had spoken about the strike in general, Mr. Wagenfuehr submitted the following list:</p>
   <p>Cigars 4-41/2" long...$5.50 per 1,000</p>
   <p>" 4 3/4" long...$6.00 per 1,000</p>
   <p>" 5" long...$6.50 per 1,000.</p>
   <p>This rate scale would be equivalent to a reduction of fifty cents, compared <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0283.jpg" n="4"/>with the scale of the union men.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cohen made a motion to adjourn, since all the questions had been discussed and the manufacturers now knew what the men wanted. Finally, Mr. Wagenfuehr gave a short address; he thanked the assembly for the confidence shown him and expressed hope that the difficulties would soon be settled.</p>
   <p>The committee of the cigar makers adjourned until Saturday afternoon. A meeting of the cigar makers is scheduled for this evening, at Romer's hall, to hear the conference report.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
