<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-06">Nov. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The "Day after Election"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-06">Nov. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE "DAY AFTER ELECTION"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At times it must seem doubtful to any citizen who takes his civic duty seriously and takes some part in the political life of city or country, whether the democratic form of government is the right one for the people and the nation. Important problems are solved and experienced representatives and officials are ousted by a small majority of voters who often hardly constitute an absolute majority of the entire electoral body. The question arises whether better results could not be obtained, politics become more stabilized, and a more efficient, more experienced officialdom be secured for the nation and the community, if the "people"--whatever may be understood by that term--were not allowed to make decisions so arbitrarily and so much in accordance with the mood in which they happen to be.</p>
   <p>Such reflections are usual after an election when hopes have been shattered, but <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0565.jpg" n="2"/>he who is wise will quickly recover, for on the "day after election" he will really appreciate the beautiful and beneficial features of democratic self-government by the ballot if he looks around him and observes how the people act and react.</p>
   <p>On the day after an election like yesterday's, a reflecting and observing citizen cannot have any further doubts that the American people are ripe for democracy, for a day like today proves that the American people, in spite of any conclusion we might draw from other considerations, possess political judgement and self-restraint to a high degree and thereby fulfill all the preliminary conditions for self-determination and self-government.</p>
   <p>In a democratic community the majority rules and the right of government by majority--the current majority of the lawful electorate--must be recognized unconditionally; otherwise democracy cannot exist and prosper. This "day after election" conclusively proves this to be the case. The campaign was short but <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0566.jpg" n="3"/>lively. At stake were decisions on important problems and the filling of a great number of very important offices. Many expectations have been realized and almost as many hopes shattered. Hundreds of thousands "were right" and won, and just as many saw their opinions and candidates repudiated, turned back by a majority which hardly made up one third of all citizens who were entitled to vote. Here there might be an opportunity and some reason for ill-humor, resentment, and disgust--but in reality there was nothing of the sort!</p>
   <p>There are today many bitterly disappointed candidates in the city of Chicago and each one of them can count hundreds and thousands of friends and adherents who are equally disappointed by the results of the election. But the countenances of those that have failed smile as cheerfully as a sunny day, and the exchange of greetings between victors and vanquished is either friendly and sympathetic or teasing. The great game of politics was being played. Some won and others lost. What is the difference? The victor of today may lose in the next election and he who was defeated today may be victorious the next time. In the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0567.jpg" n="4"/>meantime everybody tries to get along as best he can. The fight and the arguments are over, and any resulting animosity and ill-will are things of the past. Forgotten are the hard words which were spoken and those who were enemies before are again good friends and neighbors--until the next election!</p>
   <p>This is the way the sovereign people of Chicago act, this is the way the nation as a whole acts. So must a people be that wants to decide its own fate.</p>
   <p>.... There remains only the completion of the system of self-government, its improvement; and, if necessary, its change, in order that this great idea may be of the utmost benefit for the people in its application and accomplishment. There is much to be done yet. It is a great and difficult task, but the essentials for a successful solution are at hand and the greatness of the problem should encourage cheerful co-operation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
