<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-07-09">July 9, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The Bakers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0096</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0096.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-07-09">July 9, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The Bakers.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The union of the Bakers is active in its quiet but energetic way, in putting an end to the most undesirable conditions, to which this group of workers have been subjected.---- The establishment of a registry office, has proven a great success, and both parties, the employer as well as the employee, recognize the advantages of this office. Many of the most repulsive conditions, have already felt the activity of this new institution, especially the one, of the boarding system.</p>
   <p>Conditions of this kind, can be remedied only, not by hiding them, but by exposing them. In case of any reform, the important factor is, to know the truth, which is also time saving in the end. With this in mind, the Labor Committee of the Bakers-Helpers Union, motivated their demands in a written document, which stated nothing but facts, and as such brought to the knowledge of Chicago's employers. This document reads in parts: In the name of Chicago's Bakers - Helpers Union, the undersigned take the liberty to inform you of the Union's decisions, and beg of you for a reply.The conditions of the Bakers helpers in German bakeries, compared with the working conditions of workers of other branches, and even compared with the conditions of the English Bakeries of this city, are unjust and disgraceful. --- We expect, that our demands, for the abolition of the boarding system, and shorter working hours will be met with your approval.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
