<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-02-04">February 4, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">In a New Part.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0736</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0736.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-02-04">February 4, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">IN A NEW PART.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If there are people still who believe in Nina Van Zandt's sanity, they will change their minds when the report reaches them that she is the author and publisher of a book glorifying her "worthy husband" August Spies. To convince the readers that they do not miss much if they don't purchase the first product of this writer, we are giving here the contents of the book.</p>
   <p>First, of course, the title of the book which is: A. Spies' Autobiography; his speech in the court room; notes, letters etc. The book cover bears, of course, the name of Nina Van Zandt, the publisher. Not to forget, a new book must have a "preface" also. Nina explains in this preface her reason for publishing the biography and defense speech of A. Spies; also letters written by Spies while in jail and sent to her.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0737.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The intention is to acquaint her American fellow-citizens with the life, character, and efforts of the one who has been and still is misjudged and who is the victim of a conspiracy of social hawks. Contrary to press reports, she found the accused anarchists to be intelligent men and, being convinced that the police and detective force are trying their best to have the accused condemned, she determined to stand up for the persecuted men.</p>
   <p>Upon her and other friends advice, August Spies expanded his autobiography and consented to its publication..........Quite indignantly, she criticises the conduct of newspaper representatives who called her marriage "scandalous", being an American girl and of respectable "extraction". She says: "Had I married an old decrepit invalid with a large fortune, these "ethical" gentlemen who chose to attack me thus, would have had only high praise for me and many of my Christian sisters and brothers</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
