<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1875-03-19">Mar. 19, 1875</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1875-03-19">Mar. 19, 1875</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3 - 5 The workingmen - the communists who have been howling all winter over the oppression of capital, and wildly storming around the doors of the Relief and Aid society, entertained themselves, last evening, at the West-sider Turner Hall with speeches, tableau, dances, lager beer, cigars, and stale pipes, the entertainment was in commemoration of the uprising of the people in Germany in 1848, and the Paris communes in 1871, and drew together that class of our population who have made themselves conspicuous and notorious in their against law, order, decency, and capital.</p>
   <p>There were present about 500 persons, men, women, and children, and a more motley-looking crowd has never assembled in Chicago. It was neither a fashionable nor good-looking assemblage. There were lean and fat, tall and short, round and angular, wiry and muscular, and weazen-faced and brazen-faced individuals, who had neither grace of form and movement nor comeliness of face to make them especially attractive. They evinced neither hard labor nor pinches of poverty, but on the contrary gave indications that they were far above the sufferings which the blatant leaders had depicted to our city authorities.</p>
   <p>They came plain but neatly clad, and judging from the manner in which beer <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1107.jpg" n="2"/>flowed and cigars were consumed, their scrip was by no means exhausted in the struggle to maintain themselves during an unprecedentedly severe winter and scarcity of employment. Some seemed to have plethoric purses, and others carried currency of no mean proportions. They all came to enjoy themselves, and they did enjoy themselves regardless of expense. From the moment they entered the hall, they gathered about the tables and sipped the amber nectar until the close of the festivities.</p>
   <p>Among the throng, Carl Klings, Leopold Teller, John McAuliff, Simmon, Jeffers, and Krauser, the leaders of the communes in the city, were conspicuous, and seemed the heroes of the hour.</p>
   <p>A speech was called for. In response, Carl Klings came forward and said that they were assembled to celebrate the anniversary of two great episodes in history - the 18th of March, 1848 and 1871, the days when the people rose as a mass to fight against tyranny and despotism. After a few remarks on the revolution of 1848, Klings spoke of the motives of the Paris commune.</p>
   <p>The despots of those days, not satisfied with having taxed the people to <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1108.jpg" n="3"/>the utmost, demanded, in 1871, after the population of Paris had manfully resisted the Prussians for a time almost incredible, that they surrender the arms they had so manfully carried. The people objected to this, they did not choose to be given defenseless into the hands of the so-called government, in reality their bitterest enemy. They defended their rights, and forced the troops out of Paris.</p>
   <p>"Then," the speaker pursured, "the government of Versailles entered into an agreement with the Prussians against their own country men. Then they sold these men, their own flesh and blood for the sum of five hundred millions." (Applause). "Oh! This is a dark spot in the history of the human race, a spot darkened by the blood of thousands, and it will take ages to deface it.</p>
   <p>"I have but one reproach to offer to the commune, and that is, that they were too lenient. Like honest men they guarded the property belonging to their enemies, the money in the bank of France. They touched not one sou of it, but made a paltry loan of 500,000 francs from Rothschild.</p>
   <p>"Here, too, we are trodden down by capital and the bourgeois. But for us, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1109.jpg" n="4"/>too, the day of deliverance is coming, sooner than you imagine."</p>
   <p>At this stage Klings was fairly overwhelmed by passion, and in perfect frenzy he hissed forth between his teeth the following words: "When this day comes, brethren, you must remember what I have told you today, and not, like the Parisians, be merciful. Discard all feelings of mercy and think of our enemies, as they showed themselves two weeks ago. Think of the cannons they had in Readiness, ready to shoot you down like dogs, had you dared to murmur. 'Eye for eye and tooth for tooth' be our motto on that day, and we will revenge our brethren slaughtered at Paris." (Howls.)</p>
   <p>Mr. John McAuliff then addressed the throng, and spoke at some length of the tendency of capital to ignore poor people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
