<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-29">Aug. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A Delicate Situation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0170</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0170.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (1)</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-29">Aug. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A DELICATE SITUATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is reported from Washington that Harry Hopkins, chairman of the Federal board for relief of the needy, has asserted that the commission will support the textile workers who suffer want because of the strike. The strike of the textile workers is scheduled to begin on September 4th. On that day, it is alleged, a half-million persons employed in the textile industry will lay down their work. According to other reports, their number is 850,000. The national union of textile workers has a strike fund of a round million dollars. This sum is so scanty that there is only a little more than a dollar for every striker, or two dollars at most.</p>
   <p>Some of the local unions have special strike funds, but these are likewise supposed to be small. It is therefore a foregone conclusion that the strike will break down within a short time unless the strikers receive financial <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0171.jpg" n="2"/>backing from other sources. This backing is to be given them by the government. That is a very delicate affair. The funds were put at the disposal of the commission to help the needy, and it goes without saying that they should, in first place, accrue to the needy unemployed. Strikers, however, are not among the needy unemployed; they could work if they wanted to; but they prefer to go on strike.</p>
   <p>If this plan materializes--and to judge from Mr. Hopkins' statements there is no longer any doubt that it will--then the relief funds will be converted into a war chest for striking workers, and this was by no means intended when these funds were appropriated. Hopkins further stated that needy strikers will be supported from these funds only until the Labor Department or the National Board for Industrial Relations decide that the strike is unjustified. He further declared that, up until now, all strikers have been supported when in need, and the authorities have never yet declared that a strike was not justified.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0172.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Hopkins takes the view that there is nothing else for him to do but to ascertain whether the persons seeking relief are or are not in need. If they are in need, they will be helped. This is quite a magnanimous attitude but it harbors the gravest perils for industrial peace and for the national economy. Should this procedure be consistently applied, workers will be able to paralyze industry at the expense of the taxpayers.</p>
   <p>Until now, the principle was adhered to that the authorities may only mediate in industrial struggles. If the mediation is without results, the government withdraws and lets the parties fight it out. Now this principle is to be thrown overboard; the government is taking its stand on the side of the strikers from the outset, and plans to help them financially in their struggle. This is certainly not in the interest of the vast majority of the American people. It smacks of crass partiality in favor of the strikers, and even the intelligent and thoughtful among the workers will shrink back from such a step.</p>
   <p>For if the government helps the strikers obtain a victory by supporting them <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0173.jpg" n="4"/>financially, it is natural that it support the employers as well. This implies that it must, by deliberate raising of prices, put them in a position to meet all demands of the strikers. In other words, it must nationalize the whole industry. No other way out would be possible under the circumstances, and what is more aggravating is that the problem in some strikes is merely that of organization. In such cases, the authorities are still less entitled to intervene.</p>
   <p>It must be left to each worker and to every group of workers to decide whether they want to belong to a union affiliated with the American Federation of Labor or to a company union--or whether they want to belong to any union at all. Every worker must decide this for himself; it must be left to the choice of every worker as to whether he wants to recognize an organization or not. Either party, employers as well as employees, must have a free hand in this respect; they must both carry the responsibility for their decisions, and alone bear the consequences.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0174.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Mr. Hopkins' procedure is not prompted, in this case, by social or humanitarian considerations, it is, rather, tantamount to interference with economic life, which is bound to result in complete nationalization of industry. The American people are not ready, as yet, to take such a step.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
