<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-03-30"> Mar. 30, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal of the Republican Executive Committee to the Germans of Chicago</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1630</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1630.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-03-30"> Mar. 30, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL OF THE REPUBLICAN EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE TO THE GERMANS OF CHICAGO</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When you realigned yourselves with the Republican party three years ago to end the mismanagement of our municipal affairs under Democratic rule you voted for Monroe Heath, and thereby you gave the city an administration which successfully combated bankruptcy and brought prosperity. The best administrations which Chicago ever had were Republican and you Germans have always helped in electing them. We appeal to you to support us again by voting the Republican ticket next Tuesday, as we are convinced that only a Republican victory and Mayor Heath's continuance in office give assurance that the efficient management will continue and that taxes will not increase. We believe we have an especial claim to your vote, because we supported a man for the mayoral candidacy whose independent attitude toward prohibition and blue laws created the enmity of the temperance fanatics even before <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1631.jpg" n="2"/>the nomination.</p>
   <p>The man, for whose election as mayor of this great trade center, we seek your votes, is A. W. Wright. He has been a resident of Chicago for more than a quarter century, is connected with the commercial interests of the city and can be regarded as a suitable representative of the business world, to which Chicago is indebted for its prosperity and commercial importance. He was a poor but ambitious young man when he came to Chicago. Being diligent,circumspect, and scrupulously honorable, and possessing rare tact in commercial matters, he soon attained a reputation among businessmen, not only in Chicago, but throughout the land. Like many of you, he suffered heavy material losses in the Chicago Fire, but nevertheless he never failed to honor a promissory note. His character is spotless. As merchant, as well as citizen, he proved a credit to the city.</p>
   <p>He should prove especially acceptable to the Germans, because of his fearless <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1632.jpg" n="3"/>fight for freedom. When the temperance members questioned him, prior to the nomination, to ascertain whether he might be a suitable tool to foster their schemes to put a restraint upon your personal liberties and mode of life, he declared unhesitatingly and candidly that he did not care to be associated with the prohibition movement. He told the "drys" that a mayor of a metropolitan city has more important duties to perform than to be the servant of a sect which insists on dictating what others may eat or drink. Furthermore, he assured them that the enforcement of a puritanical Sunday law will only be possible after Chicago's streets sprout grass, and declared abruptly that he was not inclined to inaugurate another temperance conflict. "Chicago is a cosmopolitan city and must be ruled in such a manner that everyone within its boundaries can attain happiness according to his own discretion--as long as he does not jeopardize the life or property of his neighbors or interfere with the public peace."</p>
   <p>Mr. Wright was so definite in his refusals to deal with the temperance <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1633.jpg" n="4"/>element that the latter consider him an archenemy of their cause. Is it not likely that the man who aroused the bitter enmity of the temperance fanatics and Sunday saints will be your friend, particularly if the animosity ensued from his fearless espousal of the principles for which you fought so consistently?</p>
   <p>Besides, Mr. Wright proved repeatedly that he is well informed about city problems, and, if elected, he will not only continue the beneficial policies of Mayor Heath but will enlarge their scope. Under his leadership taxes will be reduced and yet more will be accomplished than heretofore--commensurate with the just demands of all citizens.</p>
   <p>And whom does the Democratic party offer as candidate for mayor? Its candidate is Carter H. Harrison, a man who accomplished the great feat, during a four year congressional term, of making more speeches than the combined national representatives of Chicago since the founding of the town. Of <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1634.jpg" n="5"/>course, he spoke occasionally for a measure of specific benefit to Chicago, but whatever he did in this respect is forgotten when one considers how, in spite of his rare gift of eloquence, he listened and sat in silence while the Rebel chief, Ben Hill of Georgia, made the despicable declaration that Camp Douglas was the Andersonville of the North. Furthermore, when Blaine, in contradicting this southern arrogance, sought the assistance of Chicago representatives, then Harrison, the great orator, remained mute--and denied knowing even where Camp Douglas was situated! Do the inhabitants of Chicago want to be encumbered with a mayor who remains indifferent when such slanderous aspersions are cast on their city? What Carter Harrison did for the city can be said in a few words; however, he acted differently when in his native environment.</p>
   <p>Raised among slaveholders, he still feels drawn toward the Southern Rebels and is sympathetically inclined toward them even today. Though he was too cowardly to defend his views on the battlefield, he was brave enough to trample on the Union banner during a murky night, while inciting a rabble <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1635.jpg" n="6"/>horde in Covington, Kentucky, during the winter of 1860. And how resolutely he extols the cause of the North was shown last fall, when George Mapes, a Union soldier, crippled by Harrison's Southern friends, was evicted by Harrison, because the man was seven dollars in arrears with his rent. The veteran's wife was expected to become a mother at the time. Only a man can do that who fights clandestinely on the Rebel side to oppose the Northern heroes' endeavors to preserve the nation. And further, I cannot find anything to recommend in Harrison's "career" as a citizen which might justify especial confidence in him. He resided here for about fifteen years and, during the entire period, was active only in usurious business involving land speculation. He made his pile with "tax titles," obtained at the expense of poor people who could not pay their assessments, and thus Harrison acquired a princely income.</p>
   <p>He is not a man of positive opinions, and if he has them, then he refrains from making definite statements. What he told the temperance people did <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1636.jpg" n="7"/>not induce them to regard Harrison as their enemy, and, in the same manner he answered evasively the questions of the liberal-minded citizens. About city affairs he never went beyond the stereotyped phrase that he knows nothing regarding them [city affairs]. And then, remember, he is a Democrat and his election would result in the abolition of the Republican administration. A ravenous horde of Irish office seekers would storm the city hall and you know from personal experience that where the Irish rule, the Germans have no chance. If Harrison is elected, then an increase in taxation is unavoidable, because the Democrats must have jobs and the mayor is expected to provide them. The good credit rating now enjoyed by the city will soon terminate, and the greater expenditures would provide no improvements for Chicago.</p>
   <p>For City treasurer the Republicans recommend M. A. Farwell, who, like A. M. Wright, is a faithful representative of Chicago's businessmen. He is prosperous, whatever he achieved resulted from his own efforts, and the gentle man may well be entrusted with the city's funds, since he has an excellent <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1637.jpg" n="8"/>reputation as a businessman of long standing and no one can assail his integrity.</p>
   <p>On the other side, the Democrats seek your votes for W. C. Seipp, candidate for city treasurer. He is unquestionably a nice young man, but we doubt that anyone would have ever heard of him, if he had not been the son of a rich beer brewer. If you can be induced to cast your vote for him, you merely prove that you still believe in class distinction due to birth. No one should be honored by public trust in this land, except a person proved by his own efforts to be worthy. But Mr. Seipp thus far has had no opportunity aside from being a descendant of his father, to prove that he has accomplished anything which shows him to be a man worthy of representing Germans. In order to uphold the Teutonic principles the Germans should disdain this Democratic bait and thus give the young gentleman time to prove his mettle and show his capabilities by his own initiative.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1638.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>For corporation counsel we ask you to vote for R. W. Ricaby, a gentleman requiring no recommendation on our part. He is a patriot who, in defending the cause of the North during the Civil War, was crippled for life. He is well known as a capable lawyer and is popular because of his liberal views and joviality, whereas his adversary, Julius S. Grinnell, is absolutely unknown.</p>
   <p>And you will vote just as gladly for your young countryman, Peter Buschwah, to elect him as city clerk. He was born in Chicago of German parents and, due to his diligence as well as his staunch character, earned the esteem of all who know him. He is a young gentleman qualified to represent Germans, while his adversary Pat. G. Howard, is a man enshrouded with a dark past. Of late he has not come in conflict with the law, but it is still remembered that he was associated with the most villainous and dangerous rowdies who perpetrated their ignominious deeds on the West Side during election days.</p>
   <p>It would be entirely too much of a risk to entrust him with the task of <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1639.jpg" n="10"/>watching the ballot count, as he tried often enough to forestall an honest election.</p>
   <p>In regard to the town tickets, you need only compare the names on the list to give preference to the Republicans.</p>
   <p>Your own interests as taxpayers demand that you favor the Republican candidates. And we also appeal to you to elect your Republican Aldermanic candidates. They are better men throughout and inspire more confidence than their Democratic opponents. You, as taxpayers, only favor yourselves when you vote the Republican ticket in its entirety.</p>
   <p>We do not believe that the Republican party will meet with ignominious defeat, when their main candidate was nominated unanimously--without a single dissenting voice--and we do not think that the Germans will ignore A. M. Wright, whose fearless espousal of the German liberal view aroused the unmitigated <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1640.jpg" n="11"/>hatred of our bitterest enemies.</p>
   <p>If you, the Germans, remain faithful to your colors, then the Republican ticket will be elected with a majority that will inspire terror within the ranks of Union enemies in Congress as well as among the opponents of order and liberty within our own city.</p>
   <p>The Executive Committee of the Republican Party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
