<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-03-28">Mar. 28, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Ernst Schmidt's Letter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-03-28">Mar. 28, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">DR. ERNST SCHMIDT'S LETTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Schmidt's letter reached our office last night shortly before closing time so we printed it without comments.</p>
   <p>But now we wish to make a few observations. The letter of our old comrade certainly needs explanation and we intend to give it to-day.</p>
   <p>It is unnecessary to state that Dr. Schmidt is actuated by the most noble motives, when he defines his position and say that he will vote for Roche and Mr. Connell at the next election.</p>
   <p>Our readers as well as we who know Dr. Schmidt and his activities, do not doubt his sincerity.</p>
   <p>At the same time there cannot be any doubt that Dr. Schmidt knows exactly what he is doing; he therefore must have very important reasons for recommending the election of a man like Roche.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1561.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If, nevertheless, we cannot sanction Dr. Schmidt's letter it is because we cannot recommend Mr. Roche not only on account of his past, but also on account of what he may do in the future.</p>
   <p>His qualifications right now are of a very elusive nature.</p>
   <p>His record in bridge and viaduct building was the result of the fast development of Chicago and therefore was an absolute necessity, proving that Roche has not done anything except what circumstances forced him to do.</p>
   <p>Neither is it to the credit of Mr. Roche that he suspended the two corrupt police officers,Schaack and Bonfield, as he did only after having been compelled to adopt this measure by the exposures of the Arbeiter Zeitung and later by those of the Times.</p>
   <p>To suspend those policemen was to his own advantage and he deserves no thanks for it. At present the situation is as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1562.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The election of a socialist Mayor is out of the question.</p>
   <p>Who,therefore,should be elected; Roche or Cregier? Indications are that the latter would reinstate Schaack and Bonfield; these two gentlemen would then be puffed up beyond limit and as a result, police abuses would reach new heights, while Roche, no matter for what reasons, will not re-instate Schaack and Bonfield.</p>
   <p>Concerning Mr. Connell, there is no controversy. Mr. Connell has proven himself a true friend of the working-class and of justice under the most trying conditions. It is, therefore, superfluous to state that the working class will support him again.</p>
   <p>This, in a few words ,is our viewpoint.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
