<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-04-06">Apr. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">German Speakers at the Meeting of the 47Th Ward.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1201</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1201.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-04-06">Apr. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SPEAKERS AT THE MEETING OF THE 47TH WARD.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the Bell School on Oakley Avenue and Grace Street more than 300 persons attended a meeting which was called by a special committee of the 47th Ward, under the direction of Professor Harry Ellerman. The purpose of the meeting was to give information a bout the candidates of German extraction who are seeking public offices on the Deneen ticket.</p>
   <p>First of the three speakers was George H. Weideling, who is a candidate for the sheriff's office. He described the untenable conditions prevailing in Chicago and placed the responsibility for them upon the shoulders of State's Attorney Crowe.</p>
   <p>Dr. Teichmann, president of the Korner Mint of the Steuben Society spoke in a similar vein. He described the activities of the State's Attorney and proved how he used his official position to build up a political machine, which eventually would become a danger to the state and the city.</p>
   <p>Mayor William Hale Thompson also was under the harmful influence of Crowe's <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1202.jpg" n="2"/>political power. Naturally the German-Americans are grateful to Thompson for his attitude during the world war, but even gratitude has its limits. If Thompson joins Crowe and Small, then it is time that the German-Americans do not vote for him any longer. Thompson has to thank the German-Americans for his last year's victory, and the reward for it is that in public offices scarcely any Americans of German descent are to be found.</p>
   <p>Scarcely did Joe Haas die, when seven German-Americans were discharged from the Recorder's office. At the head of this department they placed a woman, who was nothing else but a good housewife. The husband of Mrs. Jaranowski is the real boss, and he also holds the position of Mayor of Calumet, and is also a member of the county commissioners.</p>
   <p>Why is this possible? Because the Americans of Polish extraction stick together, a characteristic which is lacking in the German-Americans. Next Tuesday an opportunity is offered to purge the state and city of the impure elements. If this favorable occasion is not taken advantage of, then nobody should complain later, if things get worse.</p>
   <p>Dr. Teichmann then recommended the German candidates, of whom he said that they all deserved the full confidence of the population.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
