<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-03">June 3, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Judicial Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1169</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1169.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-03">June 3, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE JUDICIAL ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Seldom has a campaign aroused so little interest as has the campaign leading up to the judicial elections, which will take place Monday. For years we have been accustomed to seeing only a small part of the electorate participating in such elections. As a result the judicial elections have become the private business of the political organizations. The professional politicians and their followers take part in the elections, and decide them, since the bulk of the citizens stay away from the polls.</p>
   <p>It was always that way, but this year the indifference has been noticeably greater than usual, in spite of the fact that the people of Illinois must, at the same time, decide about the retention or repeal of Prohibition. The English-language press is obviously completely indifferent about the matter. A few of big English-language papers have for years been fighting energetically for the repeal of Prohibition. It seems inconceivable that they have <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1170.jpg" n="2"/>not spent weeks drumming up interest and propagandizing in articles, pictures, and cartoons for a big turnout at the election. In such a case the judicial election, also, would be a real expression of the people's will.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless this paper considers it its duty to urge those among its readers who are entitled to vote to take part in the election. The right to vote is the only right that enables the citizen to exert a direct influence upon the Government and the Administration, and a person who fails to exercise this right because of indolence or indifference does not deserve to possess it. In its local section this paper makes definite recommendations for the judicial election and it entreats its readers to look these over carefully and to take them into consideration.</p>
   <p>This paper has also taken into careful consideration the recommendations of the Bar Association with regard to judicial candidates. In several instances, however, its recommendations differ from those of the Bar Association. This paper is unable to see why judges who have performed the duties of their office honorably for years, and who have been recommended once or <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1171.jpg" n="3"/>several times by the Bar Association, should suddenly fail to have the qualifications for a judicial office.</p>
   <p>There are three tickets in the field, the Democratic or Fusion ticket, the Republican, and the Independent or People's ticket. The last of these is not supported by any political organization. Nevertheless, this paper has endorsed several candidates on this ticket who are of German stock and who have long been well thought of by German-American citizens. All the other recommendations, also, were made after long and careful consideration. They should assist the reader in making his decisions in the election. If readers select different candidates, that is their privilege. The main thing is to vote!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
