<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-10-14">October 14th, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Democratic Mass Meeting.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1502</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1502.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-10-14">October 14th, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Democratic Mass Meeting.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Democratic Mass Meeting sponsored by the German-American Democratic Club of Cook County and held last night in the Central Music Hall, took place in a very satisfactory way to the friends of Cleveland and Altgeld. The attendance was much better than two weeks ago in the same Hall of a Republican meeting. It was regretted that the candidate for Governor, Mr. Altgeld, was prevented from appearing in person. Dr. Sermer of the New York State Newspaper and Julius Goldzier, Democratic candidate of the 4th congressional district, were the main speakers.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by a short speech of Louis Nettlehorst, who said, that the Republican Party had long ceased to embody the ideals of the Germans in their principles. They were only serving the almighty Dollar and an uncouth Nativism.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1503.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Democratic Party does not create monopolists. Dr. Sermer said that the Germans of the East had sent him to give a brotherly hand to the Comrades of the West, and to ask them for their support in the great battle in which both interests are alike. He cannot comprehend, that there are still Germans, who will be fooled by the promises of the Republicans. It is as if a farmer painted on the walls of his stable a landscape with a beautiful pasture for his cows. He compared the pasture with the Mc Kinley Bill and the cows with the credulous Germans. It is true, that, business is at the upgrade, but the reason is not the Mc Kinley Bill but the good harvest of the previous year, and the poor conditions of Europe. American industry is already among the largest of the world and the immense tarifs only benefit the Monopolists. The Democratic Party protects the workman and if the Repunlicans are victorious it will be too bad for the working man. The small business man, and the preservation of the dear Mother tongue. The speaker gave his appreciation of the principles of Grover Cleveland, the German's friend and the Gubernatorial candidate Altgeld.</p>
   <p>The final speech was made by Julius Goldzier, who pointed out that the Republican Party had imported foreign workmen which shows the way they were protecting the American Working man.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1504.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He asked the German American people to stand man by man with the Democrats, their true friends. During the war the Republicans received the German warriers with open arms, but in peace time they wish to destroy their language and spirits. Grover Cleveland and the German American, John P. Altgeld are the true friends of the Germans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
