<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-04-02">Apr. 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Timely Warning</title><title level="a" type="sub">Appeal to the German Voters of the 26th Ward Co-Operation Necessary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1279</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1279.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-04-02">Apr. 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A TIMELY WARNING</title><title level="a" type="sub">Appeal to the German Voters of the 26th Ward Co-Operation Necessary</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An urgent appeal to the German voters of the 26th Ward to support unanimously the German candidate for mayor of the Democratic party, Robert M. Sweitzer, and not to split up the German vote because of religious or other differences of opinion, and not to let themselves be induced to abandon their objective of electing a German mayor, was issued by the German-American Sweitzer Campaign Committee by the Ward. The appeal points out that a defeat [of Sweitzer], caused by a split of the German vote, would make the German population the object of scorn and derision by the hostile [anti-German] press of the country. It is also pointed out that it would be desirable, perhaps even absolutely necessary, after the election, for the voters of German descent to form a politically independent organization, in order to use their power judiciously and maintain their rights.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1280.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Applies to the Entire German Element</p>
   <p>The appeal is so worded that it applies not only to the German voters of the 26th Ward, but to the German voters of the entire city, who should take this warning to heart. Pointing to the sensation which Sweitzer's nomination has caused all over the country, and to the obvious significance it has attained, the appeal continues:</p>
   <p>"In order to add weight to the success thus far gained, it is absolutely necessary to continue on the course adopted, and to vote for Robert M. Sweitzer in the April 6 election. Under no circumstances let yourselves become confused by false prophets, who right now are trying to split up the German element with the promise that a Republican mayor would do just as well. Don't forget the old German slogan: 'Boys, hold fast!' Keep what you have attained so far. Do not let yourselves be induced, in this serious hour, to abandon your objective. We do not want to become the target of scorn and derision by the hostile press of this country."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1281.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Regarding the establishment of an independent political organization by the German element, the appeal has this to say:</p>
   <p>"After the election, it would be desirable at least, if not downright necessary, for the voters of German descent to form an independent political organization in order to make use of their power and preserve their rights.</p>
   <p>"With an independent organization, we can compel recognition and make our voices heard.</p>
   <p>"For this purpose, the voters of German descent in every ward and election district have to organize in such manner that their sheer number will be proof of their influence in any election. The leaders of the two major political parties will then have to pay attention to the wishes of this organization as far as political problems are concerned."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
