<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1884-01-02">January 2, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">From the North Side.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0834</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0834.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1884-01-02">January 2, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE NORTH SIDE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Socialist club of the North side held its agitation meeting last Saturday night, at which Comrade Schnaubelt presided. Comrade Wilhelm Lange reviewed in short the important happenings of last week. He said: "It is regrettable that the oppressed people of Ireland are still strong believers of the church, as it was evident at the demonstration of the Catholic church there.</p>
   <p>Instead of annihilating the disgraceful contrivers of oppression, the priests recommend thanking "God" for everything received, slavery included, and the flock does not perceive that it is this black-robed riff-raff of humanity who joining the oppressors, are responsible for existing conditions". He then spoke of Germany and condemned the ways of the Frankfort police during the funeral of our deceased Comrade Rudolf Doll who, throughout his life fought valiantly for the interests of the proletariat.</p>
   <p>Then he spoke of the Socialist Labor party's Congress at Baltimore regretting that they still expect salvation from the election nuisance, (When everybody else is convinced to the contrary) but hopes, that enlightenment will come to those men too.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0835.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"It is pleasant to report on the wide-spread sale of Henry George's work "Progress and Poverty'! That a good deal of propaganda has been spread with this popular writing among farmers, especially in Texas as is shown by the shouts of the Chicago "Times".</p>
   <p>Comrade Lange concluded by reproaching the Staats Zeitung for stirring up feeling against the Irish, and remarked that it was up to us to take stand against a few of the good-for-nothing Irish; branding the oppressors and enemies of the people.</p>
   <p>It was decided therefore, to instruct the delegates to the general committee, to join the Socialists of the North-west side in calling an Irish and German mass meeting to protest against such intolerance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0836.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The new club has a membership of 27 already. As there was no other business on the calendar the meeting was postponed till next Sunday on which day Gen. Reiser is going to speak.</p>
   <p>Let's hope that all members, their friends and their women folks will be present in order to increase the number of fighters."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
