<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-07-26">July 26, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">[Socialist Meeting Report]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0933</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0933.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-07-26">July 26, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">[SOCIALIST MEETING REPORT]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Southern Section called by their Agent of the German party met Sundat at the store of member Schmitt on 25th Street near Portland Avenue. Member teacher Schaf was chairman. Mr. Franz Franz and H. Schmitt were elected as department chiefs, the first as Assistant agent, the latter as financial secretary.</p>
   <p>There followed an interesting argument about the newspapers of the party and their attitude to the present position. All speakers especially member Bartells, Schmitt, and the Chairman pointed out that all workers who take their membership honestly and seriously should support the party newspapers to the fullest extent. This is the more necessary as only by their own Press can the interests of the working men be brought to the notice of the public. Only by publications in the workingmen's Press can the necessary explanations which are needed by the public be given. This will assist the public to recognize Political fraud and to protect <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0934.jpg" n="2"/>themselves against it. Only endurance, love and fidelity to the cause of the disinherited will bring results and make evolution possible. In this direction our local party Press has established itself for which reason it should be able to count on the full support of all just thinking persons.</p>
   <p>All present agreed to be active in the future in that direction and that they will assist in the best possible development and largest circulation of the Workmen's local Press, "Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung", the "Fackel" and "Vorbote."</p>
   <p>The Chairman announced that the former organizer, Mr. Morgan, who has been very active organizing the Greenback Labor Party in the 5th ward has held a speech lately advocating their cause and also has induced his friends, the singer, Creech, to publish a song of praise for them.</p>
   <p>The members present declared their indignation against this action of a so-called Socialist and the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
