<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-08-18">August 18, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting on the Northwest Side.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0891</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0891.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-08-18">August 18, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING ON THE NORTHWEST SIDE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A well attended agitation meeting was held yesterday evening at Nutzhorn's Hall. Michale Schwab presided.</p>
   <p>Comrade Spies gave a short weekly report; Comrade Grottkau delivered a rather long and well thought-out speech about labor politics in contrast to politics of all other parties. He pointed out that the bourgeois in the economically, most progressive countries pursues only one aim, that of exploration and has only one point in mind - to secure its property. The bourgeois is not interested in progress, for he has no ideals. Therefore, the working man cannot identify himself with any party, which considers private property a justified and sacred thing. Their interests are of such conflicting nature that no clear thinking person could attempt to unite them.</p>
   <p>Mr. Grottkau was applauded for his speech. The following resolutions were accepted: In consideration of the well-known occurence on String street a few days ago where the police ill-treated our citizens, brutalized decent and upright working women and made a number of arrests, we have decided to give utterance to our disgust as to the ways our "order and peace preserving guardians" are exercising their duties, and we declare it an act of cowardice on <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0892.jpg" n="2"/>the part of a people to suffer such degradation without protest. Decided: That we, the citizens of this community, will not respect laws which are entitling one individual to ride rough-shod over the rights of others and we will do our utmost to contribute to the removal of such laws. The meeting's large attendance was a sign that the expulsion of Sievers and his henchmen, was the only course to be taken to induce honest and decent people to again come to our meetings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
