<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-10-24">October 24, 1876</date><title level="a">The German Congressional Candidate, Lorenz Brentano, to the Editor of the Staats-Zeitung.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-10-24">October 24, 1876</date><title level="a">THE GERMAN CONGRESSIONAL CANDIDATE, LORENZ BRENTANO, TO THE EDITOR OF THE STAATS-ZEITUNG.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republican voters of the third congressional district are looking forward proudly and with confidence to their candidate's election.</p>
   <p>And in that they are truly justified, because Mr. Brentano is a man of an untouchable character, perfect education and ability, known everywhere for his devotion to liberty, and the greatest courteousness to his friends.</p>
   <p>Endowed with such qualities this old active fighter for liberty, the first German congressional candidate in our city, certainly does not need any recommendation to our German fellow citizens, to insure him the unanimous vote and undivided influence of his countrymen.</p>
   <p>Still I think it my duty to remind you of the period when I had the honor to represent, together with our candidate, the German element on the Chicago School <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1679.jpg" n="2"/>Board, and especially of the memorable May 16, 1865, when Mr. Brentano after a hard and unceasing battle obtained the nomination of a committee charged with making a report - on the "advisability to introduce German instruction into the Public Schools of the city". Mr. Brentano was chairman of this committee, and thanks to his well-chosen arguments in the report, which was read at the next meeting, this discipline was temporarily estalished at the Washington School.</p>
   <p>With what faithfulness and self-sacrifice Mr. Brentano has fought through long years for the preservation of this right, and for the further and permanent introduction of the German language in our public schools, you all well know. It is remarkable, and that Mr. Brentano in spite of his everlasting attempts to satisfy the demands of his German fellow-citizens, has through his excellent qualities been able to gain the respect and the confidence of his non-German and in some cases anti-German colleagues, in such measure, that after a short period in office he was promoted to the Presidency of the School Board. This position he has managed with complete success down to the time of his retirement.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1680.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Brentano has been active also and prominent in other circles, but through his attempts and successes in the indicated direction he has made himself particularly well deserved for the Germans in our city, and we should show him a small part of our recognition by lending him our support and our votes at the common election.</p>
   <p>Yours truly,</p>
   <p>Hermann Felsenthal.</p>
   <p>Chicago, 23 October, 1876.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
