<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-10-20">Oct. 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Beginnings of Religious Intolerance and Persecution.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-10-20">Oct. 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">BEGINNINGS OF RELIGIOUS INTOLERANCE AND PERSECUTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For Several years, semi-secret societies have been agitating in our midst. They pretend to attack, first of all, Catholicism, but they are fighting equality or the equal rights of foreign-born citizens.</p>
   <p>Shortly before the school controversy arose in Illinois, we reported a letter received by a respectable German Protestant clergyman, which revealed the fact that even among the non-Catholic Germans those secret societies carry on their activities. That Protestant German clergyman was even then aware, that the pretext of aiming at Catholics only, was merely a cloak for the real purpose, namely, to fight all immigrants, irrespective of their religious affiliations. He knew the history of the Know-Nothing movement during the fifties. The latest Know-Nothing movement not only attacks the civil rights of Catholic citizens of this country, but interferes also with their private business.</p>
   <p>There is our fellow-citizen, a German in Chicago, H. Detmer, who manages a piano store in the Schiller Theater Building. Detmar is a Catholic.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0603.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He is friendly, and eager to help everybody, and has been generous also toward non-Catholic charitable institutions.</p>
   <p>Some time ago he rented a piano to a local club. The instrument was very satisfactory, and the club decided to purchase one from Mr. Detmar. A piano was selected and delivered after the transaction was completed... At a meeting of the club the decision was made to return the unpaid piano, because Detmar is a Catholic. Since the sale was black on white, Detmar could have refused to take it bakc, but he acted magnanimously.</p>
   <p>It was revealed that the club, returning the instrument because Detmar was a Catholic, belongs to the Know-Nothing movement of the Patriotic Sons of America...</p>
   <p>But we have not only the Patriotic Sons of America. Detmar recently had an experience with the Patriotic Daughters. A certain club wanted to rent a piano from him. A woman was sent to make the necessary arrangements. Finally the woman told the clerk, "We are convinced that Detmar is a Catholic, and that he engages Catholics only in his store." The clerk replied <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0604.jpg" n="3"/>truthfully: "Detmar is a Catholic, that is true; but when he engages any one in his business, he does not inquire about religious or political affiliations, and at the present, Detmar is the only Catholic in his business."</p>
   <p>The woman retorted: "Since Detmar is a Catholic, the club can not consider either the purchase, or the renting of a piano." It is needless to say that the renting of a piano was not carried out. This intolerant woman was a member of the Patriotic Daughters of America.</p>
   <p>And such happenings are possible in the cosmopolitan city of Chicago, whose marvelous development can be credited primarily to the cooperation of the different nationalities, irrespective of their religious faiths!</p>
   <p>It is estimated by those who should know that the membership of these intolerant societies has increased to 60,000 in Chicago and Illinois alone. To the many Germans, who once belonged to the party of the noble A. Lincoln, it is indeed painful to know that these intolerant and persecuting persons are active within the Republican party.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0605.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The hatred of these recent Know-Nothings is directed with equal vehemence against the German Lutherans, and other German Protestants, as well as against Catholics, ever since the school controversy started in Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
