<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-29">Dec. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Mayoral Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1156</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1156.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-29">Dec. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAYORAL ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Various movements are beginning to be noticed in local polities. The Republicans cast their eyes everywhere for a candidate for the office of mayor who would make a good impression upon the citizens, and whom the organization could trust. Speaking of Republican candidates for mayor, one cannot avoid mentioning, in accordance with tradition, William Hale Thompson, who for three successive terms led the party to victory. Whether Thompson is going to be a candidate is not yet known. In keeping with his habits, he surrounds himself with deep and ominous silence.</p>
   <p>The only Republican who, until now, has announced his candidacy is the attorney, Emil C. Wetten. He has elaborated an extensive platform which he submitted to the press a few weeks ago. Besides, Arthur F. Albert is <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1157.jpg" n="2"/>mentioned. Albert is of German descent. For almost ten years he represented the 43rd ward in the city council, and was known as the most pugnacious and ablest of Thompson's opponents in the council. It has been reported that his friends have already circulated petitions for his nomination. He has, however, not expressed himself as yet as to whether he will accept the candidacy or reject it.</p>
   <p>The Republicans are compelled to conduct their campaign with an organization which is quite scattered and, owing to the grave defeats of recent years, quite demoralized. They need more offices, and, for that, also money; for without money no campaign can be conducted as it should be. The Democratic party is in a very favorable situation. The leader of the Democrats, Pat Nash, has succeeded in holding the organization together and although many of the candidates for county offices expressed their dissatisfaction in the beginning, they nevertheless submitted to the will of his leadership. Thus, they entered their campaign with closed ranks with the result that they <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1158.jpg" n="3"/>gained a victory on the entire front.</p>
   <p>Now, the Democrats appeared before the public with their ticket for municipal elections. As was generally expected, the present mayor, Edward J. Kelly, is at the top of the ticket. Needless to mention that the Democrats could not find a better candidate. Mayor Kelly, who was elected Anton Cermak's successor by the city council, achieved a great deal during his last term. Let us only be reminded that the city's finances were scattered when Thompson abandoned the scene of his activities. The finances of the city's administration, of the board of education, and of the county were in a deplorable state, and taxes climed to unheard-of heights.</p>
   <p>The financial condition of these institutions is today quite satisfactory, even though the taxes have been considerably reduced. This is, so far as the city administration and board of education are concerned, primarily due to the efforts of Mayor Kelly. It seems that this is also generally credited <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1159.jpg" n="4"/>to him, because strong and influential citizens' groups, which had otherwise nothing to do with politics, declared their readiness to support Mayor Kelly's candidature to the full. As a candidate for the office of city clerk, Peter J. Brady, was nominated by the organization; he is the present incumbent of that office.</p>
   <p>The present administration has shown ample consideration for the German population of the city in the filling of political offices. The heads of the organization had the desire to see a German-American on the city's ticket. That is why they turned to Gustave A. Brand, who has been active in the German movement for many years and, as president of the German Day Organization, has done a good job in every respect. Mr. Brand declared himself ready to accept the candidacy for office of city treasurer. The character and career of Mr. Brand are sufficient assurance that the choice could not be a better one. It is certain that Mr. Brand's candidacy will be received most favorably in German circles. The endorsement of this ticket on the part of the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1160.jpg" n="5"/>Democratic organization took place at a brief session which proceeded harmoniously and almost without debate. Thus the primaries will become a mere matter of form for the Democrats. It is quite certain, even now, that the ticket will be approved by an overwhelming majority of the Democratic voters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
