<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-10-09">Oct. 9, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Where Are the Agitators?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-10-09">Oct. 9, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">WHERE ARE THE AGITATORS?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As known to everybody, Mr. Hermann Raster invented the title "agitating bums" for the sacrifices of the judicial murder of November 11th, which invention gave him so much fun that he tries to apply this title whenever possible.</p>
   <p>In his use of language today, therefore, everybody is an "agitating bum" who is not convinced that we live nowadays in the best of all worlds, and that the ideal relation between capital and labor can by no means be interrupted. Such people should receive every morning, 25 strokes on the back; until, finally, suitable laws have been passed, so that they can be sunk in the ocean -where it is deepest.</p>
   <p>Our cozy Mr. Raster was therefore overjoyed when the infamous Merritt law was passed. This law was aimed entirely at the bad "agitating bums" who stir people up to all kinds of forceful deeds and thereby give a reason for more slaughters after the example of November 11th. A fine feeling for a great patriot of Mr. Raster's kind.</p>
   <p>But the story has two sides. Under present conditions, the workers do not even consider the use of force, because they know that the enemy is still <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0250.jpg" n="2"/>superior in this line and they realize therefore that the application of force would only demand sacrifices without showing any worth while gains.</p>
   <p>This is different with the reigning classes. Their system is one of "blood and iron." They have the power in their hands, they keep up the present system through force only, and they have shown not once but hundreds of times that they stand firm in their determination to use force also in the future. Therefore the Merritt law should become dangerous, especially to the reigning classes, providing it is applied correctly.</p>
   <p>But as things are not done right and laws only founded to be used in favor of the dominating gang of robbers against the working class, there is no reason to be afraid, that any of these sovereigns in power will ever get into trouble on account of the aforesaid law. Still, it is necessary from time to time to nail down publicly the activities of our adversaries - if only in order to show the disinterested public on which side the genuine "agitating bums" actually are.</p>
   <p>Today Mr. Raster shows himself again in such a role in regards to the car strike, and he does it in such a way, that it can only be explained by assuming that this gentleman stayed in the well known saloon on Fifth Avenue too late again yesterday.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0251.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For Mr. Raster proposes to declare the horse-drawn street cars in big cities as postal routes, so that in case of strike the regular army could be used against strikers. Mr. Raster wants to use the army,as in contrast to the uniformed store clerks who call themselves militia, the regulars do not shoot holes in the air but send their bullets where they are most useful, directly into the masses of the striking workers.</p>
   <p>If this is not agitation then we do not know at all what we can understand as agitation. The government is being asked to send troops against striking car employees and the troops themselves are asked not to shoot in the air but into the masses of workers.</p>
   <p>And this from the same Mr. Raster who cries himself hoarse for whips and gallows when somebody says that the social question cannot definitely be solved by the sprinkling of some rose water. Of course it would be only a few hundreds or a few thousands of hungry workers who would eventually be sacrificed to the bullets of the troops and these workers are but criminals who demand higher wages or shorter working hours. The sending away from this world of such "canaille" would serve to make things quiet again for imperiled capital.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0252.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>How, then, if the present strike should develop in such a way that the government would see fit to give in to Raster's demands and send regular army troops to Chicago? Considering Mr. Roche's provocative attitude, a thing like that is not impossible at all. And when the soldiers would kill so and so many of the workers? - Would the state's attorney then be ready to indict Mr. Raster on account of the Merritt law for "accessory to murder," and could a jury then be elected that would sentence our honorable fellow citizen to die on the gallows?</p>
   <p>Of course not, as Mr. Raster is only agitating in the interest of the dominant class, and against workers; and there he is naturally right! The big robbers must be protected even if it is by mountains of workers' corpses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
