<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-05-21">May 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[Religion and Labor]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-05-21">May 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[RELIGION AND LABOR]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Editor of the Abendpost:</p>
   <p>The article by "One from the ranks of the workers" touches upon a very important matter. Similar molestations of workers by radical union men in European factories led to the union of all workers who wish to prevent having the union movement used as a tool by antireligious persecutors. Union men who favor the Christian religion could not tolerate the shameless attacks which were made upon their religious convictions by the trade journals and organization publications which they helped to establish and maintain. Railroaders and miners started the organization of those who opposed the antireligious tyranny of the radicals. Before the war, the Christian Association of Miners in Germany had a membership of more than 100,000. Soon the Christian Union of Workers was organized and the number of charter members was over 350,000. More than a million Christian workers <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0131.jpg" n="2"/>were represented at the second convention of the Christian Union. Christian organizations in Italy, Switzerland, Holland, Belgium, and Austria joined with those in Germany and formed the International Association of Christian Unions. In many areas these societies are so strong that no strike is successful without their co-operation. It is advisable that Protestant, Catholic, and Jewish unions of Chicago meet to discuss an eventual merger in order to counteract the antireligious activity in individual organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
