<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-04-15">April 15,1892</date>.
<title level="a">Lutherans Protest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-04-15">April 15,1892</date>.
<title level="a">LUTHERANS PROTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>German Lutherans have protested energetically against methods and means, whereby they are abused for political purposes. A definite and emphatic declaration against this abuse will be forthcoming soon.</p>
   <p>The politicians, indeed, have of late embarrassed and vexed the German Lutheran voters. Politicians, who two years ago were drastically unconcerned about the opinions of Lutherans in regard to their candidates, and the same politicians who insulted the Lutherans, calling them enemies of public schools, are now overflowing with endearing terms for "our German fellow citizens." They are exceedingly anxious to scrutinize the attitude of the Lutherans in regard to the one or the other candidate, and with political shrewdness they make their decisions against certain candidates, if they think their respective nomination is against the wishes of the Lutherans.</p>
   <p>Why are they so exceedingly anxious? When in 1890 the Lutherans elected H. Raab with a majority of 36,000 votes, they demonstrated to the Republicans what the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1531.jpg" n="2"/>party is without them. It was natural, of course, that the Republicans took this matter to heart.</p>
   <p>This, undoubtedly, met with the approval of the Lutherans. The overwhelming majority of the Lutherans are no more involved in political machinations than any good citizen should be, but they were deeply concerned to have the school controversy settled. The Democrats had proven their friendship in time of need, and it was therefore logical that the Lutherans turned to them first. When, however, the Republicans suddenly changed their attitude all along the line and promised to amend their ways and be helpful, it was up to the Lutherans to decide which one of the two parties would be more reliable, and could be more readily depended upon definitely to remove the evil.</p>
   <p>This situation was exploited by the politicians, and each one claimed that he alone was able to obtain the votes of the Lutherans. Fifer's enemy declared the Governor's unpopularity among the German Republicans to be a sufficient reason against his nomination. At this time the candidacy of Judge Collins was announced and it was said he was able to lead the Lutherans back into the camp of the Republicans.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1532.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The fact of the matter was that the Lutherans had not decided for or against any of the candidates, including Fifer, Altgeld, and Collins, although Collins was agreeable to all Germans, because of his liberal viewpoint. For the Lutherans it was not a battle for personalities, but for principles; it was not a question of nominating this or that man, but to thoroughly abolish the compulsory school law.</p>
   <p>Now the Lutherans must know from experience that there are certain people, who pretend to speak for them, but who have no authority to so do, who publicly in ward meetings dicker for their vote and openly announce the candidates who can have the votes and who not.</p>
   <p>An eminent German stated last night: "Nobody has a right to speak for the Lutherans. We fight for a principle, and not for this or that candidate".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
