<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-17">Feb. 17, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Plans for Democratic Convention.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bring Resolutions and Indorsements in Favor of Washington Hesing.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1468</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1468.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-17">Feb. 17, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">PLANS FOR DEMOCRATIC CONVENTION.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bring Resolutions And Indorsements In Favor Of Washington Hesing.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Democratic convention will be held on February 28th, at Central Music Hall. This resolution, which originated with the executives of the Democratic party, a salutory proposal it must be conceded, gives sufficient guarantee that the convention will be orderly and civilly managed and this surely conforms to the interests of both candidates.</p>
   <p>Wild scenes and fights will be dispensed with; no repetition of the last County convention proceedings will mar the occasion in this instance, because only the actual delegates and members of the press will be admitted, while guests must show their tickets before entering the gallery. The plots of certain statesmen, whereby the convention was to be in the Battery D Hall, went awry.</p>
   <p>The imported clique and stentorian bellowers who were to create sentiment for Harrison, find themselves shelved, but the respectable element of the party, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1469.jpg" n="2"/>which desires to see a candidate nominated, -the delegates of well-nigh 100,000 voters, - may feel well appeased. Another little scheme, which the fixers of the Harrison campaign concocted, was exposed to daylight yesterday, just in time to spoil the mess.</p>
   <p>The proponents of this somewhat involved Machiavellian method, contemplated the following: McGillen, candidate for treasurer, was to be given support by the Harrisonians on a contingency; he is the chairman of the County Central committee which will open the convention, and as such, he was to appoint a temporary chairman, a subtle, amenable man who would nominate a committee to examine the credentials of delegates; and here we finally succeed in unravelling the intricacies of the Gordian Knot: the committee would exclude the Hesing delegates.</p>
   <p>This selected and choice promoter of "Fair Play Carter", is "Black Jack" Fitzgerald, who is, incidentally, candidate for assessor of Southtown, - but that is another story.</p>
   <p>The Hesing campaign managers delved into these sinister plans yesterday. Evidently, Harrison's continuous parade of confidence does not hide the trepidation he feels in the saddle, otherwise he would not stoop to such means.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1470.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This uncertainty is understandable; one need only while away a few hours at the Hesing headquarters, Dearborn and Washington Streets, and view that continuous procession. A candidate of the Hesing caliber, who interviews 600 to 700 citizens daily, who received constant, hearty assurances from business men and politicians of all nationalities with their ardent promises of support, such a man's strength must not be underestimated. It cannot be over emphasized, that in this fight the Germans show a profound interest, in contrast to their usual phlegmatic attitude towards the primaries, and even if Mr. Hesing does not obtain the nomination (for mayor, expl.) it will nevertheless be an honorable testimonial expressing the esteem he enjoys among his compatriots.</p>
   <p>Within the next 48 hours, order will come out of chaos; active, effective organization shall rule; at the primary districts the committees will function and then, it is up to us to do our share at the ballot box. Next Saturday the election-places will be announced; by that time, also disputes will have been settled by the party leaders.</p>
   <p>The Hesing campaign managers are not able to nominate their own committees until this preliminary detail is disposed of. The Committees on Complaints, of <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1471.jpg" n="4"/>the Democratic Central Association was again in session yesterday, throughout the day. The grievances of the 1st Ward even went to the Executive Committee, which revoked the decision of the lower committee; it decided in favor of the Ward committee representatives, Leiendecker, Kenna, Gelder and Carroll. The infamous gamblers, Shakel and o'Donnell, appeared for Harrison.</p>
   <p>The demands of the Harrison representatives for the 4th and 9th Wards were upheld by the committee which so far showed thorough impartiality. In the 23rd Ward, where the fight pivots on the aldermanic question, the committee allowed Senator John F. o'Malley one judge in every primary district.</p>
   <p>Resolutions of the 24th Ward: "Resolved, in consideration of the friendship and confidence which Grover Cleveland and John P. Altgeld have in Mr. Hesing, our delegates are hereby instructed to vote for Mr. Hesing's nomination at the convention.</p>
   <p>"Resolved, that the Democrats are convinced, that the personal intercession of Mr. Washington Hesing and the influence of the Illinois Staats Zeitung have brought about the establishment of the Western Headquarters here, which in turn gave us the great western victories; that he was the recognized leader in the school fight which induced the Lutherans of the entire state to support <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1472.jpg" n="5"/>the Democrats, resulting in Altgeld's election.</p>
   <p>"Resolved, that aside from the Democratic party, thousands of Independents, Laborites, and Republicans, will vote for Washington Hesing. All friends of a free conscience are grateful to him; the advocates of Open Sundays for the World's Fair' consider him a leader while Labor recognizes his attitude towards just demands and unionism, as well as his emphatic sympathy for the Homestead (Pa.) strikers, and his unselfish valuable support of the Executive Clemency movement (verbatim: amnesty) for Neebe, Schwab and Fielden. (Explanation: Haymarket riot.)</p>
   <p>"Althouth an American by birth, he was always intimately associated with everything pertaining to the German cause, and acted as a definite bulwark against the teetotalers. In recognition of his valiant service in the field of education he obtained a large following. As a reform advocate he has done much towards the acceptance and improvement of our present Australian election laws. He agitated for a municipalization of the gas trust, for improvements and so forth.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1473.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"Resolved, that we recognize in Mr. Hesing a man who is endowed with intrinsic knowledge, universal, worldly experience in European and American affairs and conditions, who because of his linguistic abilities is particularly capable of expressing our city's hospitality to the visitors; likewise he shows a true recognition of the various separate national groups which further the interests of our city. In one word, we declare that we consider him the ideal World's Fair mayor and that Chicago honors itself when it gives honor to Washington Hesing."</p>
   <p>The German Democratic Club of the 33rd Ward decided unanimously in favor of Hesing's nomination.... The assembly represented business and labor elements.</p>
   <p>A mass meeting of all German Democratic Club members is scheduled for this evening at Orpheus Hall, to make them more conversant with their impending duties on election day.</p>
   <p>The German Democrats of the 15th Ward elected the following officials: A. H. Bertram, president; and five others. The club will hold its next meeting on February 20th, at Turner Hall, Hammond and Railroad Avenues. The <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1474.jpg" n="7"/>15th Ward organized a German-Democratic Citizen's Club last Wednesday evening... Sentiment is very strong for Hesing----</p>
   <p>A meeting of 300,12th Ward Democrats at the Oakley and Polk Street Hall was unanimously in favor of Hesing....</p>
   <p>About 300 Democrats of the 32nd Ward met at Oxford Hall. An attempt to indorse Harrison was frustrated and it was resolved to send uninstructed delegates to the convention.</p>
   <p>The Cab Drivers' union, at its Monroe St. meeting, indorsed Hesing....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
