<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-02-20">Feb. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Mayoral Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1324</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1324.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-02-20">Feb. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAYORAL ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Party politics should really not enter municipal elections at all and party-political problems and inclinations should not play any part whatever in these elections, because the only thing that matters here is to elect good judges and competent officials and aldermen who know the city's needs and are capable, and willing to work for the city's further progress.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, party politics will always play a decisive part in any municipal election campaign.</p>
   <p>National party politics are in some way reflected in local elections, although the latter, like the pending municipal election here in Chicago, have no direct bearing on national party problems and the voters have to decide for themselves whether and to what extent they will let their judgment in local elections be influenced by party politics. Certainly they are under no compulsion to be so <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1325.jpg" n="2"/>influenced, and it seems the prudent thing to do for voters who are concerned with the welfare of their city not to give too much consideration to national politics in the coming election. They will serve their city and themselves best, by letting the following considerations be their guide: Which candidate promises to make the best official; which of the candidates comes closest to our own idea as to how a municipality should be governed and administered; and, how can a homogenous population element [the German] best prove its political significance.</p>
   <p>Under these circumstances, the election of Robert M. Sweitzer, Democratic candidate for Mayor, seems advised, in the interest of the city and in the interest of the German element of Chicago, because Sweitzer's business record and business success prove him to be a diligent and outstandingly efficient and conscientious worker; that is the kind of man our city needs. Besides, Sweitzer is of German blood, he wants to be looked upon as the German candidate for mayor and will be considered by the non-German population of Chicago as the candidate sponsored by the majority of Chicago's Germans, whether he will win or lose in the primary election. Sweitzer's defeat will be advertised as a German defeat or, at <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1326.jpg" n="3"/>best, as a proof that German disunity in this country is still in evidence, notwithstanding all the wonderful exhortations for unity and all the enticing descriptions of influence and power which this unity would bring to the German-Americans.</p>
   <p>Under those circumstances it is unfortunate that Alderman Jacob A. Hey is seeking the Republican nomination for mayor. We are afraid that he will not be able to obtain a majority, but he will win over many German Republicans, who otherwise would disregard national party politics and, to accentuate their Deutschtum, would give their votes to the German Democratic candidate Sweitzer, who stands an excellent chance to win the nomination.</p>
   <p>Jacob Hey is an efficient man, well versed in municipal administration and legislation, and a good German. He would make an ideal candidate and could well be glad of his decision to seek the Republican nomination, if there wasn't the probability that he might be defeated in the primaries, thanks to the power of the organizations that are backing his opponents, and thanks to the fact that <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1327.jpg" n="4"/>he turned "progressive" at the last minute and thereby offended his party comrades. But we are afraid he will take many German votes from the German Democratic candidate who could use them to advantage.</p>
   <p>In this case, the good German Hey would have rendered a poor service to the German element and the city would have lost a chance to get a mayor, whose whole career would be a guarantee for a diligent and promising official, and would have safeguarded Hearst's continuous influence on the city's administration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
