<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-09-16">Sep. 16, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Against Anarchism.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-09-16">Sep. 16, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">AGAINST ANARCHISM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The population of the United States consists of persons and families, who left their fatherland to improve their economic conditions for themselves and their children, and this self improvement becomes their motive power......</p>
   <p>What right have the anarchists to think that they can depend upon German workers and German unions? The anarchists demand the abolition of private property and deny to owners of production facilities and business leaders the right to exist as such. They are of the opinion that any kind of work is of equal value, and that the personal acquisition and accumulation of capital wealth must be prohibited.</p>
   <p>But no intelligent man believes such theories, which are entirely contrary to our present form of civilization. Alleged publications for workers containing such absurdities should be treated as a fire brand and destroyed at once by the German public. Anarchists are no German world reformers, and they can not consistently point to Carl Marx and F. LaSalle as their predecessors.</p>
   <p>Employees and employers are not of necessity mutual enemies, as the anarchists <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0619.jpg" n="2"/>try to make people believe. The worker, as well as the industrialist, are actually sustained and enriched by the consuming public.... In this age of inventions and discoveries the large industrialists find it necessary to combine, and the masses of workers unite to strengthen their position.</p>
   <p>But this is not a sufficient reason, however, to mutually fight and injure each other. Employers and wage earners must discover ways and means of supplementing and of assisting one another for the welfare and progress of men in general. The associations of industrialists and the trade unions should appoint a conference committee to discuss mutual affairs and to iron out disagreements or to relegate them to a board of arbitration. This is their duty toward the public.</p>
   <p>The masses of workers should be enlightened in order to use their power to vote as well as their liberty to organize to a better advantage. The wealthy as well as the educated should not think it beneath their dignity to cooperate for the intellectual emancipation of the workers from prejudices and dangerous delusions. This may require some money and time, but it is worth while.</p>
   <p>The economic welfare of the German skilled workers, as well as the steadily increasing middle class of Germans in Chicago demand imperatively the cessation of anarchistic agitation. This can be achieved only, if the Germans take a real <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0620.jpg" n="3"/>interest in the urgent problems of today, and pay out of their own pockets the expenses for renting halls, etc. It is deplorable that the impoverished office holders and the political job hunters have been compelled to pay all expenses for party politics.</p>
   <p>Under such conditions the political potency of the Germans could not exert itself, therefore the weeds of anarchism prospered and made Germanism contemptuous. Anarchism is entirely un-German.... A lively agitation about the high tariff, and about the political system of indirect taxation, as well as a discussion of practical methods of improving the relationship between capital and labor, would in a very short time dispose of the anarchistic spooks in the minds of the people, and the wasteful, destructive disturbances of labor would cease. The Chicago Turngemeinde (Athletic Club) should make a beginning by calling a meeting for mental gymnastics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
