<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-05-22">May 22, 1892</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0211</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0211.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-05-22">May 22, 1892</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Having failed in their test of strength with the newspaper publishers, the striking German compositors are reported to be resorting to the boycott." They call, it is said on all labor unions in Chicago and on all business-men to assist them. They claim that had to resist an attempted reduction of their wages, and that the life of their organization was at stake. The letter addressed by the publishers to Typographia No. 9 contained in substance the following propositions:</p>
   <p>The German compositors were to retain the eight-hour day, and the alphabetical system, and their union was to be recognized as having equal rights with the association of publishers. The tariff of the Typographical Union No. 16 was to be accepted-that is the tariff agreed upon by all the English papers, and nine-tenths of the compositors of Chicago. The difference between the "running" of German and English type was to be equalized by an addition of two cents per 1,000 ems to the English scale of wages, and by giving the "fat" of all advertisements to the German compositors.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0212.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The publishers declared themselves willing to submit to arbitration. Typographia No. 9 refused to arbitrate and struck at once. The publishers were not to have the right to make any propositions at all. Unconditional surrender was the request of Typographia No. 9.</p>
   <p>The publishers of the German papers affected by the strike are willing, they say, to submit their case to an impartial investigation. If it can be proven that they gave their compositors provocation to strike, they declare their willingness to bear all the consequences.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
