<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-04-18">Apr. 18, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Indian Socialists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0907</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0907.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-04-18">Apr. 18, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">INDIAN SOCIALISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The majority of our Indians are in accord with the white man's doctrine of Socialism, inasmuch as the question of land possession enters the picture. The Indians adhere to the belief that land is the property of the nation, and no one individual can claim the right to it. This is also the opinion of the civilized Cherokee Indians of the Indian territory who are opposing the Minister of the Interior, Mr. Schurz's recommendation, that the land thus far owned by the Indian nation or Indian tribe should be divided among the individual members of the Indian nation.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bushyhead, the present chieftain of the Cherokee tribe, expressed himself thus, in an open letter to the white people: "If we were to consent to private land ownership, it would be but a short time before the whole district would be under the control of only a few. In consequence, our poor would not own a foot of ground in which to bury them, as is so often the case with you white people. If that, to which your urgent invitation is extended us, is called civilization, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0908.jpg" n="2"/>it should not be at all surprising that we feel skeptical about the good results of that unrepublican (sic) system. From time immemorial our people were taught, that the earth was here for the benefit of everyone and was never meant to be commercialized. The Indians are neither Socialists nor Communists, but they do have a land system far superior to anything you could recommend. We do respect individual rights, but not to the extent of sacrificing the right of the nation. Give us a chance to go on with the execution of our plans, and you do likewise, and then compare the results."</p>
   <p>It is obvious that Mr. Bushyhead, does not like to be regarded as either a Socialist or a Communist, notwithstanding the fact that he is a stronger believer in either of the two doctrines than any of his Caucasian opponents of private ownership of land. He condemns private land ownership, although this continuation of Indian policy by Mr. Schurz, would provide every member of an Indian tribe with large farm lands. It may be pointed out on this occasion that, in contrast to the Redskins, there are many Socialists and <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0909.jpg" n="3"/>Communists belonging to the white race, whose policy of hatred for private land ownership would instantly disappear and their political viewpoint would assume a different character at the prospect of the offer of free land.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
