<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-18">Mar. 18, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Stonecutters' Strike Involving the City Hall</title><title level="a" type="sub">What They Have to Say</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0308</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0308.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-18">Mar. 18, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE STONECUTTERS' STRIKE INVOLVING THE CITY HALL</title><title level="a" type="sub">What They Have to Say</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A committee of the Stonecutters' Union, consisting of Messrs. Heinrich Sonne-born and Otto Schanzenbach, visited our editorial staff yesterday, and asked for the correction of certain erroneous reports, in English language newspapers, about the strike involving the City Hall (now under construction) and the contracting firm of Tomlinson and Reed.</p>
   <p>The first statement was that the Union does not pay the striking members $2.50 per day, as reported; only one dollar per day is given to married men, and single workers receive only enough to defray board and laundry bills. Our informants also said that Tomlinson and Reed did not pay two dollars per day last year, but only $1.25 to $1.50. In November, after the reorganization of the Union, the firm paid two dollars a day for three weeks, and then work was suspended.</p>
   <p>Stonecutters have worked on an average of eight hours per day for the last <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0309.jpg" n="2"/>twelve or thirteen years. It is hard, exhausting labor, and only a few men can work longer than eight hours. All other cut stone contractors are satisfied with the eight-hour period; only Tomlinson and Reed are not. Furthermore, cut stone contractors are willing to pay $2.50 for a day's work. Tomlinson and Reed have no reason to pay less, since they have not signed a disadvantageous contract. Besides, just as much work will be performed in eight hours as in ten.</p>
   <p>The stonecutters are not making unfair demands; they can work only seven or, at most, eight months a year; they must provide their own tools, costing from fifty to sixty dollars, and keep them in proper condition, which cost at least twenty dollars a year. Aside from that, apprenticeship lasts four to five years before the worker can command the full wage.</p>
   <p>The committee asked us to interview some stonecutters to corroborate the aforesaid. We complied, and every statement was verified. Mr. Henne, of Boldenweck and Henne, for instance, told our reporter that their best <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0310.jpg" n="3"/>worker, who is always given a job if the weather permits, earned only $470 last year. The stone dealers are all in favor of the eight-hour day, because it is believed that more work is actually produced in eight hours than in ten. The work is very strenuous and fatiguing, so that only exceptionally strong people can continue for longer periods. Besides, the foremen gain more time to prepare the work, make plans, and order stone.</p>
   <p>It appears, accordingly, that the strike at Tomlinson and Reed's is fairly justified, as not only the stonecutters, but also other stone contractors, approve it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
