<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-11">Apr. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Bolshevist Dreams (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-11">Apr. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">BOLSHEVIST DREAMS (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to a well-known anecdote, Rothschild of Frankfurt (Germany) was visited by two ragamuffins who introduced themselves as Communists, and demanded that he share his wealth with the people.</p>
   <p>"I agree," said the "king of finance". "My wealth amounts to 90,000,000 florins (approximately $37,800,000). Germany has 45,000,000 inhabitants, so each person will receive two florins."</p>
   <p>Thereupon he gave each of his dumbfounded visitors a two-florin note, saying: "This is your share. Please send the other 44,999,998 to me. I know what I owe the people."</p>
   <p>In these days while Bolshevism aims its propaganda at nations which it may <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0523.jpg" n="2"/>devour, its more or less sincere advocates are often heard to declare that all poverty would vanish and a nation of wealthy people would inhabit the country if the masses were to take possession of our national resources and all private fortunes to operate the means of production and distribute the wealth according to communistic principles. And many who listen to their ravings, see themselves riding about in luxurious limousines, dressed in the latest Parisian styles, owning palatial residences, and seated at tables loaded with all manner of delicacies. With prospects of such an easy life, anyone would want to be a Bolshevik. However, anyone who assumes that the leaders of such movements are not aware of the utter impossibility of carrying out the plans which they outline to the gullible, completely underestimates their intelligence. The number of those who are poor is so much greater than that of the wealthy, that an equal distribution of all wealth would deprive a small percentage of the population of great riches, but would change the economic condition of the masses but very little.</p>
   <p>It is generally admitted that the United States has proportionately more <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0524.jpg" n="3"/>wealth than any other country in the world. Now suppose we assume that a revolution here was successful, that the new social order was established without harming existing values or disturbing industry or commerce, and that the property equalization had been effected. According to the latest available estimate, the national wealth of the United States was $187,739,071,090 in 1912. This sum includes all landed property (taxable and nontaxable), agricultural implements, machinery, animals, bullion, tools, railways and their operating materials, public conveyances, canals, ships, waterworks, telephone and telegraph plants, lighting plants, factories, manufactured merchandise, furniture, clothing, jewelry, etc. According to the last census there are 105,118,467 inhabitants in the United States.</p>
   <p>Simple arithmetic proves that on the basis of the above figures, each person in the United States, man, woman, or child, would be entitled to $1,785.98, or its equivalent. Of course, it is supposed that the United States and all its constituents would repudiate all property debts and that the property could be converted into cash without loss of value. This sum, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0525.jpg" n="4"/>$1,785.98, is not to be scorned; without a doubt it is more money than most of the recipients have ever possessed. But if anyone thinks that he could squander this money, or spend it to his own advantage, he is badly mistaken. For railroads, streetcar lines, waterworks, lighting plants, telegraph and telephone plants, and many other indispensible municipal institutions must be maintained by a part of this money, as must also public charity [sic]. Nor would it be possible for one to live on the interest on this money; for at the rate of four per cent the interest would amount to only $71.43, and it is hardly possible that a higher rate of interest would be permitted under the new government. Even the most frugal person could not live on $71.43, and the sum would certainly not be sufficient to purchase a limousine, fashionable clothes, a palatial home, or imported delicacies. Thus, when analyzed carefully, the golden dreams by which the Bolsheviki would entice us vanish, and our hopes of dying as landlords shatter on the cliffs of reality. And then, too, promises must be considered in the light of the wise saying, "one who neither marries nor inherits money will remain a pauper as long as he lives."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
