<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-10-11">Oct. 11, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Advice for the Strikers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-10-11">Oct. 11, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">ADVICE FOR THE STRIKERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The strikers should, one of these evenings arrange mass meetings in all city districts and on public square, all at the same hour, and explain to the assembled public their grievances from their standpoint, free from the hateful distortions of the capitalistic press, which is friendly to monopolies.</p>
   <p>The strikers should submit the situation by way of a resolution, quiet, based on facts only, but sharply accurate, submitted to these meetings for a vote and, if accepted to the mayor and aldermen.</p>
   <p>If in this way, which could easily be done at the present, the mismanagement of the police and the street car monopolists is denounced by from 80,000 to 100,000 voters of Chicago at the same time, and if energetic <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0245.jpg" n="2"/>repressive measures by the great masses were put into action, then the pride of Mr. Yerkes and the fresh misuse of executive power in the service of capitalism would be quickly diminished. But quick action is necessary because every delay is damaging.</p>
   <p>In the long run, the victory will still be on the side of the lying, treacherous and changeable money-bag press, unless it is fought against energetically and prevented from trying to poison public opinion.</p>
   <p>The strikers must start action in this direction and not wait until others pull their chestnuts out of the fire for them.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0246.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>With what sheep-like patience the tax-payers of Chicago endure the fact that the mayor and his police-chief and the whole army of strikswindlers who are being fed by them, are being used in the service of a single company of out-of-town capitalists and against the citizens of this city.</p>
   <p>Bums and rowdies have a free hand on all streets without tracks. Yerkes is being well protected by the municipal police according to his own statement. Other citizens are being shot at by the same police in Yerkes' interests, and clubbed. This shows the equality accorded by law to the citizens of Chicago.</p>
   <p>By what right does the mayor expect that Chicago's citizens pay for the expenses of the starve-out of workers by the street car monopolists?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0247.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Against this, the workers first of all should energetically protest by demanding the recall of the policesquads.</p>
   <p>Yerkes should keep peace with the employees of the company, then no police would be necessary.</p>
   <p>And if after a simultaneous protest of a great mass meeting the police should not be recalled then there would be no other alternative left for the majority than to drive back the police even if it should cause violence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
