<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1893-03-21">Mar. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Germans in Line for Allerton.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1455</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1455.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1893-03-21">Mar. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANS IN LINE FOR ALLERTON.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>German Americans are getting into line for the Citizens ticket. There are 43,000 voters of that nationality in Chicago. Already two German Democratic Ward Clubs have passed resolutions indorsing the ticket headed by Mr. Allerton. This week a number of similar clubs in various wards will, it is expected, take like actions.</p>
   <p>Yesterday at the Citizens headquarters a great many prominent German Democrats were callers. At one time came a delegation of a dozen from the Twenty-first Ward. Among those who dropped in singly during the afternoon were Albert Weigel, delegate to the late Harrison convention, from the Thirty-first Ward; John Forst, Twentieth Ward; William Zimke, Seventh Ward; Charles Bachstein, Eighteenth Ward; William Schroder, Ninth Ward; Julius Wegman, Twenty-second Ward; George Braham, Fourth Ward. They are all Democrats but they came yesterday to declare their preference for decency in municipal affairs.</p>
   <p>Sunday evening the German-American Democratic Club of the Eighteenth Ward with a membership of 160 passed resolutions denouncing the Harrison ticket and pledging their support and influence to the citizens movement. In the Tenth <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1456.jpg" n="2"/>Ward circulars were distributed at each of the four Lutheran churches in the ward reading as follows: To the Germans of the Tenth Ward. The German Independent citizens of the Tenth Ward passed the following resolution at a meeting held March 8th, and recommended the same to the careful consideration of the citizens: Whereas Carter H. Harrison has obtained his nomination through the most corrupt means, whereas on the Democratic town as well as city ticket no representation has been given to the German citizens and not a single German has been nominated; therefore be it resolved by the Independent German citizens of the Tenth Ward not to support the so-called Democratic ticket. We call upon all German citizens and voters of the Tenth Ward who are in favor of honest primaries and who want to see honest and conscientious officials to join us. We are in favor of the independent citizens tickets and we pledge our earnest support to the same. Fred Kurt, President. Karl Knolk, Secretary.</p>
   <p>In the Eighteenth Ward, where the resolutions were passed Sunday there are 674 voters of German parentage. In the Tenth Ward there are 2,385. But not only in these wards has the feeling of hostility against the Harrison ticket been aroused. As a prominent German-American Democrat put it yesterday: The Harrison gang has slapped the Germans in the face. Out of the thirty-<pb facs="5418474_3_1_1457.jpg" n="3"/>four candidates for aldermen nominated by the so-called Democratic Party, and which are to be voted by the coming election, twenty-one are Irish-Americans, and but four Germans. The same proportion prevails in the make up of the city and town tickets. The Irish are in the saddle. The Germans have been entirely ignored.</p>
   <p>"Now the facts are that there are 4,000 voters of German parentage in Chicago against 23,578 of Irish birth. Those figures are significant. German-American voters are bound to resent the insult which has been cast upon them."</p>
   <p>As an indication of the almost universal feeling a committee of prominent German Democrats has issued a call for a meeting of active workers of their party, to be held this evening at Orpheus Hall, on Randolph Street, at which an organization in the interest of the Citizens movement will be formed. Only Democrats are invited or expected to attend. But not alone are the German Americans up and doing. The great body of men employed at the Stock Yards and in the packing houses are already at work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
