<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-12-08">Dec. 8, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">[The Haymarket Riot]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0742</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0742.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-12-08">Dec. 8, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">[THE HAYMARKET RIOT]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Tribune printed in its last Saturday's issue a lengthy article in which it accuses the Arbeiter Zeitung of its stand toward, and the approval of the use of bombs and dynamite. Of course, "under certain circumstances" the use of powder, lead, bombs, and dynamite grenades is quite justified in the eyes of the Tribune, that is when used by Pinkerton's against raging strikers. But we are of a different opinion about Pinkerton's and also about the bomb throwing of May 4th which regarded by the Tribune as the murderous instrument. The tragedy of May 4th is nothing else but an unfortunate police maneuver in which the policeman and not the anarchists for whom it was intended, lost their lives. And we also contend that had the bomb been thrown by a member of the anarchists, whose patience may have been exhausted when their guaranteed rights for freedom of meeting and freedom of speech had unjustly been interfered with by the police, it would have been done in self defense. The right to arm is not a special privilege of the capitalists but was originally instituted for the protection of democracy against the tyranny of the ruling class. Spies and his comrades were fully within their rights as the anarchists are even to this day, when on May 4th they warned the workingmen: Look about you and arm! The dealers in human flesh are appropriating all the public power, and their money can buy whole armies which at their demand would make use <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0743.jpg" n="2"/>of powder and lead and even of ropes to strangle that precious right belonging to every one namely, liberty and equality, which was established by the fathers of this republic.</p>
   <p>If Fielden had said: "strangle the stranglers of the law", would have been by far more correct, than when he said: "strangle the law".</p>
   <p>The Tribune refuses to accept the fact, that there are at least 1,000,000 men in the United States, who would be willing to work for a small wage, if employment could be found. The proverb "none is as blind as the one who refuses to see" could be properly applied to the Tribune.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
