<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-06">Dec. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Negro's Right to Work</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0430</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0430.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-06">Dec. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEGRO'S RIGHT TO WORK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every fair-minded person must admit that the Negro regiments in our victorious army are entitled to part of the glory with which our armies will soon return to our native shores. The commanders of our army have frequently praised the bravery of our colored troops and have duly recognized their accomplishments. At the same time we have reliable reports that the Negro people have done their full share in supporting the Red Cross and the Liberty Loans, and have done their patriotic duty satisfactorily by working in the mines and war industries.</p>
   <p>For these reasons our government has decided to do everything possible to bring it about that, during the ensuing period of peace, the Negroes also get their chance to work for a living. The employers are, almost without exception white <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0431.jpg" n="2"/>men, and so is the majority of their employees. During the first period of peace, with its upheavals, an aggravation of race antagonism and deep-rooted prejudice can be expected more than ever before. That the task of bringing about co-operation and a better understanding is not an easy one, can be seen from the fact that a special bureau for Negro employment has been created within the Department of Labor.</p>
   <p>This bureau has already done much good during wartime by obtaining work for Negro girls in the war industries. Moreover, meetings and public lectures were held to enlighten and educate the Negroes. But the hardest job is still ahead for the bureau when the Negro troops return home. An organization to take care of this problem has already been established by committees in six Southern and five Northern states with large Negro populations. These committees have already accomplished much by arranging meetings of white employers, white unionists and Negroes to discuss thoroughly employment problems.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0432.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Even if the race problem never is completely solved, at least a better understanding and co-operation can be brought about with a little mutual good will. This, after all, is no more than right, and is earnestly to be desired, for the sake of the loyal Negro soldiers who are returning home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
