<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-09-28">Sept. 28, 1879</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0344</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0344.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-09-28">Sept. 28, 1879</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>shares, and the bricklayers' union, which is in a sound financial condition, will also subscribe.</p>
   <p>The motion to issue an appeal was tabled.</p>
   <p>The secretary said that 1425 shares at $25 had been subscribed for, and that, when 1700 shares are sold, enough money will be available for the start. Ippsen, one of the members, said that the factory can be put into operation if another block of 200 shares is sold; 100 shares were taken during the evening, and another sale of 100 shares will make possible a start next Spring. Milentz asserted that the Association does not advertise enough; the members don't come to the meetings, although it was announced that the present meeting would be the last. Thon made a motion that every shareholder take an additional four shares; that would solve the problem. The furniture carpenters [cabinetmakers] earn enough money to enable them to make such an investment.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0345.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Christian, another member, declared that there are enough furniture carpenters at the meeting who could subscribe for three, four, ten, or even twenty shares, but that the men hesitate because they are afraid.</p>
   <p>The secretary said that within six weeks, fifteen per cent should be collected and another ten per cent sometime during the winter. Perhaps another small bond issue may have to be sold in the spring.</p>
   <p>A number of pledges were received, and the meeting was then adjourned. Hereafter, only the executive board will convene, until sufficient funds are available to warrant another general meeting.</p>
   <p>The committee hopes to be able to elect officers and start a full-fledged organization within two weeks. The next meeting of the committee will be held Monday evening, at 130 West Lake Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
