<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-02">Apr. 2, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Germans, Do Your Duty Today</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1391</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1391.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-02">Apr. 2, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANS, DO YOUR DUTY TODAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Who will be at the helm of the city admistration during the coming two years is the question to be decided upon by the voters of Chicago today.....Sufficient information in print and otherwise was given to the public during the past several weeks in order to prevent any possible mistake on the part of the voters. Today calls for action, however, and it is the voters' duty to avail themselves of this opportunity. But one more warning before going to the polls. Regardless of all that has been said and written, it would be well to remember that the same Record-Herald which is now boosting Harrison, was bitterly opposed to his candidacy only as far back as February 16 when it made this statement: "An honest and conscientious administration of public funds--righteously expected of the executives in whom the citizens have placed their faith--was a disappointment in the instance of the Harrison administration. Neither have measures been taken for the suppression of vice and crime, all of which are fundamental principles of any honest city government." This speaks volumes, having been said <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1392.jpg" n="2"/>by Harrison's now most fervent supporter, the Record-Herald. Bear this in mind German fellow-citizens, when casting your votes today. As we sow, so we reap. No improvement can be expected of the Harrison administration; four years of experience have taught us that.....From all the pulpits of the city--especially from those of liberal churches - warnings were given last Sunday to put an end today to Harrison's mismanagement. Said one of the foremost preachers: "If your time will not permit both, to pray and to vote next Tuesday, then of course you will do no wrong to omit the prayer in order to perform this important civic duty."</p>
   <p>Fellow citizens! We urge you to take an interest in this election. Promote the chances of Hanecy's victory with your votes, also the election of Doctor Bluthardt, Oscar Hebel and Shaughnessy those seasoned and trustworthy candidates for aldermen, who will reform the city administration and will defend the unrestricted Sunday laws as well as the German language and gymnastics in public schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
