<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-20">Mar. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Federal Employment Bureau</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0409</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0409.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-20">Mar. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE FEDERAL EMPLOYMENT BUREAU</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The last Congress failed to appropriate the necessary funds to continue the work of the Federal Employment Bureau in its present scope until the end of the present fiscal year, and, as a result, the beneficial activity of that generally useful body may be considerably curtailed. The money on hand will permit the Department of Labor to spend only one fifth as much as it usually did for employment service. In consequence it was necessary to decrease the number of branch offices of the organization from seven hundred and fifty to fifty-six. These fifty-six offices will be situated in strategic points of industrial regions. The Department of Commerce hopes, it is true, that many communities will be willing to continue the work done by the Bureau, since it is in their own interest to do so. But for the time being it is impossible to state to what extent the expectations of the Department of Commerce will be realized. The Federal Employment Bureau also maintains about two thousand subbureaus, beside the regular service offices. These subbureaus handle only <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0410.jpg" n="2"/>cases of returned soldiers; they will be kept open, and the subbureau's representatives in the various demobilization camps will also be kept at work. The Employment Bureau, which has found employment for about seventy-five per cent of the soldiers who applied for work, is now faced with the unusual situation of having to find jobs for eighty per cent of its own employees, who have lost their positions through the shortsightedness of Congress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
