<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-10-21">Oct. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Our Duty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-10-21">Oct. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">OUR DUTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very important election will be held November 3. A new House of Representatives and thirty-two United States Senators are to be elected on that date, and a number of state and county offices are to be filled. There are only twelve days until election day!</p>
   <p>We call ourselves German-Americans. We are German by culture and American in the political sense of the word. People often hold that against us. They question our right to call ourselves that. They scornfully refer to us as "hyphenated Americans," and are inclined to treat us as second-rate citizens. And over there, in the old country, we have frequently been regarded and treated in a similar manner. Anglo-Americans had, and still <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1361.jpg" n="2"/>have, a better rating on the other side of the ocean. The German Kaiser was supposed to have said that he knew only Americans--just Americans, without any prefix or "hyphen".</p>
   <p>Our German-Americanism is frowned upon equally by friend and foe. We are less respected because we cling to this more detailed designation. People just do not appreciate our position. They either cannot or do not care to. But we will stick it out, just the same, in spite of the fact that, besides the ill repute, it only imposes extra obligations on us, which the American, or the German, as such, does not have, and for which we do not receive any special privileges or advantages in return. This has always been the case and how much more is this true today, during these turbulent times!</p>
   <p>Our heart goes out to our old homeland, fighting a hard battle, but our intellect belongs to our adopted country. We mustn't let our hearts carry <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1362.jpg" n="3"/>us away. We must not let our loyalty to the land of our fathers make us forget our duty toward the land of our children. It is not always easy to do justice to both. The danger is not that our hearts may grow cold [toward the old country], but that we may put aside good common sense. We are still sentimentalists and inclined to listen to the dictates of our hearts rather than of our intellects. There is danger that, in these grave days, we might forget the American in us, and let the German in us gain the upper hand; that we might neglect the duties to which the former has a claim. If that should happen, we would deserve the disrespect which is shown us; then we would really become second-rate people, a credit neither to Germany nor to America. Only he who does his duty fully and wholeheartedly can claim one hundred per cent respect from his fellow men. Only if we prove ourselves politically to be one hundred per cent Americans will our championing of the German cause carry the full weight which our numerical strength in this country calls for.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1363.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Politics are odious. At this time, American domestic politics do not make us very enthusiastic. It seems to us rather ridiculous, in these great times, to be asked to direct our attention to American domestic affairs and the coming elections when world empires are in the balance, and when every day, every hour, news of a world-shaking event may arrive, affecting world history for hundreds of years to come.</p>
   <p>American [domestic] politics and the World War! On one side the fascinating study of the war news and the war situation abroad, and on the other side the patty squabble about the offices and political jobs now to be filled here in America! Just the same, we have to direct our attention to the local issues. This is our duty, because loyal fulfillment of duty is one thing we have learned in the old country. It has been preached to us time and again.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1364.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It is our duty and obligation to our adopted country, as well as to ourselves and our homeland, to take an interest in the coming election and to make up our minds how and for whom we are going to vote on November 3. And this duty should not be so hard to carry out if we realize that the issue involved is of great importance and not a trifling matter.</p>
   <p>On November 3 practically a new Congress will be elected: A new House of Representatives and over one third of the Senate. And Congress decides the policies of the country. In the last analysis it depends upon Congress how this great Republic will react to the struggle of the belligerent powers. It depends upon Congress whether the administration can pursue its policies unhampered or not during the next two years. Our history shows that constructive legislation and political progress can be achieved only if Congress and the administration work hand in hand. For this it is necessary that the party of the administration has a majority in Congress. The Wilson <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1365.jpg" n="6"/>administration, to be given a fair test, should be supported by a Democratic Congress. Assuming that the Wilson administration is pursuing an honestly neutral policy, doing justice to the best interests of this country during these turbulent times, we suggest that German-Americans give their full support to the administration and to its candidates, providing the latter are not opposed by genuinely German candidates. If that should be the case, the German should get preference by all means, because the more Germans we have in Congress, the better it will be for the country; the more truly American our future policy is going to be.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
