<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-17">Oct. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">One Must Know How to Take Care of Oneself</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-17">Oct. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">ONE MUST KNOW HOW TO TAKE CARE OF ONESELF</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since February 6, 1932 the State of Illinois has, according to information given by the governor, spent 170 million dollars for the support of the unemployed.</p>
   <p>This enormous sum shows, in much sharper relief than anything else, how large and how serious the problem of unemployment is.</p>
   <p>It does not look like conditions are going to change within a predictable length of time so as to relieve the people of that burden. Furthur enormous sums will be needed to support the unemployed. It is going to become an increasingly great problem to raise all that money. And yet, of late they have been pretending in Springfield that there is no problem at all, and that a solution could be easily found at any time.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0383.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was openly put before the public that, owing to the coming election, the problem could not be touched; that it would not please the administration to carry these things over to November 6. To all these allusions, the administration failed to react until now. It knew how to get out of it.</p>
   <p>The governor made it known that he had nominated a special commission of sixteen members to make a thorough study of the question of aid to the unemployed. This commission, however, is not by any means supposed to interfere with the Illinois Emergency Relief Commission; nor is it supposed to substitute for the special committee of the legislature. No, it is supposed to find ways and means to free Illinois from the dole. It should first determine the real needs of the unemployed, and then point out how to satisfy these needs.</p>
   <p>There are two things contained in this program. First, it is admitted that, in spite of such a long period, there is still no clear understanding of the real needs, and it is also admitted that a "blue sky" economy has been <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0384.jpg" n="3"/>practiced, and that the aid extended has exceeded the actual needs.</p>
   <p>Second, a discussion [of the problem] is thus avoided in a most convenient manner. In case the commission is not able to solve the problem, it has a beautiful excuse for its own deliberate inefficiency. By the time the commission submits any proposals at all, the election will be over. It will then be possible either to let the mask fall or keep it in place, in accordance with the results of the election.</p>
   <p>The preceding administration was often reproached for helping itself out of unpleasant situations by speedily naming some kind of commission, and so put the emergency off for a long time.</p>
   <p>One is not unlike the other. The administration could have had it otherwise. The people had confidence in the candidates at that time, and the latter had a good chance to help their party to be in power for a long time. The charm of 1932 has been broken.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0385.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Even if the commission should offer useful proposals, what is to be expected? It is now exactly seven months since another commission, appointed by the governor to handle taxation problems made its proposals after long toil and serious deliberations. The rate of taxation was to be adjusted to one per cent of the full value, It was simply ignored; it did not suit the gentlemen. It would have ruined their beautiful political structure.</p>
   <p>Everything that is likely to become dangerous to that structure will be fought. No great scruples will be shown in the choice of means. This was proved by the sudden nomination of the commission.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
