<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-31">Mar. 31, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Vote!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1230</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1230.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-31">Mar. 31, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">VOTE!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tomorrow the citizens of Chicago will be called upon to select the man who, beginning May 1st, is to head the municipal government for four years. They are also to choose a city treasurer, a city recorder, and thirty-five aldermen.</p>
   <p>This election is of vast importance to the city. It has assumed special significance as a result of the special issues which were set forth during the campaign. Registration was unusually spirited; the campaign was even more animated. There are confident expectations that many will cast their ballots, for: "Whoever does not co-operate, does not rule". Voters of either sex who do not exercise their franchise, forfeit their right to a voice in their government and by their silence declare that they are content to be governed. It is not likely that readers of Abendpost are of this type. The citizens of German <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1231.jpg" n="2"/>origin are conscious of their duty and are resolved to preserve their rights.</p>
   <p>Abendpost has no recommendations to make regarding the mayoral election. We have informed our subscribers about the issues involved. They know that national party politics plays no part in the mayoral election, which is the concern of strictly local organizations. They also know that in tomorrow's election the best possible administration must be secured for the city; it must be an administration which is intent upon preserving and promoting the interests of the city and its inhabitants--particularly their security and freedom.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow it will be the duty of the voters to choose that candidate who in their opinion will be the most likely to promote the interests of Chicago and the welfare of its citizens.</p>
   <p>The leading candidates have long been before the public; they are well known in the city; and they are all "men of honor". We believe that our subscribers are as familiar as we are with the various aspirants and their stand on vital <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1232.jpg" n="3"/>issues, and we believe that our readers will encounter no difficulty in making the right selection. Therefore, Abendpost has no recommendations to make on the mayoralty.</p>
   <p>Faithful servants are worthy of our appreciation and our confidence. Successful private industry adheres to this principle; it should be followed also in politics.</p>
   <p>Henry W. Stuckart, who proved himself an honest, capable official and the faithful servant of the taxpayers during his tenure as County Treasurer, is a candidate for the office of City Treasurer. On the basis of his record he should be elected by a large majority.</p>
   <p>James T. Igoe, who served as City Recorder, is a candidate for re-election. There is nothing in his record which justifies opposing his re-election. His work has been satisfactory, and he should be permitted to remain in his office.</p>
   <p>Judge John M. O'Connor, Democratic candidate for the office of Judge of the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1233.jpg" n="4"/>Superior Court, has conducted himself well and deserves re-election.</p>
   <p>In the aldermanic election the voters should and will choose those candidates who appear to be liberal, progressive, and honest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
