<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-11-16">Nov. 16, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[Political Matters]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1724</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1724.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-11-16">Nov. 16, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[POLITICAL MATTERS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Union published a list of the election returns in 71 of the 101 counties of the State of Illinois and totals them as follows: Greeley 95,959; Grant 189,900; Korner 131,901. To this it makes the following comment; From this can be seen that the Liberals in those 71 counties cast 95,959 votes, and that of our countrymen (aside from those Germans who voted for Greeley, too), 36,972 more marked their ballots for Korner.</p>
   <p>Anybody who has the slightest knowledge of the population and party distribution in our State will give this a loud laugh. Altogether there were in 1870 only 203,705 Germans (men, women and children) in Illinois. There could not be more than 37,000 or 38,000 voters among them. In the 71 counties which the Union mentions there were 116,727 Germans, among whom there can hardly be more than 20,000 or 22,000 voters.</p>
   <p>Perhaps this will convince the Union that its calculation is pure nonsense. It imagines that in 71 counties in which only 22,000 German voters live no less than 36,972 voted for Korner, aside from those who voted for Greeley.</p>
   <p>The figures the Union gives are altogether wrong. The more accurate Tribune finds <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1725.jpg" n="2"/>in 89 counties a difference of only 4,524 votes. The final total for the whole State of Illinois will not be far from the estimate of the Tribune - Grant's majority 56,000; Oglesby 43,000 (Oglesby ran for Governor against Korner). Then the number of those who voted for Grant (Rep.) and also for Korner (Lib.) would amount to 6,500. And that these 6,500 were not all Germans, the editor of the Union knows as well as we. Hundreds if not thousands of faithful Democratic Irishmen voted for Grant electors, but otherwise for the whole Democratic State ticket. This has been only partially balanced by a good number of Liberal Democratic knownothings voting for Greeley but striking the "Dutchman", Korner, from their ballots.</p>
   <p>Less than one fifth of the German Republicans in the State therefore voted for Korner. This far and no further has the influence of Mr. Schurz reached and the half dozen little Liberal sheets, which altogether have perhaps one-fourth the subscribers of the Illinois Staats Zeitung.</p>
   <p>The other four-fifths have acted on the conviction that as American citizens they have to vote according to their political opinions, not according to birth and extraction. They have told themselves that if the elections were decided according to nationality, the Germans would be lost. A German know-nothing would inevitably bring forth an American know-nothing. Of the inhabitants <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1726.jpg" n="3"/>of Illinois in 1870, 2,024,693 were born in America, and only 203, 750 in Germany. of those born here about 360,000 were children of German parents. Even suppose that if all these were to combine against the other nationalities, they would still be only one-fourth of the total population. The moral of these figures is too obvious for any sensible person to ignore.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
