<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-09-04">September 4, 1886</date><title level="a">The Worst Enemies of the Germans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-09-04">September 4, 1886</date><title level="a">THE WORST ENEMIES OF THE GERMANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nothing has hurt the Germans more in the United States in the eyes of its other population elements than the shocking agitation of the anarchists. Of course the anarchists deny any nationality. They are "international". It is a deplorable fact that most of them bear German names, many talk no other language but German, and the most abominable anarchistic propaganda is printed in German. Therefore the Germans have been blamed in the end with the existence of this anarchism.</p>
   <p>Anyhow, the most noisy "German" anarchists must be thanked and praised for directing their most vicious attacks against the German press, which is overwhelmingly their bitter opponent. Only in this way are the English American newspapers, which are watching closely the activity of anarchists, reminded that the most important and most influential German newspapers are fighting Anarchism. As a further fact, derived from this attitude, the majority of German newspaper readers are opposed to Anarchism. But in excited times, logic has a poor standing. And so we see it happen time after time, that even enlightened American elements are holding the German nationality responsible for the fantastic and criminal activity of a few <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0749.jpg" n="2"/>fanatics. Even the most lenient German observers must admit that the "German" anarchists have done a lot of damage to the political and private interests of German-American business people and workers. What German industry, German honesty and German Wisdom have built up during several generations in this country with the greatest difficulties, is now dangerously shaken by the outrageous actions of a gang of so-called Germans. And there are many greenhorns among them, who cannot understand the institutions of this country and who have no idea of the hard and long struggle, endured by the Germans to reach their present respected position among the other elements of this country.</p>
   <p>At the same time, the threatening and raging anarchists today see the most dangerous enemies of their own comrades, trapped by the law. It is to be expected from the standpoint of broadminded Americans that every means of legal help will be granted to the sentenced culprits. But vicious threats and low accusations against court officials, who have simply done their duty, are indeed a bad introduction towards legal aid for the prisoners. And did the German-speaking anarchists of Chicago ever consider the possibility that, if all legal means have failed, only an appeal to the Governor of Illinois can obtain a pardon for the sentenced comrades? But no American governor will allow himself to be intimidated by threats to grant a pardon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
