<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-09-10">Sep. 10, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Turngemeinde Will Withdraw from the League.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-09-10">Sep. 10, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO TURNGEMEINDE WILL WITHDRAW FROM THE LEAGUE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a meeting of the Chicago Turngemeinde held last evening in the North Side Turner Hall it was decided to withdraw from the Personal Rights League. The motion to that effect, made by Louis Kohtz, was received with a shout of laughter and was carried without discussion, and with only one dissenting vote.</p>
   <p>Louis Nettlehorst, President of the Turngemeinde, told a Tribune reporter last evening that respectable Chicago Germans had become thoroughly disgusted with the political methods of the league.</p>
   <p>He said: "Bary claimed he could control 5,000 German votes in Chicago when he could not control ten votes. We are tired of being made tools by such a man."</p>
   <p>At the last National Turners' convention held at New York, 40,000 members were made nominal members of the Personal Rights League by a single resolution. Since that time the subordinate societies have been withdrawing one by one until there are now few remaining in the league. Last night's action robs <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1541.jpg" n="2"/>the league of 700 members, and deprives it of the prestige of the largest Turner society in the west.</p>
   <p>Important action bearing on the recent rebellion of conservative Turners from the North American Turn Bund was also taken last evening. President Nettle-horst, Max Stern, and others made spirited speeches on the question, which were loudly applauded. The tenor of the remarks was that either the national organization would have to be purified by the expulsion of all the anarchists and socialistic elements which had crept into it, or all the conservative societies would decline to remain in it, and would form a rival National organization, which would exceed it in wealth and dignity.</p>
   <p>A committee of sixteen was appointed with discretionary powers to represent the society at the convention of conservative Turners to be held Sunday morning in the North Side Turner Hall. It was decided to take no action on permanent withdrawal at present, but to form a separate district organization pending the action of the next convention of the society.</p>
   <p>The committee appointed consisted of Messrs. Lewis Nettlehorst, Henry Carr, Max Stern, L. O. Kohtz, Henry Suder, William Kuecken, George A. Schmidt, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1542.jpg" n="3"/>Fritz F. Goetz, M. Rosenthal, F. Fiedeler, G. Hauser, O. Durant, G. Schlotthauser, John C. Miller, A. G. Hambrock, and Julius Zimmerman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
