<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-05-31">Wednesday, May 31st, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">The Brickmakers Strike</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0268.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-05-31">Wednesday, May 31st, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">THE BRICKMAKERS STRIKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Due to a union, that the brickyards on the Northside has engaged between 150 and 200 Scabs and put them to work in their yards, and that clashes had resulted between them and the union workers to suppress which police had to be sent for. A reporter of the Arbeiter Zeitung went yesterday afternoon to Nickersonville, where most of the brickyards are located to get to the bottom of the matter.</p>
   <p>Arriving at the first brickyard, near Fritz's Grove which is the property of P. Multing, he found 16 Scabs at work mostly, Poles, Swedes and Germans. For their protection, two policemen were on duty in the yard. The foreman, a German, whose sympathy was more or less divided, informed our reporter, that last year 44 were working; yesterday he said 20 Scabs started to work but also mentioned that it will take some time for them to produce a good standard brick. "Was there any fighting between the strikers and the Scabs this morning?" asked the reporter. "One could hardly call it fighting; naturally the strikers asked them to quit work, and when this was not done, the Scabs, were bombarded with stones as a result of which four of them disappeared. I too, was hit with a stone.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0269.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The quick appearance of a police wagon stopped further disturbances.</p>
   <p>The two policemen when interviewed said they had seen nothing and did not even seem to know why they were really there. They were following only their superior's instruction.</p>
   <p>The only brickyard which pays the new union scale is managed by Diehl &amp; Dresselt, and is working with full capacity. etc. Mayor Harrison denied having sent any policemen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
