<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-12-09">December 9th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Local-Political Candidate Hopkins Addresses an Open Letter to the German Voters.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1435</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1435.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-12-09">December 9th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">LOCAL-POLITICAL CANDIDATE HOPKINS ADDRESSES AN OPEN LETTER TO THE GERMAN VOTERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Leo Austrian presided last night at the great assembly of the Democratic ward-delegates at 137 Monroe Street. First John P. Hopkins was indorsed by a resolution; General Lieb held a speech in favor of the candidate and then a letter was read in which Mr. Hopkins addressed the German-American voters. of the City:-</p>
   <p>"To the German-American Central Association:-</p>
   <p>Gentlemen:-</p>
   <p>I am sorry that I am not able to attend your assembly today. I congratulate the Germans first for the brilliant success of the assembly at the Brigg's House and in general upon the prospects under which you have opened the campaign.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1436.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I, personally, like yourselves also take a lively interest in this battle, not only, because I am a candidate, but because I believe that we are for a principle, for the principle of personal liberty: Chicago is a Democratic City. It is in its composition more cosmopolitan than any other city on the globe. Its inhabitants are liberal-minded, have progressive ideas and hate all violent laws. While the Germans, more than the inhabitants of any other City of the American continent, always have been the most fearless and persevering opponents of any kind of narrow-mindedness and bigotry, they always showed themselves as the true representatives of law and order.</p>
   <p>I recognize fully the rights that are high and dear to the great element of our population, to which you belong. I herewith give you my word, that these rights shall be preserved and the customs which are so dear to you, shall not be touched.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1437.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During the campaign I hope that I will meet you more often and find occasion to give to my numerous German friends whom I have become acquainted with during my political activity of the last years, the assurance that you surely shall find full representation corresponding with your power and number, and that your voice shall be heard in future in the leadership of the party.</p>
   <p>Whatsoever I am able to do on any occasion, to protect the rights of the Germans, I shall not fail to do. Your nationality shall find recognition in every way.</p>
   <p>- John P. Hopkins.-</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
