<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-11-12">Nov. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Armistice and Victory</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0198</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0198.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-11-12">Nov. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ARMISTICE AND VICTORY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Armistice Day, 1919, dedicated to the memory of the eleventh day of November, 1918, a day which brought to the world a declaration of armistice and a hope for peace, also conveyed to the American people a new armistice and a new peace hope--but there the parallel ends. On November 11, 1920, we will not have to look back upon an armistice year full of disappointments and breaches of trust, unrest and struggle, but we will enjoy the benefits of a prosperous peace, which yesterday's armistice has given us. That is our hope and aspiration, for the victory which led to this armistice is a twofold one: a victory of enlightenment and good will on one side, and a victory of right and justice on the other: a victory of right over might, and in the final analysis, a victory of the State[of Illinois] and a victory of the national interest over individual and group interests.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the mine workers' union have decided to abide by the court <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0199.jpg" n="2"/>order, to call off the strike, and have requested the mine workers to return to their jobs. They realized that the right of the majority was more valid than the right of the individual, and that they would not be able to resist successfully the power of the State--the will of the people. By their submission they have won; they have gained definite rights, and now the State is obligated to them. The mine operators and companies were forced to subordinate their individual and group interests to the interests and rights of the majority. The Federal Government is fully aware of the obligation which the State has assumed. President Wilson and his Cabinet have instructed Labor Secretary Wilson to call the representatives of all soft coal operators as well as all mine workers' unions to a conference in Washington for Friday[November 14], to sign a new working agreement. This will be done and the mine workers will be dealt with fairly; so will the operators, although the latter will probably have to "sacrifice" a lot--and we hope they do. It will hardly be possible to settle definitely all controversies, but ways and means will certainly be found to guarantee a general return to work and an undisturbed and efficient operation of the mines.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0200.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After that, there should be, and probably will be, a committee of trustworthy men appointed to study the situation thoroughly and to work out a plan that will do justice to both parties involved; one that will safeguard permanent and undisturbed operation. That must be possible, and we believe it can be done. It is possible now, even though it seemed impossible yesterday. Because the Government now can speak the final word in case either party should obstinately insist on unjust demands and refuse to settle on an agreement that will serve the best interests of all the people.</p>
   <p>The supreme and sovereign power of the State[nation, people] is today recognized in America as never before. The German doctrine of the State rules in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
