<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-10-27">Oct. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Support Sullivan</title><title level="a" type="sub">Evangelical and Lutheran Pastors Appeal to Colleagues in the State</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1353</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1353.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-10-27">Oct. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">SUPPORT SULLIVAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Evangelical and Lutheran Pastors Appeal to Colleagues in the State</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several Evangelical and Lutheran clergymen of Chicago have issued an appeal to their colleagues in the state to support Roger C. Sullivan, Democratic candidate for United States Senator, in the coming election, and to campaign for him among the members of their congregations. The appeal, sent in the form of an open letter to all the congregations in the state--over two thousand--was signed by the following pastors: William Hattendorf, pastor emeritus; F. Weber, superintendent of the Deaconess Hospital, Chicago; H. H. Fleer, Salem Congregation; August Fleer, St. Philip's Congregation; B. C. Ott, St. Stephen's Congregation; John Hoffmeister, Immanuel Congregation; Dalton, Illinois; Gustav Koch, St. Luke's Congregation, Hans Jacoby, St. Paul's Congregation, Elgin, Illinois. Here is the text of the appeal:</p>
   <p>" 'Political pastors are an absurdity!' This criticism of Kaiser Wilhelm has <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1354.jpg" n="2"/>always had our approval too, but today, at a time when our most sacred possessions and the existence of the German people are involved, an indifferent and indecisive attitude by the pastors toward the election of a United States Senator could hardly be condoned.</p>
   <p>"Not for political reasons, but out of love for a worthy cause, the representatives of five synods consider it their foremost duty to take an active part in the campaign of Mr. Roger C. Sullivan for United States Senator, and to urge every member of our congregations--and every friend of the German element--to vote for him. And we are convinced that we can fully rely upon the man of our choice, who stands for tolerance, for a neutral attitude of our country in the present European conflict, for personal liberty, for respect for the Germans over here as well as in the old country. He will support the justified demands of the German-Americans; we could expect nothing of the sort from the opposing candidate. The Irish people, from whom Mr. Sullivan originated, are today the natural allies of our [Germanic] race, our aspirations coincide with theirs, while the opposing candidates [Sherman and Robins] are <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1355.jpg" n="3"/>steeped in hatred for the alien. The kind of treatment they would dish out to us can be sampled every day from the 'Anglo-maniac' newspapers of our country.</p>
   <p>"For reasons of self-preservation and self-respect, we have decided, for once, to go in for politics, and we hope to find understanding and active co-operation among our colleagues and friends in our congregations, whose interests are the same as our own.</p>
   <p>"Please try to get all the members of your congregations and societies interested in this matter and use all your influence for this purpose. We know Mr. Sullivan personally, and assume full responsibility for the veracity of all the claims made about him in the paragraphs above."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
