<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1884-03-15">Mar. 15, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">[Socialists Meet]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0802</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0802.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1884-03-15">Mar. 15, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">[SOCIALISTS MEET]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The General Committee of the I. A. A. held its regular meeting yesterday. Comrade Rau presided. New delegates are: Fritz Hermann of the Bridgeport Group and Albert Behrend of the Unity Group. 18 delegates were present. Group "Forward" reports about progress, also Group Northwestside. The following froups: Jefferson, Fraternity and Liberty complain that the agitation meetings lack attendance; all Groups report about the progress of collections for Stellmacher, The groups I, II and III were not represented. The groups Unity and Bridgeport report progress.-</p>
   <p>The Committee for the arrangement of the Commune celebration reports, that the necessary preparations have been completed. Comrade H. Linnemeyer was named Ticket-seller, as cashier at the bar Comrades Stange and Hirsch; as Ticket-collectors Comrades Schnaubelt, Reiser and Hettig were elected. In the regulation committee Uhlhorn, Behrend and Hacker were elected.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0803.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As Treasurer Comrade Kaulbitz. A Bill for payment of hall rent was allotted.-Group Liberty proposes establishing of an arms fund and to place collection lists for that purpose.</p>
   <p>The motion of the group Northwestside, to hold an "International" indignation meeting against the action of the Federal Chief Solicitor in regard to manufacturing dynamite, etc. was postponed till the next meeting.-</p>
   <p>Comrade Stange proposes to translate good pamphlets into English and use them for agitation purposes. Accepted. Comrade Engels should be asked, whether he does not object if his "pamphlet" From Utopia to science" is translated. Resolved to ask the groups to subscribe to a number of copies of the "San Francisco Truth" in order to give them some assistance. Further resolved that the Groups should participate against the actions of Rome's agents at the city councils meetings.</p>
   <p>After this adjournment.-</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
