<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-10-11">October 11, 1893</date><title level="a">Again the "Vote of the Lutherans"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1446</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1446.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-10-11">October 11, 1893</date><title level="a">AGAIN THE "VOTE OF THE LUTHERANS"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Will it not soon be time to let the German Lutheran vote disappear from American politics? Without doubt there are single persons or newspapers who are believed to have a special influence over the German Lutherans and get paid for it accordingly, but the Lutherans in general can only feel sorry to see their religion pulled into the morass of politics.</p>
   <p>Of all the confessions they alone plead most convincingly the principle, that church and state should be strictly separated from each other. As citizens and taxpayers they have in the public affairs exactly the same and no other interest; as the Catholics, Methodists, Presbyterians, Jews or free thinkers. Therefore they will be partly Republicans and partly Democrats. Some of them will be enthusiastic about protective tariffs, others about free trade. There will Lutherans who want to vote for Swift and those who want Hopkins. But that all Lutnerans, by virtue of their belief can be claimed for this or that party, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1447.jpg" n="2"/>for this or that candidate, well this can only be traced to the impudence of the "influentials", who once tasted campaign money and liked the taste of it.</p>
   <p>There are more Catholics in Chicago than Lutherans. If therefore the Lutherans had in fact set up the principle to vote against each Catholic, only because he is a Catholic, so could the Catholics turn the stick and let not a single Lutheran come into office. These certainly would be very edifying conditions. But, there is, aswe said before, not the smallest reason existing that the incitements of the campaign - money hungry influentials are paid attention to, by the multitude of the German Lutherans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
