<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-12-28">Dec. 28, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Laborers Association and the Police.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-12-28">Dec. 28, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">LABORERS ASSOCIATION AND THE POLICE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The trial of the laborers' union versus the police of the city of Chicago was continued yesterday before Master in Chancery Windes.</p>
   <p>Kraft and Greenacre, representing the union, argued that the Constitution guarantees all the inhabitants of the United States the right to publicly assemble to hold lawful discussions and that the police should not infringe upon this right.</p>
   <p>Regarding the meetings of the laborers' union, the police might have at most the right to dissolve them in case anything unlawful should happen there - but to prohibit them altogether is illegal.</p>
   <p>It was interesting to watch the stupid faces of Messrs. Bonfield, Hubbard, Knight and Green when the answer from the police was read and it reached the passage about the "adherents of the above murdered Spiess."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0058.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The gentlemen of the police declared immediately it was a deplorable error in writing and should read "above mentioned."</p>
   <p>Green and Knight, the corporation counsel and his assistant, insisted in their answer that according to city ordinances the mayor possesses authority to suppress meetings which he considers revolutionary or otherwise illegal.</p>
   <p>But they did not seem to have too much confidence in their case as they stressed the fact that this case did not appertain to the chancery's court which deals only in civil suits. The present case - they maintained-concerns the prevention of a crime.</p>
   <p>Master in Chancery Windes declares finally that he would render his decision next Thursday.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0059.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are informed that stool-pigeons of the police have given the members of the union the "well-meant" advice to organize under a different name and that then everything will be all right.</p>
   <p>Roche, Hubbard and Bonfield know very well that the Citizens' Association would not blame the laws but would blame them - should they lose the fight against the laborers' union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
