<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-04-04">April 4, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">The German Mass Meeting.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-04-04">April 4, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN MASS MEETING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Luxenbourg Independent Club called a meeting yesterday afternoon. The president of the club, Mr. Joseph Lauf, a war veteran, opened the meeting. After several speeches had been delivered and after an unpleasant episode caused by a disturber in the audience, Mr. Theodore Brentano addressed the gathering in German. The speaker explained that, personally, Nelson might be a straightforward man, but politically he represents the Socialist and Anarchistic ideas, and made the remark that there is no difference, in his opinion, between a religious procession with the display of flags, or a Socialist procession headed by the symbol of their societies, the red or the black flags. Then again, Nelson, a single man, does not pay a penny of taxes, and carries all of his worldly possessions with him in a handkerchief, and could, as easy as not, disappear some day if he chooses to do so. Such a man cannot possibly be trusted with the great responsibility which falls to the lot of a mayor.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1568.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Roche, on the other hand, is a personality which excludes any doubt as to his ability for an honest city administration, and he, the speaker, can assure the assembly upon his own word of honor that Mr. Roche will not interfere or prohibit the Sunday entertainment of Chicago's respectable citizens.</p>
   <p>William Vocke said in a short speech in English that during the eight years of Mayor Harrison's administration the tricolored flag of our city has been insulted, and while our prominent Democrats are openly advocating the election of Mr. Roche as mayor of Chicago, Harrison declared himself in favor of Nelson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
