<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-14">Jan. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A Survey of the Milk Strike</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0186</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0186.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-14">Jan. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A SURVEY OF THE MILK STRIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last two weeks much milk has been spilled and much has been written about it. In line with its NRA plan the Government had tried to force an official code which involved price fixing upon the milk industry. This experiment was undertaken despite the fact that economists have long known, and other people should have learned, that price fixing is possible only if the Government itself assumes control over the manufacture and sale of the specific article--in other words, if business is socialized.</p>
   <p>Within a very short time a general fight ensued in which each participant accused the other of taking advantage of his unfortunate situation. The farmers who furnished the milk, the dealers, the deliverymen, and the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0187.jpg" n="2"/>consumers, were the participants. The large organized dairies could not continue to retail the milk at the price agreed upon with the Government, because other dealers sold at lower prices.</p>
   <p>In order to eliminate the latter dealers from competition the farmers went on strike; whether voluntarily, or after some friendly persuading, we cannot say. Thus the large dairies and the organized deliverymen were apparently in complete accord, for the former immediately closed their establishments and furnished milk for children and sick people only, and the deliverymen and farmers succeeded in preventing deliveries to the City from the country.</p>
   <p>The strike was marked by many acts of violence, and, strange to say, neither the State authorities nor the National Government took effective measures to stop them. The task of ending the strike, and bringing about <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0188.jpg" n="3"/>an armistice between the fighting factions, was reserved for the Mayor of Chicago, and he was equal to that task. Thus Mayor Kelly proved conclusively that Chicago is well able to take care of its interests. The people in Springfield ought to put that down in their "memory book" for future reference.</p>
   <p>And now, what is the result of the strike? Was it worth-while to start a fight and deprive 4,000,000 inhabitants of a city, among whom are many thousands of children, of milk? What was gained could have been accomplished just as well by peaceful negotiations. The strike aroused angry feelings, because it was accompanied by violence, and it has harmed the reputation of the authorities, because they permitted unlawful abuse of nonpartisan citizens. Thus the meager respect for the law has suffered a further decrease. And nobody bothered about the interests of the consumers during the course of the entire strike. The consumers are not even represented in the committee which is trying to bring about a settlement during the armistice.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0189.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If the price is to be lower, as is reported, then it is owing to the fact that the law of supply and demand has again asserted itself. All of the persons concerned in this matter must make allowances; the producers, the dealers, and the consumers, and the sooner they recognize this fact, the better it will be for the people who have been forced to serve as objects of experimentation. Artificial price fixing on a basis that is contrary to the law of supply and demand is sheer nonsense, unless it is done in a country or state where socialism rules.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
