<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-05-30">May 30, 1883</date><title level="a">Workers of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0853</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0853.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-05-30">May 30, 1883</date><title level="a">WORKERS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>met last night at Mueller's Hall to express their indignation and confer on the horrid murder committed by the militia on wage workers of St. Clair County. August Spies was elected President and H. Bonnifoi and H. Hirschberger Secretaries. First speaker was A. R. Parsons who gave a vivid picture of the violence and murder of the poor miners struggling for their existence. He expressed his admiration for those women who displayed so much bravery, preceding their men folk. Conditions must have been unbearable when women found it necessary to resort to force. Is it not enough that a great many miners are being murdered in the mines? But when the poorly paid wage slaves asked for a wage to enable them to feed and satisfy the hunger of their families and themselves-the response was, death from bullets by the hangman's servants of "order." Through force and deception labor is deprived of its rights and existence. Therefore the oppressed people have to unite and employ every means possible to overthrow that gang of robbers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0854.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The President then read the following resolutions which were accepted unanimously: In consideration that the State militia under the command of our Governor Hamilton opened fire on a number of St. Clair County miners gathered there to defend their rights against oppression by their employers, and caused the death of several, wounding others and in consideration that this brutal attack on our comrades is the natural outcome of present conditions when thievery and murder of the working class is the privilege of the ruling class who dont hesitate to use bullets and bayonets in their combat against righteousness and freedom and in consideration that the constitution of the United States guarantees each of its citizens the right to life, liberty and happiness, it was resolved that the crime committed by the State authorities is considered an infamous and cunning breach of confidence perpetrated by the so-called representatives of the people; that through this action our constitution has been made a worthless shred of paper with no other but an illusory and literary value; the phrase of equal rights is a lie and our Government is nothing more or less than a confederation of the wealthy class, that of the bourgeoisie, against the exploited masses- the working people.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0855.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was further resolved that we the citizens who met here, express our sympathy to our comrades in St. Clair County and pledge vengeance on the perpetrators of this brutal murder when the right time for the revolution is at hand.</p>
   <p>Then spoke Mr. George Schilling in English and Paul Grottkau in German.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
