<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-04-05">Apr. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Last Word</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1271</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1271.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-04-05">Apr. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A LAST WORD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Deutschtum [German element] is engaged in battle, not only over there in Europe, but all over the world. And so it must be, if the German name is to survive. Because the struggle which the allied German people are waging in Europe was forced upon them by lust for revenge, envy, and hate. It was the hate of the inferior toward the superior, and the envy of the failures towards the more successful competitors. It was the kind of vengance which was nursed by the growing realization of the moral and economic superiority of the German character. It would be admitting that this character was of an inferior quality, if we were to deny that the American German element, too, has to reckon with jealousy and, to a certain degree, with this hatred. We would be turning our eyes from the truth. It would be un-German and a sign of weakness, if we would not take up the fight and lend all our efforts <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1272.jpg" n="2"/>and use every means at our command to carry it through.</p>
   <p>It is a far cry from the river Spree [flowing through Berlin] to the Bosphorus. We cannot claim that the Germans and the Turks have very much in common. But Germany and Austria-Hungary did not hesitate a moment to accept Turkey as an ally when she made this offer and the former have every reason to be satisfied with their new brother-in-arms. The great majority of the Irish element have offered to co-operate with the Deutschtum of Chicago in their fight for the election of a mayor, and the latter have every reason to be grateful for the active support which the Irish-Americans are lending the German-American candidate. Is he to be defeated just because many Germans might find it impossible to rise above petty side issues, instead of having one goal in mind, namely to secure victory, recognition, influence, and political power for the Deutschtum?</p>
   <p>Nothing succeeds like success. Everybody knows that. If the German candidate for mayor is elected now, the German-American vote will be respected, and next <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1273.jpg" n="3"/>year it will have a big word to say in the selection of candidates for state and federal offices. The German vote will have to be reckoned with. Democratic party leaders in particular will have to pay attention if they want to have a chance for success. That is the only way to remove the anti-German elements from the party leadership and make it pro-German. If, contrary to all expectations, this should fail, then there is only one course left for the German element [Deutschtum] in city, state, and country: To present a united front against the enemies of the Deutschtum, and to support those candidates who recognize the justified demands of the German element, regardless which party the former be-long to--the Republican if necessary!</p>
   <p>It is often said that the non-German elements behind Sweitzer constituted a danger for the city; all they were interested in was to sit by the public trough and gorge themselves. That is an unfair exaggeration. Let us go back to our example again. What didn't we hear about the Turks! Their <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1274.jpg" n="4"/>army was supposed to be undisciplined, ragged, and degenerated, unable to give battle and content to murder and pillage. And how different things turned out to be! Because German officers and petty officers and German gunners and marines were put in charge? Because German science and experience lent a hand? Probably so; very likely so. And it's going to be like that in our case, too.</p>
   <p>In the person of Sweitzer, German diligence, German conscientiousness and German honesty will be represented, and other competent Germans will be his collaborators during his administration. It will be up to the Germans to make his administration an efficient, honest and progressive one--the best the city has ever had. And it can be done if only the German element will demonstrate tomorrow that it stands behind him and the other German candidates, including the German-American Sergel, who is running for the office of city treasurer as a Republican, and many other candidates for the city council, running on either ticket. It can be done, if only the German element of the city will vote for Robert M. Sweitzer tomorrow!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
