<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-02-16">Feb. 16, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">An Enthusiastic Meeting at the Vorwarts Turner Hall.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0733</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0733.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-02-16">Feb. 16, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">AN ENTHUSIASTIC MEETING AT THE VORWARTS TURNER HALL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Turner Hall was crowded to its capacity last night, the audience evidently much interested in the announced order of the day: "Fusion or independent labor policy?"</p>
   <p>Mr. Altpeter was unanimously elected president of the meeting and was received when he stepped on to the platform with loud applause. Mr. Georg Rohrbach was elected secretary.</p>
   <p>The first of the evening's speakers was Mr. Jacob Winnen who gave a short sketch of the development of the new Labor Party. The speaker pointed out, that through technical development the working man loses ground, and as self preservation is the first law of nature, he tries to protect himself against complete enslavement and poverty. The happenings of May 4th, 1886 gave us an idea what organized labor has to expect if it would protest against the permanent oppression, and the cheating through the capitalistic oppressors. It was an eye opener for our citizens and working men toward a subsequent breaking away and severing the ties with the old parties and rely more in its own strength. Mr. Winnen encouraged the pursuance <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0734.jpg" n="2"/>of the course taken and expressed hopes that the result of the coming elections will overshadow last fall's elections.</p>
   <p>Secretary Rohrbach then read the following resolution: "In consideration, that the U. L. P. has announced in its first public platform that labor can not expect fair play, either from the Republican nor from the Democratic party and furthermore, that corruption dominates both parties which are entirely under the control of organized capital,and considering that the U. L. P. announced also that capitalistic societies no longer employ ordinary ways to further their interests but take refuge in secret political machinery and thus showed labor that unity means strength, and considering that the U. L. P. declared the necessity of labor organizations to follow the example set by capitalists and become politically independent, and this can be only achieved by means of unity. Only then could labor hope for a just share of the profits which is the fruit of its work, and which was denied him by the Republicans as well as by the Democrats; and considering that the U. L. P. severed herewith the ties with all of the existing political parties declared itself absolutely independent with only one aim, to further such principles of righteousness which the party will conscientiously introduce. And considering that 25,000 citizens voiced their desire for an independent political party, it was decided at this great meeting of Chicago's independent citizens, that the new organization <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0735.jpg" n="3"/>continues its activities for the benefit of the working men.</p>
   <p>It has also been decided that the organization will work toward one goal, the election of renowned labor representatives, who will win the nomination from representatives of the U. L. P. Our work will not be finished before righteous ness will be restored to human society."</p>
   <p>This resolution was passed unanimously.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
