<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-06-17">June 17, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">The Funniest of Conventions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0944</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0944.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-06-17">June 17, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">THE FUNNIEST OF CONVENTIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For giving such a comprehensive report about the National Convention of the Greenbackers, communists, and women's franchise advocates, and for judging the doings of these people in such a friendly and tolerant manner, the Illinois Staats-Zeitung is taken to task by the New York Volkszeitung. Then, too, there are not a few old-time and dyed-in-the-wool socialists who find the expressions used in the [Illinois Staats-Zeitung] headlines-- "The Fools in the Exposition Building," "Voting Females," "Paper Fanatics"--too mild and who are not amused by the Convention, but rather disgusted.</p>
   <p>If the New-York Volkszeitung wants to sulk and carry a chip on its shoulder, it would do well to study the opinions of the Anglo-American press first. There it could find more grounds for indignation. But, unfortunately and <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0945.jpg" n="2"/>for obvious reasons, the English language press is a book with seven seals for most of the German socialistic newspaper heroes; and those who have any connections with the Anglo-American world feel so humble toward it that they consider themselves highly honored if they are tolerated at all by Anglo-Americans. For instance, the "National President" of the Communist party (sic), Dr. A. Douai, writes in the above-mentioned Volkszeitung with great satisfaction: "It is a sign of recognition that the Palmer House, the first and best hostelry in the city of Chicago, has given us a room for our headquarters". The rooms of this hotel are available to all decent guests and the "National President's" feeling of gratitude is simply touching.</p>
   <p>Since the communist German gentlemen in New York seem to be just as reverential toward the Chicago Anglo-Americans as they are touchy about German opinions, they would probably feel flattered about what the Chicago Tribune has to say regarding this Convention. Since this may prove of interest, we are reproducing here a close translation....[Translator's note: Since the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0946.jpg" n="3"/>rest of the article is nothing but a translation from an English original, I did not feel justified in re-translating it.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
