<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-24">Feb. 24, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">To the Ballot Box! Germans, Vote at the Primary!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-24">Feb. 24, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE BALLOT BOX! GERMANS, VOTE AT THE PRIMARY!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Germans! The day which marks the preliminary battle for the important spring election draws near and everyone who is interested in this contest, all who consider the public weal, whould be reminded that this day marks the time when the banner bearers for the next battle must be chosen by our legions, the German voters, if victory is to be attained. Next Monday will be the primary election for the Democratic party; the delegates must be elected which meet the next day at the convention; this primary will decide whether or not our city shall have a German mayoral candidate on April the fourth....</p>
   <p>The enemy is well prepared and looks to the support of an unconscientious clique of boodle politicians and office seekers.... He will not win if the free citizens who are not influenced by machine-politics will do their duty and vote! Therefore, hark again, German citizens! Do not rest in smug complacency, but march forth to the ballot box on Monday and vote for delegates who will unfurl the standard of a man who is impervious to the dictates of the ring-cudgel-rule.</p>
   <p>In order to facilitate the task for the Germans, we have printed diagrams of <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1461.jpg" n="2"/>every voting precinct... (Detailed maps show the 34 wards with their respective precincts plainly numbered. All boundaries, rivers, railroads, etc., are marked; a separate map of each ward is published, three pages altogether. Translator)... Addresses of all voting places are appended.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
