<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1936-01-02">Jan. 2, 1936</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0354.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1936-01-02">Jan. 2, 1936</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>the arguments of the WPA'S opponents are not always tenable, and occasionally they are fraught with exaggeration. The objections about increased costs will affect uninformed people who are unaccustomed to independent thinking, but such statements do not stand up under a thorough analysis.</p>
   <p>First, one must consider that financial aid given for a long time without a corresponding return in labor undermines morale. Only too readily do men grow accustomed to idleness, whereafter it is difficult to induce them to resume some useful activity which will support them.</p>
   <p>Besides, one must realize that the increased costs do not only consist of payments to the unemployed; for part of this money is used to buy material, tools, etc., whereby certain branches of industry enjoy a longed-for revival.</p>
   <p>Regarding the utility of certain projects opinions may be divided; many projects, however, probably produce lasting values, and ere long other projects must be started.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0355.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In so far as some of this work is concerned, one might wish for greater efficiency and experience. Yet not all the blame can be heaped upon the WPA administration. First of all, there may have been insufficient time available for the necessary preparations prior to the opening of a project. The intention was to give help quickly to the jobless, and this could only be achieved by slighting the advance work; that is, expert production had to be dispensed with. Here also increased difficulties were encountered through successive changes in the emergency work system. In the beginning the CWA was created, which did much good, but it was abandoned because of the protests of businessmen who regarded it as a competitor. Aid for the unemployed was then shifted to the FERA, and its management of the problem aroused still stronger criticism. Finally the WPA was brought into being, and it is too early to give a final dicision on its activities.</p>
   <p>Among other objections critics declare that it would be preferable to employ only experienced men and to pay them the prevailing wages of their trades. In <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0356.jpg" n="4"/>this manner the Government would not compete with private business, and the money thus expended for emergency work would indirectly reach the unemployed. This view is more or less justified, but the results would be forthcoming very slowly in so far as the effect throughout the country is concerned, and it would not solve the problem of providing the necessary aid for the unemployed immediately.</p>
   <p>The contention of the critics that primarily members of the Democratic party are considered cannot be disputed. However, if the Republicans were in power similar accusations would probably be made against that party. Because of our political system we simply cannot extricate ourselves from party politics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
