<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-25">September 25th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">"Meeting of the Socialist Labor Party" " German Section of the Westside."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0992</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0992.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-25">September 25th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">"Meeting of the Socialist Labor Party" " German Section of the Westside."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At yesterday's Agitation meeting, which was held at Canalport Avenue and Union Street. Jacob Wisner was elected Chairman, and then requested Mr. L. Thorsmark, to give his previously announced speech, concerning the present business situation and the Socialist Labor Party.</p>
   <p>It was something to this effect: For real criticism of this theme, it would be necessary, to look up business conditions of the past. Most of us, have adopted America not for political, but for financial reasons. We were seeking an existence worthy of a human being, which we have found, until that enemy depression came. Then came the crisis in Europe and spread according to the Socialist prophecy and against the prediction of the capitalists to this country. Just now, the clouds of the depression seem to be lifting but what will be its consequences? First of all, in the usual American manner, wild speculations will ensue; but it will bring forth an alliance, amongst the more farsighted Laborites with the purpose of securing their position. And the capitalists will do likewise.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0993.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But it is not honorable when some, as for instance, the coal kings of Pennsylvania, make an attempt to lure thousands of workers from England, under the pretext, that there was not a sufficiency of workingmen in America and that therefore the wages are high.</p>
   <p>The money kings are afraid of a rebellion among the slaves and, therefore, eager for a new reserve from England.-</p>
   <p>Using the booming of business that way, they are digging their own graves.--Hold to our principles, and never enter into any compromise. To these sentiments, Mr. Wiener gave support by saying, that he too is against compromises, but would favor it in case the party in order to succeed in special issues would unite with the before mentioned parties, and thus develop a strength, which would even be sufficient to elect a presidential candidate. Thorsmark replied to this, that he is not opposed to a coalition on practical questions, and only spoke against the jeopardizing of important party principles to obtain alliances.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
