<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-20">Mar. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[Vote for Fitzpatrick, Not Thompson]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter to the Editor)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1239</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1239.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-20">Mar. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[VOTE FOR FITZPATRICK, NOT THOMPSON]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter to the Editor)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although Mr. K. S., in his contribution yesterday, did his level best to justify the administration, or rather the semblance of an administration, of Mayor Thompson, I cannot agree with him, but am duty-bound as a loyal citizen (born in Chicago) to call attention to the Mayor's many mistakes, etc.</p>
   <p>1. Although William Hale Thompson made a written promise to the Vereinigten Gesellschaften (Allied Societies) that he would not revive the old Sunday law, if he should be elected, one of his first acts as chief executive of our city was the closing of saloons on Sunday.</p>
   <p>2. Before his election he had a secret understanding with the prohibitionists that he would act as I have stated. That act in itself should be sufficient reason why nobody should vote for him.</p>
   <p>By his act William Hale Thompson has done more than the prohibitionists of our <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1240.jpg" n="2"/>whole country, more than all prohibitionists could have done in years. Now every saloon is to be closed on and after July 1, and the people who worked in them are to be dismissed; innumerable other businesses are effected thereby; and yet he nonchalantly attempts to gain liberal votes.</p>
   <p>3. It was not Thompson, but I, who wrote the Chicago Tribune a serious letter, requesting earnestly that this publication cease writing spiteful editorials against German-Americans, because they merely aroused hatred and prejudice. Yet it was but a week later when another objectionable editorial appeared. Again I acted, for the sake of justice, when a theater on Madison Street showed the film, "The Kaiser, The Beast". The Mayor should never have given permission for the performance, because the picture could only be considered vile.</p>
   <p>4. Months ago William Hale Thompson ordered an investigation of all coldstorage warehouses, which are filled to the brim with food, and although he and the city have the power to provide relief, these officials and so-called <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1241.jpg" n="3"/>humanitarians permit matters to go on unchanged.</p>
   <p>5. The city administration has incurred an indebtedness of five million dollars. When Thompson entered upon his mayoral duties there was a balance of three million dollars--a fine situation, which speaks for itself.</p>
   <p>6. According to latest reports there are sixty-three persons for every available position. Is it a wonder, then, that murder and robbery are everyday occurrences in Chicago? Still the Mayor spends but one hour daily in his office. He should exercise all diligence to remedy the situation. If he has executive ability, the results do not show it.</p>
   <p>7. How about his Commonwealth Edison stock which is worth $117,500? Robert Sweitzer also owns fifty thousand dollars'worth of People's Gas, Light, &amp; Coke Company stock.</p>
   <p>Every worker, man or woman, and every small businessman should vote for the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1242.jpg" n="4"/>Labor Party, which is sponsoring the mayoral candidacy of John Fitzpatrick. He has been President of the American Federation of Labor [Editor's note: John Fitzpatrick actually is President of the Chicago Federation of Labor] for twelve years, and enjoys a good reputation among union people. That is why sixty-one locals have endorsed his candidacy and the entire ticket of the Labor Party. Since the large newspapers say nothing about his candidacy nor about the meetings which are held in his behalf, the entire labor ticket should be elected.</p>
   <p>Therefore, fellow citizens, do not let the old parties deceive you in this election--only to laugh at you after election.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Charles Bechstein.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
