<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-09">Apr. 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Endangered Right of Self-Administration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-09">Apr. 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">ENDANGERED RIGHT OF SELF-ADMINISTRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A number of candidates for the coming primaries have taken the view that the problem of prohibition is no issue in itself. One can agree with this view only in part. Prohibition may not be an immediate issue this spring, but beyond all doubt it may become an issue this fall or at the latest in the fall of 1928. The anti-prohibition landslide has certainly gotten under way and will not attain its highest point until the people, in one manner or another, have given their decision in the matter. For this reason a large number of voters will be guided at the coming primaries by candidates who will voice views on prohibition.</p>
   <p>Otherwise, the question still remains an issue, but perhaps only indirectly. In these elections the prerogatives of the states will be an issue as against the usurping of the rights on the part of the Federal government. Whenever any government takes it upon itself to regulate the consumption of alcoholic drinks, then we say that the states should be concerned with it. This right <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1213.jpg" n="2"/>was taken from the states by the eighteenth amendment, and many more rights will be wrenched from them if all those were to have their way who further the centralization of the powers of government. In this connection, let us point to the endeavors to create a new state department for education in Washington which will be given the task of bringing about uniformity in methods of education throughout the whole country. Let us further mention the ostensible abuses made by the interstate communication commissions, and their impositions upon state communication commissions. Other examples are the aborted attempts to regulate the protection of children by national legislation, and the plan to punish states in which lynchings have occurred. It is nothing but another means of bringing officers of the state under the jurisdiction of the Federal government.</p>
   <p>These examples could be multiplied with ease. But they suffice to justify to warning that the people are about to sell a considerable part of their rights of self-administration for dubious advantages, not unlike Esau, who sold his birthright for a mess of pottage. Eternal watchfulness is the price of freedom. <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1214.jpg" n="3"/>As soon as the people relax in their watchfulness, powers begin to rise who intend to deprive them of pearl after pearl in the crown of their sovereignty. Their motives are not bad, to be sure. For those who jeopardize the people in their freedom do so unconsciously. They hold the weakening of states' rights as necessary in the interest of the nation, without intending to dig the grave for democracy. But they do it, in fact; for the greater the circle of administrators gets to be, the smaller will be the influence of the individual citizen upon the activities of the government. The rock upon which democracy is founded is local self-administration. Upon it is built the governments of the states, while the national administration is based on the structures of the individual states.</p>
   <p>Today there is a strong inclination to circumvent state and local government, and thus lead people as with a leash. Against such tendencies no protest is strong enough. The means to protest are the elections, including the next primaries. Chicago's citizens should, in principle, elect only such candidates to office, to Congress, and to the legislature, whom they know would decidedly exert themselves in favor of local and state self-administration. How en-dangered <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1215.jpg" n="4"/>is Chicago's local self-administration, the city's voters have experienced many times to their own peril. Every Chicagoan knows that the local voters do not have the same number of legislative representatives to which the constitution entitles them. This is why they do not possess the influence which should be theirs when it comes to the distribution of the state taxes paid by themselves. Every Chicagoan knows that the city is not even the unrestrained owner of its streets, as legislature and Federal government are interfering in affairs which are essentially no one else's concern but of the city's population. Therefore, the voter who wants to preserve his influence upon the administration will have to vote for such candidates who publicly promise to fight emphatically for the preservation or recapturing, as the case may be, of this very influence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
