<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-02-19">February 19, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting at Westphal's Hall.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0868</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0868.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-02-19">February 19, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING AT WESTPHAL'S HALL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Socialist movement is on the ascendant. Large crowds attending meetings, etc, are an indication that they want to put a stop for the almost unbearable conditions. Comrade Winnen was appointed Chairman at this meeting and comrades Scholz, Schwab and Migalanda, Secretaries. First speaker was comrade Spies addressing the audience in English.</p>
   <p>He said:- "The fundamental idea on which Society was built was to protect every member belonging to this Society, and thereby promoting the general welfare. In the course of years, this has changed. The primitive beginning of civilization changed to a system which deprives the masses of their rights while a comperative few took possession of land and of means needed for production. The worker is the prey of the exploiter with no consideration shown him. He gave a short sketch of the dreadful disaster in Braidwood denouncing the company for lack of responsibility and neglect</p>
   <p>"Wealth was produced by the masses, therefore it is theirs, and they ought to have a right to it. In Chicago alone there are 10,000 to 15,000 person unemployed; the Press giving the excuse that there is no demand for production,- which is a natural cause for unemployment. "</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0869.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>the tools of production who live from the earnings of other people.</p>
   <p>It can not be expected that these conditions will change, unless the exploited and deprived worker himself puts a stop to it.</p>
   <p>A relief from unemployment can be obtained only by introducing a shorter working day, abolishing child labor and by the exclusion of women workers to a large extent. The radical cure for unemployment is the removal of the system of exploitation and to see to it that the parasites work, unless they prefer to starve to death. It is necessary for every worker to join an organization, which spells power.</p>
   <p>I. Resolutions:-Considering that class opposition is becoming more intense in America and the so-called freedom of the workers becomes more of an illusion as time goes on and,-</p>
   <p>II. Considering that the ruling capitalist class deals death through starvation, when unjustly discharging the worker and committing other crimes, when they neglect to afford the worker the simplest precautions to protect his life and,-</p>
   <p>III. Considering that labor has nothing to look forward to but oppression, while those oppressors are quite concerned about their mules, as the dreadful catastrophe at Braidwood proved again, it has been decided to urge <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0870.jpg" n="3"/>labor to organize and overthrow the capitalist system installing a new and just one which would give the worker his well earned compensation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
