<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-10-01">Oct. 1, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">[Unequal Treatment for Capitalists &amp; Workers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-10-01">Oct. 1, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">[UNEQUAL TREATMENT FOR CAPITALISTS &amp; WORKERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Milton Weston, a millionaire in Harrisburg, had a law suit against the Pennsylvania Fuel Co., in 1883, contesting the possession of a natural gas well. The well, being in the hands of the Pennsylvania Fuel Co., was the scene of a forceful attack by Weston's workers who were ordered there by him to make the opposing crew evacuate the well or to shoot those workers down with fire-arms supplied by Weston.</p>
   <p>His coolies did as ordered and killed one and wounded three of their opponents. Weston was indicted for "incitement to murder with deadly consequences" and afterwards sentenced.</p>
   <p>But how? Not, like Spies and his comrades, to death, and not to life-long imprisonment either or even to 15 years, but listen, and be surprised - to only five years in the penitentiary. Now comes even a better part.</p>
   <p>A few days ago this man was discharged from the prison as pardoned after serving half of his term only. The reason given was that he thought that "right was on his side", a right to kill people who had nothing whatsoever to do with his quarrel or suits.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0671.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>By comparing these two cases we find that in each, one man was killed and several wounded. But in one case, seven men were given the death penalty, and one a 15-year penitentiary term, although it could not be proven that they even knew the man who committed the crime, while in the other case it was proven that the accused not only knew the murderer but that he himself ordered that deed which was committed solely on account of his order.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless there were seven men sentenced to death in the first case, while in the latter the confessed criminal got five years, and is already being pardoned after only three years.</p>
   <p>Even the most fanatic defenders of our present mode of society cannot deny that Spies and his comrades had the best intentions in their speeches and writings. They saw that the working class was suppressed, enslaved and harrassed in the interest of a few who lived in luxury and disregarded those who created fortunes for those few.</p>
   <p>The fact cannot be changed that Spies and his comrades not only had no personal advantage in their minds, but were confronted with great trouble, in <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0672.jpg" n="3"/>seeking the realization of their ideals, which they endured like heroes.</p>
   <p>How different was that Harrisburg murderer! No ideals, but plain murder for robbery, to get possession of something that someone else had.</p>
   <p>It is lower than robbery, because the criminal is an intelligent person and a millionaire whom necessity did not force to rob but who just wanted to add some more millions to his fortune.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless the noble pioneers of Chicago's working class were murdered in cold blood or imprisoned, while that man, that convicted dirty murderer and robber is being pardoned after three years, because he thought that "right was on his side".</p>
   <p>But August Spies and his comrades were poor workers who had nothing but warm hearts and ardent desires to help the suppressed, while Weston is a millionaire.</p>
   <p>You workers, fold your hands and send your thanks to heaven for American justice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
