<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Fackel</title>,
<date when="1881-06-19">June 19th, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Meeting.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>DIE FACKEL</title>,
<date when="1881-06-19">June 19th, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Meeting.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bakers meeting, which was held yesterday at 70 North Clark Street, did not have as large an attendance as it was expected. After the president Mr. Eschenbach opened the meeting. The minutes of the last meeting were read, and accepted. Thereafter Dr. Ernest Schmidt was requested, to deliver the speech, which has been announced some time ago, dealing with the question:"What is the influence of nightwork and heat, upon the human organism?"</p>
   <p>Black slavery has replaced white slavery, but the worst slavery is still with us, and the time will come, when it will be abolished. During the 25 years of my practice as M.D., I can not recall one instance, when an employer had taken enough of interest in his employee, and would say to me: Here is a man who has worked for me about ten years; do what you can for him, and I will pay the bill.</p>
   <p>The owners of black slaves, have to pay a good deal, before they get into the possession of human material, but the white slave drivers are only interested in their workers as long, as they are well and can be driven. All these conditions have to be changed. He was interrupted many times during his speech, with a wild <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0098.jpg" n="2"/>applause. He earned the gratitude of the bakers, which was expressed by the President Mr. Eschenbach. Following ensued a debate, as to the proper procedure in making their demands.</p>
   <p>One speaker proposed a 12 hour working day, which was accepted by general voting. The abolishment of the boarding system, was also accepted by a majority of votes. Then the wage question, and the establishment of a registry office, have been discussed. All these demands have been generally accepted, and the president of the Union requested, to work out the plan, and submit such for an approval, at next Saturday's meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
