<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-01-30">Jan. 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Come Out of Your Trance!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1338</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1338.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-01-30">Jan. 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">COME OUT OF YOUR TRANCE!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the many reasons why the Germans have no political influence in this country is their inclination (due to their modesty) to let other people "make politics". It is a well-known fact that we Germans are very good at criticising. We do an excellent job of analyzing the shortcomings of the administration. We even go so far as to give advice as to how things should be done and take it upon ourselves to make detailed suggestions as to how matters could be improved.</p>
   <p>As organizers, we have a reputation; our thoroughness and honesty is not denied even by our worst enemies, but rather, unreservedly recognized. The only argument which can be advanced against us is the "disgraceful" fact that we are Germans, who recently have been promoted to "barbarians" and "Huns." Everything our enemies tell about us is accepted with a grin of satisfaction.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1339.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But when it comes to draw the logical conclusions and co-operate actively to put our [German] useful ideas into practice, we withdraw into our shell. Vote? What for? [Translator's note: There seems to be no coherent thought within the last four or five sentences, but that is the original text, of which the foregoing is a close translation.] These politicians do what they want anyway! Whether I vote or not won't help matters any! This and similar arguments are heard from citizens, who are always criticising.</p>
   <p>Let's do away with this sloppy attitude, and cut out this criticism that does not get us any place! Action is the password. The German element has to gain the position to which it is entitled by numbers. The only way we can promote our own welfare and that of the Republic is to do our duty as citizens. Therefore, we repeat: Let yourselves be registered next Tuesday. If you are not registered you cannot vote. We need one hundred thousand German women! Get out and pitch in! It is your privilege! Make use of it!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
