<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-08-03">Aug. 3, 1935</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0442</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0442.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-08-03">Aug. 3, 1935</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>wages or better working conditions, the strike could endanger public safety and prevent the transportation of necessary food. Although one could raise the objection that the Government has no right to interfere until such a condition really exists, that would not be a valid objection.</p>
   <p>In this connection it should be noted that the Third International, which is now holding its seventh congress in Moscow, has adopted the principle of non-intervention in the affairs of the communistic parties of other countries. If this was done in good faith, and the resolution is honestly carried out, the Soviet Government has relinquished a very vital principle. The Soviet Government is not the Third International, but the ideas and aims of the two are identical. The only important object of the Third International is to win all other nations over to communism. Hence, a world-wide revolution is, and must remain, the most important item of its program.</p>
   <p>And so it appears to be highly improbable that the Third International will <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0443.jpg" n="3"/>strictly follow its decision not to interfere with the affairs of communistic parties in other countries; for it forfeited the right to its own existence, as well as the right of the Soviet Government to exist. The idea of a world revolution is inseparably united with both the Third International and the Soviet Government. Soviet Russia is merely an economic, religious, cultural experiment. It can develop into a truly communistic state only if all other countries or the world also adopt communism.</p>
   <p>The Soviet Government's Committee on Foreign Affairs is, of course, equivalent to the office of the minister of foreign affairs of other countries, and to the Department of State of the United States. Its routine work is practically the same as that of our Department of State. However, the main object of the Soviet Committee on Foreign Affairs is to bring about a world revolution, and thus it is, and can be, nothing but the executive organ of the Third International, although the two are allegedly separate bodies. The <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0444.jpg" n="4"/>Moscow Congress apparently knows this, for it has greatly modified its resolution. A subsequent provision of the resolution states that the Third International is to direct its entire attention to general issues of the labor movement, and that its chief task consists in persuading the working classes of the entire world to fight Fascism.</p>
   <p>Thus it seems that the second provision of the resolution cancels the first provision. The agitators of the Communists have caused the governments of many countries more than one severe headache. When the Moscow Government received complaints about this activity of the agitators it usually replied that the propaganda was carried on by the Third International, and that Moscow had neither authority nor influence over that organization. Theoretically that was true, but not actually. Closer scrutiny reveals that the resolution of the Third International was evidently merely a trick to make the world believe that the Soviet Government is not responsible for the propaganda of the Third International. Moscow very likely knows that it is not <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0445.jpg" n="5"/>deceiving anybody by its explanation; but Mr. Litvinov will find it very convenient to direct the attention of those governments that complain about the aggressive methods of Russian emissaries to the resolution of the Third International.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
