<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-12-04">December 4th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Hopkins and Swift.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1438</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1438.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1893-12-04">December 4th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">HOPKINS AND SWIFT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editorial:-</p>
   <p>As it will not come to an independent citizen's movement in Chicago just as in any other American City, so the much hated political "machines" have to undertake the task of nominating the candidates for the,(in reality) non-political Municipal offices.</p>
   <p>Therefore it should not surprise anybody, that last Saturday in the Republican as well as in the Democratic convention a man has won who is no orphan in the line of politics...</p>
   <p>...Therefore it can be presumed that the voters in general stick to the candidate of their party. The German Democrats and Independents have, in any case, not the slightest reason to vote against Hopkins and for Swift. That the Democrats put up no German candidate, was the fault of some "leaders" of the Germans with whom accounts can be settled at the proper time.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1439.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Hopkins is not responsible for this. On the other side John P. Hopkins is a true friend of the Germans, a thorough liberal and tolerant man and, of all things, not a hypocrite. How in the later connection it stands with "Deacon" Swift cannot be said with such a certainty. In general the "deacons" do not count as very hot admirers of the German views of life.</p>
   <p>The German citizens would lose all political influence, if on December 19th, they stay behind the warm stove. It is in their own interest to participate in complete formation at the by-election and to keep that party at the wheel, which stood up so manly for the just demands of the Germans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
