<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-23">Feb. 23, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">More State Socialism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-23">Feb. 23, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">MORE STATE SOCIALISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Undoubtedly the political economy of the Washington Administration, which aims at far-reaching interference in all phases of industrial life by national authorities, appears to most observers to be a direct result of the depression, as a means, devised by President Roosevelt and the professors who are members of the so-called "brain trust" to combat the depression. Future historians who will view present events from a greater height and distance, will discover in them the outflux of world-wide tendencies that are merely coincidental to the battle against the depression.</p>
   <p>Many people have already pointed out that there is a parallel between the political economy of the United States and that of national socialism in Germany. Now similar tendencies are noticeable also in conservative and traditionally individualistic England. The iron and steel industries of <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0461.jpg" n="2"/>England are contemplating the introduction of a kind of planned economy which is to be carried on under the supervision of the English Government. It is significant that this plan did not originate with the theorists, the Government, or employees, but with the leaders of these industries.</p>
   <p>Two years ago industry was in a deplorable condition. At that time the Government decided to comply with the urgent request of industry by placing a 33 1/3 per cent import tax on iron and steel. However, it was impressed upon the leaders of the industry that this protective tariff was to be only a temporary measure. The industry was expected to adjust itself to changed conditions, and to be able, after a few years, to maintain itself without the aid of a high protective tariff.</p>
   <p>The protective tariff term will expire in October of this year, and a committee consisting of members of the steel industry has devised a reorganization plan which is to be put into operation by the time the protective tariff term expires. The plan provides for the merging of the entire British steel industry into one <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0462.jpg" n="3"/>gigantic trust, for the purpose of systematizing planned economy, which is to include importation and exportation, production, prices, purchase of raw materials, and the general regulation of the industry. The control of the industry is to be placed into the hands of a committee in which the various interested groups are represented. Later this plan is to be extended to all parts of the Kingdom of Great Britain. The plan was worked out by a committee under the chairmanship of Charles Mitchell. Its aim is to reorganize the entire industry according to the principle of planned economy, but it is against operation under Government control.</p>
   <p>Sir William Firth, the head of the London iron and steel exchange, which is the great central market for steel, iron, and other metals and metal products, thinks that the plan is not sufficiently comprehensive. He demands that the industry voluntarily place itself under direct control of the Government, at least temporarily. He is of the opinion that this step is necessary for the regulation of exports. He points out that other countries can undersell England in world markets, either because their production costs are lower, or <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0463.jpg" n="4"/>because they are subsidized by their governments, or because the exchange policies of certain countries afford the manufacturers and merchants of those countries special advantages.</p>
   <p>Then, Sir William Firth also calls attention to the fact that the British iron and steel industry cannot increase its exports because it has no reserve fund to use in a war of competition against other countries. He claims that the plan which the committee has worked out merely provides for the elimination of underselling in home markets, but does not protect exporters. All this is significant.</p>
   <p>Apparently all the leaders of this great industry are agreed that economic individualism has outlived its usefulness. They disagree only on the question as to whether the trust which is to be formed, shall operate independently, or under control of the Government. They all agree that planned economy in the true sense of the word is absolutely necessary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0464.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This is so much more remarkable because the steel industry of Great Britain has made great strides towards recovery since 1932. It employs about a million people. The production of iron increased from 3,600,000 tons in 1932 to 4,154,000 tons in 1933, and the production of steel from 5,500,000 to 7,305,000 tons during the same period. Despite these encouraging results, a radical reorganization of the industry according to state socialistic principles, was decided upon. Socialism as a political factor has disappeared from nearly all countries, but socialistic ideas, especially state socialism are on the march. All countries are strongly opposing the propaganda which emanates from Moscow, but all of them are imitating the economic structure of the Soviet Government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
