<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-10-15">Oct. 15, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">End of the Street Car Strike.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-10-15">Oct. 15, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">END OF THE STREET CAR STRIKE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The strike has come to an end and we can state to our satisfaction that the result was a victory for the workers, a defeat of the monopoly.</p>
   <p>No doubt the victory could have been more far-reaching if the workers had taken our advice and thrown their damned good nature to the devil.</p>
   <p>But as Yerkes was skyhigh superior to them in disregard and bluff and as under present conditions, a ruthless intriguant almost every time scores above sincere good nature, it was to be expected that the strikers would not wholly go through with their demands.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0237.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are even convinced that the Philadelphia convict would have scored an absolute victory if the whole working-class of the North Side had not sided so energetically with the strikers. That the workers achieved a considerable success is to be attributed to this fact only, in our opinion at least.</p>
   <p>But they should have now an unconditional victory; none of their only too well-justified demands should have been disregarded. By all means, they should not have agreed to the scabs remaining and to the expulsion of about 200 men, supposed to have been active during the riot.</p>
   <p>The latter concession seems to us equal to suicide for the organization of the employees.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0238.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These 195 supposed agitators did not do any more in the worst case than let themselves be driven to actions inspired by the baseness of their slave-drivers, which, although they should have been abandoned, cannot be condemned, either lawfully or morally.</p>
   <p>That the organization for which these men stood abandoned them and allowed Yorkes to put them temporarily on the black list - until a jury passes judgment - is a procedure which created only very grave doubts among the members as to the value of their organization.</p>
   <p>The same difficulties will be encountered by the association on the subject of remaining scabs, as this constitutes a continuous source of humiliation - for the thinking worker to be forced to associate with people who proved to be traitors in the common cause of the proletariats.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0239.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Even if it should perhaps be possible to get rid of some of these people, the majority will stay, without a doubt, and just those thick-skinned and basest ones who will always play the scoundrel against their colleagues.</p>
   <p>If, in spite of all this, we express our joy about the course of this strike we do this principally because of the feelings of solidarity between the employees of the North Side and those of the West Side, proven in this case in such a splendid way.</p>
   <p>Such a confirmation of homogeneity makes up for small defects, especially when it concerns comparatively conservative organizations.</p>
   <p>Besides, it is at all times an achievement to gain a victory over a man of Yerkes' kind, no matter how small.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0240.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The victory is more important in this case became the way laying "baron" disposed of the complete police force of the city of Chicago and his corporation was thus able to "get away with anything."</p>
   <p>Any one who saw the declaration of the great martial law of Madison Street last Friday will be able to get an approximate conception of what the tyrant Roche did to suppress the strike and help to assure a complete victory for his friend Yerkes. We really doubt that the Berlin or Viennese police force would have taken such a despotic regime upon themselves as did ours on that day on Madison Street. Under such circumstances the victory gives twice as much joy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
