<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-02-18">Feb. 18, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">In Regard to the Strike of the Bakers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-02-18">Feb. 18, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">IN REGARD TO THE STRIKE OF THE BAKERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>You have published an article in today's issue wherein you say, that the strike at the Schmidt Bakery on Clybourne Avenue is unjustified and, amongst other statements you claim that the Schmidt Baking Company only ascertained the reasons for this strike in the press, and that Schmidt had made a contract with the majority of his men, which does not expire until July, 1892. I beg, that you may also show the other side:</p>
   <p>1. Mr. Schmidt has not first read about the grievances in the press, instead he was informed by a committee of the two German Bakery Unions, eight days before the strike, and, in order to settle the controversy peaceably, on the very evening prior to the strike, a committee was sent to Mr. Schmidt. He dismissed them with the words, that it was immaterial to him, whether his men strike now, or on May 1st.</p>
   <p>2. Only a minority of Mr. Schmidt's employees, merely 11 men signed the agreement. Thereby they committed an offense against their co-workers, since the rules of the organization do not permit separate contracts with individual members, without <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0223.jpg" n="2"/>the knowledge of the union.</p>
   <p>3. It is not true, that Mr. Schmidt has obtained substitutes, since in several German and English papers, want ads offered jobs there, and today, the Swedish Bakers also joined in the walk out.</p>
   <p>Very respectfully,</p>
   <p>August Mueller,</p>
   <p>#252 - 43rd Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
