<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1875-02-24">Feb. 24, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">Load Your Guns, They Will Be Needed To-Morrow to Shoot Communists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1119</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1119.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1875-02-24">Feb. 24, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">LOAD YOUR GUNS, THEY WILL BE NEEDED TO-MORROW TO SHOOT COMMUNISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The camp of the communists presents a spectacle of unprecedented activity. Ever since Sunday, their leaders have been in earnest consultation as to the manner in which the proposed raid on the office of the Relief and Aid Society shall be conducted, and have listened attentively to the numerous propositions made by the officers of the different sections which are scattered all over the city. The press of their organ, the Vorbote, is constantly in motion turning out thousands of hand-bills and posters, by which the workingmen are to be invited to attend the mass-meetings called for to-night. The speakers, and principally Messrs. Klings, Krause, and Nusser, are preparing elaborate addresses to fire the hearts of the malcontents and arouse them to imprudent action. In short, everything is done to make the proposed coup d'etat a grand success, and from present appearances it seems as if La Salle Street would on to-morrow be the scene of an immense gathering of people.</p>
   <p>The proclamation, which is printed in the English, German, Bohemian, and Scandinavian languages, and distributed in the various factories and large manufacturing <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1120.jpg" n="2"/>establishments, read as follows:</p>
   <p>To the Citizens of Chicago</p>
   <p>While the misery and the destitution now prevailing in the city of Chicago has reached an unprecedented climax, and the great mass of unemployed workingmen and artisans are at present without sufficient clothing, food, and fuel, nay, a great portion thereof is without even a shelter, thus craving immediate help, the Relief and Aid Society refuses to employ the money entrusted to them for the purpose of relieving those destitute people, referring the sufferers to the county agents, viz.; to the pockets of the taxpayers, as the capitalists are paying few or no taxes; preferring to fight the city claims in court.</p>
   <p>According to the company's own statement, $347,000 is in their hands, which are deposited with the banks, belonging to the very indentical taxfighters. The Relief and Aid Society pays, if we believe public journals, $60,000 annually to officials, that to do not care to relieve the really needy, but squander the money upon favorites, or use them for their own personal gratification.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1121.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As the Relief and Aid Society is now refusing the necessary support to the really needy, throwing the burden upon the taxpayer, speculating with the funds solely destined to relieve the poor, and supporting therewith a mass of idle officials, leaving the citizens of this city to starvation and cold, it is the duty of every good citizen to protect against this shameful proceeding and to demand a decided and immediate change of this state of affairs.</p>
   <p>As a thorough and decisive abolition of the existing corruption and the shameful wholesale robbery of greedy politicians has become a question of life for the community, all citizens of Chicago affected by the pressure of the present state of things, are invited to attend the above meetings. Nothing but firm, prompt, and concerted action can procure help and assistance to the poor and relief to the taxpayers.</p>
   <p>Come all! Down with corruption! Down with all swindlers! Put your shoulders to the wheel and soon we shall live to see better times. United we can accomplish everything; single-handed we can accomplish nothing!</p>
   <p>Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1122.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The principal features of the news contained in these two columns are embodied in the following synoptical review.</p>
   <p>A few of that blood-thirsty crowd are running their necks into the halter.</p>
   <p>Thousands of incendiary proclamations scattered broadcast in the city.</p>
   <p>The militia and police preparing for the impending conflict.</p>
   <p>The Relief and Aid Society will give no more aid to vagrant fire-brands.</p>
   <p>The Authorities will "Make it Warm" for the malcontents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
