<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-09-25">September 25th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">[To the Chicago Unions]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-09-25">September 25th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">[TO THE CHICAGO UNIONS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "Arbeiter Zeitung" which is a paper for the laboring class, and as such, took upon itself the representation and promotion of the Unions labor organizations; but our task can not be successful, unless the Unions themselves take a hand in this matter, and supply us with the necessary material, meaning trade conditions, which we in turn would bring before the public's eye. We would advise the Unions to furnish us with statistics as to the machines in use, and how many workers have lost their jobs, on account of installing new and better machines.</p>
   <p>Only in this manner, can the public be informed of existing conditions. The workers themselves are urged to keep track of the number of accidents and, the cause of such. They also have to keep statistics, as to the number of days, unemployed during the year.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0102.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All of this, requires very little effort, for which the Unions would qualify much better than, any person who could not give correct information. What other aim could an organization of clear thinking people pursue, but to eliminate undesirable conditions, and to work toward cultural progress in general. By this we mean, the welfare of all people, with first consideration for the oppressed and needy. The oppressed ones, are the working men, and as their interests are contrary to the interests of the capitalists , it is important that Labor unities because only through strength in unity, can they fight against the capitalist interests.</p>
   <p>We have noticed the mistake made by the Union organizations, that the active members engage in preaching, to get organized, etc.but dont take any step to effect, what they preach. Become active in the sense, we have pointed out. This will create an interest of workingman outside the Unions, and eventually cause them, to join and work toward one goal. To action! Chicago unions, get to work for your own salvation, and the support of the "Arbeiter Zeitung" is yours.</p>
   <p>If you will, success will not be lacking.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
