<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-03-02">March 2, 1914</date><title level="a">There Are Still Unemployed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0433</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0433.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-03-02">March 2, 1914</date><title level="a">There Are Still Unemployed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Secretary of Commerce Redfield, a few days ago, expressed his conviction that the complaint about general unemployment is a fairy tale, with which only party party politics can be carried on, but, in fact that nothing of the kind exists in the United States under the present administration. And now comes, suddenly the report that a national investigation of the unemployed has been started. Therefore, it seems that there are unemployed in such masses, that the same administration to which Mr. Redfield belongs, has found it necessary to institute a nation-wide investigation.</p>
   <p>All municipalities of the country are directed to send policemen from house to house, who not only should establish the number of unemployed, but also the causes for same. This order of the Government is practical in but one way, and that is by its means the fact of general unemployment will be proved.</p>
   <p>To the unemployed there will be no special advantage as a result of the investigation. Till the cumbersome investigating apparatus begins to move, <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0434.jpg" n="2"/>and finishes its work, the unemployed might starve ten times, or driven to desperation, undoubtedly commit unlawful acts.</p>
   <p>It would be the duty of the Administration, after being compelled to observe the sinister results of the tariff reduction, and the economic experiments, to start immediately the relief projects in the country. The "Watchful Waiting", which became the motto of our Government, should under no circumstances be applied to this burning economical question. The stomach cries for bread and cannot be consoled by the outcome of a prolonged investigation.</p>
   <p>General Coxey is already organizing his army, and if he succeeds in carrying through his plan to order 500,000 people on April 16th to Washington, the concentration of such desperate men, and the consequences, even if they are guided by the most peaceful motives, cannot be foreseen. To avert such danger through adequate measures should be the earnest problem of the authorities. It certainly would be a risky game, if they should try to quiet the grumbling stomachs with police sticks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
