<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-05-02">May 2, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[National Turner District Expels Julius Volteich for Anarchism]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0609</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0609.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-05-02">May 2, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[NATIONAL TURNER DISTRICT EXPELS JULIUS VOLTEICH FOR ANARCHISM]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Members of the National Turner District held their first annual convention yesterday at Freiberg's Hall. The are delegates from the Chicago Turngemeinde, South Side Turngemeinde, the Central Turn Verein, and the Germania Turn Verein. These societies are the conservative Turners. They seceded from the parent body because the Chicago Turngemeinde, the largest Turner society in the city, had expelled Julius Volteich for anarchistic speeches. They were ordered to reinstate him by the parent body (the Chicago Turner District) and refused. Then the Turngemeinde seceded and was joined by the foregoing societies in forming the National Turner District. At yesterday's meeting Theodore Oehme, the First Speaker, read his message reporting a membership of 1,450 and a good financial outlook. Louis Nettelhorst was made temporary First Speaker. There were represented the Central Turn Verein. South Side Turngemeinde, Chicago Turngemeinde, and German Turngemeinde.</p>
   <p>A banquet was given the delegates by the South Side Turngemeinde.</p>
   <p>A lively debate took place on the question of carrying their complaints against the Chicago Turner District for expelling them to the North American Turner Bund.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0610.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was finally decided to do so. This means a final fight for supremacy in the highest court of American Turners between the Reds, or Anarchists, and the conservative Turners. Should it transpire that the Reds rule there, it will mean a split of the Turner Bund, for the Turners of New York, Minnesota, and several other States will withdraw and unite in forming a new national bund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
