<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-05">Apr. 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Coming Elections Cause Tension in the Parties</title><title level="a" type="sub">Many Political Meetings Arranged</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-05">Apr. 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">COMING ELECTIONS CAUSE TENSION IN THE PARTIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Many Political Meetings Arranged</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The last week of the primaries campaign began today. In the various political camps, especially on the side of the Republicans, among whom the struggle is particularly fierce, work goes on under high pressure. During the midday hours the various candidates and their friends give speeches in downtown theaters. Their audiences are composed mostly of businessmen and employees, with a scattering of women. In the evenings, ward meetings are held in the various parts of the city, where appeals are made to the voters. There the merits of the candidates and the demerits of the opposition candidates are made clear.</p>
   <p>Edward R. Litsinger, member of the board of tax revisions, and other prominent Republicans, all friends of Senator Deneen, were the speakers in a well-attended midday meeting at the Princess Theater. Frank L. Smith, Republican candidate for United States Senator, spoke at the Cort Theater and the leaders of the Crowe-Barrett group spoke for their candidates for county offices at the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1217.jpg" n="2"/>Olympic Theater.</p>
   <p>Among the many prominent citizens who give support to the candidacy of the present municipal judge, Daniel P. Trude, is Dr. Frank Billings, the widely known physician; we too, can recommend him [Trude] with good conscience. He is not only a talented expert of the law, but likewise has some medical knowledge which will serve him in excellent stead as county judge. (sic)</p>
   <p>One more candidate to Congress, William Gaughrin, running for the Democratic nomination from the Tenth District, has openly declared himself against prohibition and for modification of the Volstead act. The district, inhabited largely by a liberal population, has been represented in Washington for many years by the "dry" Carl R. Chindblum. It depends, therefore, on the people of the district to get some action in this respect.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
