<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Illinois Staats-Zeitung)
<date when="1877-10-07">October 7, 1877</date>
<title level="a">Labor Convention</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_1097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Illinois Staats-Zeitung)
<date when="1877-10-07">October 7, 1877</date>
<title level="a">LABOR CONVENTION</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A convention of the Labor Party, which considers itself the ruling party of the future, was held on the South Side last night.... Mr. W. B. Barr, one of the speakers said, that capital is politically powerless without the wage earners' votes. Only as long as Labor is willing to be led by the nose by capitalists, is it necessary for Labor to endure the present oppression, which fault lies with them. He had proof that taxpayers are none else than the workingmen, therefore the proposal that only taxpayers should be allowed to vote, would ascertain labor's rule in public life.</p>
   <p>The organizing of the party took place then with the election of P.T. Morgan, President; H. Stahl, Vice-President and A. Vorschuh, Secretary. Messrs. Simmons, Schilling, Laufermann, Barr and Belshradsky were assigned to the task of working out resolutions, which are as followz:</p>
   <p>Resolved to ask the abolition of the contract system, which is largely responsible for the corruption in the county administration. All public work of the county should be under county management and under the supervision of their able officials.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_1098.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Resolved: that if we should come out victorious we promise to give the county an honest administration, which will enable us to stop the tremendous money spending, and in course of time, the lowering of taxes would be the result.</p>
   <p>Resolved: that those candidates nominated at the Convention shall give their Christian pledge to support the platform of the Labor Party of the United States and the resolutions as well, and that this promise shall be presented to the Central Committee of Cook County....</p>
   <p>Frank A. Stauber was nominated for the office of Treasurer. Mr. A. R. Parsons received the nomination to the County Clerk's office. The nomination for County Commissioners fell upon Messrs W. B. Barr S. Caldwater, A. L. Thorsmarck, William Bichler and Max Nisle. And the choice for Superintendent of Schools fell upon Mr. John McAuliff.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
