<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-14">June 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0361</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0361.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-14">June 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For years, experts have been unanimous in their opinion that the return of prosperity has been hindered by the exorbitant wages in the building trade. Time and again it has been illustrated that, with wages as they are at present, the building of dwelling houses is a poor capital investment. Anyone investing his money in such fashion is bound to lose it. With respect to buildings for industrial and commercial purposes, the situation is somewhat more favorable. If the factory owner or businessman has to pay exorbitant prices for buildings he can, in most instances, make good his increased expenses by a small increase in the price of merchandise. But those who build houses for private use, or for renting, cannot do that. This is why building for industrial and commercial purposes has been a little more brisk of late, whereas no improvement is shown in the building of dwelling houses.</p>
   <p>Louis J. Horowitz dealt with this problem in the last issue of the Saturday <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0362.jpg" n="2"/>Evening Post. Horowitz was for many years head of the Thompson Starret Company; he is a contractor. His statements are based on the solid ground of a thorough expertness and many years of experience. Based on the material on hand, he makes the statement that wages for building workers in New York has doubled since the year 1930, as compared to the average wages between 1916 and 1918. He further states that wages in all other industries (and the costs of living as well) during that period either have not risen in the same degree or have been lowered again.</p>
   <p>Horowitz goes briefly into the reasons why building workers can realize their demands for increased wages much more easily than workers in other industries. He points out that the building owner and the contractor are always ready to grant higher wages during active building periods because they would suffer greater losses through a protracted strike. But it developed that the building industry was at last completely ruined by that practice.</p>
   <p>Continuing, the author discusses the wage scale of building workers in New York <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0363.jpg" n="3"/>between the years 1916 and 1918 inclusive, comparing it with the present wage scale, also with the wage scale at present in effect in England for some working groups. Wages for unskilled workers were at the time $3, for painters $5; wages of other classes of building workers ranged from $5 to $6.50 for an eight-hour day. At present, wages of unskilled workers are $7 to $10 (sic), for painters $9 and for all the other classes from $11.20 to $12. In England, the wages for unskilled workers are $2.16, for other classes, $2.88.</p>
   <p>Accordingly, the contention of the author that wages have doubled since 1918 is approximately right. Now, he points out that the wages of all other workers and employees are considerably lower, and that it is impossible to sell houses built with twelve-dollar wages to people who receive considerably lower wages. Horowitz emphasizes that the maintanance of exorbitant wages is to be blamed on the leaders of the workers, and not on the workers themselves, for it is the latter who have suffered the greatest losses. This can be easily proved, because for about five years building activities have been almost at a standstill, and millions of building workers have had to rely on public charity, although, with an <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0364.jpg" n="4"/>appropriate reduction of wages, they could have found profitable employment. Horowitz also points out that, owing to exorbitant building costs, the manufacturing of ready-made sectional buildings in factories is assuming increasingly greater proportions, because the sections can be easily put together. This factor threatens the very existence of the entire building trade.</p>
   <p>The statements of the contractor from New York, who expressly emphasizes that he has always enjoyed harmonious relations with his workers, show clearly that it is impossible to keep the wages of one industry on an artificially high level, when they have been reduced in other industries. This has been known for a long time. Because of the attitude of the union leaders in the building industry, the return to normal economic conditions has been retarded for years. The losses inflicted upon the national prosperity are too large to be figured out. Gravest, however, has been the suffering of the building workers themselves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
