<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-02-02">Feb. 2, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">Expensive Charity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-02-02">Feb. 2, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">EXPENSIVE CHARITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What charitable people are not our highly esteemed German notables! What sacrifices do they not make in the performance of their benevolent duty!</p>
   <p>Not only do they once in a while contribute a quarter to the Relief Fund of the Deutsche Gesellschaft, and thereby purchase that peace of conscience which proceeds from the fulfillment of the biblical commandment: "Do good and share what you have, for it pleases God," but they also undergo bodily discomfort and forego entertainment for the sake of charity!</p>
   <p>Just imagine sixteen well-fed gentlemen for more than an hour kept away from the card tables in the cozy Weine Stube yesterday, and gathered in the conference room of the Deutsche Gesellschaft in order to look over the monthly statement of their agent, and to pass resolutions for the welfare of the institution.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0141.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They listened to a long statement describing the misery of the people who had been supported by them and felt somewhat compensated for their exertion.</p>
   <p>A satiated person always gloats over pictures of suffering and misery.</p>
   <p>He might put on a serious face and he might even shed some "crocodile tears," but inwardly he laughs, because he is glad that he is better off than the others and he becomes proud of his success.</p>
   <p>The Deutsche Gesellschaft is a "benevolent" society. Just listen to this: Last month the receipts were $438.50 while the expenditures amounted to $436.29. A total of one hundred twenty five persons was given aid by them.</p>
   <p>The sum disbursed for relief amounted to $198.64. This means that the average monthly subvention by the Deutsche Cesellschaft to these one hundred twenty-five needy persons amounted to $1.59 a person.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0142.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If one deducts the relief money from the total expenditures $237.65 should be left, but where is this money?</p>
   <p>Well, it has been spent for wages of employees, or for sundry expenses of the office.</p>
   <p>It is true, and really amusing that in order to deal out charity to the amount of $198.64, the expenses exceeded the charity fund by $39.01. There must be a method even in relief, and methods cost money. The monthly account states, furthermore, that only $256.50 was collected in dues from the members of the Society.</p>
   <p>The balance, therefore, was solicited from other sources, for those in need, or for the officers of the Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0143.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>One hundred two workers the statement continues proudly, obtained jobs, while ninety-six employers called on us for labor help.</p>
   <p>This means in other words that one hundred two poor people, unacquainted with local conditions received an opportunity to be exploited by good friends of the Society.</p>
   <p>The Deutsche Gesellschaft, from this standpoint, is a pretty profitable institution. The "greenhorns" can be "hooked" by it like fish in a pond.</p>
   <p>The "benevolent gentlemen" also resolved yesterday to loan money to the Society in the future, but only on double security.</p>
   <p>The Finance committee was ordered to apply this ruling to $5,000 which had accumulated during the last months in the so-called Charity Fund.</p>
   <p>Much misery could be alleviated by the good use of this $5,000. but the <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0144.jpg" n="5"/>Deutsche Gesellschaft intends to buy a lot where it can build a monumental structure which will glorify the munificence of the Chicago German notables.</p>
   <p>The poor ones could then stand on the street in front of the building and fill their stomachs by looking at it, provided that the police do not object.</p>
   <p>Enjoyment of art is supposed to have a satisfying effect on the stomach also.</p>
   <p>We see that these notables are not as dumb as they look!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
