<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-10-20">October 20, 1882</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_3_1_0882</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0882.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-10-20">October 20, 1882</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. August Spies spoke next commenting on each phase of the Pastor's speech and causing him much embarrassment by attacking the Church. He contended that private land ownership is a denial of the right for existence for those without any such possessions which means the "Masses" therefore are not in accord with the fundamental teachings of Christianity.</p>
   <p>2. Socialism is a question of economy; politically, modern Socialism is not concerned with the centralization of government power, but is rather endeavoring to decentralize it through municipal autonomy.</p>
   <p>3. With his development the needs, too, of the individual grows. In comparison, the conditions of the working classes are at present much worse than fifty years ago.</p>
   <p>4. Too long have the oppressed people looked to the Christian Church for salvation; they awoke to learn the truth. The people are aware of the fact that the chains of slavery can not be broken by a God or Saviour but, by themselves only. on the ruins of Christianity, humanity will breathe easier. Were the bloody atrocities of the inquisition not far more barbarous than those of Nero? And the burning of a large number of witches in our country only a short time ago, an act supported by your church, was that an exhibition of Christian love and humanity? The Church is the foundation pillar of this horribly barbarous system of robbery,(Capitalism). This explains why Socialism is trying to annihilate it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0883.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Socialist Blake contended that not every Socialist is in accord with the viewpoint of Mr. Spies. Socialism asks for real Christianity but the Church has always stood on the side of the oppressor. The Catholic Church of Ireland has recently joined the party of the oppressed; the Protestant church should do likewise. Before the audience dispersed the Reverend McGregor declared that he was interested in every speaker with the exception of Mr. Spies, who, in his opinion was a scoundrel and whose loose tongue had insulted the most sacred.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
