<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-14">Mar. 14, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Krylov Branch's Entertainment</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Nekrylovetz</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-14">Mar. 14, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">KRYLOV BRANCH'S ENTERTAINMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Nekrylovetz</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although more than once in the pages of Rassviet the entertainment has been described which was given by Krylov Branch Number Eighteen of R.I.M.A.S., I am tempted to write again in more detail to Rassviet's readers about that evening. The atmosphere at the entertainment was unusual, such as I had never before observed at any place where Russians have gathered. At four o'clock the guests began to appear, cordially shaking hands with their friends and acquaintances. It seemed that all those arriving for the occasion had known one another from childhood. At 5:30 P.M. I Raskatov, master of ceremonies, greeted the guests with a few words and explained the purpose of the gathering. He reminded them that three years ago a group of five or six Russian men had made up their minds to form a branch of R.I.M.A.S. in the northwest part of the city, the Hanson Park section. The newly founded Branch was named after Krylov, the famous Russian fable writer. The initial <pb facs="5423967_3_1144.jpg" n="2"/>group had made no little effort to start the ball rolling. The men went from house to house to persuade their friends and neighbors to join the society. Seven meetings had to be called before the Branch came officially into being. By this time, three years after its foundation, the Branch has already more than sixty members regularly paying their dues. More than that, the Branch has become widely known not only in Chicago but in many other cities of the United States and Canada. The aim of the Branch, besides mutual aid, is to promote cultural, educational, and selfeducational activities.</p>
   <p>After Mr. Raskatov had spoken, Mr. A. Metelsky, president of the Branch, briefly outlined its history. He reminded his hearers of the difficulties and the obstacles which had to be overcome in the initial period. Thanks to the unwavering and concerted efforts of the initial group these difficulties were overcome. In conclusion he expressed his joy that their efforts had not been in vain and thanked the members and the friends of the Branch for their co-operation in the common cause. Mr. Metelsky in conclusion pointed out that the Branch, lacking, as it does, its own quarters, was unable to carry out the <pb facs="5423967_3_1145.jpg" n="3"/>program originally planned. For that reason at its last annual meeting it was decided to build in the district a Russian social center, and to promote this, a special committee was elected.</p>
   <p>Mr. Metelsky was followed by Mr. A. Pasiuk, president of R.I.M.A.S., who commented briefly on the achievements of the Branch. In the name of the whole Society he expressed thanks to the members of the Branch and to their officers, with ardent wishes for success in the work that remains to be done.</p>
   <p>Then the floor was taken by Mr. E. Moravsky, the editor of Rassviet, who said that people are often afraid of the word progress itself, although progress is the motive power in our lives, and Branch Number Eighteen is in many respects the most progressive of them all. The fact that in the three years of its existence it has grown in membership from seven men to sixty cannot but be considered as progress. Further on Mr. Moravsky called attention to the cultural and educational activity of the Branch.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1146.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>I. Volos next called the Branch the "right hand of the Society".</p>
   <p>Mr. W. Olesiuk, the godfather of the Branch, characterized it as the most advanced unit in the organization and advised other branches to follow the example of Branch Number Eighteen. Dr. Nedzelnitsky told the audience that the wide publicity which is enjoyed by the Krylov Branch and the prominent part which it plays in the affairs of the Society is directly due to the untiring efforts of Mr. S. Volodkin.</p>
   <p>Speaking on behalf of the Krylov School, of which he is president, Mr. Volodkin called upon Russian parents to send their children to the school or to the dance classes maintained by the Branch for the benefit of all Russian children.</p>
   <p>The speakers appeared between the musical numbers, and the guests for that reason did not feel themselves overburdened with speech making. The musical part of the program was arranged and executed entirely by pupils of the <pb facs="5423967_3_1147.jpg" n="5"/>schools or by children whose parents are members of R.I.M.A.S. Young and vivacious, the children did their best to entertain the older folks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
