<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-16">Feb. 16, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Our Life</title><title level="a" type="sub">By A. F. Bernov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1390</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1390.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-16">Feb. 16, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">OUR LIFE</title><title level="a" type="sub">By A. F. Bernov</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Let us look back, friends, on our past life, and let us think of the future. Years ago we were strong and energetic. Are we the same now? The difference is considerable. Today we are like an old machine, which is soon to be discarded and thrown on the scrap heap. Such is our life. When we are healthy and strong, we work and American dollars find their way into our pockets. Then we forget everything and everybody, even ourselves. Then, many of us consider ourselves very smart, so smart that we even refuse to speak to anybody. But when hardships befall us, we think and speak differently, and even regret the mistakes which we made in the past.</p>
   <p>With these words I wish to remind all members of the Russian colony, all Russian people--young and old--that they should not wait for the time when they will be rejected and forsaken by their friends and relatives. It is not too late to join RNzOV [Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society] which is located on Wood <pb facs="5423967_3_1391.jpg" n="2"/>Street. This is one of the best societies. In our Society, new insurance policies have been issued. We are now in a position to give every kind of insurance offered by private insurance companies, although our premiums are much lower; in other words, you pay loss and receive just as much as you would from private companies. These policies are excellent for everybody, but particularly for young people.</p>
   <p>Now it is your turn, branches of RNzOV; you should show what you can do. Our Society is not made up of bachelors alone.....Do your children belong to the Society, and, if not, why not? Formerly many refused to join on the pretext that they did not like the policies. Now this pretext has been removed. If you are Russians and rely upon yourselves, you must sign your children up with our Society. But if you do not rely upon yourselves, you are not Russians. There is the question for you to answer: Are you a Russian or not?</p>
   <p>The time for the convention is approaching. RNzOV's administration is already making preparations to receive the delegates. In two or three months the delegates will begin to gather in Chicago. During this convention, we will be able <pb facs="5423967_3_1392.jpg" n="3"/>to judge, from the reports of the delegates, which branch put in the most effort, and which indicates the most devotion to the Russian cause and to the Society. During this convention, all of our failures and our victories will be revealed. I think that every branch of the Society, during this intervening time, will make every effort to present a good report at the convention. Every member of RNzOV should take pride in his Society and should try, by every means possible, to increase the membership of the Society, particularly of the younger element. I think that every Russian should belong to the Independent Society. If you belong to a mutual aid society, you are protecting your wife and children in the event of your death. Besides, in every misfortune, you acquire friends who will always help you. And this is a great thing for every man. After your death, your friends and relatives will not be compelled to pass the hat to cover the burial expenses, as is done so often now.</p>
   <p>Many Russians die in public hospitals. Nobody knows and nobody cares about them. And why should they die that way? They were unfortunate enough not to belong to any Russian organization. For that reason, nobody knows or cares about them.</p>
   <p>One could write a great deal about the people who have forgotten themselves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1393.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>I will cite only one example, the case of our member A. Maiorov, who was buried on February 6. Many people knew him. When he was in sound health, when he worked and had money, he had many friends and relatives who considered him a worth-while person. But when he was bedridden, when his money was gone, and he could not work, his friends disappeared. So did his relatives.</p>
   <p>But RNzOV did not forsake him. It paid him one hundred and eighty dollars in sick benefits, to which every member is entitled. Besides, he was helped in a friendly way, so that during the sickness he received over two hundred dollars. But the sickness was a prolonged one, and turned into tuberculosis. The sick man had to go to a sanatorium, where he was confined for a long time--until his death.</p>
   <p>Even before he went to the sanatorium, Maiorov felt that his condition was hopeless. He called, therefore, on Mr. A. Kirsch [Translator's note: One of the Russian undertakers] and asked him to pay the membership and policy installments for him and to bury him, in the event of his death, according to the Russian Church ritual. Mr. Kirsch consented.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1394.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>When Maiorov died, Mr. Kirsch kept his promise to the letter. He arranged the funeral according to the Russian custom. After the interment, Mr. Kirsch asked everybody present at the cemetery to go to his home for a cup of coffee. Many people accepted the invitation.</p>
   <p>At the undertaker's home a prayer was read; the guests were asked to be seated at the tables, which were heaped with all kinds of sandwiches. From the talk around the tables, it developed that RNzOV, after all, was the best mutual aid society and that every Russian should belong to it.</p>
   <p>And so my friends, members of the Russian colony, do not forget that most of our friends are only fair-weather friends. While we have dollars in our pockets, everybody loves us, but when they disappear, our friends will disappear, too; however, RNzOV will never forsake you, and will never betray you.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
