<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-10-31">Oct. 31, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Active Members of the R. C. M. A. S. A. (Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society in America) in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-10-31">Oct. 31, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">ACTIVE MEMBERS OF THE R. C. M. A. S. A. (RUSSIAN CONSOLIDATED MUTUAL AID SOCIETY IN AMERICA) IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Alexeyev and Mr. Komiakov, (a former secretary of R. I. M. A. S. A.), representatives of the New York branch of the R. C. M. A. S. A. arrived in Chicago last week. The Independents of Chicago R. I. M. A. S. (Russians Independent Mutual Aid Society) held several conferences with their participation, and Mr. Alexeyev, submitted a report at the Peoples School 917 N. Wood St., on the subject: R. I. M. A. S., R. C. M. A. S. A. and R. P. M. A. S. (Russian People's Mutual Aid Society). This report was read on Saturday, Oct. 24, 1931, to a large gathering. Several Bolsheviks, taking advantage of the kind attitude of the Independents came to hear the report, and in their customary outlandish manner created a disturbance, warning the members, of the danger caused by the "white-guards," counter-revolutionists: etc., <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>tacles, in preventing the Bolsheviks in joining the ranks of the Chicago as well as of the New York Mutual Aid Societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1671.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Alexeyev's report was heard with great interest by the Independents.</p>
   <p>Sunday Oct. 25, 1931. Mr. Alexeyev and Mr. Komiakov were invited to the social affair given by branch No. 1 of R. I. M. A. S. (St. George Brotherhood); they had the opportunity personally to be convinced of the great influence exerted by the independents among the Chicago's Russian immigrants. S. V. O. Y. ( A member)</p>
   <p>[Note: It may seem strange to the American readers why so many articles published in the newspaper Rassviet, are not signed by the author's real names. This is done exclusively for the simple reason that the authors of these articles, in criticizing the Bolshevik regime and the activities of the Communists in general, are afraid of reprisals against their relatives in Soviet Russia. N. Korecki.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
