<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-11-26">Nov. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">An Intolerable Incident</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-11-26">Nov. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">AN INTOLERABLE INCIDENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago a ten-year-old girl, Regina Pervinski, entered the Russian parochial school to learn the Russian language. Her father was Russian, of the Greek Orthodox faith, and her mother was Polish and a Catholic. Regina and the other children of Pervinski's family were brought up in the Catholic religion and attended the Polish Roman Catholic church. Both parents spoke Russian.</p>
   <p>Regina desired to learn the Russian language. At first, she went to the Russian grammar school operated by the Bolsheviks. But when her parents were warned by some good people that the child's mind might become harmfully influenced by the communist teachings, the Pervinskis placed their daughter in the Russian parochial school. On the second day, she was told by her teacher that she must leave the school because of her religion. So after two days, she left the school. The parents said they would never send the child to another Russian school.</p>
   <p>The action of the teacher of the Russian parochial school in refusing the child <pb facs="5423967_3_0284.jpg" n="2"/>the right of attendance was unjustified and was harmful to the Russian cause. It is possible that by his invidious and stupid act the teacher has once and for all killed in the child the desire to learn the Russian language. The administration of this Russian parochial school should seriously reconsider this incident and should grant the girl the right of attending the parochial school.</p>
   <p>Regina Pervinski is rather a talented little girl.She dances well and often participates in public performances. Such mockery of an innocent little girl by a teacher of the Russian parochial school should not be tolerated in this age of enlightenment and understanding.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
