<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1931-08-29">Aug. 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Special Meeting of St. George Brotherhood</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-08-29">Aug. 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">SPECIAL MEETING OF ST. GEORGE BROTHERHOOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Saturday, August 22, a special meeting of St. George Brotherhood (first branch of RIMAS, i. e., Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society) was held at the Parochial school hall, 917 N. Wood St. D. Mikhalchik was chairman. The main subject of discussion at this meeting was the reorganization of the Parochial school. Chairman D. Mikhalchik reported to the meeting about previous decisions and intentions of the Brotherhood to take under its control the parochial school, to reorganize it and make it a pattern for other Russian schools in the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>V. Dedovich spoke in favor or reorganizing the school and called upon all present as old members to take part in the reorganization work. G. Dedovich (sic) emphasized that the parents themselves, who still send their children to the school on Wood street, were not satisfied with the previous state of affairs in this school. Therefore, it is not necessary to discuss this question - until the work of reorganization is begun. P. Hulks wished the Brotherhood success in such an important undertaking which had been long expected by the parents. It was necessary long ago to reorganize this school in the interests of all independents. A. Pasuk remarked that the parish had this school under its management for fifteen years, and during all this time <pb facs="5423967_3_1675.jpg" n="2"/>could not improve the school, and eventually the school took a downward course. The brotherhood should take the school over and improve it in accord with the high principles implied by the very name of the organization that sponsors it.</p>
   <p>Our, as it were, central school must serve as a pattern for others. K. Lees protested against the reorganization. He declared that in spite of the decision of the parochial majority to put the school under the brotherhood's supervision, the committee decided against such a step and that the brotherhood should not interfere with the school problem at all. V. Sabinsky objected to such a protest, remarking that if the brotherhood abandons the idea of reorganizing the school it may have to open its own school elsewhere.</p>
   <p>V. Dedovich for the second time maintained that the brotherhood should not be deterred by the obstinacy of the parochial committee, for it has enough authority and influence in order to take the school under its control. By taking a vote the meeting decided to take control of the school and immediately reorganize it and engage a teacher in order that the school may be opened in the near future and serve as a pattern for other schools. After that the <pb facs="5423967_3_1676.jpg" n="3"/>meeting elected a school committee composed of the following persons: A. Pasuk, P. Nagorny, K. Ryabchuk and G. Vanasky. Concerning school books it was decided: as text books printed in Moscow are unobtainable in the near future, to permit use of books now on hand. In the future we should try to furnish all schools with the same books.</p>
   <p>The brotherhood so far could not appoint an agent to insure children because it was unable to pay such an agent any salary. The board of directors elected V. Konashevsky as their agent for Branch 1, on the condition that he would receive seven percent of the money collected.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, the president of RIMAS, Elarion Horoschenia, made a speech calling upon the Independents to resist the hostile agitation of agents from the Pittsburgh society. This society, under the mask of uniting all, does harm to the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society in Chicago. It sends its adherents into all branches of RIMAS, and these persons slander our elected officers and carry on an agitation with the purpose of inducing our members to join the Pittsburgh society. The Independents should not pay attention to <pb facs="5423967_3_1677.jpg" n="4"/>to Bolshevik agents and, wherever it is possible they should unmask these uncalled for "traitors." At present the worth of their promises of a "heaven on earth" is known, and the "independents" should remember their duty to the people's organization and give these enemies a stern rebuff so that they would keep their hands off the Independent Society.</p>
   <p>D. Vorobey.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
