<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1932-02-06">Feb. 6, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Organizations Should Be Active</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial - by R. I. M. A. S.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1665</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1665.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1932-02-06">Feb. 6, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZATIONS SHOULD BE ACTIVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial - by R. I. M. A. S.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Any organization, and especially the one whose foundation is based upon mutual aid, i. e., upon a certain kind of financial transaction, should not limit itself merely to routine formalities, such as collecting membership dues and paying its bills when its regular meeting is called.</p>
   <p>The organization by all means must try to arouse in its members a keen interest in the sphere of their activities, and not limit itself to attracting their interest solely to the official meetings.</p>
   <p>In order that an organization be of value and interest to its members, as well as to all those who are occupied with or interested in social activities,it should present to them something more than that which is formulated in the dry articles of the by-laws of that organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1666.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Experience shows, that organizations that are not interested in anything but merely in the insurance policies of the members, sooner or later fade out.</p>
   <p>In order that an organization should continue its existence and prosper, its active leaders should do their utmost not only to enlist new members, but also try to keep the old as well as the new ones interested alike in the affairs of the organization.</p>
   <p>This should be taken into consideration by some of our branches, the progress of which apart from other reasons, is often handicapped by the fact that their leaders are not interested in anything else, but in collecting dues from its members at their regular meetings.</p>
   <p>And yet, it would be possible, to diversify the activities in our branches, this making them more interesting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1667.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The committee of a branch should not wait until the last minute when the regular meeting is called, but could take the initiative and arrange a lecture, (educational, scientific, etc.,) also all kinds of gatherings for amusement, such as family parties, evening parties, movie pictures, etc.</p>
   <p>As is known to us, the general management of the R. I. M. A. S. has at its command many talents, who could help any branch of the R. I. M. A. S., to diversify its activities by arranging various entertainments.</p>
   <p>Our branches should assume the responsibility of taking care of such activities and see to it that their members do not feel lonesome, that their families are in permanent contact with each other, and that their individual members do no go astray from their homes. The branches should come to their assistance in case of misfortune and that not only financially, but also by satisfying the spiritual and moral needs of the members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1668.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The organization must not fall asleep, it should uphold its activities by fruitful and often pleasant undertakings.</p>
   <p>The branches of R. I. M. A. S. are apt, in comparison with any other organizations in the Russian colony, to give to their members the maximum of satisfaction.</p>
   <p>This possibility must be taken advantage of by all means.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
