<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-12">Mar. 12, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[Madame] T. V. Cherniavin's Lectures in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0765</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0765.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-12">Mar. 12, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[MADAME] T. V. CHERNIAVIN'S LECTURES IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Madame T. V. Cherniavin's lectures have proved to be the most outstanding event in the life of the Russian colony for a number of years past. It is several years since the Russian colony has heard any eyewitness accounts of what is going on in Soviet Russia, in what direction and by what paths the Bolsheviks are leading a bleeding and turbulent nation. Madame Cherniavin briefly referred to all this in her two lectures.</p>
   <p>In passing, we may state that Madame Cherniavin is not a professional lecturer. She is more a narrator than a lecturer. She does not deliver purely academic lectures in conformity with well-established traditional rules from material prepared in advance. She simply relates her experiences and observations, as it were, in private talks to her listeners. She tells what she saw, tells of her escape with her husband from the Solovki concentration camp. All that she relates comes not so much from her intellect as from her sensitive Russian soul. For that <pb facs="5423967_3_0766.jpg" n="2"/>reason her narratives have so much more value than purely academic talks.</p>
   <p>Have her appearances been successful or not? It's very difficult to answer this question. The auditorium was filled to a degree of overcrowding. There were no incidents or disturbances of any sort during her lectures, as the local Bolsheviks did not honor her lectures with their frequently undesirable presence. Each time Madame Cherniavin appeared on the stage she was greeted with tumultuous applause. Each time she finished her talks she was warmly acclaimed by her audience. From this point of view her lectures were very successful. On the other hand, her lectures led many of her listeners to gloomy thoughts, for she made many ominous statements that resounded with gloomy forebodings. But this was not Madame Cherniavin's fault.</p>
   <p>The lectures were attended by many intellectuals; Russian churchmen with Bishop Leonty at their head were present at both her lectures. There were guests from other nearby cities. There were representatives of other nationalities. One <pb facs="5423967_3_0767.jpg" n="3"/>could observe in the audience the most advanced and cultured elements of the old immigration; but there were only a few ordinary rank-and-file members of our organizations and still fewer of their leaders. This is, of course, extremely regrettable. One would expect every member of the Russian colony to visit these instructive and very interesting lectures, for they are eager, no doubt, to know how the Russian people get along under the Bolshevik rule; they want to know the truth about Russia. But there were very few members of the colony present. This only goes to show that the preponderant part of the Russian colony is actually very little exercised about the fate of its fathers, mothers, sisters, and brothers, and still less about the fate of the Russian people as a whole. It is no wonder, therefore, that the Russian colony in Chicago does not represent a force that anyone need reckon with; that it is neglected and slighted by other national groups.</p>
   <p>It is very possible that, from all we have said about the attendance at Madame Cherniavin's lectures, adventurers from Novy Mir [Translator's note: Novy Mir was a Bolshevik newspaper published in New York] will hastily draw certain conclusions <pb facs="5423967_3_0768.jpg" n="4"/>tending to show that the masses of the Russian colony support the Bolsheviks' views on all that is transpiring in the U.S.S.R.; but these inferences will be plainly misleading, because the attendance at Bolshevik lectures and other gatherings promoted by them is only a fraction of what it was at Madame Cherniavin's lectures.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
