<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-25">Apr. 25, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">At the Meeting of St. Mary's Sisterhood</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-25">Apr. 25, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">AT THE MEETING OF ST. MARY'S SISTERHOOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday a regular meeting of St. Mary's Sisterhood was held at the People's Auditorium, 917 North Wood Street. Secretary M. Kirsh first read the minutes of the last meeting and put into the record the financial statement for the month of March. It was decided to hold a benefit entertainment, the proceeds to go into the Sisterhood's treasury as a reserve fund. The president of the Sisterhood, Mrs. Leshchuk, asked all those present to attend the entertainment given by the Krylov School on Sunday, April 26, and by their presence to support a good cause.</p>
   <p>Mme. Chepelevich also called upon the members to support the School and pointed out that the members of the School [board] and the pupils have done a <pb facs="5423967_3_1114.jpg" n="2"/>great deal for the Sisterhood in the way of arranging concert programs and taking part in them, and that all such services have been rendered without any remuneration; therefore it was the duty of the Sisterhood's members to support the school at least by attending its benefit entertainment. Mrs. Chepelevich explained to the members that the fathers of the children attending the Krylov School, besides contributing much to the stage presentation of the plays at the People's Auditorium of St. George's parish, have painted and decorated the parish hall. All this work, for which a contractor would have charged at least two hundred dollars, was done gratis, and the parish bought only the materials; therefore the parents' organization of the school deserves the full support of the parish members.</p>
   <p>[Mme.] P.S. Svatikova in the name of the central administration of R.I.M.A.S. appealed to the sisters to bring their children into the ranks of the Society, and she advised the ladies themselves to change to the new forms of insurance <pb facs="5423967_3_1115.jpg" n="3"/>now issued by R.I.M.A.S. because in the new policies the interests of the individual policyholders are better protected. The sisters listened with a great deal of attention to other information supplied by Mme. Svatikova concerning the new forms of insurance recently introduced by the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society (R.I.M.A.S.) on the advice of the State Insurance Department.</p>
   <p>At the same meeting it was decided to support in every way the educational and cultural work that is being carried on by R.I.M.A.S.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
