<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-07-08">July 8, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Conference of Russian Schools for Children</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">The Inauguration of the Conference by I. S.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0486</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0486.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-07-08">July 8, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONFERENCE OF RUSSIAN SCHOOLS FOR CHILDREN</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">The Inauguration of the Conference By I. S.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The conference of Russian schools for children in Chicago was inaugurated on July 3, 1924, at the former quarters of the Soviet school, 1902 W. Division Street.</p>
   <p>As usual, the delegates came late.</p>
   <p>The conference was opened by the secretary of the committee. Mr. Tureyko, who called the delegates to harmonious labor for the good of our people's <pb facs="5423967_3_0487.jpg" n="2"/>are aroused from their apathy, and the active members of the Communist "cell" (the federation) also listen with eager attention. What is the matter? The explanation is that the federation demands for itself fifty per cent of the profit derived from lectures, entertainments, concerts, etc., being arranged for the benefit of the separate schools.</p>
   <p>A teacher, Voronko, suggests that the funds of the federation should be limited to the necessary expenses for office supplies, and that each school should share in covering them. His view gets support from the speeches of A. Zmagar, Romanovich and Logunets. But alas! this motion is rejected. Its opponents succeed after all to eliminate entirely this proposal; the Douglas Park School and the South Side School were those that insisted most on its rejection. It was proposed to establish the same tuition fee for all schools, and also the same <pb facs="5423967_3_0488.jpg" n="3"/>membership fee; but it was proved that this could not be put into practice, and it was resolved that each school would have to decide as to the amount of the tuition fee and of the membership fee, according to the conditions prevailing in that school.</p>
   <p>It was resolved next that the supreme authority in the federation would belong to the school council, into which two delegates from each school would be elected; however, schools with a number of children exceeding fifty would send three delegates. The school council elects out of its membership and executive committee, consisting of a chairman, a financial secretary, a treasurer and a recording secretary. The Communist chatter-boxes wanted very much that the conference elect the executive committee out of the delegates, but this proposal was rejected.</p>
   <p>On the whole this session was all devoted to the examination of the <pb facs="5423967_3_0489.jpg" n="4"/>by-laws of the federation, which, generally speaking, did not differ much from all other by-laws. As in all such constitutions and by-laws, in this case also many beautiful things were formulated on paper, but it remains to be seen how all these things will work out in real life.</p>
   <p>On that day at last the laws of the federation were thoroughly examined and approved.</p>
   <p>Session of July 6, by "A Teacher." This session was held at the quarters which had been formerly occupied by the Soviet School. Turovets, the delegate from the Brighton Park school, was elected chairman. The order of the business called for the discussion of point four, about the revision of the programs of the schools. The reporter on behalf of the commission for the working out of the program of the schools was the teacher J. Eberhardt. His opponents were I. Voronko, A. Zmagar, Zusser, Romanovich and Logunets. After a long discussion the program <pb facs="5423967_3_0490.jpg" n="5"/>was somewhat changed.</p>
   <p>The First School Year (Preparatory Form).</p>
   <p>First term. Reading of the elementary text-book; first acquaintance with writing; explanation of pictures.</p>
   <p>Second term. The same studies are continued. The text-book must be learned to the end; explanation of pictures; calligraphy and copying from books.</p>
   <p>The Second School Year (First Form).</p>
   <p>First term. First text-book after the elementary one; copying; first <pb facs="5423967_3_0491.jpg" n="6"/>acquaintance with numbers; explanation of pictures in Russian.</p>
   <p>Second term. First text-book after the elementary one; reading and relating; easy dictations consisting of separate words; learning of poetry by heart; arithmetic, addition and subtraction; also explanation of pictures.</p>
   <p>Third School Year (Second Form).</p>
   <p>First term: Second reader; reading and relating; learning of poetry; more difficult dictation; grammar, declensions of nouns, pronouns, adjectives and numerals; arithmetic, multiplication.</p>
   <p>Second term: The same second reader; reading and relating; learning <pb facs="5423967_3_0492.jpg" n="7"/>of poetry; grammar, verbs, adverbs, prepositions and conjunctions; written accounts of short stories; arithmetic, division; geography and history of Russia (elementary information).</p>
   <p>Fourth School Year (Third Form).</p>
   <p>First term: Study of the reader; learning of poetry; etymology; beginning of syntax; arithmetic, problems involving all four operations; geography and history of Russia.</p>
   <p>Second term: Reading of fragments from the Russian classics; completion of the study of syntax; writing of easy compositions of a descriptive character or in the form of a discourse; a short history of Russian literature.</p>
   <p>Further it was recommended to arrange morning entertainments for <pb facs="5423967_3_0493.jpg" n="8"/>children in the schools, excursions to industrial plants, farms, theaters, etc.</p>
   <p>The clause eliminating the teaching of religion from schools belonging to the federation gave rise to very lively debates. This clause was opposed energetically by the teachers J. Voronko, Zmagar, Romanovich, Logunets; those named last pointed out that, as the teaching of religion is not mentioned in the program of the schools anyhow, it is unnecessary to introduce a special clause. This view, however, was not supported by the other speakers. The teacher Logunets moved that there should be no more than thirty-five pupils in each form, as a larger number does not allow to teach the children properly and successfully. This motion was carried. After that the teacher A. Zmagar moved that in the third (last form) the children should go <pb facs="5423967_3_0494.jpg" n="9"/>to school also on Saturdays in all schools, irrespective of the number of pupils, as the program of that form would be too large otherwise. This motion was supported energetically by Piven, the delegate of the South Side School. The motion was carried. The next motion was that the school council of the federation elect a commission which during the school year should arrange not more than three examinations in order to check the results of the teaching in the schools of the federation. This motion was also carried.</p>
   <p>As to the regular examinations it was resolved that at the end of the school year there should be examinations in each form of a school, held by an examination committee consisting of the following:</p>
   <p>(1) A delegate from the School Council of the Federation; (2) the <pb facs="5423967_3_0495.jpg" n="10"/>teacher of the school (in the case of schools having more than one teacher, a second teacher participates in the Examination Committee); (3) a representative of the parents of children being taught in the school.</p>
   <p>A Teacher.</p>
   <p>After a recess the session is resumed and the fifth clause of the order of the business of the day is discussed; namely, that concerning the teaching personnel. The debate about this question lasted over two hours. It became obvious, owing to this discussion, that there are too few teachers with college education, and that it is impossible to rely on such teachers alone; the need is felt of a special staff of trained teachers recruited from among the local intelligent workmen. Because of that it was resolved to <pb facs="5423967_3_0496.jpg" n="11"/>organize special courses for teachers. A special committee was elected for the working out of a project of such courses,which project would have to be approved by the next school council. It is also necessary to mention that Zusser, the teacher of the South Side School, raised at his own initiative the question about some criticism which is often directed against the teachers, namely, that they are receiving too high wages for their work. But in reality it is found that the wages are pretty small; because the teachers cannot manage to stay in the schools only two hours and have all their work done during that time. When lectures, entertainments, etc., are being arranged much time is spent in getting everything ready for these; then the teacher has to spend much time at home correcting dictations, etc., and nobody pays any attention to that. As regards this, the teacher Zusser found support from the teacher Eberhardt, who also finds that the teachers <pb facs="5423967_3_0497.jpg" n="12"/>should get a better remuneration for their work, for the teaching in the schools and the work done for the federation take too much time; and without the participation of the teachers in the work done by the delegates in the school council, that council would become a dead institution.</p>
   <p>Delegate Piven pointed out that our teachers' wages, when compared with those received by the teachers of other nationalities, are really very small. However, the teachers A. Zmagar, Romanovich and Logunets abstained from participating in this discussion, not wishing to be found fighting for a raise to the teachers.</p>
   <p>Other delegates, as, for example, Tureyko, from the North Side School, expressed the opinion that at present our schools are too poor and that, therefore, the question as to the raise should be left open.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0498.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>However, the meeting could not arrive at any definite conclusion. One thing, though, is very characteristic; as we know, the conference had made a serious mistake in refusing to grant the right of a decisive vote to the teachers, being misled by the demagogic assertions of the Communists headed by Stolar and Shklar. But now when the question was raised as to what vote should be given to the teachers in the school council, not one of the delegates dared to raise objections against the granting to the teachers the right of a decisive vote.</p>
   <p>Thus the teachers, when they joined the council, had the right to cast a decisive vote. The session was a pretty quiet one because the politicians, for some unknown reason, had quieted down and <pb facs="5423967_3_0499.jpg" n="14"/>understood that the majority of the conference stood for a Russian school, a school where the Russian language should be taught, and not a Communist school for the teaching of the Communist ABC.</p>
   <p>A Teacher</p>
   <p>Note: According to the statement of a teacher of the federation, F. Tureyko, seven schools numbered more than four hundred pupils. N. K.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
