<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-08-24">Aug. 24, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">An Appear to the Old Believers of Chicago and Vicinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-08-24">Aug. 24, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAR TO THE OLD BELIEVERS OF CHICAGO AND VICINITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Chicago and suburbs there are more than two thousand Old Believers, who came from Russia, Poland, Lithuania, Austria-Hungary, Rumania, and other countries. As in the past, so now, there have been many things common to all Old Believers. Our ancestors suffered much, especially during the years of Patriarch Nikon, at the time of Tsar Alexei Mikhailovitch [Romanoff, in the beginning of seven- teenth century], when they were introducing, new reforms into the Russian Orthodox Church. At that time, those who refused to accept the changes and remained faithful to the old canon books were persecuted and burned at the stake. These persecutions forced the Old Believers to flee the country and seek refuge beyond its borders, usually in countries bordering Russia, where their descendants live even today.</p>
   <p>We, contemporary Old Believers, have preserved, until the present time, some feelings of kinship, which help us to keep our ties of blood. This circumstance now makes us feel a desire for union in one brotherly family.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1471.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Several years ago the Russian Old Believers of Chicago took upon themselves the task of uniting all Old Believers in Chicago and suburbs into one mutual aid society.</p>
   <p>This attempt has been crowned with success. The Society has been formed without particular efforts. It has gained strength and has produced good results. At present, the Society has a good many members. The affairs of the Society are in splendid condition. There is complete harmony among the members. The Society has a large fund from which it takes money to extend financial aid to members in case of sickness, death, or accidents. The Society frequently has social gatherings and entertainments for members and their friends; such enterprises usually are crowned with success.</p>
   <p>The Society holds its regular meetings every month. With the approaching fall and winter seasons, the Old Believers Society intends to extend its cultural and educational program and to increase its membership. To attract more members, the Society has decided to suspend, for the months of August and September, the admission fee required of new members. The Old Believers <pb facs="5423967_3_1472.jpg" n="3"/>Society is inviting all Old Believers living in Chicago and vicinity to join our Mutual Aid Society. Here you will find your own brothers, in spirit and in faith, who will receive you with outstretched hands, and who will always be ready to help you in misfortune and in the difficult hours of life.</p>
   <p>Remeber, brothers, our wise Russian saying, "In union there is strength".</p>
   <p>Regular meetings of the Old Believers Mutual Aid Society are held the last Sunday of each month in the hall of Mr. Zhelandowski, 4501 South Hermitage Avenue.</p>
   <p>With hearty welcome,</p>
   <p>J. Yershoff, Secretary.</p>
   <p>Note: In all business matters, please see Mr. Yershoff, 320 W. 35th Place, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
