<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. I, owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. <date when="1929">1929</date>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1028</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1028.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. I, owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, April 7, 1929, 2 P. M., the first public appearance of V. M. Chernov will take place. He is one of the foremost theorists and leader of the Socialist-Revolutienary Party, the president of the All-Russian Convention, one of the best orators. He will speak on the subject, "The Contemporary Russian Situation and Prospect for the Future."</p>
   <p>This lecture will include such important questions as Trotskyism, the recent appearance of left wing Communism, its connection with other opposition to the Communist Party, the possibility of Bona-partism and restoration of monarchism in Russia, the peaceful evolution of Bolshevism towards democracy or its catastrophic downfall. No one else except B. M. Chernov, who has live connections with Soviet Russia, and who is in charge of party work there, can answer these questions so clearly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1029.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The lecture will be held in the Amalgamated Center, corner Ashland Boulevard and Van Buren Street. Beginning at 2 P. M. Admission 50 cents and $1. Tickets may be obtained in the office of the newspaper Rassviet, 1722 W. Chicago Avenue; in the Lithuanian newspaper office, Naujienos, 1739 S. Halsted Street; at the Russian National Orthodox Society, 917 N. Wood Street, and at the office of the Amalgamated Center, corner Ashland Boulevard and Van Buren Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
