<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-01-14">Jan. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Russian Independent Mutual Aid and Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ivan Okuntsov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-01-14">Jan. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT MUTUAL AID AND RUSSIAN CONSOLIDATED MUTUAL AID SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ivan Okuntsov</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The two largest Russian economic organizations, Russkoe Nezavisimoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society) and Russkoe Ob'edinennoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society) in the Russian colony have been trying for a long time to unite into one great moral and mutually beneficial organization, but they cannot find a common tongue and a set of principles upon which there can be brotherhood.</p>
   <p>In regard to this matter, I will take extracts from the speech of Mr. Winslow, chairman of the Roov in New York. He spoke about this unification at the conference of the branches of Roov in New York and the vicinity. At this conference, forty-five delegates, chiefly chairmen and secretaries of the branches, were present.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1569.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The conference was held at the headquarters of the first branch of Roov, "Nauka" (Science) in New York City.</p>
   <p>On the subject of unification of Rnzov and Roov, Mr. Winslow said the following:</p>
   <p>"For a long time we have continued our fraternal negotiations concerning unification, but we cannot see the end of them. We (Roov) sent two of our representatives to Chicago. They (Rnzov) sent their delegates to us. We met each other in a friendly manner, talked amicably about unification, but up to the present day, there has been no consolidation.</p>
   <p>"Much water has escaped since that time.</p>
   <p>"About three weeks ago, we sent to Chicago a plan for our proposed union. By this plan we have already united with other mutual aid organizations, and therefore, I think this plan is just as good in this case.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1570.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"A copy of this plan was forwarded to the Department of Insurance of the State of New York to be examined and the possibilities of unification of Roov and Rnzov considered. Up to now there had been no answer from Chicago. Evidently they are discussing it, or preparing their own plan for us.</p>
   <p>"In my opinion such an exchange of papers is only a delay of time. Resides we understand that our friends in Chicago have many difficulties. Various persons from the "left" who are trying to win them over to their side have influence over them. But the "left barkers" will hardly succeed, because we and Rnzov have many things in common and are suitable to each other.</p>
   <p>"The best thing for both organizations would be, instead of exchanging letters, to meet somehow in a centrally located city, and through each other's representatives talk this matter over, face to face.</p>
   <p>"In this way all of our common desires and terms would be disclosed more quickly and justly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1571.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"It is our wish that our next annual convention should be held together with the convention of Rnzov; we are thinking or proposing this plan to our Chicago friends.</p>
   <p>"With good intentions, the unification will unquestionably be crowned with success, and both Rnzov and Roov have good intentions.</p>
   <p>"If we unite, our power will increase twofold."</p>
   <p>This speech of Mr. Winslow, the chairman of the Roov, received great sympathy and applause.</p>
   <p>Let us see what Rnzov is going to say.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
