<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russian National Almanac</title><date when="1929">1929</date> (Russian National Orthodox Society), p. 7.
<title level="a">From the Editorial Board</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0153</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0153.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian National Almanac</title><date when="1929">1929</date> (Russian National Orthodox Society), p. 7.
<title level="a">FROM THE EDITORIAL BOARD</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The birth of the present Russian National Almanac, - to our way of thinking, - is a great step forward of that organization the name of which is closely allied with this publication.</p>
   <p>It is true that the Russian National Orthodox Society of Chicago, which issued this almanac during the years of 1916-23 (the flourishing period), has even published a daily newspaper (Free Russia), later participated in publishing a newspaper (Russian Herald), which has replaced the first, and at present owns a small amount of stock in the newspaper Rassviet.</p>
   <p>As can be noticed from the foregoing, after the first period of its growth, the Russian National Orthodox Society has lived through a period of depression in which the publishing activity of our national organization also experienced a noticeable crisis. At present, as is known,</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0154.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>the Russian National Orthodox Society, represented by us in this edition, is undertaking a new and great activity within the colony, and is becoming a factor in uniting the colony.</p>
   <p>In our opinion, the existence of a national organization and our almanac should serve this aim of unifying our colony.</p>
   <p>We do not aim to convince the reader that the present Russian National Almanac is in a position to answer all questions of the masses of the colony so dear to us.</p>
   <p>Like with any new enterprise, this first experience in editing has met with many difficulties which could not be foreseen. Moreover, the small group of members of the Russian National Orthodox Society, who had resolved to make the publication of a Russian national almanac a reality, have not stopped in the face of difficulties, and have brought the undertaking to a successful end.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0155.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Much more could have been put into our almanac, although the present edition, regardless of its size, is becoming the largest in the ranks of the publications of the Russian emigration. Perhaps in the future those who will replace us will regard the shortcomings of this almanac as well as the difficulties we have met during the process of formation of the first Russian national almanac in Chicago, and will answer the questions of the colony more comprehensively than we have.</p>
   <p>The editorial board deems it its duty to announce that in all matters concerning the solving of the problem given us, our guiding star was the welfare of the national organization.</p>
   <p>THE EDITORIAL BOARD</p>
   <p>Dimitri Vorobey, Joseph Voronko,</p>
   <p>Dimitri Michalchik, and Dimitri Sleznik.</p>
   <p>Chicago, Ill., Dec. 10, 1928.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
