<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>News of the Russian People's University</title>, No. 1, pp. 64-65.
<title level="a">Program of the Convention of Russian Educational Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>News of the Russian People's University</title>, No. 1, pp. 64-65.
<title level="a">PROGRAM OF THE CONVENTION OF RUSSIAN EDUCATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The board of the Russian People's University which is calling a convention of the Russian educational organizations communicates to the whole Russian colony of the United States of America and of Canada the following preliminary program of questions which will have to be elucidated at the convention to be held in Chicago on December 27, 28 and 29, 1918.</p>
   <p>The following program has been elaborated by the board of the Russian People's University in Chicago:</p>
   <p>(1) The founding of regional Russian People's Universities with agricultural and technical divisions.</p>
   <p>(2) The founding of a Russian-American commercial institute.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0619.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(3) The founding of provisional schools for instructors.</p>
   <p>(4) The founding of elementary schools for the teaching of the Russian and the English languages.</p>
   <p>(5) The organization of a control bureau of traveling lecturers.</p>
   <p>(6) Cultural aid to the population of Russia.</p>
   <p>(7) The organization of a committee for the study of the cultural educational and pedagogic institutions of North America.</p>
   <p>(8) The election of delegates to be sent to Russia and the definitions of the aims of this delegation.</p>
   <p>(9) The organization of traveling scientific-educational and industrial-commercial <pb facs="5423967_3_0620.jpg" n="3"/>Russian-American exhibitions.</p>
   <p>(10) The repatriation of Russian emigrants and cultural problems.</p>
   <p>(11) The organization of all-American unions</p>
   <p>(a) of Russian engineers in America</p>
   <p>(b) of Russian physicians in America</p>
   <p>(c) of Russian scientists, writers, journalists and artists.</p>
   <p>(12) The recognition by Russia of educational degrees obtained by Russian immigrants in America.</p>
   <p>(13) The establishment of a council for a convention of Russian educational and cultural organizations in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0621.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>(14) The publishing activities of the council.</p>
   <p>(15) Relief fund for young Russian scientists.</p>
   <p>(16) The finding of ways and means for the realization of the program of activities worked out by the convention.</p>
   <p>The administrative board of the Russian People's University which is in charge of the calling of the convention considers it as its duty to explain that the above program is only a provisional one and will be discussed before the beginning of the convention, and that such clauses will be added to it as will be proposed to the convention and discussed and passed by it. The administrative board earnestly appeals to all interested organizations and to the Russian colony, <pb facs="5423967_3_0622.jpg" n="5"/>requesting them to send delegates who can make reports which answer the questions raised in the program.</p>
   <p>The names of the reporters and organizations will be published when information is received about their participation in the work of the convention.</p>
   <p>A. Lutnutsky, Secretary</p>
   <p>S. I. Novakovsky, President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
