<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-03-02">Mar. 2, 1931</date>,
<title level="a">N. Komiakov's Lecture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0801</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0801.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-03-02">Mar. 2, 1931</date>,
<title level="a">N. KOMIAKOV'S LECTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Wednesday, Feb. 25th, in Chicago, the secretary of the Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society gave a lecture on mutual aid. He spoke of mutual aid among animals, men, and in the vegetable kingdom. For example, he <gap unit="word" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> from the well known book by P. Kropotkin, "Mutual Aid a Factor of Evolution", and from other sources. The lecture was purely scientific, without any reference to politics.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, an incident occurred. The Bolsheviks on hearing of this lecture came as an organized group, headed by the chief of "chekists", Kutsko, Klimko, Trushinsky, and others. They came to the lecture not to promote mutual aid, but to make an appearance and to talk nonsensically.</p>
   <p>To the Russians in Chicago, the Bolsheviks are well known. They settled on Division St., and no worthwhile activities of theirs were heard of in the Russian colony. Most of them were engaged in economical and political affairs.</p>
   <p>Mr. Komiakov's lecture offered the Bolsheviks an opportunity to create a disturbance. They came not alone, but with Polish and Latvian Communists, with the intention of agitating the people. They mobilized, so-to-speak, their entire small army, undoubtedly intending to interrupt the lecture.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0802.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But their plans were frustrated. The public was aware that the Bolsheviks represented the minority in the hall, and the majority of the people did not permit them to interrupt the lecture. The Bolsheviks made an attempt to go through with their plans. Just as Mr. Komiakov began to speak, Mr. Kutsko (Manager of the Bolshevist cooperative restaurant, who escaped from the Bolsheviks' Utopia and built himself a home here, in Chicago, becoming thus a "kulak", according to Bolshevist terminology), demanded that the right of the floor be given the Bolsheviki, in order that they could voice some objections.</p>
   <p>The public, being hostile to the Bolsheviki, refused to support Mr. Kutsko's motion. After numerous threats uttered by Mr. Kutsko's supporters, the Bolsheviki were made to understand that they would be permitted to remain in the hall only if they agreed to listen to the lecture quietly, without causing any further disturbance. The Bolsheviki, seeing that they could not achieve their purpose, remained orderly for the rest of the lecture.</p>
   <p>It is necessary to mention that business in the Bolsheviks' restaurant is not too good. The restaurant has a deficit. At the same time, strangely enough, the comrades who worked there acquired houses of their own, and the food in the restaurant became worse. This caused many customers to cease patronizing it.</p>
   <p>(A Visitor)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
