<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-01-13">Jan. 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Neither Chicago Nor Wilkes-Barre, but General Consolidation</title><title level="a" type="sub">by N. Komiakov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1576</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1576.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-01-13">Jan. 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">NEITHER CHICAGO NOR WILKES-BARRE, BUT GENERAL CONSOLIDATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">by N. Komiakov</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday in "Novosti" [The News--page in Rassviet devoted to the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society], an editorial was printed under the title "Chicago or Wilkes-Barre" in which a grievance was stated because Levitskoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi" (Russian Orthodox Catholic Mutual Aid Society at Holy Trinity Cathedral, 1121 North Leavitt Street, Chicago, Illinois) is again making overtures toward the Vilkes-Barskomu Obshchestvu (Russian Orthodox Catholic Mutual Aid Society) at Wilkes-Barre, from which organization they withdrew sometime ago; the article also states in conclusion that "Chicago is better than Wilkes-Barre". In the article the statement is made that "Levitsi" [Russian Mutual Aid Society on Leavitt Street, Chicago, Ill.] Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society) of Chicago, because "we Chicagoans must take care of ourselves."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1577.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"To take care of one's self"--that is an old problem. Who today does not think of taking care of himself?</p>
   <p>The capitalist cutting the wages of the workers is taking care of himself because he wants to receive more profit. The same capitalist is taking care of himself when he closes the shop and throws the workers on the streets because he is afraid that the workers may eat up the capital which he has accumulated. The speculator on the stock exchange, gambling on the rise and fall of the stocks, is taking care of himself because the fluctuation of prices goes into his pocket. The bandit robbing the safe takes care of himself because the contents pass into his hands. The banker, his bank insolvent, pays out to his clients [a few] cents on the dollar; he is taking care of himself because the remaining part of the dollar goes to his benefit. Capone, serving at present a term in prison, took care of himself when he was engaged in the bootlegging business by removing his competitors from his path.</p>
   <p>Examples of "taking care of one's self" can be given by the thousands, but <pb facs="5423967_3_1578.jpg" n="3"/>each one of them reveals only genuine selfishness and has no relation with the brotherhood ideal even if such illustrations are covered with the best intentions. The brotherhood organization should take an opposite attitude--to take care not of one's self but of others, of everyone. The goal of the brotherhood should be to fight against egoism, not to put it forward as a slogan to be fulfilled.</p>
   <p>With the reproach addressed to the Russian Orthodox Catholic Mutual Aid Society we might agree, if the writer of the editorial had definitely confirmed the fact that the Wilkes-Barre organization has, for a long time been frozen to the point of death, that the membership decreases, and that generally the organization actually lags behind, and that the Chicago organization, to the contrary, strives to develop and to keep in step with the requirements of modern life; it works and develops the idea of general unification, it wishes to gather all the Russians into one united family, and to prove this fact, RNzOV states that the organization is on the eve of merging with ROOV Russkoe Ob'edinennoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Consolidated Mutual <pb facs="5423967_3_1579.jpg" n="4"/>Aid Society), etc. Unfortunately the author did not say a word about this matter.</p>
   <p>And therefore not only did the author of the said editorial not prove the preferability of "Chicago" over "Wilkes-Barre", but on the contrary suggested to the reader that "Chicago" itself was not on the right path, since it was not seeking general consolidation, but showed it up as taking care of one's self."</p>
   <p>As long as the leaders of Russian organizations praise only their own home cities, be it Chicago, New York, or Wilkes-Barre--it makes no difference which--there will be no general solidarity in the Russian colony, not to mention the small individual organizations, which sooner or later become bankrupt if they do not unite. Therefore the salvation rests not in Chicago or Wilkes-Barre, but in a general consolidation of Chicago, New York, Wilkes-Barre, "Levitsi" and others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
