<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-18">Apr. 18, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">School Affairs of R.I.M.A.S.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0206</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0206.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-18">Apr. 18, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL AFFAIRS OF R.I.M.A.S.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In about a month classes in the Russian children's schools will be dismissed for the summer vacation. The schools maintained by the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society will also close their doors for the summer. At present the school committees are very anxious to close the school season without any deficit, and what is more important, with some money saved for the next school year so that the committees will be able to open the schools on time after the summer recess.</p>
   <p>Those who cannot look forward inevitably must turn and look backward--must lag behind in life, not keep pace with it. There are many things in life the loss of which can be made up, but lost time in the education of children can never be regained. From nine to fourteen years is the most critical period, the most vital period in a child's life. During this period the child's character is being molded, and its habits are being formed, and what is acquired by the child in these years will remain with it for the rest <pb facs="5423967_3_0207.jpg" n="2"/>of its life. We all desire, first of all, that our children shall remain Russian, that they shall know something about the country of their parents, that they shall understand their own people and not be strangers among them. For that very reason the Russian children's schools, educating the children in the Russian spirit during this critical period, deserve the special consideration of every Russian patriot, for their work is priceless and quite necessary for the children of every Russian colonist.</p>
   <p>The most active members of R.I.M.A.S., participating in the work done by the school committees, make heroic efforts to shake the Russian colony out of the lethargy into which it has fallen, to awaken it to the realization of its own needs, and to make it think of the future, of the fate which awaits Russian children in a strange land. At present, as we have already pointed out, the school committees are primarily concerned with the material side of the existence of the Russian children's schools. For that reason almost simultaneously in the coming week three of the R.I.M.A.S. children's schools will give their benefit entertainments. All three schools to-day <pb facs="5423967_3_0208.jpg" n="3"/>address their appeal to the Russian colony and call upon its members to come to the entertainments and by their presence to help build up the funds that are necessary for the opening of the schools next fall. The appeal is addressed to all those who have preserved their Russian hearts and national sentiments. The appeal must not go unanswered, must not remain a call in the wilderness.</p>
   <p>For Chicago is not a desert; there are eighty thousand Russians in the city proper, and many thousands besides in the suburban territory. It is the duty of every Russian to attend the school benefit entertainments. It is the duty of every one whose Russian soul has not grown cold, and who still responds to our social and national needs. We firmly believe that all Russian people, and particularly the members of R.I.M.A.S., will consider it their sacred duty to attend, if not all three, at least one school entertainment.</p>
   <p>And thus, dear brothers and sisters from Argo, Pullman, Gary, and of course from Chicago, remember your sacred obligation toward Russian culture and toward <pb facs="5423967_3_0209.jpg" n="4"/>your own children. Come in a body to these entertainments. Prove that you are Russians who still remember and love their country! Remember that while attending the entertainments, you not only help the national cause, but you help your children as well, and you help, besides, yourselves, for you will enjoy the programs and will have a good time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
