<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. IX, owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. <date when="1918">1918</date>
<title level="a">(Unidentified newspaper clipping, Dec. 28, 1918)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. IX, owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a">(Unidentified newspaper clipping, Dec. 28, 1918)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Dec. 28. - The convention of Cultural Progressive Organizations takes place in the Douglas Park Auditorium, 3202 Ogden Avenue.</p>
   <p>Second Day of the Conference. The chairman, Professor Petrunkevich, opens the session at 10:30 in the morning. Owing to the illness of Secretary Jenderov's assistant, delegate Jesper is temporarily chosen for the post.</p>
   <p>A Telegram of Sympathy to Professor Novakovsky. Delegate Volkov moves to send the ailing Professor Novakovsky a wire of the following text: "Deeply esteemed Stanislav Yosifovich: The first Russian Cultural Progressive Convention in America, sponsored by the Chicago People's University, sends you its profound and sincere sympathy in your illness <pb facs="5423967_3_0651.jpg" n="2"/>and regrets deeply that you are unable personally to participate in the sessions and various committees of the convention, you being the soul of it all. The convention sincerely wishes you a speedy and complete recovery, and hopes that in the very near future you will be able to return to the cultural and educational activity, which you started for the benefit of the Russian toiling masses."</p>
   <p>The text of this message is unanimously approved. On the order of the day is the reading of a report on organizing a committee for a survey of cultural progressive educational institutions. Because this report was not prepared, delegate Volkov recommends the report sent by Mr. M. Vilchur, of the Russkoye Slovo editorial staff, and which is approximately on the same topic. Agricultural Engineer Volkov reads it, and the convention listens with interest.</p>
   <p>Next is a report on the great need to teach the Russian immigrants farming. Delegate Jesper reads this report. Delegate Reshkov expresses <pb facs="5423967_3_0652.jpg" n="3"/>a sentiment in favor of the opening of a Russian-American commercial institute. According to his statement, commerce and industry of Russia are completely in the hands of foreigners, chiefly Germans, and in order to nationalize the people's economy in farming and industry, adequate preparation for it is necessary.</p>
   <p>Professor Galatsky reads a paper on the need to open temporary instructors' schools. He points out in his lengthy discourse the necessity for general educational work, and for preparing workers for a general education. "Difficult and intricate," says Galatsky, "is the general educational work, and each one in this field must be on the summit of the situation, must have adequate background for the job. As a leader of the people's mental development, as one who hands out to the latter a certain amount of information, one should before all else, himself be equipped with a sufficient background of general education. At present one of the chief problems of general informal <pb facs="5423967_3_0653.jpg" n="4"/>education is a civic education of the masses. The Russian people, having attained to the right of full participation in the government, have yet to acquire a knowledge of civics. But where is one to get it? Only a general educational program affords it. And the dispenser of general education must, before all else, himself acquire a civic and economic background.</p>
   <p>General informal education means an all-round development of personality, mentally, ethically, aesthetically, and physically. Professor Galatsky finishes his discourse by saying that without serious preparation one cannot undertake such comprehensive work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
