<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1931-10-28">Oct. 28, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Prof. Swanish's Lecture about Soviet Russia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0792</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0792.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-10-28">Oct. 28, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">PROF. SWANISH'S LECTURE ABOUT SOVIET RUSSIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The lecture given by Prof. Swanish on Oct. 18, 1931, at the premises of the Russian-American Citizens Club, met with success. The public attended in spite of the fact, announced in the newspapers, that the lecture would be in English. It is apparent that at present many Russians understand the English language well enough.</p>
   <p>Prof. Swanish in his lecture gave an impartial illustration of the contemporary life in Soviet Russia. He mainly dealt with the collectivization of agriculture.</p>
   <p>Prof. Swanish declared that the Soviet government is not forcing the peasants to join the collective farms.</p>
   <p>The organization of collective farms is carried on in the following manner. A party organizer comes to the village; he calls a meeting and explains to the peasants the beauty of the life in the collective farms. For the illiterates he has special ready made "snapshots" of <pb facs="5423967_3_0793.jpg" n="2"/>existing collective farms. These snapshots portray not the real life on collective farm at all, but a paradise.</p>
   <p>After the report the question was to be decided by vote; those who were in favor of collective farms had to raise their hand, and if there were few people present, the meeting would be postponed for another time.</p>
   <p>In general the life of the peasants and workers in Soviet Russia is unenviable. They live through great scarcity, are fed only on "slogans," which in Russia are so numerous that they may be said to be innumerable.</p>
   <p>Everybody awaits the end of the five year plan, after the fulfillment of which so the young Communists predict, life will not be a struggle, but, a pleasure; the elders, however, are skeptical about it.</p>
   <p>On surveying all the events that take place in Soviet Russia, the following question involuntarily arises. How is it possible for such a Government, as the Bolshevik, to still remain in power?</p>
   <p>To this there are several answers. In the first place, no one is allowed <pb facs="5423967_3_0794.jpg" n="3"/>to leave Russia. In the second place, the Russian people still hopes that the slogans of the Bolsheviks will become realities in the future.</p>
   <p>The third reason is the endurance of the Russian people. These are the reasons why the Bolsheviks still retain the power.</p>
   <p>The Bolsheviks who were present in the hall started to raise objections. Prof. Swanish was not affected by their action. He politely addressed them and said: "If you do not believe me, then I advise you to go there and be convinced that I am telling you the truth. And if any one from you will give me his word that he will not return, then I will pay his expenses." A roaring laughter and applause net this statement. Prof. Swanish answers to the various questions were very pleasant and witty. Question: "Have they got bread lines in Russia?" "Yes, every laborer hurries to get in line earlier, as he is afraid that the goods will be given out before his turn comes."</p>
   <p>Question: "Why then Bernard Shaw, an English author, praised so highly the Soviet system?"</p>
   <p>"That is why: When Bernard Shaw visited Moscow, he was welcomed pompously. <pb facs="5423967_3_0795.jpg" n="4"/>From the R. R. station of Alexander he was driver in a luxurious automobile to one of the best hotels of Moscow. There, in his home, an artistocratic banquet was given. After the banquet Mr. Bernard Shaw with Lunatcharsky, and other Communist leaders went to the theatre, where a special program was presented in honor of the distinguished guest. The old man was accommodated in a luxurious box. Between intermissions he went behind the curtains and became acquainted with the actresses.</p>
   <p>Bernard Shaw, left the next day for Tambov in a "special car." From Tambov he visited the collective farms, where everything was prepared in advance to give him a hearty welcome. The children were washed combed and wore new dresses. The old men were decently dressed and shaved.</p>
   <p>Bernard Shaw, when looking at such jolly life on collective farms,was greatly impressed.</p>
   <p>One of the Bolsheviks asked the lecturer the following question: "What regime in your opinion, fits better the Russian people?" To this Prof. Swanish answered: "I have come here not to recommend "governments" to the Russian people, but to tell you what I saw in Soviet Russia."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0796.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"I would like myself to know, what government in your opinion would be the best for the Russian people?" No answer followed.</p>
   <p>Question: Do they have in Russia at the present time railroad cars of different classes?" Yes, they have three classes: there are cars with soft, medium and hard seats. The foreigners travel on soft seats, the communists use the medium, and the laborers and farmers the hard.</p>
   <p>The audience was with the exception of few Bolsheviks very pleased with the lecture.</p>
   <p>Professor Swanish spoke of what he has seen in Soviet Russia.</p>
   <p>One of those present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
