<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-08-03">Aug. 3, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Board of Directors of Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society Holds Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-08-03">Aug. 3, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">BOARD OF DIRECTORS OF RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT MUTUAL AID SOCIETY HOLDS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Board of Directors of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society held its regular meeting July 31 at the Russian parish hall, 917 North Wood Street. Among the matters discussed was the question of new types of life insurance, with policies which are particularly well adapted to the requirements of young people. This insurance, only recently introduced by the Independent Society, has met with great success, and promises still greater success in the near future. The youth department of the Society is now growing steadily because of an uninterrupted influx of new young members who are taking out the new insurance. It was decided at the meeting to stimulate all youth activities of all the branches of the organization. The educational committee, the organization committee, and the committee on cultural activities were instructed to spare no time or effort in bringing their work to the highest point of speed and efficiency. The members of the Board of Directors also decided to enlarge <pb facs="5423967_3_1203.jpg" n="2"/>the membership of the present committee on culture and education by adding to it one representative from each branch of the Society located in Chicago and vicinity. It was also agreed to undertake the sharpest measures in order to destroy Bolshevik propaganda and extirpate it from the midst of the Russian colony in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The general secretary of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society read a resolution passed by Branch No. 2 of the Society, and signed by Yurkovsky, one of the members of that branch. This resolution was published in Novy Mir, the Russian communist sheet, and was directed against the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society and against the Society's recent convention. At this convention, all the Red agitators, even though members of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, were summarily ousted from the convention. The Board of Directors of the Society, after a thorough investigation of this treacherous work of Branch No. 2, and especially of its chairman, Yurkovsky, and its secretary, Kravchuk, decided upon disciplinary measures for these two men: each <pb facs="5423967_3_1204.jpg" n="3"/>of them will have to pay a twenty-five dollar fine within ten days, and will be deprived of voting privileges for one year. If they fail to pay the fine within the designated time, they will automatically lose their membership in the organization, in accordance with section 86 of the constitution of the Society.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that this last decision of the Board of Directors of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society will serve as a timely lesson for all those remaining members of this organization who, because of their ignorance, support and follow these Red agitators, who are trying to bring ruin and destruction to the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
