<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1928-03-27">March 27, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Steinberg's Lecture in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0858</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0858.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1928-03-27">March 27, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">DR. STEINBERG'S LECTURE IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. I. Z. Steinberg, who came to Chicago from Europe, gave a lecture in Russian for the Chicago Russians on March 24. His theme was: "The Situation in Soviet Russia at Present." He believes that the October Revolution gave expression to all the desires of the Russian population. And if the Bolsheviki, after confiscating private property, would not have confiscated also freedom, the Russian revolution could be considered as completed. But the Bolsheviki proved to be different from what people imagined them to be. They proved to love power above all, to be cruel, intolerant towards other people's opinions, and they have cheated all the population of Russia. They talked one way, but acted in a totally different way.</p>
   <p>Mr. Steinberg began his lecture by characterizing the conditions which <pb facs="5423967_3_0859.jpg" n="2"/>had caused the October Revolution. Before the mental eye of those who were listening to him passed a panorama of all the events that had happened in Russia during the last ten years. Dr. Steinberg's approach to this complicated problem was chiefly a psychological one. His opinion is that the October Revolution did not happen because of the attacks of the Bolsheviki on the Kerensky government, but because the slogans written on the banners of the October revolutionists corresponded to the yearnings of the soul of every Russian. The population of Russia, freed from the yoke of the autocratic regime which it had borne for centuries, was pursuing two aims: improvement of material welfare and achievement of both political and economic freedom. "It would be difficult to tell," said Dr. Steinberg, "which was the stronger motive affecting the consciousness of the Russian peasant - the desire to get some land or the desire to get freedom. But anyhow, it would be very unjust to believe that all that the Russian peasants wanted was to grab the land that belonged to the rich landowners.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0860.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They are not the kind of monsters that would think only of filling their bellies."</p>
   <p>[Note: Dr. Steinberg was one of the chief leaders of the maximalist (extreme) fraction of the Social-Revolutionist Party and held the post of commissar of Justice in the beginning of the Bolshevist regime. The maximalist fraction had decided to cooperate with the Bolsheviki. D. S.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
