<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-09">Sept. 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Why I Left the Russian National Mutual Aid Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. Vorobey</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-09">Sept. 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">WHY I LEFT THE RUSSIAN NATIONAL MUTUAL AID SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. Vorobey</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Soon after I had become a member of the RNMAS (Russian National Mutual Aid Society) Branch 35, I noticed a terrible injustice practiced by the bosses in their relations with ordinary members of Branch 35 (now Branch 105 of the International [communist] Russian Order).</p>
   <p>During the annual meeting of the Branch, when everybody was expecting to hear the financial report on income and expenditures for the fiscal year, our bosses--Milkoff, acting as chairman of the meeting; Kutzko, treasurer; Deviatkin and others--announced that the report was not ready, and that it would be prepared for the next meeting. I should mention here that they usually hold two meetings a month--why, I don't know.</p>
   <p>At the next meeting the bosses again declared that the financial statement <pb facs="5423967_3_1457.jpg" n="2"/>could not be presented, because the treasurer had been busy collecting dues from members, and had no time to prepare it. Therefore the reading of the report would have to be postponed. Then suddenly one of the more daring members jumped up and made a flat demand that the treasurer present the financial report. The treasurer, offended by such a bold and unexpected demand, got up and said: "Don't be afraid. My books are in complete order, and to prove it, the auditor will read the report to you."</p>
   <p>Mr. Trushynsky, the auditor, then read the financial report, but he read it so fast, machine-gun fashion, that no one could understand a single item in his report. However, when he had finished, I realized that there was not a single penny left in the Branch's treasury. In a word, they had cleaned out the treasury in true communist fashion.</p>
   <p>Having finished reading his report, the treasurer concluded by saying that <pb facs="5423967_3_1458.jpg" n="3"/>the books were in good order. Then one of the members stood up and asked, "Where are the books of the financial secretary?" The bosses began to laugh at him and gave him this answer: "This is not Wood Street, but Division Street, and here we are satisfied with just one set of books." [Translator's note: At the Wood Street address there is another Russian Society, not dominated by communists.]</p>
   <p>After this incident the treasurer pulled out of his pocket a crumpled piece of paper, showed it to his questioner, and shouted: "Here is your report, if you don't believe me." And he put the piece of paper into his pocket. What this paper contained is known only to the bosses. The same member then declared that the method of keeping only one record of financial matters is very impractical and unjust, and demanded that two records should be kept. The bosses, however, prefer a single record, as more convenient for thieves.</p>
   <p>The longer I stayed in this organization the more I was convinced that a <pb facs="5423967_3_1459.jpg" n="4"/>bunch of crooks were in the saddle and were exerting power over unsuspecting people. Moreover, I also became convinced that Deviatkin, Mornell, and other "internationalists" are but pupils of such swindlers as Gurevitch, Kappagelli, Stoklitzkyi, and Stolar. It was Stolar, they say, who had brought Deviatkin to the Division Street Branch.</p>
   <p>I assume that all these fellows are well known to the entire Russian colony in America. I myself have suffered not a little because of them. I had spent six weeks at the "Isle of Tears" [Ellis Island], and they had cheated me out of four hundred dollars under the pretext of freeing me. And now these apostles of international hate have succeeded in getting the reins of the RNMAS Into their own hands, and, under divers pretexts are extracting the last pennies from the pockets of their members.</p>
   <p>At every meeting, the Comsomols [members of the Young Communist League], their caps or collection boxes in their hands, go around among those present and squeeze out their pennies, for there are no more dollars left.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1460.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>When I was a member of the RIMAS Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society) my insurance premium was $1.55 on an eight-hundred-dollar policy, while at the RNMAS my premium on a seven-hundred-and-fifty-dollar policy is $1.99. Consequently, my monthly loss is 44 cents, or $5.28 in one year. According to the general secretary, the society has over five thousand members. When we multiply this amount [i.e. the annual "loss" of $5.28] by the number of members, we see what an enormous sum of money is being devoured by the Communists who have fastened themselves on the RNMAS. And look how much of our hard-earned money is being eaten up by the Novyi Mir [the Russian Communist newspaper]. That many members are not able to pay their dues does not worry them. It is true that I myself have never made any contributions to this wretched Novyi Mir, but the bosses of the RNMAS, without asking us, take four thousand dollars every year from our common treasury, and give the money to this communist newspaper. And if we add to this the money received from collections, offerings, balls, and picnics, the total reaches huge proportions. They are indeed the robbers of the Russian workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1461.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>But Mr. Shklar [local communist leader] is still unsatisfied. At every meeting, Mr. Deviatkin and a few other henchmen of Shklar's shout and do their utmost to get more money out of the members for the Novyi Mir. By subscribing to this newspaper, which is hostile to the Russian people, we are paying tribute to Shklar and his satraps. Many times I have questioned several members of this Society regarding the finances of the organization, and regarding the money which was being so mercilessly extracted from us, the workingmen. But I have always received the same answer: "Ask Deviatkin about it."</p>
   <p>When I asked Deviatkin he answered that the rank-and-file members are not supposed to know where the collected money goes, that no one can make any financial report, since the Novyi Mir is being published by the Communist party, and therefore only the party knows how the money is spent.</p>
   <p>This answer of Deviatkin's really made me think. I began to ask myself, "Who are these Communists? And what good have they done to the Russian people in <pb facs="5423967_3_1462.jpg" n="7"/>America to merit our trust in their honor?" And I have come to the conclusion that they have not done anything good, but have merely robbed the Russian people, and have taught them how those imposters should be looked upon and dealt with in the future. Thanks to this lesson many Russian immigrants have long ago turned away from them. Today, only the members of the RNMAS, though not all of them, still believe in those scoundrels.</p>
   <p>And now these swindlers are up in arms against the RIMAS. At all their meetings and at all social affairs they conduct a systematic propaganda campaign against the Independents. Moreover, they have established a large army of agents who have flooded the RIMAS, and are trying to overrun it. Some of these traitors have already revealed their treacherous character, while others are still waiting for a more propitious time and a signal from Deviatkin to start their dirty work. Day and night they scheme and plan so that they can lay their filthy hands upon the independent RIMAS.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1463.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>I am firmly convinced that their intentions will not succeed, if they have not succeeded up to this time. They will not succeed in their undertaking for the following reasons: In the first place, the Independents will never agree to be governed by uninvited guardians. In the second place, the Independents are protected by such a strong fence that Deviatkin will not even be able to gain access to them. By the word "fence" I mean that section of the Independents' Constitution which forbids persons of non-Slavic origin to become members of the RIMAS. [Translator's note: This provision in the constitution of the Society was intended to deny admission to Jews. And Deviatkin is a Jew.]</p>
   <p>I also want to urge the Independents not to use much ceremony in dealing with Deviatkin's envoys. Simply chase them out; they are not your friends, even if they are Russians. I happen to know not a few Russian workers who are serving as spies for the Communists. Under the influence of the Communist opium they have completely lost their wits. They are ready to lend their <pb facs="5423967_3_1464.jpg" n="9"/>aid to the most vile undertaking, if only they can be of service to Deviatkin and his crew.</p>
   <p>Somehow I could never reconcile myself to the fact that any intruder and enemy of the Russian people can worm his way into the Russian organization and then boss everybody according to his own liking. In the beginning I was told by some members of the RNMAS that Deviatkin is not such an important person in the affairs of the Society, but now I know that he is the boss there, and what he says goes.</p>
   <p>Look at Klimko, look at how he wriggles at the feet of Deviatkin in his effort to carry out all his orders. Deviatkin had ordered Klinko to brand and smear all Russian organizations and all Russian people, and Klimko carried out all his orders to the last dot. Klimko does not seem to realize that Deviatkin had joined the organization for the sole purpose of setting one Russian group against another, and thus prevent their union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1465.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Observing this mockery and ridicule of the Russian people, I decided to leave this organization, so that my ears should not hear and my eyes should not see.....To remain a member I consider below human dignity.</p>
   <p>I am calling upon all honest, reasonable Russian workers not to turn over their hard-earned pennies to Shklar's treasury. Do not allow them to deceive you.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
