<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-22">June 22, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Independents Celebration in Argo, Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-22">June 22, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">INDEPENDENTS CELEBRATION IN ARGO, ILLINOIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, June 16, the Brotherhood of St. Trinity (Branch No. 5 of R. I. M. A. S. [Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society]) celebrated its traditional holiday. A great many people gathered for the occasion, and the hall could hardly accommodate all who came to join in the festivities. Beside residents of Argo, many Russian people from Chicago and its environs joined the crowd. There were also present numerous delegates from Russian and Polish organizations. There were two delegates from the Brotherhood of St. George (Chicago Branch No. 1 of the R. I. M. A. S.). There were representatives from various sisterhoods and other women's organizations. The Polish organizations were represented by several delegations from their fraternal orders. Among them one could notice delegates from the Order of St. Stanislaus and of St. Joseph.</p>
   <p>The reception of the delegates was conducted with a certain degree of solemnity. Mr. Drevgan, chairman of the Brotherhood of St. Trinity, in a dignified way <pb facs="5423967_3_1223.jpg" n="2"/>pinned his official ribbon on, and greeted the delegates, one by one, shaking their hands. Then the national anthem was played. After the ceremony was over members of the reception committee, with Mr. Drevgan as the host, conducted all the guests to the banquet tables, heavily laden with food.</p>
   <p>Several tables had been reserved for the delegates, and they were treated with real Russian hospitality. During the banquet some of the delegates addressed the guests in a few friendly words of greeting. Mr. Erin, delegate from Branch No. 1 (Chicago), was called upon to greet the guests and representatives of three organizations: the Brotherhood of St. George, as the host of the occasion; the Sisterhood of Russian Women in Argo; and the Polish organizations represented at the banquet. Erin's address was brief, but full of meaning and fine sentiments. The words addressed to the Polish organizations particularly pleased the fraternal delegates of Polish nationality. They were deeply moved by the friendly Slavic sentiments addressed to the people who are so closely related to the Russians. Some of the Polish delegates responded with words of gratitude and mutual cordiality. It would be of great advantage to the Slavic peoples, <pb facs="5423967_3_1224.jpg" n="3"/>and would promote mutual understanding, if such meetings of their representatives in the atmosphere of friendliness and complete confidence were held more often than is now the case, particularly in Europe.</p>
   <p>Through such exchange of sentiments and opinions in the past the Slavic peoples could have formed a mighty united family in the Old world, and could have avoided the mistrust and the enmity which are being generated between Russian and Polish people by those whose interests are inimical to the Slavic race. Erin, in his statements, was ably supported by Mr. Gulko, another delegate from Branch No. 1.</p>
   <p>The speakers appealed to the Argo residents of Russian descent to fill up the ranks of their branch. They explained to them the new forms of insurance which have been but recently adopted by the Society; also, the new forms of insurance adopted for children, and called upon parents to bring their children into the ranks of the children's branches, which are being organized by the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1225.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>They spoke also about the new buildings with modern facilities which are being put in shape by the R. I. M. A. S. on Wood Street for the convenience of its members, and appealed to the people to give financial support to the undertakings of the R. I. M. A. S.</p>
   <p>The appeals were heard with marked attention. A collection was taken for funds to help finance the construction work in progress on Wood Street. This yielded a goodly sum of money. Thus ended the official part of the program.</p>
   <p>The festivities as a whole were conducted in the friendliest of spirit, with utmost cordiality, and with moral and material success. There were present as many people as the limited facilities of the hall could accomodate. A feeling of great animation prevailed throughout the day among the guests. They enjoyed dancing and conversation with friends and neighbors. The hosts gave careful attention to their friends, and all the workers who volunteered their services for the day were in their places, performing their duties.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1226.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Most conspicuous among the guests by the originality of his appearance was a man by the name of Petia. He closely resembled "Taras Bulba," the chief character in Gogol's novel of the same name. Long mustaches adorned his face, and he carried himself among the guests with a particular air of aloofness.</p>
   <p>From conversations with the Russian residents of Argo, one gained the impression that they live in perfect harmony and peace, not only with the members of their own Russian family, but with the people of other nationalities as well. They dislike only the Communist "comrades," who conduct themselves provokingly, and try to do harm to the fraternal organization whenever an opportunity presents itself.</p>
   <p>The visit I paid to the traditional holiday festival in Argo has given me great pleasure, and it only remains for me to express my wish for the highest success of their organization in the future in the fruitful work the Russian residents of Argo are carrying on.</p>
   <p>One who was present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
