<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Voronko, J. J. "<title level="a">Our Goal</title>," <title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title> (Russian Review) (Monthly),
<date when="1927-11">Nov. 1927</date>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0119</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0119.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Voronko, J. J. "<title level="a">Our Goal</title>," <title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title> (Russian Review) (Monthly),
<date when="1927-11">Nov. 1927</date>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.3-4--For the first time, as far as we know in the brief history of Russians in the Central States, there appear in the city of Chicago a Russian monthly.</p>
   <p>Any publishing house believes that the work it has started is the best and that it answers the current needs of the public.</p>
   <p>That is the custom. But we, on the contrary, with our first issue, believe that we shall be unable to give the best interpretation of our current needs immediately. Yet we hope to create a most satisfactory new monthly of literature, art and social life later.</p>
   <p>Why? Russians are too mottled a crowd; among them there is a variety of views and it would not be an easy task to satisfy various groups who are all equally seeking spiritual nourishment yet each of them wants to get only a special kind of it.</p>
   <p>How should we then understand the name "Russkoye Obozrenie"? Everything relating to Russian life; the life of Russian immigrants; everything what <pb facs="5423967_3_0120.jpg" n="2"/>Russian culture offers that is new and brilliant and whatever relates to it; everything that should interest the Russian immigrant and should be known to him under the conditions of American life; everything concerning his interests as an individual and member of a local group--from enlightment and schools to economical and social problems.</p>
   <p>All this we are striving to present in such a manner as not to arouse antagonism among neighbors, but to pacify them and bring about closer relationship between them; we shall endeavor rather to teach and educate them, than to arouse strife between groups, classes, or races. In this case, with such a path towards our future goal, we intend at every step of ours to seek only those relationships which are common to all the various groups of society, and which give rise to more idealistic contacts,--and "society" we understand in a very broad, democratic way.</p>
   <p>In the United States, at present, there are to be found many distinguished Russian scientists, literary men, and artists. We will strive to have them take an active part in our cultural work. Besides, in many places in the colony itself, whenever we hear of new talents born on American soil, we <pb facs="5423967_3_0121.jpg" n="3"/>will not permit them to be drowned in the chaos of American streets.</p>
   <p>On the other side, the best productions of contemporary Russian literature, wherever they appear, if noticed by the Russkoye Obozrenie (Russian Review), will be published in the pages of our magazine. Outstanding contemporary events; events in our social life; and discoveries of science will be published in due time.</p>
   <p>Our aim is to make the Russkoye Obozrenie an encyclopedia on questions which embrace our program.</p>
   <p>But, in issuing Russkoye Obozrenie in America, where our social life at present is just being born, we reckon that we can realize completely our aim, only with the cooperation of all live, active workers of the colony who sincerely will point to us: how we run the Russkoye Obozrenie; whether or not we are deviating from our aim; whether or not we are changing our mapped course because of accidental influences; whether or not we zealously serve mankind and the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0122.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Hence, in our opinion, our problem is easily understood. Everything else--the development of our general principles and intention--our friends and readers will gather from the current material.</p>
   <p>The Editors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
