<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Unidentified Newspaper Clipping</title> Dated
<date when="1918-12">Dec. 1918</date>
<title level="a">in Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. IX, Owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a" type="sub">At the Chicago Convention of Educational Organizations Third Day of the Convention</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0606</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0606.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Unidentified Newspaper Clipping</title> Dated
<date when="1918-12">Dec. 1918</date>
<title level="a">in Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. IX, Owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a" type="sub">AT THE CHICAGO CONVENTION OF EDUCATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS Third Day of the Convention</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This being Sunday, also it being after the ball given yesterday by the People's University, the delegates arrived slowly. Chairman Petrunkevich opens the session.</p>
   <p>First in order is the discussion on establishing a Soviet of the Convention of Russian Educational and Cultural Organizations in America. Professor Galatsky presents the discussion with a number of arguments proving that it would be more strategic to have a Soviet of People's Universities in close connection with the Central Committee of the Federation of Russian Organizations, for then the <pb facs="5423967_3_0607.jpg" n="2"/>Soviet would be backed by all the organizations that make up the federation, and all would collaborate with the Soviet. Professor Petrunkevich seconds the motion. In his opinion this is all the more necessary in order to get co-ordinated action in the educational work of the Russian colony. Also the federation pursues educational ends, and one of its problems is to establish Russian universities. Through united efforts there will be a conservation of energy and of means.</p>
   <p>A majority of delegates are residents of Chicago and suburbs and they contend that Chicago should be the center for managing the work of creating people's universities.</p>
   <p>The convention adopts a resolution to the effect that the Soviet <pb facs="5423967_3_0608.jpg" n="3"/>of People's Universities must retain full autonomy, cooperating, nevertheless, wherever possible with other cultural and educational organizations.</p>
   <p>The question as to which of the two cities, New York or Chicago, should serve as the pivotal point from which the Soviet will conduct the work, calls forth a long discussion. Delegate Lipetsky argues that destiny itself was pleased to choose Chicago for this purpose. He reprimands the Russians in New York with the statement that notwithstanding their numerous organizations, they have done nothing in the cultural and educational fields.</p>
   <p>Delegate Khinoy's rebuttal is that New York has several such people's universities like the one in Chicago; only that they do not call themselves universities, do not deal with such complex problems, and <pb facs="5423967_3_0609.jpg" n="4"/>do not burden themselves with such comprehensive regulations as does the Chicago People's University. He makes the motion to establish the Soviet in New York and also to establish regional Soviets in towns with considerable Russian population.</p>
   <p>Other speakers favor the idea of establishing the Soviet in New York, pointing out the abundant cultural-educational forces in that city.</p>
   <p>Yet, the Chicagoans do not capitulate. A vote is taken and by a majority of fourteen to twelve it is decided to establish the Soviet in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The convention holds elections for the principal Soviet of the Convention of Russian Educational-Cultural Organizations in America. It is decided to elect seven people, - three from New York and four <pb facs="5423967_3_0610.jpg" n="5"/>from Chicago and suburbs. They are vested with power to increase this number with persons useful to the cause.</p>
   <p>One of the nominated candidates, Professor Petrunkevich, declines in view of the fact that he promised the central committee of the federation in New York to collaborate with them in their cultural and educational work.</p>
   <p>The elected members of the Soviet are Professor Galatsky, New York; Agricultural Engineer Volkov, Urbana, Illinois; Professor Novakovsky, Chicago; Engineer Bregovsky, Chicago; K. M. Oberuchev, New York; Father Mardary, Chicago; Doctor of Jurisprudence D. Z. Krinkin, New York.</p>
   <p>Professor Galatsky, as the only Soviet member from New York present, thanks the convention for his election and expresses hope that by <pb facs="5423967_3_0611.jpg" n="6"/>concerted efforts it will be possible to conquer the principal foe of the Russian colony in America and of the Russian people generally, that is, to conquer ignorance.</p>
   <p>One hour recess is announced.</p>
   <p>When the session is resumed the remaining two topics of the program are in order, namely, the publicity work of the Soviet and ways and means with which to carry out the outlined plans.</p>
   <p>The convention leaves to the elected Soviet the task of applying its efforts to the solution of these problems.</p>
   <p>As there are no extraordinary motions, Chairman Petrunkevich declares the First American Convention of Russian Cultural-Educational Organizations closed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
