<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya, (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1922-09-16">Sept. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Life in the Russian Colony to the Russian Colony of the City of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya, (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1922-09-16">Sept. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">LIFE IN THE RUSSIAN COLONY TO THE RUSSIAN COLONY OF THE CITY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Comrades! The great Russian revolution stirred the deepest strata of the toiling masses in our homeland. From a slave without rights or speech, the working class became all at once the master of the great Russian country. He proved to be a master without knowledge and without experience.</p>
   <p>In order to rule so great a country, in order to organize the economy of the country, which has been subjected to ruin by war and counterrevolution over a number of years, experience and knowledge are indispensable. Therefore things did not go right in the beginning of the revolution; there was a scarcity of experienced and educated peasants. It is true that Russia suffered much from the intervention of the foreign capitalists, who, with their armies, invaded the country from all sides, attempting to crush the revolution and to reinstate a tsar. With internal enemies, the capitalists, the landowners, and the nobility; with the help of parties hostile to the Soviets; with the S-R's <pb facs="5423967_3_0514.jpg" n="2"/>and the monarchists organizing counter-revolutionary uprisings and sabotaging; and with other forces interfering with the organizing of a peaceful order of life in the country it was impossible to set up a stable government. If the workingmen and the peasants had been better equipped with knowledge, Russia would have suffered less. At present things are getting into shape in Russia, but there still exists a scarcity of experienced workers. Remember, that up to the revolution Russia had only 21 per cent of literacy in her population, i. e., of every hundred only twenty one could read and write. Now the educational program is making big strides.</p>
   <p>But what about us, the Russian immigrants, living in Chicago?</p>
   <p>There is here a society of technical assistance to the Soviets. This society has a school for adults and children. Come and learn in this school. Equip yourselves with experience and knowledge, so that upon coming back to your homeland you will be able to help in the building up of the country, in the construction of a new life, and in the governing of it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0515.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Send your children to study in this school. Give your children the knowledge of their native tongue. Give them the opportunity of knowing the country of their origin. Fathers and mothers! Do not estrange your children from their own family and from Russia by giving them an American education only. By that education alone you will become strangers to your children. Your children must know your language! Do all you can that our school, which is your school, may spread out abounding with pupils.</p>
   <p>Registration of pupils will continue through September 12-25 in the school, at 1417 N. Hoyne Avenue. The following subjects will be taught: The Russian language, arithmetic, algebra, geometry, physics, chemistry, drawing, automobile construction, tractors, farming, etc.</p>
   <p>When there are a sufficient number of students enrolled, courses in dramatics will be organized.</p>
   <p>The School Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
