<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous - <title level="a">"Pioneers of School Work in Communities,"</title> <title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title>,
<date when="1928-02">Feb. 1928</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous - <title level="a">"Pioneers of School Work in Communities,"</title> <title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title>,
<date when="1928-02">Feb. 1928</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.24-25--In connection with the increased drawing of the school in the Russian colony, we are involuntarily reminded of the recent past of the community. The sad memory of the past recalls to our mind how tens of thousands of former landtillers, the majority of whom were ignorant or illiterate, and thrown unto alien soil, were forced to think of the fact how to teach their children their mother tongue.</p>
   <p>The majority of these people, did not have in their childhood the opportunity of receiving education even in elementary schools. Life taught them deeply the old adage: "Learning is light, and ignorance is darkness." And with all means available, they strove impetuously to give their children at least some education in their mother tongue; but how difficult it was to fulfill this desire!</p>
   <p>With the exception of two or three parochial schools, there were no such Russian institutions in existence. There were practically no teachers, because at that time the Russian immigration consisted wholly of peasants, and the intellectual Russian was rare. There were no resources for the upkeep of <pb facs="5423967_3_0369.jpg" n="2"/>the schools; communities were very poorly organized; and the individuals of the colonies were illfortunate paupers in a strange country.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, they still found it possible, in some manner to teach their children to read and write. Occasionally, even to learn themselves.</p>
   <p>The Russian Revolution, aroused in the colonists an even more passionate desire, a flaming aspiration after the establishing of schools. And after that, there appeared in different sections of the country one school after another. Russian youths, at that time, earnestly raised their voices for the need of schools and for adults as well. In the year 1918, as a result of many efforts, struggles, and ventures, there was founded in the city of Chicago a so-called People's University. The appearance of the University was a great event for the Chicago Russians.</p>
   <p>"The Russian People's University is a kindled flame among the Russian American, which compellingly beckons them to knowledge and enlightenment." Thus wrote a worker, one of the first students of the University, in the <pb facs="5423967_3_0370.jpg" n="3"/>in the local newspaper, Svobodnaya Rossia (Free Russia).</p>
   <p>"It is the duty of each of us," wrote another student, a worker, "to learn and complete our education in order to be useful members in our native land, upon returning there."</p>
   <p>"For many succeeding years, I dreamed of completing my education," wrote a Russian girl, "and now, as soon as I learned of the opening of the People's University, I said to myself - 'now or never'. It was the most happiest day in my life and it will remain in my heart forever."</p>
   <p>In appealing to the colony, Russian students, by the way, wrote: "We students, understanding the meaning of education, the importance of learning, felt that the school is a source of intellectual wealth, and that it will give us not only satisfaction and enjoyment, but also prepare us to be cultured and useful workers!"</p>
   <p>Later, one of the students wrote of the results of attending the school: "Eight months ago, I was barely able to read syllables and scrawl letters.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0371.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But at present, I write this letter without any assistance. Just as much time ago, I could barely do simple figures, and now I solve problems of fractions, and am learning such important subjects as geography, metallurgy, drafting, and others."</p>
   <p>One of the students, president of a large organization, wrote: "We Russians are wearied of living in darkness....and now we emerge from darkness unto the path of enlightenment. In order to do this, it is necessary to establish more schools and attend them."</p>
   <p>The University, to our sorrow, existed only about a year. Internal dissension in the colony and "politics" within the walls of the University, put an end to its existence. Later, a school was opened for adults, bringing much benefit for the colony in the sense of raising the level of education among those who were thirsty for it. This school also did not last very long. But this was a period, in which there was very much eager talk of the necessity of establishing as many schools as possible; a period in which the Russian colony in the city of Chicago, as well as in other cities, began to think seriously of the necessity of teaching their children their native language, and of the necessity of acquainting them with the culture, <pb facs="5423967_3_0372.jpg" n="5"/>spirit, and history of our native land.</p>
   <p>At that time, little was accomplished in this direction, but great and strong was the impulse of the working people of the colony towards the realization of their ardent desire of establishing the schools.</p>
   <p>Glancing at the activities of the school in the colony, and at the inspirers of it, we see clearly that the chief guiding thread is to be found in its past idealistic attitude towards the school--an attitude which was common among the elder colonists. Indeed, among the present chief workers, who support the schools both morally, and materially, we see mostly the old familiar faces of former enthusiasts, and energetic workers who were upholding the idea of creating schools and other organizations in the colony.</p>
   <p>Taking into consideration some unfavorable circumstances in the work of creating schools, it is necessary to admit that during the past few years in this venture, noticeable progress has been made. On the other hand, taking into consideration, the former enthusiasm in relation to the establishment of schools, and the assimilation by the colony of new and fresh forces, it seems that much more could have been accomplished.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
