<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-27">Apr. 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Are You a Member of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1347</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1347.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-27">Apr. 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">ARE YOU A MEMBER OF THE RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT MUTUAL AID SOCIETY?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society is an organization devoted exclusively to the cultural and economic interests of Russian immigrants. The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society offers sick and death benefit insurance to its members.</p>
   <p>Over a half million dollars has been paid out by this society to its members in the form of death or sick benefit during the period of its existence. The money collected by the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society is used to aid members in time of need, and to raise the prestige of the Russian name. None of the money is spent for political propaganda or other purposes, as is the case with many other Russian organizations.</p>
   <p>The newly introduced forms of insurance, such as the ordinary life insurance policy, the twenty-year life insurance, the twenty-year endowment policy for <pb facs="5423967_3_1348.jpg" n="2"/>adults as well as children, offer excellent advantages to our members, as do the twenty-year term policies for adult members.</p>
   <p>Every Russian should belong to the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
   <p>Become members of this society and enroll your wives and children. Talk to your friends and acquaintances and tell them about the advantages derived by members of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. The new members are enrolled without payment of any initiation fee, and the medical examination is paid for by the main office of the Society.</p>
   <p>Send your children to the schools maintained by the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
   <p>For more particulars, apply by letter to the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, 4129 North Mobile Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
