<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-06">July 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Picnic of the Saint George Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-06">July 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE PICNIC OF THE SAINT GEORGE PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Saint George parish, Branch Number One of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, held its annual picnic Sunday, June 30, in the woods at the end of Elston Avenue.</p>
   <p>Besides the usual picnic attractions, which were enjoyed by the large crowd at the picnic, there were several important speeches, delivered by the officers of the Society and by invited guests. Among the speakers were the following: V. Oleksink, chairman of the St. George Society; Mr. Novin, secretary of the Rassviet Publishing Company; I. Volos, who recited one of his own poems; and Paul Nervana, the new superior of the Saint George Parish.</p>
   <p>Mr. Nervana summed up what had been said by the other speakers, and appealed to all Russians in Chicago, and especially to the young Chicago Russian-Americans, <pb facs="5423967_3_1210.jpg" n="2"/>to join the ranks of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, the largest Russian benefit organization in the Middle West. He concluded his speech by asking all those present at the picnic for contributions to the Society's building fund for the new buildings the organization is now erecting on the Wood Street site. The contributions neeted $74.75. Mr. Nervana thanked the contributors, and the Saint George choir sang an old Russian song, "Many, Many Years". Before and after the various speeches, the orchestra played popular Russian tunes, to the great joy and satisfaction of the public.</p>
   <p>The picnic was a big success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
