<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-01-04">Jan. 4, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society in 1935</title><title level="a" type="sub">by P.S.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-01-04">Jan. 4, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT MUTUAL AID SOCIETY IN 1935</title><title level="a" type="sub">by P.S.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The days and years pass by really very fast. Unnoticed the year 1935 has gone by carrying away all our joys, sorrows and anxieties of the past year. What will the year 1936 bring forth? What joys, what sorrows has it in store for our immigrant people?</p>
   <p>In the life of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society [R.I.M.A.S.] the most important event during the past year was, of course, the introduction of the new forms of insurance.</p>
   <p>Formerly, as everybody knows, we had only the uniform straight-life policies. During the past year, however, we adopted almost all existing forms of insurance. The introduction of these new forms cost the Society a great deal of <pb facs="5423967_3_1186.jpg" n="2"/>money and involved a great deal of work both for the Executive Board and for our general secretary, Mr. Nicholas Kozak.</p>
   <p>The importance of this innovation is perhaps not fully understood by all the rank and file members, although the step has an all-important bearing on the future life and development of our organization. These new forms of policies are, in their meaning, like a reinforced concrete foundation for a building. They impart to the Society the strength and stability of steel and concrete. Resting on that kind of a foundation, R.I.M.A.S. will undoubredly grow and develop, for the money put in its treasury will be perfectly secure, and the monthly payments much smaller than in any other insurance company.</p>
   <p>Not less important for the Russian people is the fact that the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society is the only mutual aid organization in Chicago and its vicinity. They can communicate with it in Russian either by mail or by wire, and speak to its officials in Russian. Meetings, conventions, and <pb facs="5423967_3_1187.jpg" n="3"/>the minutes of all proceedings are carried on in their native Russian language, which is dear to their hearts. Allegiance to their own society and the possibility of addressing others as "brothers" or "sisters" make the Russian people thrown into a strange land less lonesome, more confident in their strength and ability to survive. The moral support it gives is the main service rendered by R.I.M.A.S. to the Russian people. This is quite well understood by the Russian colony in Chicago, and this explains the fact that new members are continually being added to the ranks of the organization. During the year just closed several new branches were organized, and outgrew the old ones in membership.</p>
   <p>Some of the branches carry on intensive cultural and educational work among the young people, which will help to preserve the Russian language and, consequently, the youth itself for Russia.</p>
   <p>During the past year, R.I.M.A.S. also opened permanent offices where all Russian people can apply for necessary information or in any case of need.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1188.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>During the past year the page financed and edited by R.I.M.A.S. has given space to many valuable articles written exclusively by the members of our society. Successful, also, was the fight against the enemies of the Russian people and those of all working people.</p>
   <p>From all that has been said it is clear that during the past year R.I.M.A.S. has accomplished a great deal that is good and useful.</p>
   <p>Let us express the hope that during this new year of 1936, also, we shall continue ceaselessly to go ahead without loss of faith and courage on account of obstacles which we may encounter in our work.</p>
   <p>Let us continue to create those spiritual values which help to lift the Russian community to the height it properly deserves and thereby gain respect of other nations.</p>
   <p>The Independent Society has taken upon itself another new task--the task of <pb facs="5423967_3_1189.jpg" n="5"/>raising the cultural level of the Russian colony.</p>
   <p>Let us, then, rally around our organization and help it to carry out this noble and beautiful task.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
