<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novy Mir (New World)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-01">April 1, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">The Federation of Russian Children's Schools in Chicago and its Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0219</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0219.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novy Mir (New World)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-01">April 1, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">THE FEDERATION OF RUSSIAN CHILDREN'S SCHOOLS IN CHICAGO AND ITS SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Back in August of 1922, through the assistance of the writer of this article, at that time, on the staff of the newspaper Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia), there was formed in Chicago a White Russian committee to aid White Russians in their struggle against the Polish imperialists.</p>
   <p>In March of 1923 on our horizon there appeared a "new" man. Anton Zmagar. A radical of radicals, an enthusiastic fighter against imperialistic Poland, who had just arrived in the United States from White Russia. The writer called for his benefit a White Russian Meeting in the South Side School. Zmagar declared himself a "positive" defender of Soviet White Russia."</p>
   <p>He, without any delay, joined the White Russian committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0220.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Here this "John the Baptist" said: "Who am I?" I baptize you only with water, but he who follows me will baptize you with the fire of life. Send money and bring him from White Russia."</p>
   <p>They sent money.</p>
   <p>And Joseph Voronko arrived.</p>
   <p>Both White Russians made their bow in the Russian colony. They became teachers in our schools and took off their masks soon after.</p>
   <p>Zmagar, who is also known as Ivan Charapuk and who proved to be a Catholic priest, began a struggle for the "Russian spirit" at school; Voronko, a White Russian chauvinist, began organizing anti-Soviet groups in the then existing White Russian societies of the schools.</p>
   <p>This was the beginning of a struggle within the Federation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0221.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At that time in the colony appeared another "nincompoop" by the name of Nicolai Kaluzin - at present a doctor L. Pertsov, or Percy.</p>
   <p>A cadet, an agent of Miliukov and at present a monarchist-fascist and one of the "spiritual" leaders of the so-called "Mladorossov" or "young Russians," he has gained the confidence of the owner of the newspaper Russkii Viestnik and became its editor.</p>
   <p>Immediately Kaluzin-Pertsov opened a bitter fight for the removal of "internationalism" in Russian workers' schools. Although personally, the White Russian chauvinists were miles apart from Kaluzin, his poison against the Federation was very handy for them.</p>
   <p>The struggle became intensified. Not a day passed when there were not lies and gossip against the workers of the Federation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0222.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The aim of the enemies was to capture and dissolve the Federation, to convert the workers' schools into their white-guard stores and to win over the non-resisting Russian colony. But from the point of view of tactics, this struggle was not directed against the Federation as such, but against "individuals" and mainly against the first president of the Federation's Soviet, Jacob M. Eberhardt. He was accused of establishing and "internationalism" in the schools.</p>
   <p>Incidentally, the fight for the "Russian spirit" could not be based very well on the fact that Eberhardt's name spoke little to the "Russian heart.</p>
   <p>Between June 3-6 and 9-14, 1924, the second convention of the Federation took place, with seven represented, that is, the South Side, Douglas Park, North Side (on Elston Avenue), Brighton Park, Wicker Park, Pullman, and East Chicago schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0223.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The South Side School, which at the beginning of the year, being incited by the teacher Zmagar, had temporarily broken away from the Federation, sent again its delegates to the convention at the initiative of the old workers of the school.</p>
   <p>At this convention - one of the most exciting conventions of the Federation, - two entirely opposing camps have been established.</p>
   <p>But our side has conquered.</p>
   <p>Kaluzin, who with his yellow press succeeded in stirring the colony previous to the convention, had his mouth shut by the delegates, who with scorn have rejected his mandate as a representative of the Russkii Viestnik.</p>
   <p>The Russian chauvinists were compelled to pretend that they were in <pb facs="5423967_3_0224.jpg" n="6"/>step with the majority of the Federation.</p>
   <p>At the second convention the constitution of the Federation was renewed and amended concurrently with the experience acquired during two years. The executive and educational committees were instructed to obtain text books. It was decided to establish a library of the Federation, to create educational courses for adults, etc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
