<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title><date when="1935-04-20">Apr. 20, 1935</date>,
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0160</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0160.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet, (The Dawn)</title><date when="1935-04-20">Apr. 20, 1935</date>,
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: Mr. Volos was at this time president of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, RNzOV.]</p>
   <p>The country in which we live affords us every liberty of action within the framework of the law. In the United States we enjoy freedom of speech, press, and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> are permitted to form their own national or <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> privileges which they would be unable to obtain <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <p>Cultured people take <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in order to preserve their national identity so far as their cultural and economic lives are concerned. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the people <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to improve their cultural or educational status, form economic and educational associations. They develop spiritually and grow stronger economically.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0161.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> official statistics in America, there are two hundred large organizations of the type represented by the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, with about 102,000 local branches. Membership in these organizations totals eight million people. These organizations possess financial resources estimated at one billion <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> million dollars. The figures just given indicate <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the working population of America that belongs to the mutual aid associations <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> that the latter have accumulated. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>; there are many thousands of other <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> which are not subject <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> supervision.</p>
   <p>In a word, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> <pb facs="5423967_3_0162.jpg" n="3"/>and assistance prevails among the members of a national group. Many Russians are still unable to understand this simple truth. The membership of a great majority of the organizations of which I have spoken is made up of immigrants. This is also true of the Russian organizations, including the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
   <p>When we examine the statistics pertaining to the composition of the mutual aid organizations, with reference to the national groups, we find a sad situation as regards the Russians. We Russians constitute only a small percentage of the membership in this type of organization. That small percentage cannot be explained by the allegedly small number of Russians present in America as compared with the people of other nationalities. The discrepancy is due to the failure of the Russians to recognize the advantages of organizations and the benefits to be derived by the members of a national group from organizations. We treat the whole problem with indifference. We have no plans for the future, we live from day to day; we have no ideals to carry <pb facs="5423967_3_0163.jpg" n="4"/>us forward. We prefer to live in darkness and for this perference we sometimes pay dearly. We have no central authority. Very often dubious characters attach themselves to our unorganized people. These adventurers mislead the Russian colony.</p>
   <p>On the doors of one of the schools I read the inscription: "Where there is no vision, the people perish." This is the truth by which we shall abide. The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society has not adopted this axiom for its slogan, but it strives in all its activity to serve the best interests of the Russian people. Our society preaches the advantages of organization for our people, for their preservation, and the attainment of a better future. Then, what ideal does our society set before itself? The ideal which we follow can readily be seen from the very name of our organization. Mutual aid is our motto! This means helping one another in an hour of need, mutual support in case of necessity.</p>
   <p>As I said before, America is perhaps the only country in the world where <pb facs="5423967_3_0164.jpg" n="5"/>there is full liberty for action within the law--action directed at the preservation of national identity. And if this is so, it would be criminal if we did not take full advantage of the liberties given to us.</p>
   <p>RNzOV calls upon all Russians who do not belong to any organization, to join its ranks. Assure yourselves and your family of the benefits offered by our organization. Join in the activity of our society. There is no initiation fee for new members.</p>
   <p>The new policies being issued to our members offer many advantages not enjoyed formerly by our people. For all information, apply to the main office of our society, 4129 North Mobile Avenue, or to the local branches.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
