<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous - <title level="a">"The Anniversary of the Moskva Magazine"</title>, <title>Moskva (Monthly)</title>,
<date when="1930-03">Mar. 1930</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous - <title level="a">"The Anniversary of the Moskva Magazine"</title>, <title>Moskva (Monthly)</title>,
<date when="1930-03">Mar. 1930</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Exactly a year ago, the first issue of the magazine "Moskva" saw its first light. During that period it had met with great obstacles in its publishing career. It is an exceedingly difficult task to publish a Russian magazine here in America. During that short period of time, I witnessed many daily, weekly, and monthly publications appear and disappear. Nevertheless, the magazine "Moskva" under its able helmsman, Dr. L. G. Pertsov the editor steadfastly surmounts these difficulties and is guided ably to a cultural and nonpolitical haven. The Russian Colony is in need of such a magazine.</p>
   <p>In a small room which is used as the Editors office (the same building in which the office of the Doctor is located), the editor works alone, using all his energy and strength in developing his beloved hobby.</p>
   <p>He is aided in this hard and noble work by the secretary of the Russian Center, Mr. V. D. Maslov. And so both Dr. Pertsov, in his spare time and Mr. Maslov, labor unintermittingly, without any assistance.</p>
   <p>One has to admire and wonder at the inexhaustible energy of these men.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0111.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All their free time is donated to the work, and time is valuable to every immigrant. They receive no compensation for their efforts, except the moral satisfaction of doing this great cultural work abroad and at the same time not loosing any cultural connections with their native country.</p>
   <p>It is not the thirst for fame nor any financial reward that guides them, but the great task of creating a Russian magazine abroad, which would be satisfactory from a literary standpoint to the Russian immigrants who are scattered all over the world.</p>
   <p>Let this magazine "Moskva" carry with it our immigrant masses and guide them to a better, brighter, and more cheerful future.</p>
   <p>Sow, Ye Russians the Seeds of Russian Greatness in Foreign Lands.</p>
   <p>A. Antsiferov.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
