<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-09-29">Sept. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">More Russian Schools for Children</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0293</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0293.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-09-29">Sept. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">MORE RUSSIAN SCHOOLS FOR CHILDREN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A good beginning spells success. Two years ago, the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society opened a number of schools for Russian children in Chicago and vicinity. Today, the schools are filled to capacity; their presence is making itself felt, and they are appreciated by an overwhelming majority of the Russian people in Chicago and nearby towns. Judging by the success of these schools, it will be necessary to open a few more schools in other parts of the city for the next school season. The Russian School Council receives many letters from parents asking aid in organizing new Russian schools for Russian children.</p>
   <p>The Russian School Council employs capable persons of proven ability to teach the children. Perhaps this is the reason for the great success of our schools. In addition to the regular teachers, the Council provides visiting <pb facs="5423967_3_0294.jpg" n="2"/>lecturers, who, with the aid of slides, show the children the cities, rivers, mountains, and other natural treasures of our homeland.</p>
   <p>In the schools maintained by the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, there is room enough for young and for old. Special classes for adults are being held regularly. The Russian School Council intends to introduce one system of teaching in all Russian schools in the Chicago area, and to standardize all school activities. The Russian School Council shuns all politics, since politics brings corruption into any good work.</p>
   <p>The Bolshevik sympathizers in our group wanted us to use Bolshevik textbooks in our schools. But these textbooks are not understandable to Russian-American children. The children do not want to read excerpts from Marx, Lenin, and Engels. They want the verses of Pushkin, the fairy tales of Krylov, and reading material from other great Russian writers. In the Russian schools in Chicago maintained by the Bolsheviks, the instructors poison the children's minds with <pb facs="5423967_3_0295.jpg" n="3"/> politics. During stage plays in their schools, for instance the children often appear with guns in their hands, with which they threaten their own parents, saying they would not scruple to kill their fathers and mothers if the latter opposed the Communist ideology. In their recitations, one often hears such exclamations as "Strike, plunder, destroy!" and similar expressions. These methods of education will have a terrible effect on the future lives of the Russian-American children now under the influence of the Bolsheviks.</p>
   <p>In the schools maintained by the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society the children are taught to love their parents and to respect other people, and how to be good and useful members of society.</p>
   <p>The parents who permit their children to be taught by the Bolsheviks in the Bolshevik schools are but blind tools in the hands of shrewd and cunning Bolshevik politicians. Such parents are hopelessly gullible to all Bolshevik <pb facs="5423967_3_0296.jpg" n="4"/>promises, because of their total ignorance. A prominent American once said : "You Russian people teach your children how to read and write. When they grow up they will be able to know good from bad, wrong from right. It would not be so easy to fool them as it has been to fool you. You made the revolution, you overthrew your czar; yet you have permitted a band of political adventurers to govern you and to oppress you even more than you were oppressed by the czars. Czarist oppression and Bolshevik oppression have been possible only because seventy-five per cent of all the people in Russia could not read or write."</p>
   <p>If Russian-American parents want to see their children living happy lives in the future, they should send them to one of the Russian schools of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
