<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. Theodore S. Komar</title>, President of the Slavonic Club, International House, U. of Chicago.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1022</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1022.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. Theodore S. Komar</title>, President of the Slavonic Club, International House, U. of Chicago.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Slavonic Club was organized in 1927 through the efforts of Dr. D. D. Droba, who conceived the idea of uniting the better element of the Slav people residing in Chicago. At that time Dr. Droba was a student of psychology at the University of Chicago and was first president of the club. The Slavonic Club includes Russians, Bulgarians, Jugoslavs, Czechs, Polish and other nationalities who are interested in Slavenic culture. At present the membership is about one hundred. Among the active members of the club are students and alumni of the University of Chicago and other institutions of higher learning. There are also about 150 friends of the Slavonic Club who interested themselves in the club's activities. Once a month, on the second Friday, the club meets on the campus of the University of Chicago. Headquarters of the Slavonic Club is International House. The Slavonic Club quite often entertains its members and friends with lectures on Slavonic culture, exhibitions, artistic as well as cultural dramatics. Plays such as "Marriage," by Gogol, and "Protegee of the Mistress," by Os rovski were presented recently by the Slavonic Club in the Auditorium of International House.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1023.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At present the club is engaged in sponsoring, in the near future the play "The Lower Depths," by Maxim Gorki. Small sketches, farces, etc., are presented quite often at the Auditorium of International House. Also popular programs of individual and combined groups of International House.</p>
   <p>In conjunction with the above, an educational program in the from of sound motion pictures is being presented by the club. "The Earth Sings" was shown lately. They also present pictures of peasant Slavonic life, etc. These pictures are photographed in the European countries and produced under the direction of the department of ethnology in the Czecho-Slovakian Institute of Art and Sciences.</p>
   <p>Theodore S. Komar is the present president of the Slavonic Club and is serving in that capacity for the second year. Mr. Komar is a native of Russia, born in Novogrodsk, province of Minsk (present-day Poland), <pb facs="5423967_3_1024.jpg" n="3"/>and came to America in 1921. He is a graduate of the University of Detroit and holds an M. A. degree from the University of Chicago. Mr. Komar came to Chicago in 1927 and has resided here with his family since. At present he is connected with International House as cashier. Mr. Komar is preparing himself for the degree of doctor of philosophy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
