<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-08-10">Aug. 10, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Branch Number I Passes a Timely Resolution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1195</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1195.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-08-10">Aug. 10, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">BRANCH NUMBER I PASSES A TIMELY RESOLUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Branch Number 1 of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, at its last meeting, held on August 4, considered at length the hostile resolution against the Independent Society by Branch Number 2 of this organization. The resolution was published in Novyi Mir (the Russian communist newspaper) under the signature of I. Yurkovsky, chairman of Branch Number 2 of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. In this resolution, Mr. Yurkovsky accuses the present board of directors of the Independent Society of embezzling the organization's funds; he charges that the members of the board seek self interest in conduction the Society's affairs, and that they committed illegal actions at the recent 24th convention of that organization.</p>
   <p>In view of the fact that all these allegations and accusations are without any foundation whatsoever, and are but sheer lies intended to undermine the confidence of the people in the organization and to harm the prestige of the members of the board of directors, all members of Branch Number 1 present at the <pb facs="5423967_3_1196.jpg" n="2"/>meeting resolved to issue a public reproof of the action of Mr. Yurkovsky, and to request the board of directors of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society to apply all punitive measures stipulated by the constitution of this organization against members who disobey the regulations of, or in any way bring harm to, the organization.</p>
   <p>Branch Number 1 hereby expresses its gratitude to the board of directors for its fruitful and disinterested work for the welfare of the organization, and for the Russian cause in general. All members of Branch Number 1 feel convinced that the directors of the Society, as well as the delegates to the 24th convention, acted justly and wisely when they excluded from the debates of the convention all men who represented the Russian Peoples' Mutual Aid Society. This is a communist organization; its delegates were communists who came to the convention with the convention with the definite plan to further the interests of the Communist party, which, as everyone knows, is striving to disrupt all Russian patriotic organizations in this country and to disorganize and destroy the entire Russian group in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1197.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Branch Number 1 of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society pledges its full support to the actions and policies of the high council of this organization in its fight against all harmful elements within our organization.</p>
   <p>It would be desirable, also, for members of Branch Number 2 of this organization to pay more serious attention to the harmful activity of their chairman.</p>
   <p>V. Olesiuk, chairman,</p>
   <p>P. Yushko, secretary,</p>
   <p>A. Bernov, treasurer,</p>
   <p>Branch Number 1,</p>
   <p>Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
