<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-18">Feb. 18, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Likes the Singing, Not the Lecture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0714</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0714.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-18">Feb. 18, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">LIKES THE SINGING, NOT THE LECTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On January 31 Bishop Leonty delivered a lecture on "Religious Motifs in A. S. Pushkin's Poetry". In the press announcement it was promised that in the intermission the Cathedral choir under direction of Mr. Grivsky would sing several songs of Pushkin's. Yet there was no choir but only three young women who recited some of the poet's verses. [The choir] had been the bait for the working class. I think that many people on so cold an evening came [merely] to hear the church choir. I myself came to hear the singing and not the lecture.</p>
   <p>There were about four hundred people in the audience, among them many churchgoers. There were also present numerous active members of the Chicago Russian colony. It was noticeable that many listeners fell strongly under the influence of the Pushkin Memorial Committee. When the lecture was over, one of the Ukrainians in the audience wanted to say a few words about Russian peasantry and religion, but Chairman Nedzelnitsky declared that no debate would be permitted.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0715.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>P. Zaychenko had written about this lecture. He said in his article that one of the false beginnings is the beginning of atheism, which is the source of the slavery and the enslavement that we observe at present in Soviet Russia. I am not a defender of communism, but I ask Zaychenko to answer me without offending his conscience before God and Church, [the two] objects of his faith, whether there was not any enslavement of man by man under the czarist regime. If the answer is yes, then why should he heap all the blame on the atheists?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
