<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-09-03">Sept. 3, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">New Elections at the School Federation</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0400</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0400.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-09-03">Sept. 3, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">NEW ELECTIONS AT THE SCHOOL FEDERATION</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The session was called to order at 11:30 A. M. on Sunday, Aug. 30. First of all a roll call of the delegates was taken and their credentials were examined.</p>
   <p>Delegates from the following schools were present:</p>
   <p>1. Brighton Park School -- Delegates P. Turovets, S. Abranchik, and the teacher S. Mornel.</p>
   <p>2. Douglas Park School -- Delegates I. Zhukov and J. Eberhardt.</p>
   <p>3. Progressive Fullerton School -- Delegates Komyak and Zhestkov.</p>
   <p>4. Wicker Park School -- Delegate Moiseyenko and the teacher Miss Roghinskaya.</p>
   <p>5. Cicero School -- Delegates T. Tureyko and Morozov.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0401.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>6. Pushkin School (Pullman) -- Delegates Smolik and Levkovich.</p>
   <p>The delegates from the North Side School and the East Chicago School were absent.</p>
   <p>The question was raised as to the necessity of making the attendance of the meetings of the federation (once a month) compulsory for the teachers of the schools. A motion was made by the delegate Levkovich and was accepted unanimously. This motion is as follows: It is the duty of all teachers to attend the sessions of the federation; those who will not do so without giving any serious reason, will be discharged.</p>
   <p>Next came the elections of the officers. Three times candidates were nominated, but they all declined the nomination. Ultimately, in order to enable the convention to get out of this difficulty, Turovets, the delegate from the Brighton Park School, agreed to be nominated president of the Federation of Schools for Children. His candidature was put to <pb facs="5423967_3_0402.jpg" n="3"/>the ballot, and he was elected unanimously. Ivan Zhukov was elected recording secretary; T. Tureyko, financial secretary; S. Abramchik, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The following persons were elected members of the Educational Committee: Mornel, Eberhardt and Zhestkov.</p>
   <p>Mr. Remenchik was nominated manager of the bookstore; the accepted the nomination and was elected unanimously.</p>
   <p>J. Eberhardt was elected librarian.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
