<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Moscow</title>,
<date when="1930-09">Sept. 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The Object of the Russian-American Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0806</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0806.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Moscow</title>,
<date when="1930-09">Sept. 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE OBJECT OF THE RUSSIAN-AMERICAN CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. The Club shall put forth all efforts to organize a series of popular, educational, and social lectures, discussions, meetings, trips, excursions, picnics, shows, concerts, etc., in the Russian and English languages, inviting for this purpose experienced lecturers, social workers, teachers, engineers, artists, musicians, etc. A special Committee, consisting of three members elected by the Assembly of all the Club from among people having sufficient experience and desire of cultural work, has complete charge of this work.</p>
   <p>2. The Club shall put forth all efforts to establish a library, reading room, recreation room, gymnasium, Russian school with kindergarten, night school (English language, study of America, the people, life and customs). The Club shall help the Russian youth desiring to enter American schools to make their way through school. The Club shall also assist the working people who cannot get a normal education to enter the American free <pb facs="5423967_3_0807.jpg" n="2"/>summer schools, to secure work and vacations for them. For the execution of this work a special School Committee shall be elected by the Assembly of all members of the Club from among the best teachers and doctors. This Committee shall have three sections: General, women's, and children's.</p>
   <p>3. The Club shall propagate its ideas and attainments among Russian-American people through newspapers, magazines, booklets, book, radio, etc. The Club shall correct all untrue statements in the American press regarding Russian life, culture, etc. The Club shall cultivate the love for the printed word among Russian-American youth. A special committee, entitled Press Bureau, shall take complete charge of this work, acting in closest contact with all Russian and American press, supporting the Russian-American Club.</p>
   <p>4. The Club shall establish connection with all Russian and American cultural organizations, state and federal institutions and organizations in order to improve the moral and material conditions of members of the Club and their families.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
