<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Minutes of the Supreme Assembly of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society Held Saturday</title><date when="1933-04-30">April 29 and Sunday, Apr, 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">At the Hotel Morrison 85 West Madison Street in Chicago, Illinois, (In Manuscript, property of Rimas).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1477</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1477.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Minutes Of The Supreme Assembly Of The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society Held Saturday</title><date when="1933-04-30">April 29 and Sunday, Apr, 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">At The Hotel Morrison 85 West Madison Street In Chicago, Illinois, (In Manuscript, property of RIMAS).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first session of the 22nd Supreme Assembly of Rimas was held Saturday, Apr. 29, 1933 at the Hotel Morrison, 85 W. Madison St. Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>1. E.Horoschenia's Address To The Assembly.</p>
   <p>President of the Society, E. Horoschenia, opened the Assembly with a short welcome address at promptly 4:00 p.m. and suggested that two sentries be elected to supervise order in the room. The duties of sentries were accepted by Ivan Pyatnitza and W. Sabinsky.</p>
   <p>Roll Call.</p>
   <p>Recording secretary of the Society, James Sleznik called the roll of the delegates to the Assembly.</p>
   <p>From Branch 1--The Brotherhood of St. George, Chicago, Ill., the following were present: Semen Jakimowich, George Wallace, W. Sabinsky, Jacob Dziako, V. Konashewsky, J. Michalchik, M. Horozanko, Trofim Marchuk, Andrew Haponovich, D. Vorobey, <pb facs="5423967_3_1478.jpg" n="2"/>I. Karpin, Andrew Shustitzky, James Sieznik, Fedor Davidchik, Alexander Pasink, V. Dedovich, P. Nagorny, John Pyatnitza, Alexander Grigorchuk, and Dr. P. L. Chadovich; absentee--Zachary Stolarana.</p>
   <p>From Branch 2.--Brotherhood of St. Vladimir: Leon Stanko, and S. Parfeevetz. Absentee: John Oleksink.</p>
   <p>From Branch 3.--Sisterhood of the Feast of the Intercession of the Holy Virgin: Katherine Paroda, Julia Jakimowich, Agafla Dedoshko, Maria Kiersch, Anna Boris and Fedora Syman. Absentees: Maria Davidchik, Vera Sergenia, Fedora Ustich, Xenia Popeiko and Natalia Omelianiuk.</p>
   <p>From Branch 4.--Brotherhood St. John the Baptist Semen Fedorovskii.</p>
   <p>From Branch 5.--Brotherhood of Holy Trinity--Jacob Borisuk, Nicholas Krupka and Vladimir Sviridiuk.</p>
   <p>From Branch 7.--Society of L.N. Tolstoi of East Chicago, Ind.,--Ivan Skoliuk.</p>
   <p>From Branch 8.--Sisterhood of St. Anne-Julia Zavada.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1479.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From Branch 10.--Sisterhood of the Assumption of the Holy Virgin: Anastasia Gorbachuk.</p>
   <p>From Branch 12.--Brotherhood of St. Peter and Paul in Benton Harbor, Mich: Luka Dulko.</p>
   <p>From Branch 14.--Society of F. M. Dostoevsky, Detroit, Mich: Stephen Korin.</p>
   <p>From Branch 15.--Society of A. S. Pushkin, Chicago: Nikon Sidorovich.</p>
   <p>From Branch 16.--Harvey, Ill: Daniel Kupchik.</p>
   <p>From Branch 17.--Baltimore, Md.: Delegate not present.</p>
   <p>From Branch 18.--Society of I.A. kryloff: Foma Tureiko.</p>
   <p>From Branch 19.--Society "Faith, Hope, and Love", Benton Harbor, Mich: Artemii Rak.</p>
   <p>From Branch 20.--Baltimore, Md.: Delegate not present.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1480.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Besides the delegates to the Assembly there were present: Representatives of the children's Russian school of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society: Michael Nesteriuk of the Kryloff school; Anton Bernoff from Humboldt Park school, also representatives of the Pullman, Douglas Park and Argo schools, and the School Council was represented by A. Bernoff.</p>
   <p>In his address to the Assembly on behalf of the School Council he thanked the Rimas for the moral and material support it has lent the schools and requested the delegates of the 22nd Assembly and the Supreme Officers of the Society to support the schools in the future because the schools open the light to our young generation in whom we must place our hopes and of whom we should be proud, since the duties of continuing our beginnings on a larger scale for the welfare and flourishing of the entire Russian working colony in America will lie on the shoulders of our young school children.</p>
   <p>2. Election Of Ballot Tellers, &amp; Committee On Credentials.</p>
   <p>After the committee on credentials has examined the credentials of the delegates, the Supreme President of the Society, Horoschenia, moved that tellers be elected: Those unanimously elected as tellers were: Fedor Davidchik, and Trofim Marchuk.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1481.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The committee on credentials was elected of the following: D. Vorobey, V. Dedovich and Vladimir Olesiuk. The following were elected to the Audit committee: Vasily Konashewsky, Alexander Pasiuk and Stephan Korin.</p>
   <p>Aten minute intermission was called for the purpose of giving the committee on credentials time to examine the credentials of the delegates.</p>
   <p>3. The Committee On Credentials Report.</p>
   <p>The committee reported that all credentials were in order, and that among these there was one from Rnov, appointing Stephan Nikolaiuk to the Assembly of Rimas.</p>
   <p>President of the Society, Horoschenia, made a motion that the committee on credentials express its opinion on the credentials of Stephan Nikolaiuk. The committee reported that the credentials are in order out at the same time recommended to the Assembly that S. Nikolaiuk should not be accepted as a delegate to the Assembly and that no relations with Rnov be recognized until the latter Society ceases to cast dirt upon our foremost workers, calling them the treacherous head, etc. But together with this a motion was made by delegate S. Korin that the matter be put to a vote of the Assembly for decision. The Assembly voted 26 to 15 against acceptance of S. Nikolaiuk to the Assembly. Likewise it <pb facs="5423967_3_1482.jpg" n="6"/>was announced that Nikolaiuk may remain as a guest to the Assembly.</p>
   <p>A letter was also received in the name of the Assembly from the newly formed group of Independents, who, having fallen under the influence of the communists-Rnov, are hostilely attuned toward the Rimas and its Supreme Officers. It was signed by F. Kakasiuk, president, and John Aybaka, secretary, and reads that Rimas should not consolidate with the New York Society, Roova, which in their opinion is ruled by white guards, enemies, of the workers and peasants, out it should consolidate with the worker's society--Rnov whose members are all workers and which is ruled by workers only.</p>
   <p>Delegates to the 22nd Supreme Assembly resolved unanimously not to direct any attention on the group of impostors and referred this letter for investigation to Branch 1 of Rimas.</p>
   <p>5. President E. Horoschemia proposed to the Assembly that a presidium be elected to conduct the Assembly and requested that nominations for chairman begin:</p>
   <p>Nomination And Election of Chairman Of The Assembly:</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1483.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Nominees were: G. Wallace and S. Parfeevitz. In a closed ballot G. Wallace received 34 votes and S. Parfeevetz, A. G. Wallace was therefore elected vice-chairman of the Assembly.</p>
   <p>6. Nomination And Election of Secretary Of The Assembly.</p>
   <p>The following were nominated for secretary of the Assembly: A. Haponovich, D. Vorobey, J. Sleznik, <gap unit="char" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Horozanko, J. Dziako, <gap unit="char" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Kiersch, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Jakimowich, <gap unit="char" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Konashewsky and T. Marchuk. All declined the nomination with the exception of A. Haponovich who was unanimously elected as secretary of the Assembly. N. Sidorovich was elected unanimously as assistant-secretary of the Assembly.</p>
   <p>7. Installation Of The Presidiun Of The Assembly.</p>
   <p>President of the Society, E. Horoschenia announced the erection of the officers of the Assembly concluded, and called the latter to assume their duties. Chairman of the Assembly in a brief speech thanked the Assembly for the honor bestowed upon him and asked the delegates to conduct themselves peacefully and settle the business before the Assembly logically and wisely, and requested all delegates to the Assembly to rise and silently pay tribute to the memory <pb facs="5423967_3_1484.jpg" n="8"/>of the chairman of the last Assembly, Anton Tichanovich. Thereupon there were read congratulatory messages received in the name of the Assembly.</p>
   <p>9. Messages To The Assembly.</p>
   <p>The following messages were received in the name of the Assembly: From Branch 17 of Rimas in Baltimore, Md., Branch 7, in East Chicago, Ind.; from Rassviet publishers; Branch 18, Roova, Gary, Ind., Independent Cooperative Bakery, 1525-27 N. Ashland Ave., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>10. Speech By Irene Gulko.</p>
   <p>Irene Gulko, pupil of the I. S. Turgenieff school, read a speech which was met with loud applause. The content of the speech was: Permit me to greet you on behalf of us students of the I. S. Turgenieff school in Douglas Park of Chicago, Illinois, one of the schools of the Rimas. We, who are learning, all know what benefit the Independents bring to the Russo-American Youth, creating and supporting the independent schools where Russian people live, members of the Independent Society. The school year which just ended was the first for our school, and this year proved that our parents, the independents, have taken the right course.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1485.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>The creation and consolidation of schools around the Rimas is a consolidation of us, children of the independents, with the parent organization, for which we are ready to work as our parents have worked in establishing it. Teaching us the language of your fatherland, whence our fathers and mothers have come, you are joining us with great cultural Russia and broaden our intellectual horizon, our education. You have heard what grief was caused in Chicago by the announcement of the closing of the American schools. Americans exclaimed: Do not close the schools, they are the beaconlights of the nation. The same can be said of our Russian schools. Our schools are the beaconlights of the Russian colony. The pupils of the Turgenieff school thank the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society for the support lent to the school and wish the 22nd Supreme Assembly greatest success.</p>
   <p>11. A Similar welcome to the one in paragraph 10 was delivered by V. Sviridiuk, a pupil of the Argo school.</p>
   <p>12. Reading of The Minutes of The Last Assembly.</p>
   <p>Secretary of the Assembly, A. Haponovich, began reading the minutes of the last, the 21st Supreme Assembly. After the reading, the chairman asked the delegates <pb facs="5423967_3_1486.jpg" n="10"/>whether or not anyone noticed any errors or did not understand some decision in the protocol of the 21st Assembly. Delegate of Sranch 1, J. Dziako stated that there are two points in the protocol absolutely incorrect, namely, where he (Dziako) spoke regarding consolidation with Roova. But, perhaps, the secretary of the Assembly did not note what anyone said at the Assembly out only rewrote from the newspaper what, the editor had written. To this remark the secretary of the previous Assembly, J. Sleznik, replied, that it something was not recorded as J. Dziako had spoken, it was because J. Dziako made his speech not from writ ten copy out orally, which was impossible to write word for word. Pasiuk made his speech from written copy and it was placed in the protocol in full. After this, the Assembly found that the correction should be made in the minutes. Paragraph 49--J. Dziako says that it is not necessary to hasten with the consolidation for the reason that as there are among our members many opposed to consolidation, so there are in Roova, also. For this, it is necessary to delay with consolidation until members of Rimas and Roova reach a better understanding. And also paragraph 59 was corrected to read: J. Dziako requested the delegates to the 21st Assembly to allow him to print his speech in full in the "News" page of Rimas; instead of: J. Dziako may print his speech only in the columns of the newspaper. The remainder of the protocol was accepted without correction.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1487.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>13. Reports Of Committees.</p>
   <p>Elarion Horoschenia, on behalf of the Executive Committee, reported what efforts were made to improve the social work for the benefit of the Russian colony. Much work was done in creating schools; concerning consolidation with Roova, we have completed the preliminary work in this respect, but we have not hurried to conclude it. This matter still requires much work. The question of consolidation of local organizations must be left open rather than create unfriendliness of one toward the other. It is impossible to conduct social work on such funds as are allocated for the administrative fund. In order to develop the work of mutual aid and conduct cultural work, it is necessary that every member pay toward the fund 15c monthly.</p>
   <p>14. Financial Secretary's Report.</p>
   <p>N. Kozak, financial secretary, reported that as of December 31, 1933 the membership of the Society was 1301 adult members and 519 minor. There new branch as had been organized. After the report of the financial secretary, Joseph Sleznik, treasurer of the Society, reported that the capital of Rimas as of <pb facs="5423967_3_1488.jpg" n="12"/>April 1, 1933, was $62, 894. 36; cash in banks, $17, 103.36; $12,487.49 in the Continental Illinois Bank. &amp; Trust Company; the Juvenile Branch, $2,205.12 at the Continental Ill. Bank &amp; Trust Company; in the Noel Bank $1,068.18; loans to members, $39,000. In a checking account there is $1,361.77; notes receivable from members, $1,291.00; $5,500 invested in society property at 6925 South California Avenue.</p>
   <p>15. Audit Committee Report.</p>
   <p>The audit committee report was made by K. Jarmolik. According to this report, the financial books of the Society are in order. Then Jarmolik thanked the executive committee for its fine social work and added that we should not pay any attention to our enemies, who spread rumors that there are no friends in the Society (Independent Society), and that they cannot conduct the people's affairs. Other auditors, F. Davidchik and T. Marchuk confirmed that spoken by Jarmolik.</p>
   <p>16. L. Stanko's Request.</p>
   <p>L. Stanko, delegate of Branch 2, requested an explanation of the report of the <pb facs="5423967_3_1489.jpg" n="13"/>Treasurer, Jos. Sleznik, regarding the money in the Noel Bank, and those monies not approved by the city auditors. E. Horoschenia explained that the Insurance Department of Illinois does not allow money to be invested in shares, and therefore, the shares were removed from the assets of the Society, out they are nevertheless in our hands.</p>
   <p>17. Question of Payment of Taxes On Society Investments.</p>
   <p>J. Dziako asked whether or not the Supreme Officers have examined and promptly paid the taxes and other levies for those properties in which it has $39,000 invested. Elarion Horoschenia explained that last year, in the month of June, they were examined and everything was in order and interest on mortgages was paid practicably by all in full; out this year they were not examined, and I (Horoschenia) think that everything will be checked after June, namely, when the books of taxes for Cook County will be closed. Whereupon the financial report was unanimously approved.</p>
   <p>18. Recording Secretary's Report.</p>
   <p>Recording secretary, James Sleznik, reported that the directors of Rimas have <pb facs="5423967_3_1490.jpg" n="14"/>accurately attended meetings; there were no meetings missed; every member tried to the best of his ability to execute that work which was placed in his charge. He expressed that in the future the directors are desired to take the work of the Society just as seriously.</p>
   <p>19. School Committee Report.</p>
   <p>A. Bernoff spoke in behalf of the School Committee. In his report, Bernoff expressed the interest in schools indicated by the parents. He recommended to the Assembly to act and support the schools in the future.</p>
   <p>Nagorny: The school work has proceeded satisfactorily. The crisis which all parents are experiencing has hurt the schools strongly. But notwithstanding all the difficulties in the school situation, the schools at present have gained a great popularity and are seriously interested in culture.</p>
   <p>Horoschenia: The schools, they are the cultural hearth which must receive attention. Because of the schools, we have increased Rimas. This is our future; the schools are the best means of inoculating Russian culture to the young people striving for it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1491.jpg" n="15"/>
   <p>Nesteruk : Kryloff school has 16 pupils. The work is progressing; there is hope that in the future the number of pupils will increase because in the said district there are many Russians and many children.</p>
   <p>Kichkailo: At the Turgenieff school, thanks to the support of the Society, there are 19 pupils; the financial condition of the school is not enviable. There are efforts being exerted to protect the school's existence in the future.</p>
   <p>Sidorovich: In the Pushkin school there are 16 pupils who are studying well and have already achieved much, namely in the learning of the Russian language. The material condition of the school, as everywhere, shows deficiency, but notwithstanding the difficulties, we must focus our attention on the school work; the schools have enhanced us and will supplant us in the future. In this inclination we should work for the sake of the younger generation.</p>
   <p>S. Korin: The Dostoevsky school in Detroit, Mich., is attended by 15 pupils. It has brought great benefit to the Russian children, in their study of the Russian language, history, geography and other subjects. In financial condition, we are all limping, but we shall speak of this later.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1492.jpg" n="16"/>
   <p>20. Report Of The Organization Committee.</p>
   <p>S. Jakimovich spoke on behalf of the Organization Committee: In his report, Jakimovich stated that because of the unemployment situation much was not accomplished, therefore, no serious measures were undertaken in this respect.</p>
   <p>Sidorovich: Certainly, because of unemployment, the organization work was complicated, however, we have organized schools and three new branches.</p>
   <p>21. Intermission.</p>
   <p>Promptly at 9:00 p.m. Saturday, April 29th, J. Michalchik moved that a 10 minute intermission be made. The motion was seconded and carried and simultaneously a question was raised as to the closing hour of this session. The delegates expressed that the session be continued until 10:00 p.m.</p>
   <p>22. After the ten minute intermission, the chairman, M. Sabinsky, called the delegates to take their places and announced that the speeches from the branches will begin.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1493.jpg" n="17"/>
   <p>23. Branch 1.</p>
   <p>A. Haponovich, from Branch 1, St. George Brotherhood in Chicago, greeted the Assembly and wished it success in all its decisions of the business in the order of the day for the Welfare and improvement of the entire Russian colony and read a written report. There were 523 members in Branch 1, January 1, 1935. Four members have passed away during the past year. Eighteen new members in mutual aid. Last year $500 was paid to schools. The Branch annually pays about $2000 in sick benefits.</p>
   <p>24. Branch 2.</p>
   <p>L. Stanko reported that there are 61 members in the Branch; two new members were enrolled. There is $1500 in the Treasury of the Branch, and $150 is due from members.</p>
   <p>25. Branch 3.</p>
   <p>Sisterhood of the Assumption in Chicago. Julie Jakimowich reported that on April 1, 1933 there were 230 good paying members. In 1932 the income was $3,680.43.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1494.jpg" n="18"/>
   <p>There was $2,985.75 turned over to the Society for the death benefit and the fund. The income for the first quarter of 1933, January, February and March, $905.89; and $810.65 has been turned over to the Society for the Death Benefit.In the treasury of the Branch as of April 1,1933 there was $3,525.55. In 1932 there were 20 new members and two old ones returned. During the first quarter of 1933 there were 11 new members enrolled.</p>
   <p>26.Branch 4.</p>
   <p>S. Fedorovsky reported that the branch has 14 members and there is $50 in the treasury. Everything is well in the Branch.</p>
   <p>27. Branch 5.</p>
   <p>N. Krupko reported that there are 66 members in the Branch and $655.00 in the treasury. All is quiet in the Branch. Due to unemployment it is difficult to attract new members. Difficulties are encountered in collecting payment of dues from old members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1495.jpg" n="19"/>
   <p>28. Branch 8.</p>
   <p>I. Skoliuk reported that the branch has 40 adult and 7 minor members. Because of the depression, the membership has decreased by 13 members this year. Last year there were 53 members. The treasury is also diminishing. In the bank there is $153.04. $859 has been loaned to needy members. We have no school. The branch arranges two functions annually, one Jubilee and one picnic, out these result usually with deficits. Our committee works for almost nothing that is $20 annually. The place cost $25 annually. Our branch favors maintaining the sick benefit at the branch and no payments for the administrative fund, out keeping the $40 in the treasury of the Branch. We have no sick members.</p>
   <p>29. Branch 9.</p>
   <p>Julia Zavada reported that the branch has 30 members. There is no sick benefit in the branch. The branch favors a central sick benefit fund not to be forced on the branches. The branches desirous of having a central sick benefit may have it, but we wish to remain as at present, that is to have it as formerly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1496.jpg" n="20"/>
   <p>30. Branch 10.</p>
   <p>A. Gorbachuk. Our branch is advancing forward, although slowly. Recently there were 5 new members added. Now there are 37 members. There is $766.99 in the treasury. Our members do not wish to receive sick benefit and do not wish to pay for it. Our meetings are peaceful. For the treasury there remains 25c from each member. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>e have no depression. All the members are employed.</p>
   <p>31. Branch 12</p>
   <p>L. Dulko. There are in the Branch 17 admit and 5 minor members. There is $63.00 in the treasury. Because of the depression activity in the Branch is slow. The branch needs lecturers in order to settle the school problem.</p>
   <p>32. Branch 14, of Detroit, Mich.</p>
   <p>S. Korin. Our Branch has 19 members who pay dues regularly. On April 1st there was $86.93 in the treasury, and $63.45 due from members. Two lecturers were arranged during the year. Our branch finds no need in arranging frequent lecturers <pb facs="5423967_3_1497.jpg" n="21"/>as relative (sic) organizations often arrange them. Our branch has a school with fifteen pupils receiving instruction. There was a string orchestra at the Branch, out it ceased to exist because of the lack of funds.The Branch favors more varied forms of insurance for adults, and for children, if such are possible; the branch has no affiliation with groups, societies or private individuals who strive to bring politics into the activities of the Society. Branch 14 is in favor of consolidation with Roova. It is indifferent as to the name and place of headquarters of the consolidated society. A sick benefit treasury at the headquarters of the Society with payment of 40c a month and payment of a $6.00 weekly sick benefit is also favored.</p>
   <p>33. Branch 15.</p>
   <p>N. Sidorovick. There are 36 adult and 12 minor members in the branch. There is $90 in the treasury and the branch has paid $50 for the unemployed; making the total $140. Although Mr. Mshar has taken $73.73 from the treasury, our branch is progressing. With the branch rid of the detrimental elements, it is going ahead.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1498.jpg" n="22"/>
   <p>34. Branch 16.</p>
   <p>K. Krupka. In the branch there are 20 adult and 10 minor members. The number of members fully covers the small Russian colony of Harvey. Three new members have joined the Branch. We are not conducting any cultural--education work. Because of the small number of children, members we have not organized a school. There is $26.00 in the treasury.</p>
   <p>35. Branch 17, of Baltimore, Ed., there were no delegates, but a letter was received from there, in which they recommend the establishing of a central sick benefit treasury. The question of consolidation of Rimas and Roova is left to the decision of the Assembly.</p>
   <p>36. Branch 18.</p>
   <p>F. Tureiko. Our branch is new, only three months since is has been organized. In the branch there are 12 members, and $84 in the treasury. Branch 18 recommends that the sick benefit treasury be at the headquarters. It also recommends that attention be paid to our youth which is matured, but we do not give them attention and they are leaving us gradually. We must closely watch them, create <pb facs="5423967_3_1499.jpg" n="23"/>groups for the youth at the Branches and not let them go, because they are our pride and fortress on which we will depend in the future.</p>
   <p>Our branch also favors supporting the schools which enhance Rimas and also favors consolidation not only with Roova, but also with all the Russian societies on the basis of mutual aid.</p>
   <p>37. Branch 19. Benton Harbor, Mich.</p>
   <p>A. Rak. Our Branch No. 19 of Rimas named "Hope, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> and Love" has been in existence only 14 weeks. In the membership of the branch there are 22 members, half men and half women who pay dues regularly. There is no sick benefit, also no treasury in the branch. We have assessed each member 5c for expenses. our branch jointly with Branch 12 has a school named after <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> which is attended by 20 to 25 children. This is dissatisfaction with the teacher and the pupils do no wish to attend classes. The pupils for another teacher. If there would be another teacher the class would be attended by many pupils. Delegate from Branch 12 reported that the school does not exist. "I do not agree with him," said Rak. "The school existed and will continue to exist, out if the <pb facs="5423967_3_1500.jpg" n="24"/>children are dismissed for summer vacation, then this does not signify that the school does not exist. It is necessary to have more energy and action, not live in a hut on the edge. It is unforgivable to the parents of those children who observe the school business from under the sleeve; by such action they will leave their children without any knowledge of the Russian language and history which are dear to us.</p>
   <p>38. Branch 20. Baltimore, Md. No delegate was sent to attend the Assembly.</p>
   <p>39. The Report Of The School Branch.</p>
   <p>T. Marchuk reported for the school branch. He indicated that for the nine month period, from August 1932 to April 1933, of his work there was collected $401.00. From these funds, 7% commission amounting to $25.49 was deducted, leaving in the treasury $375.51 as income for the 9 months. In all there is in the treasury of the Juvenile branch $3205.15. During the 9 months, fifty (50) new children were enrolled. In all, in the 1st Juvenile Branch there are 210 children members.</p>
   <p>40. Delegate From Branch 5 requested explanation of enrolling new members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1501.jpg" n="25"/>
   <p>N. Krupka of Branch 5 requested an explanation. In their Branch several now members were enrolled in January, out since it was a privilege, they paid nothing into the Branch, and according to the distribution of dues, an assessment is required for them.</p>
   <p>F.S. of the Society, N. Kozak, explained that he acted in accordance with the by-laws, as an initiation fee was not necessary, out the membership dues for January must be paid, because the Society is responsible for such from the first day of their being admitting into the Society. Delegates to the Assembly approved the explanation of N. Kozak.</p>
   <p>41. L. Stanko, Delegate Of Branch 2, Motion To Consider The Following Three Matters.-</p>
   <p>1. Non-members of the Society shall not be in the Society Committee.</p>
   <p>2. In case a member desires to decrease or increase his death benefit can he do so without a doctor's examination?</p>
   <p>3. Social insurance.</p>
   <p>To the first question a reply was made that there is no such person in the Society. The second was rejected because in accordance with the by-laws, a member cannot increase his death benefit without a doctor's examination.</p>
   <p>The Third question was approved and placed in the order of the day.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1502.jpg" n="26"/>
   <p>Delegate of Branch 2, S. Parfeevetz, stated that if a member is paralyzed and is unable to pay his dues, can the Society help him, and in what manner can such a member be helped. E. Horoschenia explained that as long as there is no fund in the Society for such purposes, it is recommended that branches should take care of such members, and this question was put in the order of the day for deliberation.</p>
   <p>42. J. Dziako's Motion.</p>
   <p>J. Dziako, delegate of Branch 1, moved that the assembly pass a decision on the question, that if a member pays his dues regularly to the Society with the exception of some special assessments (which the Branch levies) may he transfer from one branch to another, not having paid the special assessments in the old branch? The question was approved and placed in the order of the business of the meeting.</p>
   <p>43. F. Tureiko's Motion:</p>
   <p>F. Tureiko delegate of Branch 18 made a motion that more privileges be given to newly enrolled members at any time during the year, if the same shall wish, in order that there be no waiting until July or January when privileges are usually extended to new members, that is, without payment of Initiation fees. The motion was approved and placed in the order of the business of the day.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1503.jpg" n="27"/>
   <p>44. Motion to Adjourn The Session.</p>
   <p>A motion was made, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> seconded, and unanimously carried, that the meeting be adjourned. The meeting was adjourned promptly at 10:15 p.m. Saturday, April 29 and the second session was set for 10:00 A.M. Sunday, April 30.</p>
   <p>45. The Opening Of The Session of The 22nd Supreme Assembly of Rimas.</p>
   <p>The second session of the 22nd Supreme Assembly of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society was declared open at 11:00 A.M. Sunday April 30.</p>
   <p>Roll Call.</p>
   <p>All the delegates present at the first session were also present at the second, in addition John Oleksiuk, delegate from Branch 2, who was absent at the first and was replaced by alternate S. Parfeevetz, was also present. Natalia Omelyaniuk, delegate from Branch 3 who was substituted for by alternate Maria Davidchik of the same branch, was present at this session although absent yesterday.</p>
   <p>46. Address To The Assembly By Olga Baturevich, Pupil Of The Pushkin School.</p>
   <p>Olga Baturevich, a pupil in the senior class at the A.S. Pushkin school in Pull man, Ill. addressed the Assembly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1504.jpg" n="28"/>
   <p>She thanked Kimas for the support to the children's school in Pullman and wished the Assembly fullest success in productive work for the good of the entire Russian colony. The pupil was rewarded for her welcome to the Assembly by loud applause from the delegates.</p>
   <p>47. Motion Made that the Editing Colleague (sic) Give its Report.</p>
   <p>A motion was made and duly seconded that the editing colleague of the "news" of Rimas give a report on its work which is published each Saturday in the newspaper Rassviet.</p>
   <p>Horoschenia: The work was executed with practically no pay. Only some persons were paid for their participation in the work, and this was a minimum expense, but lately the work was conducted with insignificant expense.</p>
   <p>G. Wallace indicated several deficiencies arising from those workers who had connections with the page of Rimas, but this matter shall be brought to light later. Erin recommended that all the work of the editing colleague be conducted by the directors.</p>
   <p>Horozanko: He recommended that in the future the president of the Society make no changes in the editorial colleague, of his own accord, without the knowledge of the whole Board of Directors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1505.jpg" n="29"/>
   <p>Parfeevetz: He favored fully that the president direct all the business of the Society.</p>
   <p>M. Kiersch: "We must first of all hear the explanation of the President of the Society, Horoschenia, in regard to the negative and positive sides of the page "News," Sidorovich: In my opinion our directors are elected and they must direct this work. Horoschenia: "I will not go into detail about former misunderstandings and put them before the Assembly. But the matter was of such a nature: I made various corrections in the page. The editing colleague were slighted because I had done this, and therefore, turned in their resignation.</p>
   <p>Dziako. As is evident, our president did not consider the editing colleague, but acted only by his own discretion, and he is not right in this,. I read all the copies of the newspaper and see that lately the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> printed in the page of Rimas does not fully justify the interests of the Society, but only touched and justified the interests of Horoschenia for his greedy purposes.</p>
   <p>Horoschenia: We have utilized only half a page. The rest of the page was occupied by various material. But, it seems to me that, in our page, material was not printed which is contrary to our Society as some of our delegates have remarked to me, and especially Dziako.</p>
   <p>Korin: In order to avoid all misunderstandings In the future, my opinion is that the Supreme Board in charge of all the work of the page of Rimas. And now, let us <pb facs="5423967_3_1506.jpg" n="30"/>approach the other business in the order of the day; and the question of the page shall be placed in the order of the day.</p>
   <p>48. Delegates Of Branch 35 of Rnov Appear With Credentials.</p>
   <p>The delegates of Branch 35 of Rnov appeared at this second session as at the first, this time with new credentials. P. Baran and K. Gedkov with a written notification appeal to the delegates of the Assembly of Rimas that they give the right to the representative of the Pittsourgh Society, Rnov, S. Nikolayuk, to expound the position of Rnov in regard to consolidation.</p>
   <p>The question was voted upon with the result that 18 voted against granting him the floor and 16 in favor. Several delegates expressed their dissatisfaction with the Assembly, motivating (sic) themselves on the fact that at the Assembly everything should be accessible to all.</p>
   <p>It was necessary to take a second vote and the result was that 15 voted against permitting Nikolayiuk to speak and 16 were in favor of permitting him to speak, while 3 withheld their votes. After this, the question regarding granting Nikolayiuk the floor was placed in the order of the day.</p>
   <p>49. Consolication Of Rimas with Roova, And Other Russian Societies Of Mutual Aid.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1507.jpg" n="31"/>
   <p>E. Horoschenia took the first word in regard to the question of consolidation with Roova and indicated to the Assembly that this matter is already decided in principle, it remains only to make a final formal conclusion of consolidation in agreement with the state laws. Whereupon the chairman of the Assembly, W. Sabinsky, asked the delegates to express themselves in regard to consolidation, if they desire. The following delegates asked for the floor: W. Olesiuk, T. Marchuk, D. Ttanko, J. Dziako, A. Bernoff, Grigochuk, Maria Kiersch, Korpin, Konashevsky, Pasiuk, Michalchik, Rak, Erin, Syman, Sidorovich, Korin, Oleksiuk, Dedovich, Tureiks, Wallace and P. Nagorny. After these requests, a motion was made that the time for speaking be limited to five minutes or three minutes. The question was voted upon and the result was that 9 voted for 5 minutes limit for each speaker and 15 voted for 3 minutes. It was decided by a majority that each speaker limit himself to three minutes.</p>
   <p>Olesiuk--I have never held anything against consolidation, but it must be seriously discussed how to bring about consolidation. Roova is ruled by whites, in Rnov the red leaders dictate. We must consolidate with all workers such as we are, but we must rid ourselves of leaders forever.</p>
   <p>Marchuk--My opinion was practically expressed by Olesiuk. I find no need to say much, but consolidation is necessary to us.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1508.jpg" n="32"/>
   <p>Stanko--The Society, Rnov, has more money in the treasury than Roova and Rimas, and I think therefore we should consolidate with them.</p>
   <p>Dziako--Branch 1 of Rimas at its meeting decided in principle to consolidate with Roova. But, I think that this will not be sufficient for consolidation, because at that time there were only 67 votes cast whereas we have 600 members in the branch. My opinion is to convene all members of the branch and act as they shall decide, for I know what occured last year at the meeting, 9 were for and 88 against consolidation.</p>
   <p>Bernoff--The Assembly must lay the foundation for consolidation, and our future assemblies must be united. A technical plan for consolidation should be drafted. We must unite with everyone.</p>
   <p>Grigorchak--In order to prove our desire to unite, we must actually consolidate. Rnov has intention to gain possession of our Society and subjugate us to its dictatorship. Bolsheviks continually abuse and spread rumors about us, calling us white-guards.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1509.jpg" n="33"/>
   <p>Maria Kiersch--We speak too much about consolidation. Now, especially, the moment has arrived which requires consolidation in the interests of our Russian Youth. Such consolidation we need that will be harmless to all.</p>
   <p>Karpin--Consolidation is urgent for us. Our ranks are thinning. We can not yet attract the youth in satisfactory numbers to our ranks. We must by all means consolidate. For this, we must lay aside egotism if it is an obstacle in consolidation. A plan for consolidation must be worked out and promoted on an equal basis.</p>
   <p>Konashevsky--Consolidation is profitable to us, as it will increase our strength. Now the travelling expenses of Rimas, Roova and Rnov are high. I am wholly for consolidation.</p>
   <p>Pasiuk--There arises some sort of fear and danger in that the one, its seizes the others and subordinates them to its will. No separate Soceity can develop on a large scale and increase its ranks, that is why consolidation is necessary. But it must first take place with Roova on a nationalistic basis.</p>
   <p>Michalchik--Today we cannot finally decide the matter of consolidation with Roova. To this end we shall have to work much more in order to make a final plan for consolidation. For the present we must guide ourselves by the decision of Branch 1 of <pb facs="5423967_3_1510.jpg" n="34"/>Rimas. I am in favor of consolidation because it will bring benefits.</p>
   <p>Rak--I see that all have expressed themselves in favor of consolidation. I wish to remark that strength does not lie only in consolidation, as many think, but strength also lies in the quality of mental inclinations and moral attitudes. Rnov members spill dirt upon us, yet we speak of consolidation with them.</p>
   <p>Erin--A wise Russian saying goes--"In unity there is strength." By the course of the general matter, we see the striving toward consolidation of Rimas and Roova. Concerning Rnov, you, yourselves, see what work is practiced by them in regard to us. They summon us to trials, cast verdicts undeserving of us, etc. I appeal to you with the call to bring about consolidation based on our great Russian culture.</p>
   <p>Syman--We must consolidate, but we know how the leaders of Rnov have slandered us. I propose that we delay and observe in the future the activity of Rnov and their attitude toward us.</p>
   <p>Bidorovich--A most favorable moment for consolidation with a relative organization, Roova, has arrived. Rnov's insults at us and disgrace of our Society's name and <pb facs="5423967_3_1511.jpg" n="35"/>foremost workers, we have felt. Consolidation of Rimas and Roova is fully possible on a nationalistic basis. However, consolidation on an international scale is inadmissible, which Rnov is aimaong at.</p>
   <p>Korin--Our Branch 14 in Detroit favors consolidation with an organization relative to us, Roova, but we oppose consolidation with Rnov because they are always against us are sling dirt at us.</p>
   <p>Olesiuk--Consolidation is needed by all three organizations.</p>
   <p>Dedovich--Today we must decide the matter of consolidation with Roova and express our opinion positively in regard to this question. The conditions for consolidation must be carefully examined by the delegates to the Assembly. Concerning consolidation with Rnov, first it is necessary to find out on what terms they with to unite with us.</p>
   <p>Tureiko--All hostile nations conclude treaties of alliance one with the other, and the idea of consolidation should not be terrifying to us. But all this must be done wisely, with certainty and on an equal basis, so that one would not deceive the other and not allow the one to rule the other.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1512.jpg" n="36"/>
   <p>Wallace---The matter of consolidation is being discussed from a political viewpoint, but not with the idea of mutual aid. On the basis of mutual aid, consolidation could be promoted without adding politics. Our Society has been directed by regular members for many years. Consolidation must be made only on the basis of mutual aid. Our Society is not in need of political adventurers. It is necessary only to feature the idea of mutual aid, give it more general character and draw up concrete terms. We must inform all our branches about the question of consolidation and sooner or later promote consolidation of a Russian fraternal family.</p>
   <p>Nagorny --- Branch 1 does not oppose consolidation as Dziako indicated, but consolidation is possible only under the circumstances when the blackening of our characters is stopped. Should this continue, then consequently consolidation with them is not admissible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1513.jpg" n="37"/>
   <p>Sabinsky ---Consolidation may be made with Rnov, according to Branch 1, only in case when all malicious activity will be discontinued, now practiced by Rnov against Rimas.</p>
   <p>Dziako --- In that case, I agree with Wallace and the matter of consolidation should be handed for a referendum to the branches.</p>
   <p>Jakimovich --- The Assembly must decide in principle the question of consolidation together with this prove the benefits of this idea to all the branches.</p>
   <p>Horoschenia --- In regard to consolidation the Assembly must work out a plan and distribute it to all the branches, then the matter will be cleared. First, it is necessary to draft the project in the form of a resolution and send it to Roova. After these speeches, the question of consolidation was put to a vote of the delegates of the Assembly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1514.jpg" n="38"/>
   <p>36 favored consolidation, none were opposed. For better clarity it is necessary to point out that the question of consolidation with Roova is solved, with the agreement that the new Society shall be named the Russian Independent Consolidated Society for Mutual Aid with headquarters in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Assembly entrusted the old administration of Rimas to draft the resolution of consolidation with Roova.</p>
   <p>50. Establishing a Central Sick Benefit Treasury. Horoschenia explained to the assembly that the by-laws for the sick benefit treasury are already worked out in a general form by the old administration. It remains for the Assembly to examine it and correct it if necessary.</p>
   <p>The following persons asked for the floor to express themselves on the matter. Jakimovich, Tureiko, Dziako, Pasiuk, Grigorchuk, Olesiuk, <pb facs="5423967_3_1515.jpg" n="39"/>Karpin, Erin, Sidorovich, Marie Kiersch, Wallace, Horozanko and Dedovich.</p>
   <p>Jakimovich --- My opinion is that the administrative fund (should) be protected. The question of a sick benefit treasury must be carefully investigated and acted upon, as should be.</p>
   <p>Tureiko --- In small branches the treasuries are not large and not very dependable to secure its members. It will be better if we create a central sick benefit treasury which will be more dependable and secure for all the members.</p>
   <p>Dziako --- Our Branch 1 resolved to create a central sick benefit treasury at headquarters in Chicago. This will help to add new members to Rimas and increase the membership.</p>
   <p>Pasiuk --- Let the matter of a central sick benefit treasury be referred <pb facs="5423967_3_1516.jpg" n="40"/>to the branches for decision. How the branches will find it more practical to create a central sick benefit treasury and pass it by 3/4 votes then it shall be established, but it will be impractical to force the central sick benefit on the branches without their consent.</p>
   <p>Crigorchuk --- I fully support and insist on the establishment of a central sick benefit treasury.</p>
   <p>Olesiuk --- I am against establishing a central sick benefit treasury and our branch will remain as before.</p>
   <p>Karpin --- Small branches cannot establish a sick benefit fund. The fact proves that a large sick benefit treasury can be created only on the condition that there is a central sick benefit treasury. Those branches which will not desire to join the central sick benefit treasury, may remain as before.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1517.jpg" n="41"/>
   <p>Erin --- Small branches have nothing to fear of a central sick benefit treasury. It must be proved to all the branches as to the benefits and advantages of such a treasury.</p>
   <p>Marie Kiersch --- Our 3rd Branch of Rimas does not pay sick benefits and therefore it will protect its existence as formerly.</p>
   <p>Wallace --- Probably the creation of a central sick benefit treasury will not be advantageous to our Branch 1 with its large membership and its quite strong treasury. It will not be advantageous because less money will be left in our Branch; the entire sick benefit dues will be sent to the Society. Up to the present time, there has been excellent control over the sick members in our branch, and because of this our branch did not pay out all the money which it collected. From the remaining funds, the branch paid salaries to the committee of the Branch, clerical expenses, aided the unemployed members to meet their membership dues to the Society and other small expenses. If a central sick benefit <pb facs="5423967_3_1518.jpg" n="42"/>treasury is established, the branch will have to obtain funds by other means. Notwithstanding this, the Branch will lose much, yet it considers those circumstances in which the small branches are found without a sick benefit treasury and has entrusted its delegates to recommend to the Assembly to establish a central sick benefit treasury in the Society.</p>
   <p>Horozanko --- Some branches do not agree to the establishment of a central sick benefit treasury. Such branches may remain as before, if they do not wish to join the central sick benefit fund.</p>
   <p>Dedovich --- My opinion may point to that the central sick benefit treasury will bring great benefit to our Society.</p>
   <p>Karpin --- A sick benefit fund is not obligatory by the by-laws as (is) the death benefit. And the question of a central sick benefit treasury depends upon the desire of the branches.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1519.jpg" n="43"/>
   <p>Horoschenia --- It is most important if a branch voluntarily joins the central sick benefit fund, but it should not be forced action. Life itself indicates this to us.</p>
   <p>Whereupon it was put to a vote: should a central sick benefit treasury be established? There were 34 votes for the establishment of a central sick benefit treasury and 4 for the old system. Therefore, it was also resolved by the Assembly that $7 a week be paid to a member as sick benefit, and 40 cents shall be collected by the Society each month from each member, and 10 cents shall be retained by the Branch treasury each month. The remaining by-laws for the sick benefit treasury were accepted unanimously as drafted by the administration with the correction of several paragraphs.</p>
   <p>51. Audit Report. V. Konashevsky gave the audit report. He stated that <pb facs="5423967_3_1520.jpg" n="44"/>the budget for 1933-34 was $1,700. Out of this amount $445 was spent for salaries to the Supreme Administration: president, treasurer, financial and recording secretaries. For other expenses there were expended: for transportation of delegates to assemblies, of directors to meetings, telephone, and clerical expenses, $668.00. For organization, educational work $60 was spent. The total expenses were $1,173. In reserve of the Society there remains $527, which may be used for organization and educational purposes, for conducting (the) "News" page and to aid the schools of the Society.</p>
   <p>Delegate of Branch 18, Tureiko, moved that the report of the Audit Committee be accepted. Dziako seconded the motion. The motion was then voted upon and it was accepted by 25 to O.</p>
   <p>52. Increase of Budget. In view of the proposed large expense for the next year, it was indicated that $1 as assessed annually would be insufficient. For the next year the budget must be increased.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1521.jpg" n="45"/>
   <p>The delegate expressed (sic) that 10 cents monthly be assessed for the administrative fund, which will amount to $1.20 from each member instead of the present $1. Some delegates cited the depression and proposed that it remain the same, i. e., $1.00 annually. The question was voted upon and it resulted that 16 voters were for the $1.00 annual assessment, and 26 votes for 10 cents monthly.</p>
   <p>Intermission. A motion was made to make a one-half hour intermission. The motion was duly seconded and carried, that there be a one-half hour intermission.</p>
   <p>After the dinner intermission, the roll of the delegates was called and all the delegates were present. At 4:40 P. M. the Assembly again resumed its work.</p>
   <p>53. Surety Bonds of the Executive Committee. Elarion Horoschenia explained that the insurance department of the State of Illinois finds <pb facs="5423967_3_1522.jpg" n="46"/>that such a system which existed until the present is not practical and not secure. He proposed that a surety bond be procured. Horoschenia recommended to the delegates to insure the officers of the Society in the amount of $15,000 for protection in case of embezzlement of society funds. The suggestion of Horoschenia was unanimously approved by the delegates.</p>
   <p>54. Juvenile Department Report. V. Konashevsky reported on the Juvenile Department and suggested to the Assembly that every branch should be interested in the organization of youth and should attract youth into the branches.</p>
   <p>Horoschenia moved that every branch be obligated to organize youth and conduct the most extensive campaign in this trend.</p>
   <p>Pasiuk recommended that 50 cents be given to any member for each newly <pb facs="5423967_3_1523.jpg" n="47"/>enrolled minor member into the branch and who will remain in the Society not less than six months, and for all other under-aged members admitted previously into the branch the agent will receive 7% commission. Likewise it is necessary for all members to take and active part in order to attract our youth into our ranks, then only will we achieve our desired aim.</p>
   <p>Xichkailo --- First of all, it is necessary that all the Independents, (member of Rimas), register their children in the Society and thus prove their active work.</p>
   <p>Sabinsky --- He recommended that every branch elect special persons to enroll new members of youth.</p>
   <p>55. Appointment of Agents for Juvenile Division. The Assembly unanimously recommended to continue this work as formerly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1524.jpg" n="48"/>
   <p>56. Uniting the Russian Schools of Rimas. E. Horoschenia gave his opinion first in regard to the uniting of the children's schools of Rimas. He stated that in order to attract and organize the youth, it is necessary for every man to understand the Russian language. Our schools exist for the purpose of teaching the youth the Russian language. We have made all efforts to hold the existing schools for this purpose.</p>
   <p>Dziako -- Schools are our pride and we must support the opinion regarding schools as expressed by Horoschenia.</p>
   <p>Dedovich -- It will be better to turn the question of schools over to the school committee for investigation.</p>
   <p>Bernoff -- In order to create a firm foundation for existence of the schools it is necessary to establish a special strong fund.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1525.jpg" n="49"/>
   <p>Pasiuk -- Schools must be supported, but to keep the schools up at the expense of the Society it is impossible to further do so.</p>
   <p>Kupchik -- Schools must be reorganized on a new basis, if there are difficulties to hold them in the state in which they have existed until the present. Unimportant subjects may be removed from the school program. The study of the Russian language does not require much time.</p>
   <p>Marie Kiersch -- Schools must exist, but for their upkeep large expense must be avoided. The parents themselves must be interested in this matter and support schools at their expense, but not at the expense of Rimas.</p>
   <p>According to the expressions of many delegates, it was indicated that it is necessary to support the schools as much as possible. Thereupon <pb facs="5423967_3_1526.jpg" n="50"/>the matter was turned over to the School Council of Rimas for consideration.</p>
   <p>57. Introduction of New Forms of Insurance. E. Horoschenia informed the delegates that we did not hurry to introduce new forms of insurance inasmuch as there was in view the consolidation with Roova. Roova has already worked out plans of insurance and if consolidation will materialize, then our new forms of insurance will prove unnecessary. We have tables of new forms of insurance and it depends on the decision of Roov's Convention whether or not to promote them, but my personal opinion is to wait until May 6th at which time the Convention of Roova will have been concluded and then we shall know what to do. The suggestion of Horoschenia was upheld unanimously.</p>
   <p>58. Expense of Delegates to the Assembly. Up to the present the transportation expense and loss of time of delegates to the Assembly have <pb facs="5423967_3_1527.jpg" n="51"/>been paid from funds of the Society's treasury. The Board of Directors recommended to the delegates of the Assembly to decrease some expenses: those connected with payment for loss of working time of delegates. The Assembly resolved that in the future payment for loss of working time would not be made, only transportation would be covered.</p>
   <p>59. Salaries to Officers of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
   <p>Chairman of the Assembly, W. Sabinsky, announced the question of salaries to the officers of the Society. He asked the delegates for expressions of the matter. Delegates informed that they wish to hear from the officeholders of the Society what they have to say in regard to this question and how they value in general the work.</p>
   <p>First, Horoschenia stated that the salary of the president of the Society is determined by the person; for one $50 may be designated and it will not be too small; for another $100, and it will not be too large.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1528.jpg" n="52"/>
   <p>N. Kozak, Financial Secretary, announced in order that the Society develop, a permanent secretary is necessary. At present the sick benefit is paid to the Society, then consequently the work of the Financial Secretary is doubly increased, and no one will therefore consent to work for such remuneration which the secretary receives at the present time.</p>
   <p>After some discussion, J. Michalchik moved that (a) the financial secretary's salary be increased $100 yearly. V. Konashevsky seconded the motion. V. Olesiuk moved (b) that the salary of the Supreme Secretary be increased $150 yearly. Joseph Sleznik seconded this motion.</p>
   <p>The motions (a) and (b) were voted upon with 31 votes for $100 increase and 11 votes for $150 increase. Therefore the salary of the financial Secretary was designated as $350 per year with transportation and telephone expenses paid.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1529.jpg" n="53"/>
   <p>The salary of the president and the treasurer remained the same, that is, $80 per year; the salary of the recording secretary was designated at $35 per year; the remaining members of the Board of the Directors of the Society work without pay, only their transportation is paid for.</p>
   <p>There was a five minute intermission called after the above motion.</p>
   <p>60. Election of Officers for 1933-1934. After the intermission, chairman of the Assembly, W. Sabinsky, called the meeting to order and proposed the election of the officers for 1933-1934.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of the Supreme President of the Society. The following were nominated: Horoschenia, Wallace, Dziako, Pasiuk, Jakimovich, Michalchik, Konashevsky, Dedovich and Sabinsky.</p>
   <p>The nominations were accepted only by Wallace and Pasiuk.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1530.jpg" n="54"/>
   <p>In a closed ballot, 30 votes were cast for Wallace and 14 for Pasiuk. Therefore Wallace was elected by majority vote as president for the coming year. Loud applause hailed the new president of the Society. The Supreme president of the Society serves at a salary of $80 a year. Wallace expressed his thanks to the Assembly for the trust and requested the delegates to the Assembly to try to work for the good of the Society and elect active workers as his co-workers.</p>
   <p>J. Michalchik was unanimously elected vice-president of the Society.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Treasurer of the Society. The following accepted the nomination: J. Sleznik, S. Jakimovich and A. Pasiuk.</p>
   <p>In a closed ballot, Jakimovich and Sleznik received 18 votes each, and Pasiuk 6. A second ballot was cast for Jakimovich and Sleznik;</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1531.jpg" n="55"/>
   <p>Jakimovich received 24 and Sleznik 21. Chairman Sabinsky announced that S. Jakimovich is elected by majority votes for the office of Supreme treasurer of the Society. The treasurer serves at a salary of $80 a year. A. Pasiuk was elected Assistant Treasurer by a majority of votes.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Supreme Secretary of the Society. Only one person accepted the nomination, N. Kozak, who was unanimously re-elected as Supreme Secretary of the Society at a salary of $350 a year.</p>
   <p>Marie Kiersch was unanimously elected assistant secretary.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Supreme Recording Secretary of the Society. Only A. Hoponovich accepted the nomination for recording secretary of the Society, and since there were no other candidates for the post Hoponovich was unanimously elected recording secretary of the Society, at a salary of $35 a year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1532.jpg" n="56"/>
   <p>The Nomination and Election of the Members of the Board of Directors.</p>
   <p>The following were elected to the Board of Directors of Rimas: J. Olesiuk, V. Konashevsky, W. Sabinsky, D. Vorobey, J. Karpin, Jos. Sleznik, N. Sidorovich, T. Morchuck, W. Olesiuk, M. Horozanko, I. Pyalnitza, H. Davidchik, W. Dedovich, and N. Krupko; A. Shustitsky was chosen as alternate.</p>
   <p>Five minutes recess.</p>
   <p>61. Discrepancies Presented by the F. S. for the Decision of the Assembly.</p>
   <p>Supreme Secretary of the Society, N. Kozak, announced that after the death of two members in 1932 and one in 1933 there are some discrepancies which the Supreme Directors could not decide alone, only the Supreme Assembly may.</p>
   <p>One member, F. Kisko, Branch 1, died in July of last year. His death <pb facs="5423967_3_1533.jpg" n="57"/>benefit was made in favor of his sister, residing in Europe. Before his death, it was changed in favor of a friend and only a cross was made, while it was a fact that the deceased was literate and could sign his own name. In view of the fact that in accordance with our by-laws the death benefit is payable only to the nearest relatives, and no friends are mentioned, the Board of Directors stopped payment of the death benefit and now the matter is in court. His friends who were made beneficiaries demand that the Society pay out the benefit to cover the funeral expenses of the deceased which amount to approximately 700 dollars. Several delegates opined that the expenses be paid for the hospital and funeral, others suggested that action be taken in accordance with the by-laws. For the motion that the expenses for the funeral be paid there were 10 votes cast; for the motion that action be taken in accordance with the by-laws 31 votes were cast. Therefore, it was resolved that action be taken in accordance with the by-laws of the Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1534.jpg" n="58"/>
   <p>Another member, Ivan Kozakevich, reduced his age by 8 years when admitted into the Branch. Delegates expressed various opinions. Wallace intimated that, if it will not be contradictory to the by-laws of the Society, the death benefit be paid to the widow of the deceased, with deductions for the falsified 8 years plus interest. If it be denied altogether, then it will be poor publicity for the Society. The motion made by Wallace was seconded and carried by majority votes.</p>
   <p>In agreement to the by-laws of the Society and laws of the Insurance Department, this decision cannot be legal. The by-laws clearly state: paragraph 70: The Society does not assume and shall be exempted from payment of any death benefits on account of persons who (a) obtained admission into the Society through fraud, misrepresentation in their applications or false statements. And for the decision by the Assembly of this question, it will have been necessary to amend paragraph 70 of the by-laws, and for an amendment of this paragraph 60 days prior <pb facs="5423967_3_1535.jpg" n="59"/>to the convening of the Assembly are necessary to inform all the branches of the Society, and since this was not done, such a decision is not valid.</p>
   <p>Executive Committee.</p>
   <p>A third member made his nephew beneficiary at the time of being admitted into the Branch, afterwards he changed it in favor of a half-sister, but the form was not received by the Board of Directors and the Society was not aware of this. The question of this case has been decided by majority votes to be given to the Board of Directors for consideration.</p>
   <p>In agreement to the by-laws, Paragraph 60, corresponding rules were not made on the prescribed form and an oral notification of the change of a beneficiary is not examined.</p>
   <p>Executive Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1536.jpg" n="60"/>
   <p>After some discussion and explanation by Horoschenia in regard to the dying members of the Society who have no rightful heirs in the United States (or heirs are still minors) to take charge of the funeral of a deceased member, he suggested to the Assembly to allow the Board of Directors to pay out $200 for the funeral of a member, and leave the remaining sum for the rightful recipients. Such a suggestion was accepted and was carried without objection.</p>
   <p>This resolution also concerns the previous deceased members, whose claims are in full order.</p>
   <p>62. Question of Fund for Needy Sick Members. Member of Branch 1: L. Stanko had raised the question of the creation of a special fund to help the sick members who are not in the position to pay their membership dues.</p>
   <p>E. Horoschenia announced that the sick benefit fund can be established <pb facs="5423967_3_1537.jpg" n="61"/>only on the condition that the members pay 10 cents a month. Such a decision will not be binding to all members of the Society, but only those individuals who are interested in this and wish to establish it.</p>
   <p>63. Re: Transfer of Members from one Branch to Another. The question raised by J. Dziako, delegate of Branch 1, for the consideration of the Assembly was that of the transfer of members to other branches if their dues are paid in full with the exception of some extraordinary assessments which are practiced in Branch 1. The question was: may such members transfer to other branches even if they have not paid the extraordinary assessments in the old branch?</p>
   <p>The delegates to the Assembly resolved: That members may transfer from one branch to another if they will have transfer certificates to the effect that they have no indebtedness in the branches where they were formerly members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1538.jpg" n="62"/>
   <p>The Assembly resolved that a point be added to the by-laws, reading:</p>
   <p>That the secretary of the Society will not accept such members into another branch without the consent of the old branch.</p>
   <p>64. Extension of Privileges to New Enrolled Members. Delegate of Branch 18, F. Tureiko, moved that if possible the privileges to newly enrolled members in the new branches of not paying initiation fees be extended. B. Horschenia explained that this is declined because, in the future, admissions for membership into branches will be made on a new plan.</p>
   <p>65. Loan Made to Douglas Park School in 1930. Delegate of Branch 1, G. Kichkailo, made a written notification which was placed in the order of the day. It was the question of $200 which was loaned by the Society <pb facs="5423967_3_1539.jpg" n="63"/>in 1930 for the opening of the children's school in Douglas Park, the guarantors of which loan were Omelganuk, Chopko, Kichkailo. (a) Murchuk moved that this money be brought into the treasury of the Society before the next Assembly convenes. The motion was seconded by Stanko. (b) J. Michalchik announced that it should be considered a debt until the next Assembly, and at the same time there should be an investigation to determine what the money was used for. The motion was duly seconded.</p>
   <p>The matter was put to a vote and there were 10 in favor of the (a) motion and 20 for (b).</p>
   <p>66. W. Sabinsky's Request for Funds due him and Expended by Him During his Period in Office. W. Sabinsky made a request to the 22nd Supreme Assembly to give its attention to that fact that he, W. Sabinsky, former Supreme President of the Society, 1930-1931, in giving up his <pb facs="5423967_3_1540.jpg" n="64"/>office to the new president of the Society claimed that his expenses for the societies work in the amount of $45, including transportation, telephone and miscellaneous (expenses) be paid, but since it was not shown in detail where and how much he expended, the committee of the Society refused to pay him the entire amount, $45, having considered this amount as exaggerated and agreed to pay him only $25. Sabinsky, considering himself offended at the time, refused to accept the $25, and now appeals to the Assembly to give the matter attention and judge it rightfully, offending neither the Society nor Sabinsky.</p>
   <p>Inasmuch as two years have already elapsed since that time and now (not) only the delegates to the Assembly but also Sabinsky himself do not remember all the expenses, the Assembly resolved to uphold the resolution of the directors, that is, pay Sabinsky the amount of $25 for his expenses.</p>
   <p>67. "News" of the Society. The delegates expressed various opinions <pb facs="5423967_3_1541.jpg" n="65"/>regarding the news.</p>
   <p>Syman: The page "News" either should be abolished or published once a month. The material in the "News" of the Society has lately brought dissatisfaction and created hostility.</p>
   <p>Olesiuk: criticized the newspapers Rassviet and Novy Mir for publishing material of a political nature. In his opinion political material should not be printed in the newspapers for that is one of the reasons that dissatisfaction arises amongst readers.</p>
   <p>Sidorovich: "Friends, you reason wrongly. The material printed in the page "News" of Rimas gives us the opportunity to elucidate our social work. Due to the page we can express in the press all that which is happening everywhere and in our society. Together with this <pb facs="5423967_3_1542.jpg" n="66"/>we refute in the page "News" the attacks which are practiced by our enemies who try to bring disorder and dissolution to our Society. By the aid of the page we strengthen the development of our social work and we have the opportunity to promote cultural, educational work. I am in favor of keeping and prolonging our page "News" of Rimas in the newspaper Rassviet.</p>
   <p>Pasiuk: The page is necessary to our Society. In our page we can write that which we wish about the doings and happenings in our ranks. Rassviet is the most suitable newspaper for us, and besides it is published daily.</p>
   <p>Erin: The page "News" is necessary to our Society. In the page we can inform about the activities of Rimas. I am in favor of retaining the page.</p>
   <p>Dedovich: We have need of the page "News." When we need to enlighten <pb facs="5423967_3_1543.jpg" n="67"/>questions (sic) pertinent to our social work, we can better express and inform through the page "News."</p>
   <p>After these various expressions of the delegates, the question of the page "News" was referred to the Supreme Administration of the Society. The motion to keep the page was voted upon and there were 35 votes in favor of it and none against.</p>
   <p>68. Re: Convening the Assembly Once Every Two Years. J. Sleznik recommended that in the future assemblies be called once every two years. Pasiuk asked for the floor to prove the advantages of calling the Assembly annually. His request was granted. Pasiuk stated that little money is expended for Assemblies. For the last Assembly only $42.14 was spent, and to convene once a year the representatives of the branches to discuss matters for improving the Society is indeed a very fine thing. The Assembly approved this expression by Pasiuk.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1544.jpg" n="68"/>
   <p>Whereupon the chairman of the Assembly, Sabinsky, announced that all the business in the order of the business of the Assembly is finished.</p>
   <p>Chairman Sabinsky thanked the delegates and guests for the fine attention to the Assembly and asked the delegates to rise and in silence pay tribute to the memory of the deceased members of the Society, the names of the thirteen deceased were read to the delegates of the Assembly.</p>
   <p>After a minute's pause the chairman requested the delegates to designate the date for the next, the 23rd Supreme Assembly of the Society. The question was referred to the Board of Directors for consideration.</p>
   <p>Thereupon the Assembly was declared closed on Sunday, the 30th day of <pb facs="5423967_3_1545.jpg" n="69"/>April, 1933 at promptly 9:30 P. M.</p>
   <p>Chairman of the Supreme Assembly,</p>
   <p>W. Sabinsky</p>
   <p>Secretary of the Assembly,</p>
   <p>A. Hoponovich.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
