<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Minutes of the 24th Supreme Assembly of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society</title>, held
<date when="1935-05-12">May 11 and 12, 1935</date>,
at the People's Home, at 917 North Wood Street, in Chicago, Illinois.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Minutes of the 24th Supreme Assembly of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society</title>, held
<date when="1935-05-12">May 11 and 12, 1935</date>,
at the People's Home, at 917 North Wood Street, in Chicago, Illinois.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first session of the 24th Supreme Assembly of RIMAS was held Saturday, May 11, 1935, in the People's Home, at North Wood Street, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>1. Mr. George Wallace, Supreme President of the society, opened the session of the assembly at 4 P. M., Saturday, May 11th, acquainting in detail the delegates to the assembly with what the Independent Society has achieved during the twenty-four years of its existence, what the aims of the Independents are, and what their purpose and problems are of the future, and in order to achieve the desired results what action they must take. The address produced a touching impression on the delegates to the assembly, as was proved by the tremendous applause accorded Mr. Wallace.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1299.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Roll Call:</p>
   <p>Recording secretary, A. Naponovich, called the roll of the delegates, who arrived to the session of the assembly.</p>
   <p>The following were present: Supreme President of the Society, G. Wallace; Financial Secretary, N. Kozak; and Treasurer S. Yakimowich of the administration.</p>
   <p>From Branch 1 - Brotherhood of St. George: A. Naponovich, D. Vorobey, P. Gulko, P. Oshko, V. Sabinsky, A. Bernov, I. Vdovich, G. Kichkailo, W. Olesiuk, V. Dedovich, Dr. P. Chadovich, J. Sleznik, J. Erin, J. Wallace, A. Pasiuk, D. Zhogalsky, <gap unit="char" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> Polishchuk, J. Pyatnitza, and F. Kashtelyanchik. Substitutes: Z. Stolarana, F. Parada and A. Grigorchuk.</p>
   <p>From Branch 2 - S. Parfeevets, N. Kucherepa, and alternate D. Bregin.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1300.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From Branch 3 - Sisterhood: Z. Leschuk, <gap unit="char" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> Ross, V. Sergeya, M. Kiersch, J. Yakimowich, E. Kasper, A. Zhogalsky, M. Putzeiko, P. Svatikova, and S. Shuran</p>
   <p>From Branch 4: S. Fedorovsky</p>
   <p>From Branch 5: L. Kujava and J. Borisiuk</p>
   <p>From Branch 7: A. Petruchik and <gap unit="char" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> Melnik</p>
   <p>From Branch 8: Anna Kravs</p>
   <p>From Branch 10: Z. Schelkun</p>
   <p>From Branch 14: Delegate not present; greetings were received by letter.</p>
   <p>From Branch 15: E. Horoschenia and G. Batyushko.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1301.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>From Branch 16: P. Vasilkov</p>
   <p>From Branch 17: P. Abramuk</p>
   <p>From Branch 18: J. Dziako and S. Volodkin</p>
   <p>From Branch 23: P. Rolik</p>
   <p>From Branch 24: Greetings were received; delegate not present</p>
   <p>From Branch 25: A. Markovich</p>
   <p>From Branch 26: Sofia Levkovich</p>
   <p>From Branch 27: M. Metelsky and A. Rak.</p>
   <p>Eight delegates arrived later. In all there were 55 delegates present.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1302.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Besides the delegates, there were present at the assembly representatives of the St. George Church, J. Mikahalchik, I. Kuriga, and G. Chepelevich; V. Shimuk of the Russian Children's School of I. A. Kryloff.</p>
   <p>After the roll call, the president of the society, Wallace, proposed to the delegates to rise and pay tribute to the twelve members who passed away in 1934, the names of when were read by the secretary of the assembly in the profound silence of the members.</p>
   <p>President Wallace spoke briefly in an expression of eternal memory to those deceased.</p>
   <p>Election of Credentials Committee</p>
   <p>The following were elected as the committee on credentials: D. Vorobey, V. Clesiuk, and D. Zhogalsky.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1303.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Election of Sentries</p>
   <p>The following were elected as sentries: I. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and J. Pyatnitza.</p>
   <p>Recess of ten minutes was declared to give the Committee on Credentials time to verify the mandates of the delegates.</p>
   <p>After the recess the Committee on Credentials reported that all the credentials from the delegates of branches are in order. Among the credentials there were also credentials from the Russian People's Society for Mutual Aid (RNOV) for representatives S. Nikolaiuk, who just arrived in shock-brigade fashion from the RNOV convention in New York.</p>
   <p>Hereupon the Committee on Credentials recommends to accept all the credentials of members of the branches of RIMAS, except those of RMOV, and remove S. Nikolaiuk from the assembly, as a representative of an organization hostile to ours.</p>
   <p>A motion was made to ratify the report of the Committee on Credentials.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1304.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The motion duly seconded and carried that the RMOV delegate and all correspondents be removed from the assembly. The vote was 37 to 1 in favor of the motion. Therefore, Mikolaiuk unwillingly left the 24th Supreme Assembly of RIMAS.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Ballot Tellers</p>
   <p>Of those nominated the following were elected ballot tellers: F. Kashtelyanchik, I. Vdovich, E. Kasper and Joseph Sleznik.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of the Presidium to Conduct the Assembly</p>
   <p>The following nominees accepted candidacy for chairman of the assembly: Dr. P. Chadovich, J. Dziako, V. Sabinsky, and V. Olesiuk. In a closed ballot, Dr. P. Chadovich received a majority vote and was therefore elected chairman of the assembly. V. Sabinsky was elected as vice-chairman of the assembly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1305.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Secretary of the Assembly (Senior Clerk).</p>
   <p>There was some delay in the election of a secretary of the assembly. (Senior Clerk). Three times nominations were made and each time the nominees declined to accept the clerkship of the assembly. V. Olesiuk moved that the clerk of the assembly be paid for his services. The motion was seconded and carried by a majority of votes, that $5 be paid to the senior clerk of the assembly for the two days.</p>
   <p>This motion did not ease matters, thereupon the assembly appealed to A. Naponovich with the request that he accept the duties of the Senior Clerk of the Assembly. A. Naponovich accepted and recommended that in the future the branches elect as delegates to the assembly such members who love the society, are interested in its work and who will accept the duties with pride for the benefit of the society.</p>
   <p>M. Kiersch was unanimously elected as Junior Clerk of the Assembly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1306.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Election of Grievance Committee</p>
   <p>The following were elected to the Grievance Committee: A. Bernov, J. Erin, and F. Parada. This committee was also entrusted with the work of the committee on expense of the assembly.</p>
   <p>Election of Committee on Resolutions</p>
   <p>The following were elected to the Committee on Resolutions: J. Dziako, S. Volodkin, and P.V. Svatikova. Upon completing the election of the presidium of the assembly, the Supreme President of the society, G. Wallace moved that all the elected officers assume their duties.</p>
   <p>Upon taking his place as chairman of the assembly, Dr. P. Chadovich briefly thanked the assembly for the trust placed in him and requested the delegates to be attentive to the business in the agenda of the assembly and have faith in each other as this will make it possible to conduct the assembly more successfully.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1307.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Intermission</p>
   <p>During the intermission the newly elected officers of the assembly were enabled to acquaint themselves with the business on the agenda to be presented to the assembly for decision.</p>
   <p>Resumption of the Assembly</p>
   <p>Reading of felicitations: Branch 14 of RIMAS in Detroit, informs by letter that due to the distance and wishing to avoid extra expense, the Branch withheld sending a delegate to the assembly.</p>
   <p>Therefore Branch 14 trusts the assembly and will agree with the decisions made by the assembly. Besides this, Branch 14 recommends to the assembly not to put aside the matter of consolidation of RIMAS with ROOVA, two kindred organizations, having the same purpose: mutual aid.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1308.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>Greetings from Branch 24 of <gap unit="word" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> were read. The branch states that there are 14 members in the branch and 21 in the treasury. This branch was organized one year ago.</p>
   <p>Branch 7 sends its felicitations to the assembly and wishes it success in its work.</p>
   <p>Likewise, messages were received from Dr. Pertzoff, Attorney Pelechovich, undertaker V. Kuzyka, and A. Zmagar, all of whom extended best wishes to the assembly in their productive work for the good of the Russian colony.</p>
   <p>In behalf of the publishers of Rassviet newspaper, N. Novin greeted the assembly and pointed out that the newspaper is in existence 11 years and has always extended assistance to RIMAS in its time of need. "The newspaper Rassviet will in the future maintain this policy," announced Novin.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1309.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Reading of the Minutes</p>
   <p>The minutes of the 23rd Supreme Assembly were read and approved unanimously by the delegates of the assembly.</p>
   <p>S. Volodkin proposed that in the future the minutes of the assemblies be more brief, that only the important decisions without details be recorded. The recommendation was accepted unanimously.</p>
   <p>Reading of the Financial Report</p>
   <p>Supreme Secretary, N. Kozak, read the financial report from which it was evident that the capital of RIMAS as of May 1, 1935, was $80,628.40.</p>
   <p>Treasurer Yakimovich and senior auditor, Joseph Sleznik, confirmed the accuracy of the report.</p>
   <p>Delegate of Branch 2, N. Kucherepa, asked that all funds be explained <pb facs="5423967_3_1310.jpg" n="13"/>in detail, separately. The secretary explained every item separately, after which Kucherepa was satisfied.</p>
   <p>Report of the Executive Committee</p>
   <p>Supreme President of the society, G. Wallace, reported that the work of the Executive Committee was conducted with vigor this year. All members of the Board of Directors of RIMAS were very active and accurate in executing their work. Because of this, our work was productive this year. New policies of insurance were adopted this year, and this will enable us to increase our ranks, and will help us lift the society financially, as well as morally. On the initiative of the Board of Directors, lectures were sponsored in the branches, subscriptions of new members and a creation of new branches were successful. Regarding the branch of youth, work in this field was not satisfactory. The parents should worry about this themselves. The Board of Directors has done much this year. There is, however, much work not yet completed. To complete all the work and expand the society, we need a permanent secretary. Some branches have not displayed sufficient activity in cultural, educational <pb facs="5423967_3_1311.jpg" n="14"/>work, which of course reflects on the work of the society.</p>
   <p>Supreme Secretary of the society, N. Kozak, reported that the membership of RIMAS is 1,329 adults and 548 juveniles, a total of 1,877 members. The technical work of the society was executed with great difficulties.</p>
   <p>Treasurer Yakimovich reported that the president and secretary have said everything which was done during the past year and that he has only to show the condition of the treasury. There is $34,818.40 cash in the treasury of the society, which is kept in four banks. The senior auditor confirmed the accuracy of the financial report, and what the treasury is in order.</p>
   <p>Recording secretary, A. Haponovich, reported that the entire technical work of the society was executed accurately by all the committees. Besides, the president and the secretary, the heaviest work was effected by the editing committee of the News of RIMAS, headed by Mme. P. V. Swatikova. Likewise, other committees were very accurate in regard to the society's <pb facs="5423967_3_1312.jpg" n="15"/>work and loyally defended the interests of the society. In conclusion, Naponovicn, on behalf of the assembly, expressed thanks to the Board of Directors for its fruitful work and requested the delegates to elect to the Board of Directors good, honest workers.</p>
   <p>Having heard the reports of the Board of Directors, the delegates were satisfied with the work of the Board of Directors during the past year.</p>
   <p>Intermission. Then Report of Organization Committee.</p>
   <p>A half-hour intermission was called, after which the chairman of the assembly, Dr. Chadovich, requested the delegates to take their places and continue the work before them. On behalf of the organization committee, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Olesiuk announced that in organization work there was not much accomplished. On one hand the depression and on the other enemies interfered, but notwithstanding these obstacles, we did organize two new branches.</p>
   <p>Second member of the organization committee, W. Sabinsky, reported that <pb facs="5423967_3_1313.jpg" n="16"/>many places were visited not only in Chicago but in other states, and for various reasons much could not be accomplished. Besides the depression, some colonists varying in age from 55 to 60 years, are poisoned by enemies with remarks to the effect that persons are not admitted into the society's membership who are of such <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <p>Reports of the School and Cultural-Educational Committee</p>
   <p>A. Bernov reported that much cannot be said of the cultural-educational work, insomuch as the work was poorly conducted. However much can be said of the schools. Although we have few schools, in quality they stand high.</p>
   <p>This year we have spent little on schools, and have not incurred any indebtedness. Some parents have fully appraised the school work and warmly respond to the schools. Besides grammar, singing and music are taught in the schools. We have attempted to create new schools, but parents themselves were indifferent to this, therefore, more schools could not be organized.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1314.jpg" n="17"/>
   <p>The delegates must give thought to the schools and not place the entire work on individual school workers and the school council, but try during the meeting to decide so that schools may expand in the future.</p>
   <p>Report of the Editing Committee</p>
   <p>On behalf of the editing committee, P. Swatikova reported that these who read The news of RIMAS have noticed how we have tried to publish in our page such material which would bring benefits to the society. Besides beneficial articles, enlightening life and activity of branches locally, we have also reflected in our page the attacks of our enemies. In Madame Swatikova's opinion the page of RIMAS should be enlarged in the future.</p>
   <p>J. Erin proposed that the editing committee be given thanks for its fine work and that the question of enlarging the page of RIMAS be placed in the agenda. The question of enlarging the page of RIMAS was placed on the agenda of the assembly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1315.jpg" n="18"/>
   <p>Report of the Real Estate Management Committee</p>
   <p>Dr. Chadovich reported that the committee was very attentive to its duties and now everything is in order. Second member of the committee, Z. Stolarana, added that he and Dr. Chadovich have supervised the real estate holdings, have had the necessary repairs made, and reported everything to the meetings of the Board of Directors.</p>
   <p>Delegate of Branch 27, M. Metelsky, remarked that the expense of the Real Estate Management Committee are not very clear. Stolarana gave the necessary explanation which was satisfactory to everyone. The committee announced that there was in mind an exchange of one property for a farm, but no suitable farm was found which could meet the needs of the society.</p>
   <p>Reports of the Branches</p>
   <p>Branch 1: There were greetings and wishes for success extended to the <pb facs="5423967_3_1316.jpg" n="19"/>assembly by W. Olesiuk, who reported that Branch 1 is working toward consolidating the entire Russian colony in Chicago and vicinity. Since May 1, 1934 until May 1, 1935, there have been 35 new members enrolled in Branch 1. During this period 12 members have left the ranks for various reasons. There are in Branch One 402 regular paying members. During the same period Branch 1 paid $6,213.50 into the treasury for death benefits, and $2,248.10 to the sick benefits; and $776.80 into the Administration Fund. There was $9,238 paid into the RIMAS's treasury by Branch 1. The Branch annually arranges two social functions: a picnic and a ball. In various parts of Chicago members of Branch 1 have night schools for children. Branch 1 has a juvenile department whose membership is 250 members. Branch 1 has contributed $3,731.05 to the newly constructed St. George's Church. On May 1, 1935, there was $9,490.37 in the treasury of the Branch.</p>
   <p>Branch 2: D. Bregin reported that he could not say much. There are 73 members in the branch and $1,500 in the treasury.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1317.jpg" n="20"/>
   <p>Branch 3: Maria Ross reported that activity is successfully conducted. There are 245 regular paying members, and $4,486 in the treasury. In the future they shall try to increase the membership.</p>
   <p>Branch 4: S. Fedorovsky reported that the branch was organized at the same time as Branch 1, but it has only 15 adult members and 6 minors. There is no treasury.</p>
   <p>Branch 5: Borisuk reported that there are 61 members in the branch and $1,206 in the treasury. It is difficult to gain new members.</p>
   <p>Branch 7: A. Petruchik reported that there are 60 adult and 6 minor members in the branch and $392 in the treasury. Many members are in debt. The branch has also a school.</p>
   <p>Branch 8: Anna Kraus. She reported that there are 31 members in the branch and $115 in the treasury.</p>
   <p>Branch 10: Z. Schelkun reported that there are 33 members in the branch, <pb facs="5423967_3_1318.jpg" n="21"/>$839.85 in the treasury. Members do not pay the sick benefit and do not receive it. Every member pays 25 cents into the treasury and it is impossible to gain new members.</p>
   <p>Branch 15: E. Horoschenia reported that there are 40 adult members and 13 minors in the branch. There is $170 in the treasury. The branch has a school.</p>
   <p>Branch 16: P. Vasilkov reported that the branch has 18 adult and 8 minor members. There is $22 in the treasury. All is in order at the branch.</p>
   <p>Branch 17: (Baltimore,Md) P. Abramuk reported that the branch is only three years old. Eight new members have been admitted during the past year. There are 27 members in the branch and $150 in the treasury. In the Club of Youth there are 15 members. He has been entrusted also to report for Branch 20.</p>
   <p>Branch 20: P. Abramuk reported that there are 15 members. Baltimore has branches of ROOVA AND RNOVA, but we have found that RIMAS in an organization, <pb facs="5423967_3_1319.jpg" n="22"/>non-partisan which can consolidate around itself a non-partisan mass larger than ROOVA and RNOV, which have traces of political inclinations.</p>
   <p>Branch 18: J. Dziako reported that the branch is still young, having been organized February 1, 1933. "I will not discuss in detail how much work, energy and time was spent in organizing the new branch during the worst of the depression. The branch now has 45 members. There is also a group of youth with 15 members. The treasury consists of $166.51. Complete solidarity exists among the members in the branch. There have been no misunderstandings in the branch. Officers do not receive salaries, and do not demand transportation expenses. Cultural-educational work is slow, the reason for which is lack of permanent location. The branch works jointly with the School Society of the Russian Children's School of I. A. Kryloff. Cooperation and solidarity reign between the branch and the School Society. Branch 18 has formulated a plan for the coming fall season to find a good location together with the School Society, and give a good start to cultural-educational work in the branch, since the branch is enriched with some excellent workers. Branch 18 has a plan with the help of the school that it organize a Club of Youth, a large <pb facs="5423967_3_1320.jpg" n="23"/>Russian choir, and open a new school of music and dance. Branch 18 thanks the 23rd Supreme Assembly and the Board of Directors for the issuance of policies of new forms of insurance, because of which the branches locally will be able to subscribe its youth and thus help to merge the strength of youth with our noble Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society."</p>
   <p>Branch 25: A. Markevich. He reported that they are members of the former Russian Aid Society of Melrose Park and have become affiliated with the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society on November 1934. The branch is in existence seven months. It has been given the name of Branch 25 of RIMAS. The branch has 31 members, 21 have policies and the other 10 pay only for the sick benefit. There are frozen assets in the bank amounting to $971.99.</p>
   <p>Branch 26: Sophia Levkovich. The branch has been newly organized. There are 11 members, 9 adults and 2 minors. There is no treasury yet.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1321.jpg" n="24"/>
   <p>Branch 27: M. Metelsky reported that the branch has 44 members and $77 in the treasury. The branch has a school for a number of years, but lately, due to the depression, it was difficult to maintain.</p>
   <p>Second delegate of Branch 27, A. Rak, reported that there is a school at Branch 27. The school term began November 1, 1934 and ended March 1, 1935. The attendance was poor, as there is no instructor who would be responsible for the demands of the school. The school treasury cannot afford employment of a capable teacher.</p>
   <p>Representative of St. George's Parish:</p>
   <p>G. Chepelevich was given the floor. He greeted the assembly with best wishes for success of the business of the assembly. In his address he broached the subject of the construction of the new church building, which will serve to develop the Russian social work in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1322.jpg" n="25"/>
   <p>Attorney K. P. Gugis:</p>
   <p>Upon being granted the floor, Mr. Gugis extended his felicitations to the assembly and recommended that more force be exerted so that more new members be enrolled to increase the membership. With such a membership it is difficult to maintain a mercenary committee, and without a permanent committee it is impossible to conduct social activities.</p>
   <p>Upon motion duly made and carried the first session of the Supreme Assembly was adjourned Saturday, May 11, at 11:15 P. M.</p>
   <p>The second session was announced for Sunday, May 12, at 10 A. M.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1323.jpg" n="26"/>
   <p>SECOND SESSION</p>
   <p>The second session of the 24th Supreme Assembly of RIMAS opened Sunday, May 12, at 11:00 A. M., due to the late arrival of some of the delegates.</p>
   <p>Roll Call</p>
   <p>All delegates were present.</p>
   <p>Complaints</p>
   <p>Branch 16 of Harvey, Ill., was the first to voice its complaint in regard to the information issued by financial secretary, N. Kozak, to the effect that old policies are no longer in effect. On the strength of such a resolution, members of Branch 16 decided to make it known to the 24th Supreme Assembly that such measures by the secretary have frenzied effect on the members of the society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1324.jpg" n="27"/>
   <p>In self-defense, Supreme Secretary, N. Kozak, read a copy of the letter sent to Branch 16, and the assembly found that the former (Branch 16) misunderstood the content of the letter. The assembly recommended that a letter be sent again to Branch 16, explaining to the members that matter more thoroughly.</p>
   <p>Welcome Address by Olga Haponovich</p>
   <p>Olga Haponovich, student of the Kryloff School, read a congratulatory message to the assembly: "Honorable Chairman and Dear Delegates: I, a member of the Kryloff School of the RIMAS, have been chosen to greet you and wish you success in your undertakings, and express our best wishes. All of you know well that any organization, like living flesh, needs a constant flow of fresh forces, Where can this fresh source be found? In order to make useful members of the youth, they must be prepared. In order to get this preparation they must attend Russian schools. The more Russian schools there be, the more new useful members will you have in the organization, members who will in time take your places and with pride lead the <pb facs="5423967_3_1325.jpg" n="28"/>organization in the path of culture. I hope that you will help the school organization and thus you will be helping yourselves. To you, delegates, I wish productive results and flourishment (sic) to the RIMAS," concluded Miss Haponovich. Her speech was tumultuously applauded.</p>
   <p>Likewise, a pupil from the Bunin School, S. Shuran, spoke: "Dear Independents: It is my great honor to greet you on behalf of the pupils of the Bunin School of RIMAS. We know that on our shoulders lies a great social task. You are confronted with the solution of your important problems. You must work out a plan of activity for a whole year. On a wise decision of all problems will depend the success of the society. From my full heart I wish you success in this important and responsible work, and I express the hope that you will not forget us, your younger generation. Remember that the future RIMAS must be prolonged by your children. All this will be possible only in the event we obtain the preparation necessary. This preparation we can receive only through schools. Therefore, we beg you to seriously consider the school situation. One again I wish you success," concluded Shuran.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1326.jpg" n="29"/>
   <p>The assembly accorded the two youthful speakers with applause as a reward for their efforts and expressed appreciation of the instructors for the fine preparation.</p>
   <p>V. V. Shumkoff, instructor, requested to speak and announced that it was with great pleasure that he greeted the 24th Supreme Assembly of RIMAS, that last year he was junior clerk of the assembly. He has thought long to help the organization and induct life into RIMAS. Formerly there were persons in the society who caused rifts and unwrought (sic) the work of the society. Now this condition is removed. The younger generation will bring fresh energy to our society. Young strength will enter with new ideas and force. From the heart he wishes the assembly success.</p>
   <p>Announcements and Reports to the Supreme Assembly</p>
   <p>L. Kujava, member of Branch 5, announced that after the death of a member <pb facs="5423967_3_1327.jpg" n="30"/>of Branch 5, in accordance with the request of the deceased, the entire death benefit was spent on the funeral. The Board of Directors protested such action and allowed us to spend only $250, the remaining sum was to be sent to the widow who resides in Europe. We have a number of members who do not approve of the interference of the Board in matters of the branch.</p>
   <p>President of the Society, Wallace, explained that the matter is settled. The remaining $250 were sent to the widow. She is satisfied and the matter is considered closed.</p>
   <p>S. Parfeevetz of Branch 2 sent in an announcement wherein he states the occurrence of a misunderstanding in Branch 2. At the yearly meeting the directors of the branch were elected. But a report was made to the administration of the society that all these members are not good, but the administration approved their installation, having not presented <pb facs="5423967_3_1328.jpg" n="31"/>against them any blame. Secondly, bonds were demanded for officials of our branch, but this is not practiced in other branches.</p>
   <p>The Supreme President, Wallace, explained to the delegates of Branch 2 that the whole trouble lies in the fact that the branches do not elect good workers for the society. We know immediately after the meeting that he was doing harm to the society, distributed among the members handbills directed detrimentally against the society. We found that such members cannot be at the head of a branch and then there were many other derogatory remarks against this group members. On these grounds he was disclaimed and to his post members should be elected who will not injure the work of the organization. The Board does not defend itself, but the entire society. Every branch may elect to this administration those whom they like, but if the member will do harm, the Board is obligated to take action, even to expel such.</p>
   <p>Delegate of Branch 27, M. Metelsky, announced that there have been no <pb facs="5423967_3_1329.jpg" n="32"/>misunderstandings, but there is one matter which is quite complicated. The new forms of insurance cost more to the member than insurance in American insurance companies. We must give this matter consideration. Why could we not get cheaper policies for our society, as otherwise many members will leave the society.</p>
   <p>President Wallace explained that the remark by Metelsky is untrue, that in other companies it is not cheaper. Members are not as yet informed on the new policies. There are companies which offer cheap insurance but a person knowing insurance business will not fall for such propositions. "I would not recommend to anyone to be insured in such companies," remarked Wallace.</p>
   <p>Delegate of Branch 7, A. Petruchik, announced that there was dissatisfaction among the members for the fact that in order to obtain free services of a physician, dues must be paid in advance for a whole year. Supreme Secretary, N. Kozak, explained that this applies only to those members who take out time - ten year policies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1330.jpg" n="33"/>
   <p>Permanent Secretary and His Salary</p>
   <p>The next question in the agenda was that of a permanent secretary and his salary. It caused quite a discussion. The following members asked permission to speak: Wallace, Volodkin, Erin, Bernov, Grib, Petruchik, Kichkailo, Horoschia, Jujava, Stolarana, Yakimovich, Dziako, Pasiuk, Markovich, and Sabinsky. From the speeches it became clear that a permanent secretary on a salary was necessary. With the introduction of new insurance policies the secretary will and is overburdened with work, so that it is impossible for him to execute it during evenings and he cannot continue, thus, much longer. Besides, for the success of the organization there would be a permanent secretary. Of the expense becoming greater, this is a matter of the future. With a permanent secretary the work shall be done on time, more members will be enrolled and there shall be a larger fund. Therefore, perhaps, can get by without an additional increase of the fund, that is, leave the fund as previously, ten cents per month from each member.</p>
   <p>The question was put to a vote with the result that there were 42 votes <pb facs="5423967_3_1331.jpg" n="34"/>against one in favor of a permanent secretary.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Nedzelnitsky welcomed the delegates to the assembly and wished it success. He recommended to the gathered delegates to subscribe youth into the society, for without it the further existence of the organization is impossible. "I ask you, fathers and mothers, to subscribe your children into the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society," appealed Dr. Nedzelnitzky to the delegates and guests present at the assembly.</p>
   <p>Discussion of Permanent Headquarters for the Society</p>
   <p>It was disclosed that heretofore the office was located in a private home. The books and property of the society were held at the home of the secretary. For the technical work a permanent office is demanded. It was unanimously resolved that there be permanent quarters.</p>
   <p>The Board of Directors was entrusted to find an office at their discretion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1332.jpg" n="35"/>
   <p>Change in the Date of Assemblies</p>
   <p>N. Kozak recommended that future assemblies be held in the fall instead of spring, as work greatly accumulates each year, and it is impossible to solve all business in two days, therefore, there was a resolution passed that the next assembly of RIMAS be held in September, when it can convene for three days.</p>
   <p>Salaries of Officers of RIMAS</p>
   <p>From opinions voiced by many delegates it was decided to leave the salary of the president of the society at $80 per year. The salary of treasurer it was decided by a majority to decrease it from $80 to $60 per year.</p>
   <p>Salary of a permanent secretary was discussed; after which it was decided by a majority votes of the assembly that $20 a week be granted as salary to the financial secretary. In view of the fact that the financial secretary will receive $20 a week, the assembly unanimously resolved that the <pb facs="5423967_3_1333.jpg" n="36"/>secretary must execute the work of the recording secretary.</p>
   <p>Upon motion duly made and seconded and carried by a majority, it was decided that a small salary be paid to the senior auditor, that is, $1.</p>
   <p>Intermission.</p>
   <p>Election of Officers for 1935-1936:</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Supreme President of RIMAS: The Assembly approached past Supreme President G. Wallace to accept the post for another year. Wallace, thanking the assembly for the honor, asked the assembly to elect another person for the post, ina smuch as he is quite tired and is in need of rest for a while.</p>
   <p>The following delegates were nominated: Dziako, Pasiuk, Bernov and Kucherepa.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1334.jpg" n="37"/>
   <p>In a closed ballot A. Pasiuk received the majority of votes and was elected Supreme President of RIMAS for 1935-1936.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Supreme Vice-President: Dr. Chadovich was elected as Supreme Vice-President by a majority of votes.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Supreme Secretary: There was sone controversy. The assembly expressed itself that the supreme secretary holds all the strings, and in some degree the progress of the entire society depends on the knowledge and experience of the secretary. Besides secretarial work, it is demanded that he be an organizer. In this respect the assembly finds only three delegates suitable to execute the office of secretary of the society, namely, N. Kozak, Wallace and Horoschenia, who were nominated to the post. E. Horoschenia and Wallace declined in favor of Kozak.</p>
   <p>The election of N. Kozak as Supreme Secretary was unanimously ratified by the assembly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1335.jpg" n="38"/>
   <p>G. Wallace was elected assistant to the Supreme Secretary by a majority vote.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Treasurer of the Society: Joseph Sleznik and S. Parfeevetz accepted the nomination. In a closed ballot Joseph Sleznik received 49 votes and was elected Supreme Treasurer of RIMAS. S. Parfeevetz received 5 votes.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Assistant Treasurer of Society: S. Yakimovich received a majority of votes and was therefore elected assistant treasurer of the society. The following were elected as directors of RIMAS for 1935-1936: W. Sabinsky, J. Dziako, P. Swatikova, P. Ushko, F. Kashtelyanchik, S. Volodkin, F. Parada, A. Bernov, J. Erin, J. Vdovich, D. Zhogalsky, R. Polishchuk, J. Wallace, J. Pyatnitza, and S. Parfeevetz. Substitutes: Bregin and Kucherepa.</p>
   <p>After the election of the administration and directors, Supreme Secretary N. Kozak made a motion to the assembly to make corrections to the <pb facs="5423967_3_1336.jpg" n="39"/>by-laws in paragraphs 70, 151 (sic), and 55. The assembly, having carefully listened to what these paragraphs signify, unanimously approved the motion of N. Kozak, that is, that the corrections be made in the first two paragraphs, and the third be left as it cannot be changed.</p>
   <p>Rev. Paul Nervana's Address to the Assembly</p>
   <p>It was granted to Rev. Paul Nervana, priest of St. George's Church, to address the assembly. Rev. Nervana welcomed the delegates and all those present with Easter greetings. He stated, "I am here only one week, but the name of your society, the Independent Society, is heard everywhere. Formerly I did not know the bounds of your society, the membership constituency, and its aims. Today I see that delegates not only from Chicago and vicinity greet you, but even from Baltimore, Md. This signifies that the Independent Society is growing far and wide. This is being done with the purpose of preserving the native language, culture and education. Having attended your assembly, I can say that your society is a strong Russian organization, in existence only 24 years. Now you are <pb facs="5423967_3_1337.jpg" n="40"/>entering into a new period and strive for new conquests, in the field of mutual aid and education. From distant countries you have gathered and with impatience you spread your work. This conquest is to be supported and expanded. It is necessary that lectures be arranged and acquaint people with the truth on the following themes: religion, philosophy, and cultural education. If the intelligentsia will join with us, then our work will flourish. In this work the newspaper Rassviet will help us much, which is a widely circulated publication in America and is published by experienced people. Many Russian children do not know their names, other peoples do not have this fault. We are striving for creative and progressive work, and Russian names should not be forgotten. Consider even enemies as friends. And so, forward with force and faith in truth and the Lord will bless you."</p>
   <p>Supreme Secretary, N. Kozak, pointed out that there is much to say and think in regard to youth. Many of the juvenile departments are being transferred to the adult branches. Their place is being very slowly replaced by new youth. There has been a call sent to all branches to <pb facs="5423967_3_1338.jpg" n="41"/>attract more youth into their ranks. Only branch 15 has fulfilled this work completely. It is necessary that other branches follow the example of branch 15 and make it a duty to subscribe youth into the society. We already have children's policies, and there should be no barriers.</p>
   <p>This question provoked great interest amongst the delegates and 15 speakers asked for the floor.</p>
   <p>Each of the speakers presented his personal views and expressed his thoughts as to how the organization of youth may be successful, and each arrived at the conclusion that youth should be organized in the branches. For the purpose of organizing youth, the assembly recommended to the Board of Directors that to make this a reality it is necessary to send instructions from the Board to the branches in a number of not less than three times a year, to explain the meaning and benefits of the Juvenile Department.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1339.jpg" n="42"/>
   <p>Schools of RIMAS</p>
   <p>Many speakers expressed their opinions on this question. Madame Swatikova pointed out that the future of RIMAS depends largely on youth. None of the parents can understand and inspire their children as to the greatness of Russia, as to its beauty. There is only one means for this: That is, education and upbringing.</p>
   <p>V. Dedovich pointed out that without schools Russian youth is similar to an anchored boat, where fish bite various Passeres by hooks (sic), who at the expense of Russian youth, build their own well-being.</p>
   <p>After all the speakers had finished, the delegates reached the conclusion that schools must be supported by the branches locally and that the School Council will be safeguarded in the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1340.jpg" n="43"/>
   <p>Interest on Mortgages (Loans)</p>
   <p>The Board of Directors recommended to the assembly on the question of interest that the rate of interest should be lowered, because many debtors are unable to pay 6%, and besides they request a reduction.</p>
   <p>A motion was duly made that the rate of interest be lowered from 6% to 5%</p>
   <p>This motion was seconded and voted upon with the result that there were 49 votes in favor of lowering the rate of interest to 5% and 2 votes against, favoring 6%.</p>
   <p>Society Farm</p>
   <p>The Assembly made a recommendation on the question of a farm for the <pb facs="5423967_3_1341.jpg" n="44"/>society, that the resolution made last year be followed, that is, the Board of Directors continue to seek a farm and also to appeal to members of the society for voluntary donations to acquire a farm.</p>
   <p>Creation of Fund for the Needy Members of RIMAS</p>
   <p>A motion was made that due to the depression unemployed members are not able to pay their membership dues, therefore the Board of Directors resolved to put this question before the assembly for discussion.</p>
   <p>Volodkin made a motion that every branch help its unemployed members and cover their dues. The motion was duly seconded and carried by a unanimous vote.</p>
   <p>Grievance Committee's Report</p>
   <p>The Grievance Committee reported that five documents have been received <pb facs="5423967_3_1342.jpg" n="45"/>for the decision of the assembly:</p>
   <p>(1) Maria Kulich appeals to the assembly with a request by letter that the assembly permit the Board of Directors to pay to her the death benefit of her husband, B. Kulich, who died May 31, 1934.</p>
   <p>The assembly demands that the board of directors show the reason for non-payment of the death benefit to Maria Kulich.</p>
   <p>Supreme Secretary, N. Kozak, disclosed to the assembly the document of the late B. Kulich, and stated that in the document it is said that the deceased committed suicide by cutting his throat.</p>
   <p>In accordance with the by-laws we do not pay the death benefit for suicide, and it is for this reason that payment has been delayed to M. Kulich.</p>
   <p>Having heard the report of the Board of Directors, the assembly resolved <pb facs="5423967_3_1343.jpg" n="46"/>that action be taken according to provisions in the by-laws.</p>
   <p>(2) The matter of mailing quarterly reports to the branches is referred by the assembly to the Board of Directors.</p>
   <p>(3) Expulsion of L. Stanko from RIMAS.</p>
   <p>In regard to the expulsion of L. Stanko from the society, the Board of Directors pointed out that a special meeting on this case was held on March 25th. At this meeting L. Stanko was told that if he continued further to cause harm to the society, then he shall be expelled from the society without warning.</p>
   <p>However, Stanko paid no attention to this warning, and at the meeting of Branch 2, when representatives of the Board of RIMAS (Sabinsky, Kozak and Yakimovich) were present, L. Stanko quite ardently attacked them, insulting them, and generally conducting himself repulsively towards the <pb facs="5423967_3_1344.jpg" n="47"/>representatives of the society. On the basis of such conduct at the meeting of the Board of Directors, held April 23, 1935, L. Stanko was expelled from the society for violating paragraph 86 of the by-laws of RIMAS.</p>
   <p>Having heard the disclosure by the Board of Directors, the assembly ratified the resolution of the Board expelling L. Stanko from RIMAS for undermining activities.</p>
   <p>Release of Members for Loan on Douglas Park School.</p>
   <p>The assembly, by a vote of 38 to 2, decided to release members of the Douglas Park School, P. Chopko, G. Kichkailo and J. Omelianuk from payment of $200 which was spent by them to organize the Douglas Park Russian Children's School.</p>
   <p>St. George's Church Appeal for Loan.</p>
   <p>An appeal to the assembly of the committee of St. George's Church for a <pb facs="5423967_3_1345.jpg" n="48"/>loan to the parish of $6,500, for the purpose of completing the new constructions - church, school and auditorium - was heard. The delegates of many provincial branches announced that they were not prepared to speak on this question inasmuch as this question was not brought up in their branches. Delegates of other branches were permitted in order, to speak their opinions on the question.</p>
   <p>Financial secretary, N. Kozak, reported that the society cannot grant a loan of a large sum as all the money is distributed according to the funds and each fund must have a certain sum on hand.</p>
   <p>After some discussion, the assembly resolved that an additional loan of $3,500 be granted, that is, a total of $7,000.</p>
   <p>Reports of the Accounts Committee</p>
   <p>The accounting committee reported that the expenses of the delegates to the assembly amount to $78.54.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1346.jpg" n="49"/>
   <p>In conclusion the assembly recommended that an expression of thanks be made to J. J. Voronko for announcing the assembly over the radio.</p>
   <p>A motion duly made and seconded and carried that the assembly be closed, was passed and the assembly was closed Sunday, May 12, 1935, at 11:30 P.M.</p>
   <p>Dr. P. L. Chadovich, Chairman of the Assembly</p>
   <p>A. Haponovich, Clerk of the Assembly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
