<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1923-11-08">Nov. 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">To Our Readers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-11-08">Nov. 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">TO OUR READERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The publishing of the paper Svobodnaya Rossiya was re-organized at the end of October of this year. A group of persons joined the first owners and expressed their wish to make efforts to put the paper on a more sound basis. The new administration of the paper undertook first of all to bring order in the financial affairs of it, and to work out plans for reforms necessary for its further strengthening economically. It considered also many other problems which are connected with the publishing of the paper and now finds it necessary to inform the honorable readers about their intentions. The new publishers of the paper Svobodnaya Rossiya considered it expedient to change the name of the paper. Beginning November 12, 1923, it will be named Russkii Viestnik. The paper will be published daily as before and will contain six pages, without change in price.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0042.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Russkii Viestnik's aim will be to serve the interests of the Russian-American colony in general and those of the masses of Russian workers in particular. It will strive to throw light on the life of the Russians in America; will help them analyze the questions of their lives, and will aid in their educational undertakings. Some new powers for the editorial office were suggested and it is proposed to invite some more collaborators. In the meantime the directors of the paper are applying to the public to give the paper a helping hand; to give more information about the life of the Russian colony, to write us about the gatherings of societies and clubs, parties and other undertakings. Only with the help of its readers can a paper such as ours, which has no funds for hiring a great number of paid workers, become interesting and alive. We hope that in renewing the powers and enriching the contents of our paper we will in the future win the sympathy of still wider circles of the Russian colony.</p>
   <p>The Editorial Office.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
