<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-12-16">Dec. 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Education of the Colony</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0435</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0435.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-12-16">Dec. 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE EDUCATION OF THE COLONY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The education of the Russian colony is one of our chief problems. The right solution of this problem is incumbent on every intellectual who is loyal to his people.</p>
   <p>"If thou knowest anything," says a sage, "teach it to one who does not know."</p>
   <p>There are still many ignorant people among the Russian colony. Among these ignorant persons, however, there are often to be met persons who, having acquired the first rudiments of knowledge, will go further and many reach the point when they themselves will teach others and be workers for the great cause of the enlightenment of the people.</p>
   <p>Such persons may not be noticed by others; they may not even notice themselves, and that because they have not been taught properly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0436.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Who should teach them?</p>
   <p>The colony should be taught by competent people: by persons who know history, agriculture; by physicians, engineers, lawyers, etc.</p>
   <p>The editorial office of the Russian Herald, desiring to meet the demands of the colony for more education, has resolved to invite such competent persons and to organize a cycle of lectures on various subjects, in order to increase the knowledge of the colony.</p>
   <p>On Saturday, Dec. 13, took place a meeting of the initiators of the group which was to undertake the organization of the lectures. The following resolutions were passed at this meeting:</p>
   <p>"The lectures will be given on such subjects as are not taught in the Russian schools existing in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0437.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Each lecturer will give to the students a complete course on some subject.</p>
   <p>"The courses will constitute a school for adults, the name of which will be either the Peoples University or The Institute of Knowledge or Courses of Journalism."</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be devoted to the working out of the program of these courses, and in accordance with that program will be chosen the name of the courses. If this undertaking is going to take the form of a People's University an appropriate program will have to be elaborated.</p>
   <p>If courses of journalism will be opened such courses will have to be thorough.</p>
   <p>In order to complete a course of journalism one has to study the laws, Russian literature, history and geography, become acquainted with hygiene, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0438.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>One who completes a course of journalism must know how to write not only about the events of the day; he must be able to understand many intricate problems in order to be able to write an article that would interest the readers.</p>
   <p>And all this can be achieved only by an enlightened person, knowing a good many things.</p>
   <p>To sum it up, the question as to what name should be adopted for the courses, courses or university, is to be solved in the nearest future. Meanwhile it has been definitely decided to start the lectures about the 1st of January, 1925.</p>
   <p>Soon the program will be published, also the names of the lecturers and teachers.</p>
   <p>The Initiatory Group.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
