<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-20">Apr. 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Russian People Unite Around RnzOv</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-20">Apr. 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIAN PEOPLE UNITE AROUND RNzOV</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the approach of spring and the twenty-fourth annual convention of RNzOV, Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, the Russian colony in Chicago is showing signs of unusual animation.</p>
   <p>In the springtime, people in villages usually clean their barns and clear their orchards and gardens of refuse. The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society has also started the season with a spring cleaning. It expelled some members from its midst and cautioned others to behave, under threat of expulsion. As a result, the voices of the disrupters have been subdued, and those of the active workers are more resonant. The older members speak more firmly, and with greater authority; the newer members are becoming more active, and are becoming enthusiastic supporters of RNzOV.</p>
   <p>Almost all the branches have increased their memberships. Particularly conspicuous is the influx of young members, some of whom are underage. New <pb facs="5423967_3_1363.jpg" n="2"/>forms of insurance, like the rays of the sun, have revitalized the Russian colony, which is gravitating toward the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. Parents, mindful of the future of their children, enroll them into the ranks of our society in ever-increasing numbers. Such parents deserve high praise and approval. Their children, on reaching maturity, will be able to receive an education and a financial start in life in the form of a sizable sum of money. With the money thus received, they will be in a position to go into business, and with this aid, in the course of time, they will be able to gain a firmer foothold in the economic setup of modern society.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday, over the radio, we heard Mr. and Mrs. Torbachuk in Argo present their son, Volodia, with a thousand-dollar endowment on the day of his maturity. This was an excellent and sensible gift, and it would be a very good thing if other Russian parents followed this example. One should not look back and regret past errors and failures. One must always look into the future and move forward. Our future is our children. We must hope that whatever we have failed to accomplish, they will accomplish. Faith <pb facs="5423967_3_1364.jpg" n="3"/>moves mountains, and let us have faith that our Russian-American youth will remain Russian, will attain a high moral level, will accept the ideals of our Russian idealists as well as those of their fathers, and will, ultimately, raise the prestige of the Russian name abroad.</p>
   <p>But in order to accomplish this, we must keep our Russian national spirit alive, and we must be united. Meanwhile, in Chicago and its vicinity, there is only one really Russian organization, and that is the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. Therefore, let us unite around RNzOV, around this old stand-by of the Russian colony in Chicago, which has done so much good for both old and young Russians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
