<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-13">Mar. 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Russian Radio Hour</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-13">Mar. 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUSSIAN RADIO HOUR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All nationalities in America broadcast their national programs over the air. We Russians also, supposedly, have our own radio hour. Despite the fact that Chicago is a large city with a considerable number of Russians, what can we say, what can we pride ourselves on with reference to our own radio program? Perhaps we can take pride in ourselves when we hear one godmother greet another over the waves, and send her best sentiments, or when cheap advertising talk fills up the entire hour.</p>
   <p>It is pleasant and enjoyable to hear the native songs and music when far away from the motherland; but, alas, we, seemingly, are not fated to enjoy productions of the excellent Russian art. Our Russian program is so "good" that we have to conceal it from foreigners in order to avoid possible offense against the "Russian" art. When somebody is present at your home and the guest does not understand Russian you are afraid he may say: Shut off that confounded....bla-bla-bla....</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0166.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To our great pity we cannot invite people of other nationalities to listen to our music broadcast over the radio during our own program, despite the fact that we are rich in talented composers, musicians, and artists. The Russian music is well known throughout the entire civilized world. Many foreigners like to listen to the Russian music and greatly appreciate the works of Tchaikovsky, Rimski-Korsakov, Glinka, Rachmaninov, and other Russian composers and musicians. However, the Russian radio hour can "flatter" us with only recorded music performed mostly on accordions and consisting of trivial songs and other similar trash.</p>
   <p>I think that in Chicago there are many businessmen, physicians and men of other professions to be found who are willing to pay for advertising and announcements on a good program. At present, we have only one hour during the entire week and that only on Sunday morning when many possible listeners are still in bed.</p>
   <p>The program hides as if from shame in a faraway corner and is afraid to show itself before other nationalities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
