<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-07-25">July 25, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Our News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-07-25">July 25, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">OUR NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Beginning with today there will be a special section under the headline, News of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, published on Saturday in Rassviet.</p>
   <p>The active members of the organization have dreamed about this section a long time ago. In the last years the interest of our Society demanded that our peoples' foremost organization should have if not its own press organ, at least, a special section in one of the local newspapers.</p>
   <p>To-day such a section is put at the disposal of the readers.</p>
   <p>What is the aim of its initiators?</p>
   <p>Why do the interests of the organization demand the use of the local press for its needs?</p>
   <p>The financial report of the Board of Directors of the Russian Independent Aid Society and of the Brotherhood of St. George (the largest branch of <pb facs="5423967_3_1684.jpg" n="2"/>the R. I. M. A. S.) contains an eloquent answer to the above.</p>
   <p>The organization, the capital of which reached the sum of $50,000, with 2000 members respectively cannot use in the future absolete methods of informing its members about the activities of the organization.</p>
   <p>Numerous branches, with its members scattered in various states, have to be advised in due time of what is going on in the mother organization, and in all its branches.</p>
   <p>The exact and timely information concerning the organization's activities is the necessary condition of a normal development of the organization.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, the same exact and timely information is the only natural way to come into direct touch with the unorganized members of our colony, and to advise them about the problems and aims of our organization.</p>
   <p>The organization, by publishing full particulars of its activities, not only binds closer the actual members, but induces the new immigrant to join the organized family of R. I. M. A. S.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1685.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society in Chicago, extends the benefit of mutual aid over several thousand people. But, as is known, the R. I. M. A. S. is far from serving all the Russian immigrants in the Middle West; the number of these immigrants, according to the last census, exceeds several scores of thousands.</p>
   <p>To organize as many Russian immigrants as possible for the purpose of making them join the mutual aid organization in those cities and states, which gravitate toward the city of Chicago, this is an object which is put before the organization by life itself, by its situation,and by the progress it has made in the last years. And certainly, in order to solve all the problems that stand before the R. I. M. A. S., we need the present section, we need our "News." The near future will prove to our readers and members how important is the regular publishing of the "News."</p>
   <p>The editing committee of the "News" requests in the meantime the secretaries of the R. I. M. A. S. branches and its local co-workers not to be embarrassed by the style of their literary contributions and to send reports, accounts, and minutes, correspondence,and all kind of information about the life of the R. I. M. A. S. branch offices.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1686.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[illegible]"/>
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
