<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-05">Jan. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Fight in Branch # 115 of Rnov</title><title level="a" type="sub">by M. Davidovsky</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-05">Jan. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">FIGHT IN BRANCH # 115 OF RNOV</title><title level="a" type="sub">by M. Davidovsky</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the annual meeting of Branch #115 of Rnov, Russian Peoples Mutual Aid Society, they had a fight again. This time, some members of the branch, which has been misled by the communists, protested against the betrayal and shakedown of the rank and file members by the "big shots" from the leadership of Rnov.</p>
   <p>"I pay more for a $250 death benefit policy than the members of the Roova pay for a $500 policy. We pay fifty cents for four dollars weekly hospital care, whereas in Roova, they pay the same premium for eight dollars weekly hospital care. You have claimed that Roova was dying, that White Guards would destroy it, but you did not tell us that Roova had purchased a farm, had built a Russian settlement, an orphanage, and an old people's home. We have just been examining the bottomless pockets of the men from Novyi Mir [Translator's note: a <pb facs="5423967_3_1417.jpg" n="2"/>Bolshevik daily newspaper in New York] and various other Bolshevik parasites, living off our backs. When our treasury managed to accumulate twenty-five dollars, our chairman hurried to send the money to Troyanovsky [Translator's note: Soviet ambassador in Washington], but he never tried to find out whether the dues of the unemployed members had been paid. We are considered as an organization of workers, and yet we are ruled by a contractor-speculator."</p>
   <p>The chairman ordered the member who was protesting to be thrown out. Voices were heard saying, "He told the truth".....[Then the battle began.] Bottles were thrown, chairs flew in the air. Everything that could be grabbed, went into the fight. As a result of this melee, the boss of Branch #115 was taken to the hospital, with a cracked skull. Other "comrades" also suffered injuries. This is an example of the cultural life of the Bolsheviks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
