<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-03-12">March 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A New Guest in Chicago</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0906</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0906.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-03-12">March 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW GUEST IN CHICAGO</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The lecture on Bolshevism given by Mr. M. L. Slonim, a literary man and a prominent member of the party of Socialist-Revolutionaries who has come to Chicago, proved to be very instructive, well thought-over and rich in serious and well authenticated data.</p>
   <p>One can agree or disagree with the conclusions reached by the lecturer (this depends on the views held by the respective person), but one cannot but acknowledge that his lecture was a brilliant one, as it contained a rich material founded on fact, was based on logically sound promises, was carefully thought over and, in spite of the fact that the lecturer belongs to a definite party, was free from any prejudice. (This is something rare).</p>
   <p>We Russians living in Chicago have been used to lectures in which some representative of a certain party or current of thought speaks most <pb facs="5423967_3_0907.jpg" n="2"/>excitedly and spitefully about some other party or current of thought of which he is an enemy. Very often spiteful reproofs and "critique" are being fortified just by our celebrated "in general," and not by any solidly established facts, by true knowledge and logical arguments such as are required for a good lecture.</p>
   <p>On this occasion, however, we had before us a highly cultured lecturer, possessing marvelous erudition, and one who was quite free from the tendency of appealing to the base passions of man.</p>
   <p>The lecturer is a socialist-populist (narodnik) of very strong convictions. He spoke about Bolshevism, considering it from the standpoint of a socialist.</p>
   <p>What appealed to one strongly in his lecture was his staunch faith in <pb facs="5423967_3_0908.jpg" n="3"/>the creative forces of the Russian people and in Russia's bright future.</p>
   <p>Another appealing feature of this lecture was the aversion of the lecturer to all the bloodshed that has been going on in Russia.</p>
   <p>"Too much precious blood has been spilt by the Russian people." These words resounded from the platform several times.</p>
   <p>And one could feel that these words were spoken by a man who had been deeply affected by the horrors of the civil war.</p>
   <p>The lecture did not come off without some of those curious incidents which are such a common thing in our colony; some rightists and extreme leftists interrupted the lecturer by wild questions and exclamations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0909.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We have been told that in a few days Mr. M. L. Slonim will lecture on "Literature in Soviet Russia."</p>
   <p>We recommend to the members of our colony not to miss this lecture. Mr. M. L. Slonim has the reputation of being one of the outstanding authorities on modern Russian literature. His Critical Essays are very interesting reading.</p>
   <p>Zemetchinsky (S. E. Scheinmann).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
