<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-01-13">Jan. 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Problems of the Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-01-13">Jan. 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROBLEMS OF THE RUSSIAN CONSOLIDATED MUTUAL AID SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Any living organism--be it a solitary human being, a group, or a large organization--must progress, and should aspire towards some goal. Otherwise there is no active life; there is no interest, and sometimes there is only a very injurious vegetation. Roov, Russkoe Ob'edinennoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (The Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society) is a great social organization composed of several branches. As a large organization it must lead an active life, aspire toward some goal in life which is sought by the majority of its members. Without such a goal, without a common ambition, the organization cannot progress. What, then, are its problems--or to speak correctly, requirements--at the present time?</p>
   <p>There are several. Three of them are foremost: to establish a loan and savings bank, to organize the youth and to encourage their activity in the Roov, and to develop a better Roov page in Rassviet.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1573.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Let us begin with the last. It is necessary to discuss openly and clearly from all points of view the mediocrity of our page. Its main shortcoming is that the articles are of a political or polemical character, and such articles are not acceptable in the page of Roov. In general, they are weak on all points; in ideas, in the experience and authority of the writers, and in the manner of exposition, that is, in simple elementary grammar. Besides, all these articles are against some members of our organization. After reading such illiterate trash, some amount of filth settles and always remains on the soul, and one does not care to read further.</p>
   <p>The page of the Roov must serve as a bond which ties together the branches and the central organization, as well as each branch with the other. For this purpose, it should have the character of a news page. Yet, how will we receive the necessary information about the social work of the branches at present? We must have a permanent correspondent whose duty will not be <pb facs="5423967_3_1574.jpg" n="3"/>to write political articles, but to inform us by absolutely correct and authentic reports of the social activities of his particular branch.</p>
   <p>Incidentally, as I understand it, the central organization has repeatedly directed the branches to send statements of their social activities, but there have been no results. And this is understandable because the center should appeal not to the branches, but to the individual members of the branches who are more or less educated. There should be a correspondent in every branch of the organization for the page of Roov.</p>
   <p>The last problem, to establish a loan and savings bank, was approved by the branches and the majority of the committee, but as difficult as it is to organize [such a bank] in the branches, it is just as essential to organize it in the center and to do this as soon as possible. It is necessary for the main committee to pass on this question very speedily. I do not doubt that the loan and savings department will be established and that it will bring the desired and successful results.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1575.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>To organize the youth is the vital problem of the society. The center is doing everything possible to accomplish this promptly. But the center has neither the sufficient resources nor sufficient members among its organizers. It is urgent that the branches shall not only indicate their desire to organize the youth but shall work toward the realization of that desire. Instead many branches make a laughing matter of this problem. More action is required.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
