<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-28">Mar. 28, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">An Example to Be Followed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-28">Mar. 28, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">AN EXAMPLE TO BE FOLLOWED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday on our page, over the signature of N. Kozak, a small notice was printed with very interesting information concerning Branch Number Twenty-eight of R.I.M.A.S., in Kenosha, Wisconsin. We should like to call the special attention of members of our Society to this notice and at the same time to point our the fact that a great deal can be done by men inspired with a good idea when they do not spare their efforts for the common cause.</p>
   <p>Branch Number Twenty-eight in Kenosha was organized toward the end of last year. At the meeting held on December 29, 1935, it was reported that the Branch had only fourteen members, and yet on March 8, 1936, after a lapse of only two months since the opening of the Branch, the committee reported that the number of members had increased to seventy. Evidently the Russian colony in Kenosha lives a more harmonious, more closely associated life than in any other place, and to the call of the Society to work and act together <pb facs="5423967_3_1141.jpg" n="2"/>for the interest of all Russian people in strange lands the colony in Kenosha responded as one man, began to organize, and joined the ranks of R.I.M.A.S.</p>
   <p>The second important factor in making unity an actuality is the proper approach to the task on hand by the men who head the organization. The organizing committee of Branch Number Twenty-eight undoubtedly has succeeded in awakening the interest of the Russian people in Kenosha and was able to instill in them the idea of the necessity for joining the ranks of our rapidly growing organization, and as a result in less than three months we have a strong Branch with a very active membership. We are sincerely glad of that, and we desire for our people in Kenosha that they may meet with even greater success in their work in the future. Only by united effort can we improve our condition and assure a better future for our children. Our Society has set as its goal to unite under its wing as many Russian people as possible and to form one large harmonious family in order that it may be easier for us all to struggle and live under the <pb facs="5423967_3_1142.jpg" n="3"/>difficult and complicated conditions of modern cities.</p>
   <p>We believe that in other cities and in all other places where there are Russian settlements our people will follow the example of Kenosha, and that all our branches will be enlarged by new and active members. However, the enrollment of the new members should proceed only conformity with the new regulations announced in connection with the adoption of the new forms of insurance. It is also to the interest of the new members that they shall take out the new policies. We have already written much about the advantages derived by our members of this new [form of insurance]. We believe that the secretaries and the chairmen of the branches have explained to their members what these advantages are, and that they will see to it that members make the change for the new form of insurance as soon as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
