<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-07-16">July 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The House of Enlightenment</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0943</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0943.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-07-16">July 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE HOUSE OF ENLIGHTENMENT</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This institutions is already in the fifth year of its existence.</p>
   <p>It is known to almost every member of the Russian colony of Chicago.</p>
   <p>In spite of its being so generally known at times one hears strange rumors about it.</p>
   <p>Sometimes one hears that this house belongs to a religious organization, to the Baptists. Some people hold the opinion that the House of Enlightenment belongs to anarchists; others maintain that it is in the hands of monarchists; and some say that it belongs to the communists.</p>
   <p>In the presence of such rumors and opinions, it is difficult for some people to come to any conclusion as to what this institution really is.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0944.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to refute all such rumors it is necessary to point to the activities of the House of Enlightenment. This institution wants that its name should be taken in the broadest sense.</p>
   <p>Taking into consideration the very Broad meaning of the word "enlightenment," this institution cannot be considered as belonging to any narrow-minded partisan organization.</p>
   <p>Literally all persons, whatever their political and religious convictions and opinions may be, can be members, visitors, guests, sympathizers and friends of the House of Enlightenment.</p>
   <p>Freedom of thought and conscience is not interfered with by anybody.</p>
   <p>People are allowed to discuss without fear any question that may occur to them, whether they want to do it in the auditorium, or in the club, or just in a private conversation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0945.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The spirit of brotherhood, equality and freedom - such is the motto of the House of Enlightenment. One who discusses questions with some one who holds antagonistic views, must listen to his opponent without gnashing of teeth. That is the most important part of human education.</p>
   <p>The House of Enlightenment endeavors not only to foster the spirit of mutual respect among men, irrespective of the difference of their views, (but) it also does its best to broaden as much as possible the mental horizon of its members; to give as wide an outlook on the unlimitable field of human life and activities as possible. With this purpose in view, lectures are given in the House of Enlightenment; excursions are arranged, and classes are organized. In order not to leave these statements unsubstantiated, I shall briefly illustrate them as follows:</p>
   <p>During the last two years there have been given at the auditorium of the House of Enlightenment more than 120 scientific lectures. These <pb facs="5423967_3_0946.jpg" n="4"/>lectures were given by experienced, well-trained persons, sometimes bearing well-known names. It may be interesting to enumerate the persons who have been giving these lectures and the subjects of the latter:</p>
   <p>S. Prokopov has given lectures on the following subjects: Astronomy, physics, chemistry, geology, archaeology, botany, psychology, history (ancient, medieval and modern), history of the development of industry, Darwinism, etc.</p>
   <p>(Note: As far as I know, Mr. Prokopov, who is the writer of this article, is not a well trained specialist in any of the sciences enumerated, nor a graduate of any college. His name should not stand first in a list containing such names as Dr. O. Struve, Professor Gidoni, Professor Popov and others. D. S.)</p>
   <p>Dr. G. Krasnow - on anatomy and physiology.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0947.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Professor Gidoni - on "The Downfall of the Power of the Tsars." (An episode from Russian history).</p>
   <p>Prof. G. Popov - on heredity</p>
   <p>Dr. O. Struve (Russian astronomer) - on "Man and the Universe."</p>
   <p>Dr. Platin - on Biology</p>
   <p>A. Stepanov - on "The Evolution of the Solar System."</p>
   <p>Dr. M. Sahud - on "The Food Elements and Health."</p>
   <p>Dr. M. Volkov - on "The Chemical Elements."</p>
   <p>I. Voronko - on Ethnography</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0948.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Professor Braghin (Note: Col. Braghin is meant. D. S.) - on "Einstein's Theory."</p>
   <p>Besides these persons many others have contributed to this long series of lectures. Also about 20 excursions to various noteworthy places have been arranged under the direction of S. Prokopov.</p>
   <p>From all that has been said the reader will understand that the House of Enlightenment is not bound to any narrow religious or political creed.</p>
   <p>On the contrary, its doors are wide open for all political views and religious creeds.</p>
   <p>(Note: Mr. Prokopov does not mention that the House of Enlightenment was founded by the American Church of the Disciples of Christ in order <pb facs="5423967_3_0949.jpg" n="7"/>to create a center where Russians seeking to improve their educational, moral and spiritual standard, could gather, in some cases even live, use the library and the reading room, attend lectures, etc. Its program was that of all so-called settlements, but it was not intended by its founders to become a center for the propagation of revolutionary and atheistic ideas. Mr. Karl Borders was put at the head of this institution, which has contributed much to the enlightenment of the Russian colony. It could have done even more good if Mr. Karl Borders had not invited assistants who were in sympathy with bolshevist communism and atheism, such as Mr. Yaroslavsky and Mr. Prokopov represented. When the Russian Evangelical Christians of Chicago broke relations with the American Church of the Disciples of Christ, that church liquidated the House of Enlightenment. D. S.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
