<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald)
<date when="1925-09-03">Sept. 3, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The School Federation in the Hands of Non-Partisan Russians</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0403</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0403.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald)
<date when="1925-09-03">Sept. 3, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCHOOL FEDERATION IN THE HANDS OF NON-PARTISAN RUSSIANS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday took place new elections of members of the board of directors of the Federation of Russian Schools for Children in the city of Chicago and suburbs.</p>
   <p>Instead of Eberhardt, who had declined his candidature, the non-partisan workman Turovets was elected president of the federation; Ivan Zhukov was elected recording secretary; Tureyko, financial secretary, and Abramchik, treasurer.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time the president of the federation had been a member of the Communist Party, and many members of the colony were dissatisfied with this state of affairs. They were saying that politics should not be tolerated in the schools; that the teachers and school committees should be concerned only with teaching the children and finding funds for the upkeep of the schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0404.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Turovets and Zhukov are men who are just fit for the offices they are holding now. They are non-partisan Russian workmen who think only about the welfare of the schools; they will be able to get the federation out of the blind alley into which it had almost been led. The "opponents" of yesterday will be forced to understand today that there is no more room for "politics" and intriguing politicians in our schools; that now only live Russian educational activities are being conducted there.</p>
   <p>If even in the future the "opponents" continue to manifest the same antagonistic attitude towards the schools, they will only prove thereby that they are not interested at all in the work of the schools if they do not see in this work any opportunities for furthering their own private, selfish interests.</p>
   <p>Now that a non-partisan Russian holds the office of president of the school federation, there can be no talk about certain "tendencies," about "our men," and "your men."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0405.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And if, in spite of all, persons holding partisan views are found in the schools, all we can say is that there should be no place for such persons in the ranks of those who endeavor to enlighten the Russian colony of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Observer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
