<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-11-11">Nov. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Intellectuals and the Colony</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-11-11">Nov. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE INTELLECTUALS AND THE COLONY</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The evening-entertainment arranged by the Federation of Russian schools for children in Chicago and suburbs has been a great moral and financial success. It has demonstrated how much can be achieved when the colony desires to do some real work, especially when the rank and file are willing to cooperate with the intellectuals.</p>
   <p>Until the present time, to our great regret, there have been in the Russian colony (and there still are) certain "intelligent" men in whose opinion every intellectual is a "bourgeois," an "aristocrat," "not one of our kind," etc.</p>
   <p>Such wiseacres made a disorganizing propaganda, fanning the flame of evil passions and telling to the rank and file of the colony: "Do not trust the intellectuals! Keep aloof from them; we shall educate our children ourselves."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0442.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This is what happened as the result of such propaganda: The children learned well how to sing the "Internationale," learned the words "bloody fight" (Note: occurring in the "Varshavyanka" -a socialist revolutionary song popular among the Polish and Russian socialists. D. S.)-this from children!-were taught by a teacher of dancing how to dance like horses, but remained illiterate.</p>
   <p>But now things are different.</p>
   <p>The Federation of schools for children has invited teachers who belong to the intellectuals and know how to teach.</p>
   <p>The Federation does not make "propaganda," but works at the education of the children.</p>
   <p>It has invited an intelligent teacher of dancing, Miss Barashkova, and a teacher of singing, Mr. Serebrennikov.</p>
   <p>As a result of this, the performance of the chorus of the School Federation was the best number on the program of the concert; and the dancing of two <pb facs="5423967_3_0443.jpg" n="3"/>girls, pupils of Miss Barashkova, delighted all the audience.</p>
   <p>Children, who have been taught only a short time ago the modern "popular" dances by an incompetent teacher, now performed their dances on the stage so nicely that one has to wonder how fast progress may be achieved under the tuition of a teacher who is intelligent and competent.</p>
   <p>The chorus of the Federation is really a beautiful blending of voices; every member of the chorus knew exactly what to do, how to sing, and all without exception, led by the conductor, Mr. Serebrennikov, gave to the audience something which it could not have received from the same school children some time ago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Serebrinnikov has performed a miracle with the raw material which he had at hand.</p>
   <p>Such is the result of the cooperation of the Russian workmen's colony with the Russian intellectual workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0444.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We hail the Federation of schools! It deserves our gratitude because it was, perhaps, the first to discover that it could bring much more benefit to the colony by doing some vital and useful work than by cheap politics and 'clamorous' propaganda.</p>
   <p>Is this not true?.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
