<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-08-08">Aug. 8, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Reorganization of Parochial Schools at Wood Street</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0335</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0335.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-08-08">Aug. 8, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">REORGANIZATION OF PAROCHIAL SCHOOLS AT WOOD STREET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The board of directors of St. George Brotherhood jointly with the parochial committee of St. George, held a meeting on Thursday, July 30, at the parochial school, 917 N. Wood St., concerning the reorganization of the parochial school.</p>
   <p>As we know, at the semi-annual meeting of the brotherhood, it had been agreed upon to take all the necessary steps for the reorganization of the parochial school, which lately lost all its significance in the parochial district, despite the fact that it had at its disposal considerable funds.</p>
   <p>The joint meeting, held on July 30, resolved to transfer the parochial school to the brotherhood of St. George, and to take immediate steps to raise its prestige. All the present members, with the exception of two members of the parish, have agreed to the reorganization and have further decided to call, as soon as possible, a special joint meeting of the brotherhood and parish in order to approve the minutes of the meeting <pb facs="5423967_3_0336.jpg" n="2"/>held on July 30.</p>
   <p>In order to carry out the aforesaid decision a special committee consisting of five members, was elected as follows: A. Pasiuk, P. Nagorny, A. Palaichuk, K. Riabchuk and V. Konashevsky (temporary). This committee is empowered to appoint a good teacher, who, would be qualified to teach besides general courses, such subjects as singing, music and dances.</p>
   <p>The brotherhood, on its part, agreed to give $150. for the purchase of school books and supplies.</p>
   <p>Mr. P. Chopko, a member of the committee for schools of R. I. M. A. S., who was present at the joint meeting, made a report on the work conducted by his committee for the reorganization of the schools sponsored by the R. I. M. A. S.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
