<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-07-29">July 29, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Why There Should Be Union between the "Rimas and the "Rmas"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1933-07-29">July 29, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THERE SHOULD BE UNION BETWEEN THE "RIMAS AND THE "RMAS"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A lot has been written about it in Rassviet, a lot has been said about it at both our conventions, and for some reason up to the present time the union has not been accomplished.</p>
   <p>I am not a member of either of the two organizations; however, I regret, that two societies of the same nationality and having the same aims cannot get together, talk matters over, and unite on the common ground of co-operation. What is co-operation?</p>
   <p>Co-operation is a ray of light, without which all life is but darkness. As a fire gives us light and warmth, so co-operation supports all living things upon the earth. Co-operation stands above man, above his personality. All in nature exists and depends upon co-operation.</p>
   <p>This principle should be incorporated as a rule at the beginning of the beginning of the <pb facs="5423967_3_1474.jpg" n="2"/>constitution of our organization.</p>
   <p>But in order to bring about peace and union between the two Russian organizations (Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society and Russian Mutual Aid Society), it is desirable that they first get together, talk matters over, and reach a complete agreement. Only then will they be able to give to each other due credit, become real friends, and accomplish the union according to the principle of justice and fair play. In order, however, to reach complete agreement, both societies should abandon their selfishness and should voluntarily submit to a detailed analysis of their regulations and of the future regulations of the proposed union. After such an operation many of the scarecrows will become just commonplace affairs.</p>
   <p>It is true that neither of the two societies may have its own idol, who to the other seems just a common booby. Every popular name provokes enthusiastic bows in one quarter, while in another it causes much criticism and censure.</p>
   <p>Considering these phenomena it is necessary for the members of both organizations <pb facs="5423967_3_1475.jpg" n="3"/>to remember that constructive criticism has nothing in common with enmity, and that without real, severe criticism it is impossible to accomplish anything wise and productive in the way of co-operation. Much can be attained if the members of both organizations know how to approach their task without prejudice and with the determination to make their work really fruitful.</p>
   <p>Many things have to be decided now by the members of both societies because in the near future it will require many real efforts and some expense to bring the union of both societies to a successful conclusion. In particular, why should the members of the societies hurry in their efforts for the merger? Because of our young people. Our youth, the children of our colony, at present are only our guests. But in the future they will become the hosts; they will receive all from us as a heritage.</p>
   <p>The bringing up of our youth is a great task; their education decides the future fate of mankind. The young people, who want to live, but who do not think and have no time to think about how one should live will take as an <pb facs="5423967_3_1476.jpg" n="4"/>example to be followed the life which we leave them.</p>
   <p>This is why it is necessary for the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society and the Russian Mutual Aid Society to unite, and this is why they should not delay their action.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
