<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Eugene Moravsky</title>, Editor of Daily Rassviet.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0078</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0078.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Eugene Moravsky</title>, Editor of Daily Rassviet.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Rassviet is the only Russian daily in America, outside of New York. It is published by the Russian Publishing Company, Inc., at 1724 W. Chicago Avenue.</p>
   <p>The present owners of Rassviet acquired the property in 1926 from the owner of Russkii Viestnik. In 1917 the Mutual Aid Society, a Russian organization, began to publish the Svobodnaya Rossiya in Chicago. This publication was bought by Mr. Casimir Gugis, a Russian attorney, several years later and edited under the name of Russkii Viestnik up till the middle of May 1926. Mr. Moravsky, who is the editor-in-chief of Rassviet, stated that the paper is non-Communistic and non-partisan in scope. Rassviet is a liberal paper, marching with the trend of times, and politically has remained the same since its foundation. Rassviet can be found on all newspaper stands in Chicago, where the Russian colony <pb facs="5423967_3_0079.jpg" n="2"/>is concentrated, as well as in Detroit, Mich. It is a cooperative organization with its six employees sharing in the profits. The building at 1724 W. Chicago Avenue is rented, but the machinery, the presses and other property is owned by the Russian Publishing Company. Rassviet does not make any distinction between the Orthodox Russian Church in Chicago or any other Russian sect. The policy of Rassviet is non-partisan. It tries to serve to the best of its ability the community in general, particularly the Russian-Americans living in Chicago. It is devoted to the interest of the Russian colony and its organizations. As a permanent institution it spreads culture and refinement among its nationals. In the years of 1931, 1932, 1933 and 1934 the Rassviet, as any other commercial undertaking, has suffered materially from the depression, but, according to Mr. Moravsky, the years of 1935 and 1936 have brought remarkable improment both in its circulation and advertising departments. According <pb facs="5423967_3_0080.jpg" n="3"/>to a sworn statement, the average number of copies of Rassviet sold and distributed through the mails and otherwise during the past six months is close to the 20,000 mark.</p>
   <p>In conjunction with publishing and editing the Rassviet, the Russian Publishing Company operates and maintains a bookstore and library consisting of Russian classical literature as well as present day authors. A lover of Russian literature can always find, to his heart's content, a substantial supply of books in the Russian language at prices which are in line with the ordinary pocketbook. It also maintains a translation department, where Russian is being translated into English and English into Russian. The Rassviet also publishes books in the Russian language whenever the opportunity presents itself, although the latter is very limited.</p>
   <p>Ben Chase.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
