<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Material owned by Dr. Moses Sahud</title>, 549 W. Addison Street
<title level="a">(Letter-Reply of Doctor Sahud to Mr. Noskov)</title><title level="a" type="sub">Political Difficulties in Russian People's University in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0644</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0644.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Material owned by Dr. Moses Sahud</title>, 549 W. Addison Street
<title level="a">(Letter-Reply of Doctor Sahud to Mr. Noskov)</title><title level="a" type="sub">POLITICAL DIFFICULTIES IN RUSSIAN PEOPLE'S UNIVERSITY IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"As a member of the Board, in answering your letter, I shall do my bit towards solving this vital question. I beg you to take it as my personal opinion..... The problem of opening a People's University was first raised by Professor Novakovsky. His profound belief in the necessity of training intelligent workers in all branches of industry and agriculture, so that they might eventually apply their technical achievements to newly-born free Russia, stirred every one in whom the love for Russia is kept alive.</p>
   <p>"At this time the question of Bolshevism, which inflamed entire Russia, reached its peak in the Russian colony of America. Not a single meeting or undertaking would pass without touching in one way or another on the <pb facs="5423967_3_0645.jpg" n="2"/>mighty Russian political question. This invariably brought dissension, which split the colony instead of uniting it..... Yet the spirit of the times is, and always has been, stronger than any groups, however wise, just, and practical their ideas may be..... It will thwart all that is good and useful for the people if the time for a change is ill-chosen, but will add strength to the very same thing when the right moment comes.</p>
   <p>"Had there been only Bolsheviks or Mensheviks, or Cadets, or monarchists at the helm during the school's birth process, its beginning would have been also its end. Fortunately, the people at the helm understood that education must not become involved in party opinions, and so a multicolored political group got together and started to work. Members of the Soviet of the R. P. U., while collaborating in education with persons who were their enemies in politics, found out that, outside of politics, these same persons could be their sincere friends, <pb facs="5423967_3_0646.jpg" n="3"/>Material owned by Dr. Moses Sahud, 549 W. Addison Street.</p>
   <p>real people. And so the monarchists, Cadets, Socialists and working men of all shades started to work all together in order that national education in the Chicago Russian colony may be realized in life.</p>
   <p>"Yet the spirit of the time would not abate. It caused friction...., existed also among the students; and no matter how much we guarded against it, nothing availed, political convictions did enter. However, the spirit which reigned in the school triumphed at last, partisanship without a sufficient reason disappeared; the students remained with a conscious desire to study, and the teachers, even more so, to teach......"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
