<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1931-11-02">Nov. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">At a Kino - Lecture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0790</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0790.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-11-02">Nov. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">AT A KINO - LECTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Kino-lecture was given on Friday, October 30, 1931, on the premises of the Russian-American Citizen Club, and the hall was packed with interested Russian immigrants, who had come from all parts of the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The picture was accompanied by explanations in English, and illustrated the development, step by step, of the daily press industry in the United States, from the felling of trees, from which the paper is produced, to the printing of the daily press.</p>
   <p>The representatives of the Chicago Daily Tribune are very pleased to see that the Russian immigrants are so interested in lectures of this kind. At the end of the lecture the representatives of the "Committee for Enlightenment," of the Russian-American Citizens Club, thanked heartily <pb facs="5423967_3_0791.jpg" n="2"/>the representative of the Chicago Tribune for the lecture, and later made a request to organize an excursion for an evening to the Tribune building for the purpose of acquiring a practical knowledge of the press industry. They have been assured that such an excursion will be welcomed at any time.</p>
   <p>After the departure of the representatives of the Tribune, the members of the Enlightenment-Committee asked those present if they desired to see the various processes of printing a newspaper in the Tribune building. The response to this proposal was great and many of those who were present agreed to enlist. The day and time of the excursion will be announced in the newspapers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
