<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Archimandrite Timon, <title>Under the Shield of Faith</title>, Chicago: St. Michael's Russian Orthodox Church, <date when="1934">1934</date>, pp. 56-60.
<title level="a">Brotherhoods</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1421</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1421.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Archimandrite Timon, <title>Under the Shield of Faith</title>, Chicago: St. Michael's Russian Orthodox Church, <date when="1934">1934</date>, pp. 56-60.
<title level="a">BROTHERHOODS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mutual aid societies in America act as insurance societies and have a following of several tens of thousands of Russian orthodox people. The societies are divided into small units, brotherhoods. These brotherhoods are secular organizations whose aim is to insure their members against injuries, sickness or death, and at the same time these organizations are practical adherents of Christianity in daily life, and their motto is: Feed the hungry, give drink to the thirsty, clothe the naked.</p>
   <p>All these organizations are orthodox, and it is compulsory that their members be members of the church.</p>
   <p>In addition that that all organizations, through their publications, are promoting national unity of the Russian people.</p>
   <p>In Europe, in view of unfavorable historical situations, the Russian <pb facs="5423967_3_1422.jpg" n="2"/>people were divided among various governments (sic).</p>
   <p>These governments had an especially mapped-out program, aimed to divide the Russian people, and within the course of several centuries this program bore its fruit: the sons and daughters of mother Russia have become alien to each other. With such a feeling of dissension and loss of originality, they arrived in America. Thus, the problem of uniting all European Russian immigrants was upon the shoulders of the brotherhoods.</p>
   <p>They have successfully performed their noble enterprise. In exile they have united the Russian people.</p>
   <p>Within every parish, on the strength of their unity and discipline, the brotherhoods play a very important role in the strengthening and uniting as well as the material aid of the parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1423.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Each brotherhood is under the patronage of some saint, and once a year to honor the name of this saint they have a mass during which they memorialize all members who have departed for their permanent resting place.</p>
   <p>According to seniority in organization at the church of St. Michael, there exists the following brotherhoods.</p>
   <p>The Brotherhood of St. Vladimir. This brotherhood was organized in July 1909, and on the 20th of this month has celebrated its 25th jubilee. At this celebration the banner of the brotherhood (the American flag) was consecrated, a mass celebrated at which all departed souls of the brotherhood were memorialized and a banquet was held in the basement of the church.</p>
   <p>At present the brotherhood has sixty-four members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1424.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Brotherhood of St. Michael. This brotherhood was organized December 7, 1913. Hence, the parish of St. Michael was gradually gaining strength during the period of three years. Ninety-six members joined this brotherhood. They all became members of the church.</p>
   <p>In 1933 the brotherhood affiliated with the largest and most influential organization in America, the Union of Russian Orthodox Brotherhoods.</p>
   <p>At present this brotherhood consists of twenty members.</p>
   <p>Brotherhood of St. Cyril and Methodius. This brotherhood was organized May 1, 1916. It is independent, has its charter, and at present consists of fifty members.</p>
   <p>Sisterhood of the Birth of the Most Holy Mother of God. This sisterhood <pb facs="5423967_3_1425.jpg" n="5"/>was organized September 11, 1916, and then joined one of the largest women's organizations in America, the Russian Orthodox Catholic Women's Mutual Aid Society.</p>
   <p>The sisterhood has always answered the call of the church in all its needs. Thus, in the beginning of 1932 when the bank in which church money was deposited was closed and debts had to be met, the sisterhood loaned $300 without interest. At present the sisterhood has sixty members.</p>
   <p>Sisterhood of St. Ann, the Prophetess. This sisterhood was organized December 17, 1917. It is composed of the wives and children of St. Vladimir Brotherhood. At present it has thirty-one members.</p>
   <p>Brotherhood of St. Nikolai. This brotherhood is affiliated with the Russian Orthodox Mutual Aid Society in America. It was organized in <pb facs="5423967_3_1426.jpg" n="6"/>Kellis Island in the state of Ohio. On account of unemployment the Russians have left that place and the brotherhood was transferred to Chicago, Ill. The brotherhood consists of seven members. Ivan Stefanishin is the president, cashier and secretary.</p>
   <p>The Altar Sisterhood of the Mother of God. All men's and women's organizations are primarily concerned about their members. Several zealous workers, members of the St. Michael Church, on May 10, 1932, decided to organize an Altar Sisterhood, with the sole purpose of aiding the church, decorating it, and purchasing all the requisites of the church. In order to accomplish these aims, every sister pays ten cents a month. In addition to that the sisterhood arranges various social affairs. For the brief period of its existence the sisterhood has acquired for the church a sacrificial altar and its decoration, and a renovated Gospel. They also donated $50 for the 25th jubilee of the church, and have contributed towards the purchase of a $100 icon, "The Blessing of Children." The sisterhood consists of thirty-eight members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
