<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-09">Apr. 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">On Minsky Muzhik's Book</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0147</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0147.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-09">Apr. 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">ON MINSKY MUZHIK'S BOOK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For politically minded individuals and those who know what the despotic and bloody Bolshevism is, the writings of Minsky Muzhik do not reveal anything new. They only confirm the statements which have been made during the past seventeen years. But aside from such people, there are others who are still uninformed and can be swayed one way or the other. For such people the book written by Minsky Muzhik is very necessary; it is, in fact, indispensible to those people, as well as to the American public which knows very little about Bolshevik atrocities and the sufferings inflicted on the Russian people. For this reason, this book would be more valuable if it were published in English. It should be published in both Russian and English, and the English version should be published in a larger edition.</p>
   <p>Considering the fact that we do not have to pay any royalty to the author, the book could be sold at a nominal price, which would make it accessible to a wide range of the American people. It should be published in a large edition.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0148.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The cost of publishing this book should be raised among the Russian organizations. The latter must be induced to collect the necessary money either from among their membership or from their own treasuries. Many of the individual readers of the Rassviet will, I am sure, send in their contribution for the purpose of publishing this book. When the book is published, every contributor can redeem the money he has contributed in books, and thus the money he has donated, will be advanced only temporarily, for a good cause. In such a way, the money to publish the book will be raised; and we will be able to ensure its wide distribution.</p>
   <p>I, therefore, recommend that Rassviet appeal to the Russian organizations, as well as to its readers to donate the necessary dollars required to publish the book by Minsky Muzhik, entitled The Truth About Russia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
