<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1928-12-18">December 18, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Debate about the Recognition of Soviet Russia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0851</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0851.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1928-12-18">December 18, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">DEBATE ABOUT THE RECOGNITION OF SOVIET RUSSIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On December 16, 1928, a debate about the recognition of Soviet Russia took place. The debate was arranged by the Rassviet Society. The hall was very crowded and many of the people could not find any place. One of the orators, Dr. Pertsov, in his speech tried to prove the necessity of the recognition of Soviet Russia. He read an indictment against the Bolsheviks, pointing out the many crimes committed by them. He called the Bolsheviks Jesuits and followers of Machiavelli. He came to the following conclusion: the recognition of Soviet Russia must be obtained in order that the Russian immigrants could return to Russia and play there a decisive role in the fight of the Russian people with the Bolsheviks. Mr. Moravsky, who spoke against the recognition of Soviet Russia, pointed out all the inconsistencies of the arguments of Dr. Pertsov: first, that there is nothing to gain by imitating the <pb facs="5423967_3_0852.jpg" n="2"/>Bolshevik tactics; secondly, that even if the Bolsheviks would be recognized, the return of Russians to Russia would be not permitted because of the decree of the Soviet Union that any citizen who had not registered before a certain date loses his citizenship. Even if Soviet Russia will not be recognized by the United States, the Soviet government will certainly admit to Russia emigrants who want to be repatriated. But the Soviets will admit only Russian Bolsheviks and their sympathizers, as it is being done at the present time.</p>
   <p>Though many Bolsheviks and sympathizers were present at the discussion, the audience was against the recognition of Soviet Russia. This could be seen from the applause given the opponents and also from the discussion in which took part Mr. Ilyin V. Khomich, Doctor Chapman, who were for the recognition of the Soviet Union, and Mr. Yusefovich, Mr. Senkevich, and Mr. E. Duvan, who spoke against the recognition.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0853.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In spite of the rainy weather, many of the people arrived from such places as Gary, Ind.; Pullman, Ill.; Kenosha, and many other towns. The debate lasted nearly five hours. Mr. R. Rozhin was chairman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
