<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. J. J. Voronko</title>, 2009 Cortez St., Dir. Russian Radio Programs, Stations Wedc and Wsbc.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0086</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0086.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. J. J. Voronko</title>, 2009 Cortez St., Dir. Russian Radio Programs, Stations WEDC and WSBC.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Voronko a White-Russian was born in the state of Grodno and was reared and educated in St. Petersburg (present Leningrad.) He came to the United States in the Fall of 1923 and has resided with his family in Chicago since then. Mr. Voronko came to America for the sole purpose of lecturing among the White Russians. At that time nationalism started to play a very big part among the White Russians, especially among those in America, and for that reason Mr. Voronko began upon his arrival to lecture among the White-Russians in Chicago as well as in the states of Wisconsin and Michigan. As a fiery White-Russian he has tried to awaken their national pride and to bring them out from that sleep in which he found them. Mr. Voronko admits that he met with little success due to the geographical and  ehtnographical ignorance of his countrymen. Finding Bolshevism among them he was hampered in his undertaking. In the opinion of Mr. Voronko they were not Bolshevists but Bolshevist-maniacs (sic.)</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0087.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Mr. Voronko's opinion there is no pure Russian colony in Chicago. According to his version only five percent are genuine Russians (Great Russians) the rest are connected with Russian more through love of the Russian culture than anything else. The Russian colony in Chicago is composed largely of White-Russians from the States of Grodnio, Minsk, Vilno, Vitevsk, and Mogilev; next are Ukranians from the States of Volin, Podolia, Kiev and the southern part of Grodno and the west part of Chevnigov.</p>
   <p>Incidentally, Mr. Voronko thinks that the White-Russian is obligated to the Jew who has been most influential in his emigration to the United States. As an example he relates the following: A Jew persecuted by the Russian government emigrated to America. A year later he begins to send money to his family. A White-Russian, his next-door neighbor, finds out all about it. He thinks to him that the golden land is a better place for the peasant, both politically and economically, the result is Russian emigration to America.</p>
   <p>As stated Mr. Voronko upon his arrival in the United States began to <pb facs="5423967_3_0088.jpg" n="3"/>lecture in October, 1923 about the White-Russian National Movement among his countrymen in Chicago. He has tried but in vain to unite them and awaken in them their national pride and self-respect. Coupled with that he has met opposition from a number of Russian churchmen who are opposed to the enlightment of their countrymen. Having retained the religious spirit of the times of the Tzar they remained even in America patriots of the old school as such were opposed to his undertakings. Finding such difficulties he made up his mind to change the field of his activities.</p>
   <p>He started to open schools for children and Russian laboring men who did not know the Russian language. On the north side of Chicago and in Benton Harbor, Michigan he opened seven schools and at present is still conducting such a school in Pullman.</p>
   <p>In January, 1924 he became associated with the then Russian Vestnik <pb facs="5423967_3_0089.jpg" n="4"/>a Russian daily. When the latter was sold to the present owners of Rassviet he became connected with the Rassviet. In 1927 he edited the monthly "Belorusskaia Tribuna." This paper was edited irregularly, As a professional journalist, he also edited the journal Russian Review for a short time. During the years of 1928 and 1929 he edited the weekly Vestnik. In 1929 Mr. Voronko published the Russian Almanac.</p>
   <p>Mr. Voronko claims the distinction of being the editor of the first Ukranian weekly in Chicago, Ukrania in the Little Russian language.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
