<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-07">Mar. 7, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">St. George's Brotherhood</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1151</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1151.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-07">Mar. 7, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">ST. GEORGE'S BROTHERHOOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On February 29 the regular meeting of the executive committee of St. George's Brotherhood (Branch Number One of R.I.M.A.S.) was held with fifteen members present. The committee discussed several questions and heard reports submitted by subcommittees and by officers of the Brotherhood. The program of future work was planned. For the board of directors of R.I.M.A.S. N. Kozak, the general secretary, made a report and explained in detail the advantages of the organization's new [insurance] policies. On the same subject but even in more detail Mr. G. Volos also spoke. It took him an hour and forty-five minutes to enlighten the members on the meaning of the new policies and to supply them with the necessary information. He dwelt a great deal on the benefits that will be enjoyed by those members of the Society who carry the new form of insurance. Since he is secretary of the Brotherhood, he touched upon the practical ways of introducing the new policies into our organization.</p>
   <p>The committee decided to start a new campaign for enlisting new members in the <pb facs="5423967_3_1152.jpg" n="2"/>organization and for widening the scope of cultural and educational work. It was also decided to concentrate particularly on the enrollment of children and young people in their respective branches. On the whole the meeting was conducted in a businesslike way, for it was obvious that all the members of the executive committee take a very lively interest in the affairs of their own Brotherhood, which is by far the largest single branch of R.I.M.A.S.and the strongest. As a matter of fact, this Brotherhood is the original nucleus around which in the course of years the Society has grown to be one of the largest Russian mutual-aid organizations in the United States and Canada.</p>
   <p>Next year the Brotherhood will celebrate its twenty-five-year jubilee. The members enjoy certain definite advantages, and it therefore pays to belong to this solid organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
