<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-04">Jan. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">During the New Year</title><title level="a" type="sub">by N. Komiakov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-04">Jan. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">DURING THE NEW YEAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">by N. Komiakov</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The old year has gone. A new year is here. Time moves on, and we, the living, move onward, together with time. Our movement is determined by the direction in which we are going, and our goal. Striving to get ahead is, in itself, movement--movement toward something new. To strive for something new means that we are not satisfied with the old. In our social work, which has been based on mutual aid and the improvement of the welfare of our organization, its membership as a whole, and each of us individually, all efforts should be directed toward the goal of finishing the unfinished work, and achieving the desired goals during this year--for the improvement of our organization and for the benefit of each one of us individually. We have joined an organization for the sole purpose of helping one another, and by our joint efforts, of carrying out beneficial work in the interests of us all.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1419.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the last year we were not asleep despite the baneful influence of the depression, for we have started new and important enterprises. One such undertaking is the purchase of the communal farm. Another is the publication of our official magazine, The Herald. If the first enterprise is purely of a practical nature, in the economic interests of our members--so that they can enjoy their rest during the vacation periods--then the second--the publication of the magazine Herald--is a step toward satisfying and enriching our spiritual well-being. By means of our periodical, we shall be able to increase the mutual understanding among our members concerning all the problems which are constantly posed by[the realities of] life. With the help of the periodical, we shall know better where to go and what to do in order that each of us personally and collectively, united in organizations, can prosper and develop.</p>
   <p>Our energies must not remain dormant this year, particularly in the sphere of our civic endeavor. To stop half-way for us is impossible because it would mean that we had lost courage, and that we had neither the strength <pb facs="5423967_3_1420.jpg" n="3"/>nor the desire to go forward. We have not yet finished all the improvements we plan to make on our farm. This should be done this year, whatever the cost may be. For this purpose, each one of us who has not contributed his share, must do it now because it is a communal effort for the benefit of us all. The beginning of the new year is important for us because it forces us to take a look backward, and to think of the future--to consider what was done and what is to be done. But in order to accomplish anything, we must act and we must be practical. We issue a call to action and joint effort in this editorial addressed to all members of Roova[Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
