<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview Regarding Michael Borodin and the Berg Preparatory School with Dr. Henry Krasnow</title>, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago.
<title level="a">By Ben Chase</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0999</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0999.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview Regarding Michael Borodin and the Berg Preparatory School with Dr. Henry Krasnow</title>, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago.
<title level="a">By Ben Chase</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Michael Borodin, whose name in Russia was Grusenberg, left that country immediately after the revolution in 1905, and emigrated to London. He had been a student and had suffered the hardships and privations of the Jewish intellectual in old Russia. After a brief stay in England he came to Boston. In Boston Mr. Grusenberg, now known as Berg, resided for a while and from there went to Valparaiso, Ind., where he attended the University of Valparaiso. It was at this school that he met Dr. Krasnow. In a short time he became a leader among the Russians in this section of the country, and joined a number of organizations. He visited Chicago from time to time, giving lectures, and tutoring. He finally settled in Chicago in March 1909.</p>
   <p>Dr. Krasnow describes Mr. Berg as a young man of winning personality, already showing that ability to lead which was later to make him <pb facs="5423967_3_1000.jpg" n="2"/>world famous. He was not much of a talker, speaking only infrequently (people who knew him in China in later years have remarked on this characteristic). As soon as he had established a residence in Chicago, Berg decided to open a school where immigrants might learn English and get the rudiments of an education. Hull House supplied one room and he began with four pupils.</p>
   <p>In September, 1909, Mr. Berg and Dr. Kranow opened another school at Roosevelt Road and Newberry Avenue. The new school was housed in an eight-room flat. The student body had in this short time grown to forty, all immigrants, and predominantly Russian. Classes met three times a week; tuition was $2 per subject. The school had both elementary and higher sections, and was accredited. Most of the students were working and could pay a little. As a result the school treasury was never very full, and often empty. During the years 1910-1912 there were many strikes in Chicago which cut into the workers' incomes. Of <pb facs="5423967_3_1001.jpg" n="3"/>the one hundred and thirty students at the Berg School only forty were able to pay any tuition. However, those unable to pay were not turned away on that account. After three years at Roosevelt Road and Newberry Avenue, the Berg Preparatory School moved to Division Street and Hoyne Avenue, in the center of the Russian colony. Its financial condition improved; better equipment was secured, and more space rented.</p>
   <p>Several of those associated with Mr. Berg have attained prominence in scientific and academic work. One of these was Professor Kennedy, at one time of the Department of Economics at the University of Chicago. Still another, Mr. Karp, head of the School of Social Service, New York City. Alderman W. E. Rodriguez at one time taught for Mr. Berg.</p>
   <p>After the February revolution, the Russian Provisional government dispatched a so-called Kerensky Commission to the United States. Mr. Berg was chairman of the committee organized to welcome the commission to <pb facs="5423967_3_1002.jpg" n="4"/>Chicago. Here he met Mr. Lomonosov, one of its members, and decided to return to take part in the revolutionary developments.</p>
   <p>During his residence in America Mr. Berg was not a strict party man, but rather was interested in all phases of the Russian revolutionary movement.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
