<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-20">Apr. 20, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">An Answer to the Joke</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1116</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1116.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-20">Apr. 20, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">AN ANSWER TO THE JOKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On March 28 appeared in the pages of the News and of Rassviet a jocular item about N. Kozak, general secretary of R.I.M.A.S., which told us that Mr. Kozak sits in his office, poor soul, and wonders what he shall do with the money that R.I.M.A.S. has piled up in the banks. My opinion is that if Mr. Kozak succeeds in lending all the Society's money to its members under good mortgage security, that will be well and good, but if some money is still left over, I can suggest several ways to dispose of it. I know clients to whom hundreds of thousands of dollars can be lent with perfect security and for a good cause.</p>
   <p>On Division Street there is a so-called co-operative restaurant conducted by the half-baked Russian Bolsheviks of Chicago. The Russian colonists have already invested in the place almost eleven thousand dollars of their hard-earned money. I have heard it said that the enterprise still needs funds and is ready to borrow at least to the extent of twenty thousand dollars if some one can be found who has the money and is foolish enough to throw it away.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1117.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The other place for investment is the Ukrainian People's Home. In that building the Russian colonists have sunk not less than twenty thousand dollars. One Russian women's society lent to the Ukrainian Bolsheviks fourteen hundred dollars and has forgotten since then what the money looked like.</p>
   <p>The third good prospect is Novy Mir, the Russian Bolshevik paper in New York. Mr. Kozak quite properly may approach the editor of that journal, and what remains of his money may to very good advantage be consumed by "comrades" in New York. Last year they put over two collections (one more than the parsons take) and succeeded in trimming their sucker readers to the tune of twenty grand. We hear that the newspaper is again ready to close up shop. We think that Mr. Kozak can save the situation if he does not care about saving his skin and is tired of his job with R.I.M.A.S.</p>
   <p>Z.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
