<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-19">Mar. 19, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A Lecture at the Independents'</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0782</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0782.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-19">Mar. 19, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A LECTURE AT THE INDEPENDENTS'</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The War Spirit in Europe" was the topic of a lecture given recently in the Russian National School building, 927 North Wood Street. The lecturer, Mr. Victor Niedzielnitzky, who arrived recently in this country from Europe, began his interesting two-hour lecture by reading a number of excerpts from European newspapers and magazines, revealing the feverish preparations for the impending war. During his lecture the speaker said that Hitler in his talk before a large Nazi gathering had declared that Germany had been so squeezed on all sides that it was absolutely necessary to widen its territory, and widen it not only to the west, where they would be opposed by two of the mightiest powers, England and France, but also to the east, where the uncivilized Slavs could easily be crushed and utilized as manure for the expansion of German territory and the great German "kultur". In the opinion of Mr. Niedzielnitzky Hitler will try not only to conquer the Ukraine, but also Caucasia and all of Asia as far as Persia. <pb facs="5423967_3_0783.jpg" n="2"/>the lecturer, with the aid of slides, described to the audience the large territories of Manchuria now in Japanese hands and formerly a province of Russia. Mr. Niedzielnitzky stated that Manchuria should go back to Russia because czars of Russia spent many millions of rubles building railroads, houses, hotels and other improvements.</p>
   <p>The writer of this article does not agree with the views held by the lecturer in respect to Manchuria. This writer maintains that Manchuria should not belong either to Japan or Russia, but should be given back to China, its rightful owner, from whom it was sold out to Russia by two treacherous Chinese warlords, who paid with their heads for their treason.</p>
   <p>Continuing his lecture, Mr. Niedzielnitzky showed moving pictures of the red army, fully equipped and fully armed, stationed on the border of Manchuria and waiting for the signal from Moscow to start marching into Manchuria. New Russian tanks and other modern armaments to be used against Japan were also shown on the screen.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0784.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During the second part of the program Mr. Niedzielnitzky exhibited some pictures of the old buildings in Moscow and in Leningrad, following which he showed the latest modern structures erected by the Soviets in various parts of the Soviet Republic, some of which, in the words of the lecturer, are as tall and as modern as the New York skyscrapers. The lecturer also showed a number of pictures of the Russian peasant girls in the new Russia. These girls appeared to be well fed and well clad, silk kercheifs on their heads, and colorful patterned aprons on their clean, white skirts.</p>
   <p>This writer was struck and astonished by these last pictures. They contradicted what we here in America know about the conditions in Russia. We read in the letters received from our relatives in Russia that people are dying like flies from starvation, and here we see them on the pictures well fed and happy. This leads this writer to believe that there must be a lie hidden somewhere. The question now arises: whom should we believe--the pictures of the lecturer or our relatives in Russia? It is possible that some of the members of the Independent Society may be inclined to think, <pb facs="5423967_3_0785.jpg" n="4"/>after seeing these fine-looking Russian girls on the screen, that there is no hunger in Russia. But I am disposed to think that perhaps Mr. Niedzielnitzky thought that his lecture would not be attended by the Independents but by the Bolsheviks. Or perhaps he might have thought that we had been serfs for such a long time that we would not be able to understand his lecture anyway...</p>
   <p>Here we see an example of how some of our Russian intellectuals living outside of Russia are currying favors from the Red lords by trying to fool and benumb the Russian peasants living in America. They are ready to burn truth and justice at the stake in order to satisfy the Moscow Reds.</p>
   <p>These are my impressions of the lecture given by Mr. Victor Niedzielnitzky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
