<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Minutes of the 26th Supreme Assembly of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society</title> Which Convened on
<date when="1937-09-06">September 4. 5, 6, 1937</date>
in the Auditorium at 917 Wood Street, Chicago, Illinois.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1044</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1044.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Minutes of the 26th Supreme Assembly of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society</title> Which Convened on
<date when="1937-09-06">September 4. 5, 6, 1937</date>
in the Auditorium at 917 Wood Street, Chicago, Illinois.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first session of the 26th Supreme Assembly of Rimas was held on Saturday, September 4, 1937 at 5 P. M.</p>
   <p>Dr. P. H. Chadovich, vice-president of the Society, opened the Assembly with a brief welcome address, promptly at 5 P. M.</p>
   <p>Roll Call.</p>
   <p>Fifty delegates were present.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of Ballot Tellers</p>
   <p>The following were elected: Mr. Kichkaylo, Mr. Jogalsky, F. Syman, and A. Shuran.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1045.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Election of Committee on Credentials.</p>
   <p>The mandates of all the delegates were in order.</p>
   <p>Election of Sentries.</p>
   <p>J. Baturevich and N. Kozlovsky were elected sentries.</p>
   <p>Nomination and Election of the Presiding Body of Officers of The 26th Assembly.</p>
   <p>The following were elected:</p>
   <p>John F. Erin, chairman; J. Mikhalchik, vice-chairman; A. Haponovich, senior clerk; Mrs. Zinovia Leschuk, junior clerk.</p>
   <p>Election of Grievance Board, Audit Committee,</p>
   <p>And Resolution Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1046.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Minutes of the 26th Supreme Assembly</p>
   <p>The following were elected: Z. Stoliarenia, S. Bakaletz, G. Veremiuk, P. Ushko, and W. Sabinsky.</p>
   <p>Dr. P. H. Chadovich announced the results of the election and turned the assembly over to the elected presiding body.</p>
   <p>Agenda Of The Supreme Assembly.</p>
   <p>J. Erin, assuming his place as chairman of the assembly, thanked the assembly for the honor bestowed upon him and requested the delegates to be attentive to the business before the assembly so that their decisions on important matters set up by the Board of Directors may be successful.</p>
   <p>Tribute to the deceased members of the Society was paid by one minute of silence by the delegates, while the names of the late members were read by the clerk of the assembly.</p>
   <p>Reading of Communications.</p>
   <p>Messages from organizations and individuals were read.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1047.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Minutes of The 26th Supreme Assembly</p>
   <p>Reading of the Minutes.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the 25th supreme assembly were read and approved without correction.</p>
   <p>Reading of the Financial Report.</p>
   <p>For the year 1936, the net receipts were $28,201.15; disbursements were $14,225.43; net profit was $13,945.72. The capital of Rimas for 1936 was $102,426.71.</p>
   <p>For the seven months period of 1937 the net receipts were $17,030.26; disbursements $10,155.95; net profit for the period was $6,874.34. The capital of the Society, as of July 31, 1937, was $109,301.05.</p>
   <p>The financial report was confirmed by the committee of audit and it was unanimously accepted by the Assembly.</p>
   <p>Report of the Executive Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1048.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Vice-president Dr. P. H. Chadovich reported that, having received no instructions from the supreme president, Geo. Wallace, it will be necessary to await the arrival of Mr. Wallace.</p>
   <p>Financial secretary, N. Kozak, reported that the work of the secretary is complicated. Much time was spent on keeping the books and on minor office duties, so that, little time was left for organization work. Since it is difficult for one man to perform such work as has to be done at one time Mr. Kozak accomplished as much as possible. During the year there were 1532 members in the Society. The supreme treasurer of the Society, J. Sleznik reported at what banks the funds of the Society are kept.</p>
   <p>The report of the executive committee was taken into consideration, while it was decided to await the report of the supreme president upon his arrival.</p>
   <p>Report of the Organizing Committee.</p>
   <p>J. Erin reported that he had delivered speeches on eight occasions and had given reports on the entire work of the organizing committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1049.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Results were good although attempts to organize new branches were unsuccessful. Other members spoke briefly.</p>
   <p>School Committee.</p>
   <p>Anton Bernov reported that there were more schools formerly, because more attention was devoted to them. Conditions are different now. The interest of parents is on the wane, and the schools are fewer in number.</p>
   <p>Other members of the committee reported also that conditions were not favor-able for the schools since interest was lacking.</p>
   <p>Cultural Committee.</p>
   <p>J. Osipik reported that the committee was unable to do much, since members of this committee were not in accord. One important function was held, the commemoration of the anniversary of the death of the celebrated Russian poet, Pushkin.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1050.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The Committee is now making preparations for the celebration of the Day of Russian Culture, with all the Russian organizations participating. The committee is working zealously. This report was taken into consideration.</p>
   <p>Report of the Editor of the Jubilee Journal of Rimas.</p>
   <p>Dr. L. G. Pertzov praised the efforts of the Society which has already reached its 25th year of existence. His speech was loudly applauded.</p>
   <p>The first session of the 26th supreme assembly adjourned on Saturday, September 4, 1937, at 11:00 P.M.</p>
   <p>The second session was announeed for Sunday, September 5, 1937, at 10:00A.M.</p>
   <p>The second session of the 26th supreme assembly of Rimas convened Sunday, September 5, 1937, at 11:00 A. M.</p>
   <p>Roll Call.</p>
   <p>There was a quorum present.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1051.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Report of the Supreme President.</p>
   <p>G. Wallace, supreme president of the society, reported that during 11/2 years there was in progress a revision of policies which greatly affected the membership. The organization suffered from the agitation carried on among the members. The membership is now again normal. The board of directors has spent much energy, but the benefits are small. The board of directors cannot do anything alone - it must be supported by the members, and it can only instruct the branches. Each member must do his share of leading the people into the Society. It is the duty of the members to strengthen it.</p>
   <p>Report of the Editing Committee.</p>
   <p>J. Erin acknowledged the importance of the press, and its value in organization work. He appealed to the branches to assist in this work, by submitting interesting material for the pages of Rimas. The mind of one man cannot be a constant source of supplying material.</p>
   <p>Report of the Branches of Rimas.</p>
   <p>Branch 1. Delegate P. Ushko reported 430 members and 2 youth groups, one of which works independently. There is $8,323.68 in the treasury; 25 new <pb facs="5423967_3_1052.jpg" n="9"/>members were admitted during the year. Delegate of branch 1, W. Olesink, appealed to the other branches to follow suit, by paying the sickness insurance to the supreme treasurer; he also stated that branch 1 had approved a recommendation to pay 1% of every dollar paid into the Society, for the creation of a special fund, to be used for organizational and educational work in attracting our youth to our ranks. He appealed to the branches that if they should favor the recommendation as a beneficial one, and will support branch 1, the fund will increase and the Society will be enlarged by new members. The delegates reported that they are not empowered to vote on such matters, and did not agree with the decisions of branch 1. They stated that, as yet, the branches did not comprehend the full benefit of the organization, and resolved to carry on the work locally to attract youth to enlarge their ranks.</p>
   <p>Branch 2. Delegate Ivan Stalko reported that for 1 1/2 years there was discord in this branch. There are 40 members, and $1,167.90 in the treasury.</p>
   <p>Branch 3. (Women's Branch). Delegate Maria Putzeiko reported 219 members in the branch and $5,288.48 in the treasury.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1053.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Organizing work is slow. Since 1930 much improvement has been shown. The 1936 revision effected the loss of many members. Efforts are being made to enroll new members.</p>
   <p>Branch 5. Delegate Dreichin reported 41 members in the branch and $1,500 in the treasury. There are no young members in this branch.</p>
   <p>Branch 7. Delegate John Skolink reported 62 members in the branch and $1,568.39 in the treasury. The branch has both men and women. They find it difficult to obtain young members. The branch supports 2 orphans donates $15 yearly to them. There is no school and no library in the branch.</p>
   <p>Branch 10. Delegate Tatiana Yushchuk reported 29 members in the branch and $929.32 in the treasury.</p>
   <p>Branch 14: Delegate D. Shablink reported 100 members in the branch, both men and women, and three minors. There is $893.19 in the treasury. All members carry the new form of insurance. The only disadvantage in this branch is its lack of own quarters.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1054.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>Branch 15. Delegate F. Vinnik reported 38 members in the branch and $230 in the treasury. They find it difficult to attract new members.</p>
   <p>Branch 17. Delegate Anton Karpuk reported 26 members in the branch and $350 in the treasury. There is a young group numbering 15 members.</p>
   <p>Branch 18. Delegate Z. Stoliarenia reported 60 members in the branch and $400 in the treasury. The branch is active. There were two schools, a school of dancing, and a schools of languages, but unfortunately both were closed. In the future the schools will be given support, in the event they should reopen.</p>
   <p>Delegate J. Osipik said old scores will be forgotten and the work will progress so that the schools might exist.</p>
   <p>Branch 24. Delegate J. Vaskovsky reported that the branch is newly formed. There are 43 members, and $230.00 in the treasury. The branch gives two affairs annually.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1055.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Branch 25. Delegate G. Piskun reported 33 members in the branch; twenty-one carrying insurance and twelve with sickness benefit only. The branch is in need of advisers to inform as to what action should be taken in regard to the latter members. There is $1,400 in the treasury. A request has been made to place the matter of the twelve members in the agenda.</p>
   <p>Branch 26. Delegate J. Yakucenia reported fifteen members in the branch and $11.33 in the treasurty. The group is small, and tries to do all it can for the organization. It supported a school once but found it difficult to continue doing so.</p>
   <p>Branch 28. Delegate D. Ogorodnik reported 66 members in the bramch and $546.80 in the treasury. There are two clubs - a Women's Club and a Youth's Club.</p>
   <p>Report of N. Kozak, supreme secretary.</p>
   <p>N. Kozak reported that the twelve members of branch 25 who pay for the sickness benefit only can have no connection with the Society, and have no right to use the Society's seal for their purpose.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1056.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>After some discussions the assembly appointed a new board of directors to settle this matter.</p>
   <p>Address by the Guests.</p>
   <p>A. Denisov and Mr. Kipen of Detroit addressed the Assembly and recommended consolidation with other Russian societies on a nationalistic basis. After an intermission for dinner the following business was transacted.</p>
   <p>Schools of Rimas.</p>
   <p>The question of schools is referred to each branch. The branch should encourage schools with administration's aid.</p>
   <p>Youth.</p>
   <p>The matter of youth is associated with the question of schools, and it is therefore also referred to each branch for decisions, with the recommendation that all members of Rimas have their children enrolled in the branch and inculcate in them the love for all things Russian.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1057.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>On Sunday, September 5, 1937, in the afternoon, all delegates were invited to attend the banquet in celebration of the occasion.</p>
   <p>The Third Session Of The 26th Supreme Assembly convened on Monday, September 6, 1937, at 11 o'clock in the morning.</p>
   <p>Recommendations were made to send greetings to the convention of the Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society of America, and Associated Clubs of Russian youth in Milwaukee, Wis.</p>
   <p>Recommendations were also made to appeal to the Secretary of State Cordell Hall for aid for the Russian people in the Far East.</p>
   <p>Re: Consolidation with Russian Organizations of Mutual Aid.</p>
   <p>Minutes of the meetings held December 1 and 13, 1936, in Philadelphia, and November 14, 1937, in Pittsburgh. Both minutes were approved unanimously. The assembly entrusted the board of directors to conduct negotiations for consolidation with all Russian organizations, at all events with not less than three.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1058.jpg" n="15"/>
   <p>Administration Fund of the Society.</p>
   <p>The administration fund is accepted on the same basis as previously, with the recommendation that if necessary, the administration has the right to appeal for an assessment to be collectable at one time, in the amount deemed necessary.</p>
   <p>Salaries of the Executive Committee for 1937-1938.</p>
   <p>The salaries shall remain as per. period 1937-1938.</p>
   <p>Election of Officers for 1937-1938.</p>
   <p>Inasmuch as both the supreme president, G. Wallace and the supreme secretary, N. Kozak, declined re-election, it was necessary to elect new officers in their stead. The following were elected: Dr. P. H. Chadovich, supreme president of Rimas was elected by 39 votes, salary $80 per year. Supreme vice-president, J. Osipik received 26 votes: no salary. Supreme secretary, J. F. Erin elected by 27 votes; salary $100 per month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1059.jpg" n="16"/>
   <p>Assistant supreme secretary, D. Vorobey; no salary.</p>
   <p>Supreme treasurer, Joseph Sleznik, unanimously re-elected; salary $80 per year. Assistant treasurer Mrs. Z. Leschuk, unanimously elected; no salary. Supreme recording secretary, Andrew Haponovich, unanimously reelected; salary $25 per year.</p>
   <p>The following were elected as members of the board of directors: J. Vaskovsky, W. Sabinsky, W. Olesink, G. Wallace, A. Lobchuk, G.Kichkailo, S. Bakaletz, J. Piskun, J. Baturevich, J. Stanko, D. Jogalsky, Mrs. Maria Putzeiko, A. Shuran, and N. Poshvenchuk. Alternates: J. Kuriga, N. Kozlovsky and J. Semenchuk.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. J. Nedzelnitzky (Nedzel) was unanimously re-elected supreme physician of the Society.</p>
   <p>Mr. K. P. Gugis re-elected counselor of the Society.</p>
   <p>Re: Amendments to By-Laws and Corrections.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1060.jpg" n="17"/>
   <p>N. Kozak, supreme secretary, reported that in connection with the new forms of insurance new by-laws must be issued, but if consolidation is successful in the near future, it will be unnecessary to create additional printing expense. He recommended for the board of directors to print the by-laws if the consolidation failed to materialize.</p>
   <p>Designation of Next (the 27th) Supreme Assembly</p>
   <p>It was resolved by a majority of votes, to hold the 27th supreme assembly on the next succeeding Labor Day, in the Auditorium, at 917 N. Wood St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>New Recommendations.</p>
   <p>The supreme assembly entrusted the new administration, with the task of organizing functions for youth, with the cooperation of other branches. Likewise the Board is entrusted with the honoring of former supreme secretary, N. Kozak.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1061.jpg" n="18"/>
   <p>Requests</p>
   <p>Delegates of branch 1 requested that supervision over sick members be paid from the funds of the Society. This matter was referred to the board of directors.</p>
   <p>The 26th supreme assembly, upon motion duly made, seconded and carried, was adjourned on Monday, September 6, 1937, at 5 o'clock in the afternoon, promptly.</p>
   <p>John F. Erin, chairman of the supreme assembly.</p>
   <p>Andrew Haponovich, senior clerk of the supreme assembly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
