<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-17">Mar. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The St. George Fraternity Gives a Lecture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0786</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0786.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-17">Mar. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE ST. GEORGE FRATERNITY GIVES A LECTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Conquering the Air by Man" was the title of a lecture given Sunday, March 11, in the Russian National School building at 917 North Wood Street, under the auspices of the St. George Fraternity (Branch No. 1 of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society). Mr. P. Homko, Russian air force pilot at the time of the World War, was the lecturer.</p>
   <p>He gave in detail the history of the development of the airplane and of aviation from the time there first appeared the desire in man's mind to be king of the air to the present day of highly developed air transportation and military aviation. The lecture lasted over two hours, and was profusely illustrated by slides.</p>
   <p>It was very noticable that the audience was extremely interested in the lecture, since it followed closely the lecturer as he demonstrated on the screen old and new airplane models.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0787.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Let us hope that these popular lectures, now regularly arranged by Branch No. 1 of the R.I.M.A.S., will greatly help our people to increase, and systematize their general knowledge, and at the same time stimulate their interest in education. It is to be regretted that our intelligentsia are so reluctant to spread among the common people the knowledge and learning they possess. By their disinterest and abstention from participation in our public life our intellectuals make it possible for various politicians and adventurers to draw our people into their holes, thus beclouding their insufficiently enlightened minds with deceitful ideas and promises.</p>
   <p>There are many subjects in the field of popular science which could be used by our lecturers to good advantage for popular lectures. Our people crave such lectures.</p>
   <p>It is desirable that other branches of our Society follow the example set by Branch No. 1, and organize a series of popular lectures for their members as well as for non-members. All our activity is directed to one goal--progress, the progress of our organization and also of each individual member. In this <pb facs="5423967_3_0788.jpg" n="3"/>way we shall serve as a model for all Russian activity of this sort in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
