<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1929-04-02">April 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">V. Chernov in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0846</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0846.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1929-04-02">April 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">V. CHERNOV IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, March 31, 1929, there cane from New York the well-known leader of the party of Russian Social-Revolutionists, Mr. V. M. Chernov.</p>
   <p>In spite of the very bad weather,-the rain was coming down in sheets, -there had gathered in the depot a considerable crowd of people who wanted to greet Mr. Chernov. Representatives of various currents of thought started immediately to ask Mr. Chernov questions, and he answered them in a very lucid and exhaustive way.</p>
   <p>At the same tine a photographer was busy trying to get a good snap-shot of Mr. Chernov.</p>
   <p>The representatives of the American press asked Mr. Chernov some very interesting questions about important matters concerning the present situation in Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0847.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Chernov gave several very instructive lectures, illustrated by pictures projected on a screen. In these lectures he gave a very complete review of the chief events that have occurred in Russia since the revolution had begun, and of the evolution of the social and economic life of Russia during the ten first years following the revolution.</p>
   <p>The first lecture was given at the Amalgamated Center on April 7, at 2 P. M. The theme was: "The Present Situation in Soviet Russia and the Prospects of the Future."</p>
   <p>Towards 3 P. M. the public filled the large hall which can hold over two thousand persons. When Mr. Chernov appeared on the stage the public gave him a rousing ovation. He was greeted by representatives of various Socialist organizations; among them were some Ukrainians and White Ruthenians. There proved also to be in the hall a small group of Bolsheviki <pb facs="5423967_3_0848.jpg" n="3"/>who had come in order to interfere with the lecture by causing some disturbance. When Mr. Chernov started to talk they became noisy. But a police inspector rebuked these troublesome Bolsheviki and spoke to them as follows: "The American constitution guarantees freedom of speech, so that anybody can express his opinions, even though these views may not please us. You can express your objections to such views in a peaceful, lawful way, but have no right to cause disturbances. If you will not keep quiet and continue to make trouble during the lecture, I shall be forced to remove you from the hall."</p>
   <p>But the Bolsheviki did not obey the request of the police inspector, and when Mr. Chernov started to speak again they began to shout at him. The police lost patience and removed from the hall six of the most troublesome and noisy Bolsheviki. After that there were no more disturbances during, the lecture.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0849.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. V. N. Chernov conquered the hearts of the audience by his inspiring and poetical speech. His exposition of his theme contained much valuable information and was masterly as to its form. He spoke for two hours, and the audience listened to this long lecture with the greatest attention. Even those of the Bolshevik; who had remained in the hall listened most attentively, forgetting about the intended protests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
