<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-07-30">July 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Who Snculd </title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0406</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0406.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-07-30">July 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">WHO SNCULD <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the sessions of the third <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the Russian School Federation of the city of Chicago it has become obvicus that even the delegates belonging to the extreme left demand the elimination from the schools of all politics and political intrigues.</p>
   <p>"We do not want to teach our children either Leninism, or Trotskyism, or White Russian altra-nationalism, or monarchism," say the parents' delegates.</p>
   <p>"Our children must learn in the schools to read and write Russian, they must be told everything about Russia so that they would learn to love and respect their fathers' native country, their language and history."</p>
   <p>"That is all we want.</p>
   <p>"When the children grow up they will understand themselves where and with <pb facs="5423967_3_0407.jpg" n="2"/>whom they have to go; but now there is no need of carrying on propaganda among them."</p>
   <p>This is what has been said at the convention. And in telling this the delegates were proving that in the federation there is no room for "political" discussions and personal quarrels which arise among certain persons who have to divide some spoils.</p>
   <p>The general opinion at the convention was that the personal element should be eliminated from the discussions, and that the sooner this is done, the better. It is necessary to put the management of the affairs of the school federation into the hands of honest Russian people who will be thinking about the children and the knowledge they are acquiring, and not about themselves and the fact that their rotten egotism has been offended.</p>
   <p>Who are these honest people?</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0408.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They are those Russian non-partisan toilers who love their native country, Russia, who are not under the influence of either the reactionaries or the radicals and are just busy doing their useful work of enlightening the Russian children.</p>
   <p>Neither the teachers of Leninism and Trotskyism, nor White Russian ultra-nationalists who poison the minds of our children with ideas about the enmity which is supposed to reign between Russians living in different provinces of Russia, neither of there elements should rule the federation.</p>
   <p>The non-partisan colony of toilers should itself elect those who will manage the affairs of the federation. The federation - that glorious achievement of the colony - should be turned over to these persons elected by the colony.</p>
   <p>If Communist politics is introduced into the federation by the members of <pb facs="5423967_3_0409.jpg" n="4"/>the American Labor Party, or if the federation will fall under the baleful influence of "White Russian ex-ministers and public men," nothing will be left of this useful organization. A Russian undertaking will fall to pieces. But it is necessary to preserve it at all costs.</p>
   <p>Remember this, Russian toilers, and get ready for the next elections.</p>
   <p>And this is most important: do not allow the open and secret enemies to destroy the school federation.</p>
   <p>A Russian Father.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
