<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novyi Mir (New World)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-04">April 4, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Federation of Russian Children's Schools in Chicago and Suburbs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0210</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0210.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novyi Mir (New World)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-04">April 4, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">FEDERATION OF RUSSIAN CHILDREN'S SCHOOLS IN CHICAGO AND SUBURBS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fourteen years ago at our parties youngsters with a bottle of pop in their hands were hanging on to the skirts of their mothers, disturbing their dancing. These were our pupils.</p>
   <p>At present the 'old' are sitting on one side yielding the hall to the 'youth,' and to the skirts of many a youthful mother the third generation is hanging with a similar bottle of pop in their hands. This is the reason why the number of children in our schools is decreasing every year. Will this third generation be in our schools as their fathers and mothers? That is the question. Of course, we should also try to conquer this generation.</p>
   <p>At any rate our federation should play, - as it has already played to <pb facs="5423967_3_0211.jpg" n="2"/>to a great extent, - its historical role of completeness with the present and second generation of immigrants. The cultural work which the federation and its schools have performed in the Russian colony for the past thirteen years is colossal and invaluable. There were mistakes and shortcomings. We have not fully succeeded in organizing and instilling a love for (pro-Russian) activity within the youth after their graduation from our schools.</p>
   <p>Lacking funds we were also unable to organize permanent high schools for the youth. But we have not lost the youth; they are and always will be with us.</p>
   <p>Not only have we given our youth a Russian education by teaching them the Russian language, but we have been able to instill in them an inextinguishable love for the birthplace of their parents, the land <pb facs="5423967_3_0212.jpg" n="3"/>which in 1917 laid the foundation of a new era in the history of humanity. We have been able to awaken within them the class-consciousness of proletarian children, a consciousness of the necessity of struggle for a better life for the workers, for the power of labor; a consciousness of equality and brotherhood of nations.</p>
   <p>Hundreds upon hundreds of children of Russian immigrants have emerged from the walls of our schools during these thirteen years. All these beautiful young women, these bodily and spiritually healthy youths at our meetings and parties are our former students. Our youth is not sufficiently active in our organizations, but they are with us forever and everywhere. They are leading the cultural and conscious life of the generation that will replace us. We are proud of our youth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0213.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Now we are insulted because our boys and girls speak only English among themselves, or because they prefer to speak English with us. But in this we do not consider the circumstances facing us in the land which though alien to us is not alien to them. English, of course, is their language. And after all, a language is only a form; in idealism they are with us, they are conscious working children and thus all our labor and energy is justifiably spent.</p>
   <p>At present the president of the federation is M. Niesteruk. During the last years the secretary has been M. Miklov. Among the members of the Soviet federation faithfully remains a number of old school workers, among them Rutovets, Yacubovich, Maksimenia, Abramchik, Klimkov, Mornell, Kuletzky, and others.</p>
   <p>The federation and the schools are in reliable hands. Much have our <pb facs="5423967_3_0214.jpg" n="5"/>school workers labored. Much have they succeeded. Many difficult problems are as yet facing us: they will solve them also.</p>
   <p>Our inspiration, the great Union of Socialist Soviet Republics; our ideal leader, Novyi Mir, which we will all joyfully join in honoring.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
