<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-08-29">Aug. 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">New Plan of Unifying the Russian Colony.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1672</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1672.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-08-29">Aug. 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">NEW PLAN OF UNIFYING THE RUSSIAN COLONY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Quite often in the columns of Rassviet, articles are published inviting the independents to join the colors of R. C. M. A. S. A. (Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society in America).</p>
   <p>The authors of these articles state that there is no difference between R. C. M. A. S. A., (and R. I. M. A. S. Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society). That is well. But why had R. C. M. A. S. A. workers not thought of it five or six years ago? Instead of splitting up the Russian colony they could join and help us in promoting the R.I.M.A.S.A.</p>
   <p>Surely, the authors of these articles and the R. C. M. A. S. A. had active workers justify themselves by the fact that the R.I. M. A. S. had a religious name and, therefore, as a progressive group, they could not see the way to join such an organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1673.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1918 the R. I. M. A. S. had proposed to be amalgamated with the Pittsburgh Mutual Aid Society.</p>
   <p>Thanks to the vanity of certain individuals, who wanted to have the main office in Pittsburgh, this offer failed.</p>
   <p>During twenty years of our existence such incidents have happened often and, therefore, the invitations of the R. C. M. A. S. A. as well as the R. P. M. A. S. (of Pittsburgh) should be considered very carefully. My personal advice to our friends of New York and Pittsburgh in regard to the amalgamation is as follows: to accept fully the by-laws of the R. I. M. A. S., and to authorize the executive board of each organization to become incorporated with the Chicago R. I. M. A. S. Such a plan would not be mere words, but would bring about the long awaited consolidation.</p>
   <p>We call on the R. C. M. A. S. A. and R. P. M. A. S. to be amalgamated with the R. I. M. A. S. of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Ivan Coroshchenia</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
