<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. X, of H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. Russkii V. Amerike, (probably <date when="1911">1911</date>).
<title level="a">The First Russian Paper in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0061</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-V.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0061.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. X, of H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. Russkii V. Amerike, (probably 1911).
<title level="a">THE FIRST RUSSIAN PAPER IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the occasion of the publication of Russkii v Amerike, there came an expression of rejoicing from O. P. Timist.</p>
   <p>He calls attention to the heightened spirits everywhere among Russians here as a reaction to the existance of Russki v Amerike. His hope is that this paper will buoy up the indifferent Russian, the nostalgic Russian, the Russian of the Oblomov-type, the disgruntled Russian, and the drinking, maladjusted Russian--the entire colony, with its multitudinous shades and divisions in political, economic, ethical, and social credos--to action for things useful, practical, and helpful towards a better, healthier, cleaner and more interesting everyday life, without breaking in on their moral, intellectual, or emotional hobbys. "Do not all Russian immigrants need to know the English language? Do not most of the Russians here, 95% of them workmen, need a shield under which to resist, by united efforts, the exploitation by their employers, and shocking working conditions? Do not most of them need a community chest for mutual aid, the same as other communities?</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0062.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"I have lived in America about ten years," continues O. P. Timist, "and having been most of the time in close contact with Russian immigrants of all strata and degrees of learning, I have come to the conclusion that what they need most is, to unite into one powerful force, and prove by so doing that they are not a backward, uncivilized people, incapable of orientation in this country of immense progress."</p>
   <p>He urges the Russian immigrant to learn the language of his new country rather than mope about the "cursed English language;" to devote evenings and Sundays to good books or lectures, rather than drinking.</p>
   <p>"Study, develop, feed your brain, and ennoble your soul, and you will soon realize that life is beautiful, and that there is nothing better than love of knowledge and humanity. Nothing more noble than to work for common progress.</p>
   <p>"Let us prove ourselves capable of useful, great work; prove that not only in Russia we knew how to fight for a better future but also here we can fight for'd."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0063.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In conclusion the enthusiastic correspondent expresses his fervent hope that the moral animation called out by the appearance of Russkii v Amerike will be lasting, and the newspaper will never cease to be a source of inspiration and guidance in the untiring fight by the Russians for a well-earned share of the blessings of life in this New World!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
