<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii v Amerike</title> (probably <date when="1911">1911</date>). <title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. X, owned by Dr. R. H. Krasnow, Chicago.
<title level="a">The First Russian Paper in Chicago</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0064</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0064.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii v Amerike</title> (probably <date when="1911">1911</date>). <title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. X, owned by Dr. R. H. Krasnow, Chicago.
<title level="a">THE FIRST RUSSIAN PAPER IN CHICAGO</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Good Luck!</p>
   <p>The foundation of a Russian newspaper in Chicago, Russkii v Amerike, was a source of intellectual animation in the local Russian colony of Chicago and vicinity.</p>
   <p>A letter by Dr. Krasnow, welcoming the birth of this publication, envisages the scope of service it could render to Russian immigrants, and the objectives which should become the goal of this organ so that it could assume the responsibility of leadership, of thought in the colony. Dr. Krasnow further points out the crying need in the Russian colony for the newspaper here, because the Russian immigrant "no longer chooses his destination from among the nearest points to Ellis Island, namely, <pb facs="5423967_3_0065.jpg" n="2"/>New York or Philadelphia. He now sets his face to the West of North America.</p>
   <p>The writer further reflects that Russkii v Amerike marks a new era in the Russian colony of Chicago and its outskirts, with its approximately 50,000 Russians, after many attempts in the past five years to establish a Russian paper had failed.</p>
   <p>Realizing that the degree of success in this enterprise is not to be predicted, he points out the opportunity for the local public-spirited and intellectual Russians to promote culture, education, insight, and Americanization in its best sense among the much-harassed Russian newcomers through this publication.</p>
   <p>He recalls the unsuccessful efforts in the past "for a mutual help society; for a library for the immigrants; a lodge; popular lectures in <pb facs="5423967_3_0066.jpg" n="3"/>science; progressive organizations to assist banish a political offenders and prisoners in Russia; drama and music circles; popular concerts and plays and many other useful activities," which remained up to now unsuccessful, but could now, with Russkii v Amerike as an instrument, be realized.</p>
   <p>The writer hails this publication for its broad possibilities of becoming the faithful and useful servant of the Russian immigrant in America, irrespective of creed; whether of the Greek-Orthodox Church or of any other creed; whether he worships a church God or any other god.</p>
   <p>Doctor Krasnow stresses the need for "a new guiding current in Chicago" and hopes that Russkii v Amerike will be the expression of such a current, inasmuch as it will, he hopes, uphold the ethics of a clean Russian publication, and will "cling to the principles of justice and brotherliness, always striving towards the objectives of progress, common welfare and enlightenment for everybody."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0067.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In conclusion the writer greets the arrival of "the healthy promising child" in the midst of the Russian community, when there is such great need for its presence.</p>
   <p>G. K.</p>
   <p>Ed. Note: This letter is an illustration of the reception granted a Russian newspaper in Chicago by intellectual Russians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
