<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-04-26">April 26, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Kerensky's Address</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0872</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0872.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-04-26">April 26, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">KERENSKY'S ADDRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A. F. Kerensky's arrival to Chicago is the sensational event of the day in the Russian colony. His address on Sunday, April 24, at the Ashland Auditorium, had been expected with great impatience.</p>
   <p>Though the zenith of the fame of this hero of the February Revolution, who has achieved such great notoriety, had passed at the time of the fall of the Provisional government, the name of Kerensky, so intimately connected with the first grand days of a liberated Russia, has not yet lost its glamor and attractiveness.</p>
   <p>Consequently, it is not to be wondered at that every public speech made by Kerensky attracts the attention of all those who are for some reason or other interested in the fate of Russia.</p>
   <p>Kerensky's public appearance before the Chicago Russians coincided with <pb facs="5423967_3_0873.jpg" n="2"/>the Russian Easter. The Russian <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of Chicago <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> forget on this day all their earthly sorrows and tribulations. On this day it is most difficult to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to some lecture or address. And only kerensky's magical name <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> them away from the Easter table to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to an address. And this meeting <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> attended not only by Chicago Russians, but also by Russians who had <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> from other cities.</p>
   <p>The tickets for admission to Kerensky's address were being sold speedily during the whole last week at the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the Rassviet, and on the day of the address just as speedily at the booth at the entrance to the hall which was open early in the morning.</p>
   <p>The hall of the large Ashland Auditorium which <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> more than 5,000 persons began to be filled a long time before the hour announced for the meeting. Many provident Russians came very early in order to secure good seats so that they could see well the ex-premier and not miss any word spoken by him.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0874.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On the whole the taking of seats was going on without any incidents. A part of the public was somewhat intoxicated. The communistically-minded "comrades" did not lag behind those who had been "celebrating"; they had absorbed some liquor, perhaps in order to increase their courage or, maybe, to show some <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> a religious "superstition." These last, according to a strategic plan, worked out before hand by the communist "cell," occupied, as a compact group, some seats in the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the hall, and some also in the alleries.</p>
   <p>Some more important communists belonging to the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> (Note: <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> stands for "Now <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Policy." D. S.) class penetrated to the stalls, and the most enterprising took <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <p>It is already 2 o'clock - time to call the meeting to order. But Kerensky is not there yet. The communists in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> galleries applaud noisily, protesting thus against the lack of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the speaker, that "counter-<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0875.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>However, Kerensky does not make them wait very long. He appears on the stage accompanied by some important-looking gentleman. The ex-premier is greeted by loud and prolonged applause which ultimately becomes a stormy ovation. Gradually the enthusiasm of the audience quiets down; Kerensky bows to the public without saying a word and sits down.</p>
   <p>The "important-looking gentleman," who is the chairman of the meeting, presents to the audience the editor of the evening newspaper Evening Post Mr. Clark, saying, as is usual on such occasions, a few complimentary sentences about this gentleman's merits and importance. Mr. Clark is a tall, gaunt American; he is not a bad orator and is very fond of presenting to audiences public men and politicians. He talks loud, but his voice is not resonant; his speech is smooth, there is no hesitation about it; one would think that he is dictating an editorial to his stenographer for the next issue of his newspaper.</p>
   <p>"It is not America's business," says the worthy editor," to meddle with the internal affairs of any other nation (America does it, of course) -<pb facs="5423967_3_0876.jpg" n="5"/><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[illegible]"/> <pb facs="5423967_3_0877.jpg" n="6"/>which he door not attribute to his personal popularity or merits, but believes to be the expression of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the first heroic days of Russian freedom which <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> its one Russian in the days of the February Revolution. That was really <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of great, daring <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and of true freedom - such as, perhaps, no other country has known.</p>
   <p>After this praise given to the February Revolution, Kerensky took up the attacks against him made by his political <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> from among the "rights" - the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> said, dug its <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> grave. Rasputin, treason among the courtiers, especially the disloyalty of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> who <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> princess, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> who together with some of the high dignitaries of the court was held <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to be responsible for all the reverses at the front - all <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> instilled <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> towards the resigning dynasty into all social <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Russian people. And the most <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> be found among the extreme right elements of the monarchist parties, among some aristocrats <pb facs="5423967_3_0878.jpg" n="7"/>at the imperial court, among general and the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. In other words, those who were supposed to be the staunchest supporters of the government had deserted it just before the February Revolution and wanted to get rid of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> dynasty even at the cost of a revolution.</p>
   <p>Kerensky says that now it <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> been proved by <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> that not only the court, but even the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of Police was conducting anti-nationalistic political activities amounting to defeatism, helping the cause of Germany by endeavoring to bring about the defeat of Russia.</p>
   <p>He, Kerensky, and Rodzyanko did not want a revolution and warned the tsar against the impending danger. But the tsar did not want to make any concessions and continued to do the will of the tsaritsa and of Rasputin.</p>
   <p>Thus the February Revolution was the result of the fusion of two streams: on one hand of the monarchist parties of the right which had <pb facs="5423967_3_0879.jpg" n="8"/>lost all respect for the authority of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>; on the other hand of the lefts, the revolutionary parties. There could being other outcome of this situation except the overthrow of tsarism which had degenerated and was in a state of dissolution.</p>
   <p>And monarchism, of course, has died once for all and is not going to be res<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>rrected.and is not going to be resurrected.</p>
   <p>(Kerenksy's Address, 2nd Instalment -- April 27, 1927).</p>
   <p>The February Conquests and the political and Social Reaction of the Bolsheviki.</p>
   <p>The February Revolution was not only a political one, but also a social One. It recognized as sacred rights the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of personal free <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and other liberties. It made the workman and the peasants the real masters of the country, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the beurgeoisie was weak in Russia; and the intelligentsia went hand in hand with the masses of the people during the February Revolution. Not the Bolsheviki, but the February Revolution <pb facs="5423967_3_0880.jpg" n="9"/>gave the land to the peasants. The decree about the abolition of private land-ownership had been signed by the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of agriculture of the Provisional Government (a member of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>-<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> party), Shingarev.</p>
   <p>And if with the coming into power of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> was taken from the people, still the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> did not dare to take the land from the peasants. And this is the reason why <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> thinks that <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> cannot <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in Russia, as the peasants know very well that its restoration would mean also the restitution of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to their former owners.</p>
   <p><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> such a sworn enemy of Russian freedom as Lenin, said Kerensky, has declared once in the Soviet of workmen's and soldier's deputies (it happened while the Provisional Government was still in power) that there is no juster land than Russia - no land where the rights of the workmen would be so thoroughly guaranteed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0881.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>According to Kerensky's opinion Bolshevism arose in Russia because of the weakness of national feeling and owing to dissensions in the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Government itself. On one hand the rights were reproving the Provisional Government for making too many concessions; they were saying that it is necessary to take back these concessions; yet that would have aroused the indignation of the country; while the lefts reproved us for having taken too little. And in such conditions, when the army was disorganized, we had to put through social reforms and to carry on the war ... An extraordinary responsibility was put on the shoulders of the government - a responsibility the more heavy because in the government itself there was not sufficient unanimity.</p>
   <p>The Bolsheviki took advantage of the vacillation and the weakness of the Provisional Government and seized power. They brought with them an absolute political and social reaction. They not only destroyed all the liberties, but instituted a complete slavery for the workmen and peasants. These last they rob by levying exorbitant taxes; and in no other country are the workmen exploited as cruelly as they are in Russia. A workman is <pb facs="5423967_3_0882.jpg" n="11"/>forced to work in a factory belonging to the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for 11to 12 hours, and all his energy is being sacked out of him by a system of piece-work.</p>
   <p>The Bolsheviki did not abolish <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> old <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> time he was creating a new, worse edition of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> If the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> regime the Jews were not allowed to reside and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> limits of certain restricted areas, now the Bolsheviki <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of Russia into such an area where no one could freely reside where no one chose nor move when he wanted to do so.</p>
   <p>While Russia was participating in the World War, it lost seven million men. But the Bolshevist dictatorship cost Russia twenty million men, as admitted by the Bolsheviki themselves.</p>
   <p>The liberation of Russia from the Bolsheviki can come about in two ways. The Bolshevist <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> can be <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> by a new revolution. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> holds that a revelation costs too much to the country where it happens. This applies especially to Russia which is at present entirely exhausted <pb facs="5423967_3_0883.jpg" n="12"/>both economically and spiritually. It would be much better if the Bolsheviki, having begun to listen to the voice of reason, would restore to the people the liberties of which they have robbed Russia, and if they would do this without waiting for any <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> disturbances. In such a case they may remain in power.</p>
   <p>But, says Kerensky, we do not know of any such <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in the history of humanity. We never <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of tyrants or despots <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> making the necessary concessions to the people. Therefore kerensky thinks that Russia cannot avoid new revolutionary upheavals which can bring to the country some horrible experiences.</p>
   <p>At the close of his address Kerensky made an appeal to all Russians for national unity, for the creation of one will and one endeavor to liberate Russia from the yoke of the Bolsheviki. When the Russian people in Russia are all fused into one body by their one desire to get rid of the Bolsheviki and by the consciousness of the necessity of such liberation. Then even the guns of the chekists will cease shooting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0884.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>In Kerensky's opinion Russia will return sooner or later to the February regime, i. e., to a democratic republican regime; to a rule of the country according to Abraham Lincoln's formula: "by the people, for the people."</p>
   <p>Kerensky finishes his speech. He is given a stormy ovation. The majority of the audience rise from their seats.</p>
   <p>Mr. Clark, who acts as chairman, reads in English a short summary of Kerensky's discourse for the benefit of those among the audience who do not understand the Russian language. The Americans interrupt from time to time Mr. Clark's reading by applause, being strongly impressed by some passages of Kerensky's address. The reading of the summary of Kerensky's address in English is finished, and Kerensky agrees to answer questions put by persons from among the audience.</p>
   <p>Questions and Answers</p>
   <p>From all ends of the hall are heard voices of persons asking to be given <pb facs="5423967_3_0885.jpg" n="14"/>the right of the floor. Many hands are raised. The Communists who have been listening attentively to the address without emitting one sound seem to have awakened to the situation; now they begin to be noisy, they become excited and swear as befits "comrades." They want, of course, to cross-examine Kerensky, to make him commit some blunder in order to be able to declare before all the people that he harbors some "counter-revolutionary" designs.</p>
   <p>The Chicago chekists have, naturally, been preparing for such an emergency, and they were triumphing beforehand, expecting to be victorious in this encounter with Kerensky. But they were disappointed in their expectations, as always happens with all Communist plans.</p>
   <p>The answers which Kerensky gave to the attacks of the Communists proved to be so weighty that the Communists went away not with their heads proudly raised, but rather ashamed; some of them may even have lost confidence in their communist creed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0886.jpg" n="15"/>
   <p>We quote below a few questions illustrating the depth of the Communists' wisdom.</p>
   <p>- You, Mr. Kerensky, maintain that in Russia the Communists form less than one percent of the population. If such were the case how would it be possible for the Communists to rule Russia - a country with a population numbering so many million people - for ten years?</p>
   <p>The Communists applaud the person who has asked this <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> meaning by this applause that this question <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Kerensky pretty hard.</p>
   <p>Kerensky warns the applauding Communists not to celebrate a victory prematurely. His answer to this question is as follows:</p>
   <p>- The Communist Party numbers 500,000 members. In Russia everybody who has a membership card of the Communist Party is a member of the government. Now the Communists reason in the following way: If some time Nicholas I had declared that he rules Russia with the help of 100,000 <pb facs="5423967_3_0887.jpg" n="16"/>chiefs of the police why should we, communists, not be able to rule Russia with the help of 500,000 members of our party?</p>
   <p>Kerensky's very pointed answer is rewarded by stormy applause. But the Communists do not want to consider themselves beaten. One of them, wishing to prove that the democratic form of government is unsuitable speaks about the oppression of the workmen in democratic America and mentions the policemen armed with clubs.</p>
   <p>- But in Moscow there are more policemen and chekists armed with guns. And in Russia strikes are entirely forbidden, retorts Kerensky.</p>
   <p>Some Communist "nepman," looking pretty well fed, tries to assure Kerensky that in Moscow the proletarian fares very well while in America he is in the clutches of poverty.</p>
   <p>Kerensky answers:</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0888.jpg" n="17"/>
   <p>- Anyone of you, American workmen, in Russia would be considered as a "millionaire," an arch-bourgeois. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> saw many American workmen going out of a factory and looking for their own automobiles which were standing right near the factory. They get into these automobiles and go home. But the Russian workman, after working 11 or 12 hours in a factory, gets out dressed in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> clothes, and, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> tired, unshod feet, walks home.</p>
   <p>Someone asks Kerensky why he ordered the army to continue the war.</p>
   <p>- The Provisional <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> acted thus <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the following considerations: no allied country and the right to end the war by concluding a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> peace as this could lead to very disastrous <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, first of all for the very country which would act thus. Our considerations proved to be quite correct. For the peace <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the Bolsheviki had to pay a very high price; they had to give away some of the best regions of Russia; <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, a part of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Russia, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> provinces, Finnland, and on top of that they had <pb facs="5423967_3_0889.jpg" n="18"/>to pay a contribution to Germany which had been defeated. Not to mention the millions of human lives lost during the civil war which had been caused by that very same anti-national policy of the Bolsheviki.</p>
   <p>Why don't the Bolsheviki allow the Russian immigrants to return to Russia?</p>
   <p>In Europe the Bolsheviki are even agitating, trying to induce the Russian emigrants to return to Russia; they are even organizing societies of Russians who want to be repatriated. It is in their interest to carry on such an agitation which brings disintegration into the ranks of the emigrants. But as soon as the persons who had trusted the Bolsheviki consented to return to Russia, the Bolsheviki would not always be willing to allow them to be repatriated, as they (the Bolsheviki) were afraid that the miserable actual conditions in Russia would cause the repatriated to become disappointed.</p>
   <p>Many other questions were asked, but we shall not dwell on them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
