<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-24">Dec. 24, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">The School Problem</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Editorial Colleagues of "Novosti" (The News).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0323</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0323.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-24">Dec. 24, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCHOOL PROBLEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by EDITORIAL COLLEAGUES OF "NOVOSTI" (The News).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The school problem is not only a significant question, but one of cardinal importance to the Russian people in foreign countries. It is very strange that our Rnzov-Russkoe Nezavisimoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society), being behind the cultural movement in most of the large Russian-American centers, did not take up this problem ten years ago.</p>
   <p>We think it was a result of the Russian's negligent attitude toward education; while the Russian was shaking himself and getting ready, the schools and [the education] of Russian children were put under the control of all sorts of international scoundrels. They organized the socalled Federation of Schools, where two or three persons, neither of Russian origin,nor of Russian culture, were in charge of management.</p>
   <p>To maintain these schools, hundreds of dollars of the hard-earned money of the Russian colony, were wasted; but where is the result of this <pb facs="5423967_3_0324.jpg" n="2"/>expenditure, where is that youth which is supposed to come to relieve the old colonists?</p>
   <p>There are no such replacements and nothing comes from the Federated schools.</p>
   <p>Results can be achieved only when the school and the affairs of the school will be built on the foundation of love for Russian culture, of consideration for the Russian customs and characteristics of the native land and of the parents, and, last but not least, [built on the foundation of] respect of the children for their parents.</p>
   <p>The Federated School cannot offer any of this because the supervisors, such as Comrade Mornell, surely cannot bring up the Russian children to love Russia since they hate Russia with a burning hatred which has been developed for centuries.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0325.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>How can they understand the reasoning or the psychology of the Russian child, being themselves of a different race and of different ideals?</p>
   <p>Do you not think it is a disgrace to the Russians that the supervision of the Russian schools, and the education of their children at Federated schools, are in the hands of strangers, whose aim is to destroy the pure Russian that has been developed for centuries?</p>
   <p>No nation would entrust the education of its children to strangers, and yet the Russians do not have Russian teachers.</p>
   <p>It is not strange therefore that the Federation, in its ten years of existence, has not given to the Russian colony one young, and energetic new member, qualified to replace his elders in Russian social activity.</p>
   <p>Comrade Eberhardt, maintained and warmed by the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society in the past, has been using all his strength to prove that the tenth jubilee of the Federation of the school was successful and significant.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0326.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But we were present at this occasion and felt deeply ashamed for the Russian people.</p>
   <p>Ten years of the schools' existence, hundreds, to be more exact thousands of hard-earned dollars spent, and what are the results?</p>
   <p>Not one of the students of the Federated School, could recite even a few words in Russian, Not one of them could say that he was happy and honored to be a Russian, that he was thankful to his parents as well as to the supervisors of the school for what he had learned about Russia--that he had been taught to love Russia and to be proud of it.</p>
   <p>We do not mention that a few words could have been said to the effect that the youth educated in the Federated schools would give their strength and ability for the happiness and commonweal of the distant homeland of their fathers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0327.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Alas, the Federation has nothing to brag about.</p>
   <p>There was not even a decent declamation by the children. There was some sort of absurd dance without rhythm or music, performed by the pupils of the L. N. Tolstoy School, and some revolutionary play given by the pupils from Whiting, Ind., innocent little children who, like parrots, cried out revolutionary words the sense of which was meaningless to them.</p>
   <p>It was a pity to look at them, and a reflection upon the brainless supervisors of the Federation. But comrades Mornell, Eberhardt, Deviatkin and Company, like nightingales, effusively warbling and exalting themselves, stated that they were honest and good "workers" with "calloused hands", who"came from the plough and worked in the mines". And the Russian colonists listened and applauded.</p>
   <p>[The performance] was a disgrace to the Russian people and their reputation. The time is ripe for the Russian people to release themselves from this international riffraff.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
