<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-27">Apr. 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">It Is Necessary to Call an All-Russian Convention</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Kharitoniuk</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-27">Apr. 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">IT IS NECESSARY TO CALL AN ALL-RUSSIAN CONVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Kharitoniuk</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During 1933 and part of 1934 many good, thoughtful suggestions were made concerning the necessity of calling an All-Russian Congress.</p>
   <p>More than once the newspaper Rassviet devoted whole columns to the discussions which were going on concerning this important matter.</p>
   <p>We talked, we wrote and then quieted down as though we had reached our goal of uniting the Russian colony.</p>
   <p>But the time slips by unnoticed and the problem of uniting all Russian organizations and societies into one solid block still remains to be solved.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1350.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Instead of an All-Colony Congress it is necessary to call an All-Russian Congress of the United States by sending invitations to all Russian mutual aid societies and all church brotherhoods.</p>
   <p>The other day I paid a visit to the editors of the newspaper Pravda, published in Philadelphia by the United Russian Church Brotherhoods. I had a brief talk with several active members of the brotherhoods and with the editor of the newspaper, Mr. Dzvonchik. All of them are lovely, good-hearted people, sons of the Carpathian.</p>
   <p>They know and realize perfectly how they should value and respect everything that is Russian. From their talks one could infer that Mr. Kazuschik, Mr. Shkliar's right hand man, had approached the various societies [Translator's note:--Mr. Shkliar is one of the communist leaders and the editor of the communist newspaper Novy Mir in New York City], but suffered complete failure in his attempts to swing them over to his own camp. From the editor's statement I found out that the Church Brotherhoods have 263 local <pb facs="5423967_3_1351.jpg" n="3"/>branches and that they are desirous of entering into negotiations with the Russian mutual aid societies for the purpose of uniting with them into one society.</p>
   <p>From the financial statement published in Pravda of March 26 and verified by the auditing committee, it can be seen that the Brotherhoods have cash resources of $1,524,493.</p>
   <p>We have also discussed the fact that ROOV and RNzOV [the two largest Mutual aid societies] so far have not been able to agree to unite their societies. Mr. Dzvonchik declared that the time is not far off when not only these two organizations but all other Russian societies will be forced by circumstances to unite or disband altogether. Only recently, the editor said, officials of the state department in charge of supervision of foreign mutual aid societies visited their offices and stated that in the very near future none of the national groups will be allowed to have more than one or two mutual aid organizations in place of scores of such organizations existing at <pb facs="5423967_3_1352.jpg" n="4"/>present.</p>
   <p>Would it not be better for us Russians to unite our scattered organizations into a solid All-Russian society before we are forced by state department officials to do so?</p>
   <p>Despite the fact that I belong to one of the largest Russian mutual aid societies (ROOVA) I am certain that both our managing board and our membership on the whole desire to unite with other similar Russian organizations and form one large Russian brotherly family.</p>
   <p>It would be desirable if the question of calling together of an All-Russian Congress were raised and widely discussed in Russian papers like Rassviet, Russian Herold, Pravda and other publications interested in the activities of mutual aid societies.</p>
   <p>Just think what an accomplishment it would be in the life of Russians in <pb facs="5423967_3_1353.jpg" n="5"/>the United States if the United Society of Russian Brotherhoods with its 263 branches and twenty thousand members joined hands with the Russian United Society of Mutual Aid with its 80 locals, with the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society and its four thousand members and with the other Russian national organizations grouped around the newspaper Russia, excluding, of course, the Bolshevik organizations.</p>
   <p>We need all our active public leaders among the Russian colony to raise this problem for discussion, for we Russians stand to gain a great deal politically, economically and culturally if we unite our forces for our common good.</p>
   <p>The Congress should be called in the near future.</p>
   <p>Long live the All-Russian Congress in the United States! Long live the unification of all Russian organizations into one brotherly family!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
