<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-13">June 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Day of Russian Culture in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Paraskin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0726</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0726.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-13">June 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE DAY OF RUSSIAN CULTURE IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Paraskin</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Celebration of the Day of Russian Culture in Chicago was an outstanding success. On that day the entire Russian colony gathered to pay respects and express its loyalty to Russian culture.</p>
   <p>Speakers taking part in the celebration pointed out those great spiritual values which are embodied in the Russian culture.</p>
   <p>The first speaker of the day was Mr. E. Z. Moravsky, editor of the newspaper Rassviet. In his speech he briefly traced the development of the Russian culture. In this speaker's opinion Russian culture is only a young growth as compared with the cultures of other peoples, for its history of development can be traced back only to a recent past--to the time of Pushkin and <pb facs="5423967_3_0727.jpg" n="2"/>Lomonosov. These two men are regarded as pioneers. Prior to their time Russian culture was undergoing the embryonic stage of development, but since their appearance on the Russian scene the development of Russian culture has been rapid and broad. Creators of cultural values began to appear in all spheres of human endeavor. Russian literature and Russian art received from them a great impetus, and at present they occupy a place of honor in the world culture.</p>
   <p>Russian literary works have already been translated into all languages. In all countries works by Tolstoy and Dostoevski are being read, for these authors are known by the entire cultured world for their writings. The same is true of Russian music and Russian song. They have spread their enchanting airs throughout the world.</p>
   <p>The Russian ballet, as it was represented originally by Pavlova and Nizhinsky, has never been excelled anywhere. The modern version of the Russian ballet, known under the name of Monte Carlo, enjoys popularity all over the world <pb facs="5423967_3_0728.jpg" n="3"/>and still occupies first place in choreographic art.</p>
   <p>The Russian Art Theater, headed by Stanislavsky and Nemirovich-Danchenko, has acquired a world renown. There is no equal to it anywhere in the world. World famous singers, Chaliapin, Kurenko, and others, still entertain the world with their interpretation of the Russian song.</p>
   <p>With the coming of Bolshevism to Russia, the growth of Russian culture stopped, due to lack of freedom of expression.</p>
   <p>Professor Henzel, another speaker of the day, pointed to the fact that Russian scholars honestly and loyally worked for the cause of science, that Russian scientists paid very little attention to comforts in their personal life, and devoted all their knowledge and genius to scientific studies. At present, Russian men of science are mainly engaged in developing applied science. As far as humanitarian sciences are concerned their development, under conditions imposed by Bolshevism on the country, is altogether impossible. Prior to the <pb facs="5423967_3_0729.jpg" n="4"/>revolution Russian scientists enjoyed much greater freedom than now.</p>
   <p>Dr. Pertzov, the speaker that followed Professor Henzel, briefly outlined the achievements of Russian scientists. He recounted the discoveries and inventions contributed by Russian genius to the world culture and its progress. He mentioned Lomonosov in the science of physics; Mendelyeev, in chemistry; Pirogov, in surgery; Mechnikov, Bekhterev, Maximov, Pavlov, in anatomy and physiology.</p>
   <p>Dr. Pertzov also told the audience that only recently A. L. von Grosse, a Russian professor of chemistry at the University of Chicago, discovered a new element while following clues offered by Mendelyeev's table. He also pointed to the valuable research work and discoveries made by Professor P. I. Kapitza in the sphere of physics. Professor Kapitza is residing in Russia. Dr. Pertzov also referred to N.K. Peurich, the famous Russian painter, who initiated the pact which was accepted by all American countries as a guide to the preservation of the world culture.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0730.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Last of the speakers was the Right Reverend P. Nirvanna, whose task it was to explain to the listeners that cultural attainments belong to the spiritual order of things, and have nothing to do with material well-being, and that a Russian culture of this sort has been created by the Russian genius. Spiritual culture is the cardinal factor in the progress and betterment of mankind.</p>
   <p>The time of the speakers was limited and, consequently, they could not say all they wished or were able to say about the Russian culture. They did, however, tell a great deal about the Russian culture and its contributions to the world progress.</p>
   <p>The Day of Russian Culture, I assume, will remain for a long time in the memory of those who attended the celebration, for it was truly a Day of Russian Culture. For that day the Russian people in and around Chicago united into one family, and gathered to honor their native culture in a foreign land. Our culture is our common heritage which glorifies Russia all over the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0731.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Bolsheviks attempt to distort the great ultimate aims pursued by Russian culture, but the time is not far distant when Russian culture will free itself from the Bolshevik clutches.  </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
