<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-07-22">July 22, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The Second Session of the School Federation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0413</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0413.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-07-22">July 22, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE SECOND SESSION OF THE SCHOOL FEDERATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second session of the third school convention took place on July 18th at the quarters of the Workmen's House. The teacher S. Mornel was elected chairman; <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>hestkov and Turovets were elected secretaries.</p>
   <p>The same delegates who attended the opening session were present also at this second session. There had come also a delegate from the Cooperative Restaurant, Konchakovsky, and a delegate from the Progressive Women's Society, Tsybulya.</p>
   <p>After the minutes of the preceding session had been read and accepted with a few amendments, the delegates listened to the reading of the report of the Executive Committee about the activities of the federation during the current year. After a long discussion this report was approved.</p>
   <p>The next point to be discussed was that of the financial report of the <pb facs="5423967_3_0414.jpg" n="2"/>federation. After a few questions had been asked and answered this report was approved.</p>
   <p>The financial reports of the separate schools were also approved. At the same time those schools which did not send any written reports were told that it is their duty to send then in.</p>
   <p>The report of the Central Bookstore was approved.</p>
   <p>The sixth point of the order of the business of the day is the report of the library of the federation.</p>
   <p>The reading of this report arouses a lively discussion as the library of the federation consists of three sections: (1) textbooks, (2) fiction, and (3) books on social and political questions. The chief causes of the discord were of course the books belonging to the third section. After a careful consideration of this question the following resolution was <pb facs="5423967_3_0415.jpg" n="3"/>passed: The third section of the library has to be eliminated, and the books have to be given to the Workmen's House, together with the bills sent in by the "Gosizdat." (Note: The State Publishing Concern. D. S.) Thus it was resolved to let the federation keep only the two first sections of the library. At the same time it was resolved to send to the Gosizdat a letter requesting this concern in unmistakable terms to stop sending publications which have not been ordered by the Federation. After that Comrade Zhukov was given the right of the floor. He read a report about the South Side School. Comrade Zhukov was appointed at the last session of the School Council to find out the reasons of the absence of any delegates from the South Side School at the three last sessions of the School Council and to inquire whether this school intends to participate in the labors of the third school convention. Zhukov briefly reported to the convention the answer of the South Side School. He states that the school has decided not to participate in this convention.</p>
   <p>The question was raised whether the convention should open a discussion <pb facs="5423967_3_0416.jpg" n="4"/>on this subject. It was resolved by a majority vote to start a discussion. After a very lively debate the following resolution was passed: The third school convention disapproves the doings of a few persons who undermine the educational work and try to persuade the teachers and active workers of the South Side School to secede from this common work of enlightenment. The convention appeals to the South Side School to join again the family of schools and hopes that the South Side School will do so in spite of the intrigues of separate individuals.</p>
   <p>Concerning the publication of a Federative Schools' Bulletin. It was resolved unanimously to publish such a bulletin, if possible. It was also decided that the proceedings of the convention should be published in the first issue of the bulletin.</p>
   <p>M. D.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
