<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-08-15">Aug. 15, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">At the Conference of the School Committee of R. I. M. A. S.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0333</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0333.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-08-15">Aug. 15, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">AT THE CONFERENCE OF THE SCHOOL COMMITTEE OF R. I. M. A. S.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Thursday, Aug. 12, a conference, of the school committee of R. I. M. A. S. with the representatives of schools, was held under the chairmanship of Mr. Jacob Dziako.</p>
   <p>The committee was discussing the question of text-books. It was found out that in certain schools they were using text-books published in Moscow, in others, the text-books of Gudkov published in Riga. Mr. Jacob Dziako, proposed to accept the Moscow editions. The majority of the members of the committee agreed that in all schools there should be used books of the same type, namely those adopted as standard text-books, in Soviet Russia. The delegates from schools who represented the F. M. Dostoyevsky memorial school, J. A. Kryloy memorial school, and L. N. Tolstoy memorial school at Clybourn Ave, exchanged their views in regard to the organization of the work of the schools in Chicago and concerning the revival of this activity of the R. I. M. A. S.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0334.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The delegates of the Dostoyevsky memorial school, K. Nirovich and S. Korzun, declared that they are going to report the plans of R. I. M. A. S. to the general assembly of the F. I. Dostoyevsky memorial school, and the delegates from Clybourn Ave., Mr. Simon, announced that the school located at Clybourn (the former L. N. Tolstoy memorial school, which name has been at present adopted by the federation school of Douglas Park), could be reopened at any time, provided that R. I. M. A. S. will assist it financially. It was found at the conference that the majority of Russian schools in Chicago and suburbs have a tendency to join the R. I. M. A. S. This would create a network of schools, so necessary for the flourishing of cultural work in the Russian colony of Chicago. This has been for many years the drears of the "independents" (members of R. I. M. A. S.)</p>
   <p>It has been also decided to establish a central school committee, entrusting it with the duty of uniting all the Russian people's schools under the auspices of R. I. M. A. S. Mr. M. Gorozhanko, Secretary of the conference.</p>
   <p>M. Gorozhanko.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
