<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-08-21">Aug. 21, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">New Book about Russia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-08-21">Aug. 21, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">NEW BOOK ABOUT RUSSIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new and rather unusual book about the U.S.S.R. has just been published. The book bears the title, "What I Saw in Soviet Russia". The author of the book, who decided to conceal his real name for fear of persecution of his relatives in Russia, prefers to be known only as the Minsk Muzhik (a peasant from the province of Minsk). The author, actually a former peasant of Minsk, and a resident of the United States for more than twenty years, recently made a trip to Russia. After his return to America, he published in Rassviet a series of articles on Soviet Russia entitled "What I Saw in Soviet Russia". The articles aroused such wide interest among Russian people in America that his friends prevailed upon the author, a simple worker, to publish all his observations about Russia in a book.</p>
   <p>Many books have been written about Russia in recent years, but only a very few of them have any merit or value. A large commercial publishing house usually sends a writer to Russia to gather material for a book.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0144.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This foreigner, without a knowledge of the language, the people, or the country, spends most of his days on Russian soil in a hotel room, or visits such places as he is permitted to visit by the Soviet authorities, and is always accompanied by a Soviet official. Seldom does any writer visit the country districts and talk with peasants and factory workers without being closely watched by the ever-present secret police agent.</p>
   <p>Our new author, the "Minsk Peasant," followed his own method of gathering material. He did not go to Russia as a writer, but rather as a returning emigrant. He went to his native village and to his folks, whom he had not seen for the last twenty years. He thought he might stay in Russia for good, if conditions under the Soviets should prove bearable. He plodded, hiked, and rode village carts for several hundred miles of the countryside around his village; he visited the country fairs and the bazaars on market days; he talked with people, attended their weddings and other ceremonies; he worked with them in the fields. When he went to the cities and to the larger towns, he observed the life of the industrial workers, <pb facs="5423967_3_0145.jpg" n="3"/>of petty Soviet officials, and of the detachments of the Red army stationed in various localities. He even talked with a number of minor Soviet commissars whose addresses he received from his and their friends in America. When he visited Moscow, Leningrad, and other big cities, he was not interested in the life in high places, but in the living conditions of industrial and commercial workers, of small shop owners, and of the common people in general.</p>
   <p>When the "Muzhik of Minsk" returned to America and related to his friends what he had seen in Soviet Russia, he was urged to write down his experiences and to publish them in a Russian newspaper for the benefit of all Russians in America. Rassviet gladly published all the letters of the "Minsk Peasant" dealing with his experiences in Soviet Russia. The interest awakened by these letters was so enormous that the author resolved to publish them in book form. The book has 336 pages and has been carefully prepared. It is printed in distinct, readable type on good quality paper. The book has more then ten illustrations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0146.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Because the book "What I Saw in Soviet Russia" has been published privately, and not by a publishing house, its price is very low. It costs only one dollar; with postage prepaid, one dollar and fifteen cents. The book is selling fast. Its author received an offer to have it translated into English and to present it to the American public.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Rassviet was the publisher of Minsk Muzhik's book, "What I Saw in Soviet Russia." The author's attempts to have it published in the English language were unsuccessful, The real name of the author of this work may not be revealed at this time because of the possibility of revenge, by the Soviet government, upon his relatives.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
