<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Russian Herald (Russkii Viestnik)</title>
      <date when="1924-09-04">September 4, 1924</date>
      <title level="a">Society of Russian Intellectuals of the City of Chicago</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0939</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0939.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Russian Herald (Russkii Viestnik)</title>
     <date when="1924-09-04">September 4, 1924</date>
     <title level="a">SOCIETY OF RUSSIAN INTELLECTUALS OF THE CITY OF CHICAGO</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first meeting of the Society of Russian Intellectuals of the City of Chicago, which took place on Sunday, September 1st was a very lively one.</p>
   <p>Professor A. A. Maximov was the chairman, and Professor O. L. Struve read a report on the constitution and laws of the Union. The assembly accepted, with a few amendments and additions, this constitution which had been worked out by a special commission.</p>
   <p>The chief features of this constitution are as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Society of Russian Intellectuals has for its purpose to be the center around which may be unified the educated Russian of the City of Chicago as well as those outside of Chicago, irrespective of their political views, national origin or religion."</p>
   <p>In order to achieve this purpose the Society arranges meetings, readings of reports, lectures etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0940.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The Society does not pursue any political aims, either as regards Russia or the U. S. A., or any other country."</p>
   <p>"Educated Russians and persons interested in the purposes of the Society are eligible to regular membership."</p>
   <p>Persons desiring to become members of the Society present their applications to the Board of Directors of the Society through one of the members. The Board of Directors examines their applications and makes a circumstancial report on the candidates to the next General Assembly of the Society.</p>
   <p>"The membership fee is $8.00 a year, the admission $2.00."</p>
   <p>Guests recommended by two regular members of the Society are admitted to the meetings of the Society.</p>
   <p>After having accepted this Constitution, the Assembly elected by closed ballot the first Board of Directors of the Society of Russian Intellectuals of the <pb facs="5423967_3_0941.jpg" n="3"/>City of Chicago, consisting of the following persons: Professor O. L. Struve, President; I. Y. Voronko, vice-president; S. G. Prokopov, Secretary and Treasurer. The temporary address of the Society is: Society of Russian Intellectuals of Chicago, 1080 West 14th Street, Chicago Illinois.</p>
   <p>(Note: I did not translate the complete Constitution of the "Society of Russian Intellectuals", of which I enclose the Russian text copied by Mr. Korecki, as the important paragraphs are included in this article. D. S. )</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
