<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-17">Dec. 17, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to the Secretaries and the Members of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-17">Dec. 17, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO THE SECRETARIES AND THE MEMBERS OF THE RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT MUTUAL AID SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our page "Novosti" (The News) in Rassviet is already two years old.</p>
   <p>Everyone realizes the importance of the press. Everyone admits that by means of the press it is much easier to win greater sympathy for an individual and for all society. By means of the press any organization or society can become widely known for their activities among the non-organized masses. Everybody knows that by means of the press we can discuss the chief problems of our society.</p>
   <p>Our enemy has spent large sums of money for the press, because they know that the existence of big organizations without the press is impossible; they would be as helpless as the blind man without his stick.</p>
   <p>Through the use of "Novosti" it is easier to explain to colonists, who for <pb facs="5423967_3_1588.jpg" n="2"/>some reason have not yet joined our Society, what benefits they can receive for themselves and their families in case of illness or death, which may come to anyone of us. In case of any kind of an accident to one of our members, it would not be necessary for the wife or relatives to beg for charity for the funeral expenses, or for a morsel of bread. Our Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society takes care of this matter and is responsible for everything.</p>
   <p>Rnzov-Russkoye Nezavisimoye Obschestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society) for the past twenty-two years has not cheated any of its members, because the Society exists not for profit, but for the benefit of the Russian people in a foreign country.</p>
   <p>To our deep sorrow, the secretaries of our branches, not excluding the secretary of the first branch, somehow do not realize that by means of the page "Novosti", they could gain a great deal if they would picture the activities of their own branches and the lives of their members.</p>
   <p>It is very important that every branch should take this matter into consideration <pb facs="5423967_3_1589.jpg" n="3"/>and appoint its own correspondent who would take the necessary steps to tell us of the activities within the branch.</p>
   <p>Thus we would be able to win the sympathy of the workers in the Russian colony.</p>
   <p>From the reports of our various branches, in spite of critical conditions, we are very glad to hear that we are progressing.</p>
   <p>It is essential that we write about these things in "Novosti." The editorial colleagues urge us to consider the importance of this matter.</p>
   <p>Write about the lives of the Russians in your city. Write about the activity in your school for the children. Reveal the enemy of our Society; try to get new members into one great Russian family under the flag of Rnzov.</p>
   <p>Toward this end we all have to work, earnestly--for the general welfare of the public and of society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1590.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>For the past twenty-two years of the existence of Rnzov, the Society has had a great field on which to develop this type of benefit for ourselves and for our young and future generation.</p>
   <p>It is up to you. What do you say?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
