<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-05-11">May 11, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of RNzOV Opens This Evening</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. Osipik</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1293</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1293.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-05-11">May 11, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF RNzOV OPENS THIS EVENING</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. Osipik</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This evening, the delegates of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, RNzOV, will gather in annual convention for the twenty-fourth time. For the first time, they will meet in their own auditorium on Wood Street. When the delegates meet in their own building, they will feel perfectly at home, and this feeling will give them added hope, strength, and energy. Each delegate will, perhaps, become more conscious of a spirit of comradeship and [of the need for] solidarity. Each of the delegates will see that with teamwork and co-ordination of effort, they are able to create and build. This convention should inspire each delegate with such thoughts. Today, as never before, each delegate should feel a sense of duty and moral obligation to the Society. Each delegate should be proud and glad because he is a trusted member of a great family--a family that is very dear to his heart. Let each delegate to this convention tell himself that he does not stand alone--he has been sent by his <pb facs="5423967_3_1294.jpg" n="2"/>branch to perform a mission. He has come to work out plans to strengthen and enlarge his own particular center in the central states.</p>
   <p>There was a time when we gave no serious thought to such matters. We all considered ourselves temporary residents; we felt that somewhere we had a native land, and that we could return, at any time, to our homeland--to our native village. For this reason, we did not feel that we ought to build anything here. Our attitude has been completely changed by the events of the past twenty years. Very different problems confront us at present. We have lived to see a time when we all recognize the need of building a permanent home for ourselves in this strange country that has given us asylum. If human beings do not have roots, life becomes unbearable. To have solid ground under one's feet is an instinctive need of every human being, and no man is powerful enough to overcome it. One's native land offers spiritual sustenance to man, and humanity must have spiritual sustenance. Only those who have never known spiritual hunger, can survive without spiritual sustenance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1295.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What is this spiritual sustenance which only the native land can supply, and without which life becomes gloomy and dismal? It is the mother tongue; it is the song, the music, the literature, the customs, and the characteristics [of the native land]. Poor and rich, commoners and aristocrats, educated and illiterate, even extreme revolutionaries, who in principle reject patriotism or nationalism--all need this spiritual food. Among our Russians there is a saying: "No matter how good it is to be a guest, it is still better to be a host." In other words, no matter how much one enjoys life among strangers, it's still more enjoyable to be among one's own. This is what has happened to us. Many of us here have tried to smother our feelings and our craving for our native land, but we have failed. The more we have tried to suppress our sentiments, the stronger they appear.</p>
   <p>Formerly, when we thought that some day we would return to our native land, the feeling of homesickness was not so acute. Now, when we have completely given <pb facs="5423967_3_1296.jpg" n="4"/>up hope of ever returning home, we yearn for the homeland as a child yearns for his lost mother.</p>
   <p>Here, in a faraway strange land, we hunger to be united in a closely knit family. This unity first developed around RNzOV. During the past two years our organization has doubled its membership. Several new branches have sprung up and their membership increases every day. The membership of the old established branches also grows, both in quantity and quality. There is no doubt that in several years, RNzOV will be the focus of attention not only in Chicago, but in the whole Middle West.</p>
   <p>Why has RNzOV recently begun to attract the attention of the Russians in Chicago and to command greater respect from the Russian colony in the city and the surrounding territory? This situation has developed because our society has proved to be the only nonpartisan Russian organization that is able to stand on its own feet. Our society, unlike RNOV (Russian People's Mutual Aid Society], which sold out to Novyi Mir [Communist newspaper] and through it to <pb facs="5423967_3_1297.jpg" n="5"/>the International Workers' Order, has not lost its Russian identity. Even though at present several members have fallen victims to Deviatkin's [Communist leader] propaganda and blandishments, and have left our society and gone over to the Communist-controlled camp, nevertheless, there will come a time when these members will realize their mistake and will ask to be readmitted to our fold. For the present, however, they are victims to Shkliar [Communist leader] and Deviatkin's schemes because they are too credulous and do not realize that they are following the footsteps of those who are intent on misleading them. Life will teach them, however, as it has taught many others, whom they should follow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
