<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1930-01-24">Jan. 24, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Chernov's Lecture on Soviet Russia.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0810</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0810.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1930-01-24">Jan. 24, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">CHERNOV'S LECTURE ON SOVIET RUSSIA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite the predictions of the communist official organ, the Daily Worker, that Mr. V. M. Chernov will get the same reception in Chicago as he got in San Francisco, where he was attacked by the local communists, his lecture last Wednesday in Chicago was a success. Present at the lecture were several communists, who caused no disturbance surprisingly enough, but attentively listened to Chernov's criticism of the famous Soviet five year plan. Mr. Chernov based his lecture on facts and data obtained from recent official Soviet publications. From these data he drew his conclusion as to the practicability of these grand Soviet plans.</p>
   <p>The five year plan, according to the Soviet papers, is carried on so successfully that the program of the project of the socialization of industry and of the collectivization of farming will be fulfilled before the indicated time. The speeding of the project has, certainly, increased the sum assigned in the budget, which has has reached the amount of 11,500,000,000 roubles. From what sources does the Soviet Government expect to obtain this money?</p>
   <p>By indirect taxes they could extract from the population only a few billion <pb facs="5423967_3_0811.jpg" n="2"/>roubles. The rest of the amount is covered by issuing "greenbacks" which will depreciate the Soviet currency.</p>
   <p>On the industrial front the Soviet government puts all its energy into creating the heavy industry, while the light industry is disregarded. As a result, the population suffers from a chronic goods' famine. According to the avowal of one Soviet economist, the share of each individual in Soviet Russia is onehalf meter of woolen fabric per year. At the end of the five year plan it is estimated that this figure will be raised to one meter per man. With hides and consumers' goods the situation is still worse. And that is why even a Soviet economist asks the question: "Is it possible to reach socialism bear-footed?"</p>
   <p>The Peasants Storm the Collective Farms.</p>
   <p>Mr. Chernov, states that the socialization of the villages took an unexpected turn for the Bolsheviks. The peasants flocked to the collective farms. The Bolsheviks promised them wages for eight hours per day in the collective farms, with extra pay for overtime and free meals. The peasants most willingly agreed to all these terms.</p>
   <p>What happened in reality? The result was that the collective farms and state <pb facs="5423967_3_0812.jpg" n="3"/>farms, under that system of labor, proved to be unprofitable. Who had to cover the state farms' deficit? Naturally, the state! From what sources can the state draw its revenue? By means of taxing those farmers, who conduct individually their farms. But if they collective all the peasants, who will be the "goats" to cover the state and collective farms' deficit?</p>
   <p>It is clear, that the Soviet government kills the hen that lays the golden eggs. Perceiving this, the Bolsheviks decided to proceed slowly with the collectivization of the villages. The peasants, for example, under threat of severe punishment, are prohibited to slaughter their cattle and to liquidate their household effects. Mr. Chernov indicated that under the present Soviet tax policy the enmity between the city and village is unavoidable. The Soviet industrial goods are three times more expensive than similar goods on the world market; and at the same time the Bolsheviks take the peasants' crop and pay for it far below the regular market price. In 1913, the peasants netted from the rouble received for his corn 70 copecks, while in 1926 - 1927 he netted only 42 - 43 copecks.</p>
   <p>There is no equality in the field of taxation, nor in the earning of wages, between the peasant and the city worker. The annual income of the peasant does not exceed on an average 229 roubles, while the average earnings of the city <pb facs="5423967_3_0813.jpg" n="4"/>workers are 693 roubles. The inequality is much more conspicuous in comparing the living expenses of both concerned. The yearly budget of the city worker is estimated at 222 roubles, while that of the peasant is only 74 roubles.</p>
   <p>In politics the same inequality exists; the vote of one city worker equals the votes of five peasants. In general, according to the opinion of Mr. Chernov, the Soviet five year plan is based on wrong principles and leads the country towards a disaster. The condition of the Soviet population is not improving; it is becoming worse. In the cities the lack of goods is felt also in food stuffs. The former days of famine of the "military" period of communism are restored.</p>
   <p>Mr. Chernov finds that the fundamental mistake of the communists consists in this, that they consider the restoration of heavy industry as the main corneratone of the five year plan. One should begin the construction of the industrial building not from the roof, but from its foundation, i. e. from light industry, which serves the vast majority of the population consisting of peasants. Funds, spent for the construction of the Dnepr power plant and similar projects, should be used for the improvement and help of the agricultural industry, which is the live nerve of the country. After strengthening the <pb facs="5423967_3_0814.jpg" n="5"/>foundation - agricultural industry - one could proceed with the building of the upper structure of the commonwealth. The Bolsheviks act just the other way. They build the upper structure on a weak foundation full of cracks, which well might crumble at any time and cause a catastrophe.</p>
   <p>Questions and Answers.</p>
   <p>Following the lecture,which lasted about three hours, the lecturer answered various questions put to him verbally and in writing. His answers were sharp-witted and irrefutable. The following straightforward question was put to Mr. Chernov: "In other words, if Mr. Chernov was in power in place of the Bolsheviks, then everything would be O. K.?"</p>
   <p>Mr. Chernov's answer was as follows: "I do not claim that everything would be O. K. I only insist on this, that the population should be asked whether it considers the Bolshevik regime to be good or bad? But this is exactly what the Bolsheviks avoid to find out. If I were in their place, the first thing I would do, would be to put this question before the people fearlessly."</p>
   <p>From further questions and answers the attitude of Chernov becomes clear. He <pb facs="5423967_3_0815.jpg" n="6"/>does not wish new upheavals and revolutions in Soviet Russia, where already enough blood was shed and enough suffering endured. The present Soviet policy, destructive and ruinous for the country, may bring about new disasters. The communists must renounce their dictatorial methods. The Bolsheviks annihilated the other political groups and parties and have reached the point where they abolished the right to free thinking and free speech, depriving of these rights the members of their own party - even such former leaders as Trotsky, Zinoviev, Bukharin, Rykov, etc.</p>
   <p>In Soviet Russia, the democratization of the Bolshevik party, the Soviets institutions, etc., has become necessary. And because the Bolshevik regime has deprived the citizens of the right of freely expressing their will, this regime is not safe from a revolutionary upheaval.</p>
   <p>A Soviet Specialist Has a Word to Say.</p>
   <p>Present at the lecture was a Soviet specialist, who had recently arrived from Russia, and who participated in the creation of the five year plan. He expressed the wish to say a few words. This was willingly granted to him. The audience was amused by his speech.. This is what he said: "In Soviet Russia everything is planned in advance; the Soviet plans are very good, we <pb facs="5423967_3_0816.jpg" n="7"/>cannot make a step without a plan. We have plans for everything. The only misfortune is that we miss the money. According to the plan, for example, it is required to spend three hundred million roubles on a project, but in the state treasury we have not got even thirty cents. One can easily imagine the consequences...</p>
   <p>"The Soviet Government in carrying out the five year plan, lacks seven billion dollars. This sum cannot be obtained from the country. If America should give this amount, then the five year plan could be realized." He finished his speech thus: "Things are going well in Soviet Russia, all is done according to some plan, but one cannot live there."..</p>
   <p>The lecture lasted until midnight. The public listened with great interest and rewarded the talented lecturer with stormy applause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
