<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-07-07">July 7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Threat to the Russian School</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0500</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0500.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-07-07">July 7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE THREAT TO THE RUSSIAN SCHOOL</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian school in Chicago is under the threat of a definitive seizure by the local pseudo-communists. As we already have said, the bolshevist elements, who broke into the schools two weeks before the convocation of the conference and in their usual manner had prepared a bogus representation, are definitely moving toward taking the education of our children into their hands.</p>
   <p>Extremely significant is the circumstance, that the conference just closed began with deliberation about the Russkii Viestnik and ended with the same kind of talk. It was not a school conference, but a typical bolshevist orgy of gabble, a garrulous exchange of words. In spite of the energetic protest of the representative of the "R. V." who was present at the conference, he was forced to keep his mouth shut by the obedient majority of the pseudo-bolsheviks (6 against 4; 3 abstained from voting).</p>
   <p>An unheard of insult was thrown at all the teaching staff of the schools, who were deprived of the right of a deciding vote.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0501.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The leaders of the conference, having noticed at the first session the representatives of the influential South Side School and having counted the number of votes, correctly estimated that if the right of a deciding vote is granted the teachers, they, the Communists, will not get the necessary majority. And thereupon the delegates of an unknown, insignificant school as the "East Chicago" one having only five pupils, were allowed the right of a deciding vote, while the basic element of the schools, their teachers, was graciously allowed to make only recommendations, leaving the discussion of such recommendations to the obedient Communist "nurses," the delegates not without reason the most valuable worker of the Brighton Park school, who enjoys a well-deserved good reputation among the Russian colony, declared that he does not wish to be present as a doll on a regular political show arranged by the bolsheviks, and left the conference.</p>
   <p>Not without reason did the teachers of the South Side School declare, that if they were not allowed the right of a deciding vote, they would not appear at the conference.</p>
   <p>The old, well tried masters of the art of falsifying public opinion have <pb facs="5423967_3_0502.jpg" n="3"/>managed at this time also to conduct the affair of the now closed conference in the spirit which suits them. By means of the votes of the delegates of the insignificant East Chicago School they put through all the resolutions of the conference, prepared by them beforehand.</p>
   <p>And these delegates raised their hands only when the leaders, or the Communist "nurses" raised them. In spite of the statement of one of the most active Chicago pedagogues, J. Voronko, that the leaders of Communism had signally failed in their desire to falsify the work of the conference, because one of the most important points of their program (namely the one concerning the executive committee) was rejected, we nevertheless declare that the conference was conducted and concluded according to the preconceived designs of the local pseudo-communists. Those of the teacher-delegates who were most passive and completely ignorant in regard to the simplest questions proved to be a splendid field for the activities of our local humdrum communist babblers. They are working only where it is dark; where there is yet a possibility of throwing dust in people's eyes; where they still listen to them. We intend to throw light in these dark corners of the Russian school. The workers' paper will carry on its work, elucidating the school-problem and proving with facts on hand the evil of the admission <pb facs="5423967_3_0503.jpg" n="4"/>within the schools of communist blockheads of American stamp. The The banishment of the communist and Bolshevist elements from the school is the next problem of the parents and pedagogues of Chicago who are working in the field of education.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
