<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-08">Oct. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Profanation of Russian Art</title><title level="a" type="sub">About Russian Radio Programs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-08">Oct. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROFANATION OF RUSSIAN ART</title><title level="a" type="sub">About Russian Radio Programs</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many Russians in America no doubt listen to the Russian radio programs presented regularly by the National Broadcasting Company of New York on their coast-to-coast network. These splendid programs (the Samovar, the Symphonic Choir, and the Siberian Choir) are doing a great service to Russian art. Some local radio stations often feature Russian music--the works of such composers as Tschaikovsky, Rimsky-Korsakov, Rachmaninov, and others. There are American artists who study the Russian language in order to be able to sing Russian songs in Russian--Jessica Dragonette, for example. These facts indicate the high regard in which Russian music and Russian song are held by the cultured American public.</p>
   <p>Russian art, however, is frequently the victim of profanation and defilement at the hands of the Russians themselves. Here in Chicago, we have a Russian <pb facs="5423967_3_0168.jpg" n="2"/>radio program which is a denial, a travesty, a desecration of Russian art. The promoter of this program, some enterprising Russian, does not seem to worry much about the artistic aspect of his program or about the good reputation of Russian art in America. His interests are purely commercial. Almost the entire hour of this so-called Russian program is taken up with commercial announcements. To keep the radio audience from turning off the program and switching to some other station, this audacious promoter treats his listeners to some old-country music, usually phonographic reproductions. And this is not all. This obliging promoter knows how to utilize the names and the works of great Russian singers and composers to satisfy the vulgar tastes of some of his listeners and sponsors. For instance, he plays a recording by Chaliapin, or Maria Kurenko, or Smirnova, the great Russian singer of gypsy songs, and announces that this or that song or piece of music is dedicated to this or that tavernkeeper, or to an undertaker whose wife is celebrating her birthday or who has just returned from a successful fishing trip. This practice is a most outrageous desecration of Russian art. There <pb facs="5423967_3_0169.jpg" n="3"/>should be a law forbidding such practices. Musical societies and authors of musical compositions should have a right to institute court action against radio stations and individuals who prostitute the high art of music to their own vulgar ends.</p>
   <p>Tavernkeepers, politicians, manufacturers of proprietary medicines, shoe stores, and similar establishments, pay this promoter a few paltry dollars for cheap advertisement of their wares, and he dedicates to them the gems of Russian music and song. The whole thing becomes still more painful when we realize that this vulgar profanation of Russian art is being practiced by the Russians themselves, and that our groups and our societies do nothing to put an end to this infamy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
