<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>In Memoriam:</title><date when="1935-11-10">Nov. 10, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">On the Day of Consecration of the Shrine St. and Great Sufferer George the Conqueror, Chicago</title>, <date when="1935">1935</date>, p. 3.
<title level="a" type="sub">The Development of Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society Since 1912</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>In Memoriam:</title><date when="1935-11-10">Nov. 10, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">On the Day of Consecration of the Shrine St. and Great Sufferer George the Conqueror, Chicago</title>, <date when="1935">1935</date>, p. 3.
<title level="a" type="sub">THE DEVELOPMENT OF RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT MUTUAL AID SOCIETY SINCE 1912</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today it is quite appropriate to glance back upon the history of the St. George Parish, and also of the brotherhoods and sisterhoods of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, as well as of the People's Bank, all located at 917 N. Wood Street.</p>
   <p>These organizations are playing a role not only on Wood Street, but in the whole of Chicago and vicinity.</p>
   <p>From the day of founding of this brotherhood twenty-four years have passed, but this time has flashed by as if only a few days.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1191.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1912 a small group of Russian peasants and workers, emigrants from Grodno, Minsk and Wolyn, resolved to live independently and take the task of organizing the Russian people into their hands. This was five years previous to the Russian Revolution.</p>
   <p>At that time the Independents were called revolutionists.</p>
   <p>Having organized, they selected the name of St. George the Conqueror for their organization.</p>
   <p>They all began working like ants for the welfare of their organization. And lo! how much work and disillusion has fallen upon the shoulders of the St. Georgians!</p>
   <p>They began recruiting new members, but it was not sufficient to exist <pb facs="5423967_3_1192.jpg" n="3"/>without an ideal which unites everybody; it was an impossibility.</p>
   <p>During that same year they decided to organize a society of mutual aid, which at present bears the name of Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
   <p>Things of value have been done by the Independents for the Russian colony in Chicago during this time. They began opening Russian children's schools in all corners of Chicago, which had not existed until this time in our colony. These schools have brought the people around the St. George parish of the first section and new society of mutual aid.</p>
   <p>Soon after other sections were formed, such as the South Side second section, the St. Vladimir section of the Holy Trinity in Argo, and the Blessed Virgin in Indiana Harbor, Ind.; Benton Harbor, Mich.; Detroit and Baltimore, and in other locations. In due time a large Russian society of mutual aid has grown.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1193.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Georgians have organized the first Russian daily newspaper in Chicago, which the Russian colony until then had not possessed. Shortly after, this newspaper and a well-equipped printing plant were sold for lack of workers and means. At present this printing plant is the property of the newspaper Rassviet.</p>
   <p>Some time later the Georgians opened their bank on 917 Wood Street, which is still in existence, having been successful under the name of Russian National Savings Society. This bank has helped materially all their members and people in the colony during the time of depression.</p>
   <p>Were the entire Russian colony in the city of Chicago working as are the Independents of this colony, our entire colony, on the strength of natural prestige, would not get behind other nationalities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1194.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Very often the Independents have helped not only their own members, but also outsiders, widows, and orphans, and have paid out to people in the Russian colony about a half million dollars.</p>
   <p>Today, November 10, 1935, the Georgians are celebrating a holiday, - the consecration of the new shrine and the entrance into a gorgeous hall, for which the Independents have worked so hard.</p>
   <p>It is time for the Russian citizens to think about their condition in the United States and join the ranks of the Independent Mutual Aid Society in order to work for the welfare of the entire Russian colony. Only in unity there is strength.</p>
   <p>Long live the union of the entire Russian colony in one common family in America!</p>
   <p>V. N. Sabinsky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
