<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-18">Mar. 18, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Interesting Lecture on Pushkin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0704</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0704.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-18">Mar. 18, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">INTERESTING LECTURE ON PUSHKIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday E. Z. Moravsky delivered a very interesting lecture on Pushkin. The lecturer for an hour and a half spoke on Pushkin as a fighter for freedom, supporting his viewpoint on the great Russian writer by citing numerous passages from his works and from some of the letters written by the poet to his friends. The cardinal aim of the lecturer was to prove by documentary evidence that Pushkin was not only a great Russian national poet, the greatest cultural and literary reformer of Russia, but also one of her first fighters for the people's freedom.</p>
   <p>The lecture was attended by some fifty people, among whom one could not help noting Bishop Leonty. After the lecture Bishop Leonty personally and in the name of the other listeners thanked Mr. Moravsky for his fine exposition of the subject, and Mme. P. Svatikova, who presided, in her closing words expressed the desire that Mr. Moravsky might repeat his lecture before a larger audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0705.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The lecture was given under the auspices of the Pushkin Committee of Chicago. Mme. Svatikova also announced that in the near future the Pushkin Committee will give two more lectures on the life and works of the great poet. In the first lecture Mme. Svatikova will speak on "Pushkin and His Language," and in the second Mr. Voronko will speak on "Pushkin and Children".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
