<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-06">July 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal of the Editorial Committee of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1205</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1205.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-06">July 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL OF THE EDITORIAL COMMITTEE OF THE RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT MUTUAL AID SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In beginning the task of editing the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society's news page in Rassviet, a task entrusted to us by the Board of Directors of this organization, we realize that one of the most responsible functions of our organization has been deposited in our hands.</p>
   <p>The house organ, in this case the news page, of an organization is a mirror reflecting the life of the organization; it is also an inspiration and a motive power, moving the organization ahead to progress and success.</p>
   <p>In order to fulfill our task successfully, we appeal to the members of the Board of Directors, to the chairmen and the secretaries of all branches, and to all members of our organization, for full co-operation with the Editorial Committee in the building and expansion program of our Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1206.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We also appeal to all the branch committees to send in all their reports on time, so as to avoid costly delays in publishing the decisions and other important material pertaining to the life of the branches and bearing a direct relation to the further growth and development of our organization.</p>
   <p>Today, when the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society has just emerged victoriously from the blows it sustained during the political upheaval within and without the organization, it is especially important that all our undertakings be planned with care and executed with speed and efficiency. The future security, success, and happiness of our Society depend upon our firmness and our solidarity, and upon the strong unity of all members of the organization. The unreserved solidarity of all members of the organization will enable its directors to bring to a successful end the great youth program now in the process of development. The fundamental purpose of this program is the training of the Russian-American youth in the Russian spirit and Russian culture.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1207.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is the sacred duty of every member of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, irrespective of the position he holds in the organization, to value highly his Society, to support its program, and to give full measure of his sincere co-operation in the fulfillment of the plans and undertakings essential for the continuous growth and expansion of the organization.</p>
   <p>Every member of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society should always remember that his organization is one big family of which he is an important member, and that the well-being of that family depends on his active co-operation in all its vital functions.</p>
   <p>The two most urgent tasks now facing the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society are to increase the membership and to complete the buildings now under construction. Both these undertakings can be successfully and speedily accomplished with the unity and support of all branches and of all members of the organization. We hope that we shall soon be able to unfurl our national flag over our new building on Wood Street. Our new building will be the <pb facs="5423967_3_1208.jpg" n="4"/>center of Russian culture, which will radiate far and wide, sowing the seed of the Russian spirit among hundreds of thousands of young Russian-Americans.</p>
   <p>To you members of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, we make this appeal: Carry high the banner of your organization; let all Russians see it!Tell them to join the Independent Society, invite then to participate in the great constructive work for a better future for themselves and for their children!</p>
   <p>The Editorial Committee of the</p>
   <p>Russian Independent Mutual Aid</p>
   <p>Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
