<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>,
<date when="1924-09-19">Sept. 19, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Courses for Teachers of Adults</title><title level="a" type="sub">(By M. I. Volkov)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_0451</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0451.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-09-19">Sept. 19, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">COURSES FOR TEACHERS OF ADULTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(By M. I. Volkov)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The idea of courses for teachers is in the process of realization. The Executive Committee of the School Council of the Federation of Russian Schools has given its sanction to the program of these courses which will be called "Russian Courses for General Education and for Teachers."</p>
   <p>Two years will be required in order to complete the program of these courses. Each school year will consist of three terms. The lectures will be given in the evenings of five days of the week, two hours daily. Thus each student will be attending the courses for 10 hours every week.</p>
   <p>The program of the courses has been arranged so that every student may get a general education in all the most important branches of <pb facs="5423967_3_0452.jpg" n="2"/>knowledge and at the same time may prepare himself for teaching children in Russian schools if he will decide to take up this useful public activity.</p>
   <p>Program of the first term of the first year, i. e., this autumn's:</p>
   <p>English language- 2 hours; Russian language- 3 hours; arithmetic- 3 hours; Russian history- 2 hours.</p>
   <p>Second term of the first year, from New Year to the end of March: English language - 2 hours; Russian language - 3 hours; arithmetic - 2 hours; Russian history - 1 hour; geography - 1 hour; hygiene - 1 hour.</p>
   <p>Third term of the first year, in the spring: English language - 2 hours; Russian language - 3 hours; arithmetic - 2 hours; history of the United States - 1 hour; geography - 1 hour; hygiene - 1 hour.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_0453.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>First term of the second year: English language - 1 hour; Russian language - 2 hours; geography - 1 hour; natural science - 2 hours; physics - 1 hour; algebra - 1 hour; pedagogics - 2 hours.</p>
   <p>Second term of the second year: English language - 2 hours; Russian language - 2 hours; geology - 1 hour; chemistry - 1 hour; algebra -1 hour; history of the struggle of the Russian people for freedom -1 hour; pedagogics - 2 hours.</p>
   <p>Third term of the second year: English language - 2 hours; Russian language - 3 hours; political economy and jurisprudence - 2 hours; geometry - 1 hour, and pedagogics - 2 hours.</p>
   <p>Besides these subjects during the second and third terms of the second year these students who are preparing themselves for taking up teaching will have every week two or more hours of practice in schools for children.</p>
   <p>Such is the official program of these courses. But besides that the <pb facs="5423967_3_0454.jpg" n="4"/>administration of the courses intends to give a course of elementary study of the Russian language for those Russians who in their childhood have had no opportunity to learn to read and write Russian. Such a course, under the name of "preparatory course," will be given if there will be a demand for it.</p>
   <p>The administration does not doubt that among these who will register as students there will be persons who possess already considerably more knowledge than that which is required for attending the first term. Such students will be given the opportunity to complete their studies in a shorter time. In order to enable them to do so arrangements will be made allowing them to attend, besides their regular lectures, also lectures on some of the subjects taught during the succeeding terms of the first or second year. In other words, all that is possible will be done for satisfying all those who want to study.</p>
   <p>A scientific library will be organized in connection with the courses.</p>
   <p>The idea of organizing these courses was born among the workmen <pb facs="5423967_3_0455.jpg" n="5"/>themselves who were feeling the need of improving their education. The School Conference of last June had decided to realize this idea. And the workmen from the rank and file who were members of the School Council were the very soul of this endeavor; from them emanated the stimulus in all the preparatory work connected with the organization of the courses. It can be said truly that all this undertaking is the work of workmen who know what they want and are able to achieve it.</p>
   <p>It is intended to open the courses in the very beginning of October. The admission fee will be three dollars a month. Applications have to be mailed to the following address: M. I. Volkoff, 2037 Forestville Avenue, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
