<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-23">Mar. 23, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">News from Pullman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_3_1375</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_3_1375.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-23">Mar. 23, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM PULLMAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large and progressive Russian colony lives in Pullman. For more than ten years, cultural and educational work has been carried on in this suburban Chicago town. One of the oldest Russian children's schools, which is named after A. S. Pushkin, the great Russian poet, is located there. The Pullman branch of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society (RNzOV) was also named after this great writer.</p>
   <p>At present, due mainly to the energetic efforts of Mr. S. I. Levkovich, a new branch (No. 26) has been founded. This new branch of RNzOV was named after M. U. Lomonosov, the great Russian scientist, son of a humble Russian peasant from the village of Denisovka, province of Archangel.</p>
   <p>We hope that both these branches of RNzOV will unite their forces for cultural, educational, and organizational work, that their school will grow in attendance, and that the school will effect the improvements which it needs.</p>
   <p>The Pullman plant is working at full capacity now; workers are being taken on <pb facs="5423967_3_1376.jpg" n="2"/>every day because the management expects to receive heavy orders.</p>
   <p>In the spring, they are planning to erect piers on Pullman lake, and to extend 103rd Street farther South. The Russian colony has been greatly encouraged by these prospects and the present developments. It reveals new energy to go ahead, to do something.</p>
   <p>It has become the usual thing to see the members of the Independent Society in the vanguard of the Russian colony here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
