<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-02">Jan. 2, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Final Steps Taken at Mass Meeting Relative to 1895, a Year of Polish National Mourning</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0858</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0858.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-02">Jan. 2, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">FINAL STEPS TAKEN AT MASS MEETING RELATIVE TO 1895, A YEAR OF POLISH NATIONAL MOURNING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, the first day of 1895, the last steps were taken relative to the method of commemorating 1895 as a year of national mourning throughout St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish at a mass meeting held in the Polish Hall, Bradley and Noble Streets. Several hundred Polish people of the community attended.</p>
   <p>The assembly was opened by Reverend Vincent Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, who acted as chairman; Mr. Steltman acted as recording secretary.</p>
   <p>Reverend Barzynski, who was the initial speaker, pointed out the aims of the meeting. "A hundred years ago we were torn asunder by our enemies," said the pastor, "and here in America, the land of freedom, we are separating ourselves by harboring discord and hatred, dividing into various factions, fighting among ourselves, and wasting the national feeling. Therefore we should carry out a twofold program of mourning! And this is not to be a mourning of groans <pb facs="5423968_9_0859.jpg" n="2"/>and outward demontrations, but one of action. Work toward the national cause, unity, sorrow for the faults, strong desire for education--these are to be its aims," Reverend Barzynski concluded.</p>
   <p>"It is not necessary for us to wear any mark of mourning", stated Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, the second speaker of the evening, "but all that is necessary is a sincere sorrow in our hearts. There is need for work among our Polish youth in America; for it requires moral instructions as well as knowledge about Poland. This can be the greatest monument offered to our country a century after her fall, during this year of sorrow. We need to establish evening and Sunday schools, organize our youth, and give it the ten commandments of love for the fatherland," he avered.</p>
   <p>The Polish youth was called upon by Mr. Skaryszewski to safeguard its native tongue and spirit.</p>
   <p>The rearing of our youth was discussed by Ignacy Kowalski. He pointed out the influence that can be exerted by the parents--and called upon the parents to keep a careful watch over their children. He urged the parents to see that <pb facs="5423968_9_0860.jpg" n="3"/>their children fulfill the duties of the school, watch their after-school activity and set up organizations for them.</p>
   <p>Henry Nagiel in his talk urged the people to be generous in support of the Polish League, which fosters Polish culture, especially the development of reading rooms, libraries and national publications.</p>
   <p>A short speech was also given by W. Pyterek, who urged the people to commemorate this coming year, and educate our children. "Our youth is the key which some day will open the locks of our shackles, they are the tools which will cast aside the heavy stones of bondage. The white eagle will then fly and Poland will awaken," said Mr. Pyterek.</p>
   <p>Peter Kiolbassa was the final speaker to take the stand. He summarized the important points of the previous speakers, and gave a plan as to how to observe 1895 as a year of mourning. He especially hoped that the Polish people would strive to eradicate undesirable activities and drunkenness among the Polish people at large, and support education.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0861.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The following resolution was adopted:</p>
   <p>"We, the Polish people, who are gathered at a mass meeting held on January 1, 1895, resolve to:</p>
   <p>"1. Observe 1895 as a year of national mourning through the accumulation of strength and the elevation of the spirit, unity, harmony, and national work; further, by avoiding undesirable and demoralizing activity and striving to avoid scandals; finally, by thriftiness and by supporting general public causes--and to convene once a month relative to our work for the national cause.</p>
   <p>"2. Work during the course of this year of national mourning by striving for the awakening of our faith and the moral and cultural development of our youth through the organization of evening and Sunday schools, and the creation of youth organizations with the support of parents and guardians.</p>
   <p>"3. Especially contribute toward the support of education, and, above all, <pb facs="5423968_9_0862.jpg" n="5"/>help to establish Polish libraries and reading rooms, arrange lectures and support Polish publications printed in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
