<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-14">Feb. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Lincoln-Kosciusko Birthday Anniversary Observed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0428</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0428.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-14">Feb. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LINCOLN-KOSCIUSKO BIRTHDAY ANNIVERSARY OBSERVED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The day before yesterday in the evening, a celebration in observance of the birthday anniversary of Abraham Lincoln and Thaddeus Kosciusko was held under the auspices of the Chicago Society, Group 1450, Polish National Alliance, at the Pulaski Park Hall at Noble and Blackhawk Streets, to a capacity audience. The crowd was so large that many persons, unable to enter the hall, had to return disappointed to their homes.</p>
   <p>T. Szmergalski presided. The program was an interesting one, and was excellently executed. It consisted of speeches, music, vocal numbers, both group and solo, and recitations.</p>
   <p>Anthony Czarnecki spoke in Polish long and ardently on the life and deeds of Kosciusko on both hemispheres; while Judge J. P. McGoorty spoke in English on the lie of Lincoln. Judge McGoorty's address was a very beautiful one. He compared Kosciusko with Lincoln and President Wilson, for the first two fought for freedom and the peoples' rights just as Wilson is doing at the present time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0429.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The speaker expressed his admiration of the Poles and also his hope that Poland would be free and united; for this he was rewarded with generous applause.</p>
   <p>Other numbers of the program deserving of praise were: a musical trio composed of Messrs. Orzada, Mrozinski, and Richards, a recitation by V. Jozwiakowski, a violin solo by Orzada to the piano accompaniment of Mrozinski, a duet by Misses E. Stachowicz and H. Gilso (violin and violoncello), a violoncello solo by J. Richards, and another trio composed of Orzada, Mrozinski, and Richards. There was also a dance in two parts by Miss Mary Mallek. To conclude the program, the audience sang the Polish and American national anthems.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Society, Group 1450 of the Polish National Alliance, can congratulate itself upon the great success of the evening. It deserves acknowledgment for providing such a splendid spiritual treat.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
