<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-29">Aug. 29, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Falcons Meet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-29">Aug. 29, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH FALCONS MEET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great meeting, held for the purpose of promoting Falconry among the Poles in America, took place on Sunday evening at Groenwald's Hall on Holt Street. The meeting was called to order by J. Adamowski, who called upon Judge [M. A.] La Buy to act as chairman, and L. Nowak to serve as secretary.</p>
   <p>The first speaker was Dr. Dunikowski. The speaker outlined the aims of Falconry, urging support of the movement. He expressed his best wishes for the developement of Falconry in America. Dr. Dunikowski further explained the developement of Falconry in Europe; himself a Falcon of Lwow, he extended that organization's best wishes. The next speaker, Dr. C. Midowicz, spoke of the friendliness, the brotherhood that he observes amongst Falcons. As a physician, he recommended the exercise prescribed by Falcons. These exercises, he said, by developing the body physically, render it a more fitting abode for the soul.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0216.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In a short address, Dr. Janczewski reaffirmed the statements of the two previous speakers. He was followed by Judge La Buy, who made a humorous speech urging the Polish youth to become Falcons.</p>
   <p>Mr. Dorszynski explained the difficulties which had to be overcome in organizing the first Falcon nests in America, and he pointed out the degree to which the organization has thus far developed.</p>
   <p>In general, the meeting was a success. The hall was filled and enthusiasm for the Falcon movement was pronounced; a few score prominent citizens enrolled as Falcons immediately. On a motion by Dr. Dunikowski, it was decided that another such meeting will be held at Pulaski Hall during the convention of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
