<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-28">Nov. 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Commemoration of the November Insurrection</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0578</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0578.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-28">Nov. 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">COMMEMORATION OF THE NOVEMBER INSURRECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The eighty-first anniversary of the November Insurrection was celebrated yesterday in Holy Trinity Parish, with zeal and a lofty nationalistic spirit. The program, which was prepared and performed at the school hall by the literary circle, greatly appealed to the audience, which, by its conduct, indicated that it always appreciates all matters regarding the homeland, and wished to show its gratitude to its kind enlighteners and directors. The program, indeed, consisted of unusual numbers, and in general was well-performed. To this was added the colorfulness of song, the charm of artistic music, and the sweetness of Polish speech.</p>
   <p>We give you here a short summary of the entire program.....</p>
   <p>The culminating point of the program was the splendid address of Prof. R. Piatkowski. He gave the readers a vivid picture of the November Insurrection <pb facs="5423968_9_0579.jpg" n="2"/>and the causes which provoked it. In his speech he clearly tried to present the actions of the Poles, especially of the young people, in their attempt to throw off the Russian yoke. He also did not neglect to mention the two great young people's societies which were organized in Lithuania, namely the Filareci and the Filomaci, which produced some of the finest people: Adam Miczkiewicz, Zan, Goszczynski, and others. Nowosilow broke up these societies in the most brutal way.</p>
   <p>"Although the Insurrection was put down", continued the speaker, "the spirit of the nation was not put down. The Insurrection left a memorable example of love for the Homeland, for future generations to emulate." Toward the end he encouraged the young people to form educational groups, to preserve the virtues of their fathers and to foster the Polish language and customs. To the most deserving Professor we extend our sincere gratitude.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The rest of the program is given, number by number, with a description of each.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
