<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-10">Apr. 10, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Organizacya Patriotyczna Makes its First Public Appearance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0227</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0227.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-10">Apr. 10, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZACYA PATRIOTYCZNA MAKES ITS FIRST PUBLIC APPEARANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Organizacya Patriotyczna (Patriotic Organization) made its first public appearance before a large audience. The Poles, realizing that their duty is to support this organization, attended in great numbers, showing once more their willingness to participate in nationalistic work.</p>
   <p>The program opened with a short address by Mr. Ligman, president of the Organization. This address was followed by the beautiful and inspiring "Modlitwa" (Prayer), sung by a young women's choir. The singing over, Reverend Vincent Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church, spoke on the history of the Patriotic Organization, of which he is the founder. He traced the extensive activities of the Organization during its five years of existence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0228.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Father Barzynski said that after long and arduous missionary work in Chicago, home of the most populous Polish settlement, the time had finally come for a concentrated effort to direct the people's minds toward youth and the Polish cause. The Patriotic Organization was founded on May 3, 1888. It had to overcome great difficulties at first but, thanks to the perseverance of a few members, it already has begun to show results. Today it is a society with a large membership composed of people to whom the nationalistic cause lies close to heart, and its work continues energetically. Its members work wholeheartedly together. The Falcons, the Knights, the Cadets, the Library, the Parish Choir, the Dramatic Circle--all are the offshoots of noble efforts to uplift the soul, to develop the youth, and to give profitable recreation and enlightenment. In the course of its existence, the Organization has contributed considerable sums of money to the Polish cause. It offered, first of all, five hundred dollars for the relief of flood victims in Galicia, one hundred dollars to Polish orphans, two hundred dollars to the parish library, one hundred dollars for the relief of the Unites <pb facs="5423968_9_0229.jpg" n="3"/>[United Greek Church] in Ukrainia. The organization has also covered the costs of the protest against the American extradition treaty with Russia. During the past five years, the Organization has spent a thousand dollars, a sum accumulated from the collection of ten-cent monthly dues. Father Barzynski spoke eloquently during his outline of the Organization's activities, calling it "an army fighting for truth and nationalism". He urged everyone to join. The speaker's noble words were rewarded by great applause.</p>
   <p>Mr. Andrew Kwasigroch, director of the parish choir, followed with a talk on the benefits derived from singing. He declared that here on foreign soil, the songs of the homeland are the one means of keeping alive the Polish spirit. That he supports his words with deeds, Mr. Kwasigroch proved in the next number, a medley of Polish songs by the parish choir, with piano accompaniment by Madame Rose Kwasigroch.</p>
   <p>The captain of the Polish Queen's Guard, F. Jagus, appeared next and gave <pb facs="5423968_9_0230.jpg" n="4"/>a report of his society's activities. He said that the Guard owes gratitude to Father Barzynski for his initiative. He stated further that, though small in membership, the Guard's enthusiasm is unbounded. Its members are ready at all times to give their lives for Poland. The Guard's military exercises were above reproach.</p>
   <p>Captain John Kochanski appeared next with the Uhlans of Czestochowa. They were followed by the third military society, the Knights of St. Martin, whose captain is Mr. Pokorny. Mr. Pokorny told of how the Knights, organized in 1886, became a part of the Patriotic Organization for the sake of national solidarity.</p>
   <p>Mr. Szczesny Zahajkiewicz made a report of the activities of the Dramatic Circle, of which he is director. It was organized in 1871 with the purpose of arousing patriotism and encouraging the use of the Polish language. The Dramatic Circle possesses a great variety of costumes and has presented <pb facs="5423968_9_0231.jpg" n="5"/>plays which have withstood the severest criticism. In a word, it is one of the best loved of the parish societies.</p>
   <p>After an excellent monologue by Mr. Skolimowski, who called forth a storm of applause, another choral number followed.</p>
   <p>The elder Falcons appeared next, and their chaplain, Father Bernard Zmijewski, discussed the principle of "a sound mind in a healthy body". The speaker continued with a statement that the Falcons were organized through the efforts of Mr. Zahajkiewicz. He said that the chief aim of the Falcons is to create unity and brotherly love: "one will, one spirit". His ardent words were very warmly applauded. The Falcons executed their drills under the direction of Mr. B. Malinski.</p>
   <p>Then followed the beloved Cadets. Their chaplain, Father Eugene Siedlaczek, introduced them and spoke of the society's aims. He gave new significance <pb facs="5423968_9_0232.jpg" n="6"/>to the word "liberty" to such exiles as we. Our brethren in Poland are not permitted to organize, but in this free land we have every right to do all that we can for our homeland. The youth ought to be organized so that some day, under the slogan "God and our Country", everybody working together will help raise our country out of bondage. This speech, so filled with noble thoughts, was interrupted time and again by the applause of the enthusiastic audience. The exercises executed by the Cadets were, of course, irreproachable.</p>
   <p>We come thus to the conclusion of the program. Another monologue by Mr. Skolimowski provoked peals of laughter, and he retired amidst thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>The hour was already late. There were some exercises by the younger Falcons, whose smart appearance delighted the audience. Then followed the singing of "Boze coz Polske" (Lord, For Poland), and with this the program ended.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0233.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The Organization's public performance was eminently successful in every way. More than one person left the hall resolved to help its fruitful work with deed and money, to give their children this opportunity for recreation and education. Oh, that there might be thousands of co-workers gained thus!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
