<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-11">Apr. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of the Central Polish Relief Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-11">Apr. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF THE CENTRAL POLISH RELIEF COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: This article begins with a list of out-of-town delegates who came to the convention.]</p>
   <p>The local delegates were T. M. Helinski, president of the Central Polish Relief Committee; Reverend S. Zapala, president; K. Zychlinski, Joseph Magdziarz, S. Napieralski; Mrs. A. Neuman, Reverend F. Wojtalewicz, Mrs. M. Kaczanowski, Mrs. M. Milewski, P. Rostenkowski, J.S. Rybicki, Miss E. Napieralski, N. L. Piotrowski, and S. Osada.</p>
   <p>At 9:45 A. M., Mr. F. F. Fronczak, second president, opened the convention and asked Reverend Zapala to lead the prayer. The secretary read the list of members of the Central Polish Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>Dr. Fronczak, after having sworn in the new members, welcomed those present and delivered a short speech in which he emphasized the importance of the <pb facs="5423968_9_1258.jpg" n="2"/>time during which the convention is being held. He asked that, first of all, those present honor the memory of Henryk Sienkiewicz by rising. He said a few warm words in memory of this deceased leader of the nation. He then called upon the president, Mr. T. M. Helinski, to make his report.</p>
   <p>President T. M. Helinski read his report. A motion was made to accept the report; it was carried.</p>
   <p>The following people were appointed to the Motions Committee: Reverend Zapala, Mrs. A. Neuman, and Dr. Wagner.</p>
   <p>The following persons were appointed to the Committee on Resolutions: Reverend S. Sobieniowski, S. Napieralski, Mrs. A. Neuman, Mrs. H. Wolowski, Zawadzki, and Stryjak.</p>
   <p>Secretary H. Setmajer read the minutes of the last annual convention.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1259.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The press was represented by Dziennik Zwiazkowy, J. Przyprawa; Dziennik Chicagoski, T. Lasecki; Rekord Codzienny (Daily Record) of Detroit, S. Wusza; Dziennik Narodowy, H. Lokanski; and Sokol Polski; (Polish Falcon), T. Jasiorkowski of Pittsburgh.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the last convention were accepted and the secretary read his administrative and financial report. The reports of the secretary, Mr. Henry Setmajer, and the treasurer, Mr. Joseph Magdziarz, were accepted in principle and sent to the Motions Committee. In the name of the Auditing Commission, Mr. John Rybick; reported that the commission had found the books of the officers of the Central Polish Relief Committee in perfect order and balance. At the same time he complimented the officers on their conscientiousness and order. This report, which was also accepted and sent to the Motion Committee, was followed by reports of other officers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
