<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-27">Nov. 27, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Commemoration of the November Insurrection</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0580</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0580.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-27">Nov. 27, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">COMMEMORATION OF THE NOVEMBER INSURRECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Poles in Evanston, thanks to the efforts of the Casimir Pulaski Society, yesterday commemorated the November Insurrection. It must be emphasized that up to the present time the Poles in Evanston have never had a celebration of this kind. The Polish colony, which is still young, and is occupied with hard, daily labor in the factories, did not have time to think about organizing itself, much less, of organizing celebrations of national memorials. Only the last couple of years have given Evanston several individuals occupied with lighter work, and thanks to these individuals an alliance (Polish National Alliance) group was begun there, the first Polish Society in Evanston. This society is now in full bloom, because it consists mainly of young people, and gains new champions daily.....</p>
   <p>Yesterday's commemorative exercises attracted many people to Redfield Hall, in the center of the town. The chairman of the celebration, Mr. L. Bednarowicz, <pb facs="5423968_9_0581.jpg" n="2"/>called the audience to order, and named Mr. S. J. Czechowicz to conduct the exercises. The secretary of the celebration was Mr. A. Mrowczynski, the financial secretary of the group......</p>
   <p>All of the numbers on the program were carefully performed, and each number was followed by thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>After the exercises, the board of directors of Group 952, invited several of the guests from Chicago to dinner at the home of Mr. and Mrs. M. Cieslak. Two very pleasant hours were spent in conversation about the Alliance, and matters pertaining to the Poles in Evanston. It was with sincere regret that we parted from the hospitable Cieslaks and members of the board of directors of Group 952, hurrying to Chicago to the ball of the Falcons No. II. In this article, however, we wish to express our sincere thanks both to Mr. and Mrs. Cieslak and to Group 952 for the hospitality accorded to us in true Polish style.</p>
   <p>In the name of Group 952, and, at its request, I wish to thank the ladies choir, <pb facs="5423968_9_0582.jpg" n="3"/>Morning Star, the Paderewski choir, Miss Wasielewski, Mr. Zychlinski, Miss Kopek, Mr. Czechowicz, and little Miss Slomka for their generous participation in the celebration, and for adding to its charm by their particular performances.</p>
   <p>(Signed) One of those present.</p>
   <p>[Editor's note: The omissions represent either names of individuals belonging to the society or a list of the items on the program.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
