<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-06-01">June 1, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Poles Honor War Dead</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0352</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0352.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-06-01">June 1, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO POLES HONOR WAR DEAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On May 31, 1927, Memorial Day, Polish Organizations of Chicago paid tribute to the dead war veterans of all wars in which the United States had participated. At an early hour of the morning, graves of the veterans were being decorated and services held which were intended for the benefit of all cemeteries in Chicago. The graves of veterans at Saint Adalberts cemetery, were decorated by Pulaski Post No. 86, of the American Legion; and by the Ladies Auxiliary, at the Resurrection cemetery, Town of Lake post No. 7; the Polish-American Alliance and the Ladies Auxiliary No. 7, and the American Veterans Alliance donated a beautiful wreath to each cemetery. In the afternoon the veterans paraded on Michigan Avenue, to remind Chicago organizations of the consecration and death of soldiers of various wars.</p>
   <p>Taking part in this huge parade were Mexican, Civil, Spanish-American and world-war veterans. The sight of these veterans-marching-was very impressive, and was witnessed by about 300,000 people, who lined both sides of Michigan Boulevard, for more than two hours. The marshal of the parade was General James Stuart; he was followed by cadets and veterans of foreign wars. The marshal of the American Legion was Captain Ferre C.Watkins. Also participating in the parade were women of various veteran organizations In the ranks of this parade were representatives of the various foreign veteran groups, including Scouts, and the National Guards of Illinois. The gun salute was given by soldiers of the 122nd field artillery, under the command of colonel S. Lawton.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0353.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The parade started at Chicago Avenue and Michigan Boulevard, and ended at Roosevelt Road. The Polish divisions in this parade made a splendid showing. Leading the Polish division was military band of Haller's Army. Following the band was Marshall Leon T. Walkowicz, commander of the Polish-American Veterans Alliance, Francis J. Kempa, adjutant General, Nicholas Pietrzykowski, Treasurer, and W. Wojciechowski director. The flag bearers for the Polish-American Veterans Alliance were Francis Kondrocki, John Johnson and John Skupien; the flag bearer for the Town of Lake, Post No. 7,American Legion flag, was Felix Wolniakowski; Francis Ewer was the American flag bearer.</p>
   <p>Members of the Polish-American Veterans Alliance, in uniform, followed the flags under the command of Captain John Ciaglo, whose adjutant was Lieutenant Miecislaus Glod. Next in order were the Polish Army Veterans, whose Marshal was Walter Brudzniski; the leaders of the Polish Army Veterans Society were John Szymanski, General Secretary, Michael Rudncki, Treasurer and Joseph Cwik, President. The flag bearers of this organization were Albert Jastrzemski and Walter Dobrowolski. The second Polish division in the parade were veterans not in uniform, under the command of John Gall, commander of Woodrow Wilson Post, No. 3; his adjutant was Stephen Kozuch, commander of Ironsides Post.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0354.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The majority of the American and Polish veterans who participated in the parade, were not in uniform. Many other American Veteran Alliances who took part in this huge parade were: Rossevelt Post No. 4; Brighton Park Post No. 15; Cragin Hanson Post No. 18; and Ironsides Post No. 16.</p>
   <p>On the reviewing stand was Vice-President of the United States, General, Charles G. Dawes; Governor of Illinois, Len Small; General James Stuart; John A. Pelka and William Hale Thompson, Mayor of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
