<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-11">Jan. 11, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Things Go Badly at the Alliance!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0240</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0240.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-11">Jan. 11, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THINGS GO BADLY AT THE ALLIANCE!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Things go badly with the Polish National Alliance. It is only necessary to glance over the last issue of Zgoda [Harmony] to realize this. Insinuations, slander, vilification, and shameful accusations are spread throughout the entire issue of Zgoda in the form of protocols of delegates' meetings.... and in various other forms, portraying a state of moral discord so loathsome as to materially injure the paper which, after all, is the official organ of an important institution. One can only turn away from the pitiful sight with pain.</p>
   <p>The meeting of the delegates which, parenthetically speaking, was attended by many persons who were not delegates but who had shown special kindness to the Central Administration, could only have ended so: the delegates might have, in the face of the Central Administration's open admission of the disordered and <pb facs="5423968_9_0241.jpg" n="2"/>haphazard state of the books, acknowledged that this disorder constituted the Administration's only virtue. That is their affair. After all, the Sejm [Assembly]is the only competent judge in this matter.</p>
   <p>But grave harm is being done to Zgoda and its editors by the scoundrelly and disgraceful attacks upon certain members of the Alliance. The falsity and vileness revealed by the exposure of imaginary plots is a form of brutality which one would expect from hoodlums, for whom the only place is a--jail.</p>
   <p>This wave of mud, engulfing Zgoda, reaching the very foundations of the Alliance, leaves a feeling of despair. May it not perish in this mud!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
