<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-07">May 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Third of May Celebration at St. Casimir's Parish</title><title level="a" type="sub">$105.44 Collected for Polish Relief</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-07">May 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THIRD OF MAY CELEBRATION AT ST. CASIMIR'S PARISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">$105.44 Collected for Polish Relief</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday at 2:30 P. M. all societies, national as well as church, gathered at St. Casimir's Church, 23rd and South Whipple Streets, whence, headed by Mr. J. Nowosielski's band, they marched over to the beautiful auditorium of the Carter Harrison Technical High School, at West 24th Street and Marshall Boulevard. In addition to the band, the following marched in the parade: school children of Nest Jednosc (Unity) Number 9 of the Alliance of Polish Falcons, numbering about one hundred boys and girls; the Falcons of this nest in uniform; the military society, The Fourth Regiment of Polish Uhlans, in uniform; and all the national societies, groups of the Polish National Alliance, and church societies. The parade was routed from St. Casimirs Church along Whipple Street to 22nd Street, to Marshall Boulevard, and then to 24th Street and Marshall Boulevard to the High School. The large auditorium and gallery, having a seating capacity for three thousand, was packed, and many people had to stand. The <pb facs="5423968_9_0461.jpg" n="2"/>school children, Falcons, Uhlans, and the band sat on the stage.</p>
   <p>Promptly at 3 P. M. Mr. J. Malysa, chairman of the Department of National Celebrations, opened the ceremony with a short speech and called on Mr. Victor Pijanowski, director of the Polish National Alliance, to act as chairman, and Francis Skorupa to act as secretary. Chairman Pijanowski on taking his place on the stage, delivered a short address, explaining why we arrange national celebrations and what their purpose is--after which the program was begun.</p>
   <p>The first number was by Mr. J. Nowosielski's orchestra, after which the well-known Kurpinski Male Chorus, under the direction of P. Herek, sang "Modliywa Jagiell" (Jagiello's Prayer) by Czubski, accompanied on the piano by Miss Adeline Jezierna. The solo parts were sung by Edward Schlajchert, popular baritone of St. Casimir's Church. The third number was a speech by John Wedda, well-known national worker. The speaker, after giving a brief resume of the <pb facs="5423968_9_0462.jpg" n="3"/>history of Poland and the granting of the Constitution on May 3, 1791, went on to explain how our invaders have continued to oppress us, and that the present war is the battle of the civilized world against barbarism and the enemies of humanity; and since the United States joined the Allies against oppressors, it is certain that the Allies will defeat civilization's enemy. Mr. Wedda was followed by a quartet consisting of two violins and a piano duet, composed of A. and J. Pijanowski and A. and O. Peszynski. This was followed by a number by the St. Casimir's Women's Chorus, with piano accompaniment by Miss A. Jezierna. The audience particularly liked the reading by young Joseph Lomasz, dressed in a Polish costume, and Miss K. Fudalkowski, dressed in heavy mourning, in which these two asked the audience to remember the hungry in Poland. Chairman Pijanowski then asked Misses L. Pijanowski, F. Brodnicki, A. Gorski, M. Gorski, M. Rzepczynski, Ronkowski, Skorupa, and Tenerowski to take up a collection for Polish relief, while Mr. J. Nowosielski's orchestra played a medley of Polish songs. The collection for Polish relief yielded $105.44, which sum will be sent to the proper authorities. This was <pb facs="5423968_9_0463.jpg" n="4"/>followed by a duet by Mr. Francis Raczynski, a member of the Kurpinski Chorus, and Miss Frances Brodnicki, a member of the St. Casimir's Women's Chorus. They sang "W noc Ksiezycowa" (On a Moonlit Night). The audience forced them to give an encore, and they sang in English a medley of national American songs consisting of "The Star-Spangled Banner," "Battle Hymn of the Republic," and "America".</p>
   <p>Reverend W. Furman, rector of St. Casimir's Parish then made an address in English. He stated at the outset that he would have preferred to speak in Polish, but since the chairman asked him to acquaint the Americans present with the purpose of our national celebrations, he would speak in English. In his interesting speech, in good English and without a trace of foreign accent, Reverend Furman gave a short summary of Polish history and the history of the constitution of 1791. The speaker concluded by stating that now that this country has declared war in the name of humanity on aggressive Germany, and President Wilson has promised us the creation of a free and united Poland--we should fight under the Stars and Stripes <pb facs="5423968_9_0464.jpg" n="5"/>against our common enemy.</p>
   <p>The next number was a piano solo by Miss Harriet Pijanowski. This was followed by a reading by Miss Agnes Gorski, entitled "Aby Polska Nie Zginela" (That Poland Might Not Be Lost), after which, holding a Polish and an American flag in each hand, she began the singing of the national hymn "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland), in which the audience joined. At the request of the ladies of the committee on arrangements, the chairman asked the ladies who took up the collection to give little flags to the audience, and at the same time asked Mr. John Skibinski, editor of the monthly Free Poland, to say a few words. Mr. Skibinsi chose for his topic the history of Poland from the time of the acceptance of the constitution up to the present. He asked our young men to join the army of this country to fight against humanity's enemy--the Prussians. He concluded his speech by expressing the wish that he might see Poland soon free, united, and independent.</p>
   <p>This was followed by a short speech by Sergeant Wisniewski of the United States <pb facs="5423968_9_0465.jpg" n="6"/>Army, in which he exhorted young Polish men to enlist and to apply at the Polish recruiting bureau, so that we might show our force and solidarity in this country. Then Misses W. Kubkowski, M. Raczynski, and J. Miotka played an overture for six hands on the piano. This was followed by a song by the St. Casimir's Women's Chorus with the piano accompaniment of Miss A. Jezierna.</p>
   <p>Reverend W. Furman, rector of St. Casimir's, then made a speech in Polish. He pleaded for unity and harmony in these critical times. He asked the young men to join the colors of this country, and concluded with the wish that he might live to see Poland free and united from sea to sea [sic].</p>
   <p>The next number was a piano solo by Miss M. Gruszczynski, after which the Kurpinski Male Chorus sang "Piesn Bojowa" (Battle Song), by Burs, under the direction of Mr. P. Herek.</p>
   <p>After Chairman Pijanowski had thanked all those who participated in the <pb facs="5423968_9_0466.jpg" n="7"/>program and the audience for their attention, the orchestra played Dabrowski's march, "Jeszcze Polska Nie Zginela" (Poland Is Not Lost), and everyone left the hall with the hope of living to see this free Poland.</p>
   <p>It should be added that all the numbers on the program were very well performed, and the audience, to show its appreciation, applauded enthusiastically, demanding encores. The national celebrations in the district of St. Casimir's Parish, sponsored by the Department of National Celebrations, generally turn out unusually well, for which the Department deserves recognition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
