<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-13">July 13, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">To the Polish Societies and All Right Thinking Compatriots in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-V.B"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V B</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-13">July 13, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE POLISH SOCIETIES AND ALL RIGHT THINKING COMPATRIOTS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Compatriots!</p>
   <p>A solemn patriotic ceremony will be conducted at the Aurora Turner Hall, located at Milwaukee Avenue and Huron Street, on Sunday, July 17, in commemoration of the centenary anniversary of the Battle of Dubienka. The service will begin at two o'clock in the afternoon.</p>
   <p>By this exercise we wish to prove that the love of our Fatherland that inspired the hearts of those who fought in defense of Polish liberation lives even today in our hearts, despite the hundred years of enslavement. Respectful of the memory of the valiant group of defenders headed by our hero, Thaddeus Kosciuszko, strong in the belief of the justness of Divine Providence and in the victory of truth, we have withstood and will continue <pb facs="5423968_9_1063.jpg" n="2"/>to withstand the inhuman oppression and persecution, because their honorable deeds and a sincere love of the Fatherland will always inspire us.</p>
   <p>Through our services we wish to honor primarily that immortal knight who on two hemispheres, in Europe and in America, "fought only for man's freedom and rights."</p>
   <p>Compatriots! In a ceremony so memorable, let the factional disputes which tend to separate us perish, let us remember that we all are the sons of our one oppressed Fatherland. Let us indicate that despite our various outlooks on matters pertaining to the general citizenry, we know how to stand hand in hand as brethren and true sons of the Fatherland.</p>
   <p>Famous English and Polish orators will speak at this service. Therefore, compatriots, let the greatest possible number attend so that the hall may be filled to capacity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1064.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We ask the societies that will participate in this ceremony to send their Polish and American flags early, at 10 o'clock, to the Aurora Turner Hall, for the purpose of decorating the hall. The military societies will please present themselves in uniforms.</p>
   <p>M. Osush, S. F. A. Satalecki, Stanley Nicki, A. Koinski, Thomas Wozny, Leon Szopinski. (Committee).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
