<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-02">Sept. 2, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">On the Eve of the Polish National Alliance Convention</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-02">Sept. 2, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE EVE OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE CONVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The [tenth] convention of the Polish National Alliance [P. N. A.] will open Monday in Pulaski Hall. It will undoubtedly be a very important convention--we might say a decisive one. During the last two years much has been said and written about the Alliance. In this organization which has, if we consider its bylaws, a noble and commendable aim in that it seeks to promote nationalistic development on a Catholic foundation, there has been a growing dissension for the last two years. Two factions have definitely arisen in the administration and in individual groups, and a struggle has resulted. From time to time this paper has given accounts of the struggle; it would be superfluous to repeat them here. We need only say that it is a struggle of the better element--which desires conservatism, harmony with other organizations, nationalistic work, and development of our society on its rightful foundation of Catholicism--with a despotic, incapable clique which seeks to hold on to profitable offices by any means, and attempts unscrupulously to <pb facs="5423968_9_0213.jpg" n="2"/>awaken the worst instincts of our people, being ready even to support the apostasy of Kolasinski and the anarchism of Rybakowski and Bombinski.</p>
   <p>The time has come for this struggle to be resolved. Who will triumph? It is hard to predict. It is certain, however, that we sincerely hope for the victory of those who stand for harmony, conservatism, and brotherhood. We are not concerned with individuals; we are concerned with the principle involved, with the good of an institution, with the moral advance of American Polonia. We do not want to see the Alliance in the hands of agitators, at the service of anarchists and apostates; on the contrary, we want to see the Alliance develop along the principle of the Constitution of May Third [1794], which is supposed to be (why isn't it?) its very cornerstone. We repeat, individuals are not important in this struggle. If those from both factions are removed from office and replaced by honest, energetic men who are not fanatics or troublemakers, we will regard it as a triumph for the Alliance and for the Polish cause in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0214.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We believe such a victory is possible. If we are disappointed, however, we foresee only the most unfortunate consequences for the Polish National Alliance. If the Alliance does not take the road to the right, it must go to the left, down the untrodden path that leads to the loss of all the ideals by which it is now upheld. It is a miserable end, but an inevitable one.</p>
   <p>In any case, we take this occasion before the opening of the convention, to greet the delegates and to express the hope that their sessions will be conducted harmoniously and with dignity. May private concerns never blind them; may they always have only the good of their great organization and the good of American Polonia at heart.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
