<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 110,
<date when="1921-12-19">Dec. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">From the Life of the Poles in St. Francis Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1781</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1781.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 110,
<date when="1921-12-19">Dec. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE LIFE OF THE POLES IN ST. FRANCIS PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>St. Francis Parish was founded by Synowie Polski(Sons of Poland) group No. 636 of the Polish National Alliance. The church and the school were built thanks to the efforts of this group. Father Joseph Pajkowski was the first pastor. The group Synowie Polski was founded by John Kulik, Mary Ostrowski, her son, K. K. Ostrowski, Francis Kendrykowski, and Jacob Kisiel.</p>
   <p>This settlement grew very rapidly because of the very energetic activities of this society. Two new societies were formed: one is St. Hedwig's Society or group 754 Z. P. R. K., the other is St. Bronislawas' Society of Z. P. A., also the Polish Alma Mater Society and Citizens' Club.</p>
   <p>The Citizens' Club has done a great deal for the neighborhood; it helped its members take out their citizen's papers;helped put through all kinds of improvements and many other things.</p>
   <p>Lately, this neighborhood gained a new Polish businessman in the person <pb facs="5423968_9_1782.jpg" n="2"/>of S. Boyda, a very able and popular man, who bought the International Dairy Company from a Swede. He is employing over 50 people, and gaining confidence not only among our people but also among outsiders.</p>
   <p>Mr. S. Kolodziej bought a brick house from Mr. Kulik, located at Thomas St. and Kostner Ave. Mr. Peter Kucharski will open up a drug store in this building after the first of the year.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kolodziej also bought another building next to the first one in which there is a large hall.</p>
   <p>To the prominent members of this neighborhood belongs Mr. Joseph Kolosinski, owner of a first-class bakery shop located at Waton St.</p>
   <p>Mr. and Mrs. Juszkiewicz bought a grocery store located at Watton (sic) and Kostner St. They know their business very well, for they had a grocery store before. Their store has been redecorated and its appearance is very nice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
