<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-29">July 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">First Day of the Polish Roman Catholic Union Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1359</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1359.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Lithuanian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-29">July 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST DAY OF THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday at 1:45 P.M. afternoon session the president, Clement Belinski, opened the first day's afternoon session of the Polish Roman Catholic Union Convention, held at Saint Stanislaus Kostka School Hall, and called upon Reverend Vincent Barzynski, pastor of Saint Stanislaus Kostka Parish, to say a prayer.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Credentials Committee, Reverend Tarnowski informed the delegation that there were sixty delegates representing eighty-eight votes, and that other societies were represented by alternates. This was followed by the reading of the names of the delegates, whose credentials were checked. According to the list, the following groups were represented:</p>
   <p>Holy Family Society of Chicago, Illinois, delegate John Manna, 1 vote; Holy Name of Mary Society of Chicago, Illinois, Albert Tomasik, Leon Szopinski, <pb facs="5423968_9_1360.jpg" n="2"/>Peter Ligman, Jacob Mucha, Boleslav Klarkowski, Anthony Obochowski, W. Pyterek, Paul Ratkowski, and John ArkusZewski, 1 vote each; Saint Joseph Society of Bay City, Michigan, John Jachimowicz, 1 vote; Saint Stanislaus Society of Bay City, Michigan, John Jozwiak, 2 votes; Saint Dominic Rosary Society of Chicago, Illinois, John Wisniewski and Francis Czerwinski, 1 vote each; Holy Name Society of Chicago, Illinois, Clement Belinski and Francis Nowak, 2 votes each; Saint Adalbert Society of Grand Rapids, Michigan, Philip Banasiewicz, 2 votes; John III Sobieski Society Number 1, of Chicago, Illinois, Thomas Krolik, 1 vote; Saints Peter and Paul Society of Chicago, Illinois, Charles Armgart, 1 vote; Augustine Kordecki Society of Chicago, Illinois (suspended); Our Lady of Sorrows Society of Chicago, Illinois, John Damski, 1 vote; Saint Joseph [Society] of Chicago, Illinois, Anthony Rudnicki, 1 vote; Holy Name Society Number 1 of Chicago, Illinois, John Gniot, Francis Komoroski, Andrew Wolnik, John Plotka, 1 vote each; Saint Joseph Society of Erie, Pennsylvania, John Wieczorek, 3 votes; Holy Name Society of Bay City, Michigan, Thomas Gliniecki, <pb facs="5423968_9_1361.jpg" n="3"/>2 votes; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society of Chicago, Illinois, Francis Szybist, 1 vote.</p>
   <p>Also, Saint Mary Queen of Poland Society of LaSalle, Illinois, Peter Bracki, 3 votes; Saint Adalbert Society of Everson, Pennsylvania, Andrew Chmiel, 2 votes; Saint Hyacinth Society of Grand Rapids, Michigan, A. Smaglinski, 1 vote; Saint Francis Xavier Society Number 1 of Chicago, Illinois, Reverend Francis Lange, 1 vote; Saint Vincent de Paul Society of South Bend, Indiana, Lucas Ruzkowski, 2 votes, Valentine Korpal, 1 vote; Saint Isidore Society of Chicago, Illinois, Stanislaus Kolemba, 2 votes; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society of Gaylord, Michigan, Reverend Casimir Skory, 1 vote; Saint Andrew Society of Sobieski, Illinois, Adam Stachowski, 1 vote; Saint John Cantius Society of Chicago, Illinois, Michael Swiatkowski, 3 votes; Saint Adalbert Society of Chicago, Illinois, Anthony Dyczkowski and John Madry, 1 vote each; Saint Adalbert Society of Syracuse, New York, Francis Mokwa, 4 votes; Saint Vincent de Paul Society of Cleveland, Ohio, Ignatius Tarkowski, 6 votes; Holy <pb facs="5423968_9_1362.jpg" n="4"/>Cross Society of Chicago, Illinois, Michael Klosowski, 1 vote; Saint Stanislaus Kostka Society of South Bend, Indiana, Francis Gasiorowski, 1 vote; Saint Casimir Society of Chicago, Illinois, Jacob Brodnicki, 1 vote; Saint Adalbert Bishop Society [no place given] Stanislaus Budzbenowski, 1 vote; Onufry Grochowski, 1 vote; Saint Mary of Perpetual Help Society of Chicago, Illinois, Michael Reszelewski, 2 votes; Sacred Heart of Mary Society of Chicago, Illinois, John Zielinski, 2 votes; Holy Name Society of Chicago, Illinois, Vincent Spychala, 1 vote; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society of Cleveland, Ohio, John Ziolkowski, 1 vote; Saint John the Baptist Society of Chicago, Illinois, Anthony Polenz, 1 vote; Transfiguration Society of Mount Pleasant,[Michigan], Albert Piszula, 2 votes; Saint Adalbert Society Number 1 of Chicago, Illinois, Matthew Piatkowski, 2 votes; Saint Joseph Society of Manistee, Michigan, F. Jazka, 1 vote; Saint Mary of Perpetual Help Society of Chicago, Illinois, Joseph Reich and John Klukaszewski, 1 vote each; Saint Stephen Society of Perth Amboy, New Jersey, Reverend Szymanowski, 2 votes; Saint Joseph Society <pb facs="5423968_9_1363.jpg" n="5"/>of Chicago, Illinois, John P. Lama, 2 votes; Saint Mary of Perpetual Help Society of Buffalo, New York, Reverend T. Flaczek, 1 vote; Saint George Society of Buffalo, New York, Joseph Slisz, 2 votes.</p>
   <p>The following appointed their representatives: Mr. Wleklinski represented Saint Casimir Society of Leavenworth, Kansas; Saint Michael Society of Camden, New Jersey; Saint Casimir Society, Dunkirk, New York; Sacred Heart of Jesus Society, Forest City, Iowa; Holy Name of Mary Society, Peru, Illinois; Sacred Heart of Jesus Society, Cleveland, Ohio; Saint Francis Xavier Society, Sobieski, Illinois; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society, Berea, Ohio; Saint Stanislaus Kostka Society, Traverse City, Michigan; Saint Adalbert Society, Berea, Ohio; Saint Stanislaus Society, South Chicago, Illinois; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society, Antrim, Pennsylvania; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society Alpena, Michigan; Sacred Heart of Jesus Society, Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania; Saint Michael Archangel Society, East Saginaw, Michigan; Saint Anthony Society, <pb facs="5423968_9_1364.jpg" n="6"/>Detroit, Michigan; Saint Joseph Society, Cleveland, Ohio; Saint Casimir Society, [city not given]; Saint Joseph Society, Kingston, Pennsylvania; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society, Stevens Point, Wisconsin; Saint Michael Knights Society, Ashland, Wisconsin; Saints Peter and Paul Society, LaSalle, Illionis; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society, Nanticoke, Pennsylvania; Holy Name Society, Bremond, Texas; Saint Joseph Society, New York, New York; Saint Joseph Society, Brooklyn, New York; Saint Adalbert Society, Warrior Run, Pennsylvania; Saint Florian Guards Society, Glenlyon, Pennsylvania; Saint Barbara Society, Glouster, Ohio; Sacred Heart of Jesus Society, North Creek, Ohio; Kosciusko Guard Society, Wheeling, Pennsylvania; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society, Trenton, New Jersey; Saint Valentine Society, Clarendon, Texas.</p>
   <p>Also, Saints Peter and Paul Society, Saint Joseph, Michigan, represented by Lucas Ruszkowski, 1 vote; Saint Joseph Society, New York, New York, Peter Kiolbassa (not signed by a priest), 2 votes; Saint Stanislaus Kostka Society, <pb facs="5423968_9_1365.jpg" n="7"/>Berlin, Wisconsin, Clement Belinski, 2 votes; Charles Chodkiewicz Knights Society, Everson, Pennsylvania, Peter Kiolbassa; Saint Joseph Society, Nanticoke, Pennsylvania, Clement Belinski, 3 votes; Saint Joseph Society, Duryea, Pennsylvania, Albert Wachowski, 1 vote; Saint Joseph Society, Everson, Pennsylvania, Andrew Chmiel, 1 vote; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society, Sheboygan, Wisconsin, John Jozwiak, 1 vote; Saint Kunegunda Society, Pittsburg, Pennsylvania, Reverend V. Barzynski, 1 vote; Saint Stanislaus Bishop Society, Hartford [Connecticut], F. Czerwinski, 1 vote; Saint Francis Society, Nanticoke, Pennsylvania, C. Belinski, 1 vote; Saint Joseph Society, Antrim, Pennsylvania, A. Jedrzejek, 1 vote; Sacred Heart of Jesus, Cleveland, Ohio, I. Tarkowski, 2 votes; Saint Joseph Society, Schenectady, New York, A. Jedrzejek, 1 vote; and Saint Adalbert Society, Menominee, Michigan, A. Jedrzejek, 1 vote.</p>
   <p>Also, Saint Hedwig Society, Bay City, Michigan, John Jozwiak, 1 vote; Saint Hyacinth Society, So South Amboy, New Jersey, Reverend Szymanowski, <pb facs="5423968_9_1366.jpg" n="8"/>1 vote; Saint Paul Knights Society, Chicago, Illinois, Joseph Rejch, 1 vote; Saint Stanislaus Kostka Society, Manistee, Michigan, F. Jarka, 1 vote; Saint Adalbert Bishop Society, South Amboy, New Jersey, Reverend Szymanowski, 1 vote; Sacred Heart of Jesus Society, Cleveland, Ohio, John Ziolkowski, 1 vote; Saint Hedwig Society, Buffalo, New York, Reverend Thomas Flaczek, 2 votes; Saint Anthony Society, Buffalo, New York, Reverend T. Flaczek, 1 vote; Sacred Heart of Jesus Society, South Amboy, New Jersey, Reverend Szymanowski, 1 vote; Saint Martin Society, Manistee, Michigan, F. Jarka, 1 vote; Saint Adalbert Society, Manistee, Michigan, F. Jarka, 1 vote.</p>
   <p>It was also indicated that three societies were suspended. The mandates of five societies did not have the signature of their respective pastors.</p>
   <p>Because some of the representatives of suspended societies complained that their groups had been unjustly eliminated, the president was instructed on a motion <pb facs="5423968_9_1367.jpg" n="9"/>by Mr. Klarowski, adopted by the floor, to appoint a special committee to investigate the matter. The committee chosen was composed of Reverend Szymanowski, Mr. Korpal of South Bend, Indiana, and Mr. Rudnicki of Chicago, at the president's order, the committee went to another room to settle this business.</p>
   <p>Mr. Tarkowski was given the floor and said that he represented one society as delegate and another as substitute, and asked whether or not he was entitled to a vote as substitute and another as delegate. Reverend Barzynski explained that since this was an extraordinary convention, a delegate was entitled to one vote as a substitute. This gave rise to a debate in which Klarkowski, Kiolbassa, Pisula, Czerwinski, Reich, Tomasik, Polenc, and Wachowski took part. The latter insisted on strict adherence to the constitution. This kept the discussion going, which was soon joined by Manna, Slisz, Grochowski, Lama, Stachowicz, Klarkowski, Pyterek, Wachowski, <pb facs="5423968_9_1368.jpg" n="10"/>and Reverend Stanislaus Nawrocki. A motion seconded by Kiolbassa was made to close the debate. The president stated that since this was a special session, special laws should be instituted. At this point, Reverend Lange moved that every delegated regardless of the number of societies he might represent, should have only one vote. This motion was unanimously adopted.</p>
   <p>In the meantime the committee that investigated the doubtful credentials had returned. Reverend Szymanowski, in the name of the committee, announced the results. The matter of one of the socieities, the Saint Joseph Number 2, came for discussion on the floor. The question involved was that the society under discussion, which had ninety members, had been suspended for not paying the required assessments. Fifteen members, however, had paid their assessments and demanded to be heard at the convention.</p>
   <p>As a result, a heated discussion followed. Words were exchanged between <pb facs="5423968_9_1369.jpg" n="11"/>the president, the secretary, Reverend Szymanowski, Rudnicki, and others. Opinions were also expressed by Reverends Kozlowski, and Barzynski; also by Kiolbassa, Swiatkowski, Lama, and others. At the suggestion of Reverend Kozlowski, Reverend Szymanowski, in the name of the committee, formulated the following proposition: "The fifteen members can form a separate group under a new name and join the Union, and their delegate can be temporarily accepted at the convention. In the event of death in the society, however, this cannot be considered". The floor accepted this proposal. The same treatment was given the suspended August Kordecki Society.</p>
   <p>Next under discussion was the Saint Cecilia Society, also suspended. The committee considered the suspension unjustifiable, and the floor accepted this verdict after hearing the president's opinion and the claims of the defenders of the society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1370.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Then followed the business of credentials that had not been presented according to requirements. The floor deemed them void. Some of the credentials that had been written out for representatives and not for delegates.</p>
   <p>After receiving their report, the president expressed his appreciation to the members of the committee for their fine work.</p>
   <p>At this point the secretary read a letter of congratulation from the staff of Narod Polski (Polish People).</p>
   <p>Delegate Jachimowicz asked the president whether the floor should elect a marshal. The president replied that as soon as the matter was proposed and seconded, this question would be decided, and urged the choice of a capable man for this office. Delegate Jachimowicz nominated Peter Kiolbassa. The president put the nomination to a vote and the floor accepted it unanimously.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1371.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>Thereupon the president asked Mr. Kiolbassa to take the stand before the chairman's chair. This was complied with, and the new marshal expressed his thanks to the assembly and promised to fulfill his new duties to the best of his ability. Before leaving the stand, Mr. Kiolbassa suggested that an election for secretary take place.</p>
   <p>Delegate Szopinski proposed Stanislaus Szwajkart, although he was not a delegate. Delegate Reich nominated Leon Szopinski. The marshal took the floor and said that two secretaries were needed and moved that the two named be given the offices. This motion was carried.</p>
   <p>The marshal then named Mr. Manna and Reverend A. Nowrocki as sergeant at arms and vice-sergeant at arms respectively.</p>
   <p>Thereupon the marshal announced that, according to the business listed, the next in order was the reading of the new constitution. Delegate <pb facs="5423968_9_1372.jpg" n="14"/>Szopinski moved to appoint a commission to read the constitution in the evening and to make all the corrections and recommendations on the following day. Delegate Pyterek immediately proposed to have the constitution read without a commission. This was accepted. At this point the floor recessed for fifteen minutes.</p>
   <p>After a fifteen-minute pause, the marshal called the session to order and read a letter of congratulation from Reverend Andrew Ignasiak. This was followed by a request that the secretary read the outline of the new constitution.</p>
   <p>Upon a motion by Delegate Reich, the secretary read a paragraph taken from the code of laws of the State of Illinois. It was also agreed. that the president appoint a committee to study any suggestions in regard to the constitution. The secretary, at the request of the floor, read the new amendments to the constitution, including Article 1, paragraphs 11 and 12, <pb facs="5423968_9_1373.jpg" n="15"/>as well as Articles II, IV, V, and VI, which were turned over to a committee for preparation and presentation on the following day. As to Article IV, it reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Polish Roman Catholic Union is to observe two Polish national holidays--the third of May, as the day of acceptance of the new Polish Constitution [1791], and November 29, as the day commemorating the Polish rising against the Russian yoke [1830]."</p>
   <p>Delegate Szopinski moved that the committee add to this paragraph that "The Polish Roman Catholic Union recommends that the societies affiliated with it observe these holidays."</p>
   <p>The next item in the order of the day was the appointment of a committee to frame up the constitution. The following were named: Reverend Francis <pb facs="5423968_9_1374.jpg" n="16"/>Lange and Anthony Rudnicki, both of Chicago, Illinois; Ziolkowski of Cleveland, Ohio; Jozwiak of Bay City, Michigan; Reich and Belinski, both of Chicago, Illinois; Jhrka of Manistee, Michigan; Reverend Rosinski of Cleveland, Ohio; L. Ruszkowski, B. Klarkowski,and L. Szopinski, all of Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>After settling this matter, Mr. Reich moved that the delegates express their thanks to the president for his willingness to comply with the wishes of the floor. The motion was carried and the assembly rose to pay its respects to the president.</p>
   <p>At this point, at the request of the floor, the marshal closed the session at 5:45 P. M. and ordered it to be resumed on the following day at 9 A. M. Before dismissing the assembly, Reverend Barzynski said a prayer.</p>
   <p>The telegram received from the staff of Narod Polski reads as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1375.jpg" n="17"/>
   <p>"The staff of Narod Polski send the convention the heartiest congratulations and wishes of success in the work for this great organization, as is the Polish Roman Catholic Union, Long live the Union!</p>
   <p>"Sincerely,</p>
   <p>(Signed) John Tarkowski,</p>
   <p>Thomas Zagrzebski,</p>
   <p>John Chonarzewski,</p>
   <p>John Mucha."</p>
   <p>The letter from Reverend Ignasiak reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Erie, Pennsylvania, July 27, 1897.</p>
   <p>"To the delegates of the Polish Roman Catholic Union of America convened at the Saint Stanislaus Kostka School Hall, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1376.jpg" n="18"/>
   <p>Gentlemen: Not being in a position to attend in person, I wish, however, to be present in spirit. First of all I send you sincere wishes, beseeching God that you fulfill your work wisely and peacefully, and hope that the needs of the Polish Roman Catholic Union be met with success. Be wary of those within the organization that sow discord and misunderstanding, for if they are not made quiet or of their own free will quit, they must be ordered to do so. This is imperative to the welfare of the Union. I suggest that death benefits be arranged according to ages and amount of assessment, and they should amount to $500, $1,000, $1,500 or $300, $600, etc. The amount to be paid is optional with the individual and not with the society to which he belongs. Women must pay separately if they wish to have death benefits. This is the best method, for it is true and tried. All American societies follow this procedure. We cannot follow another.</p>
   <p>"With fraternal love.</p>
   <p>Reverend Andrew Ignasiak."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1377.jpg" n="19"/>
   <p>The following priests were present at this special session: Paul Gutowski, Detroit, Michigan; John Radziejewski, Saint Adalbert Parish, Chicago, Illinois; Boleslav Nowakowski, Saint Mary of Perpetual Help Parish, Chicago, Illinois; F. S. Motulewski, Saint Anthony Parish, Toledo, Ohio; C. Skory, Gaylord, Michigan; K. Fremel, Saint Casimir Parish, Cleveland, Ohio; Stephen Szynanowski, Perth Amboy, New Jersey; F. Lange, J. Kasprzycki, and John Piechowski, all of Chicago, Illinois; Thomas Flaczek, Saint Adalbert Parish, Buffalo, New York; B. Rosinski, Cleveland, Ohio; Casimir Truszynski, Peru, Illinois; Francis Byrgier, Sobieski, Illinois; Joseph Barzynski, LaSalle, Illinois; John Kubacki, Reynolds, Indiana; C. Kobylinski, Hammond, Indiana; Paul Rhode, pastor of Saints Peter and Paul Parish, Chicago, Illinois; Matthew Krawczunas, Chicago, Illinois; W. Bobkiewicz, Rutland, Illinois; Joseph Cieburowski, Chicago, Illinois; Matthew Tarnowski, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Raszkiewicz, Otis, Wisconsin; Kozlowski, Manistee, Michigan; Wrobel, Michigan City, Michigan; Koptykiewicz, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Nawrocki and Wojtalewicz, both of Chicago, Illinois; and Pescinski, Stenens Point, Wisconsin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
