<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-18">Feb. 18, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">The Kosciusko, Celebration in Bridgeport</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0685</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0685.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-18">Feb. 18, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THE KOSCIUSKO, CELEBRATION IN BRIDGEPORT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The celebration commemorating the one-hundred-and-fiftieth anniversary of the birth of Thaddeus Kosciusko, held February 16, in the Blessed Virgin Mary of Perpetual Help Parish, in Bridgeport, was truly impressive. The school hall, although large, was unable to accomodate all those present.</p>
   <p>The Pastor, Reverend S. Nawrocki, opened the celebration, and the people joined the priest in saying the Angelic Salutation (Hall Mary).</p>
   <p>Reverend W. Derdzinski was president of the celebration, and Mr. W. Swiontrowski acted as secretary.</p>
   <p>The president called on Peter Kiolbassa as the first speaker. The speaker briefly described the life and deeds of Thaddeus Kosciusko, and pointed out that our hero left us a never-to-be-forgotten example. To be a true Pole, like Kosciusko, one must always love God, to whom all honor and praise belong--and then to do <pb facs="5423968_9_0686.jpg" n="2"/>all one can for the welfare of the fatherland.</p>
   <p>Next, the St. Cecelia Choir directed by J. Reich, sang "Rocznica Kosciuszki" (The Anniversary of Kosciusko), and the younger choir sang "Krakowiak Kosciuszki" (Kosciusko's Krakowiak Dance).</p>
   <p>The second speaker was Mr. S. Zahajkiewicz. He compared our unblemished hero, the friend of the masses, Thaddeus Kosciusko, a man as pure as a diamond, with the present-day "patriots," who, in the name of antireligious and anti-Polish progress, blinded by fury, endeavor to destroy the foundations of our religious and moral wellbeing, on which the Polish people have depended for centuries....He appealed to all not to permit these false voices to fool them, but to follow in the footsteps of righteousness and truth, for fatherland and justice, as did Kosciusko.</p>
   <p>Next, the St. Cecelia Choir, directed by J. Reich, sang "Warszawianka" (Warsaw Maiden).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0687.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The secretary of the celebration, Mr. Swiontkowski, then read a short biography of Thaddeus Kosciusko.</p>
   <p>This biography touched on all the important phases of the life of Kosciusko. He especially emphasized our hero's love of freedom, his simplicity, his charitable heart, his love for the people, and his deep conviction of the need for educating them.</p>
   <p>Mr. Swiontkowski described the death of Kosciusko, and concluded with these words:</p>
   <p>"When his ashes were brought to Cracow, the old Zygmunt (once King of Poland) lying in the 'Wawel' (A burying place for kings) cried out.....The cover of the coffin was lifted and our hero's remains rested. His ashes rest between those of King John Sobieski and Prince Joseph Poniatowski.</p>
   <p>"But a greater honor than merely resting with kings awaited our leader. The <pb facs="5423968_9_0688.jpg" n="4"/>Polish people, with their own hands, erected a great mound, which still exists to the greater glory of our entire nation.</p>
   <p>"In the interior, in a marble urn, is earth from Maciejowice. At the top is a great boulder with one word, 'Kosciusko'."</p>
   <p>The last speaker was Mr. Clemens J. Belinski, president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union under the protection of the Sacred Heart of Jesus.</p>
   <p>The speaker gave a hearty greeting to those assembled in this beautiful school hall bearing the name of the man whom we honor on the one-hundred-and-fiftieth anniversary of his birth. He also mentioned that this Polish parish in Bridgeport has, in a very short time, grown wonderfully....While entering the church property, the speaker shed a tear, because the sight of these grand buildings touched his heart; nine years ago this was all a prairie. The growth is to be credited to the parishioners. They are eager to help, and are building a school for the children, ever mindful that Kosciusko said, "Education of the masses will <pb facs="5423968_9_0689.jpg" n="5"/>perform miracles."</p>
   <p>After this speech, the St. Cecelia Choirs sang "Rozmowa Kosciuszki" (The Talk of Kosciusko).</p>
   <p>In conclusion, the pastor thanked the parishioners for coming in such great numbers, which proved their patriotism, their good will, and their respect for Thaddeus Kosciusko, who sacrificed his life and his possessions for his fatherland and his people. This beautiful speech, as well as all the others, was applauded with great vigor. The singing of "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland) concluded the celebration.</p>
   <p>The sum of $12.23 was collected for the Kosciusko monument.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
