<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XXII, No. 2,
<date when="1928-01-12">Jan. 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">St. Bronislava's Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1688</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1688.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XXII, No. 2,
<date when="1928-01-12">Jan. 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ST. BRONISLAVA'S PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new Polish parish of St. Bronislava is an accomplished fact in South Chicago. The church will be erected at 87th Street and Colfax Avenue. The Franciscan Fathers of Buffalo, N. Y., took charge of it. Father O. Cyryl Kita is the pastor of the parish. The first mass for this parish was said by the pastor on Jan. 8, 1928, in the Bowen High School Hall. This parish was founded through the efforts of Father Wojtalewicz.</p>
   <p>Laying of the cornerstone. The Fourth of July, 1928, shall never be forgotten in St. Bronislava's parish, South Chicago, Ill., for on that memorable day a great celebration took place; the ceremony of laying the corner stone for their new church.</p>
   <p>The ceremony was performed by Prelate Rev. F. Ostrowski, pastor of St. Josefat's Parish, assisted by Rev. J. Dampt, and Rev. A. Socha, who are assistants in Immaculate Conception and Mary Magdalene parishes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1689.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Before the sermon the local choir sang "Veni Creator." The sermon was preached by Father Wojtalewicz; it was a wonderful and uplifting sermon. He spoke about the new parish and as he was its organizer he described his efforts lasting eight long years, resulting in a great reward and a happy ending. He spoke about the necessity of the Catholic schools, and on other subjects. The sermon of Father Wojtalewicz made a profound impression upon all who heard him. There were about twenty priests and thousands of faithful.</p>
   <p>A combination building: St. Bronislava's parish has a combination church and school building. It is built in English gothic style. It is three stories high. Under the building there is a large basement, or rather a hall, capable of accommodating eight hundred people. There are also other smaller halls suitable for meetings, kitchen, etc. On the first floor there is a church hall which will serve as a temporary church, till a regular church is built later on. The present church will accommodate 1,000 people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1690.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Later on this church will be changed into a regular hall and three school rooms. There will be nine school rooms all together. The building is so constructed that it could be changed into fifteen school rooms. It is a fire-proof building. The plans were designed by Mr. Leon Strelka. The electrical work was done by Mr. W. Obarski. The three altars are gifts of St. Hedwig's Parish of Detroit, Mich., which is conducted by Franciscan Fathers.</p>
   <p>The new St. Bronislava's church of the South Chicago Polish parish is almost finished and next Sunday, October 28, the first mass will be celebrated. A beautiful organ, which will be installed on June, was bought from the Kimball Company of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The school is attended by 512 children. There are eight grades, conducted by the Felician Sisters.</p>
   <p>Dedication of St. Bronislava's Church and School. The South Chicago Polish <pb facs="5423968_9_1691.jpg" n="4"/>settlement celebrated another great event. This time it was the dedication of St. Bronislava's Church and school building. It was on Sunday, June 16, 1929.</p>
   <p>The dedication ceremony was performed by the Right Rev. Archbishop Mundelein. The members of the parish were preparing themselves for this great occasion for a long time. Indeed, it can be said that it was the greatest manifestation in the history of South Chicago. There was nothing like it since the World War in our "Grod Stalowy," (Steel City), and our fourth Polish settlement in South Chicago.</p>
   <p>The dedication parade was a grand affair. It was a very important occasion because Cardinal Mundelein came to South Chicago for the first time to dedicate the church for the Poles.</p>
   <p>At 1:30 P. M. the church societies formed at 88th Street and Exchange Avenue, and later on other societies joined them. The combined orchestras and bands greeted Cardinal Mundelein with the American and Polish national hymns.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1692.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The procession led the Cardinal into the church. It certainly was a grand sight. Next entered Father Cyryl, the pastor of the parish, carrying a cross in his hands, which was kissed by Cardinal Mundelein. There were many clergymen. The Cardinal was greeted by a church choir singing, "Ecce Sacerdos Magnus." The Cardinal, then, dressed in pontifical robes, performed the act of dedication.</p>
   <p>Then Father Justin Figus, the Provincial of Franciscan Brothers, preached the word of God. After the Polish sermon, Cardinal Mundelein spoke in English; finally he gave the papal blessing to all. The celebration was concluded by singing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
