<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. III, No. 35,
<date when="1929-09-01">Sept. 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">About the National Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1666</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1666.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. III, No. 35,
<date when="1929-09-01">Sept. 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE NATIONAL CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Extracts:</p>
   <p>The Irish and German bishops in America, as well as the Polish priests, are attempting to usurp for their Roman-Catholic Church the name "National." They claim that since the papal church is the church for 80% of the Polish people, it is quite appropriate for them to assume that name.</p>
   <p>This statement is beyond and understanding. Although the papal church dominates over 80% of the Poles, yet it does not prove that it has a national character.</p>
   <p>When the governments of Russia, Germany and Austria reigned over our nation, nobody would have regarded them as "national" governments.</p>
   <p>The papal church took possession of the Polish nation and then through international intrigues, anathemas and other means gained great profits at our nation's expense. When Poland was being torn and divided among its <pb facs="5423968_9_1667.jpg" n="2"/>neighbors, the papal church did not utter a single word of protest. And during the insurrection of 1831, the Roman Church condemned our sons who fought for the liberation of Poland.</p>
   <p>At various times one or another Pope instigated our neighbors against us, and that always caused bloody and devastating wars.</p>
   <p>These were the benefits that the papal church bestowed upon us.</p>
   <p>Even in these contemporary times, the Vatican's policy towards Poland remained just the same as it had been in the Middle Ages.</p>
   <p>The only "National" Church for Poles is and will be the Polish National Catholic Church, which has been established in order to defend the rights of the Polish people. The rights, which so often are being disregarded and even despised by the Roman Church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
