<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-07-10">July 10, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Women Engage in Nationalistic Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0224</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0224.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-07-10">July 10, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH WOMEN ENGAGE IN NATIONALISTIC ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Patriotic Organization (Organizacya Patryotyczna) of Chicago is well known to our readers. It is always ready on occasions for patriotic activity, for noble donations; it lends its support willingly to the realization of new, beneficial ideas. The 'Organization has been especially useful in St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish. Heretofore it has been an organization for men, although its constitution permits women to participate in its activities.</p>
   <p>A group of Polish women feel it is their duty to engage in patriotic activity on a par with their husbands, sons, and brothers. To this end, they have been organizing a Women's Auxiliary which will work hand in hand with the Organization. The originators of this plan have already submitted their idea to the Patriotic Organization in writing.</p>
   <p>At a meeting of the Organization last Sunday, it was unanimously decided that <pb facs="5423968_9_0225.jpg" n="2"/>support should be given to this project. Last night, the Polish women met to discuss this matter for the first time. A number of women were present, and after a short explanation, they decided to organize a women's society to serve the above mentioned aim. A committee was elected whose duty it is to take charge of the matter. The committee consists of Mesdames Mary Kowalski, Frances Zahajkiewicz, Frances Krolik, Josephine Dudzik, Louise Szwajkart, and Rosalia Frank. The committee will shortly issue an appeal for membership to Polish women in general. The appeal will be published in the columns of Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, we acknowledge the desire of our women to participate actively in nationalistic work. Polish women have always been great patriots, for they have bred in each rising generation a love for Poland. All honor to them that, even here on American soil, they uphold this tradition and love their mother country with the intensity of their sisters in Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
