<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-06">Dec. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Commune Iii [Polish National Alliance] Holds November Exercises</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0511</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0511.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV (Swedish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-06">Dec. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">COMMUNE III [POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE] HOLDS NOVEMBER EXERCISES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, December 3, a considerable number of old Alliance members and delegates to Commune III met in front of the Alliance's building at eight-thirty in the morning. They formed into ranks, and carrying the banner of Group 1333 [P. N. A.] at their head, marched to Holy Trinity Church, where they attended solemn High Mass for the heroes who died in the November Insurrection [1830]. A beautiful sermon, suited to the occasion, was delivered by the Reverend Hosinski. The church was filled to capacity by Alliance members and pious Polish people.</p>
   <p>In the evening, the great [Polish Roman Catholic] Union Hall at Augusta Street and Milwaukee Avenue was filled with people who had come to do honor to the memory of the heroes who had given their lives in the struggle for the liberty and independence of Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0512.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Joseph P. Szymanski, president of the Commune, opened the exercises with a short address, at the close of which he named Joseph Magdziarz, treasurer of the Polish National Alliance, as chairman.</p>
   <p>In his beautiful address, Chairman Magdziarz outlined the awful fate which has befallen Poland at the present time; he mentioned also the great loss which the Polish nation suffered recently and asked the audience to honor, by rising, the memory of one of the greatest men of modern Poland--Henryk Sienkiewicz.</p>
   <p>After the various representatives of organizations, other P. N. A. Communes, and veterans of the [1863] insurrection had taken their places on the platform, the Chopin Choir, under the direction of F. Kondziorski, opened the musical portion of the program with five numbers. Thunderous applause proved that the choir had sung to the audience's liking.</p>
   <p>The first address on the program was delivered by the Reverend Sylvester Hosinski, <pb facs="5423968_9_0513.jpg" n="3"/>of Holy Trinity Parish. It was delivered with all the enthusiasm of a real clergyman-patriot calling upon his people for new deeds and greater sacrifices.</p>
   <p>"Soon," cried the speaker, "with the help of God, we will see a free and independent Poland." (Sustained applause).</p>
   <p>The next number was a violin solo by Professor [of music] Theodore Jesierski, 2971 North Ridgeway Avenue, whose artistic skill came as a pleasant surprise to the audience. The recitation by Miss V. Lukasik, delivered with true artistic finish, was also well received.</p>
   <p>An address, very interesting to the Poles, was delivered in English by Municipal Judge Harry Olson, who has always been openly sympathetic to our national group. Unfortunately, lack of space prevents us from giving even a summary of <pb facs="5423968_9_0514.jpg" n="4"/>his very interesting address. The Judge left the hall amid tremendous applause</p>
   <p>"An Insurrectionist's Last Farewell," a tenor solo, was rendered by Joseph Dumanowski, to the piano accompaniment of B. Kujawski. The enthusiasm of the audience forced him to return to the platform for an encore. The Kalina Chorus, consisting exclusively of married women, then sang a medley under the able direction of F. Kondziorski. The voices were strong and well matched.</p>
   <p>Stanislaus Orpiszewski, editor in chief of the Alliance's publications, then spoke on the subject of the Polish element in America, to the sustained applause of the audience. Then followed a violin solo by Jagielski, accompanied on the piano by Miss J. Sikorski, and finally, an unusually beautiful recitation by little Peter Cwalinski, for which the audience was not sparing in its applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0515.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In concluding the exercises, the audience arose to sing the hymn "Boie Cos Polske [God Save Poland], after which the chairman thanked the public in a few sincere words for its generous participation in these exercises.</p>
   <p>A collection for the relief fund, taken up during the intermission, netted $70.09.</p>
   <p>The Committee under whose auspice the exercises were arranged, deserves a vote of thanks, especially its president, Mr. Ball, who deserves public recognition for his capable work, which contributed much to the success of the occasion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
