<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-08">Dec. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Commoration of the November Insurrection at St. Casimir's Parish </title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0523</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0523.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-08">Dec. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">COMMORATION OF THE NOVEMBER INSURRECTION AT ST. CASIMIR'S PARISH </title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday afternoon November 29, inspiring exercises commemorating the November Insurrection were held under the auspices of the Department of National Celebrations. Patriotic inhabitants of St. Casimir's Parish began assembling before 2 P. M. at colorfully decorated Troy Hall in order to honor the memorable November night--the night on which a handful of young Poles, ignoring the greatness and power of the Tsar of Russia, threw down the glove, issued the call to battle for life, for our unexpired rights, and for the freedom of the homeland. In spite of the inclemency of the weather the Hall was filled to capacity--a thing which has rarely happened before. I must state at this point that several societies attended "in gremio" [in large number], among them the Confederation of Polish Youth, the Thaddeus Kosciusko Scythemen, Group 1405 of the Polish National Alliance, and St. Casimir's Society, Group 219 of the Polish National Alliance. Many of the older people belong to the last named group; they were the first settlers of St. Casimir's and they founded our parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0524.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At 3 P. M. Mrs. B. Brodecki, vice-president of the Department of National Celebrations, opened the exercises with a short address and invited Mr. M. Drzewicki to be chairman and the undersigned to act as secretary.</p>
   <p>Mr. Drzewicki invited the speakers and the presidents of groups of the Polish National Alliance to the speaker's table. He issued an especially cordial invitation to the president of the commune of the P. N. A. in our district, Mr. W. J. Pijanowski, and asked him to come up on the platform. He then proceeded with the program.</p>
   <p>The band of group 210 of the Alliance of Polish Falcons, which deserves particular recognition for its gratuitous performances at all national celebrations in this district, played a medley of Polish songs. The Kurpinski Choir, under the direction of Mr. Daniel, sang the beautiful national song "To Work."</p>
   <p>A speech by Mr. Anthony Czarnecki was listed next on the program. However, <pb facs="5423968_9_0525.jpg" n="3"/>when Mr. Czarnecki failed to arrive, the chairman changed the program and called on the second speaker, Mr. J. M. Sienkiewicz, chief of the Alliance of Polish Youth. The speaker selected a historic subject and gave a brief resume of events beginning with the days of Kosciusko. He presented the historical facts which forced the Polish nation to take up arms against the despotic government of the Tsars. He did not minimize the transgressions of the erstwhile oppressors of the Polish nation, such as Tsars Alexander I and Nicholas I and Prince Constantine, but demonstrated the traitorous politics of Moscow at that time and at present. At the end of his speech a storm of applause broke out and shouts of "bravo." During Mr. Sienkiewicz's speech Reverend W. Furman arrived and took his place on the platform.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Kornak recited "Be a Polish Soldier." This inspiring and tear-provoking declamation was followed by a piano and violin number by Mr. Bertman and Miss K. Zapolski. They were rewarded by thunderous applause and forced to give an encore.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0526.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Miss M. Szafranski recited "This Is Not Enough for Us," which the audience enjoyed very much.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anthony Czarnecki, election commissioner and well-known social worker, mentioned in his speech the great moments of the November night in 1830, and then, passing on to the present times,described the suffering of our brothers across the ocean. He lamented the fate of his compatriots in the homeland--a fate which they must endure because of a war foreign to them. He thundered at the Russian and Austro-Prussian sympathizers and said we must neither help nor sympathize with any one of those countries because they are our murderers and oppressors; they are plunderers of our homeland. We must prepare, because there will be no peace in Europe until the invaders return stolen property to their rightful owners. In conclusion the speaker appealed to the audience to help our brethren in the homeland across the sea.</p>
   <p>"Do not divide yourselves into parties and camps because strength lies in unity, and if someone wants to help Russia, Austria, or Germany, let him go there--the <pb facs="5423968_9_0527.jpg" n="5"/>way is open--but let him not try to entangle us."</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the speech, the audience justly thanked the speaker with thunderous applause for his impartial point of view on a matter of such grave importance to us. Many no doubt abandoned their Russian or Austro-Prussian "orientation."</p>
   <p>The collection taken up by Miss Napieralski, Brodecki, and S. Dworak, yielded $19.20.</p>
   <p>After the collection Mr. Gronkiewicz sang, accompanied by Miss J. Zapolski. He was forced to give an encore in response to the applause.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Stefanowski gave a truly artistic recitation of "The Bells," with piano accompaniment by Miss J. Zapolski. The audience applauded enthusiastically. Mr. J. Twardzik recited an "Ode" to the young people. He deserves recognition for the clear and emphatic rendition of this work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0528.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The Kurpinski choir sang "The Battle Song," and then Reverend W. Furman delivered a short address, in which he asserted among other things that in the present war the Catholic nations, such as the Polish and the Belgian--which after the Polish is probably the most Catholic--will suffer most.</p>
   <p>A letter from Reverend F. Mazur former assistant in our parish was read. Reverend Mazur was well known to every parishioner in St. Casimir's as a patriotic chaplain. He was unable to accept the invitation to the commemoration because of lack of time. Reverend F. Mazur lamented in his letter the breaking up of the Poles in America into all sorts of camps, the distortion of public opinion by nationalistic leaders who attained their dishonorable goal when, by their undignified quarrels and their twisting of public opinion, they killed the spirit of the nation. He asked the parishioners of St. Casimir's to ignore all these things and to continue to display their solidarity in regard to the homeland, because it is now in the greatest need. Those present at the exercises received Reverend <pb facs="5423968_9_0529.jpg" n="7"/>Mazur's letter with great respect, since Reverend Mazur, while assistant in our parish, was liked by all, and everyone who had known him personally regretted that St. Casimir's had lost so gallant a chaplain and patriot.</p>
   <p>When the program was completed and "God Save Poland" was sung, the chairman thanked the speakers and those who had appeared on the program for their participation. He thanked the audience for attending in such large numbers. Everyone leaving the Hall carried away with him a very pleasant impression and the feeling in his heart that "Poland Is Not Lost."</p>
   <p>(Signed) Casimir Cholewa,</p>
   <p>Secretary of the celebration</p>
   <p>2504 South California Avenue</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
