<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-12">Mar. 12, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Poles Begin Work on Mass Meeting to Organze Polish League</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-12">Mar. 12, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">POLES BEGIN WORK ON MASS MEETING TO ORGANZE POLISH LEAGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the adjoining column of Dziennik Chicagoski, the president of the Preparatory Committee in charge of the projected mass meeting to organize the Polish League makes the announcement that he has called into existence special committees and subcommittees to draw up all the details.</p>
   <p>One of these committees will hold a meeting today, and we are certain that the others will work very energetically; also, the first list of donations sent for defraying the expenses of the mass meeting has been finally announced.</p>
   <p>In other words, the work has begun. If the mass meeting is to achieve the desired results, if in reality the League is to be organized at this mass <pb facs="5423968_9_0143.jpg" n="2"/>meeting, every detail of its program, as well as every detail of the projected League, should be planned in advance, talked over, carefully prepared, and finally presented to the public for final approval in the most concise form.</p>
   <p>Such work is difficult and troublesome, yet it should be done, and we are of the opinion that it will be done.</p>
   <p>The people who are undertaking this work are not interested in applauses. For their hardships in the task they have undertaken in good faith, they have already met with ingratitude and sharp reproaches; anger and hatred have vented upon them; they were paid with personal attacks, malicious and brutal. Hence, these people have undertaken this work, not because they desire to please someone, but for the good of the public; from deep conviction that it is for a good cause and because they feel that it is their social and patriotic duty. Such people cannot be checked in the middle of <pb facs="5423968_9_0144.jpg" n="3"/>the road by hardships; they are not afraid of vociferations. "For once we should abandon the vicious circle of misunderstandings and dissensions; for once we should set our relations in order," said the originators of the plan. We must establish order and God's peace among ourselves. Believing in the good purpose of their undertaking, with good will and a gentle manner, against which all suspicious personal grudges and attempts of instigators will be shattered in time, the originators of the plan will reach their goal.</p>
   <p>They will proceed without contention, without unnecessary conflicts, self-conscious, persevering, having always a definite goal.</p>
   <p>The work has been started and its great significance will be appreciated, if not today, then tomorrow. We wish the workers who undertook this task Godspeed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
