<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-05">Jan. 5, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">News from the Resurrection Novitiate in Cragin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1705</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1705.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-05">Jan. 5, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM THE RESURRECTION NOVITIATE IN CRAGIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The year 1927 was given a farewell tribute with a prayer of thanks to Our Lord for the many gifts and benefits at the Resurrection Novitiate at Cragin, also with the singing of "Te Deum laudamus" (We praise Thee, God).</p>
   <p>The New Year was welcomed with a citation to the Holy Ghost: "Veni Sancte Spiritus," with the hope that the coming year will bring us the same blessings as bestowed on us last year. It is hoped that the necessary contributions to complete the St. Joseph Chapel near the Novitiate will be given.</p>
   <p>An unusual coincidence! On the very first day of the New Year, the St. John Cantius Young Men's Society of St. John Cantius' parish made a generous contribution towards the completion of the chapel. This was made possible by the administrative body which made a suggestion at the installation ceremonies. Many thanks are extended this young group for their kindness. Perhaps other church societies, clubs, patriotic organizations, and <pb facs="5423968_9_1706.jpg" n="2"/>national groups will follow their example, and make collections for this cause.</p>
   <p>Besides the above mentioned contribution, many individuals from the various Polish parishes have made donations according to their means.</p>
   <p>It is hoped that sufficient funds will be received shortly in order to complete the work before the 19th of March, for on that day a fitting ceremony in honor of the Saint, and the opening of the chapel is being planned. This can only be made possible through assistance from our generous citizens.</p>
   <p>Those who have made donations have been placed in the Golden Book of Benefactors, and prayers are being said for them daily, whether they are deceased or are still living. The prayers, will be continued indefinitely.</p>
   <p>Those who wish to be included in these prayers are urged to act now and send in their contribution. Names of all the donors will be placed in the Golden Book of the Resurrection Fathers' Novitiate at Cragin.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1707.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In conclusion, a reply is given to one of the donors who has asked the following question: "Why don't we have people like Napoleon III?" Before this question can be answered, this one is asked: "Do you know who Napoleon III was?"</p>
   <p>A severe, but true judgment was given by Pius IX about Napoleon III. The Pope adjudged that he was a person that always lied. His entire life was marked by hypocrisy. Do you wish that such people as he exist today--people that would always lie? We have many such people in America on the pattern of Napoleon III. Various means of combat are used to keep this number from increasing. When these are wiped out completely in America, only then will there be people who will pursue truth and goodness.</p>
   <p>Thanks once again are given to the kind contributors.</p>
   <p>Reverend John Kasprzycki, C. R.</p>
   <p>Superior of St. Joseph's Home,</p>
   <p>2249 North Lockwood Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
