<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-09">May 9, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">One Hundred and First Anniversary of the Polish Constitution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-09">May 9, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">ONE HUNDRED AND FIRST ANNIVERSARY OF THE POLISH CONSTITUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Over 2,000 Chicago Poles jammed the auditorium of the St. Stanislaus Kostki's school to take part in yesterday's 101st anniversary celebration of the Polish Constitution of the Third of May, sponsored by the Polish Patriotic Organization. The advance publicity given the program was partly responsible for this splendid turnout. The large audience enjoyed an excellent program, which surpassed all expectations.</p>
   <p>Father Francis Gordon, president of the Patriotic Organization, opened the evening ceremony with a speech of welcome. He pointed out to the audience that this type of program draws a bigger crowd than a dance or a theatrical program, both of which can seldom boast of so large an attendance. He called upon John Arkuszewski, the chairman for the evening to speak. After a few words of thanks, Arkuszewski introduced Walter Godlewski, who opened the program officially.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0290.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The guest speakers of the evening were Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, teacher and poet; Rev. Felix Zwiardowski, pastor from Santa Maria, Texas; Peter Ligman; W. Jozwiakowski; and Rev. V. Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostki's Church.</p>
   <p>S. Zahajkiewicz spoke with the fire of an inspired orator. The audience was breathless during his talk. A description of Poland prior to the signing of the constitution and the events leading to its formulation on the Third of May were the subject of his speech. His words were delivered straight from the heart, and enthusiastically received by the audience.</p>
   <p>The second speaker, Rev. F. Zwiadowski, received a great ovation as he stood on the rostrum. He spoke of the noble efforts exerted by our people in order to maintain a high morale despite the hard trials undergone abroad. As a participant in one of the uprisings in 1863, he said that he firmly believed that the day of a free Poland will come. Because <pb facs="5423968_9_0291.jpg" n="3"/>of this belief, already imbedded in the hearts of all our people, we are justified in trying to make this a reality, if not by us at least by our children. Being a true Pole, it was not difficult for him to convince the audience of this inevitable end. His encouraging words were an added incentive to the audience, for at the conclusion of the speech the applause was deafening.</p>
   <p>May 10, 1892.</p>
   <p>"The Polish Knights" was the theme of Mr. Ligman's talk. Facts of the early history of the Knights in the Poland of old were given. The events of the organization were then traced to the present. He depicted a vivid picture of conditions during those years. The heavy cloud of oppression that spread upon the peasants and their soil was compared with that of adjoining countries. The self-wilfulness of Kings of other nations by far surpassed that of Polish Kings, the speaker pointed out. Mr. Ligman <pb facs="5423968_9_0292.jpg" n="4"/>had to pause many times during his speech because of the enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>Then the popular Mr. Jozwiakowski took Peter Ligman's place on the speaker's stand. Prior to Ligman's speech, Jozwiakowski had spoken a few words to the audience. 'The Castle of Krakow' was the theme of his talk and he told our youth that it was at this castle that the declining Order of Knights revived. Besides the regular military routine, the recruits were given spiritual and physical training. It was this thorough training that made their rebirth a success. This is what is needed for our present orders here in Chicago, if their existence is to continue. He begged the young and the old to take more interest in this field and support the gymnasium (Sokol) schools.</p>
   <p>The last speaker to take the stand was none other than our beloved pastor Rev. V. Barzynski. "Second to the love for God is the love for our fatherland," stated Rev. Barzynski. "This is in line with the <pb facs="5423968_9_0293.jpg" n="5"/>statement made by St. Thomas Aquinas, the Divine Doctor of the Church, 'He who does not love his fatherland, does not love God.'" The speaker also added that Christianity without patriotism is Pharisaical.</p>
   <p>The revered spokesman stressed the importance of the need of patriotic celebrations. He praised our youth for its staunch support in attending this celebration. (Their attendance overshadowed that of the older people, which actually embarrassed the latter.) "There are only two great Polish patriotic days to commemorate in a year, The Constitution of the Third of May and the Revolt of November. Therefore, there is no reason why every seat and all standing room should not be filled," concluded the guest speaker.</p>
   <p>Chorus singing and instrumental numbers, interwoven with the speeches, added to the variety of the program. The rendition of national songs by the choir under the able direction of Andrew Kwasigroch, enlightened the spirit of young and old.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0294.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The Polish Knights, trained by Mr. Ligman, gave a series of interesting drills. Incidentally, they paraded throughout the neighboring streets before the opening of this program. The purpose of this demonstration was to attract the people to attend this patriotic affair.</p>
   <p>These drills brought out many unexpected feats, much to the admiration of the public. The military-like execution of the various orders was pleasing to the eye. This younger generation of Knights was truly a treat. The Order of Knights is composed of three divisions, namely, The First and Second Order of Cadets and the Zouaves. This last branch put on a brilliant demonstration of old-time warfare, using dummy arms.</p>
   <p>The program was closed with the national hymn "Boze Cos Polske."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0295.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>We regret the delay in opening the program. As customary, regardless of the significance attached to an affair, the public was late. At 7:30 P. M., the opening hour, the hall was less than half filled. Had the program started, countless interruptions would have ruined it, as people in two's and three's were gradually entering the hall and milling about for seats. The public also knows from past experience that programs of entertainment always start late, a reason why many are tardy. Many people have adopted the saying, "They won't start without us." It would be worth trying to start a program punctual to the minute, holding late comers at the door until the started number is completed. In this manner the people would get used to the idea of being on time or else miss a part of the program. This would be favorable to all, for interruptions would be averted and more time saved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
