<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-19">Apr. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Semiannual Convention of the Polish Central Relief Committee and the National Board</title><title level="a" type="sub">Great Internal Reforms Effected</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-19">Apr. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SEMIANNUAL CONVENTION OF THE POLISH CENTRAL RELIEF COMMITTEE AND THE NATIONAL BOARD</title><title level="a" type="sub">Great Internal Reforms Effected</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Thursday, April 18, at ten o'clock in the morning, the semiannual convention of the Polish Central Relief Committee opened at the Polish Women's Alliance Hall in Chicago. Members of the National Board who attended were: President T. M. Helinski, Vice-President P. Rostenkowski, Vice-President Mrs. A. Neuman, Treasurer J. Magdziarz, Secretary H. Setmajer, and Dr. Fronczak, Reverend B. Celichowski, Mrs. M. Milewski, Miss E. Napieralski, F. Porzuczek, Reverend [W.] Zapala, C. Zychlinski, I. Czerwinski, Polanski, A. Dembiec, F. Gruca, Mrs. M. Osuch, S. Szwajkart, S. Osada, A. Tomkiewicz, Mrs. L. Wolowski, Dr. Wagner, Z. Ulanowski, A. Wisniewski, L. Koscinski, and the Reverends Lempke and Bubacz. Also present were Grand Censor Blenski of the Polish National Alliance, and the Reverend Gogolewski. Members of the National Board were given the right to take part in the convention's discussions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1203.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the invocation by the Reverend Zapala, Reverend Celichowski administered the oath to Dr. Sadowski of Detroit.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the last convention were read and accepted, after which reports were presented.</p>
   <p>President T. Helinski discussed the situation in which the Polish Central Relief Committee found itself during the past six months, when, on the one hand, it had to set an example to the Polish people in America, urging them to co-operate in relief work for Poland, while on the other hand, the necessity of organizing and consolidating all Polish forces in the field of nationalistic work became more and more obvious. It was understood that the exigencies of the moment must be met and that conflicting projects must be avoided. A system of work was instituted and, in order to maintain unity in the organization, the National Board was formed, which remained a part of the Polish Central Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>Everything was changed, however, with the organization of the Polish National <pb facs="5423968_9_1204.jpg" n="3"/>Committee in Paris. Our representative on that committee, recognized by the United States Government, is Ignace J. Paderewski. From this point on, our whole organization for nationalistic work in America must be reformed, and in such a way as to bring the National Board to the head of the movement, while the Central Relief Committee becomes one of its departments, limiting its activity to relief work. The change will be a salutary one, for our representative, Paderewski, will also gain in authority with the American Government. It will be a proof of our political maturity if we understand that in harmony and unity there is strength.</p>
   <p>It will be necessary to consider the creation of a common fund to be used for nationalistic needs. From time to time, general collections will be made, while people of good will and with sufficient means can contribute steadily. The speaker (Helinski) proposed this for general discussion. He said that we must stand united and strong before the nations that sympathize with our cause, in order to work most effectively for a united and independent Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1205.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>H. Setmajer, the secretary, presented his report for the period of October 25, 1917, to April 18, 1918 as follows:</p>
   <p>Secretary's Report</p>
   <p>"For the past six months, the activity of the Polish Central Relief Committee has necessarily been limited to the collection of funds for the relief of Polish prisoners in German camps and the transmission of these funds to the General Relief Committee in Switzerland and to Mrs. Mary Stabrowski in London. Despite the fact that during the past half year the generosity of the Poles in America was directed principally toward organizing the strongest possible Polish Army in France, the Polish Central Relief Committee can report with great pleasure and pride that for strictly relief purposes, it collected $34,321.41, which is considerably more than was collected during the preceding six months, as the financial report will show.</p>
   <p>"In accordance with the decision made at the last convention, held on October 25, <pb facs="5423968_9_1206.jpg" n="5"/>1917, the secretariat of the Polish Central Relief Committee requested that the central administration of the American Red Cross in Washington give a detailed statement of the contributions made for Polish relief and how these funds were utilized. Just a few weeks ago we received the complete report for the period from January 1 to the end of December, 1917. It shows that during this time the Red Cross collected the sum of $13,777.09 for the relief of Polish war victims. It should be mentioned here that the states that contributed the most were; Maryland, with $5,000; New York, $2364.60; Indiana, $1,603.36; and Honolulu, Hawaii, $3,500. The states that contributed the least were; Colorado, $1; Kentucky, $2; and Michigan, $1.60. The American Red Cross sent most of this money to the General Relief Committee at Vevey, and the sum of $1,500 to Mrs. Herbert L. Saterlee, treasurer of the Legion of Polish Women.</p>
   <p>"In addition to this, the War Council of the American Red Cross, on November 1, 1917, assigned $200,000 to be used by the Warsaw Polish Committee in Bern, Switzerland, for the purchase of food for the children in Polish cities. This <pb facs="5423968_9_1207.jpg" n="6"/>sum was sent to the Polish Committee in Bern through the State Department, after a guarantee that the money would be used exclusively for the relief of Polish children without regard to religious convictions.</p>
   <p>Polish Relief</p>
   <p>"In the autumn of last year, after a long and exhausting correspondence with the State Defense Council of Illinois, the Polish Central Relief Committee was given a license authorizing it to collect funds for the relief of war victims in Poland. It is required to submit to the State Defense Council a quarterly report of funds collected and sent out. It is also required to allow its books to be examined by the public auditor upon demand. All printed matter must also carry the statement that the Polish Central Relief Committee operates under License 132, State Council of Defense.</p>
   <p>"The dispatch of funds by the Polish Central Relief Committee is placed, as <pb facs="5423968_9_1208.jpg" n="7"/>usual, in the hands of the General Relief Committee at Vevey, which is recognized by the United States Government as deserving of confidence and competent to distribute these funds. A few months ago, the General Relief Committee issued an extensive report for the whole period of its activity, published in a large volume containing the most detailed list of all of the contributions to Polish relief from all over the world, and how and where these contributions were distributed in Poland. From this immeasurably painstaking statement, a veritable sea of figures that speaks proudly of the magnificent scale on which the General Committee has conducted its relief work for Poland, it is shown that for the period from January 9, 1915, to March 31, 1917, this committee collected 15,827,499.68 francs in fifty-one countries for the relief fund, with the United States in first place with contributions of 8,689,453.78 francs, or more than half the total amount contributed. Of this amount, 707,077.67 francs were contributed by Catholic dioceses in the United States, 230,861.50 francs were contributed by the American Red Cross, and probably a certain sum was contributed by Americans to Paderewski's Polish Victims' Relief <pb facs="5423968_9_1209.jpg" n="8"/>Fund; it can easily be said that contributions from American Polonia totalled a good fifty per cent of the contributions from the whole world.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The distribution of funds in Poland and the correspondence of the secretary with the General Relief Committee in Switzerland have been omitted by the translator.]</p>
   <p>"In conclusion, it should be mentioned that those organizations affiliated with the Polish Central Relief Committee, such as the Polish National Alliance, the Polish National Council, and the Polish Womens' Alliance, have, for the past six months, sent all of the money collected by them for Polish relief to Switzerland through the Polish Central Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>"The operating fund of the Polish Central Relief Committee is supported by the <pb facs="5423968_9_1210.jpg" n="9"/>sale of buttons, postcards, and stickers, and continues to cover administrative expenses. This makes it possible to utilize the money collected for relief, for relief only."</p>
   <p>C. Zychlinski reported that the Audit Committee had examined the books and found all accounts in perfect order, after which the convention accepted all reports.</p>
   <p>Polish Red Cross</p>
   <p>President Helinski then reported that the organization of a Polish Red Cross is in the road to successful completion. For a long time, the American Red Cross created obstacles and refused to agree that the Government should authorize the formation of an institution of this sort in the United States. But in this case also, France hastened to our aid. A Polish Red Cross in France was authorized by the French Government, and Madame Paderewski was appointed president of the Polish Red Cross in America. The arrival in America of the official representative of the Polish Red Cross, Count Orlowski, is expected shortly. The <pb facs="5423968_9_1211.jpg" n="10"/>organizational work will be directed by Madame Paderewski, and the Military Commission will have as its principal aim the unifying of all efforts.</p>
   <p>The Polish Red Cross will take upon itself the responsibility of organizing hospitals, training nurses, and supplying Polish soldiers with books, tobacco, and so on. It will have the following departments: 1) Propaganda, 2) Soldiers' Needs, 3) Nurses' Qualifications; and 4) Women's Committee.</p>
   <p>The Polish Red Cross will also receive all funds collected for the soldiers, and will submit a complete report as to the disposition of these funds. A hospital with a hundred beds has already been established in Paris and further details will be supplied by Count Orlowski upon his arrival here.</p>
   <p>A report of the activity of the Girls' Aid for Girls Society was presented by Miss E. Napieralski, after which the Mothers' Aid for Children Society report <pb facs="5423968_9_1212.jpg" n="11"/>was presented. A motions committee, consisting of Koscinski, Zychlinski, Wolowiec, Dembiec, and the Reverend Lempke, was appointed. After a short recess, the resolutions committee, consisting of Szwajkart, Mrs. Neuman, Osada, Doctor Fronczak, and the Reverend Celichowski, presented the following motion and resolution:</p>
   <p>"The Polish Central Relief Committee in America, realizing the necessity of centralizing its nationalistic activities into those of one principal institution which cannot be conducted purely for purposes of relief, but one that can, by directing the political activities of the Polish element here, take over all nationalistic activity, as does the National Board, hereby renounces its organizational priority and, retaining its original title and aims, accepts the system of organization and representation imposed by the bylaws of the National Board, and becomes a part of this organization as its Relief Department.</p>
   <p>"The National Board will hereafter be known under the name of 'The Polish National Department of America'."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1213.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>The resolution and motion were accepted unanimously.</p>
   <p>In reply to Mr. Lokanski, President Helinski explained that Mr. White of the Polish Associated Press in Washington is publishing a collection of Paderewski's speeches in both the Polish and English languages. It was decided that members of the Polish Central Relief Committee may attend the conventions of the National Department. The next report was presented by H. Lokanski in behalf of the Committee for Economic Aid to Poland. It was accepted.</p>
   <p>Report of the Committee for Economic Aid to Poland</p>
   <p>"The report on our activity for the past six months is short, for the activity of our organization was limited by events of importance that could not be neglected. As is the case with many other organizations that laid aside their original aims and tasks in order to lend all their energy toward recruiting for the Polish Army, so the Committee for Economic Aid to Poland, working on the <pb facs="5423968_9_1214.jpg" n="13"/>principle that effective economic aid to Poland can best be given only after the Polish Army has become a reality, has temporarily withheld its action so as not to scatter our nationalistic effort in too many directions at the same time.</p>
   <p>"Without appearing externally, the administration of the Committee for the Economic Aid to Poland has worked internally to widen the field of that Committee's activity, and has gained many assurances from American circles that the Anglo-American public will hasten to aid in the economic reconstruction of ruined Poland. From American Committees similar in spirit to ours--namely, from committees in New York, San Francisco, and Milwaukee--we have received not only words of encouragement but announcements that action, perhaps even more effective than Hearst's propaganda for the rebuilding of France, will be taken by the American people toward the rebuilding of Polish towns and villages that have been destroyed by the war.</p>
   <p>"With this in mind, the Committee for Economic Aid to Poland has worked out a <pb facs="5423968_9_1215.jpg" n="14"/>detailed plan for establishing so-called 'Countrymen's Circles' (Kol Ziomkow) in Polish villages in localities ruined by the war. Furthermore, it is understood that, for example, people coming from the United States who were once residents of a ruined locality--let us say Zyrardowo near Warsaw or Jaslo in Galicia--will, after forming a 'Countrymen's Circle' in that locality, do more to raise funds for the economic reconstruction of a community in which they were born than those who know nothing of that part of the country.</p>
   <p>"The Committee for Economic Aid to Poland, having reorganized itself on a permanent basis, will, in the near future, cover the United States with such 'Countrymen's Circles,' and, by thus gaining numerical strength for its organization, will have the right to appeal to the American public for economic aid for the villages and towns of Poland that are now in ashes.</p>
   <p>"This is only one of the many aims and tasks of the Committee for Economic Aid to Poland; for the Polish element in America, after gaining the co-operation of <pb facs="5423968_9_1216.jpg" n="15"/>the American public, ought itself to carry aid to its homeland in every economic field. We understand also that the problem ahead of us is an enormous one, but having determined that it is recognized by a great many individuals here already, and that our institution, gaining in strength and energy, will undoubtedly soon become a means by which whole masses can act effectively, we have hopes that before the end of this year the Committee for Economic Aid to Poland will begin extensive work which will provide a corner-stone upon which Poland will be rebuilt from ashes and cinders to a state of economic prosperity for all of the peoples living within its boundaries."</p>
   <p>The report of the clothing committee, appearing in another column, was presented by Mrs. Milewski, and was accepted.</p>
   <p>After a short report by Mrs. Wolowski and Mrs. Neuman, the convention was adjourned with the singing of "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland) at 12:15 A. M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
