<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-05-14">May 14, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">To the Supporters of the Polish League</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Announcement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-05-14">May 14, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE SUPPORTERS OF THE POLISH LEAGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Announcement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As the Polish public in Chicago and other localities is greatly interested in the Polish League, of which I am receiving proofs every day, I am obliged to begin the duties of my office before the official opening of the League and its bureaus.</p>
   <p>It is easy to understand that the offices of the League cannot be opened officially before the organization is incorporated by the Central Board, before the officials furnish necessary bonds, and before the establishment of a complete bookkeeping system which is necessary in every large institution. It requires a few days and sometimes a few weeks to complete these formalities, and only after the expiration of this time will it be possible to open the offices of the Polish League officially.</p>
   <p>However, since so many persons from Chicago express their willingness to join <pb facs="5423968_9_0044.jpg" n="2"/>this splendid organization, and since so many are seeking information by letters and in person, in other words there are so many things to be taken care of that if I should not do them it would hurt the interests of the Polish League, and it would show negligence on my part in fulfilling the duties of my office.</p>
   <p>On account of other duties, I cannot devote all my time to the affairs of the League before the official opening of my office, though I have an ardent desire to do so; so I have decided to devote a few hours twice a week to the affairs of the League till the time when the Central Board will be able to establish a permanent office which will always be open to the public.</p>
   <p>Therefore, for the present--but this will last only a short time--I will personally serve my countrymen every Monday and Thursday from 6:30 P.M. to 9:00 P.M. at the offices of Wiara I Ojczyzna, if they call for the purpose of either joining the League or for information regarding this institution. I have hopes, however, that in about three weeks' time, and after I receive instructions from the Central Board of Directors, I will be able to devote much more time to the affair <pb facs="5423968_9_0045.jpg" n="3"/>of this splendid institution, which is holy to me.</p>
   <p>[Signed] Stanislaus Szwajkart,</p>
   <p>secretary of the Polish League in the United States.</p>
   <p>P. S. Other Chicago newspapers are requested to print this announcement.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
