<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-26">Jan. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">January Insurrection Exercises in St. Adalbert Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0835</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0835.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-26">Jan. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">JANUARY INSURRECTION EXERCISES IN ST. ADALBERT PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Elaborate exercises to commemorate the January Insurrection [of 1863] were held Tuesday, January 22, at 8 P. M., at Pulaski Hall, by the societies of St. Adalbert's Parish. The Second Corps of the Polish Military Societies of America welcomed the guests with the beat of drums into the beautifully decorated hall, which was soon filled.</p>
   <p>Joseph Napieralski, president of the National Celebration Committee, officially opened the program and gave a short address. He called upon Adam Blaszczynski and Francis P. Danisch to act as president and recording secretary respectively. The stage was occupied by Reverend John Radziejewski, president of societies from St. Adalbert Parish, and other speakers.</p>
   <p>Two choirs under the direction of Professor Hensl--the women's choir Halka and <pb facs="5423968_9_0836.jpg" n="2"/>the men's choir Moniuszko--sang "Pozegnanie Zolinierza" (A Soldier's Farewell).</p>
   <p>The first speaker of the evening was Jacob Slowikowski, who gave a review of the January Insurrection and mentioned some of his personal experiences as a participant. He explained the factors that contributed to the failure of the movement, urged his listeners to co-operate in national work, and called upon all the Poles to unite harmoniously, giving as an example Polish Day [held on October 7, 1893, during the Columbian Exposition] and Koscziusko Day [held May 3, 1894] as proof of what can be expected from unity. He urged the audience to attend the various lectures to be given throughout 1895, a year of Polish national mourning. His speech was received with enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>Miss Helen Przybylska recited "Do Sokolow" (To the Sokols). Her ability was recognized by the audience. Another recitation was given by little Miss Euphrosyne Wleklinska, much to the enjoyment of the public. The choirs Halka and Moniuszko sang "Wisla" (Vistula). A poem, "Znasz Te Kraine" (Do You Know This Region), was recited by Alexander Jasinski, who was dressed in full <pb facs="5423968_9_0837.jpg" n="3"/>uniform as a Pulaski Volunteer.</p>
   <p>The second speaker of the evening was Leon J. Schulc, a young man. He said that Poland was a country that had defended Christianity against pagan invaders. "A country of such ideals cannot be lost," he pointed out. "Although a century has passed since the third partition of Poland, and despite the relentless oppression of our people, the Polish nation still exists because it has not permitted the enemy to subdue its national tongue and its faith in the future. We are not as yet endowed with the patriotism that ought to be a part of us. Before this may become possible, the flower of brotherly love must first come into bloom; then we must look upon the youth for the future of our people. Upon the parents rests the heavy duty of rearing their children as Poles." The speaker concluded with the words, "God, return to us our freedom!"</p>
   <p>A series of declamations followed--seven-year-old Joseph Malkiewicz recited a national poem, "John Sobieski"; Miss Kleczewska recited "Gdzie Moja Ojczyzna?" <pb facs="5423968_9_0838.jpg" n="4"/>(Where Is My Fatherland?); six-year-old Ann Malkiewicz, who delighted the audience with her recitation of "Piesn O Oswobodzonem Polaku" (Song about a Liberated Pole), received a bouquet of roses for her performance; little Miss Gertrude Rewolinska and Miss Louise Malkiewicz also received bouquets for their renditions.</p>
   <p>Reverend Radziejewski, [pastor of St. Adalbert's Parish], followed with a spirited talk about the liberation of Poland. He said that Poland would never be lost because of the continuous support she received, as shown by the large attandance at this and similar affairs. Reverend J. Radziejewski stated that whenever and wherever a group of Polish people gather, they form a new Poland. (Applause). "It is our duty to remain Poles," he said; "God created us as such, and, therefore, we ought to remain as such forever.</p>
   <p>"There are pessimists who say that we will be denationalized in fifty years, but I say that we will not be assimilated in five hundred years, but will continue to worship God in our native tongue. (Applause).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0839.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Our entire future lies in our youth. Our youth, especially our womenhood, upon whom our future depends, ought to preserve the Polish language. I urge everyone to work for the good of our nation, for unity, harmony, co-operation, and support of the National Fund."</p>
   <p>Enthusiastic applause greeted the pastor as he left the rostrum. A recitation was given by the six-year-old Martha Kluczewska. The president of the program thanked the people for their support and participation and invited all to attend the lectures to be given in the near future at Pulaski Hall. The affair was concluded by group singing of "God Save Poland," a Polish national air. A collection for the upkeep of Pulaski Hall netted $18.17.</p>
   <p>Francis P. Danisch,</p>
   <p>Secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
