<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-01-25">Jan. 25, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Patriotic Demonstration Staged in St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0637</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0637.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-01-25">Jan. 25, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTIC DEMONSTRATION STAGED IN ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A patriotic demonstration was staged at the Polish Hall, Bradley and Noble Streets, yesterday (Sunday) at 4 P. M. by the parishioners of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church in commemoration of the thirty-fourth anniversary of the January insurrection of 1863 against Russian oppression. The large hall was filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>After the opening of the program, and the appointment of a chairman and a secretary, the students of St. Stanislaus Kostka College sang a national song as the first number of the evening.</p>
   <p>This was followed by a spirited speech by Vincent Jozwiakowski, who touched upon the things that precipitated the uprising. He concluded by calling to the minds of the youth its obligations. "Without your interest and support the fatherland will be forgotten," he said.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0638.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Casimir Neuman, editor of the Dziennik Chicagoski, spoke on the theme, "The Heart and Soul in Politics". The third speaker was the Reverend Francis Gordon, C.R., who based his talk on upholding the banner of "Faith and the Fatherland". The priest concluded his address by urging the people to safeguard the Polish tongue and customs.</p>
   <p>Silence reigned throughout the auditorium during the delivery of all speeches, while warm applause followed at the close of each.</p>
   <p>Declamations were interspersed between the speeches. Outstanding recitations were made by little Mroczkowski, a student of the local parochial grammar school, and John Sobieszczyk, a student of St. Stanislaus College. Songs by the college and church choirs rounded out the evening of entertainment. Andrew Kwasigroch, choirmaster and organist of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church, directed the singers.</p>
   <p>The exercises were concluded with the singing of "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
