<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-13">Feb. 13, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Kosctusko Celebration in South Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0702</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0702.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-13">Feb. 13, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">KOSCTUSKO CELEBRATION IN SOUTH CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Kosciusko celebration, under the auspices of the Societies of the St. Michael The Archangel Parish of South Chicago, was held yesterday, even though a terrible snowstorm was raging. The patriotic Polish people gathered in Mr. Retmanski's hall to honor the hero of Dubienko and Raclawice (two towns in Poland). The large and beautifully decorated hall was filled to capacity, and many of the people were forced to sit in the galleries.</p>
   <p>The soldiers' societies appeared in their uniforms. The audience behaved in an exemplary manner, because it sensed the importance of the celebration honoring the "leader in the peasant's dress," and listened most attentively, thus giving the occasion proper dignity.</p>
   <p>The pastor, Reverend A. Nowicki said a prayer at the appointed hour, and called on Mr. Szostakowski to act as chairman, and Mr. Watkowski as secretary of the celebration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0703.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The presidents of the various societies took seats of honor on the stage, and then the program proceeded. It included speeches, singing by the schoolchildren, recitations, orchestral music, and exercises by the cadets.</p>
   <p>Mr. Leon Szopinski, of Chicago, was the first speaker of the evening. He spoke of Kosciusko as an example worth imitating. Not only did Kosciusko fight bravely to free Poland, and perform miracles of bravery on the battlefield; but he endeared himself even more by helping the peasant class, which was scorned by the wealthier people, and, as children of one mother--Poland--called upon them for mutual defense. His famous saying, "Education of the masses will perform miracles," has been written in history. A hundred years ago Kosciusko recognized that only through genuine enlightenment can the Polish nation attain freedom. If the Poles had faithfully followed his advice, and sought to educate themselves more, who knows whether Poland would not have been free today? But our cause is not lost, even now. Poland is stronger today than it was a hundred years ago, because today the peasant at the plough and the scythe feels his Polish nationality, and knows that his country is held in terrible bondage.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0704.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Whatever patriotism they feel is due to Kosciusko. That is why our hero from the plains of Raclawice is so popular among the masses of our people.</p>
   <p>Being of noble birth himself, he extended his hand to simple folk, put on a peasant's dress, and leveled all classes. All honor to him for this, and all honor and praise to his followers, who so bravely faced the enemy for their country! Also, honor is due to the Poles in South Chicago, who, following the precepts of Kosciusko, are educating themselves under the tutelage of our noble, patriotic priests!</p>
   <p>All the recitations were rendered with a clear and perfect Polish diction and accent.</p>
   <p>The children--boys and girls--appeared perfectly at ease. The songs and recitations, of which there were a few, were very fine, and the audience was very well satisfied with the children's performances.</p>
   <p>The wonderful Polish Band, under the direction of Mr. Ladislaus Pacholski, <pb facs="5423968_9_0705.jpg" n="4"/>played our beautiful Polish patriotic songs and marches, and the audience applauded their efforts enthusiastically.</p>
   <p>The drill of the newly organized soldiers' society pleased everybody. Their various formations were executed with skill and in perfect freedom of movement.</p>
   <p>The pastor, Reverend A. Nowicki, spoke in conclusion. He spoke sincerely, as a patriot and a priest, and his words appealed to the hearts of the audience. He pointed out that, besides our duties toward God, we have also our duties toward our country. God created us Poles and He teaches us patriotism by His own example. We should, therefore, be faithful to the religion of our fathers, and should guard our native tongue and Polish customs, inculcate patriotism in the hearts of our younger generation, send our children to Polish schools, and thus we will not squander the treasures taken from our native country, which are holy religion, Polish speech, and exemplary action. Let us endeavor to keep our Polish banner unblemished and, if ever the time should come, to return to our native country with a Polish heart.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0706.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Reverend Nowicki's speech was interrupted time and again by thunderous applause. The people understood their pastor who, in such simple and convincing words, explained to them their patriotic duties.</p>
   <p>The singing of "God Save Poland" ended the celebration.</p>
   <p>Sz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
