<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-02">Nov. 2, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Funeral of Carter H. Harrison</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0206</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0206.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-02">Nov. 2, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">FUNERAL OF CARTER H. HARRISON</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The most solemn and magnificent funeral Chicago has ever seen passed through the city streets yesterday. Literally half of Chicago--hundreds of thousands of people--lined the streets, while about fifty thousand participated in the funeral procession. Business was suspended for the day; public buildings and even many private homes were draped in mourning.</p>
   <p>The late mayor's body lay in state at the City Hall until ten thirty o'clock. Until this time, it had been viewed by at least 150,000 people.</p>
   <p>Before the casket was closed, a German womens' choir sang funeral dirges. Eight police captains and eight fire captains carried the casket to the La Salle Street entrance, where thousands of people stood with bared heads.</p>
   <p>The funeral procession proper began at Washington and Michigan Avenues, headed <pb facs="5423968_9_0207.jpg" n="2"/>by a company of twenty-seven policemen. They were followed by the main staff on horseback, among whom was Peter Kiolbassa, riding a magnificent black charger. Then followed the Fifteenth Regiment of the U. S. Army, led by its staff of several hundred mounted officers. Then followed bands and companies of policemen and firemen. The Chicago Black Horse Troop composed the guard of honor escorting the hearse. A saddled horse upon which the late mayor loved to ride through the city streets, followed the hearse. The relatives and closest friends of the deceased mayor rode in the first seven carriages; then followed a few carriages bearing the honorary pallbearers. Of the endless train of carriages that followed, 320 carried aldermen and thirty carried representatives of the Chicago Bar Association, among whom was E. Z. Brodowski.</p>
   <p>Many societies of various nationalities participated, but beyond a doubt the most numerous and most splendid of all were the Polish societies. A magnificent troop of Polish cavalry under the command of Andrew Schultz led the Polish section of the parade, to the strains of a Polish band. It was <pb facs="5423968_9_0208.jpg" n="3"/>followed by the following military societies: the Knights of St. Martin, the Polish Queen's Guard, the Hussars of the Holy Virgin Mary, the St. Stanislaus Kostka Cadets, and others; then followed the St. Casimir Youth Society, Holy Cross Society, St. Hedwig's Society, St. Stanislaus Society, Sacred Heart Society, Holy Trinity Society, St. John's Society, St. Cecilia's Society, Society of the Apostles Peter and Paul, John Sobieski Society, Society, of the Sacred Virgin Mary, King Ladislaus Jagiello Society, St. Adalbert's Society, St. Hyacinth's Society, St. Anthony's Society, and St. Barbara's Society. Peter Kiolbassa was grand marshal; his adjutants were F. Kwasigroch, F. Bieszke, and Jacob Mucha. The Knights of St. Martin were led by F. Pokorny, the Queen's Guard by J. Goralski, the Hussars by F. Mech, and the Cadets by Captain Lama and Stephen Schultz. In commenting upon the above-mentioned societies, the American newspapers admitted that they were most magnificent, and estimated the number of participants to have been about two thousand.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
