<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-30">Apr. 30, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Kosciusko Manifestation in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">North Side Marshals Meet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0894</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0894.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-30">Apr. 30, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">KOSCIUSKO MANIFESTATION IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">North Side Marshals Meet</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The problem of grouping societies into divisions and subdivisions during the Kosciusko manifestation was discussed at last Saturday's meeting of North Side marshals, that is, marshals from societies in the parishes of St. Stanislaus Kostka, Holy Trinity, St. John Cantius, and St. Hedwig.</p>
   <p>Inasmuch as the bad weather didn't permit all marshals to attend the meeting, at the suggestion of Peter Kiolbassa it was decided to leave the grouping problem to the good judgment of the chief marshals, who will group the societies according to the wishes of all communities.</p>
   <p>The marshals gathered last night at the residence of A. Liszewski and prepared the following marching program:</p>
   <p>Grand Division I</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0895.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>First Brigade: Police, chief marshal band, Governor, Mayor, members of City Council; cadets from all parishes, arranged according to the seniority of their parishes, namely, St. Stanislaus Kostka, Holy Trinity, St. John Cantius, etc.; Falcon societies from the North Side; military societies, namely, Krakusy, Uhlans, Guard of the Queen of Poland, Knights of St. Martin, etc.</p>
   <p>Second Brigade: Band, chief marshal, Polish cavalry, societies from St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish (arranged according to their seniority), band, church and national societies from Holy Trinity Parish, Catholic Order of Foresters, Kosciusko societies, societies from St. Hedwig and St. John Cantius parishes, The Star of Victory Society, and women's societies.</p>
   <p>Grand Division II</p>
   <p>First Brigade: Band, chief marshal, military societies, Falcon societies, church and national societies (according to seniority) from Bridgeport and Town of Lake, <pb facs="5423968_9_0896.jpg" n="3"/>and Lithuanian church and national societies.</p>
   <p>The Uhlans from Town of Lake will escort the Governor, the Mayor, and the members of the City Council.</p>
   <p>This arrangement must be accepted by all societies if they wish to avoid confusion on a day so important to the Poles.</p>
   <p>On that day the eyes of the public will be focused on us, so that not to acknowledge and respect the orders of our marshals during the parade would reveal us as people who will never learn to obey those whom they choose as their leaders. This is a national affair in which no one has the right of priority because everyone is first. Poles honor the name of Kosciusko. Poles are staging a manifestation. Poles should prove that their slogan is "Faith and Freedom." All Poles, regardless of their social standing and convictions, followed Kosciusko, so why not then follow the orders of the marshals we have chosen as our leaders and whose orders we should obey?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0897.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Participants in the parade are warned by the marshal not to march with children, not to sit on the sideswalks during rest periods, not to shout at people watching the parade from their windows, and not to refresh themselves with intoxicating drinks. All should try to gain the sympathy and respect of all Poles and people of other nationalities by their exemplary conduct.</p>
   <p>Members of military societies will march in platoons, twelve abreast; members of other societies, six abreast.</p>
   <p>Societies from the North Side will gather as follows: the societies from Holy Trinity Parish will gather on Noble Street, between Milwaukee and Division; the societies from St. John Cantius Parish will gather on Noble Street, between Chicago Avenue and Emma Street; the societies from St. Hedwig Parish will gather on Dickson Street, from Blackhawk to Division Streets; the societies from St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish will gather on Noble Street, from Blackhawk to Division Street; and the societies from St. Josephat Parish (if they come) will gather on <pb facs="5423968_9_0898.jpg" n="5"/>Blackhawk Street, from Dickson to Noble Street.</p>
   <p>The societies should form themselves in lines at the appointed locations according to their seniority and be ready to start marching at the command of the marshals. The lines will be arranged by the chief marshals of each community.</p>
   <p>The first and second divisions will meet on Jackson Boulevard and wait there for the Governor, the Mayor, and the members of the City Council. Thence the parade will march to the hall of Battery D by the shortest route. At the front of the hall the standard-bearers will leave the ranks and enter the hall, where they will form the guard of honor.</p>
   <p>Participants entering the hall must obey the orders of the ushers. The ushers will wear badges and will show the people to their seats.</p>
   <p>The Badge Committee should not forget to sell the badges at the entrance of the hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0899.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Societies which are willing to participate in the manifestation but have not sent so far their share of the money needed for expenses are asked to send it as soon as possible to the cashier, Mr. John Napieralski, 684 West 17th Street, so that they nay get their badges.</p>
   <p>Societies from St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish are especially requested to make haste.</p>
   <p>The program to be given in the hall will be published tomorrow, Tuesday, in Dziennik Chicagoski and other Polish and American newspapers.</p>
   <p>Park Commissioner Z. Brodowski, who is always willing to help a good cause, donated flowers for decorating the hall, for which we thank him sincerely.</p>
   <p>The manifestation, which promises to be a success, will surely elevate us in the eyes of the American people, providing, of course, that the spirit of harmony, unity, and obedience that has been with us up to now does not abandon us on the <pb facs="5423968_9_0900.jpg" n="7"/>day of the manifestation.</p>
   <p>We hope that the memory of Kosciusko will prevent us from dividing ourselves, and that the work started with such pains will bring us honor.</p>
   <p>All societies from the North Side must be at the appointed locations before 10:30 A. M.</p>
   <p>Peter Kiolbassa, field marshal</p>
   <p>A. Lisztewnik, chief marshal</p>
   <p>Ignace Kowalski, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
