<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-08">Dec. 8, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">November Exercises Held in St. Adalbert's [Parish]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0503</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0503.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-08">Dec. 8, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">NOVEMBER EXERCISES HELD IN ST. ADALBERT'S [PARISH]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The November exercises [commemorating the November Insurrection of 1830], arranged through the united efforts of societies in St. Adalbert's Parish (especially the Julius Slowacki Literary Circle and the J. I. Kraszewski Library), were held at Pulaski Hall on December 3.</p>
   <p>The exercises were opened by P. W. Ziarko, president of the National Exercises [Committee], who named the Reverend Casimir Gronkowski, pastor of St. Adalbert's Parish, president, and Miss Cornelia Muchowski, secretary. The Reverend Gronkowski delivered a short address in which he said that the exercises were intended not only to commemorate the November Insurrection, but also to pay homage to the memory of the great novelist Henryk Sienkiewicz, whose excellent works the speaker recommended most warmly to our young people.</p>
   <p>The following program was presented:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0504.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>1. Julius Slowacki Literary Circle Orchestra.</p>
   <p>2. Polonia Chorus under the direction of B. Kujawski.</p>
   <p>3. Gymnastic drill by school children.</p>
   <p>4. Address by the Reverend T. M. Sampolinski.</p>
   <p>5. Vocal solo by Lucy Chmielinski; piano accompaniment by L. Symbor.</p>
   <p>6. St. Agnes Choir, of St. Adalbert's Parish, under the direction of S. Kujawski.</p>
   <p>7. Violin solo by Miss Wenda Symbor, accompanied by J. Niedzwiecki.</p>
   <p>8. Recitation by Miss A. Tyrakowski.</p>
   <p>9. Violin solo by Chester Rozmyslowicz, accompanied by Miss Mary Rozmyslowicz.</p>
   <p>10. Address by J. M. Sienkiewicz.</p>
   <p>11. Slowacki Literary Circle Orchestra.</p>
   <p>12. Patriotic play entitled "Tenth Pavilion".</p>
   <p>The program was concluded with the Polish national hymn, "Boze Cos Polske" [God Save Poland].</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0505.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Literary Circle did much to add dignity to the occasion by its rendition of "Medley of Polish National Hymns". Because of an important reason, the Polonia Chorus did not appear. Its place was filled by our famous tenor, Joseph Dumanowski, who sang the Chopin "Funeral March" and a tender ballad; he was accompanied by B. Kujawski. The address by the Reverend Sampolinski had a great effect upon the audience. His words not only awakened the Polish spirit, but showed that our youth live and will continue to live for Poland. He said that the youth will remain faithful to Poland and fight until Poland is freed from bondage. The reverend speaker's address will remain for a long time in the memories of all who heard it.</p>
   <p>In accordance with a suggestion by the Reverend Gronkowski, a committee was appointed to formulate a resolution which will proclaim a "Sienkiewicz Year," during which collections ought to be taken up for the Henryk Sienkiewicz Fund--a fund for the benefit of Polish children. A collection taken up at the hall <pb facs="5423968_9_0506.jpg" n="4"/>brought in $33.83.</p>
   <p>The resolution reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"We, the Poles of St. Adalbert's Parish, gathered here at Pulaski Hall to observe the anniversary of the November Insurrection, paying homage to those who died in the struggle for our nation's freedom, feel the necessity of paying homage to him also who, after our nation's armed resistance had failed, awakened faith in Poland with his never-to-be-forgotten works. The Trilogy and Knights of the Cross; [this great man] taught our nation to depend upon its own resources, showing that in the most trying moments there can be no wavering. At this momentous time, when the sun of liberty may at last begin to shine on the land [Poland] that he loved so much, inexorable death has taken him from us. Gathered here in deep sorrow, we pay homage to the memory of the great Polish author, Henryk Sienkiewicz. At the same time, we resolve to act in accordance with his principle--to believe in our own strength and to <pb facs="5423968_9_0507.jpg" n="5"/>concentrate that strength into one powerful unit, uniting with our whole nation for the defense of Polish freedom and independence.</p>
   <p>"Hail to Poland! Hail to her worthy son!</p>
   <p>"Resolution Committee: Reverend F. Helta, president; R. Maciejewski, J. M. Sienkiewicz, Mrs. Rozmyslowicz, Miss Clara Muchowski."</p>
   <p>The committee which arranged the exercises, on seeing how generously the event was supported, feels it its duty to give wholehearted thanks to those who participated in the program, and to the public which attended so numerously.</p>
   <p>Cornelia J. Muchowski,</p>
   <p>Secretary of the exercises.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
