<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. I, No. 8,
<date when="1927-12-25">Dec. 25, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Facts about the National Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1717</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1717.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. I, No. 8,
<date when="1927-12-25">Dec. 25, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">FACTS ABOUT THE NATIONAL CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Extracts</p>
   <p>Members of the Polish National Church believe in God and in the Holy Trinity. They worship Mary, mother of Jesus Christ, and they also worship all other saints.</p>
   <p>Members of the Polish National Church are the sole legal owners of the church buildings and all other church estates. All parishioners, through specially appointed committees,manage the parish wealth.</p>
   <p>This management is not a reign of the mob, as a certain "intelligent" fool in a letter to our editor branded it. It is rather a democracy. It is justice.</p>
   <p>In any partnership, if it is to be successful, every partner has to have an equal right to voice his claims and opinions; unless it is a partnership of thieves in which a few intend to deceive the rest.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1718.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The church is a partnership of Christ, in which every member has the right to know what and how everything is being done, and heed that the church fulfills the tasks given it by God.</p>
   <p>The National Church does not want to be a government institution, maintained by the state. This church demands the separation of the church from the state. That means that the church does not interfere with the affairs of the state, nor does the state meddle with the church.</p>
   <p>A church ought to be an association, of which everyone can be a member on his own accord.</p>
   <p>If someone does not feel the need of religion, nobody must judge him for it. It happens quite often that the so called unbeliever lives much more honestly than the hypocritical bigot.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1719.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A priest should not be a government official, because the state and the church are two entirely different institutions.</p>
   <p>The National Church serves all the people regardless of their political or social convictions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
