<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-31">Mar. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Tag Day for Working Girls' Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-31">Mar. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TAG DAY FOR WORKING GIRLS' HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In connection with tomorrow's celebration of Palm Sunday, our women are arranging an annual Violet Day, that is, a tag day for the benefit of the school, the nursery, and the home for working girls conducted by the Sisters of Resurrection. This tag day will be sponsored by the Society for the Care of the School and Nursery, and it has the sanction of the municipal authorities, as well as the approval of our parish rectors, who consider this society's work worthy of the support of all people of good will. It is a well-known fact the Sisters have to help support these institutions, especially the nursery and the home for working girls, both of which are located at 1849 Hermitage Avenue. Our women are appealing to all of us to make contributions, no matter how small, once a year around the Easter holidays, for a cause so dear to our hearts.</p>
   <p>The taggers will be Polish young women, daughters of our citizenry. They will give the passers-by violets, harbingers of spring, in exchange for their <pb facs="5423968_9_1144.jpg" n="2"/>contributions. May their contributions be as large as they can afford.</p>
   <p>The young women entrusted with the task of collecting are Victoria Biedka, Helen Augustynowicz, and Elizabeth Zamorski (St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish); W. Perlinski, Mary Rutkowski, and Constance Chrustowski (St. Mary of Angels Parish); Mary Kuflewski, Anna Pask, and Helen Herman (St. Casimir Parish); Josephine Dolazinski, Anastasia Wiedemann, and Helen Larkowski (St. Hedwig Parish); Elizabeth Szczepanski, Louise Szwajkart, and Mary Kosobucki (Avondale); Czaja and Rosalie Kozlowski (Logan Square); Frances Glomski (St. John Berchman Parish, Belgian); and Frances Pawelczyk and Ann Choinski (St. Stanislaus Bishop and Martyr Parish, Cragin, Illinois).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
