<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-04">Dec. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Patriotic Exercises Held at Slowacki Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0519</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0519.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-04">Dec. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTIC EXERCISES HELD AT SLOWACKI HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon, November exercises [commemorating the November Insurrection] were held at Slowacki Hall under the auspices of the Slowacki Library and Commune 39, Polish National Alliance. The hall was filled to capacity. The program was opened at three o'clock in the afternoon by Stanislaus Jankowski, who, after a short speech, called upon the well-known Alliance member and Falcon, Damazy Hojnacki, president of the local library, to preside. In a short but concise address, Hojnacki asked the audience to honor the memory of Henryk Sienkiewicz, the great novelist and national leader, by rising. Further, the chairman invited the veterans, presidents of local societies, and all scheduled speakers to take their places on the platform. He called upon Miss Harriet Orzewiecki, a member of the Lutnia Chorus, to perform the duties of secretary.</p>
   <p>Because the orchestra was late in arriving, the Lutnia Chorus, under the direction of B.J. Zalewski, rendered the first number on the program--a hymn, <pb facs="5423968_9_0520.jpg" n="2"/>"Z Dymem Pozarow" [With the Smoke of the Conflagration].</p>
   <p>To continue the program, Mrs. A. Newman, president of the Polish Women's Alliance, gave a succinct address in which she outlined the present situation in Europe, and especially in Poland; she pleaded that offerings be laid on our homeland's altar at every opportunity, and that our unfortunate brethren in Poland be not forgotten. The Philomen Male Chorus, under the direction of B.J. Zalewski, then sang a number entitled "Na Groby" [For the Graves], following which Miss Regina Olkiewicz, well known for her recitations, declaimed very beautifully, Next, the singing and dramatic society Druzyna sang "Wanderer", under the direction of B.J. Zalewski.</p>
   <p>After this choral number, J. Przyprawa, editor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, arose to speak. After a brief outline of the November Insurrection in Poland [1830] and the reasons for its failure, the speaker passed to the present times and to the present political situation in Poland and said that Poland is experiencing new blows daily. In speaking of the last heaviest blow, that is, the death of <pb facs="5423968_9_0521.jpg" n="3"/>Henryk Sienkiewicz, great leader of the Polish nation, he called upon all those present to rise in honor of the memory of this national hero. After Przyprawa concluded his address, the orchestra, directed by S. Kalkowski, played a medley of national hymns, while Mesdames Wrzesinski, Appelt, Marcinkiewicz, Glebowski, and Milasiewicz took up a collection for the destitute war victims in Poland. The collection netted $57.15. The program was resumed with an address by Stanislaus Jankowski, well-known Town of Lake businessman. Next followed a vocal number by Misses R. Natkowski, B. Walczak, and M. Gorczak, daughters of prominent local citizens, who sang "Medley", and, upon general demand, "The Flower Girl". This number was followed with a recitation by little Miss M. Adamkiewicz, entitled "The German Tortures Polish Children". The singing and dramatic society Vistula, directed by S. Filisiewicz, then sang S.A. Kwasigroch's "November Medley".</p>
   <p>After the chairman thanked all participants in the program for their co-operation, and the public for its numerous attendance, the audience, accompanied by <pb facs="5423968_9_0522.jpg" n="4"/>the orchestra, sang the national hymn, "Boze Cos Polske" [God Save Poland], and the beautiful November exercises came to a close.</p>
   <p>It should be added that all numbers on the program were well delivered, for which the audience was not sparing with its applause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
