<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-24">Mar. 24, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Short Biography of Thaddeus Kosciusko</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0945</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0945.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-24">Mar. 24, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">SHORT BIOGRAPHY OF THADDEUS KOSCIUSKO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On a day when we observe the one-hundredth anniversary of an important national event, it is not amiss to publish a short biography of [Kosciusko], the hero of two worlds. We are, therefore, presenting herewith the dry details of Kosciusko's life.</p>
   <p>Thaddeus Kosciusko was born in 1746. In 1769 he left Poland on an educational trip through France, Germany, and Italy, returning to his native land in 1774. The episode with Miss Sosnowski took place in Sosnowice, where he taught the two [Sosnowski] sisters drawing, history, and mathematics. He sojourned again in France, and in 1778 he came to America. He returned to Poland in 1784 as brigadier general.</p>
   <p>As a general under the command of Prince Joseph Poniatowski, he distinguished himself in a battle with the Russians at Dubienko, on July 18, 1792. The Russian army was brought in by the Polish conspirators of Targowice for the purpose of abolishing the Polish constitution of the Third of May. After the victory at <pb facs="5423968_9_0946.jpg" n="2"/>Targowice, Poland, he left the military service and retired to private life at Gniezno, Poland. In 1794 he took an oath as commander of the insurrection at Cracow. He was imprisoned in St. Petersburg, where he remained till his release by Emperor Paul in 1796. After his release he went to London and America. He returned to France with a diplomatic mission from America in 1798. After the Congress of Vienna, in 1815, he settled permanently in Solothrn, Switzerland, where he stayed with his friend Zeltner until his death on October 15, 1817, at the age of 71.</p>
   <p>In his late years, he occupied himself with music, painting, wood carving, and sculpture. He loved to be in the company of children. His remains were reburied in Cracow, Poland, on July 3, 1818. The erection of the Kosciusko Monument in Cracow began on October 16, 1818, and was completed in October 1823.</p>
   <p>In order to delineate the life of our leader a little better, we are reprinting a long chapter from the work of J. I. Kraszewski, entitled Poland at the Time of the Three Partitions, Volume III, beginning on page 185.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0947.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"In one of the least-known localities of the former Brzesc Litovsk [Brest Litovsk] Province, near the old highway connecting Brzesc [Brest] with Kobryn, there is a small village, just like other villages, located in the lowlands and surrounded with fields and sandy flats. Here and there in that flat country, a yellow hillock rises, covered with pine trees, junipers, or birch trees. Near the road there stands an old wooden church with a weather-worn turret, and farther on you can see poor huts, and among the trees a manor. This is Siechnowicze, the old abode of the Kosciusko family of Siechnowicze, distinguished by a coat of arms [with the words], 'Roch the Third'.</p>
   <p>"This family was once very wealthy, for as early as the fourteenth century it used the red seal, a privilege enjoyed only by princes of that time. Later on this family lost wealth and importance. The father of our hero, Louis Thaddeus Kosciusko, was a government official at Brest. His mother's maiden name was Thecla Ratomski. The Kosciusko family was related to the most wealthy families of the country.</p>
   <p>"Besides the manor at Siechnowicze, which was given to the Kosciusko family by <pb facs="5423968_9_0948.jpg" n="4"/>King Jagello, and besides the manors at Liniewicze and Stopiszew, Kosciusko's father had also in his possession the manor at Mereczow, which was given to his family as security by Prince Sapiecha.</p>
   <p>"Andrew Thaddeus Bonaventura [Kosciusko] was born in Mereczow on February 12, 1746. He had one brother and two sisters. Kosciusko's father was greatly respected by the Polish nobility, and it is said that he supported the cause of Prince Czatoryski at the Diet, for which the Prince owed him protection....</p>
   <p>"Prince Czatoryski sent young Thaddeus to the Military Academy in Warsaw, of which he was the guiding spirit. This institution furnished the country with many useful and meritorious men, such as Niemcewicz, Kniaziewicz, Jasinski, Sokolnicki, and others.</p>
   <p>"Here came the 18-year-old Kosciusko eager to learn with the zeal of youth. He used to get up at three o'clock in the morning. He made a request that they should wake him up with cold water, that he might not lose any time allotted <pb facs="5423968_9_0949.jpg" n="5"/>for studying.</p>
   <p>"On account of his excellent progress in school, he was given a traveling scholarship. He left the country with Joseph Orlowski at the time when the Confederacy of Bar was being organized. This educational travel lasted from 1769 to 1774. He visited Germany, Switzerland, and France. However, he sojourned the longest at Versailles, France, where he attended the military academy, visited fortresses, etc. Here he became acquainted with many military experts. He was so profoundly influenced with the French spirit of that time that it remained with him forever.</p>
   <p>"He returned to his native land in 1774. There was nothing for a military expert to do at that time in Poland, and the country still quivered after the first partition. The 28-year-old, idle, dreaming youth found himself temporarily at the home of Joseph Sosnowski, the marshal of the field forces of Lithuania. Here he taught Sosnowski's daughters languages and drawing. Kosciusko fell in love with Miss Louise Sosnowski, daughter of Marshal Sosnowski, who was as proud as all parvenus. However, his love was not returned. As a result of this episode, <pb facs="5423968_9_0950.jpg" n="6"/>Kosciusko left the country for America. Prince Czatoryski furnished him with the necessary funds. Miss Louise Sosnowski, whom Kosciusko loved, was immediately given in marriage to Prince Lubomirski. It is said that Princess Lubomirski [former Miss Louise Sosnowski] cherished his memory till the end of her life.</p>
   <p>"Contracting a debt in order to obtain the necessary funds for the journey, Kosciusko went to France, it seems, in 1776 and from there to America. Here, unknown to anyone, he gained the friendship and confidence of Washington and Jefferson during the Revolutionary War. He also gained the gratitude of the whole country. Distinguished by the Order of the Cincinnati, he returned to Poland in 1785. At first he was received rather coolly, for when the Polish king noticed the inscription 'Omnia reliquit servare rem publicam' on the Order, he was supposed to have said, shaking his head, 'I think that besides the public duties there are other obligations. It seems to me that this inscription savors of republican fanaticism.'</p>
   <p>"Koskiusko spent a few years at Siechanowicze, on a small estate in a small village <pb facs="5423968_9_0951.jpg" n="7"/>between the Biala and the Wlodawa rivers. He hung his Order of the Cincinnati on the altar of the village church. This state of affairs lasted till 1788. In that year, when the republic of Poland needed the services of the young men, Princess Lubomirski, in a letter to the king, recommended Kosciusko, asking the monarch to place him in the army.</p>
   <p>"Conditions had changed and military experts were needed. At a session of the Diet held on June 3, 1789, Ozarowski, castellan of Wojnicz, recommended Prince Joseph Poniatowski; later on, others asked for Orlowski, Zabiella, Wielhorski, and Kosciusko. On October 3, 1789, Kosciusko was made brigadier general. In 1790 Kosciusko took command, almost at the same time at which Prince Poniatowski and Wielhorski took theirs."</p>
   <p>In 1791, Kosciusko's division was stationed at Miedzyborze in Podole. His important activities began in 1792. As our space is limited, we cannot describe in full the unfortunate campaign of 1792, which was directed by Prince Joseph Poniatowski and in which Kosciusko was only a general, second in command. Our <pb facs="5423968_9_0952.jpg" n="8"/>readers still remember the details of this campaign, for they were published here and in Europe on the one-hundredth anniversary of the battle of Dubienko. Even this campaign brought fame to our hero. In the battle of Zielence, Kosciusko distinguished himself gloriously, and in his report Prince Poniatowski states: "General Kosciusko always gave proof of his great ability and bravery in times of danger." After the battle of Zielence, Prince Poniatowski decorated some officers for bravery, and Kosciusko was one of them. When the Virtuti Militari Cross was established, he was the first one to receive it. Kosciusko was partly defeated in the battle of Dubienko, but he came out a hero.</p>
   <p>Further events in the history of our hero took place in the year of 1794, the one-hundredth anniversary of which we commemorate today, in Kosciusko Year. In the adjoining column we are publishing the account of a historical event which took place on March 24, 1794.</p>
   <p>In other issues of Dziennik Chicagoski we will describe other events in the life of Kosciusko.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
