<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-02">Dec. 2, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Modestus Maryanski Delivers Address at Patriotic Demonstration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-02">Dec. 2, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">MODESTUS MARYANSKI DELIVERS ADDRESS AT PATRIOTIC DEMONSTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(The following address was delivered by Modestus Maryanski at the patriotic demonstration commemorating the sixty-fifth anniversary of the November [1830] uprising against Russian oppression, at the Polish Hall, Bradley and Noble Streets.)</p>
   <p>On the anniversary of our martyrdom--besides your</p>
   <p>sacrifices at the grave,</p>
   <p>Bloody, eyesight blinded by tears burning,</p>
   <p>Once again we humble ourselves in dust before,</p>
   <p>you, O Lord,</p>
   <p>And once again we beseech you--covered in</p>
   <p>mourning--</p>
   <p>Have pity, have pity on us, O Lord!</p>
   <p>And from the graves of our national heroes--</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0749.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>flocks of orphans,</p>
   <p>Like a sad flower that shoots upwards,</p>
   <p>Will offer their young lives in sacrifice,</p>
   <p>To mark the anniversaries and to pray sincerely.</p>
   <p>O, Lord! these anniversaries are too many--</p>
   <p>Have pity, have pity on us, O Lord!</p>
   <p>History justifies the right of revolution.</p>
   <p>The freedom that we enjoy in this country, the freedom that is enjoyed by all peoples in America, was brought about by revolution. The shackles were not shed without loss of blood. But now it is a priceless gift.</p>
   <p>This pearl of humanity, for which we fought and which we now share [reference to Kosciusko and Pulaski and others who fought in the American Revolution], was obtained by means of fire and sword, by means of revolution and not evolution, through revolution and not resolution or agreement on paper.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0750.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us now turn our attention to the east.</p>
   <p>Across the vast, briny expanse of the Atlantic, lies a land of graves and crosses, a land of sadness and sorrow, a land of the worst kind of persecution. But this land of sacrifice is also a land of people of noble hearts and noble spirits whose secret love for their country has withstood the oppression of tyrants. These people of this land have stood all the persecution with great patience, and, God willing, this patience will continue until the hour of reckoning arrives, when this spirit will be imbued with Vulcanian fire and give birth to the children of Freedom and Liberty.</p>
   <p>There was once a country that stretched from the Baltic to the Black Seas, from the sky-piercing Tatra and Carpathian Mountains to the far-reaching Vistula and Oder Rivers--even to the Elbe; a great country, a free country, a happy country, the only one in the world that respected its neighbors, and today this country is torn apart, divided into three sections like a piece of worthless material. Today this country is nailed to a cross, its hands and <pb facs="5423968_9_0751.jpg" n="4"/>feet tied while three vultures are snapping at its body, tearing away pieces of flesh and drinking its warm blood--and this country groans with pain and shame and cannot shed its fetters. This country is Poland.</p>
   <p>Under the pressure and oppression of its enemies, all opportunities save one, all chances and strongholds, and all vigilance with which this country fortified its self during the past century of horror are lost, and now nothing remains but the ramparts of national faith [reference to the faith in the Roman Catholic Religion].</p>
   <p>Religion was and is its greatest, unconquerable fortification. God is its hope and strength. God will also be its salvation and bring it victory.</p>
   <p>Do you hear the tolling of bells of this land which are brought to us on the wings of the wind and the blasts of the ocean? Time and again the majestic peal of the old, huge Sigismund bell at Wawel and the thunderous clap of the aged Adalbert bell of the Gniezno Cathedral can be discerned. The churches <pb facs="5423968_9_0752.jpg" n="5"/>are filled with the people of God in mourning, all fortified by the Holy Sacrament and praying amidst tears and pain, "Holy God, Holy Powerful, Holy and Immortal, have mercy on our fatherland! Holy God, Holy, Powerful, Holy and Immortal, have mercy on our fatherland!"</p>
   <p>And the graves, underground burial places and tombs, are opening, and from these sepulchers are arising the spirits of the great kings of this once great nation: those who have given their lives for the country and those who have defended christianity. Behind them follow the great heroes, knights, bishops, and saints. All rise above this kneeling mass of praying people and together offer prayers to God in order that He may hear their pleas.</p>
   <p>Amidst the risen, two great figures stand out: one in a white habit of a monk and the other in a white costume of Cracow.</p>
   <p>Who are they? The first is a monk--a heroic figure, a sterling knight who can rightfully stand beside the Maid of Orleans [Joan of Arc]. He is Kordecki, <pb facs="5423968_9_0753.jpg" n="6"/>for he rescued the country during the Swedish onslaught. The second is a beloved leader, garbed in a peasant smock, who delivered the peasants from national shame. He is none other than Kosciusko, the Washington of these people, although not as fortunate as Washington, who won the golden sunshine of freedom for America, which shines not only upon us but on our children.</p>
   <p>And now I ask you, you mothers and fathers, sons and daughters of Poland, whether you know this country which spreads along the Visutla, Oder and Varta Rivers, whether you know its people who are now shackled and so shamefully oppressed. This nation is Poland, our mother, to which we as her children reach out our hands, and she to us. It is our mother who, although a martyr across the vast ocean expanse, still has strength enough to out-stretch her shackled hands to us.</p>
   <p>You, our beloved mother, be glorified the more through your poverty, martyrdom, and defamation, for all these will help to make a crown for your glorious head.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0754.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>For what purpose have we gathered here tonight?</p>
   <p>We have gathered here this evening in order to observe in the most solemn way the sixty-fifth anniversary of the revolution of November [1830] and to pay homage to our fatherland on these distant shores, to show documentary evidence of our unity with our oppressed country, to give tribute to our future activity, and, despite the century of bondage, to show our belief in the future of Poland and her independence.</p>
   <p>The tyrannical powers, primarily the conquering powers which have divided Poland, ignore the one great truth, that conspiracy is the child of tyranny and that the only remedy for this is freedom, and not greater despotism.</p>
   <p>The insurrection of 1830 was caused by the unheard-of tyranny and oppression of the Muscovites. On November 29, 1830, as night fell, the members of the officers' training school, under the leadership of Wysocki, staged a bold attack on the Belvedere Palace, where Prince Constantine, the brother of Czar <pb facs="5423968_9_0755.jpg" n="8"/>Nicholas, resided. The prince managed to make his escape. Within twenty-four hours the Muscovites were forced out of the capital [Warsaw]. The Polish people rose with crude arms in hand to rid the country of Russian tyranny and oppression.</p>
   <p>Was there a justification for this move?</p>
   <p>Naturally! The country had not only the right but also the duty to protect itself. Freedom is the greatest gift of the universe; individual freedom and national freedom of all peoples comes from God alone, and if this gift is torn away from a nation, that people is duty-bound to right the wrong by means of force, if only to regain that independence.</p>
   <p>Dziennik Chicagoski, Dec. 3, 1895.</p>
   <p>The struggle of an oppressed people to regain its national freedom is therefore <pb facs="5423968_9_0756.jpg" n="9"/>not only a legal act but also obligatory, consequently necessary.</p>
   <p>This legality hinges upon the inalienable right to freedom which has been bestowed upon everyone by the Almighty--and there is no power on earth that has the strength to overthrow this legality.</p>
   <p>In the event that there are honorable people who hold themselves aloof from any revolutionary movement, and do not wish to become a part of it, this is not because they cherish the treasure of freedom less than others who willingly support the revolutionary movement, but because they have learned from experience that such a movement at an unfavorable time, instead of bringing freedom closer, only tends to make it more uncertain. Therefore there is concern, not only about the idea of freedom, but also the time, place, and means.</p>
   <p>The means by which to regain this freedom for our country is to come, and can only be realized, through proper channels of organization. There is need for <pb facs="5423968_9_0757.jpg" n="10"/>money, education, hands, and ability, in order to lift up the heads and elevate the spirit of our people. The success and position of individual citizens should act as a stimulus to the people as a whole. Citizenship and political leadership, along with proper social management, can do a great deal. All this means that where there is an abundance of everything and everything can be shared by us, it is there that we can be everything and a part of all that is going on about us and within us.</p>
   <p>But perhaps you should ask me, my compatriots, whether I truly believe in Polish independence, and whether Poland will be free. To these questions I can sincerely say that I believe in Poland's independence just as much as I believe in God. If at this moment an angel should enter this auditorium and should say to me that Poland will never be free, I would boldly reply to this heavenly messenger, "I beg your pardon, my most Holy Angel, but I cannot believe in what you say, for what then would happen to my patriotic duty?" For this duty is the star which will guide us to our goal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0758.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>We are greatly indebted to the Polish women who have borne all discomforts with silent patience for the sake of the patriotic feeling that we have toward our fatherland. You are the priestesses who kept aglow this ember of patriotic feeling, who passed it on from one generation to the next without losing a bit of its glow. As long as the Polish women harbor this feeling in their hearts, the fatherland will never be lost, for from their breasts flows the poison which poisons our enemies. An orchid to you here in America, and abroad as well!</p>
   <p>Although the November uprising [of 1830] did not turn out a success, it is one of the brightest moments of divided Poland. Although the Polish warriors were finally conquered on the field of battle, they were able to leave behind an indelible record of heroism.</p>
   <p>So much for the November Insurrection.</p>
   <p>In the history of Polish emigration there are two great epochs, namely, the <pb facs="5423968_9_0759.jpg" n="12"/>emigration of the gentry and later of the peasants.</p>
   <p>The epoch of the emigration of the gentry [szlachta] began when the last song of the republic was sung, when the hymn of the Barska confederates [This confederation was started by Adam Krasinski in 1768, during the reign of Stanislaus Augustus] died and with them fell old Poland--Catholic and knightly.</p>
   <p>The Barska confederacy is in reality the mother of this patriotism which, under the iron rod of Repnin and the blessing of the Reverend Mark [two Polish patriots] is being reborn in the blood of the martyrs. From its spirit comes the first protest and the first appeal to Europe, to the powers, to the people, to the reasoning of the entire Christian world. Amidst universal subjugation the "knights of the Cross" are going to their death, voicing their opposition against worldly politics of the conquerors and annexers--spreading Christian teachings and respect of the weak.</p>
   <p>It is from this group that the first immigrants came.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0760.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>The history of all our armed movements and uprisings is merely the repetition of the Barska Confederation, and every armed movement, besides the spilling of rivers of blood, means that legions of the most learned and most valiant sons of Poland have gone into exile or to meet a horrible death on the Siberian steppes.</p>
   <p>The dauntless Polish gentry picked up arms, spilled blood, went into exile, covered themselves with mourning, suffered at home and in their wanderings--that is why I like to call those that have come to this new world noble.</p>
   <p>To write the history of this group is to write the history of divided Poland.</p>
   <p>I only wish to point out that this gentry, these immigrants, never forgot the fatherland, for, although they left the shores of Europe under the threat of death if they ever tried to arouse the Polish spirit, they revived Polish patriotism on American soil whenever opportunity afforded. However, whenever any of them had a chance they returned to Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0761.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>Outside of Sporadic patriotic revivals, it cannot be said that the gentry became a permanent fixture in the United States, for a great majority tarried a while only to return to European soil. France became their main center.</p>
   <p>It was on this French soil that the Congregation of Resurrectionists was born, becoming today the vanguard of Catholicism on the Balkan peninsula, the guarding rampart that protected the Ruthenians from military schism; our spiritual guide, the sentinel of our nationality and religion amidst our immigrants of peasant stock in America.</p>
   <p>The spilt blood of our heroes have rehabilitated our nation to a certain extent in the eyes of the world and also in the annals of recorded history, for no one perishes miserably in the world. This was a satisfactory action for the wrongs of the past and became the cement that joined the falling pieces.</p>
   <p>As evidence of the incalculable benefits conferred on us by the Polish gentry who immigrated, it is sufficient to cite the poetry and other types of literature <pb facs="5423968_9_0762.jpg" n="15"/>for which they were responsible.</p>
   <p>Suffering is a great school of life and character, and when people are joined in a common bond for the realization of the same ideals, they are drawn together more by suffering than by triumphs.</p>
   <p>Let us look at the legions of soldiers--citizens who returned from their wanderings, exchanged their arms for pens, ploughs, or crosses, in order to continue the work for the future. The country is greatly indebted to them, and, although they gradually passed away to everlasting peace, their offspring who have been guided by them carried on their work.</p>
   <p>It is our duty to give credit where credit is due.</p>
   <p>There are many other things that the immigrants have done in elevating the Polish name. These must not be overlooked. The Polish gentry who emigrated spread all over the world and left an everlasting record of Polish endeavor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0763.jpg" n="16"/>
   <p>In the history of the United States of North America the names of Kosciusko and Pulaski have become immortal. Their participation in the Revolutionary War, as well as that of other Polish heroes, and the death of Pulaski at Savannah, have assured a moral shelter on American soil for our peasant immigrants.</p>
   <p>The Polish people in America are grateful for their valorous activity and honor them by naming countless societies after Kosciusko and Pulaski.</p>
   <p>In Australia Strzelecki made important discoveries, and was the first to discover gold, in the year 1839. Ignacy Domeyko won an estimable position for his services and learning in Chili.</p>
   <p>The late Domeyko, soldier, immigrant and miner, wrote the following letter to a friend of his in San Francisco on January 1, 1876, about Polish immigrants.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0764.jpg" n="17"/>
   <p>"No small happiness was brought to Mother Poland by her sons who made their way across mountains and oceans to distant lands, where they worked; where they aided and defended their nationality and religion.</p>
   <p>Our national strength is best shown by the magnitude of the forces fighting in its defense; they stretch from the Oder to the Dnieper Rivers, and are today as strong as ever before, for they are fortified with the spirit of religion and patriotism. The same holds true of those who have wandered to the far-flung corners of the world. All are faithful to Poland. It is apparent that the campaign for the restoration of Poland is destined to go onward and may be spread throughout the civilized world by our freedom-seeking people. The best road to the realization of this freedom is through heroic sacrifice, faithfulness, sincere work, etc., wherever Pole meets Pole. In this way not only will the name of Poland be glorified but the country will become free once again."</p>
   <p>And before I close perhaps you will ask why all the uprisings failed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0765.jpg" n="18"/>
   <p>The answer to this is short and simple and clear! There were not enough of us Polish people! There were not enough representatives of this great and grand nation of ours.</p>
   <p>But the times are changing!</p>
   <p>The older brothers are beginning to teach the younger brothers love for the fatherland. And these younger brothers are beginning to respect the older brothers, and the fatherland. This once great nation is beginning to awaken from its lethargy. New life is being instilled by the youth.</p>
   <p>The giant is beginning to feel, think, and act.</p>
   <p>Everywhere--throughout the length and breadth of Poland--signs of this are beginning to be seen. The gentry is a thing of the past in Poland. You are her future and her salvation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0766.jpg" n="19"/>
   <p>As soon as you--the Samson of our nation, thus far forgotten but recognized by Kosciusko--arise to the defense of this oppressed and martyred Poland, the chains that keep her in slavery will break. Through your combined efforts she will rise again to take her place among the free nations of Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
