<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-24">Sept. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">News from St. John Cantius Parish and Vicinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-24">Sept. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM ST. JOHN CANTIUS PARISH AND VICINITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A mass meeting, at which a detailed report of the delegates to the recent All-Polish convention in Detroit was given, was held on Sunday, September 22, 1918, immediately following the afternoon vesper ceremony. The delegates were: The Reverend S. Siatka, C.R., pastor of St. John Cantius parish, Mr. M. Kolasa, Alderman S. Adamkiewicz, Messrs. A.C. Bisek, M. Michalik, J. Sobota, F. Nowicki, Alderman S. Walkowiak, Dr. A. Pietrzykowski, Mmes. A. Peyor, S. Norkowski, A. Wasielewski and A. Stencel.</p>
   <p>There was a well-prepared program for the occasion. The meeting itself was formally opened by the singing of the American national anthem. The Reverend S. Siatka, C.R., was the keynote speaker, explaining the purpose of calling the meeting, and gave his report on the All-Polish convention. Following this, he called upon Alderman S. Adamkiewicz to act as chairman, and Mr. S. n as secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1176.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Adamkiewicz, immediately prior to accepting the function of chairman, made a brief, but inspiring speech about our motherland; of the sacrifices that each sincere Pole should willingly bear in her behalf, concluding that in this free country our people can and should do a great deal of good for Poland.</p>
   <p>The first number on the program was a declamation. Following this, there was group singing by children of the local parish, which was rendered with such simplicity that it touched upon the heartstrings of the attendance.</p>
   <p>The next speaker on the program was Mr. Stanley Swienton, Who reminded the people of Poland's oppression under her three aggressors, Austria, Germany, and Russia, and urged the people to work and sacrifice in her behalf.</p>
   <p>A medley of Polish national songs were excellently rendered by the local parish choir, under the capable direction of the organist, Mr. F. Nowicki.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1177.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A voluntary collection to defray the expenses of the mass meeting netted the sizeable sum of $73.62.</p>
   <p>Mr. A.C. Bisek was called upon as the next speaker. He gave a detailed report of the convention, and urged the people to make the ten-million-dollar Polish Relief Fund a reality as soon as possible. He was then followed by the well-known Polish physician and surgeon, Dr. A. Pietrzykowski, who also urged the people to subscribe to the Polish Relief Fund without delay. Alderman S. Adamkiewicz gave a report on the convention on behalf of the women delegates of St. John Cantius parish. This report was accepted unanimously upon a motion made by Mr. J. Smdczynski. Mr. J. Zebrowski made another motion, which was also passed unanimously, whereby it was agreed that all those present at this meeting will abide by the decisions that had been made at the All-Polish convention, and will put them into action. The Reverend W. Kmiecik, D.D., was unanimously selected as treasurer of this meeting. A collection <pb facs="5423968_9_1178.jpg" n="4"/>toward the ten-million-dollar Polish Relief Fund was taken up, and realized a sum of $4,750.50.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
