<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-04">Jan. 4, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">St. Adalbert Parish to Commemorate 1895 as Year of National Mourning</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0845</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0845.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-04">Jan. 4, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">ST. ADALBERT PARISH TO COMMEMORATE 1895 AS YEAR OF NATIONAL MOURNING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The representatives of all the Polish societies of St. Adalbert Parish held a general meeting on December 25, 1894, at Pulaski Hall for the purpose of making plans for commemorating 1895 as a year of national mourning [1895 marks the 100th anniversary of the third partition of Poland]. The following resolution was adopted:</p>
   <p>"Because April 24, 1895, marks the one hundredth anniversary of the third partition of Poland by her enemies, namely, Russia, Austria and Prussia;</p>
   <p>"Because the Polish nation, which has always and everywhere protected the rights of freedom and religion of other peoples, did not offer any cause for such ignominious and bloody dismemberment of our country and people;</p>
   <p>"Because, for over a hundred years we have innocently borne the servitude <pb facs="5423968_9_0846.jpg" n="2"/>and the horrid and bloody persecution dealt us by the three powers, Russia, Prussia and Austria, which have taken away our country and now wish to take away our language and faith;</p>
   <p>"Therefore we resolve:</p>
   <p>"From January 1, 1895, to May 3, 1895, to renounce voluntarily all social activity and pleasures as an indication of our mourning for partitioned Poland.</p>
   <p>"We appeal to every righteous Pole to deny himself all worldly pleasures during the above prescribed time, to supplement this with deep reflection upon our country's past, and to take active part in work for the good of our nation, thereby showing to others that we not only know how to love our country but that we also want to cherish it.</p>
   <p>"We protest against the tyrannies and persecutions of our brothers who <pb facs="5423968_9_0847.jpg" n="3"/>live on torn Polish land, and against the violated rights which were guaranteed them in 1815 by the Congress of Vienna."</p>
   <p>This resolution has been distributed to the Polish and English press.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
