<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-23">Sept. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Alliance Holds Convention</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1179</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1179.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-23">Sept. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ALLIANCE HOLDS CONVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The twenty-second convention of the Polish National Alliance is now history. Just as immediately preceding a storm, choppy waves break along the shore and quickly spend their force, so too were the conditions in the first days of the above mentioned convention. The hopes of those individuals who had long attempted to gain direct control of the Polish National Alliance for personal purposes began to die completely. The remainder of the dissenters and self-centered individuals gave vent to their fury, but their destructive efforts were spent long before the close of the convention. All that is past now, and it is not the wish of any good-thinking member of the Alliance to bring to life such unpleasant recollections.</p>
   <p>The first three days of the convention were marked by partisan arguments--arguments opposed to the true ideals toward which the Polish National <pb facs="5423968_9_1180.jpg" n="2"/>Alliance strives. But just as, after every storm, there follow fair and clear skies, full of invigorating fresh air, so was the case with the second half of the convention period. Worthy motions passed in rapid succession, motions which create new foundations for the future of our organization.</p>
   <p>In the first place, the twenty-second convention placed the Polish National Alliance upon a new system of insurance rates, according to the latest statistics of the table of American experience. As a result of this, the Polish National Alliance will gain a freedom to act in all the states of the Union. Having this freedom, the twenty-second convention agreed to introduce child insurance into the organization. This action will doubtless have a favorable result upon the welfare and development of the organization.</p>
   <p>This convention also decided to maintain and sustain its educational institution at Cambridge, Pennsylvania, as well as its immigration house in New York City.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1181.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It considered these two centers to be of vast importance, knowing that in the not so distant future they will be priceless in propagating our Polish national spirit. It did not permit any limitations to be placed upon these two institutions, thus opening before them new horizons of activity.</p>
   <p>Relative to our motherland--Poland--and her political matters, the twenty-second convention of the Polish National Alliance took a decided and definite position. It not only obligated all its (Polish National Alliance) members to pay direct national assessments toward the ten million dollar Polish relief fund, but it has also prepared a questionnaire for all officials and candidates for office in the Polish National Alliance, demanding of them to state whether or not they are in accord with the present political program of the Polish National Alliance as well as that of the Polish National <pb facs="5423968_9_1182.jpg" n="4"/>Committee in Paris, France. No other Polish organization has gone so far in manifesting its loyalty toward the Polish cause. It can be truthfully said, therefore, that the twenty-second convention, through these enactments, created an indestructible and immovable protective wall out of one hundred and thirty thousand members of the Alliance, upon which, as on a rock-bound foundation, the armed Polish action can support itself. These decisions taken by the Polish National Alliance became, as it were, additional leaves to the present laurel crown decorating the political efforts of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>The twenty-second convention gave full recognition to the organization and political work thus far accomplished by the officials during the past period. This the delegates proved more concretely by placing the same officials at the head of the organization. And so, for the next three years, that is until the twenty-third convention, which is to be held at Toledo, Ohio, the <pb facs="5423968_9_1183.jpg" n="5"/>following will direct the fate of the organization: The Honorable Judge M. Blenski, of Milwaukee, will act as censor, Mr. J. Werwinski, of South Bend, Indiana, as assistant censor. The presidency fell to Mr. Casimir Zychlinski, and Mr. K. B. Czarnecki was again chosen for the vice-presidency. Mr. J. Zawilinski was selected as recording secretary, whereas Mr. J. Magdziarz will serve in the capacity of treasurer. Nearly all the incumbent directors were re-elected to serve in the same position. This is perhaps the best proof that the delegates to the twenty-second convention made short work of all the lies and calumnies cast against the officials of the Polish National Alliance. They have proven this more concretely by disregarding the unfounded accusations of small groups of dissenters, and by giving full recognition through re-electing the people to their posts who were deserving. Out of this scorching fire the Polish National Alliance emerged even stronger than it was before and by re-electing the same officials it has demonstrated its unity in intent and solidarity in action, thus showing</p>
   <p>mutual confidence in its lines. Basing the arguments upon the premises <pb facs="5423968_9_1184.jpg" n="6"/>stated herein, we can truthfully say that the twenty-second convention of the Polish National Alliance was really of historical importance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
