<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-02-05">Feb. 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Liberty League</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-02-05">Feb. 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE LIBERTY LEAGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Liberty League can be of great service in the future and perform a great deal of good if it proves itself not to be a hindrance, in which case it will endanger its fundamental principles. Before joining it, a society should consider the principles upon which the league is founded, to the inclusion of its by-laws and immediate objectives, because although today there are many leagues which are outstanding in their field, there are also others which are poor imitations only.</p>
   <p>The Liberty League announces that it desires the cooperation of those societies the efforts of which are towards the promotion of patriotism, Christian endeavor, temperance, woman suffrage, a better political system, and a higher standard of living.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0303.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What is the hidden meaning of these words? The most sublime ideas are expressed alongside the most ridiculous. Woman suffrage, for example, was propounded by Christianity, which has given woman an immortal soul and equal rights with man. But the apostolic emancipators of woman go to ridiculous extremes. They place woman above man, thus disrupting the most suitable division of duties in the family in the most absurd manner and contrary to natural law.</p>
   <p>The work carried on for the betterment of political systems is taken up by all the political organizations, each formulating its particular platform. They begin with the Republican party and end with the extremist, anarchist, and nihilist. Each one of these organizations believes that its "ism" is the best.</p>
   <p>Under the banner of temperance there are those who believe in moderation and those who deny themselves the minutest drop even for medicinal purposes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0304.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Among the Christians there are those who observe Christian doctrines and traditions in detail and those who have adopted this religion under some peculiar form, such as the Mormons, Baptists, Russian Orthodox, etc.</p>
   <p>For the promotion of better citizenship there are many organizations which, sponsored by various factions, are already in this field, each having its particular system for this purpose.</p>
   <p>What does all this mean? In reality, it all means that all the societies that join the Liberty League, though they realize that they are fording the River of Darkness, gather to one common fold where the majority decides what system is best to recognize and which policies they are to follow and protect. Although each society keeps itself within its original aim, all submit to the majority rule, which governs the fundamental principles of the entire organization. From today on the Polish National Alliance will be subject to these conditions, made possible by the good graces of the Central Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0305.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Alliance, which has been primarily instituted for patriotic purposes, will lose all its independence to the majority rule of the Liberty League, which without doubt will join other radical organizations. Can anyone say today who will definitely gain superiority? Will this be agreeable in any degree to the Polish people? Will this fulfill their treasured dreams, or will it burst like a fancy bauble? Undoubtedly, the Alliance will have to accept the League's present platform.</p>
   <p>The League, in one of its statements to the press, said that it adheres to the policy of vox populi, vox Dei (The voice of the people is the voice of God) and that it believes it does more common good for the common people than Dei Gratia (grace of God), for up to the present time, the close of the nineteenth century, Dei Gratia has not as yet fulfilled our most necessary needs and desires.</p>
   <p>From this day "Vox populi, Vox Dei" will be recognized by the Polish National Alliance because "Dei Gratia" does not accomplish enough for the organization. "Vox populi" is the voice of the people, the voice for a greater League. It <pb facs="5423968_9_0306.jpg" n="5"/>would not be so bad to adhere to the voice of the people, but to deny the grace of God is an entirely different matter. This is exactly what the Alliance is doing. It is now going to listen to the voice of the people, because it is the voice of God. This has been demonstrated during the French Revolution. In Paris the people avowed that there was no God, for the people were God. Anarchists, nihilists, and communists pay homage to this maxim. The Liberty League and the Polish National Alliance have now joined these ranks.</p>
   <p>For what further purpose will these remarks serve? What is the use of making these assertions? What has been said will serve for the present. However, we will repeat that although the League would show that it is the most advantageous and accommodating organization for the people, which is shown by its previous accomplishments, the Central Committee was not justified in its action; it should have informed its constituents of its plans instead of acting independently, Had the Committee been concerned in presenting the Polish issue before the present Republican Congress, it would have refrained from joining the ranks of the Liberty League as yet. If the entire membership of the Alliance wanted to become a part of the League, a vote should have been cast. Nevertheless, the committee joined hands with the League on its own volition, just for publicity's sake.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
