<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. I, No. 3,
<date when="1927-11-20">Nov. 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Americanization or "Irishization"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1723</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1723.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. I, No. 3,
<date when="1927-11-20">Nov. 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICANIZATION OR "IRISHIZATION"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Irish bishops in America are doing everything to eliminate the Polish language from the church and school, and to justify that action they say that they endeavor to Americanize our immigration.</p>
   <p>But we know, and so knows the American public, that the sole purpose of that action is to strengthen the international power of the Roman-Catholic organization.</p>
   <p>The Irish are fanatically devoted to the papal clergy, and as such represent a great source of income for Rome. No wonder that the Roman clergy would like to melt us in the Irish pot and then take the same advantage of us, as they do with their Irish flock.</p>
   <p>The princes of the Roman-Catholic Church want to predominate here and by "Irishization" they expect to attain their aim.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1724.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We do not believe that in order to be a good American one should know the English language only. Is an American citizen who masters two languages worse than the one who knows but English?</p>
   <p>Kosciuszko and Pulaski did not master the English language, yet their merits for the United States are great. Many American soldiers of Polish descent did not speak English, yet during the world war they fought bravely for the honor of the United States.</p>
   <p>The Polish community here ought to educate itself and learn the spirit of freedom, tolerance and real democracy. The spirit which animated the builders of our great and happy country. We, Poles, should actively participate in every every enterprise that tends towards the good of our country.</p>
   <p>But if the Irish are to predominate over us and to force upon us their Irish clergy, the Polish community will become a herd of senseless sheep, <pb facs="5423968_9_1725.jpg" n="3"/>blindly devoted to their foreign master in Rome.</p>
   <p>It is high time that the honest Poles and sensible Americans discard that old Roman nightmare that so relentlessly stifles them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
