<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-11-28">Nov. 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">November Insurrection Commemorated at St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1021</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1021.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-11-28">Nov. 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">NOVEMBER INSURRECTION COMMEMORATED AT ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Commemoration exercises, sponsored by the Polish societies of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, were held at the Polish Hall last night. Over 5000 persons took part in the affair.</p>
   <p>The program was opened by Reverend F. Gordon, who spoke about the significance of our participation in national celebrations. He mentioned events in Polish history and pointed out that cruelty and oppression will find the day of reckoning. He also observed that Providence turned into dust the greatest tyrants and powers.</p>
   <p>"Our oppressors some day will come to their end," concluded Reverend Gordon. He called upon F. Zagrzebski to ascend the platform.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1022.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Zagrzebski, who was appointed chairman for the evening, greeted the audience, and delegated Francis Grabowski to act as recording secretary.</p>
   <p>The young ladies' choir of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church, under the direction of Andrew Kwasigroch, gave a beautiful rendition of a Polish song, "Leca liscie z drzewa" (The Leaves Are Falling From the Trees).</p>
   <p>Ignacy Kowalski, a teacher at St. Stanislaus Kostka School, gave a long and interesting speech on Polish history. A clear picture of Poland prior to 1830 was given, including the events that led to the November Insurrection. The uprising and its aftermath was also covered by the Polish teacher. The speaker concluded by urging everyone to attach himself more closely to the fatherland, and also drew attention to our national obligations.</p>
   <p>A mixed choir sang "November Song". This was followed by a patriotic declamation by Vincent J. Jozwiakowski. The audience applauded generously.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1023.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Next on the program were drills by Sokol societies of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish. Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, the director, can be rightfully proud, for the he has developed our young boys into fit gymnasts who will not only have a strong national spirit but a strong physical body.</p>
   <p>H. Nagiel was the next speaker. After pointing out the causes for the failure of the November Insurrection, which should be a lesson to all of us, he urged the audience to greater unity. Mr. Nagiel terminated his speech by citing the obligations of Polish-Americans, and declared that the support of faith and nationality is of prime importance.</p>
   <p>After the young ladies' choir sang "Wiazanki Listopadowe" (November Garlands), the military orders of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish took the stage. Their drills were well executed and inspiring.</p>
   <p>The men's church choir song a number of Polish national songs. The well-known quartet of this group, W. Barwig, John Kondziorski, Adam Stachowicz, and F. Kwasigroch, also captured the attention of the audience with their rendition <pb facs="5423968_9_1024.jpg" n="4"/>of national songs.</p>
   <p>Reverend Vincent Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, spoke about the hardships undergone by the oppressed Poles in 1830. He urged the Poles to organize and unite in the work of elevating the cultural and educational horizon of the Polish people. The speaker emphasized the need for carrying on such work in America, where freedom of religion and speech abounds, where an equal opportunity is given to all in the public educational institutions, and where all have an equal right in politics.</p>
   <p>A picturesque scene was presented which depicted a Polish historical event. Miss Rosalie Kwasigroch sang a number of solos. The Polish national song "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland) ended the program for the evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
