<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-13">May 13, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A Word of Thanks</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0654</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0654.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-13">May 13, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD OF THANKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As already reported, the celebration of the Constitution of the Third of May in my parish, was a complete success.</p>
   <p>We owe this to the great crowd that came from three neighboring parishes and also to the superb efforts of the amateurs, who gave their best to assure success to the celebration.</p>
   <p>Miss Agnes Wojtalewicz (later Nehring) and Miss Wanda Barwig were the stars of the program in their solo numbers, as were Miss Mysiak and Miss Grzadzinska from the Saint John Cantius Parish. They are genuine concert vocalists of whom we should be justly proud. Also, as was to be expected, Mr. Kondziorski and Miss Barwig were excellent in their duet.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Saint Hyacinth Parish we wish to extend to them our heartiest thanks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0655.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It would be unfair not to thank the members of the Saint Cecilia Choir of Saint Stanislaus Kostka Parish, who so willingly, in spite of the great heat of the day, proffered their services and sang in a truly remarkable manner. This is the fruit of the labors of their teacher, Mr. Andrew J. Kwasigroch, who directed the choir at the celebration.</p>
   <p>I thank him a hundredfold for his efforts.</p>
   <p>The Saint Hedwig Parish orchestra, directed by Mr. Jaks, also deserves mention. This parish can be proud that it possesses such a wonderful orchestra and such an excellent conductor.</p>
   <p>I wish to thank both the orchestra and Mr. Jaks for their kind help.</p>
   <p>I wish to also thank Mr. Wojanski, who donated his services and directed the two live tableux, which were beautiful. For the loan of the costumes for these pictures, I wish to thank the Library of the Polish National Alliance and the Dramatic Circle of the Saint Stanislaus Kostka Parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0656.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I sincerely thank Mrs. Wojanska, Miss Szulc, Miss Panten, Miss Swierza, Miss Kwasigroch, and others who composed the zither orchestra, for the wonderful tunes which entranced the audience.</p>
   <p>Finally, I thank Mr. H. Nagiel for his excellent speech. He graphically explained the purpose, meaning, and importance of the Constitution of the Third of May, there by raising a patriotic spirit in the audience. Again reminding us of the glorious past of Poland and its valiant defense of the Roman Catholic church on the one hand and the justice of God on the other, he gave our Polish hearts hope when he said "that God is just, rewarding each one for his deeds, and, considering the past deeds and virtues of Poland and her people, He will not permit her to die, but will resurrect her strong and beautiful, because He is just".</p>
   <p>All honor to the speaker for these words, which revive our belief in the future of Poland!</p>
   <p>Reverend Joseph Gieburowski,</p>
   <p>Congregation of the Resurrectionist Fathers,</p>
   <p>Pastor of Saint Hyacinth Parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
