<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1905-08-09">Aug. 9, 1905</date><title level="a">Polish Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Editorial]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0605</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0605.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1905-08-09">Aug. 9, 1905</date><title level="a">POLISH DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Editorial]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the preceding number of our newspaper we placed a proclamation of the committee on the building of Kosciuszko monument in Chicago, calling on the Polish population of our city to institute and observe an annual Kosciuszko holiday and proposed the observation of this holiday on so-called "Flag Day" June 14th of each year. This is a very fine project and truly constructive. It is worthy and deserves the support of all our newspapers, and the active interest of all our organizations (The Polish Roman Catholic Union has already done so), parishes and various societies and so that from this Kosciuszko Holiday they would arrange every year a form of national manifestation and celebration, in which all should participate, old and young, rich and poor, with such and such principles; Kosciuszko is equally dear to and beloved by all of us, therefore we all respect him and because homage of this kind is both beautiful and worthy, then let us not keep it secret but instead let us show it to the world. Let us voice it and <pb facs="5423968_9_0606.jpg" n="2"/>and give proofs that we remember about all our Fatherland's warriors, that we remember the Fatherland itself and we never want to forget about it. Those of other nationalities, looking upon us, observing the memory of Kosziuszko in a dignified way, will see that we are indeed still alive, and we live still with our old ideals undying within our hearts, they will see that we do not want to deny our national traditions and will respect us for that, because real patriotism and real patriots are honored by all.</p>
   <p>Similar celebrations, like this one proposed by the monumental committee to the Poles of Chicago, are sponsored here by almost all nationalities, Germans, Swedes, Czechs and all others, who has in Chicago and throughout America, and most of them are held by the Americans themselves, only we Poles up to this time did not have a celebration, not even one that would unite us for at least one day in the year. Our Constitutional Day celebrations or our Insurrection Anniversary <pb facs="5423968_9_0607.jpg" n="3"/>celebrations are observed by some and not by others, one parish or societies have it at one time, others at another time. Let us institute at least one commeration, one celebration, lovely and dear to our Polish hearts, let us on this day assemble to honor a hero at the foot of this beautiful monument. Let us all get together each year on the 14th of June. Let at this time in the park, where Kosciuszko monument stands, let there be found school children, let there come mothers and fathers, let there come all the societies, all the youth, and generally all of those who are Poles, and who wish to be considered as Poles: then there will really be a Polish Day in Chicago and that not once in ten or twenty years, but every year bringing together all Polish hearts, a great - Polish Day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
