<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-06">Jan. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Sokols of Brighton Park Present New Year's Day Program to Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-06">Jan. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">SOKOLS OF BRIGHTON PARK PRESENT NEW YEAR'S DAY PROGRAM TO CHILDREN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, January 1, a special children's program was presented by the Gnihzda Starszych Sokolic West Brighton Park (Adult Sokol Nests of Brighton Park), No. 827 of the Polish Alliance of Sokols of America, at 4 P.M., at the Polish Home, "Freedom", 46th and Mozart Streets. Children in large numbers attended with their parents to participate in the holiday celebration. Most of the children were composed of the junior groups of the Sokols, but this did not restrict the other Polish children of the Brighton Park community.</p>
   <p>The children and adults began to arrive as early as two o'clock in the afternoon. When four o'clock arrived, the hall was filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>Miss Ann Piarowski opened the children's program with a beautiful speech of welcome. She called upon Lottie Marcinkiewicz, president of <pb facs="5423968_9_1131.jpg" n="2"/>the adult Sokols, to preside as chairman. Miss Juliana Malec, secretary of Sokol No. 827, was also presented. Various other representatives were also called upon. All were then seated on the stage.</p>
   <p>The entertainment program was opened by the children of the junior order of the Sokols, who sang "The Star-Spangled Banner," the Polish national anthem, "Jeszcze Polska Niezginela" (Poland Is Not Yet Lost) and the Sokol hymn, "Ospaly I Gnusny" (Drowsy and Lazy).</p>
   <p>This was followed by a series of drills by the children, under the direction of Thomas Jagielka, commander of the Adult Sokol Nests of Brighton Park, No. 827. Throughout the drills, orchestral music was played. The execution of the exercises was acclaimed by the audience with loud and prolonged applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1132.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The third number of the evening was the splendid singing of the Oginski's Choir, No. 142 P.A.S.A., under the direction of T.T. Gulik. Five Polish songs, familiar to the lovers of Polish music, were rendered in professional style. This group really added to the success of this entertainment program. The children, as well as the adults, gave them a big hand.</p>
   <p>The young ladies of the junior groups of the Sokols presented a number of drills with piano accompaniment. This was followed by a piano solo, which was given by Miss Gertrude Blachowiak, a member of the Ognisko Literary and Dramatic Circle. Another member of this club, Casimir Dziekan, sang a solo, "Na Szary Wisly Brzeg" (On the Bank of the Gray Vistula). Piano accompaniment was played by Miss Blachowiak. Another series of drills was presented by the children.</p>
   <p>"Chlopacy Sokoli" (Sokol Boys), a poetical sketch, was recited by Miss Rosalie Wiewiorkiewicz.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1133.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>At this point of the program, the senior members of the Sokols displayed their ability in drilling to musical strains.</p>
   <p>A typical New Year's song was rendered by the Misses Wiewiorkiewicz and Juliana Olszewska. Miss H. Piatkowska played the piano accompaniment. The song was one full of wit. This was much to the liking of the audience. Applause and laughter greeted the singers.</p>
   <p>Another series of drills were executed by the adult members. The pyramid exercises were directed by T. Jagielka. The various formations thrilled the entire crowd.</p>
   <p>Miss Valintina Miszkowska, member of the dramatic club, recited a fitting verse, "W Imieniu Starszych Sokolic" (In the Name of the Adult Sokols). Her style of presentation was a true tribute to all members. She was followed by Miss Piatkowska, who played a piano solo, "Marsz Dziatwej Sokolej" (Sokol children's March).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1134.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The vice-president of Group II of the Sokols, Stanislaus Osada, one of the guests of the evening, gave a talk on the activities of the children in the Sokols. He urged the parents to take interest in the work of these groups, and influence their children to join. Mr. Paluch, a representative of Group II, talked on keeping the children active in the Sokols.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the program, gifts were presented to the children. Although the entertainment brought smiles to the children, the presentation of the presents brought broader, gleaming smiles on their faces.</p>
   <p>Miss Marcinkiewicz thanked everyone present for his support. The choir sang the Polish national anthem. However, this did not terminate the festivities. A signal from Frances Niedzwiecka started the orchestra to play dance tunes. Soon the adults were "tripping the light fantastic."</p>
   <p>Juliana Malec, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
