<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-10">Feb. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Commemoration of the Birthdays of Lincoln and Kosciusko</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-10">Feb. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">COMMEMORATION OF THE BIRTHDAYS OF LINCOLN AND KOSCIUSKO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Society, group 1450 of the Polish National Alliance, one of our best known and most active groups, whose membership is limited to Poles born in this country, arranged exercises commemorating the birthdays, on February 12, of Thaddeus Kosciusko and Abraham Lincoln. The exercises were held yesterday at Pulaski Park, Noble and Blackhawk Streets.</p>
   <p>This commemoration gathered together, as it has each year, many fine people, a large majority of whom consisted of young Polish-Americans and relatives of the members of the Chicago Society. Mr. Leon S. Mallek, counsel for the Polish National Alliance, was master of ceremonies. He opened the meeting with a short speech describing the gravity of the moment which the Poles, who believe in the realization of their century-old hope of regaining their homeland, are now experiencing.</p>
   <p>The program, previously announced, was performed as scheduled, with the <pb facs="5423968_9_0481.jpg" n="2"/>exception of the dance solos, which Miss Mary Mallek was supposed to execute, and which she was unable to do because her family is in mourning over the death of Anthony Mallek.</p>
   <p>Dr. E. G. Urbanowicz sang in his beautiful bass voice "Modlitwa Jagielly" (Jagello's Prayer), by Czubski, and "The Mighty Deep," by W. H. Judes, accompanied by Dr. H. J. Urbanowicz. He was rewarded with a storm of applause.</p>
   <p>In a speech lasting almost an hour, delivered in English, Mr. K. B. Czarnecki, vice-president of the Polish National Alliance, described the life and deeds of Abraham Lincoln, pointing to this noble and great man as an example worthy of following.</p>
   <p>The ladies' trio consisting of Misses K. Kosinski, Martha and Mary Kowalski, accompanied by Mr. J. Kowalski, met with general approval. They sang Abt's <pb facs="5423968_9_0482.jpg" n="3"/>"Water Lilly" and Emerson's "Lullaby" very well.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vincent Jozwiakowski, well-known elocutionist, recited Adam Mickiewicz's "Oda do Mlodosci" (Ode to Youth) with deep feeling and understanding. The applause forced him to recite excerpts from Lenartowicz's "Bitwa Raclawicka" (Battle of Raclawice) to the unbounded delight of the audience.</p>
   <p>We did not suppose that Mr. Edward Pijanowski was such a piano virtuoso and that he had mastered this instrument so completely, as he demonstrated yesterday by playing Lack's "Spiew Strumyka" (Song of the Brook) and Godard's "Etuda Artystyczna" (Artistic Etude). The Poles in America will have a pianist of uncommon skill in Mr. Pijanowski. He possesses all the necessary attributes of a fine artist.</p>
   <p>Miss Sophie Mankowski recited a charming piece in English, and as an encore <pb facs="5423968_9_0483.jpg" n="4"/>recited it in Polish.</p>
   <p>Mr. Thomas Osada, for whom we also predict a successful future, played the violin with his customary vigor and spirit. He charmed the audience, eager for the soft tones of the violin, with Schubert's "Serenade" and Rehfield's "Spanish Dances." He was accompanied by Mr. S. Mrozinski.</p>
   <p>In conclusion Mr. J. Przyprawa, editor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, delivered a rather lengthy speech, pointing out to the young Poles born here the duties which they have and which they should fulfill toward our country.</p>
   <p>The exercises ended with the singing of "America" and "Boze cos Polske" (God Save Poland). The voices of several hundred of our young people born in this country filled everyone's heart with gladness that she [Poland] is not <pb facs="5423968_9_0484.jpg" n="5"/>lost whose sons and daughters, although native Americans of the second and third generations, have not forgotten the sacred love for our beloved homeland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
