<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-03">May 3, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Nine Hundredth Anniversary of St. Adalbert Commemorated at St. Adalbert Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-03">May 3, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">NINE HUNDREDTH ANNIVERSARY OF ST. ADALBERT COMMEMORATED AT ST. ADALBERT PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A beautiful program in honor of the nine hundredth anniversary of the martyrdom of St. Adalbert was staged, along with tribute to the founding of the Constitution of the Third of May [1791], at the St. Adalbert parish school hall yesterday (Sunday). The rich program comprised twenty-two numbers. Five of these were given by speakers.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Adolph Nowicki, pastor of St. Michael Archangel parish, was the first guest speaker to address the audience. He spoke about the meaning of the clergy in nationalistic life, and also of the significance of true patriotism, which is based upon sound moral principles.</p>
   <p>Casimir Neuman, editor of the Dziennik Chicagoski, spoke about the Constitution of the Third of May. The journalist emphasized the roles the nobility [Szlachta] and the clergy played in bringing about the change of the old Polish <pb facs="5423968_9_0619.jpg" n="2"/>constitution.</p>
   <p>"Can A Polish Roman Catholic Priest Be A Patriot?" was the theme of Reverend Sklarzyk's talk. This was given as a retort to some of the liberals who contend that, once a priest takes his oath, he renounces his family, friends, and fatherland. The priest claimed this to be false, and said that those guilty of such assertions are "professional" patriots.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zembaczynski confirmed the opinions of the previous speakers, and Clement Belinski warned against the influences which are trying to undermine the fruits of twenty-five years of effort by the Poles in this community. All speakers were generously applauded.</p>
   <p>The recitations of the school children, the singing of the St. Cecilia Singers' Society, the piano solos, and other numbers held the interest of the audience throughout the program. These numbers were concrete evidence of the educational training and effort exerted among the youth of St. Adalbert parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0620.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The chairman of the program, the Reverend John Radziejewski, pastor of St. Adalbert parish, thanked everyone for taking part in this affair, which was opened with the singing of "Mother of "God and concluded with "God Save Poland".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
