<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. VI, No. 208,
<date when="1926-09-04">Sept. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Labor Day and Polish Labor in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0375</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0375.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. VI, No. 208,
<date when="1926-09-04">Sept. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">LABOR DAY AND POLISH LABOR IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American labor world celebrates Labor Day next Monday. It is the only holiday of its kind, building up a lofty example.</p>
   <p>It merely demonstrates that the working class of people in this country are keeping at a distance from international red standards; that millions and millions of the best workers in this great American republic are keeping in step, submissive to the general interests of the nation - listening to patriotic watchwords, politically and socially, which gives them strength, power and force! And thanks to that particular strength, this country can, at any moment, combat effectively any kind of perverse movements which has a tendency toward disorder and anarchy.</p>
   <p>Also obvious in the United States, the urgent demands of life and the pattern set up by capitalism, creates out of necessity a labor movement tending toward organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0376.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In addition, the present social make-up here favors the increase of influences and the power of trade labor unions, which today in their organizational frames, embrace no less than forty millions of the working multitude. But organized labor in America is not socialistic or communistic. On the contrary, in plain terms it possesses a direction based prominently on agreement; and even in its struggle with American capital, it is always conciliatory and in addition joins with it solidly, both internally and externally in critical moments.</p>
   <p>American methods of labor's struggle with capital are revolving within legal boundaries and above all in a legislative way, through influences in centers of government and legislative bodies. These, therefore, are the results of the rearing of the American masses of labor in an atmosphere of social obedience and equality, and relatively in an atmosphere which lacks the distinct feeling of a caste system.</p>
   <p>Society here has, due to this, a deep respect for the law as well as social order, and a high sense of duty. Under these circumstances, various encounters of labor <pb facs="5423968_9_0377.jpg" n="3"/>with capital in the United States are rather economic problems not having an outstanding mark of politics, than what is happening elsewhere.</p>
   <p>Social science in this country denies the existence of the so-called class consciousness among the American people; it renders conspicuous the equality of chance for the enterprising intelligence and the vigorous muscles of the American worker, opening for him wide areas for his future career in life. Because today's modest worker can tomorrow become a small capitalist, and in time even a wealthy person; studying then in the evening he can advance into a private profession or even strive for some dignified office as a citizen.</p>
   <p>To this great respect for labor and the understanding of its importance in the economic life of a nation, America owes, along with its natural wealth, her power, development, well-being and high standing in the world. The opinion is justified that America created somehow its own philosophy of labor, making dependent universal welfare upon the intensity of production of every worker in the country.</p>
   <p>The worship of labor penetrating the entire American community, reacts also on the immigrant. The Polish worker becomes convinced early that here is demanded of him an exertion of energy and muscles unknown in Poland. From this originates <pb facs="5423968_9_0378.jpg" n="4"/>the supposition that the Polish immigrant with this same use of energy could arrive at the same state of well-being in Poland as he does in the United States. Besides this, one must consider that in addition, the Polish worker arriving here, had to bear and overcome many unknown difficulties, and acquaint himself with numerous disillusionments before he could finally gain for himself a relatively supportable state of well-being.</p>
   <p>In America, however, it was his sudden fortune to arrive in the workshop of physical labor at whose service was science, only in order to simplify production in this country, to diversify the use of commodities, and to improve living conditions for all. Because America only seemingly appears to be a complicated mechanism, while in reality all of the symptoms of life and labor here are being placed into uniformly patterned frames and broken up into simplified functions, making it easier and quicker for adaptation to the immigrant. This mechanizing of life and industrial productiveness makes it easier for the Polish immigrant to pass from foreign soil into the ranks of American workers.</p>
   <p>It is a natural thing that at the outset he was unpleasantly looked upon by workers <pb facs="5423968_9_0379.jpg" n="5"/>over here, who, not without justification saw in him a formidable competitor. Because not knowing the language or American conditions, the Polish worker with ease agreed to worse conditions of labor and salary, which, along with his low livelihood demands, was in proportion to the salaries in Poland, very alluring; and because of his modest demands, the Polish worker found work with ease over here, whereas in addition he was not eager to strike, and in more than one instance occupied the place of the striker. And when conditions in time changed for the better, the Polish worker here was generally considered as being conscientious, dutiful, and peacefully attached to his work.</p>
   <p>In a general mass, the Polish immigrants in America belong to that class of workers which in this country is referred to as common labor, or unskilled workers; and only in the measure of their adaptation to new surroundings and conditions, by acquainting themselves with the language of the country, do they acquire better pay and more important posts in the workers' domain. This advancement is being accomplished slowly under the conditions, chiefly because of the lack of that wider knowledge and preparation for a trade or occupation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0380.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>And that is why the bettering of the Polish lot in this country has become dependent on the advancement of the educational level of the Polish immigrant masses. School - here you have the first rung of a better career in life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
