<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-01">Dec. 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Celebration in St. Hedwig Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0978</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0978.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-01">Dec. 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATION IN ST. HEDWIG PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The November celebration, commemorating the 1830 Polish insurrection, was held on Wednesday, November 29, in the St. Hedwig Parish School hall.</p>
   <p>The celebration was a grand and successful affair. The hall was beautifully decorated in the national colors, with wreaths and laurel leaves. Our young people dressed in native costumes performed various military exercises during the intervals between the numbers on the program.</p>
   <p>Reverend John Barzynski the local pastor, opened the ceremonies with a strongly-worded speech that was instructive and entertaining. He then called on Mr. J. Jablonski to act as chairman.</p>
   <p>The local choir sang "Bracia Rocznica" (Brothers, The Anniversary) to the accompaniment of the orchestra. Then the Reverend B. Pawlowski spoke about the <pb facs="5423968_9_0979.jpg" n="2"/>historical events of the 1830 Polish insurrection and explained why it was a failure. He next emphasized the duties of parents, and how they should educate their children to become good and loyal Poles. Reverend Pawlowski argued that the chief cause of the fall of Poland was lack of unity and brotherly love, and he said that if we seek for this brotherly love on a religious and national basis we will undoubtedly have our country restored to us in the near future. The audience greeted the speech with tumultous applause.</p>
   <p>Then Miss A. Kielichowska recited the poem "Smierc Sowinskiego" (The Death of Sowinski), after which Mr. B. Klarkowski read a sketch about Mickiewicz. Mr. Klarkowski spoke vigorously and with feeling about our beloved bard, who, although he is dead, left us a heritage of thoughts and words which warm our hearts and intellects. The sketch was very instructive and was frequently interrupted by waves of applause.</p>
   <p>The local choir sang "Polska Powstajaca" (Poland Arising); Miss M. Kielichowska and Mr. J. Wachowski recited a poem; and then Mr. Mirski recited "Smierc <pb facs="5423968_9_0980.jpg" n="3"/>Wiezienia Stanu" (Death of a Prisoner of State) with great feeling. This poem illustrates the sufferings and oppression of our poor nation.</p>
   <p>Then Reverend J. Barzynski invited the audience to the evening church services for those killed in the years 1830-1831. He closed the ceremonies by leading the audience, accompanied by the orchestra, in singing the national anthem "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland).</p>
   <p>The St. Hedwig celebration, the first ever arranged in this community, was very interesting. It was instructive, and many of those present were deeply moved; it renewed and strengthened the feeling of patriotism in their Polish hearts. Those who helped to arrange this affair deserve great credit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
