<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-21">Mar. 21, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Attitude of the Polish National Alliance Toward the Polish Mass Meeting and the Polish League</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-21">Mar. 21, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">ATTITUDE OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE TOWARD THE POLISH MASS MEETING AND THE POLISH LEAGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In today's issue of Zgoda, we find two announcements which elucidate the attitude of the Polish National Alliance toward the projected Polish mass meeting to organize a Polish League in America. One of these announcements proceeds from the Central Board, and the other from the censor of the organization. The censor says that any Pole not acquainted with our conditions in America would applaud the lofty idea of holding a Polish mass meeting to organize a Polish League in America, but that the members of the Polish National Alliance should take this matter under profound consideration. Finally, he calls upon every member of the Polish National Alliance to be cautious in this important matter and watch every step.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0137.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In its announcement, the Central Board of the Polish National Alliance expresses deep sympathy for the idea of promoting unity among the Poles, but maintains that the system of representation at the mass meeting makes the reconciliation of the Polish people impossible, and that to call a mass meeting is a physical impossibility on account of hard times.</p>
   <p>As regards its own participation in the mass meeting, it says: "However, the management of the Polish National Alliance, in order to prove their patriotism and desire for unity, decided to participate in the mass meeting, so that we may establish a national fund and have an opportunity to ask all Poles to discontinue quarreling and end parish disputes which degrade us in the eyes of the Americans.</p>
   <p>"The groups are at liberty to send their delegates to the mass meeting; but their delegates shall have no right to speak in the name of the Alliance."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0138.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As to the League, the Central Board of the Polish National Alliance calls it impossible and maintains that it is based on principles which place it under the influence of political parties and the clergy. It also states that such a League may prove harmful to the proper development of the Polish immigrants in America.</p>
   <p>This is the stand of the Polish National Alliance as regards the proposed mass meeting to organize the Polish League. We present the thing as it stands and refrain from commenting upon it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
