<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. IV, No. 27,
<date when="1930-07-03">July 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A Great Day in All Saints Parish of the Polish National Catholic Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1635</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1635.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. IV, No. 27,
<date when="1930-07-03">July 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT DAY IN ALL SAINTS PARISH OF THE POLISH NATIONAL CATHOLIC CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 29, 1930, the day of Saint Peter and Paul, when Mr. Herbert Hoover was the President of the United States and Prof. Ignacy Moscicki was the President of Poland; when Rt. Rev. Francis Hodur was the head bishop of the Polish National Catholic Church and Rt. Rev. Leon Grochowski was the bishop of the western diocese, the historical act of blessing the cornerstone of All Saints Cathedral, in All Saints Parish of the Polish National Catholic Church in Chicago, was performed.</p>
   <p>The ceremony of blessing was performed by the Rt. Rev. Hodur, head bishop of the Polish National Church, assisted by Bishop Jan Zenon Jasinski from the Buffalo diocese, Bishop Leon Grochowski from our diocese, the clergy from nearby parishes, and the throngs of the faithful.</p>
   <p>The 29th day of June, 1930, was indeed a great and memorable day in All Saints Parish. It was the day of proving our strength and worth for the great cause of our Free Church. On that day we had an opportunity to <pb facs="5423968_9_1636.jpg" n="2"/>observe the attitude of honest Americans towards us, especially those who rule the country. Every fair-minded observer of this celebration must admit that this test burned out excellently. We can not describe all the details of this celebration but we will give you the most important ones.</p>
   <p>At about 8 A. M. our faithful people began to gather in front of the new church. The street in front of the church was filled. The houses around the church and the church itself were beautifully decorated. At 9:30 the American Legion, led by Captain Johnson, arrived. The Legion was preceded by a company of trumpeteers and buglers dressed in picturesque costumes. There were forty of them. The blowing of the bugles and beating of the drums moved the celebrators profoundly and thrilled them very deeply, bringing tears of joy and happiness.</p>
   <p>A procession was formed. Captain Johnson, the head marshal, was helped by his assistant, Francis Kordecki. The band, directed by Mr. P. Sokolowski, started to play a march. The procession, headed by the company of buglers, which was followed by a group of 100 girls dressed in white <pb facs="5423968_9_1637.jpg" n="3"/>and girded in blue ribbons, began to march. The great number of American, Polish, church, and society banners resembled a forest. The white Polish eagle was conspicuous. The procession was a mile long.</p>
   <p>In Wicker Park. Processions from other parishes joined ours in Wicker Park. This made the procession much bigger. The weather was grand, but it was hot and the marchers were perspiring. The procession reached its destination. The motorcycle police kept order. The streets and sidewalks were filled with onlookers.</p>
   <p>The procession was greeted by Bishop Grochowski standing on the steps of the cathedral together with Bishop Jasinski and the clergy.</p>
   <p>After a short while there appeared a group of priests preceded by the ministrants, after which strode solemnly Bishop Francis Hodur, the head of the P. N. C. church, accompanied by two bishops. After a short prayor in the old church, they went directly to the cornerstone where the St. Cecelias Choir greeted the head bishop with a special song.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1638.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The grand procession reached the cathedral and Bishop Hodur performed the ceremony of blessing the cornerstone, assisted by Bishop Jasinski, Bishop Crochowski, and the clergy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
