<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-21">Jan. 21, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">St. John Kantius Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1772</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1772.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-21">Jan. 21, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ST. JOHN KANTIUS CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Like other Polish parishes on the Northwest Side of Chicago, St. John Kantius' parish had its beginning in the Church of St. Stanislas Kostka.</p>
   <p>Because those parishioners of St. Stanislas Kostka's Church who lived in what was then called "Poland in Exile" found the distance to their church too great, they began to demand a new church and a school in their neighborhood. The pastor of St. Stanislas' Church, the Reverend Vincent Barzynski, recognized their demand as just, and in 1892 the work was begun of organizing a new Polish parish in the "Poland in Exile" district. Next year, in 1893, the land for the church and the school was bought at Front and North Carpenter Streets for the sum of $75,000.</p>
   <p>The first pastor of the new parish was the Reverend Jan Kasprzycki, who later became general of the Resurrectionist Congregation. Thanks to his zealous work the foundations for the new church were laid in the spring of <pb facs="5423968_9_1773.jpg" n="2"/>1893, although the new parish was already functioning, for the buildings that were bought with the lots were remodeled, some of them for the school, others as living quarters for the teaching nuns, and [one as] the rectory. In July, 1893, Archbishop Feehan conducted the ceremony of laying the corner-stone for the new edifice, and before the end of the year, on December 24, 1893, the lower part of the church had been completed and consecrated by the Archbishop. The first Mass in this church was celebrated by the late Reverend Simon Kobrzynski. There were two assistant priests, the Reverend F. Matuszewski and the Reverend A. Babski; the Reverend J. Kasprzycki was pastor of the parish.</p>
   <p>Because of hard times the construction of the church progressed very slowly. Not until the next year did they succeed in putting the roof over the building and in finishing the front with towers. The work in the interior of the church continued for the next five years. The church bells were blessed by the Reverend Vincent Barzynski. The most memorable date in the history of St. John Kantius' parish was December 11, 1898, when Archbishop Feehan, <pb facs="5423968_9_1774.jpg" n="3"/>accompanied by many priests, church organizations, and sodalities from neighboring parishes and in the presence of great masses of worshippers, performed the ceremony of the consecration of the new church.</p>
   <p>The parishioners of St. John Kantius' Church may justly be proud of the result of their efforts and their sacrifices, for the church is one of the most beautiful edifices not only in Chicago but in the United States. It is 230 feet long and 107 feet wide and can accommodate 2000 people. The power of the church's attraction is so great that people who belong to it only for a short time and then remove to another parish feel lonely, and those who return to the old country, even to the Carpathian Mountains, recall St. John Kantius's with pleasure.</p>
   <p>After the death of the beloved Father Vincent Barzynski, the founder and the first pastor of the parish, the Reverend John Kasprzycki was nominated to succeed him. Further work for the improvement, beautification, and enlargement of the parish was carried on by the succeeding pastors, the late <pb facs="5423968_9_1775.jpg" n="4"/>Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek, the late Reverend Stephen Debkowski, the Reverend Stanislas Rogalski, and the late Reverend John Kosinski. The two last pastors have contributed very much to the growth of the parish school. An imposing edifice has been constructed according to the most modern specifications, and the unremitting labors of the teaching nuns, the Sisters of Nazareth, have gained for St. John Kantius' School special recognition from the Chicago Board of Education. The assistant priest, the Reverend Vincent Rapacz, deserves lasting recognition for his work in fostering the religious and patriotic spirit among the parishioners. Father Rapacz has been working in the parish since March 23, 1899, and is widely known for his ceaseless, and zealous labors.</p>
   <p>(Summary)</p>
   <p>The list of names follows of ten other assistants who have worked in the parish.</p>
   <p>(Translation Continued)</p>
   <p>In 1915, on the death of the Reverend John Kosinski, the administrative work <pb facs="5423968_9_1776.jpg" n="5"/>was taken over by the former assistant priest of St. John Kantius's and St. Stanislas Kostka's parishes, later pastor of St. Stanislas Kostka's Church, the Reverend Stanislas Siatka.</p>
   <p>Although two new parishes have been formed out of St. John Kantius's the life of the parish continues at the same tempo, and the proof of this is the bustling activities of the church sodalities and societies and the new parish buildings just completed this year. There are more than sixty different sodalities and church societies in this parish. The most recent society organized by the local pastor with the help of several prominent parishioners is the Educational Aid Society, the aim of which is to aid financially young people of both sexes who desire to continue their studies, but whose parents are too poor to help them. There are many boys and girls who have the necessary mental equipment for further study but because of the indifference or the poverty of their parents are not able to acquire a proper education. This society has already educated several boys and girls, and next year, with God's help, will send more of them on to their higher studies <pb facs="5423968_9_1777.jpg" n="6"/>so that our community may have more people with education and knowledge.</p>
   <p>Last year Father Kowalski bought new benches for the school and had the schoolrooms renovated, and in order to provide more free space for the children, he bought two old houses just east of the church, so that at present the pupils have more space in the open air.</p>
   <p>Several years ago the parish celebrated with great pomp the silver anniversary of its foundation.</p>
   <p>The following priests are now working in the parish: the Reverend Stephen Kowalczyk, pastor, and Assistant Priests Vincent Rapacz, Paul Sobczak, Valentine Swientek, and Stanislas Gadacz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
