<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-04-02">Apr. 2, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Patriotic Exercises Held by Poles in Town of Lake</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0814</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0814.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-04-02">Apr. 2, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTIC EXERCISES HELD BY POLES IN TOWN OF LAKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fifth in a series of patriotic exercises, commemorating the one hundredth anniversary of the third partition of Poland, was held last Sunday at the University Settlement House 4947 [South] Ashland Avenue, Town of Lake.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Kodis, M. D., presented a lecture on the origin and development of the world. Her talk was made more interesting by the use of sketches, prints, and illustrations of plant life and fossils, which were loaned by the Columbian Museum. The speaker also touched upon the world prior to the antediluvian period.</p>
   <p>The next number on the program was a musical trio, consisting of violin, cello and piano, played by members of the Settlement House, Misses Mitletone, Adams and Brown.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0815.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Young Miss Zurawaka, well known to the audience, entertained them with a declamation. This was followed by a piano solo by Miss Brown, who has often taken part in these affairs.</p>
   <p>Mr. [?] Lisicki delivered an address on the insurrection of January, 1863 [Polish rise against Russia]. Another declamation was given by Miss Ziolkowska. The program was concluded by the local choir singing "God Save Poland" [choir presumably from St. Joseph Parish].</p>
   <p>The program was received with warm enthusiasm by the audience.</p>
   <p>A collection, under the initiative of Mr. Lisicki, for the National Fund [for the Polish cause] brought $2.70. [This is all that is said about the Fund; at that time there were two: one headed by E. Jerzmanowski of New York was started about 1887, and the other was started recently by the Polish League.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
