<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-01-28">Jan. 28, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Patriotic Demonstration Staged in Bridgepor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-01-28">Jan. 28, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTIC DEMONSTRATION STAGED IN BRIDGEPOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Through the combined efforts of the Polish societies of St. Mary of Perpetual Help Parish a patriotic exercise was staged, commemorating the thirty-fourth anniversary of the January uprising against Russian oppression, at the parish school hall on January 24. With the turnout of all society members and a large attendance of parishioners, the auditorium was overcrowded.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Stanislaus Nawrocki opened the demonstration with the Lord's Prayer, after which he spoke about the part played by the Polish youth in the history of the nation. This was followed by the singing of "Ojczyzno Dlugo Grzebiona" (Fatherland, You Are Long Buried) by the St. Hedwig Young Ladies' Society. Then Miss R. Grazewicz recited a beautiful poem entitled "Garse Ziemi" (A Handful of Soil).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0633.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The school children, under the direction of their teacher, Mr. Zabka, sang "Wezwanie Do Boju" (Call to Battle); after which Dr. J. M. Stupnicki delivered an address based on the need for unity. In conclusion he stated, "When peace, unity, and co-operation exist, and the same ideals are striven for, only then will we be able to say, 'Poland is not yet lost'."</p>
   <p>Miss Helen Reich then recited "Co To Ojczyzna" (What is the Fatherland). The St. Agnes Society sang a Polish national air. Michael Swiatkowski gave an interesting lecture on patriotism. The exercise was concluded by the singing of "Co to Za Gwar?" (What is the Noise?).</p>
   <p>At this point in the program, a five-act drama, "Bohaterka Powstania" (Heroine of the Insurrection), was enacted. All the amateurs displayed their best talents. The leading roles were played by Miss Rosalie Bieszka, Miss Martha Brychel, S. Rybakowski, Joseph Skrzypczynski, and John Kunka. The latter's acting of the comic conclusion of the play had everyone almost rolling with laughter.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0634.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Sincere thanks are extended to the public for supporting this event, despite the cold weather and strong northern wind. Thanks are also given to all the amateurs and all others who took part in the program.</p>
   <p>Maximilian Wojtalewiez, chairman,</p>
   <p>Casimir Klukaszewski, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
