<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-10-01">Oct. 1, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Imposing Ceremonies in St. Bruno's Parish Tomorrow Blessing of the new Church and the Parish School--Cardinal Mundelein to Officiate, Assisted by the Congregation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik-Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-10-01">Oct. 1, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">IMPOSING CEREMONIES IN ST. BRUNO'S PARISH TOMORROW Blessing of the new Church and the Parish School--Cardinal Mundelein to Officiate, Assisted by the Congregation</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, October 2, at 3:30 P.M., His Eminence Cardinal J. Mundelein, in an imposing ceremony, will bless St. Bruno's new parish church and school.</p>
   <p>Two years ago the Cardinal, after receiving many petitions from this community, sent to us a very ambitious and energetic pastor in the person of the Reverend Alex Stanislaus Gorski, a marvelous worker and organizer.</p>
   <p>Father Gorski, with the willing and unstinted assistance of his congregation, was able within a two-year period to build, furnish, and maintain a church, an assembly hall, a home for nuns, a rectory, and an eight-grade school on twenty-five 30-foot lots situated at 49th Street and Harding Avenue, in the <pb facs="5423968_9_1729.jpg" n="2"/>Archer-Crawford neighborhood. This is a metropolitan community in which Polish-American people predominate.</p>
   <p>The parish area is bounded on the north by the Drainage Canal, on the south by 53rd Street, on the west by the Belt Line Railroad, and on the East by the Santa Fe Railroad. It is a pleasant and healthful area, carefully zoned for residence. The absence of factory buildings insures a clean and smokeless community.</p>
   <p>From the time of the establishment of the parish prosperous people, prospective home-owners, who have visited our community, have found the surroundings cheerful and pleasant and the air fresh and clean, and as a result hundreds of them have decided to settle among us.</p>
   <p>We now have more than four hundred children in our school, in which the teachers are Felician Sisters. The Board of Education has inspected the school and has <pb facs="5423968_9_1730.jpg" n="3"/>found that it fully complies with all public school requirements.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Jacob S. Organisciak, an able and devoted priest and a hard worker, is the pastor's assistant.</p>
   <p>We have a Polish Roman Catholic Union group, a Polish National Alliance group, and several clubs. There is a building and loan association which is growing very rapidly.</p>
   <p>Many of our streets are already paved; others are under construction and are to be completed in the spring. The home-owners are to be congratulated on the care bestowed on their property and the splendid order in which this [section of the city] is kept. Cleanliness prevails; green lawns, flowers, shrubs, and trees are everywhere.</p>
   <p>A beautiful statue of St. Bruno, paid for by the congregation, will also be blessed by the Cardinal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
