<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. IX, No. 50,
<date when="1890-12-10">Dec. 10, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation to National Societies in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. IX, No. 50,
<date when="1890-12-10">Dec. 10, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION TO NATIONAL SOCIETIES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Fellow Citizens:</p>
   <p>About ten years ago the Harmony Society of Chicago sent notice that in order to preserve the language of our forefathers they demanded the building of a Polish library.</p>
   <p>The Harmony Society sent letters to all Polish societies and organizations to join with us, to help support, upkeep and to enrich this library. Only few societies were interested in this undertaking. They donated money and elected the officers. In their constitution they resolved that this library be made free to all our fellow citizens, and to the Polish people interested in supporting a library of this kind. In a short time whether due to lack of money or for other reasons the societies withdrew, leaving the upkeep of this library upon the shoulders of the Harmony Society, and the Society of Teachers. Shortly afterwards the Society of Teachers withdrew, leaving the Harmony Society the sole means of support for this library. The kind of support given this library by our society in the last few years can be ascertained by examing our books. The newest and best books obtainable written by prominent Polish poets and writers can also be obtained from the secretary. Today the library numbers nearly 1,500 volumes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0338.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To this day the library is and will continue to be the property of the Harmony Society. There is a clause in the constitution stating that when times are better and the people show more interest in supporting an institution of this kind, the Harmony Society will permit other Polish societies to join and help enlarge and enrich this library.</p>
   <p>In the last ten years since this library was established, many new societies were organized which could help continue this library. Even the P. N. A. at the last meeting, held in November has taken steps with the aid of the Harmony Society, to open its own Polish library.</p>
   <p>For nearly one hundred thousand Polish people in our city, we should have at least one good library in a beautiful building, with books of the best and highest quality. But one society such as the Harmony, cannot take care of so great an undertaking. Therefore we are asking you with the permission of the officers. Do you, dear fellow citizens, want to work hand in hand in supporting, upkeeping and enriching the Polish library in Chicago? Do you want to take care of it, own it and add to the financial needs of this library? The cost of the upkeep is not very high. It is up to you to donate whatever you can. We suggest that each society interested in this send two or three delegates to the special meeting to be held Sunday evening, January 11,1891 at Nalepinski's Hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0339.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There it can be decided whether the societies are in favor of one big library or whether each society will organize and maintain a library of their own.</p>
   <p>At this meeting a new constitution will be written to be used by all libraries whether united as one or under their own separate ownership. A central group of officers will be elected, a librarian or librarians to be selected from the best men obtainable, through the aid and votes of all the present delegates. All delegates chosen to represent their group, please be present.</p>
   <p>Harmony Society of Chicago</p>
   <p>M. Rzeszotarski, President</p>
   <p>J. Olbinski, Secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
