<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-04">May 4, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">National Celebration in the Holy Trinity Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-04">May 4, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">NATIONAL CELEBRATION IN THE HOLY TRINITY PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The national celebration in the Holy Trinity Parish was held Saturday, May 2, in the school hall.</p>
   <p>The hall was well crowded when Mr. Centella opened the celebration and called on Mr. M. V. Pikulski to act as secretary.</p>
   <p>The combined "Chopin" and "Wand" choruses opened the program by singing.</p>
   <p>The first speaker, Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, in a lengthy talk, appealed to the hearts of the listeners, exhorting them to work in the name and spirit of Christian unity, for the welfare of our fatherland, and renewing their faith and belief in the Supreme Being, and reviving their hope for a happier future for our beloved country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0671.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the singing of "The Third Of May," by the Chopin Choir, Mr. Barszczewski read an interesting essay, which was very well liked by the audience.</p>
   <p>Then followed a recitation by Miss Lisztewnik, singing by the Holy Trinity Girls' Choir, a recitation by the young Anna Wojtalewicz, and singing by the Holy Trinity schoolboys.</p>
   <p>The last speaker was Mr. John F. Smulski. He urged more energetic action in the building of the Kosciusko monument, mentioned the necessity of further education, and appealed to all not to forget the national fund, but to work willingly and steadily, and promised that the results will be satisfactory.</p>
   <p>During the celebration, the sum of ten dollars was collected. According to the decision of the committee, one half of this is to be given to the educational fund of the Polish National Alliance, and the other half for the Kosciusko monument.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
