<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-09">Feb. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Commemoration of the January Insurrection at Holy Trinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0485</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0485.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-09">Feb. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">COMMORATION OF THE JANUARY INSURRECTION AT HOLY TRINITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday the young people of Holy Trinity Parish commemorated the January insurrection of 1863 with an inspiring and rather elaborate program at the Polish Women's Alliance building. The entire program, which was well chosen, was excellently performed. A large audience attended despite the inclemency of the weather.</p>
   <p>The exercises were opened by Mr. Stanley Uchacz, who explained the purpose of the commemoration tersely and briefly. Following him, Misses Clara Dymek and Catherine Sztolc sang "Kwiecisty i Wonny Maj" (The Flowery and Perfumed Month of May). Their charming voices found their way into the hearts of the audience who recalled them twice. The recitation "Biala Szata" (The White Robe) by Miss Helan Warszewski was full of spirit and artistry. Mr. S. Plucinski played the piano well.</p>
   <p>The male chorus of Holy Trinity made its first appearance of the year. It <pb facs="5423968_9_0486.jpg" n="2"/>It sang "Jagello's Prayer," with which we are all now familiar. The strong and melodious voices, plus Mr. Vincent Baluta's expert accompaniment, created the impression of a first-rate opera. The chorus deserves praise. The solo parts were sung outstandingly well by Anthony Ludwig, Anthony Ciesielski, and Peter Stawinoga.</p>
   <p>The main mumber of the program was a speech appropriate to the occasion, delivered by Reverend Anthony Rozewiez, C.S.C. The speaker chose The January Insurrection as his topic. He spoke fluently and with deep feeling for his subject. "Although the insurrection was not successful," he said, "let us not blame our forefathers for this. Our fathers, impelled by love of the homeland, did what they could to deliver it from the enemy. Perhaps we too, if we lived in their time and circumstances, would have done the same. Nevertheless the insurrection was not utterly fruitless. It aroused and strengthened the national spirit, which today--not as during the times of autonomous Poland--has penetrated all strata of Polish society and unites the into one <pb facs="5423968_9_0487.jpg" n="3"/>strong body." The speaker was applauded enthusiastically.</p>
   <p>Mr. Marian Nowakowski sang "O Gdybym Znal" (If I But Knew). The unusually good singer gave an excellent performance. Miss Veronica Fedor deserves special mention for her violin solo, with which she charmed the audience. Without exaggeration, she possesses an unusual talent. Her technique, spirit, and fantasy catches the audience. We hope that this new virtuoso will not neglect her talent before reaching perfection.</p>
   <p>As a final number the play entitled "Polska Kobieta" (The Polish Woman) was given. The amateurs performed well. Their knowledge of their lines, careful enunciation of the native language, and complete freedom of movement on the stage permitted them to perform the play as it should be performed. The following persons took part in the play: P. Adamczyk as "Marja Zelewska, Justyn Jankowski as "Zygmunt," Josephine Borucki as "Jozefa," B. Tylicki as "Ludskij," and Nicholas Bialon as "Iwanow."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0488.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The exercises were concluded by the singing of "God save Poland."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
