<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 138,
<date when="1905-06-14">June 14, 1905</date><title level="a">American Flag Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0608</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0608.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 138,
<date when="1905-06-14">June 14, 1905</date><title level="a">AMERICAN FLAG DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today is the 128th anniversary of the origination of the American flag, which bears to the present day the same form and distinction.</p>
   <p>Governor Deneen in his proclamation, appointed this day as the day of remembrance of our flag. In different parks parades are being conducted under the auspices of American Flag Day Association.</p>
   <p>In public schools the meaning of this day will be explained; and how at the request of Washington the first flag (which at that time had thirteen stars) was made by Elizabeth Ross.</p>
   <p>Why has the American flag of today forty-five stars?</p>
   <p>Of all the events in the different city parks, the most important one will take place at Humboldt Park at the Kosciuszko monument.</p>
   <p>The celebration will be started by the vice-president of a Polish society and by the master of ceremonies Mr. Henry Harrison Cleveland. At 1:30 P. M. the different societies and organizations will meet at Wicker Park, and then march on Ewing street to Robey street; then down to Leavitt street, Le Moyne street, Rockwell, Evergreen, California avenue and down Hirsch street to Humboldt Park, to the Kosciuszko monument.</p>
   <p>The program consists of about twenty different numbers of many Polish and <pb facs="5423968_9_0609.jpg" n="2"/>English songs and speeches before unfolding the American flag, march of the State Militia; march of seamen, march of war veterans of different nations, also a parade of children of the Polish Catholic school.</p>
   <p>One of the speakers will talk about the good work and deeds of Kosziuszko; this speaker is none other than Mr. I. M. Nelinski, secretary of the society of Z. N. P. The Poles have taken a great part in this celebration.</p>
   <p>Besides this great celebration, smaller ones will take place in Lincoln, Douglas, Washington and Garfield Parks. In these smaller parks the celebration will begin at 3:30 in the afternoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
