<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-06">May 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Patriotic Manifestation Staged at Polish Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0804</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0804.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-06">May 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTIC MANIFESTATION STAGED AT POLISH HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A patriotic program was staged yesterday in the Polish Hall in memory of the 104th anniversary of the Constitution of the Third of May by the local (St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish) agency of the Polish League. Despite the downpour at the time of the opening of the program, a large crowd gathered in the auditorium.</p>
   <p>The program was opened by Leon Szopinski. Boleslaw Klarkowski was appointed to preside as chairman and Simon Zielinski as recording secretary.</p>
   <p>After an introductory speech by the chairman, the men's choir of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, under the direction of Andrew Kwasigroch, sang the popular Polish song "Bialy Orzel" (White Eagle).</p>
   <p>The program on the whole was varied, holding the interest of the audience throughout. Besides the choir singing, solos, declamations, a lecture and two speeches were the highlights of the evening.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0805.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A lecture, based on the theme "The Constitution of the Third of May,"</p>
   <p>was delivered by Mr. Szopinski. The work was interesting and well done. Many lofty thoughts, observations and suggestions were offered. By the kind permission of Mr. Szopinski, the entire text of the lecture will be published tomorrow. In view of this, suffice it to say that the words of L. Szopinski were received enthusiastically by the audience.</p>
   <p>The second number worthy of note on the program was the speech delivered in Polish by Reverend Serafin Cosimi. We wish to make especial note of this, because Reverend Cosimi is Italian by birth. He spoke so fluently that one would think him a true Pole. When the chairman introduced him he explained that Reverend Cosimi became a "Pole" because of his ardent love for that nation. This was shown by his address. He received a great ovation from the audience.</p>
   <p>The second speech of the evening was delivered by Reverend Vincent Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church. He praised the audience for braving <pb facs="5423968_9_0806.jpg" n="3"/>the storm to attend this great patriotic event. The pastor urged the older people to do their share in promoting the national spirit among the Polish youth, to spread the word of knowledge, and to continue to arrange patriotic gatherings. He advised everyone to forget their differences in order to bring about peace and harmony. An appeal was made not to cast stones at the people but to judge their accomplishments. In conclusion he urged the audience to work for the common good of the Polish people.</p>
   <p>Besides this, the men's choir sang "Chlopek" (Little Peasant); the ladies' choir sang "Wiazanka Majowa" (May Garland); and solos were given by J. Kondziorski and Miss Wanda Barwig.</p>
   <p>Declamations were rendered by two boys, Kalinowski and Krepec, Miss L. Bardonska, Miss Ursula Klarkowska, and the two daughters of Mrs. Hedwig Smolinska.</p>
   <p>The program was concluded with the Polish national hymn, "God Save Poland." The proceeds of the program were assigned to the reading room of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
