<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-28">Jan. 28, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">First Convention of Polish Sokols Alliance of America Held at Polaski Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-28">Jan. 28, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST CONVENTION OF POLISH SOKOLS ALLIANCE OF AMERICA HELD AT POLASKI HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first convention of the Polish Sokols' Alliance of America, which was organized over a year ago, was held at Pulaski Hall yesterday.</p>
   <p>The hall was decorated with banners, flags and coat of arms. Various slogans were placed on the stage and side walls. Some of the posters read as follows: "He who started and has not finished is not worthy to be called a sokol"; "No gain--no glory"; "Heigh, Arm In Arm"; "Let Us Awaken and Grow"; "In Unity There Is Strength", etc.</p>
   <p>At 2 P.M. Casimir Zychlinski, president of the Polish Sokols' Alliance of America, began the proceedings with a speech. His talk was opened with the following question: "How did the sokols originate?" His speech follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1442.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The sokol was a result of the battles, fires, ruins and fears of the January rising of 1863. As the Phoenix of our nation was reborn from the flames and the pogrom....and soared high, so did the sokol originate. Its aim is physical development; followed by spiritual, patriotic and moral development. It strives for freedom and the removal of the weeds that blot our field. The Poles ought to support wholeheartedly such an organization."</p>
   <p>A report was made by a committee in charge of checking all sokols represented at the convention. It revealed that the following delegates were present:</p>
   <p>From Sokol No. 1, A. Dziadul and Messrs. Osinski and Mieczynski; Sokol No. II, J. Adamowski, J. J. Chrzanowski and J. F. Smulski; Sokol No. 8, of Bridgeport [a community of Chicago], J. Bauer, A. Piotrowski and Mr. Paliwoda; Sokol No. 4, of Jersey City, N. J., F. Marcinkowski, J. Zawielinski and S. Cichowicz.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1443.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Representatives of the Stephen Czarnecki Sokol, W. Pierzchalski and S. Arczynski, attended the convention to discuss plans for joining the Polish Sokols of America. They were accepted by a vote, with the same status as other members of the various groups.</p>
   <p>After this procedure was disposed of, telegrams from the sokol societies of New York City and Buffalo were read.</p>
   <p>J. F. Smulski was chosen to act as president of the assembly and Alfred Dziadul was appointed recording secretary.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zychlinski read a report in which he showed that the idea of sokols among Polish-Americans originated in Chicago in 1888. Today, besides Chicago, sokol branches are represented in New York City, Jersey City, Buffalo, Brooklyn, <pb facs="5423968_9_1444.jpg" n="4"/>Milwaukee, and South Bend. The Polish Sokols' Alliance of America was founded on January 7, 1894 in Chicago, where at present it is concentrating all its power. At the close of the year this newly born organization had four groups and one hundred and fifty members. The reserve capital was $47.25, the revolving fund was placed at $173.35, and the general fund was estimated at $220.60. One performance, combined with drills, was given last year.</p>
   <p>The president concluded reading his statement by stating the present aims: To get a sokol instructor from Europe, to have the same kind of uniforms for all sokol branches, to organize a sokol paper, to support the Polish League, etc.</p>
   <p>The secretary's report, which was accepted, was much like that of Mr. Zychlinski.</p>
   <p>A report was given by the financial committee, headed by Mr. [?] Baranski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1445.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The following figures were cited: $47.25 was assigned as reserve capital; $62.25 was paid out for overhead; $198.15 was the net return of last year's performance; $311.65 was the gross capital; expenses were set at $91.05, leaving $220.60 in the treasury. The accounts and property of the Polish Sokols of America are in good order.</p>
   <p>Correspondence, wishing the sokol groups success, was also read.</p>
   <p>The first question for discussion was that of uniforms. Mr. Zychlinski made a motion to have the type of dress used by the Galician sokols adopted. The following members took part in the discussion: Messrs. Blaszczynski, Mieczynski, Adamowski, Chrzanowski, and Dziadul [First names not given]. The proposal was adopted and intrusted to a committee composed of C. Zychlinski and Messrs. Mieszczynski and Baranski.</p>
   <p>The question of getting a European instructor was also taken up. It was <pb facs="5423968_9_1446.jpg" n="6"/>agreed to make arrangements with the sokols of Lwow which would make it possible to operate the Chicago sokols on an equal footing. The entire body agreed to pay for the upkeep of an instructor. Upon a motion by J. J. Chrzanowski, it was agreed to make an effort to fill the need for a European instructor by hiring one if at all possible.</p>
   <p>The following persons were made honorary members: Dr. Carol Lewakowski, delegate of the Vienna Parliament, Sigismund Milkowski, T. T. Jeza of Switzerland, and E. J. Jermanowski of New York.</p>
   <p>After the bylaws of the organization had been read, various changes were made.</p>
   <p>A debate as to the site of the next Polish Sokols of America convention ended in Chicago's being chosen again.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1447.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The election of officers was next in order, and the following members were chosen:</p>
   <p>Casimir Zychlinski, president; Leon Czeslawski, first vice-president; F. Marcinkowski, second vice-president; Alfred Dziadul, secretary; Anthony Groenwaldt, treasurer; Mr. Mieczynski, director; A. Osinski, assistant director; A. Glaza, J. J.Chrzanowski, Mr. Bauer and S. Cichowicz were appointed to the Departmental Commission (Wydzial); and W. Zychlinski, Mr. Zawalinski and A. Piotrowski were chosen for the Revision Commission.</p>
   <p>A publicity Commission, which will publicize the sokol idea in the press, was also picked; A. Blaszcznski, Mr. Nowak and C. Zychlinski were chosen for this commission.</p>
   <p>A motion by J. J. Chrzanowski, to make a collection for the Polish National <pb facs="5423968_9_1448.jpg" n="8"/>Fund, was carried; four dollars were donated and fifteen dollars were added from the treasury.</p>
   <p>A first anniversary banquet of the Polish Sokols of America was held at Pulaski Hall in the evening. Over one hundred persons attended. Some of the speakers were: C. Zychlinski, Mr. Mieczynski, J. F. Smulski, Mr. Nowak, Dr. Lande, J. J. Chrzanowski, F. H. Jablonski, and others. A beautiful verse by Mrs. T. Samolinska was read. Many toasts were given in honor of the fatherland, sokols of Poland, Czech sokols, etc.</p>
   <p>A collection for the Kosciusko Monument Fund netted $8.62.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
