<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. VI, No. 250,
<date when="1926-10-25">Oct. 25, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Sesquicentennial Celebration of United States' Independence</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0367</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0367.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. VI, No. 250,
<date when="1926-10-25">Oct. 25, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SESQUICENTENNIAL CELEBRATION OF UNITED STATES' INDEPENDENCE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday will be written with golden letters in the history of the Poles in Chicago, because thousands of our countrymen, not only witnessed a magnificent Polish manifestation, staged at the Municipal Pier, on the occasion of the 150th anniversary of the United States' Independence and the arrival in America of two of our heroes, Thaddius Kosciuszko and Casimir Pulaski, but also listened to addresses delivered by such right, honorable guests as the Vice-president of the United States, Chas. G. Dawes, the Minister of the Republic of Poland, John Ciechanowski, and the Mayor of Chicago, W.E. Dever.</p>
   <p>The Poles on the south side of the city greeted Minister Ciechanowski in St. John of God Parish. 8000 of our countrymen greeted him enthusiastically in the afternoon at the above hall, and in the evening at the Palmer House, where a splendid banquet, in which 300 prominent Poles took part, likewise city, county, state and federal officials, was given in his honor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0368.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Yesterday's Polish celebration was very successful in every respect. The representation of all Polish organizations, clubs and societies was very great. The Manifestation Committee acquitted itself of its problem excellently.</p>
   <p>8000 POLES AT THE MUNICIPAL PIER.</p>
   <p>About 1 o'clock in the afternoon, the gigantic hall in the Municipal Pier began to fill with our countrymen, who were arriving to great the eminent guests, Minister Ciechanowski and Vice-president of the United States, Dawes. About 2 o'clock the hall was filled to capacity. About 8000 of our countrymen occupied, not only all the seats, but also all the aisles.</p>
   <p>Those gathered, greeted very warmly, the honored guests as they arrived in the hall, Vice-president of the United States, Dawes; Minister to the United States from Poland, Ciechanowski; and Mayor Dever of Chicago. When the honored guests, as well as the representatives of the Polish organizations and the arrangement committee took their respective places on the platform, the program got under way.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0369.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The celebration was opened by Mr. S. Adamkiewicz, who called on the Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, Pastor of Holy Trinity Parish, to deliver the invocation.</p>
   <p>INVOCATION OF REVEREND SZTUCZKC.</p>
   <p>"C Eternal God, Creator of heaven and earth, and Founder of all the nations of the world, look down upon us, Thy children, gathered in this assembly hall to commemorate the one hundred and fiftieth anniversary of the Independence of the United States. Deign to bless us all here present and listen to our humble prayers."</p>
   <p>"America, the country, whose Independence we are celebrating, we cherish with ardent affection and love, and pledge our sincere loyalty. This we do, because America is a free and beautiful country; because her citizens, regardless of their race, conditions of life and religious tenets, live as children of one and the same family, under one heavenly Father, entitled to equalrights, <pb facs="5423968_9_0370.jpg" n="4"/>benefits, and privileges; because when the land of our fathers, we of Polish descent were persecuted, oppressed and down-trodden, America has extended to us her magnanimous hospitality, received us into her bosom and nourished us as her children."</p>
   <p>"Great and Good Lord, it is to Thee that we owe this vast and beautiful and free country. Thou hast created her. Thou hast enriched her with independence, Thou watchest tenderly over her destinies; therefore, to Thee, our most sincere and heartfelt thanks! We thank Thee also for calling the two illustrious men of our Polish blood. Thaddeus Kosciuszko and Casimir Pulaski, to the ranks of those whose privilege it was to fight for liberty and independence of the whole land of the brave and the free."</p>
   <p>"O God, All-powerful and All-good, bless America, our new and very dear Fatherland; let for all future ages, her inhabitants enjoy liberty, independence <pb facs="5423968_9_0371.jpg" n="5"/>and prosperity, for the Glory of Thy Holy Name, for their own happiness, and for the advancement of the entire human race."</p>
   <p>"May this grand celebration of the Independence Day of the United States and the arrival to this country of Thaddeus Kosciuszko and Casimir Pulaski teach us to understand better and to fulfill more conscientiously our sacred duties to Thee, our Supreme Lord and Master, and to our dear God-given Fatherland, we beseech Thee, through Thy most beloved Son and our Saviour, Jesus Christ. Amen."</p>
   <p>Following the invocation, the choir of the Polish Singers Alliance, under the direction of Mr. J.J. Jakajtis, sang Polish and American Hymns. The main soloists were Miss Joanna Jachimowicz and Miss Jadwiga Czarnecka.</p>
   <p>Continuing, Mr. Adamkiewicz called upon Mr. F. Garbarek, Vice-president of the Polish National Alliance, to act as chairman, and upon Mr. J.M. Sienkiewicz <pb facs="5423968_9_0372.jpg" n="6"/>, head of the Polish Youth Alliance, to act as secretary.</p>
   <p>Mr. Garbarek delivered a short, but beautiful speech, untroducing to the public the right honorable guests.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Mr. William E. Dever, Mayor of Chicago.</p>
   <p>"It is no small honor, "said Mr. Dever, "that I have the privilege to meet such distinguished guests as are the Minister of the Republic of Poland and Vice-president of the United States. The first of whom, represents a Nation, whose history is the most interesting of any country in this world. The other is a representative of America, paying tribute to two Polish heroes, Kosciuszko and Pulaski, in the name of the entire United States."</p>
   <p>"The Poles ought to be proud of their history, because it represents a ceaseless struggle for freedom and the final victory over the tyranny of three <pb facs="5423968_9_0373.jpg" n="7"/>oppressors. Kosciuszko was the expression of Polish ideals."</p>
   <p>"Millions of Poles came to America to find a sanctuary from tyrants. They became good citizens over here, whose character and observance of the laws of this country became an example for all other nationalities."</p>
   <p>"I am proud that I represent a city, where there are about one half million Poles, the best American citizens."</p>
   <p>In his speech Mr. Dever demonstrated an excellent knowledge of Polish history, and his friendship toward the Poles, whom he has continually tried to know better.</p>
   <p>After the speech of Mr. Dever, the joint choirs sang with success the "Pollonaise" by Kurpinski. They were accompanied by the orchestra of Mr. J. Kapalka. Following this, a speech was delivered by the Vice-president of the United States, Mr. C. G. Dawes. After the speech by Mr. Dawes, the Chairman <pb facs="5423968_9_0374.jpg" n="8"/>read a telegram from Governor Small, that due to unforeseen circumstances, he was not able to be present to take part in the manifestation.</p>
   <p>After the orchestra played selections from the opera "Halka", Mr. John Ciecnanowski, Minister to the United States from the Republic of Poland was called upon to deliver an address.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
