<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-06-19">June 19, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">New Polish Building and Loan Association Organized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0324</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0324.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-06-19">June 19, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">NEW POLISH BUILDING AND LOAN ASSOCIATION ORGANIZED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Fifteenth Ward Building and Loan Association, organized on June 8, 1891, will hold its third meeting at Mr. Joseph Kowaczek's Hall, 1025 North Hoyne Avenue on June 22 at 7:30 P. M. We wish to inform the public that our association is still in the process of organization. At present, we are not accepting any money, but new members. This will not be a small organization of ten or fifteen members. We desire to have a large gathering at which we will discuss ways and means of organizing a building and loan association, and elect qualified persons for officers of the association.</p>
   <p>At present, we have two temporary officials: John Lewandowski, president, and Constantine Swiatkowski, secretary. As soon as we have a thousand members the association will be legally organized. Then the members will pay their dues which will be twelve and a half cents on one share. We <pb facs="5423968_9_0325.jpg" n="2"/>will then have a right to elect regular officials. This rule was made at the last meeting. We have applicants already for 316 shares. Brothers please do not delay, for we need such an Association at St. Hedwig's Parish.</p>
   <p>Let us take a look at St. Stanislaus Kostka's Parish. In that parish, there are many building and loan associations, and every one is in a fine condition. Our parish is so large that we could have two or three of them, yet we have none.</p>
   <p>Let us all gather at the above mentioned hall on Monday, June 22, and we will be convinced that it is easier to help one another than to pay a large rate of interest and nice premiums to downtown rich banks.</p>
   <p>In the name of the committee</p>
   <p>Constantine Swiatkowski, Secretary,</p>
   <p>1057 Dudley Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
