<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-06">Mar. 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Second Patrotic Meeting Held at St. Adalbert Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0816</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0816.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-06">Mar. 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">SECOND PATROTIC MEETING HELD AT ST. ADALBERT PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second patriotic meeting commemorating the one hundredth anniversary of the third partition of Poland, arranged by the Polish societies of St. Adalbert Parish, was held at Pulaski Hall, Sunday evening, March 3.</p>
   <p>At seven o'clock the Hall was filled to capacity. Casimir Zychlynski, member of the program committee, opened the affair with a terse speech on the third partition of Poland. He also spoke about the significance of these gatherings. C. Belinski was called upon to preside as chairman, J. Slowikowski was appointed recording secretary.</p>
   <p>The combined "Moniuszko" and "Halka" Choirs began the entertainment by singing "Piesn Zgody" (Song of Harmony). C. Bednarz played the piano accompaniment.</p>
   <p>The first speaker of the evening was F. Gryglaszewski. He was followed by <pb facs="5423968_9_0817.jpg" n="2"/>young Miss Euphrosyne Wleklinska, who gave a patriotic declamation; she was accompanied by Carol Bednarz on the piano.</p>
   <p>A short sketch depicting "The Third Partition" was presented on the stage. This brought a vivid picture to the audience about Poland's fall.</p>
   <p>I. Machnikowski delivered an address; he was followed by Joseph Malkiewicz, who gave a recitation.</p>
   <p>A second short sketch, "Smierc Wygnanki" (Death of an Exile), followed.</p>
   <p>Piano duets were rendered by Carol and Miss Josephine Bednarz. Young Miss Gertrude Rewolinska gave a recitation, and J. Chmielinski recited a Polish poem dedicated to the women of the audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0818.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At this point of the program, a sketch of the "Roztrzelanie Padlewskiego w Warszawie" (The Execution of Padlewski in Warsaw) was depicted on the stage.</p>
   <p>A recitation by little Anne Malkiewicz was next on the list, followed by a declamation by Adam Kamprowski. Another song "Jest Kraina" (The Country Remains) was rendered by the combined choirs. Miss Marian Walachowna gave a short recitation.</p>
   <p>The fourth historical sketch "Murawiewa Na Litwie" (Murawiew in Lithuania) was then presented.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the program, the chairman invited the audience to attend the third in this series of programs within the near future.</p>
   <p>Credit must be given to Bernard Markiewicz for the arrangement of the historical <pb facs="5423968_9_0819.jpg" n="4"/>sketches, and to C. Zychlinski for giving an explanation on each historical event portrayed.</p>
   <p>J. Slowikowski, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
