<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-11">Sept. 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Thirteenth Convention of Society of Poles in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1279</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1279.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-11">Sept. 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THIRTEENTH CONVENTION OF SOCIETY OF POLES IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tuesday delegates arrived in Chicago for the special convention of the Society of Poles in America, which has its main headquarters in Milwaukee. This year's convention was supposed to have been held in New Jersey. It was the fault of that city's convention committee that the board of directors of the organization had to demand a change. The convention was preceded by a parade from St. John Cantius Church along Milwaukee Avenue to Chicago Avenue, to Carpenter Street, and back to the Church.</p>
   <p>After the services the delegates went to the parish hall where Mr. Casimir Andrzejewski welcomed the delegates in the name of the convention committee.</p>
   <p>After the opening of the session Bishop Paul Rhode entered the chamber and addressed the delegates. He emphasized the fact that since his consecration he has been present at every convention of this organization. He closed his <pb facs="5423968_9_1280.jpg" n="2"/>speech with an appeal for work for the good of all.</p>
   <p>After the president had appointed a committee to examine the delegates credentials, he adjourned the session until 3 P.M.</p>
   <p>President Grutza opened the afternoon session at 3:10 P.M., when Mr. Francis Danisch, Clerk of the Municipal Court, welcomed the delegates in the name of the Mayor of Chicago. Mr. N. Piotrowski, City Attorney of Chicago, the next speaker, discussed the war.</p>
   <p>The committee on credentials reported that there were 125 delegates, but several did not arrive although copies of their credentials were there. No credentials were questioned.</p>
   <p>Mr. John Janowiak of Chicago, was elected chairman by acclamation after Mr. Wagner of Milwaukee, who was also nominated, had turned down the office.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1281.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Messrs. Leon Kielpinski and Albert Dydus were appointed vice-presidents. Mr. John Posadzy was appointed secretary, Mr. Tytus Bejma assistant secretary.</p>
   <p>President Janowiak, on taking the chair, gave the floor to Mr. Francis Grutza, who moved that the following resolution be accepted:</p>
   <p>Resolution of the Convention</p>
   <p>WHEREAS, The Twelfth Convention of the Society of Poles in America at the City of Kenosha, Wisconsin, chose Jersey City, New Jersey, as the place where the next bi-annual convention was to be held,</p>
   <p>WHEREAS, The convention committee at Jersey City sent a letter to the board of directors dated April 22, in which it categorically demanded the payment of five hundred dollars for expenses, declaring in the same letter, without waiting for a fovarable or an unfavorable reply from the board of <pb facs="5423968_9_1282.jpg" n="4"/>directors, that in the event that their demand was not granted "they wash their hands of the whole matter, having no intentions of carrying on further correspondence, and having no intention of pleading with the board of directors since it is not granting them any favor,"</p>
   <p>WHEREAS, In the face of such an action on the part of the convention committee, one could not expect favorable results from a convention held under the initiative of said committee, and</p>
   <p>WHEREAS, Under existing conditions, it is an absolute necessity that the Thirteenth Convention of the Society of Poles in America should not be held in surroundings unfavorable and even inimical to it:</p>
   <p>Therefore we, the delegates to the special convention of the Society of Poles in America, lawfully convened by the president and certified in accordance with the decrees of our constitution, <pb facs="5423968_9_1283.jpg" n="5"/>Resolve, That the place of the convention of the Society of Poles in America shall be, and is, hereby changed from Jersey City, New Jersey, to the city of Chicago, Illinois, where said convention is to begin September 8, 1914 at 9 A.M. at the parish hall of St. John Cantius!</p>
   <p>This resolution, duly seconded, was passed unanimously. In this way the matter of changing the place of the convention was settled.</p>
   <p>One of the more interesting moments of the convention came during the reports of the state commissioners when Mrs. Dumachowska requested the organization of a Women's Auxiliary.</p>
   <p>Reverend Goral, chaplain of the organization, in a long speech, requested a complete change in the organization to make it strictly denominational. He favored ousting those who were not definitely catholic and also favored increasing the authority of the chaplain, who now has only an advisory vote and is just a puppet officer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1284.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The report of the secretary general was as follows:</p>
   <p>The cash assets of the organization are at present $87,487.97, of which $60,000.00 is in first mortgage bonds, the rest on deposit in the bank. The inventory of the organization is evaluated at $2,227. Therefore the total assets are $89,714.97.</p>
   <p>The organization at the time of the last convention consisted of 134 groups. One of the groups has disbanded since that time and seven new ones have been formed, so that the organization now has 140 groups.</p>
   <p>At the time of the last convention there were 8,538 members. Since that time 1,510 new members have been added and 1,114 members have been dropped, so that the organization now has 8,934 members.</p>
   <p>In the last two years $165,400 has been paid out in life insurance, because during that time 267 members have died.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1285.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>In the last two years the capital of the organization has not been increased: in fact, the treasury has suffered a loss of more than a thousand dollars as a result of expenditures for various law suits. The total capital in 1910 was $70,913.22; at present it is $69,714.97.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
