<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol.17. No.48.
<date when="1923-11-29">November 29, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">-Dedication of a New Church - in West Pullman, Ill</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1742</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
                    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1742.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol.17. No.48.
<date when="1923-11-29">November 29, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">-Dedication of a New Church - in West Pullman, Ill</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The ceremony was performed by the Rt.Rev.Archbishop Mundelein; The sermon was preached by Father Jan Grembowicz of Phoenix, Illinois.</p>
   <p>In West Pullman, Illinois at the parish of Ascension of Blessed Mary, where Father Teodor Langford is the pastor there was on the 25th day of November 1923, a great celebration. A new temple of God, has been dedicated in which the clergy and all parishioners participated.</p>
   <p>At the appointed time, that is 10:30 A.M., the members of many societies and school children, dressed for the occasion, formed lines and marched through Parnell St. toward the parish house located at 123rd St., for the purpose of meeting the eminent guest Rt.Rev.Archbishop George Mundelein.</p>
   <p>During the march Mr.John Ronger's orchestra played beautifully. The procession was headed by the ministrants, then the school children, led by Sisters of Nazareth who are also local teachers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1743.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Dedication.</p>
   <p>Surrounded by the clergy and parishioners, while the church choir sang, the new church was dedicated by the Archbishop. The prayers prescribed by the ritual were also said.</p>
   <p>- The High Mass in New Church -</p>
   <p>The Archbishop then entered the church where Father Franciszek Ostrowski, pastor of St.Josefat's Parish celebrated a high mass, assisted by Father Edward Kowalewski, pastor of St.Mary Magdalene of South Chicago and Father Stanislaus Derwinski. The new temple was filled to its capacity with the faithful. The illumination was wonderful. The decoration of the interior was so beautiful that it really should be called the work of art. The Sisters decorated the church.</p>
   <p>The local choir sang during the high mass and Father John Grembowicz preached a wonderful sermon.</p>
   <p>During the High Mass the Archbishop was assisted by Father B.Czajkowski paster of Blessed Mother of Czestochowa church of Hawthorn, Ill. and Father Francis Karabasz <pb facs="5423968_9_1744.jpg" n="3"/>pastor of Sacred Heart Church of Chicago. Father Joseph Lechert was a master of ceremonies.</p>
   <p>There were many other priests besides the ones mentioned above. The ceremony was completed by Archbishop's blessing.</p>
   <p>The procession returned to the parish house in the same order.</p>
   <p>Later on the Archbishop visited the parish school and viewed the new church.</p>
   <p>So ended the beautiful celebration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
