<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-02-17">Feb. 17, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Poles Honor Thaddeus Kosciusk</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-02-17">Feb. 17, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">POLES HONOR THADDEUS KOSCIUSK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois,</p>
   <p>Feb. 15, 1897,</p>
   <p>Dear Editor:</p>
   <p>Please be kind enough to publish the following article in the Dziennik Chicagoski:</p>
   <p>On February 14 the Thaddeus Kosciusko Society staged a program in commemoration of the one hundred and fifty-first anniversary of the birth of Kosciusko, immortal Polish hero of two worlds, at the Holy Trinity Parish <pb facs="5423968_9_0627.jpg" n="2"/>school hall. When the exercise was opened at 4 P. M. the auditorium was packed.</p>
   <p>D. Ekowski opened the program and called upon W. Wleklinski, treasurer of the Polish National Alliance, to preside as chairman. Mr. Wleklinski took the stand and explained the purpose and meaning of this gathering. He concluded by praising the Kosciusko Society for its fidelity to the great Polish hero.</p>
   <p>The Chopin Choir, under the direction of Anthony Mallek, sang "Patz Kosciusko Na Nas Z Nieba" (Look Upon Us From Heaven, Kosciusko).</p>
   <p>The initial speaker of the evening was the Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, pastor of Holy Trinity Parish, who spoke about the deeds of Thaddeus Kosciusko.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0628.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The pastor concluded his talk by urging the assemblage to follow the example of this immortal Polish hero. Applause greeted the priest as he left the stand.</p>
   <p>"Pocieszenie" (Consolation) was sung by the Wanda Choir, much to the enjoyment of the crowd. A. Mallek also directed this group.</p>
   <p>Mary Majewska recited "Na Dzien Urodzin T. Kosciusko" (On the Day of Kosciusko's Birth). This was followed by a number of songs by the young ladies' group of the Youth's Friend Society of Holy Trinity Parish. Then Andrew Marcinkiewicz recited "Barefoot Boys" in English.</p>
   <p>Another group of young ladies from the Youth's Friend Society sang "A Czy Znasz Ty Bracie Mlody" (And Do You Know, Dear Brother). A group of young <pb facs="5423968_9_0629.jpg" n="4"/>men from this society sang "Dalej Bracia" (Onward Brothers), and they were followed by Miss Catherine Ekowska who recited "Kosciusko".</p>
   <p>John F. Smulski was the second speaker of the evening. This distinguished Polish representative gave the highlights of Kosciusko's accomplishments in America during the Revolutionary War and his activities after his return to Poland. The speech was colorful and interesting.</p>
   <p>The combined Wanda and Chopin Choirs sang a medley of Polish national airs. Because of their beautiful singing the choirs were forced to repeat several numbers.</p>
   <p>A verse, "Jeszcze Nie Zginela" (Not Yet Lost), was delivered by John Maciejewski, and Miss Pearl Wleklinska declaimed "Bitwa Raclawica" (Battle at <pb facs="5423968_9_0630.jpg" n="5"/>Raclawica).</p>
   <p>A collection was made which netted $13.89.</p>
   <p>This was followed by Leona Nowak's recital of "Jeszcze Polska Nie Zginela" (Poland Is Not Yet Lost).</p>
   <p>Mr. Lisztewnik, president of the Kosciusko Society, thanked the audience and all participants in the program for making this event a success.</p>
   <p>The chairman, Mr. Wleklinski, extended his thanks to the audience also, and the exercise was concluded with the Polish national hymn, "God Save Poland".</p>
   <p>Joseph Rosinski, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
