<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-02-21">Feb. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[Organizacya Patryotyczna Adopts New Tactics]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-02-21">Feb. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[ORGANIZACYA PATRYOTYCZNA ADOPTS NEW TACTICS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Organizacya Patryotyczna (Patriotic Organization) held a meeting recently. It is not our purpose to give here the financial reports from national exercises and dramatic presentations. Rather than that, we will discuss a plan of action which the Organization has just adopted. It was decided that at regular intervals meetings will be open not only to members but to members' families as well. Such meetings will be diversified with lectures, declamations, music, etc., and without a doubt will prove of great advantage to all who attend.</p>
   <p>A committee of five, subject to the president, was chosen to prepare for each meeting a program that would warm the hearts of all our people and awaken them to patriotism and to action.</p>
   <p>The Organization is developing successfully, and the results of its <pb facs="5423968_9_0237.jpg" n="2"/>work become more and more evident. This proves the fallacy of rumors that only business interests and payment of death benefits hold the Organization together.</p>
   <p>Every member of the Organization not only has relinquished all thoughts of personal gain but instead contributes ten cents per month for nationalistic purposes. But every member may well be proud that he belongs to and works for such an institution, for no matter where one turns, the Organization is in evidence.</p>
   <p>At patriotic exercises--who are the speakers? Organization members. A choir sings--who are the singers? Organization members. There is a theatrical performance--who are the actors? Organization members. A parade is in progress--who are the uniformed marchers? Organization members. And the Falcons, the Church Choir, who are they but Organization members? What is the inference to be drawn from all this? Namely, that whoever in our parish desires to work for the good of Poland belongs <pb facs="5423968_9_0238.jpg" n="3"/>to the Patriotic Organization. Its members include all the priests, teachers, editors, the most influential citizens, and the most active representatives of the youth. It lacks only those who begrudge a contribution of ten cents a month for patriotic purposes. In truth, they say, "Oh, but what of that? I've already given enough. Why, I would give five dollars or even ten dollars." Usually their I-would-give is merely a boast, and our honorable would-be contributors won't give even ten cents because they happen not to be members of the Organization. Fundamentally it is not the question of the ten cents--the idea is that we must work and set an example for the Polish youth. Those duty is this? The parents'.</p>
   <p>But it is not our intention to offend anyone, and we must admit that new patriots have been flocking to us. In a short time an almanac will be issued, listing the names of the members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
