<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 67,
<date when="1922-03-21">March 21, 1922</date><title level="a">American Legion News - Pulaski Post No. 86</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1750</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1750.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 67,
<date when="1922-03-21">March 21, 1922</date><title level="a">AMERICAN LEGION NEWS - PULASKI POST NO. 86</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From time to time in the American press there appear malicious attacks on the American Legion. An attack particularly has been made on the national commander of the Legion, because he expressed himself in a very complimentary manner about the activities of the Roman-Catholic priests during the war.</p>
   <p>Not for personal satisfaction is he justifying himself, but to acquaint United States citizens as to how the American Legion stands relative to the Catholic religion. Mr. Hanford Macnider has been compelled to answer the editor of the American periodical The Protestant, in which paper there appeared an article, "Rome at the Head of the American Legion".</p>
   <p>Giving the Polish people and opportunity to find out how Mr. H. Macnider answered the accusations that were made, the Pulaski Post No. 86, American Legion, is rendering a literal translation of the letter sent out to the editor of the periodical The Protestant:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1751.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Editor of The Protestant,</p>
   <p>Washington, D. C.</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>Your article, sir, entitled "Rome at the Head of the American Legion", has come to my attention. When you came to me with a plea for forgiveness I judged that you did not understand my stand on religion and that your declaration was directed at me personally. I told you that it did not depend much on your opinion about me, but your article was an attack upon the American Legion and as such it demands an answer. The American Legion is an organization of former soldiers and women who served the country during the war, and are now endeavoring to continue to serve as active citizens, in peace as well as war. The question of religion has no place in the Legion, as well as in American life - and therefore cannot be mixed into the activities of the Legion.</p>
   <p>For the Roman Catholic Church I have the highest respect. The position and activities of that church in the aim of preserving honesty in our government <pb facs="5423968_9_1752.jpg" n="3"/>has been recorded by the heroic deaths of the soldiers, serving under my command. And may I take the liberty to add, that the priests of that denomination in the service, have demonstrated human heartful emotions, for which they were beloved by all, - Jews, Protestants and Catholics alike.</p>
   <p>The propaganda which you are spreading is endangering America, as well as the American laws. The constitution of the United States gives liberty to every citizen, to profess any religion, and the American Legion was formed only for the defense of that constitution.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Hanford Macnider.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
