<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-16">Apr. 16, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to the Poles of America on Behalf of the Polish Mass Meeting and the Polish League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-16">Apr. 16, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO THE POLES OF AMERICA ON BEHALF OF THE POLISH MASS MEETING AND THE POLISH LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first appeal, issued a few months ago, on behalf of the proposed Polish mass meeting to organize a Polish league, awakened a great deal of interest among the American Poles.</p>
   <p>Many opinions and judgments have been voiced, most of them in favor of holding the mass meeting and organizing the league. The time has come when all Poles living in America should unite and work harmoniously, perseveringly, and effectively for the good of the motherland and for their own moral improvement.</p>
   <p>The year of Kosciusko [one-hundredth anniversary of Kosciusko's insurrection] should be distinguished by a great deed; it should be recorded with golden letters in the history of American Polonia. It seems as if the commander in peasant smock, the immortal leader Thaddeus Kosciusko, has <pb facs="5423968_9_0128.jpg" n="2"/>arisen from his grave to kindle our hearts and inspire us with his spirit.</p>
   <p>Patriotic Poles, putting aside all personal differences, are responding to the appeal that there should be unity among them, that they should work for the motherland and for the creation of a Polish league.</p>
   <p>Much as in our early history, when the Polish nation gathered at mass meetings called "Wiec" for the purpose of placing Piast, a farmer, on the throne, the memory of Kosciusko, who was tenderhearted, simple, and sincere like Piast, and who wore peasants' attire like Piast, now calls us together, reconciles us, unites us, and encourages us to action.</p>
   <p>The Polish people of America are prepared for a deed of such magnitude as a Polish league; they know that in union there is strength; they remember that the duty of the Poles is to work for the future generations, for the motherland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0129.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Most of our newspapers, societies, and patriotic clergymen are in favor of holding a mass meeting in order to organize a Polish league. Honor to them for their patriotic work! May God allow us to finish the started work!</p>
   <p>Patriots are not discouraged because there is opposition here and there or because there are obstacles which the league must face and overcome. We all know that obstacles have been found even in connection with our small under-takings and that these obstacles have always been brushed aside. That being the case, what else is required in order to go ahead with such important undertaking as the Polish league, the purpose of which is to unite and organize all Poles for co-operative work? We are not discouraged by obstacles and difficulties; we are prepared for them.</p>
   <p>Faith, good will, hard work, and perseverance will conquer everything. The greater the difficulties, the more irksome the tasks, the greater will be <pb facs="5423968_9_0130.jpg" n="4"/>The prospects for calling up a Polish mass meeting and for organizing a Polish league are very good, for so far no Pole has raised any basic objection against the idea. We are of the opinion that even those who are not wholeheartedly in favor of organizing a Polish league will support the good cause and help establish a Polish league worthy of Kosciusko's memory; that they will unite the nation, for which God will bless them, and their descendants will mention their names with gratitude and veneration.</p>
   <p>The committee in charge of arrangements for the mass meeting was advised by many societies, clergymen, and interested persons that May 1 is not a suitable day for holding a mass meeting, as it would interfere with the Kosciusko and May Day manifestations, not to mention that many priests would not be able to participate in the mass meeting, since May 1 is Ascension Day.</p>
   <p>At the meeting held on April 13, the committee, after considering all <pb facs="5423968_9_0131.jpg" n="5"/>reasonable objections, postponed the Polish mass meeting until the following Sunday, May 8, at 2 P. M. All delegates as well as other persons interested in the mass meeting will be notified of this change.</p>
   <p>Along with this notice, the committee will enclose credential blanks for the delegates, as well as copies of an outline of the constitution suggested for the proposed Polish league, which will be debated by the delegates at the mass meeting.</p>
   <p>Dear countrymen! It is a poor farmer who neglects even one spike of grain; it is a poor soldier who shuns a battlefield; it is a poor patriot who does not participate in national affairs.</p>
   <p>Indifference in such matters means sinning against the nation. Dark clouds hover over us and our unfortunate motherland. We must not be idle or asleep. Let us act, then, as the poet says: "Let everyone do as much as he can for <pb facs="5423968_9_0132.jpg" n="6"/>public good. The rest will take care of itself."</p>
   <p>Z. Schmidt, president</p>
   <p>I. Kowalski, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
