<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. II, No. 23,
<date when="1928-06-03">June 3, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Power of the Polish National Catholic Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. II, No. 23,
<date when="1928-06-03">June 3, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE POWER OF THE POLISH NATIONAL CATHOLIC CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish National Catholic church in America represents a power, consisting of four large dioceses, about 150 parishes and over 200,000 parishioners.</p>
   <p>Besides that, our Polish National Church has a great moral power, in the face of which princes of the Roman-Catholic Church, such as Cardinal Mundelein, etc., become jittery and show every sign of capitulation.</p>
   <p>Not so very long ago there appeared an official statement in the Chicago clerical newspapers saying that no more Polish Roman-Catholic parishes may be established within the limits of the Chicago diocese.</p>
   <p>Due to that injunction a large group of Poles joined the Polish National Church and organized a new parish in the neighborhood known as Nowa Polska. Because the new parish was thriving, his cardinal highness withdrew his injunction and in his kind generosity permitted a new Polish Roman-Catholic parish to be set up in that neighborhood.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1679.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are very doubtful whether the Polish community in that section of Chicago will ever forget the humiliating facts which accompanied its efforts to establish a Roman-Catholic parish.</p>
   <p>At any rate, even a foe of the Polish National Church will have to admit that the mission of our church is very great not only among the Polish population, but also among the meek servants of the Roman-Catholic faith.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
