<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>,
<date when="1928-04-22">Apr. 22, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">[No Money for Rome]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1681</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1681.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>,
<date when="1928-04-22">Apr. 22, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">[NO MONEY FOR ROME]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The leaders of the clerical Polish Welfare Association appeal to the Polish population here to enlist in the association and to cover very important expenditures.</p>
   <p>We are quite aware of what these expenditures mean. Some of the Polish priests are very much interested in a Polish bishophood. They would like to have a Polish bishop who, through his authority, would be able to improve the conditions of the Polish clergy. But at the same time they realize that for that purpose they must have money. Plenty of money. The more money they send to Rome, the more certain the appointment of a Polish bishop.</p>
   <p>Why, the Rev. Syski of Boston wrote recently that if Poles sent a carload of gold to Rome, they would positively obtain a bishophood.</p>
   <p>So, come on, brethren! Let's collect the money and pretty soon we shall have a Polish bishop.</p>
   <p>Thus the Polish clergy collects. But their foes don't neglect the <pb facs="5423968_9_1682.jpg" n="2"/>situation either. On his recent visit to Rome, Cardinal Mundelein presented the Vatican with $1,500,000, and probably will send $3,500,000 more in the near future.</p>
   <p>Of course, that money was sufficient to secure a bishophood for Mundelein's German accomplice. All those millions will be paid by the poor Polish people. The papal priests know how to go about squeezing that money out of the Polish parishioners.</p>
   <p>Shall the exploited Polish community donate new millions to the hypocritical Vatican in order to eclipse Mundelein's recent present, and through it win more favorable attention from Rome?</p>
   <p>No! You Polish clerg y, keep away from it! Don't abuse and exploit the poor Polish people any more! Don't toy with their patience!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
