<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-07">Sept. 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Falcons Hold Mass Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-07">Sept. 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH FALCONS HOLD MASS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Falcons held a mass meeting at Pulaski Hall yesterday evening. The meeting was called to order by Casimir Zychlinski, president of Polish Sokol I and ardent supporter of the Falcon movement. Dr. Dunikowski was named chairman and L. Nowak secretary. In the initial address of the evening, Dr. Dunikowski spoke of the importance of the Falcon movement, pointing to the physical, educational, and even spiritual benefits derived from it. He said that gymnastic societies are common in Europe. Gymnastic exercises are considered to have curative powers and take the place of medicine. From an educational standpoint, gymnastics teach discipline, which Polish-American society lacks. Gymnastic drill promotes physical development and, at the same time, provides recreation for the youth, bringing individuals of all kinds together in brotherly companionship. The speaker then outlined methods by which the Polish Falcon movement can be spread throughout America. He advised: 1) formation of a committee to take full charge; 2) enlisting the aid of <pb facs="5423968_9_0210.jpg" n="2"/>reliable people outside of Chicago who are willing to co-operate; 3) that the general headquarters of the Polish Falcons' Alliance, which should be created as soon as possible, be located in Chicago; 4) establishment of a Falcon newspaper.</p>
   <p>Dr. Dunikowski's address was vigorously applauded. S. Zahajkiewicz was the next speaker. He enlarged upon some of the thoughts expressed by the first speaker, urging the youth to join Falcon societies. He said that there will be no partisanship in the Falcon organization, that the organization will be open to all Polish young men without exception. Since everyone should participate in so important a matter as this, it is primarily necessary that our estimable and patriotic Polish clergymen be invited to lend their aid (great applause).</p>
   <p>In accordance with the thoughts expressed in this and in Dr. Dunikowski's speech, it was decided to form a committee for the propagation of the movement among the Poles in America. The Reverends Vincent Barzynski, J. Radziejewski, <pb facs="5423968_9_0211.jpg" n="3"/>and A. Nowicki have been invited to join this committee. Dr. Dunikowski was included in the committee as an honorary member. Besides those mentioned above, the committee consists of the following: K. Zychlinski, L. Mieczynski, and A. Dziadul, of Polish Sokol I; M. Baranski, J. Adamowski, and Leon Nowak, of Polish Sokol II. The St. Stanislaus Kostka Sokol will appoint three members to the committee from its numbers at tomorrow's meeting [St. Stanislaus Kostka Sokol meeting].</p>
   <p>There were other speakers besides those mentioned above; all of them spoke of the importance of the Falcon movement and outlined methods for its propagation.</p>
   <p>Dr. Statkiewicz of La Salle [Illinois], who declared that he will do his part by organizing a "Falcon nest" in his own city, was very warmly applauded. He made two motions: 1) that the Chicago Falcons, to the extent of their means, make excursions to cities and towns in the vicinity of Chicago, and, 2) that the Chicago Falcons be the nucleus of the Polish Falcons' Alliance of America, assigning organizers to take charge of forming "Falcon nests" in other cities. Both motions were carried.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
