<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-01">Aug. 1, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Second Corps of Polish Armies of America Holds Additional Session of First Congress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1409</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1409.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-01">Aug. 1, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">SECOND CORPS OF POLISH ARMIES OF AMERICA HOLDS ADDITIONAL SESSION OF FIRST CONGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, July 28, an additional session of the first Congress was held by the Second Corps of Polish Armies of America at Pulaski Hall. This special meeting was opened by the president of the organization S. Behnke. Practically all delegates were present.</p>
   <p>The minutes from the previous meeting were read and accepted. After completing some minor business, a motion was made by I. Przymorski to consider the cause of the Polish Fund of Rapperswyl. [Translator's note: This was a fund to help the Polish cause. It was established by the combined efforts of Polish national societies in America. A museum and fund was started in the free city of Rapperswyl, Switzerland. Date established I have not found as yet.] Delegate [?] Gorecki supported this motion and suggested that the Corps join the Fund. This motion was carried and a warm debate followed. The following took active part in the <pb facs="5423968_9_1410.jpg" n="2"/>discussion: delegates Przymorski, Gorecki, Behnke, Kaminski and Francis Danisch. In conclusion Francis Danisch made a motion that a vote be taken on Mr. Gorecki's suggestion. The motion was defeated.</p>
   <p>Erasmus Jerzmanowski, of New York, F. Gryglaszewski, Peter Kiolbassa and Theodore M. Helinski were unanimously elected honorary members of the Second Corps of Polish Armies of America.</p>
   <p>A motion made by Delegate Przymorski, was made and passed to require all societies in any particular vicinity to take part in a combined drill once each month, was carried. In the event that there is no brigadier in the group, the chief will appoint a commander.</p>
   <p>Another motion was passed to permit the officers of the Second Corps to attend meetings of the various groups of the organization. This motion was made by Mr. Gorecki and seconded by Mr. Danisch.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1411.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Schmidt made a motion to make Adjutant Przymorski a colonel in appreciation of his zealous work. A motion was also made and passed to have an official statement of the first convention published and sent to all members. Delegate Malinowski also suggested that drills be made up.</p>
   <p>After a long debate it was decided to appoint a staff to work out a system of drills and to have them ready this coming fall. A motion was also passed to work out a system of Polish Army signals for the Second Corps and also to establish a system of teaching these signals.</p>
   <p>The session closed with the Lord's Prayer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
