<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-04">Dec. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Patriotic Exercises Held in St. Casimir's Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-04">Dec. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTIC EXERCISES HELD IN ST. CASIMIR'S PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Through the efforts of the National Exercises Committee of St. Casimir's [Parish], the November Exercises [commemorating the November Insurrection, 1830] were held yesterday afternoon at Troy Hall. The hall was filled to capacity. The program was scheduled to begin at two o'clock, but, as is usual with us, it was almost three o'clock before the program really opened. It would seem that "punctuality" can be found only in the dictionary.</p>
   <p>The exercises were opened by Joseph Lewandowski, who, after a short address, called upon Alexander Jasinski to preside and named Francis Brodnicki secretary.</p>
   <p>The program was executed in the following order: (1) Choral number by the Korpinski Choir, directed by P. P. Herek; (2) Recitation by Miss Catherine Fundakowski and Joseph Tomasz; (3) Address by the Reverend John Zielezinski; <pb facs="5423968_9_0517.jpg" n="2"/>(4) Violin solo by Miss W. Simbor; (5) Recitation by Miss Agnes Gorski; (6) Vocal solo by E. Schleichert; (7) Orchestral number under the direction of Stanislaus Siembicki; (8) Recitation by B. Drzewicki. Following this number, a collection, which netted $32.48, was taken up. The money was sent to the Polish Central Relief Committee. The program was resumed in the following order: (9) Orchestral number directed by S. Siembicki; (10) Recitation by Miss Julia Danisch; (11) Vocal solo by Miss Agnes Gorski, piano accompaniment by her brother, Ignatius; (12) Choral number by the Korpinski Choir, under the direction of P. P. Herek. The program was concluded with "Boze cos Polske" [God Save Poland], sung by the audience.</p>
   <p>The Korpinski Choir, well known for its splendid performances not only in St. Casimir's [Parish] but in other parts of Chicago, sang excellently, for which credit is due to its director, P. P. Herek. The recitations by little Miss Catherine Fundakowski and little Joseph Tomasz were delivered clearly and <pb facs="5423968_9_0518.jpg" n="3"/>fluently and were warmly received by the audience.</p>
   <p>The Reverend John Zielezinski, an ardent worker among the youth and in the field of education, well liked by the people of St. Casimir's,delivered a short but very effective address.</p>
   <p>Enthusiastic applause forced Miss W. Simbor to appear a second time. Miss Simbor, accompanied on the piano by her sister, Miss L. Simbor, played F. Orla's "Vision," and as an encore, "Deuxieme," a mazurka. Miss Simbor is an excellent violinist. Her interpretation of these fairly difficult numbers was perfect and augurs well for her success in the future.</p>
   <p>Miss Agnes Gorski, vocal soloist, was also recalled for an encore. In her sweet voice, she sang "Come Back to Me, Come Back".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
