<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-19">Feb. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Commemoration in Bridgeport of the January Insurrection</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-19">Feb. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">COMMEMORATION IN BRIDGEPORT OF THE JANUARY INSURRECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Commune 80 of the Polish National Alliance and the Adam Mickiewicz Education and Library Society arranged exercises on Sunday, February 4, 1917, at the Adam Mickiewicz hall, 3308-10 South Morgan Street, commemorating the January Insurrection.</p>
   <p>Mr. S. Gniatczynski, president of the commune, opened the meeting promptly at 3 P. M., calling upon Mr. Pawlak to act as chairman and the undersigned as secretary. The chairman invited the presidents of local groups of the Alliance and veterans of the insurrection of 1863 to come up on the stage, after which the program was begun in the following order.</p>
   <p>1) The orchestra of the Society of King Jan Sobieski's Polish Sharpshooters, under the direction of Mr. A. Jakubowski, played Polish compositions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0476.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>2) Speech by Mr. S. Orpiszewski, editor of the Alliance publications. The speaker, in a short and terse address, honored the memory of the heroes who shed their blood for their native land. He discussed the gravity of the present situation, calling upon the Poles to help the starving people in Poland, and expressed strong faith in the resurrection of our homeland. Mr. Orpiszewski's speech was frequently interrupted by enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>3) The Helena Modjeska Singing and Dramatic Society, under the direction of professor J. J. Jokajtis, sang a medley of Polish melodies.</p>
   <p>4) Recitation "Bracia Rocznica" (Brothers Anniversary), by Miss Irene Grzebielski.</p>
   <p>5) Anthem of the United States of America, piano solo played by Miss W. Ostrowski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0477.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>6) The orchestra played a medley of Polish songs while a collection was being taken up for Polish relief by Miss F. Okon, Mrs. Mach, and Misses Sawacki and Marczewski. The collection yielded $19.25.</p>
   <p>7) Song, "Hej Lec Ptaku," by the local choir of Raftsmen under the direction of Mr. L. A. Cieszykowski, organist of St. Barbara's Parish.</p>
   <p>8) Recitation, "Krakowiak." Very well done by little Eugene Grzebielski.</p>
   <p>9) A second speech by Mr. S. Orpiszewski, who urged the people to join the Polish National Alliance, which protects future generations from losing their national identity and fosters the national spirit. "This Alliance," he said, "has helped one hundred and twenty medical and law students, who are now useful members of our community. The Polish National Alliance has established two hundred and fifty libraries from which the Polish people can gain enlightenment <pb facs="5423968_9_0478.jpg" n="4"/>and strengthen their national spirit."</p>
   <p>10) Song "Nabozenstwo Narodowe" (National Hymn), by Miss. L. Bartos, accompanied by Mr. L. A. Cieszykowski.</p>
   <p>11) Recitation by Dr. Marczewski.</p>
   <p>12) The chairman thanked the audience for attending in such large numbers despite the blizzard and cold. He also thanked not only the Society of King Jan Sobieski's Sharpshooters for supplying its excellent orchestra gratis but also the speakers and all those who contributed their efforts to make the celebration a success.</p>
   <p>13) Everybody joined in the singing of "Boze cos Polske" (God Save Poland), with the orchestra accompanying. All the numbers were excellently performed, <pb facs="5423968_9_0479.jpg" n="5"/>as was evidenced by the applause.</p>
   <p>A. B. Chrzanowski,</p>
   <p>secretary of the meeting</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
