<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-03">May 3, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">May Exercises Staged at St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0621</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0621.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-03">May 3, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">MAY EXERCISES STAGED AT ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite the inclement weather, the Polish Hall, Bradley and Noble Streets, was filled to capacity last night when Mr. Gniot opened the May exercises in the name of the combined societies of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish. The crowd was estimated at over twenty-five hundred. This was sufficient evidence that the Polish societies not only work hard to put over their programs, but continue to do so with success.</p>
   <p>J. Tomaszewski presided as chairman, and August Klafta acted as recording secretary.</p>
   <p>At the request of the chairman, the Reverend Vincent Barzynski said a prayer at the opening of the program.</p>
   <p>All the speeches, declamations, and songs won the undivided attention of the audience, and the performers were applauded with great enthusiasm.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0622.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There were three speakers. B. Klarkowski delivered a lecture on the accomplishments of Poland from the early ages, in order to show what conditions led to the framing of the Constitution of the Third of May [1791]. Later in his discourse, the speaker gave the high lights of the Polish constitution. After pointing out its good qualities, Mr. Klarkowski explained why it could not save Poland, and then further expressed his views on the Polish partition.</p>
   <p>The second speaker was N. L. Piotrowski. He compared the Polish constitution with the Constitution of the United States. His address was made more interesting by the fact that Mr. Klarkowski wove great patriotic feeling into it. Applause greeted the speaker as he left the rostrum.</p>
   <p>Reverend V. Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, was of the opinion that patriotic demonstrations do not amount to much if an extensive effort is not made in that direction. The pastor pointed out the necessity for organization, and for the exertion of effort toward organizing units for <pb facs="5423968_9_0623.jpg" n="3"/>patriotic work. He made reference to the joy the enemies of the Poles express at the discord and disunity within the Polish ranks. Reverend Barzynski concluded by urging everyone to work toward evolving a systematic field of endeavor, in order to achieve true patriotic and nationalistic aims.</p>
   <p>These speeches were interspersed with songs, declamations, and piano solos. The St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish Women's choir sang "Wiazanka Majowa" (May Garland), the St. Cecilia Men's Choir sang "Wisla" (Vistula), and the parish mixed choir sang "Trzeci Maj" (Third of May). A local quartet sang "O Piekno Polska" (O Beautiful Poland). All the singing groups were under the skilled direction of Andrew Kwasigrocn.</p>
   <p>Declamations were rendered by Miss Sophia Knapinska and Miss Hedwig Moczynska with great feeling. The recital of the poetry was so touching that it moved many in the audience to tears.</p>
   <p>Piano solos were given by Mr. Kwasigroch and Stephen Schultz. Both gave <pb facs="5423968_9_0624.jpg" n="4"/>expert renditions of Polish patriotic numbers.</p>
   <p>The program was concluded with "God Save Poland".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
