<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-05-04">May 4, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Third of May Exercises for the School Children of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1009</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1009.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-05-04">May 4, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THIRD OF MAY EXERCISES FOR THE SCHOOL CHILDREN OF ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>National exercises were held yesterday afternoon at the school hall near Bradley Street in commemoration of the one hundred and second anniversary of the [Polish] Constitution of the Third of May. It is the first time such exercises have been held especially for the school children of St. Stanislaus Kostka parish. More than three thousand children attended, accompanied by priests, teachers, and nuns. The platform was occupied by the school committee, composed of Reverend Vincent Barzynski, W. Jedrzejek, P. Ratkowski, F. Wleklinski, A. W. Rudnicki, T. Krolik, and others.</p>
   <p>In opening the exercises, Father Barzynski explained their purpose in a short speech. Following a choral number by the Girls' Choir, Mr. Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, principal of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parochial School, delivered a lengthy but easily understandable address. He explained the significance of the Constitution of the Third of May and urged the children to be worthy of Poland, their mother country. His address was followed by choral numbers, among them several Polish <pb facs="5423968_9_1010.jpg" n="2"/>national hymns.</p>
   <p>Mr. Czajor, one of the teachers, declared in the next speech that Poland can never be destroyed, and that Polish children should always remember this.</p>
   <p>After the Girls' Choir had sung a beautiful prayer, Father Barzynski arose to speak. He spoke of the Constitution and emphasized the importance of preserving faith, virtue, and love for Poland. His words were carefully chosen so that they could be understood by, and would appeal to the children. The singing of "Boze Cos Polske" [O Lord, For Poland] by the entire assembly concluded the program.</p>
   <p>Generally speaking, the assembly was characterized by considerable enthusiasm. The children listened to the national hymns and to the patriotic speeches with close attention. It is likely that many things became clear to more than one small head, that a fire was kindled in more than one small heart.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1011.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In conclusion, Father Barzynski promised that, in the future, exercises would be held especially for children in commemoration of all national anniversaries. The children applauded this news vigorously.</p>
   <p>In truth, such exercises may prove of great benefit to our children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
