<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 15,
<date when="1894-04-11">April 11, 1894</date><title level="a">Projecting a Program of Joint Kosciuszko Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0924</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0924.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 15,
<date when="1894-04-11">April 11, 1894</date><title level="a">PROJECTING A PROGRAM OF JOINT KOSCIUSZKO CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The program of the joint Kosciuszko celebration in Chicago is already arranged. March the 30th the committee met in the editorial office of the Zgoda in an endeavor to discuss the particulars of this celebration. In charge of this discussion was the Rev. Father Sedlaczek and the secretary was Mr. K. Sawicki.</p>
   <p>After a heated discussion in which Rev. Father Sedlaczek had finally won his point, the following form of program was passed.</p>
   <p>To advertise the third of May as the day of our memorial anniversary of our constitution, and of our hero Tadeusz Kosciuszko; combine there two this year as one and to keep it as such forever; to have all the Polish people celebrate this day with the utmost sincerity.</p>
   <p>This day is to be begun with a mass at all Polish Catholic churches in Chicago, at 8 o'clock in the morning.</p>
   <p>At 10 o'clock the societies will march to meet all the Polish people of prominence arriving in this city. At 12 to 2 o'clock parade of the United States Militia and the Polish army on the Lake front before all the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0925.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then speeches will be given by our country's prominent political and business leaders, after which the people will be invited to go to the Hall of Battery "D."</p>
   <p>At 2 o'clock the celebration will take place at this hall. Music will be furnished by an orchestra consisting of twenty-five men from Thomas's band.</p>
   <p>The Polish welcome speech will be given by Mr. Schmidt, after which Mr. Bielinski, vice-president of the Polish-American citizens club, will speak in English. The committee was instructed to invite our state governor Mr. Altgeld; Senator Palmer; Mayor Hopkins and Messrs. Jeyzmanowski, Finnerty, Kennan, Enander, and Stevens. The following are also to be invited as guests: Censor of Z.N. P., Mr. Helinski, Honorary president of the Polish Catholic Union; Mr. P. Kolbassa; Rev. Father Sedlaczek will speak in Polish about the good derived from this great celebration. Miss Helen Modvzejewska will recite a declamation.</p>
   <p>Besides this the most important facts in the life of Theodore Kosciuszko will be given as a drama in three acts: - (1) National oath on the earthen urn of Crakow, (2) Fight at Raclawice, (3) Fight at Saratoga in America.</p>
   <p>To this program will be added three musical orchestral numbers and three numbers by the choirs of Z. N.P. and St. Stanislaus. The raising of the Polish <pb facs="5423968_9_0926.jpg" n="3"/>flag and singing the oath of Kosciuszko, Boze Cos' Polske (God who defends Poland).</p>
   <p>The committee is instructed to have 10,000 buttons made for this celebration at the cost of three cents each, these are to be ready a week before the celebration; have 5,000 distributed among the people to sell at 10 cents each, the remaining 5,000 to be put away for the officials and guests; send some to the different Polish societies and groups to be sold at 15 cents each, this money to be used to pay the expense of this celebration. We are informed that this program was unanimously accepted by the committee. It is a very good program, so we Poles should be proud of this work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
