<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-21">Sept. 21, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of the Polish Women's Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-21">Sept. 21, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF THE POLISH WOMEN'S ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention was opened by Mrs. Tomaszewski chairman of the convention. Then the business of questioning credentials began. After a lengthy debate the credentials of the delegates of Group 106 and Group 99 were accepted without a dissenting vote. The secretary of the convention, Mrs. Weyna then read the official minutes of the last convention, held at Cleveland, Ohio. A motion was passed to adjourn the session after reading the numerous telegrams.</p>
   <p>Telegrams were sent by the following persons and organizations: Mr. John Smulski; Mr. W. Dyniewicz, well-known publisher; Mr. John Zaremba; the Polish Bank of Chicago [Northwestern Trust and Savings Bank]; the Falcons of South Bend; the Sigismund Balicki Society; Mr. Kolski, of South Bend, Indiana; the Second Circuit of the Polish Falcons' Alliance; and Messrs. Jerozal and Kosturski. Also, a letter was received from Mrs. Josephine Filipowski.</p>
   <p>After the telegrams had been read, the morning session was adjourned.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1307.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The afternoon session was opened at 2:45 P.M. Mr. Tomkiewicz, the commissioner of the Polish National Alliance for the state of Wisconsin, extended an invitation to all the delegates, in behalf of the directorate of the Polish Theatre Guild at Milwaukee, to witness a performance in one of the leading theaters of the city as his guests. The invitation was accepted and those present expressed their assent by a rising vote.</p>
   <p>After this, Mrs. Olszewska-Krysiak read the minutes of the first session. The minutes were accepted as read. The minutes of the morning session read by Mrs. Weyna, were accepted with certain amendments.</p>
   <p>A question then came up whether the names of those making motions should be inscribed in the minutes. It was decided that only the house should present motions.</p>
   <p>The following members were then presented for the numerous committees: Revision Committee, Mmes. Bochaczewska, Krysiak, Labucka, Wargin, Brotkowska, Klarkowskia, <pb facs="5423968_9_1308.jpg" n="3"/>and Wawrzon.</p>
   <p>Appeals Committee, Mmes. Mussor, Slupikowska, and Milaszewska.</p>
   <p>Constitution Committee; Mmes. Andrzejewska, Neuman, Idzikowska, Polcyn, Gorniak, Bieszka, and Szotkowska.</p>
   <p>Resolution Committee, Mmes. Laudyn, Kaczorowska, and Szymanska.</p>
   <p>Finance Committee, Mmes. Piotrowicz, Wawrzynska, Hadych, Makowska, Drabanska, and Czarnecka.</p>
   <p>Ways and Means Committee, Mmes. Napieralska, Pawlowska, Wyrobek, Szafranska, and Thierse.</p>
   <p>Correspondence Committee, Mmes. Koflewska, Jarzembowska, and Nowak.</p>
   <p>Press Committee, Mmes. Krysiak, Laudyn, and Bell.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1309.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Organization Committee, Mmes. Sowinska, Petlak, Krepec, and Wleklinska.</p>
   <p>A motion to adjourn was then passed unanimously.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
