<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-07-17">July 17, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Women Meet to Discuss Organization Plans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0217</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0217.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-07-17">July 17, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH WOMEN MEET TO DISCUSS ORGANIZATION PLANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of Polish women was held yesterday for the purpose of discussing the details of the projected Polish Women's Patriotic Organization. About forty women were present.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Vincent Barzynski, who also attended the meeting, explained the purposes of the proposed organization in an extensive address. They are as follows:</p>
   <p>1. Prayer for Poland.</p>
   <p>2. Charitable and reform activities in the broadest sense. Such activity will include relief to poverty-stricken families, especially women in need, care of the sick, care of homeless girls, mitigation of misfortune <pb facs="5423968_9_0218.jpg" n="2"/>in families torn apart by marital discord or other reasons, reform among youth, especially girls, etc.</p>
   <p>3. Patriotic activity. This will be primarily directed toward enlightenment of Polish families, especially girls and women. To this end, the organization will support the reading rooms and libraries already in existence and will establish new ones. It will strive to spread a love for Polish literature among women, support Polish schools, and contribute to the success of Polish national exercises. It will hold social and educational gatherings, spread knowledge of Polish history, etc. The organization will also attempt to influence our young girls to speak Polish in conversation amongst themselves and to acquire a sounder knowledge of the language.</p>
   <p>The purposes of the proposed organization, as expounded by Father Barzynski, were accepted and acknowledged by the gathering. They will be <pb facs="5423968_9_0219.jpg" n="3"/>discussed in detail at a future meeting of Polish women, which will be held in two or three weeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
