<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-22">Feb. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">George Washington's Birthday</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0472</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0472.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-22">Feb. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">GEORGE WASHINGTON'S BIRTHDAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is the 185th anniversary of the birth of George Washington, the Father of our adopted country, who one hundred and forty-three years ago raised the banner of rebellion against oppressing England and won the independence of the United States.</p>
   <p>All the people in the [United] States today honor the birthday of this great man, whose name will be kept forever in the pantheon of immortals as that of one of the greatest men in the entire world.</p>
   <p>We Poles, too, whom fate has sent here to a foreign land, and who represent quite a large proportion of the people here, scattered over the large expanse of the United States, should honor and love him who fought that today we might be free among the free and equal among the equal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0473.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At that time the blood of the Poles flowed in defense of the principles for which Washington struggled. Casimir Pulaski, as well as many other Poles who came here to fight for the freedom and independence of the [United] States, was killed in action at Savannah. Even today the memory of our immortal commander in chief, Thaddeus Kosciusko, who decided the fate of the war for independence at Saratoga, still lives.</p>
   <p>Today, we should honor the memory of George Washington more than ever because by so doing we will demonstrate more emphatically our loyalty toward this land of ours--adopted, it is true, but equally dear to us. And this is a very critical time for the United States. Threatening clouds are hanging over the political horizon. The present successor to George Washington also finds himself facing a most critical situation.</p>
   <p>Today the [United] States is powerful in every respect. It has more than a hundred million inhabitants, and enough strength, to defend its honor, reputation, and the rights to which it is entitled. The [United] States neither wants nor seeks a war of conquest, but it will know how to defend that which is <pb facs="5423968_9_0474.jpg" n="3"/>dearest and most sacred to every nation.</p>
   <p>And our [Polish] immigrants here, numbering a million souls, who have also helped for decades with their ant-like work increasing the power of the [United] States, would show themselves unworthy of their forefathers and themselves were they not to go forth to defend at a critical time that which our fathers helped build, that which will be equally sacred and great to our children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
