<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-16">July 16, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Second Corps of the Polish Army of America Holds Third Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-16">July 16, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">SECOND CORPS OF THE POLISH ARMY OF AMERICA HOLDS THIRD CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The third convention of the Second Corps of the Polish Army of America, a military society, was held July 11 at Novotny's Hall, 26th and Troy Streets.</p>
   <p>Delegates met at the hall early in the morning and marched in file to Saint Casimir Church for Mass services. Among the societies represented were Pulaski Volunteers, Saint Casimir Knights, Saint Gregory Krakuses, and Stephen Buszczynski Patriotic Society. Mass was celebrated by Reverend Albert Furman for the intention of the Second Corps. After the services, the delegates returned to the hall and opened the convention.</p>
   <p>1. M. Malinowski and W. Grzegorzewski were named chairman and recording secretary respectively.</p>
   <p>2. The chairman called upon Albert Scheicherdt, president of Saint Casimir <pb facs="5423968_9_1383.jpg" n="2"/>Society to deliver a speech. The speaker wished success to the convention.</p>
   <p>3. The following were chosen for a committee to verify the mandates: J. Jackowski, M. Pietraszewski, and F. Lewandowski.</p>
   <p>4. Another committee, composed of M. Gorski, F. Lewandowski, and J. Walkowiak, was appointed to examine the books of the delegates.</p>
   <p>5. A motion was made to adjourn for half an hour in order to give the credentials committee time to examine the books of the delegates.</p>
   <p>6. After the thirty-minute recess the session was resumed, and the committee to verify the Mandates submitted its report. The credentials of the following delegates were verified: F. Danisch, J. M. Sienkiewicz--Polish Youth Alliance of America; I. Morzynski, A. Gorecki--Saint Gregory Krakuses; J. Walkowiak,--Saint Onufry Knights; J. Eichman--Fourth Regiment of Uhlans; John F. Jackowski, <pb facs="5423968_9_1384.jpg" n="3"/>M. Malinowski--Saint Casimir Knights; M. Pietraszewski, M. Gorski--First Division of Krakuses of Saint Casimir, South Bend, Indiana; W. Grzegorzewski--Pulaski Volunteers; F. Lewandowski--Saint Paul Uhlans; F. Jozwiak--Pulaski Volunteers of Saint Michael Archangel.</p>
   <p>7. Mr. Morzynski read the minutes from the previous convention, which were accepted. The reading of the minutes from previous meetings was interrupted to welcome the delegates from the Polish Falcons of America. The chairman invited the delegation to the stage and greeted it in the name of the Second Corps. In return Casimir Zychlinski, president of the Polish Falcons, expressed his thanks to the organization for a telegram the latter had sent to the Falcons convention, held July 4 at South Bend, Indiana, and wished the convention success.</p>
   <p>8. The minutes of the previous meetings were read and unanimously accepted.</p>
   <p>9. The administration presented its annual report.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1385.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>10. Mr. Morzynski made a motion to have a recess for luncheon. This was agreed upon and all delegates filed out to M. Kluczynski's Restaurant. During the course of the luncheon, Mr. Zychlinski gave a patriotic speech about the Polish nation. Mr. Blaszczynski also delivered a short speech.</p>
   <p>11. The chairman of the Second Corps gave a talk on the Rapperschwil Fund, and a collection after the address brought $1.86 for its support. The speaker expressed his thanks to the contributors.</p>
   <p>12. After luncheon the delegates returned to the convention hall and resumed the business of the day. The secretary read a letter from the Polish Youth Alliance, which expressed hopes for the success of the convention. The letter was received with applause.</p>
   <p>13. Several motions were made. The first, in connection with support of the Rapperschwil Fund, made by M. Gorski, was that compulsory assessments should not be placed upon the members, that contributions should be made voluntarily <pb facs="5423968_9_1386.jpg" n="5"/>and placed in the hands of the secretary. This motion was carried.</p>
   <p>14. The second motion concerned the support of the Second Corps. It was moved that various social functions be arranged by the groups associated with the Second Corps; ten per cent of the proceeds to be turned over to the parent organization. This motion was carried.</p>
   <p>15. A motion was made to contact by letter all Polish military societies not connected with the Second Corps, asking them to send delegates to future meetings, with the understanding of becoming members. Mr. Morzynski moved that a new department take care of this matter as soon as possible. Both motions were carried.</p>
   <p>16. A motion was made to have the Second Corps publish a newspaper of its own. This matter was set aside with other incompleted business.</p>
   <p>17. A motion was made and adopted to have the Second Corps affiliated with the <pb facs="5423968_9_1387.jpg" n="6"/>Polish Youth Alliance of America and the Polish Falcons, in order to bring about better co-operation in moral matters.</p>
   <p>18. It was unanimously adopted to have the next convention held at South Bend Indiana.</p>
   <p>19. Another motion was made to elect a chaplain for the Second Corps. Reverend Albert F. Furman was the unanimous choice.</p>
   <p>20. A motion was made to name a committee to inform Reverend Furman of his new office. The committee was picked and delegated to bring the news to the priest; however, the latter was not at the St. Casimir Rectory, a fact which the committee reported to the delegates.</p>
   <p>21. I. Morzynski presented the report on the shooting gallery and maneuvers, and moved that the matter be taken up with the new administration. Concerning the Pulaski Hall, a motion was made to take up this question at the next <pb facs="5423968_9_1388.jpg" n="7"/>convention. This motion was carried.</p>
   <p>22. A discussion took place relative to having an official newspaper. A committee composed of S. Schmidt, A. Gorecki, and J. Jurkiewicz was chosen to consider this proposal. This group was suggested to get in contact with the Polish Youth Alliance.</p>
   <p>23. Mr. Morzynski motioned to have all the printing of the Second Corps done by Sztandar (Banner). His motion was carried.</p>
   <p>24. It was moved that the Second Corps be authorized to suspend any member-society if the latter is three months behind in its dues. The motion was carried.</p>
   <p>25. A warning was given to all majors to be more careful during drills. The warning was approved.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1389.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>26. A motion was carried to pay Reverend Furman five dollars for celebrating Mass in honor of the Second Corps.</p>
   <p>27. A motion was adopted to have the captains submit quarterly reports of the drills of their men.</p>
   <p>28. A motion was made and carried that the commander in chief or his adjutant get three dollars a day and traveling expenses for trips beyond the city limits to review the maneuvers of the groups of the Second Corps.</p>
   <p>29. J. Sienkiewicz delivered a short speech and was enthusiastically applauded. It was moved to adjourn for fifteen minutes.</p>
   <p>30. After a short intermission, the gavel sounded again and order was restored. At this point Reverend Furman entered. The committee that had been delegated to inform him of his office moved forward and escorted him to the stage. The chairman, in the name of the Second Corps, greeted the priest and informed him <pb facs="5423968_9_1390.jpg" n="9"/>of his appointment the priest willingly accepted and delivered a short address of thanks. His speech was received with applause.</p>
   <p>31. At this point of the session the election of new officers for the coming year was taken up. The chairman suggested to have the officers elected by acclamation. A motion was made to this effect and was carried.</p>
   <p>32. The result of the election was as follows: A. Gorecki, president; M. Malinowski, vice-president; J. F. Jackowski, secretary; F. Lewandowski, treasurer; J. Walkowiak, first trustee; F. Jozwiak, second trustee, Officers staff: S. Schmidt, commander in chief; M. Malinowski, adjutant; M. Hazinski, first major; W. Pawlak, second major; J. Walkowiak, third major; I. Morzynski, fourth major.</p>
   <p>33. After reading the list of the new officers, the latter were called upon the stage and sworn in by the chaplain.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1391.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>34. The chairman requested the chaplain to conclude the day's proceedings with a prayer, and with this the convention of the Second Corps of the Polish Army of America came to an end.</p>
   <p>W. Grzegorzewski, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
