<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. II, No. 1,
<date when="1928-01-01">Jan. 1, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A New Disgrace</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1715</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1715.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. II, No. 1,
<date when="1928-01-01">Jan. 1, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW DISGRACE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To some of our Polish brothers the fact of being in Irish-German servitude does not seem to be adequate enough. They desire to impose upon themselves a new Italian servitude.</p>
   <p>A small group of good thinking Poles on the Northwest Side of the city organized a parish under the name of the Holy Family, and invited an Italian macaroni eater to ordain them and take care of the new parish.</p>
   <p>Naturally, the Italian welcomed the offer and spread his shepherd's care over a flock of not very fastidious Polish sheep. Not knowing the Polish language, he has to perform his duties by signs, or in a macaroni-noodle-like dialect.</p>
   <p>The flock recommended itself most laudably during the Christmas holidays. At that time there appeared in Dziennik Zwiazkowy and advertisement in form of an article, which emphasized the patriotic feelings of this group, for whom one of the most solemn masses was conducted by an Italian <pb facs="5423968_9_1716.jpg" n="2"/>macaroni eater, Ferraro, and another one by even more renowned, certain Carfora.</p>
   <p>Moreover, the latter archapostle of macaroni eaters fortified the spirit of our compatriots with his noodle-like benediction from a throne specially erected for him.</p>
   <p>As we see patriotic feelings live among our people. We have to congratulate our brothers on their new success in their emancipation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
