<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-11">Oct. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning Sunday's Manifestation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0438</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0438.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-11">Oct. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING SUNDAY'S MANIFESTATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The closer we come to the date of the manifestation of Chicago Poles to be held on Sunday, October 14, the more we realize its political significance.</p>
   <p>On Sunday, we shall be celebrating two very unusual occasions. In the first place, it will be the one hundredth anniversary of the death of Thaddeus Kosciusko, who fought for American freedom at George Washington's side, and secondly, the Polish women will present the battle flag to the first regiment of the Polish Army, a banner under which our Polish youth will cross the ocean to France to fight at the Allies' side, to avenge the hundred years of slavery and oppression suffered by our homeland, and to win its freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0439.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It will be a singular occasion. It is difficult to imagine a Polish man or woman who will not want to witness such an event as this, an event that may happen only once in a lifetime. It is our belief that thousands of Poles will fill the Dexter Pavilion to make this manifestation a success.</p>
   <p>But it is not our intention here to urge participation in Sunday's exercises, for great throngs will attend, even without our encouragement. Our purpose is rather to appeal to the civic spirit of those throngs and to their Polish hearts, urging them to maintain the dignity that such an event requires. Remember that this will be a test of our political maturity in the eyes of other national groups. It is, therefore, the concern of each individual to see to his own proper behavior, and that of the next person, in order that this mass appearance of ours may be as successful as possible, and that we may not be taken as a disorderly mob, a shapeless, formless mass.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0440.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We know from previous experience that manifestations of this sort, where tens of thousands participate, that everything cannot be perfectly orderly and cannot proceed like clockwork, but the point is that there should be as little disorder as possible, so as not to offend the non-Poles who will be present. It can proceed with a minimum of disorder if each person does his best to maintain the proper dignity.</p>
   <p>It is entirely possible that our words here are superfluous, as we sincerely hope. But we have raised the matter because, not so long ago, when the reception at the Kosciusko monument for the Franco-Polish military mission was held in Humboldt Park, we had ample proof that we are not yet able to control ourselves and must crowd and push, thereby not only defying those who are attempting to maintain order, but endangering the lives of children, who run the risk of injury when a crowd becomes unmanageable.</p>
   <p>It will do no harm, then, to appeal earnestly to all those who plan to <pb facs="5423968_9_0441.jpg" n="4"/>attend Sunday's manifestation, in order that by their conduct they should not make more difficult the task of the committee and of those whose job will be to preserve order, and at the same time, that the dignity and solemnity required by the occasion be maintained. The first commandment at manifestations of this kind is to follow the directions of those in charge and to set an example of behavior for others.</p>
   <p>This much, at least, we can do.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
