<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-04">Jan. 4, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Poles in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">Extracts from the Annual Meeting of the Patriotic Organization, December, 27, 1891</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0313</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0313.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-04">Jan. 4, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">POLES IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">Extracts from the Annual Meeting of the Patriotic Organization, December, 27, 1891</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the prayer the secretary read the minutes of the previous meeting, and the financial secretary gave his report, which was accepted without objections.</p>
   <p>It was suggested that the library be called "Parishina," and that the absent librarian should give a resume of its condition and operations at the next session.</p>
   <p>A motion was made and carried that a mass be said for the purpose of asking heavenly assistance for our persecuted brothers in Europe. The mass will be said on the first Friday of each month. The pastor of the parish had been informed and has been asked to make the announcement in this paper. [Translator's note: Identity of church and pastor not given.]</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0314.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The secretary read the constitution of the newly formed dramatic unit of the Patriotic Organization. At the conclusion of the reading Mr. Kralkowski made the suggestion that officers be elected to head this new group. As a result, three members were elected to the committee: Peter Ligman, F. Zagrzebski, and T. Krolik. They will examine the constitution and will give it full consideration for adoption.</p>
   <p>A program for the month of January was planned, and the expense [involved] was discussed. The execution of these plans will be more generally discussed at a meeting set for this purpose for January 4th. A letter of invitation was read requesting the presence of this group to visit the Young Men's Club of St. Casimir's Church. The members lauded the work of the latter organization and accepted the invitation for the 17th of this month.</p>
   <p>Pastor W. [only the initial is given] gave a vivid description of conditions among our people under Russian rule. A prayer was offered for their deliverance <pb facs="5423968_9_0315.jpg" n="3"/>, and all the members were asked to attend the mass meeting in the Polish hall to protest against these unjust persecutions.</p>
   <p>Peter Ligman was elected president, F. Wleklinski was chosen secretary, and Szczeszny Zahajkiewicz was picked for the treasurer's chair. All the members of the financial committee were re-elected to fill the vacancy. Peter Czyzan was chosen marshall, and John Kunowski assistant marshal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
