<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-22">Mar. 22, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Presidents of Polish Organizations and Delegates to the Polish Mass Meeting Gather</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0953</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0953.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-22">Mar. 22, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENTS OF POLISH ORGANIZATIONS AND DELEGATES TO THE POLISH MASS MEETING GATHER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the invitation of the committee in charge of the proposed Polish mass meeting and the Kosciusko celebration program, about two hundred presidents of Polish organizations and Chicago delegates to the mass meeting gathered last night at Pulaski Hall. The Polish National Alliance, consisting of forty-eight groups, was represented by fifteen delegates.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by Mr. S. Zahajkiewicz, secretary of the committee, who explained its purpose. Sigmund Schmidt, captain of the Uhlans, was chosen as chairman and S. Zahajkiewicz as secretary.</p>
   <p>After the chairman's address, there were discussions and speeches in connection with the Kosciusko celebration. At times these discussions were so heated that they became stormy. Finally, however, all differences were adjusted, the disputes ceased, and harmony was established.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0954.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Short speeches were delivered by Sawicki, Janczewski, F. A. Satalecki, S. Zahajkiewicz, Terczewski, J. Napieralski, H. Nagiel, Lisztewnik, P. Ligman, B. Klarkowski, Herman, F. Kaminski, Dorszewski, Czerwinski, Reverend E. Siedlaczek, J. Smulski, and [Dr.] C. Midowicz.</p>
   <p>All speeches were unusally vehement, as the ultimate object of the speakers was to unite all Poles, regardless of political affiliation, for the Kosciusko celebration.</p>
   <p>In spite of disputes, the spirit of Kosciusko seemed to inspire the speakers, all of whom favored honoring the great leader and stood for unity and brotherhood.</p>
   <p>For this reason, when Nagiel suggested that all Poles living in Chicago should hold a general celebration in honor of Kosciusko, his suggestion was accepted unanimously.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0955.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Furthermore, at a suggestion made by the same citizen, it was decided to establish a permanent committee, which will be in charge of the celebration. This committee will consist of fifteen delegates (present at the meeting) from the Polish National Alliance, fifteen delegates from the Polish Roman Catholic Union under the guardianship of the Sacred Heart of Jesus, ten delegates from the Polish Roman Catholic Union under the guardianship of the Holy Virgin of Czestochowa, and three citizens from each parish.</p>
   <p>It was announced that the next meeting would be held on March 28 at Pulaski Hall.</p>
   <p>The meeting was closed with the old Polish slogan "Kochajmy Sie" (Let Us Love Each Other).</p>
   <p>S. Zahajkiewicz,</p>
   <p>Secretary of the Meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
