<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-02">Dec. 2, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Patriotic Demonstration Staged at St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0767</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0767.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-02">Dec. 2, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTIC DEMONSTRATION STAGED AT ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(The following article was received by the Dziennik Chicagoski for publication.)</p>
   <p>This year's November patriotic demonstration, marking the sixty-fifth anniversary of the uprising against the Russian yoke, was made possible through the combined efforts of all the societies of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish. Although there was an admission fee, the proceeds of which went towards the support of the Polish Hospital, a large crowd filled the Polish Hall to pay tribute to the memory of the fallen heroes who fought valiantly for the faith and the land of their forefathers.</p>
   <p>Punctually at 8 P. M., Boleslas Klarkowski, in the name of the committee that arranged the exercise, opened the demonstration with a short speech, and invited Peter Kiolbassa to act as chairman for the evening. Leon Szopinski <pb facs="5423968_9_0768.jpg" n="2"/>was appointed recording secretary.</p>
   <p>The first number of the program was a declamation, "Pray O Poland," by Miss Angeline Wisniewska, a student of the Holy Family of Nazareth School. She recited this piece with fervor and sincerity. Many hearts in the audience were touched by her words. Hearty applause greeted the young student as she made her bow.</p>
   <p>The young ladies' choir, under the direction of Andrew Kwasigroch, sang the beautiful song, "Warszawianka" (Maid of Poland), a revolutionary song.</p>
   <p>Mr. B. Klarkowski, instructor at the St. Stanislaus Kostka College, delivered the initial address of the evening. His speech was patriotic in every sense of the word; it was filled with deep thought and observation, and worthy of being published. Mr. Klarkowski spoke principally on the subject of true patriotism and its aims. He urged everyone toward strong ties with the faith, and love for the fatherland. The speaker pointed out that education is a <pb facs="5423968_9_0769.jpg" n="3"/>medium through which to elevate the people. In conclusion he appealed to the Polish youth, as the future of the Polish nation, to uphold the traditions of Poland. Mr. Klarkowski's speech was brilliantly delivered, and the audience, greatly impressed, applauded him freely.</p>
   <p>This was followed by a recitation by seven-year-old Miss Ursula Klarkowska, who recited "Polska Stolico! Bog Z Toba" (O Polish Capital! God is with you). The men's group of the St. Cecilia Choir sang "Tesknota Za Ojczyzna" (Yearning for the Fatherland). The audience felt proud that the Poles have a group of such capable singers, as was evidenced by the applause. They are a credit not only to the director but to the parish as well.</p>
   <p>The second speaker was Modestus Maryanski. (The entire text of the speech is in another section of the paper.)</p>
   <p>One of the school boys, Mroczkowski, recited "Aby Polska Nie Zginela" (In order that Poland may not be Lost). This poetic verse is primarily directed <pb facs="5423968_9_0770.jpg" n="4"/>at the Polish youth, for it urges the youth to work, steel, and strengthen itself physically and spiritually. It also recommends that the youth place reliance upon faith and virtue, for wherever the youth walks along the paths of God it will find hope for a better future. Later on, it also expresses the thought that in order that Poland may not be lost, the Poles should clasp their hands in a brotherly circle, "for there is strength and power where the spirit of unity exists". The youth was also advised to safeguard its native customs and language.</p>
   <p>The women's group of the St. Cecilia's choir sang "Piesn Nadziei" (The Song of Hope). This was followed by a declamation, "Spowiedz W Cytadeli" (Confession in the Citadel), which was given in three parts by the school girls, the Misses Eugenia Statkiewicz, Rose Danysz, and Elizabeth Mlodzikowska. All three executed their lines like troupers. It has been a long time indeed since such splendid elocutionary ability was displayed on this stage. The voice inflections, gestures, and sincerity of world delivery of these students was nothing short of perfection. Credit should be extended to the Sisters of Nazareth for their capable training methods.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0771.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Anthony Rudnicki delivered an address filled with national spirit.</p>
   <p>"We are celebrating today," the speaker quietly began, "a truly sad anniversary, but we need not be saddened by this, for those that fought and fell for the cause of freedom set us a beautiful example of the way to work for our fatherland. Our people lost the fight for their principles and were placed in bondage. But this did not happen without cause. We deserved this fall because we did not respect the laws of God and man, we had fallen from the faith of our forefathers, and the gentry [Szlachta] did not look after the people properly. Later this evil had its effect, for when these people were needed the most, they could not be found; they did not understand what was meant by "fatherland," nor were they familiar with national problems. In this respect the gentry were at fault. If, however, we were at fault that Poland fell, her resurrection lies in our hands. The other primary causes of our downfall were discord and the fatal 'Liberum Veto,' under which one person of the Diet could dissolve the session by saying 'I object'. The Lord has sent down on us a heavy penalty, and humiliation for our past mistakes. For many years we were exposed to the worst kind of <pb facs="5423968_9_0772.jpg" n="6"/>oppression; but despite this we exist, and through us Poland lives. With our common help and God's assistance, Poland will someday rise again. Nevertheless, if we wish to do something for her we must all live in harmony.</p>
   <p>"We came to America to better our lot. Let us work, make sacrifices, and enlighten ourselves. Let us follow the example of other nationalities; let us follow their form of co-operation and support, for it is through this that they have made a name for themselves. Unfortunately we have the opposite tendency; instead of sincerely working together, we start unpleasant disturbances, thereby giving the American papers an excuse to blacken our name. This is very bad. And who is responsible for this if not our false, spent, moral and material intelligence, which is prepared to do the vilest deeds for monetary gain, and serves Paul today and Thomas tomorrow, and writes one thing today and another tomorrow. We should guard ourselves against such men. It is our duty to strive for an intelligent family which will not shame us through its acts but will represent us favorably. Therefore we should educate our children, send them to higher institutions of learning, and work together <pb facs="5423968_9_0773.jpg" n="7"/>earnestly to better our position; for we will be at a loss to help Poland if we remain in penury."</p>
   <p>The speaker was generously applauded for his inspiring oration.</p>
   <p>The next number on the program was the singing of "Leca Listke Drzewa" (The Leaves of the Tree are Falling) by a mixed choir. Miss Wanda Barwig, John Kondziorski, and Ladislas Barwig sang solos.</p>
   <p>A young schoolboy, Sobieszczyk, recited the verse "Dziecie I Czar" (The Child and the Czar), and five schoolgirls sang "Polska Odrodzona" (Poland Reborn).</p>
   <p>The Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek gave the last speech of the evening. He thanked all parish societies for arranging and making this event possible. The priest urged them all toward further work in the field of nationalism [Polish].</p>
   <p>"Adhere to your traditions, Polish people," pleaded the Reverend Sedlaczek.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0774.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"Always work together and we will be invincible, and through this invincibility a better fate will await us. We observe annually the great national events, look into the book of sacrifices to remind ourselves of the noble and heroic events of the past, in order that they may serve as an incentive for continued work. With this work and the banner of 'Faith and the Fatherland' we can set an example to our youth, the future of our nation.</p>
   <p>"The lack of unity and solidarity led to the defeat of our best hopes during 1830 and 1831," continued Reverend E. Sedlaczek. "Since then sixty-five years have elapsed, but has this helped us? Not in the least! Let us tell ourselves the truth. The same mistakes that dragged our country alive to the grave, these same errors that wasted our most valorous efforts, are prevalent in our life today. We are incorrigible. Along with the sixty-fifth anniversary of the November Insurrection [the rise against the Russian rule in 1830] we are commemorating the one-hundredth anniversary of the fall of Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0775.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"These humiliating disasters should have brought us to reflection and introspection. But what are we doing?</p>
   <p>"Is not the fourth partition of Poland taking place here in this free land, discovered by Columbus? And who is sharpening the surgeon's knife to sever our society on American soil? The spies of Prussia and Russia do not lurk in our fold, but brother opposes brother, creating dissension within our own ranks. Thus we are committing fratricide. As long as brother does not aid brother, as long as the brotherly spirit does not envelop us and give us unity, the rebirth of Poland will be in doubt."</p>
   <p>Reverend Sedlaczek warned the people also against the vile and godless newspapers.</p>
   <p>"We have slept," he continued, "and we are sleeping to this day. We look on quietly as a thief rifles our chambers and takes away our most cherished treasure, faith, and with it our identity as a nation. Let us remember that <pb facs="5423968_9_0776.jpg" n="10"/>a Pole without religion is like a child--a waif without a father or mother; a Pole without God is like a wanderer without a road. No light will penetrate his soul. Such a man is lost.</p>
   <p>"Do not permit the polemic papers to get into your homes," stressed Reverend Sedlaczek, "for they are poisonous--an unhealthy food. Let us defend ourselves through action, reveal these things to our people and warn them against impending dangers.</p>
   <p>"Things are in a critical state, it is true. But are we to give in to hopelessness and dark despair? Is it impossible for us to find our way clear in this choas?</p>
   <p>"A Pole who believes in God should never lose hope. Let us all have hope and a better future will be ours.</p>
   <p>"The surge of vileness will abate; the time must come when we will collect <pb facs="5423968_9_0777.jpg" n="11"/>ourselves and find a way to a better road--a road of mutual assistance and work for the fatherland under the banner, 'Faith and the Fatherland'. 'Poland is not yet lost'--with this song on their lips our valiant heroes gave the supreme sacrifice in the effort to liberate Poland during the insurrections; with this song thousands of shackled prisoners marched to the far-flung Siberian steppes; therefore, let this song revive our courage and let hope for a better future inspire us," concluded the Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek.</p>
   <p>The applause that greeted the speaker as he left the stand rocked the auditorium. The program was concluded with the singing of the Polish national hymn, "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland). Everyone in the audience lent his voice to this song of hope. From hundreds of hearts these words were fervently echoed:</p>
   <p>"Before your altars high we beseech Thee,</p>
   <p>"O Lord, to set us and our country free."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0778.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>This patriotic demonstration was one of the best of its kind. The speakers, singers, and elocutionists were rewarded with generous applause for their fine work.</p>
   <p>All made their way home filled with greater spirit and hope for a better future. There was a feeling of gratitude in all their hearts, not only for those that made this affair possible, but also for those that took an active part on the stage. Although it was in reality an occasion of sadness, there was consolation in the fact that the will for work for the fatherland still lives. Besides this there was deep satisfaction in all the participants because the affair had a two-fold purpose, commemoration of a national event and material aid to the Polish Hospital, which is so ably conducted by the Sisters of Nazareth. A sizable sum was derived from this affair.</p>
   <p>Leon Szopinski, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
