<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-06">May 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Third of May Celebration and Polish Army Recruiting Rally Held</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0408</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0408.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-06">May 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THIRD OF MAY CELEBRATION AND POLISH ARMY RECRUITING RALLY HELD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, May 5, a great recruiting rally and Third of May celebration was held at the Pulaski Park Hall, corner of Noble and Blackhawk Streets, under the auspices of Council III, Polish National Alliance. At 3:30 P.M., the hall was filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>The exercises were opened by the chairman of the committee in charge, [J.] Bucholz, who called upon Leon M. Nowak, president of Council III, to act as chairman, and the undersigned [John S. Zawilinski] to act as secretary. The members of the central administration of the Polish National Alliance, the commissioner of Circuit 15, the speakers--the Reverend Casimir Sztuczko and Mrs. J. Smulski--and W. Poszwinski, veteran of the 1863 Polish insurrection, were invited to take places upon the platform.</p>
   <p>After explaining the purpose of these exercises and the significance of the <pb facs="5423968_9_0409.jpg" n="2"/>Constitution of the Third of May, the chairman called for the first number on the program.</p>
   <p>The Holy Trinity Parish Choir, under the direction of [W.] Baluta, organist of Holy Trinity Church, sang two songs, one of which was a medley of [Polish] national hymns.</p>
   <p>The first speaker on the program was the Reverend Casimir Sztuczko. He said: "The Polish nation, in accepting the Constitution of the Third of May, likened itself to the Biblical sower who went forth to scatter the best and most healthful seeds. The seed fell on fertile though unplowed soil, and so did not give the expected harvest. The Polish nation, dazzled by its new-found freedom, could not stand the bright glare and did not know how to continue. On the other hand, its enemies, fearing that their peoples also might demand their rights, used every method within their means to prevent the Constitution from being put into effect.</p>
   <p>"At the present time, the Polish nation again finds itself in a similar <pb facs="5423968_9_0410.jpg" n="3"/>situation, engaged in similar work. Some look upon this work and merely shrug their shoulders, having no faith in the results. We, however, who believe in the efforts of the patriots, are convinced that their efforts are not in vain. The precepts of the Constitution of the Third of May will be realized.</p>
   <p>"In former years, the magnates who spent their time in foreign countries regarded the Constitution as harmful to them; the townspeople and the peasants had no voice in the matter. For these reasons, in spite of the superhuman efforts of the Polish patriots at the "Four Year Diet" (Sejm), the Constitution was defeated. Today there are no such obstacles, there are no magnates who attempt, for personal reasons, to defeat the efforts of patriots who are ready to sacrifice everything for the Polish cause. Today there is no Polish group that does not have the love of its mother country in its heart. As proof, one can take the Galician Legion in Russia and the Polish Army in France. If the Polish people did not love their motherland, these would not exist. These armies are proof that a deep and ardent patriotism burns in the hearts of <pb facs="5423968_9_0411.jpg" n="4"/>Polish youth.</p>
   <p>"Another fact is that, while our enemies who are striving to ruin us succeeded in demoralizing Russia, the Poles did not take their bait. They are traveling the straight and honest way to freedom. At the present time, the high principles of the Constitution of the Third of May have a good chance of realization. Today the Poles are sacrificing more and more for their homeland, which gives a guarantee of a better future.</p>
   <p>"The Russians can no longer obstruct our work of realizing the principles of the Constitution of the Third of May; they could only create dissension among the peoples who had heretofore lived in accord with the Poles. If, however, we stand firmly on our principles and realize our fondest hopes of a free and independent Poland, then the Lithuanians and the Ruthenians will come to us. There still exists our greatest enemy, the Prussian, who, in spite of the loss of hundreds of thousands of men, is still powerful. But the time will come when the Prussian, who now lives at our cost, will fall--the United States will <pb facs="5423968_9_0412.jpg" n="5"/>see to that.</p>
   <p>"The allies, striving to keep Russia's favor, never openly expressed themselves on the Polish question, but there was one man who insisted that Poland must be free, united, and independent, and that man was Woodrow Wilson. We are putting great hopes in this country, which will give us the necessary means--and Poland will arise, powerful and great.</p>
   <p>"Long live the Constitution of the Third of May, and long live the able sons of Poland who are working for the realization of its principles."</p>
   <p>The priest-patriot's address was interrupted in many places by frenzied applause.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was S. Krzywonos, organizer for the Polish Army in France. The speaker used the Constitution as a symbol which, bringing freedom, equality, and rebirth to Poland, collapsed as a result of the efforts of our enemies, who feared its influence among their own peoples. And today we are slaves. Because of the power of our enemies, our countrymen are being conscripted into the <pb facs="5423968_9_0413.jpg" n="6"/>Austrian, Russian, and Prussian armies. Are we to continue being the slaves of our enemies, shedding our blood in a cause not our own? Let us lend all our efforts toward our own independence by supporting the Polish Army. That army consists of your sons and brothers who will avenge the wrongs done you, for a better future.</p>
   <p>[Translators note: A quotation from the Polish poet, Ujejski, has been omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>"Our motherland is rich and beautiful, but we have to wander in foreign countries to earn our bread. Shall we permit our enemies to continue exploiting our land? Are we to allow our country to come out of this cataclysm ununited? Shall we allow the arrogant Prussian to spit in our faces? Our greatest men in this country and across the ocean have created the Polish Army. To the Army then, young Poles, to arms! Those who come after you [posterity] will envy you that you understood the high ideals of your task and did your part in the rebirth of a free and independent Poland."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0414.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The address was concluded amid applause.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Harriet Smulski then rendered a beautiful vocal solo, which the audience rewarded with a storm of applause. Mrs. Smulski always lends her voice willingly for the cause, and in this case her beautiful rendition was truly the gem of the program. The next number was a violin solo by S. Bialorvski, to the piano accompaniment of Miss Mary Lisocki.</p>
   <p>An address by Dr. [B.] Klarkowski followed. "The Polish ship of state was brought upon the shoals by those who guided it," he said. "Kosciusko was the first to bring the common people to the level of citizenship, for he was convinced that the people, called upon to perform the duties of citizenship, could effectively direct the affairs of state. Our nation has passed and is passing through times of great trial. Our enemies have cut us up and swallowed us, but they have never digested us and never will. There on the fields of France, a battle is being waged between freedom and slavery, between democracy and autocracy. We ought to put at least a million soldiers into that battle. There are among us those who would sell us out, those who tell us that the <pb facs="5423968_9_0415.jpg" n="8"/>Prussian will give us freedom; but we are not beggars--we do not want Prussia, Austrian, or Russian freedom. We want Polish freedom. You young Poles in whom the Polish spirit has not died: your place is not on the streets but in France, among your brothers.</p>
   <p>But it is not enough to create and send out an army; that army needs equipment and care, and for that it is necessary to sacrifice. Sacrifice in this case amounts merely to fulfilling our duty. It is up to you, Polish mothers, to give up everything that you hold dearest and place it upon the altar of your homeland. If you do not want this war to be repeated, you must awaken your husbands and sons to their duty to Poland. Let us, then, give what we can to end slavery in this world, so that freedom will triumph, and we will be able to celebrate next May in the capital of our country, in Warsaw, whither the standards of America and the Allies are leading us."</p>
   <p>The speaker was rewarded with applause. The orchestra, conducted by Professor Przybylski, then played a medley of Polish songs while a collection was taken <pb facs="5423968_9_0416.jpg" n="9"/>up for wool for the Polish Army.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was K. B. Czarnecki, vice-president of the Polish National Alliance. He said: "In going through the history of Poland, it can be noticed that the means for putting the Constitution of the Third of May into effect were lacking. Poland did not have money or soldiers. The people were not yet prepared--a man may be brave and capable, but that is not enough. A full treasury and a well-trained army are indispensable. Principles themselves, even though they may be the best, are meaningless unless there are means by which to support them. It depends upon us, after many years of practicing the principles of the Constitution of the Third of May, whether we are equal to our task. I call upon you, in the name of those who fought for the freedom of various nations and who worked in the "Four year Diet" (Sejm), to contribute liberally for Poland's needs. During this month, the "Golden Lists" are being sent out for the collection of contributions for the Polish cause--not one of us should be missing from those lists. Let us all contribute, men, women, and children, for what the Polish sword left unfinished at Grunwald, our hard-earned <pb facs="5423968_9_0417.jpg" n="10"/>dollars will complete." The speaker was applauded.</p>
   <p>The next number was a bass solo, "Prayer of Jagiello," by A. Ludwig, with piano accompaniment by [W.] Baluta. This was followed by an address by W. Poszwinski, a veteran of the Polish Insurrection of 1863. After explaining just what that motherland is to which we owe our love, the speaker passed on to the Constitution of the Third of May. He pointed out that the intent of that Constitution was the reorganization of Polish society on principles of self-government. He said: "Although it happened during trying times for Poland, while enemies were planning its ruin and the Szlachta (petty noblemen) were determined to retain their privileges at any cost, the Polish nation accepted the Constitution, and by this act was strengthened and renewed. And it proved its strength despite its downfall. We collapsed then, after rebirth. Let us hope that there will come a time when the despots will be forced to recognize and respect our efforts. When we will show that the tortures they inflicted upon our nation were in vain. The White Eagle will rise again over Polish fields and Poland will begin a new life. And then the principles of the Constitution of the Third <pb facs="5423968_9_0418.jpg" n="11"/>of May will be put into effect."</p>
   <p>The veteran of the struggle for Polish freedom was thunderously applauded by the audience.</p>
   <p>The chairman then thanked the public for its numerous attendance, and with the singing of "Boze Cos Polske"! (God Love Poland), the exercises were closed.</p>
   <p>The collection for wool for the Polish Army brought in $57.</p>
   <p>John S. Zawilinski, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
