<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-24">Aug. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution of Convention of the Administrative Board and Board of Directors of the Polish National Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1286</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1286.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-24">Aug. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION OF CONVENTION OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE BOARD AND BOARD OF DIRECTORS OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following resolution concerning our homeland's independence was passed August 22, 1914, at Cambridge Springs, Pennsylvania:</p>
   <p>When throughout all of Europe and on the plains of Poland cannons thunder, rifle salvos resound, thousands of men fall, and the cries of tens of thousands of wounded reach the skies,</p>
   <p>When in the armies of the annexer nations, a half million Poles are impressed against their will to fight for a cause not their own and to shed the blood of their brothers,</p>
   <p>When, on the other hemisphere, a terrible war for the hegemony of the old world rages among the Latin, Germanic and Slavic races,</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1287.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We, representatives of the 100,000 members of the Alliance, emigrants in the United States, convened at the request of the Mr. Anthony Karabasz, Censor of our organization, the Polish National Alliance, after three day's deliberation solemnly resolve:</p>
   <p>1. To mobilize the P. N. A. [Polish National Alliance] in all the colonies and settlements in the United States and to call upon the members of the Alliance to begin active work for the cause of Poland's independence, in accord with the basic principle of the constitution of the P. N. A. adopted at the time of the founding of this organization, and to do this in the following way:</p>
   <p>(a) To authorize, because of the importance of the historical moment and according to the precept, salus populi--suprema lex, the Department of Independence of the P. N. A.</p>
   <p>(b) To summon the Commissioners of the Alliance to control and observe the work for independence in the branches and groups of the P. N. A.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1288.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>(c) To summon the presidents of the branches and groups to appoint committees and subcommittees of the Department of Independence and to start enthusiastic action for the raising of a fund for political and relief activities.</p>
   <p>2. To send to the cashier of the P. N. A. the money collected through contributions and assessments, which money will constitute an independence fund, which can be used only and exclusively for work towards independence, in accordance with the bylaws of the Department and sanctioned by the committee on the expenditure of money.</p>
   <p>3. We agree, in accordance with the appeal received from the Czech-American Central Press Bureau, to co-operate with them in mutual action on American soil for the following purposes:</p>
   <p>(a) To draw attention through our Press Bureau to the injuries and subjection which millions of Poles and other Slavs in Europe are suffering and to gain the sympathy of the American people for them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1289.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>(b) To exhort the members of the Congress of the United States, so that, when the proper time comes, they will assume the task of presenting before the powers our injuries and our desire for a united, free, and independent Poland.</p>
   <p>(c) To draw the attention of the President of the United States--who has already offered his services as mediator between the warring countries in Europe--to the fact that without the final and just settlement of our injuries and establishment of our rights there can and will be no universal peace; that without a free Poland, an armed peace must again result in a new war, and that without a free Poland and the freedom of oppressed nations, the civilization of the world cannot travel on the road of progress for the good of humanity, as all civilized and cultured peoples would wish.</p>
   <p>(d) To appeal, through proper representatives, directly to the powers when they come to the peace conference after the war, for the purpose of a final settlement and liquidation of war gains and losses, and there to present our <pb facs="5423968_9_1290.jpg" n="5"/>just demands and our changeless right to autonomous political existence.</p>
   <p>4. We resolve and assert that our ideal and our minimum demand is a united, free, and independent Poland, encompassing all of the truly Polish lands of the former Republic of Poland, and we intend to work here for this ideal, and this ideal alone, through our Department of Independence. The decision in relation to the warring countries and the eventual support of one of them by our Polish nation we leave to our alma mater in Europe. We emigrant Poles, as her loyal sons, will follow our alma mater when she decides and declares who should be supported and alongside of whom we should fight.</p>
   <p>5. We resolve to authorize the Censor to call a special convention of the Department of Independence or its executive bodies, in case of need or sudden change of historical developments, and likewise to grant these bodias the power and authority to modify, correct, and complete the laws and bylaws of the Department of Independence as the need arises.</p>
   <p>Poles in America! wanderers on this hospitable American soil, the historic <pb facs="5423968_9_1291.jpg" n="6"/>hour has struck. Let all of us, then, together, traveling different but parallel roads, strive toward our mutual beloved ideal of a free homeland.</p>
   <p>Away with camps, away with parties and party pretentions--the Polish National Alliance in America calls you brothers to action! Do, each of you, everything in your circle, in your group, which the longing to resurrect Poland bids you, and the whole will take care of itself, and the immortal Poland of our desires will rise from her grave alive! "Serve the homeland;" the ideal of the Alliance, we place in your hearts! Long live united, free and independent Poland! Long live the Polish nation and all of its classes!</p>
   <p>For the Department of Independence,</p>
   <p>(Signed) The Administrative Board,</p>
   <p>and the Board of Directors of the</p>
   <p>Polish National Alliance</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
