<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-19">Dec. 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Speech of Mr. S. Zahajkiewicz at the Patriotic Organization Entertainment</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0192</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0192.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-19">Dec. 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">SPEECH OF MR. S. ZAHAJKIEWICZ AT THE PATRIOTIC ORGANIZATION ENTERTAINMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fulfilling our promise made yesterday to the readers of the Dziennik Chicaoski, we are publishing herewith a lengthier synopsis and some quotations from Mr. Zahajkiewicz's beautiful speech made at the entertainment given last Sunday, December 17, by the Patriotic Organization.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zahajkiewicz began by reminding the audience of the first entertainment given by the Patriotic Organization and mentioned that the night's entertainment had been arranged in order to end the old year with a good deed. At any rate, the purpose of the Organization is very evident, namely, patriotic action. The Organization again cries out to all: "Join us, you sons of Poland! Let us unite for joint co-operation, because our aims are worthy, and our work, although very modest, still gives exceptional fruits!" This is practically the only organization in the United States which has not for <pb facs="5423968_9_0193.jpg" n="2"/>its purpose the payment of death or other benefits, but, strangely, it does demand small payments from members for patriotic purposes. Its branches, such as the Parochial Choir, the Dramatic Circle, the soldiers [members of so-called Polish military societies], the turners, etc., have won the approval of Polish audiences, even if many look upon all this with levity, as a plaything. Nevertheless, the work is important, because it consists in uniting, improving, and stabilizing the Polish spirit among our youth. Instead of loitering in alleys or in saloons, the youth enrolled in our choirs and circles educate and improve themselves and become wiser and more gentle. It is almost like a school for the more mature young people. Considering these important factors, everybody should become a member of this organization and sincerely support it. The speaker bitterly assailed the indifference of some Poles.</p>
   <p>"Isn't there in our veins," he asked "that blood that ordered our fathers and our forefathers to fight in defense of faith, in defense of our country?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0194.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Are we not brothers to those who even today follow in the footsteps of our forefathers--heroes who, refusing to deny the faith of our fathers and our beloved fatherland, are baring their chests to the bullets fired by the Russian executioners? Should we forget that we are descendants of an eagle family, and deny our worthy Polish names and the famous deeds of our predecessors proclaimed in the histories of all nations, and should we become snakes, all selfish, who only wish to think of themselves and their own pockets?</p>
   <p>"No; we cannot do such a thing! We were born and will die as Poles! And we must live according to the Holy Faith of our fathers and love our fatherland, if we do not wish to be snakes, if we wish to appear before the Judge on high without fear."</p>
   <p>That portion of Mr. Zahajkiewicz's speech where he pointed out our duties <pb facs="5423968_9_0195.jpg" n="4"/>to our fatherland and the dangers threatening our young people of forgetting their own fatherland, abandoning their morals, or treading the path of evil prophets, caused a tremendous impression.</p>
   <p>We are quoting it herewith practically complete:</p>
   <p>"God gave us our country and demands an accounting as to how we perform our duties toward it; therefore, God commands us to be patriotic, to love our country, and to work for its benefit!</p>
   <p>"All of us are patriots, but only in talking! When action is demanded, when in the name of God and with God's help we call for patriotic sacrifices, then out of one hundred patriots only one or two will respond.</p>
   <p>"The truth hurts--is an old saying--but we are forced to tell each other the <pb facs="5423968_9_0196.jpg" n="5"/>bitter truth. We must speak about this painful subject, because otherwise we will never eliminate it. He who does not deserve these accusations need not consider them meant for him. For us, it is time to wake up--time to forget troubles and indifferences, time to go to work, because life is short and God's judgment is terrible but just! It is time now to save our children and youth, because a plague worse than cholera is threatenting their very hearts and souls. Can't you see this danger, which, as the sword of Damocles, is hanging over the heads of our young people? Do you not see that horrible, black oblivion is opening up under their feet?</p>
   <p>"He who soberly studies, not one small community, but the whole world, finds his hair standing up on his head, because one would imagine that God has completely turned away from the people and that the end of the world is near, as it seems that the devil, through his messengers, is coursing throughout the world as never before. Crime, dishonesty, and robbery fill the columns of newspapers of all nations; false present-day prophets, lovers of bombs, <pb facs="5423968_9_0197.jpg" n="6"/>apostles of dynamite, loud-mouthed orators who claim to be leaders and defenders of the people but sow only the seed of Satan and disbelief, build fires of anarchism which would destroy everything that we represent as superior to the animal. As Christ said on the Cross: 'They know not what they do,' so these do not realize what they are doing, do not realize that they are murdering the soul and spirit and forcing the world back into the past!</p>
   <p>"Their voices and actions are false tones amid the beautiful heavenly harmony of this world; they are travesty and cheapness, which, for the sake of praise from those that are equal and for the sake of personal gain, cry blindly and lead all they can to the abyss of hell!</p>
   <p>"What their purpose in life is, they know not, but they condemn everything and sneer at everything that is good and holy, because they recognize no <pb facs="5423968_9_0198.jpg" n="7"/>truth and do not possess it."</p>
   <p>"In view of these facts", the speaker asked, "Should we look with indifference at it? Is there nothing we can do for our young people? Shall we permit them to follow false prophets?" And he answered these questions saying that we should work for and educate the young, in order to direct them along the path of glory and truth of our brave forefathers, in the footsteps of warriors of words and followers of truth, which God has not refused Poland.</p>
   <p>"Let us go to work, then," said Mr. Zahajkiewicz, "for, even if we were good and honest, if we did nothing for the children, and for others, we would still be debtors, because we could have done a lot of more good but refused to do it. So, let us remember that Poland is the bulwark of Christianity, that every Pole is a warrior for the Holy Faith; let us be patriots, preserve our young people from becoming strangers to their own land, and let us <pb facs="5423968_9_0199.jpg" n="8"/>defend them from present-day false prophets, because we will have to give an account of our actions before God! Let us awaken, throw off lethargy and laziness, show that we are sincere sons of that poor but great and world-famous Poland!</p>
   <p>"We need faith, love and action, and no evil spirit will be able to conquer us!"</p>
   <p>With this ringing appeal and assurance, Mr. Zahajkiewicz concluded his beautiful speech.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
