<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-12">May 12, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">May Day Exercise Celebrated in Immaculate Conception Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0614</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0614.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-12">May 12, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">MAY DAY EXERCISE CELEBRATED IN IMMACULATE CONCEPTION PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A May Day exercise [in honor of the Polish constitution of May 3, 1791] was staged at Calumet Hall on May 9.</p>
   <p>The following societies took part in the event: St. Vincent de Paul Society, St. Josephat Society, John III Sobieski Society, St. Joseph Legion Society, Pulaski Guard Society, Polish Falcons Society, S. Czarniecki Society, John Kilinski Society, and B. Dembinski Men's Chorus.</p>
   <p>When everybody had been seated after the parade, Martin Wiora opened the demonstration and called upon C. Witkowski to preside as chairman and John S. Derpa as recording secretary. A rich program, arranged by a committee representing all societies mentioned, followed.</p>
   <p>After a speech by the chairman, the White Eagle Band played a march, "War <pb facs="5423968_9_0615.jpg" n="2"/>Signals of 1793". This was followed by an address, "The History of the Constitution of the Third of May," delivered by the Reverend F. M. Wojtalewicz, pastor of the Church of the Immaculate Conception. The B. Dembinski Men's Chorus sang "Vistula," after which J. F. Smietanka spoke in English on the Polish constitution of the Third of May.</p>
   <p>Miss Marianne Barzynska played a captivating piano solo, for which she received a round of applause. Judge Edmund F. Burke spoke on Poland and compared its constitution with that of the United States. He stated that both stand for freedom and liberty.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch sang "Unfortunate Halka". Her rendition was so moving that she was compelled to give an encore, for which she was rewarded with a beautiful bouquet of fresh flowers.</p>
   <p>Another speech about the history of the Polish constitution was made by Casimir Zychlinski. The Men's Chorus sang "Spring," and this was followed by <pb facs="5423968_9_0616.jpg" n="3"/>recitations by A. Walkowiak, Fronkowski, and Strozewski. The White Eagle Bank played "God Save Poland" as the concluding number of the evening.</p>
   <p>Calumet Hall was filled; more than 3500 persons attended, of whom 200 were Americans.</p>
   <p>Sincere thanks are expressed to the committee for making this program possible. Thanks are also given to the speakers, the singers, the players, and the audience for making this patriotic affair a success.</p>
   <p>John S. Derpa, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
