<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-07">May 7, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Constitution of the Third of May Celebrated at St. Michael Archangel Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0800</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0800.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-07">May 7, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">CONSTITUTION OF THE THIRD OF MAY CELEBRATED AT ST. MICHAEL ARCHANGEL PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 104th anniversary of the Constitution of the Third of May was celebrated at St. Michael Archangel Parish, South Chicago. This festivity was combined with the termination of the year of national mourning. The affair was made possible through the efforts of Reverend J. Nowicki, pastor, and was staged Sunday, May 5.</p>
   <p>The pastor opened the program with a solemn prayer, after which he informed the large audience about the purpose of this manifestation.</p>
   <p>Songs by the parish mixed choir opened the program. The Polish national songs sung by the choir were received with enthusiasm by the audience.</p>
   <p>The first speaker of the evening was Ignace Kowalski. After painting a verbal picture of the early history of Poland, he pointed out the meaning of the Constitution of the Third of May to Poland. Mr. Kowalski lauded the work of our <pb facs="5423968_9_0801.jpg" n="2"/>forefathers for their sacrifices for the fatherland, and commended them to the audience as an example worthy of emulation. He urged everyone to strive for harmony, unity and co-operative work for the good of Polonia, and above all to foster the patriotism and faith which have brought so much good to Poland. In conclusion, he spoke to the parents about raising their children along the principles of the fatherland, to make them become good Poles and Catholics.</p>
   <p>After this speech, the school children sang a patriotic song.</p>
   <p>The second speaker was C. J. Bielinski of St. Adalbert Parish. His talk was based on our Polish youth, and he urged the parents to look carefully after their upbringing. Mr. Bielinski paid tribute to the great deeds of Kosciusko, and pressed the Polish youth to follow his example. "Peace," said the speaker, "will only envelop us when enlightenment begins to bloom. I beseech the Polish youth to work and educate itself for our ultimate salvation."</p>
   <p>Songs and declamations were given by B. Rybczynski, A. Szymborski, Michael Muszynski, Max Kraskiewicz, and others (all school children).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0802.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Little Miss Louise Weclewska, age 7, gave such an animated recital of "Polka Jestem" (I Am A Polish Lady), which was rather long, that it was readily the highlight of the entertainment program. The audience was liberal with its applause, for it was familiar with the patriotic verse.</p>
   <p>The concluding speaker of the evening was Reverend Nowicki. He thanked the audience for its work and attendance at all the patriotic affairs staged at the parish, and complimented it for its enthusiasm in such work; for out of it peace and harmony would more readily be brought about. The pastor also spoke about the need of keeping up the patriotic spirit and the faith among the Poles in America. Patriotism without faith will bring us quicker to ruin than to the realization of our aims. He warned against the "paper-shelled" pseudo-patriots who shout to the world the need of bringing succor to the fatherland while they themselves do not do anything.</p>
   <p>"He who preserves the tongue, faith and culture of Poland and instills them in his children, can do a great deal more for his fatherland than the one <pb facs="5423968_9_0803.jpg" n="4"/>who cries: 'forward against the foe!' and at the same time flees from the enemy and secretly supports him."</p>
   <p>In conclusion he urged the mothers to watch over their children and to see to it that they do not neglect the Polish language, customs and habits, and to guard against the use of another tongue at home.</p>
   <p>The parish orchestra deserves a word of credit for their ably executed numbers.</p>
   <p>"God Save Poland" terminated the patriotic celebration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
