<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. II, No. 29,
<date when="1928-07-15">July 15, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">New Material for the History of the Poles in the United States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1676</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1676.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. II, No. 29,
<date when="1928-07-15">July 15, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">NEW MATERIAL FOR THE HISTORY OF THE POLES IN THE UNITED STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In commemoration of the Polish heroes who died in the World War, a monument in their honor was unveiled at St. Adelbert's cemetery on July 4.</p>
   <p>This particular celebration will pass down to the history of the Poles in the free land of Washington, and our posterity will certainly comment on the peculiar circumstances of that affair.</p>
   <p>The memory of our heroes who died for democracy and freedom of all nations, should be cherished by us. But let us not forget that the most sacred ideals are sometimes utilized for mean and humiliating purposes.</p>
   <p>We hope that some unbiased historian of Polish life in America will establish the true facts of that particular celebration.</p>
   <p>Anybody who read the reports of that solemn occasion must have been struck by the fact that, except for a few sections of veterans, there was not a single representative of the Polish population. The celebration, <pb facs="5423968_9_1677.jpg" n="2"/>instead of being an expression of tribute to Polish heroes, was rather a homage to the greatest enemy of the Polish spirit, Cardinal Mundelein, who on every occasion brutally treads upon our national pride.</p>
   <p>"Our true father," as Dziennik Chicagoski puts it in its issue of July 5, was "kind enough" to offer a place in the cemetery for the monument, for which the Polish community will ever cherish gratitude to the "Most Eminent Cardinal."</p>
   <p>A real hero of that day was Cardinal Mendelein, who, with the assistance of his Polish accomplices, clad in long, white, priestly robes of the Roman-Catholic Church, received all the honors which originally were destined for our dead heroes.</p>
   <p>These are facts which we presume to leave to an unbiased historian of Polish life in America, as evidence of how the Polish people here have been robbed of their most sacred sentiments by the pillars of the Roman-Catholic faith.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
