<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-27">Nov. 27, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">St. Adalbert Parish Stages November Manifestation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0788</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0788.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-27">Nov. 27, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">ST. ADALBERT PARISH STAGES NOVEMBER MANIFESTATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(The following correspondence has been received for publication in the Dziennik Chicagoski):</p>
   <p>On Sunday, November 24, a November Manifestation, commemorating the rise of the Poles against the Russian yoke, was staged at St. Adalbert Parish through the efforts of the parish societies connected with the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>The parish hall was completely filled, even in the galleries. The stage, gaily decorated, was occupied by the Reverend John Radziejewski, pastor of St. Adalbert Parish; Reverend Adolph Nowicki, pastor of St. Michael Parish; Clement J. Belinski, president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union; Albert Wachowski, trustee of the Polish Roman Catholic Union; officers of the Polish League, and presidents of the local societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0789.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Throughout the hall Polish flags were placed in conspicuous places, and the Stars and Stripes of the United States added an interesting contrast. Two military societies, St. Michael Krakuses and St. Florian Hussars, both national groups, were seated at each side of the large hall.</p>
   <p>At 8 P. M. Francis Czerwinski opened the celebration with a few sincere words, and thanked everyone for taking part in this national affair. Mr. Czerwinski then called upon the Reverend J. Radziejewski to act as chairman. The pastor delivered a short address and requested Leon Schultz to act as recording secretary.</p>
   <p>After a few preliminaries the entertainment started.</p>
   <p>The St. Adalbert Parish school children's choir was the first to appear on the stage, and rendered in fine style a beautiful hymn to Jesus Christ. At the close of the number the audience did not spare its applause. Credit for the fine work at this group should be given to the Sisters of Nazareth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0790.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Wachowski was the first speaker of the evening. He spoke of the history of Poland since the introduction of Christianity in the tenth century. The speaker recalled to the eagerly listening audience the time when the Swedes overran Poland and practically had victory in their grasp, but were frustrated at the walls of Czestochowa by one monk garbed in a white habit--and Poland arose anew. "And to this day," continued Mr. Wachowski, "the greatest protection and power lies in the Cross. Our best guardian is the Blessed Virgin," he concluded. Mr. Wachowski's speech was applauded enthusiastically.</p>
   <p>This speech was followed by a declamation entitled "A Polish Hussar", by Leon Merger, one of the students of the parish school, Another was delivered by John Fabisz. Both were delivered in good style, much to the enjoyment of the crowd.</p>
   <p>The second speaker of the evening was Anthony Polenc, who condemned the schism that began to crop up among the Poles. He was of the opinion that <pb facs="5423968_9_0791.jpg" n="4"/>this has no right to exist. Mr. Polenc reminded the audience of the Black Virgin of Czestochowa, who acts as a special guardian of the Polish nation. At the end he urged everyone to adhere closely to the teachings of Christ, for our forefathers have been faithful to His teachings for over a thousand years.</p>
   <p>After this speech the children's choir sang "Z Dymem Pozarow" (With Smoke and Fire), a Polish national song.</p>
   <p>At this point of the program Mr. Belinski took the rostrum. First of all he defended himself against the false charges spread about him by his enemies, who claim that he was responsible for the lack of unity among the Poles in the St. Adalbert Parish. He announced that as president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, which is an important organization, he must adhere to its constitution and to the oath that he took in public before the chaplain at the last convention.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0792.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Mr. Belinski then took up the reason for the frequent attacks on the clergy. He asserted that they are started by inexperienced persons or persons of ill will. Because of their love for creating disturbances, or because of self-interest, they raise questions about the financial reports of the parish, although they are the ones that never contributed a penny to the church. The speaker then denounced the entire schismatic movement, and referred to the moral value of these schismatics by citing as an example Kolaszewski-Rademacher and his well-known trick with the hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>In conclusion he pressed all the people to continue their belief in the Roman Catholic Church just as our predecessors did, and most certainly God will return to us our beloved fatherland. Applause and cheers greeted C. J. Belinski as he left the speaker's stand.</p>
   <p>The children's choir appeared on the stage again and sang "Patrz Mlodziencze" (Look, Young Man). This was followed by recitations by two school children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0793.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Miss Elisabeth Gasenewicz recited "Hymn of Sorrow," and Miss Anne Syka recited "To the Young". The audience did not spare their applause when they made their bows.</p>
   <p>The next speaker to take the stand was the Reverend A. Nowicki. He spoke about true patriotism and national sacrifices. As an example he recalled some accounts of the Poles who were sent into exile on the Siberian steppes, among whom were many priests.</p>
   <p>"In America," he said, "there are people and organizations that desire to take away from the priests the right to take part in national work, including participation in national manifestations. Nevertheless, if it were not for the priests our youth in America would long ago have been denationalized."</p>
   <p>In his talk on Poland, and what it means to be a Pole, the Reverend Nowicki added: "We should preserve our souvenirs, our customs, our native tongue, and our faith, which was paid for dearly in blood. Solidarity and harmony <pb facs="5423968_9_0794.jpg" n="7"/>are prime essentials within our ranks. Our enemies dispatch spies and dissenters. These alone disturb our peace and sow discord."</p>
   <p>He concluded his speech by reading a letter of the Reverend John Radowicz, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish in Baltimore, Maryland, to the Polish National Alliance. As he left the rostrum the audience paid him a tribute with unsparing applause.</p>
   <p>The children's choir appeared for the last time, and sang a Polish song entitled "Czem Jestem" (What Am I), after which the local pastor thanked the assemblage for its co-operation and attendance.</p>
   <p>In conclusion the audience sang "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland), and then the children sang "Jeszcze Polska Nie Zginela" (Poland Is Not Yet Lost).</p>
   <p>The music for this affair was supplied by Michael Susala. Mention should <pb facs="5423968_9_0795.jpg" n="8"/>be made of Mr. Susala's orchestra, which gave beautiful and stirring renditions of Polish national airs.</p>
   <p>Leon Schultz, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
