<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-07">Apr. 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Program for Kosciusko Manifestation in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0927</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0927.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-07">Apr. 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">PROGRAM FOR KOSCIUSKO MANIFESTATION IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As announced by us yesterday, the program for the Kosciusko manifestation is already complete.</p>
   <p>As late as March 30, 1894, the program committee in charge of the Kosciusko manifestation met at the office of Zgoda for the purpose of working out the details of the program. Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek presided and K. Sawicki acted as secretary.</p>
   <p>The program was proposed by Reverend E. Sedlaczek, and after an exhaustive discussion it was accepted in the following form:</p>
   <p>May 3, 1894, should be proclaimed a Polish national holiday.</p>
   <p>On that memorable anniversary of the Polish Constitution of the Third of May, we should commemorate two events and honor them by a national holiday and a great <pb facs="5423968_9_0928.jpg" n="2"/>public manifestation.</p>
   <p>The day will begin with solemn church services at all Polish churches in Chicago, at eight o'clock in the morning.</p>
   <p>At 10 A. M., the church societies in the various Polish parishes will march downtown.</p>
   <p>From 12 noon to 2 P. M., the State Militia and the Polish militia and the Polish military societies will parade along the lake front, in view of all Polonia. There a short address will be made in English, in which the purpose of the manifestation will be explained and the participants will be invited to the hall of Battery D.</p>
   <p>At 2 P. M. the exercises will begin at the hall.</p>
   <p>Music will be supplied by Thomas' Orchestra, consisting of twenty-five musicians.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0929.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The opening address will be delivered in Polish by Sigmund Schmidt, chairman of the program committee, and in English by [K.] Bielinski, vice-president of the committee.</p>
   <p>The next function will be the appointment of the chairman of the demonstration and the presentation of the guests.</p>
   <p>The following persons will be presented as guests: Governor Altgeld, Senator Palmer, Mayor Hopkins, Messrs. Jerzmanowski, Finerty, Kennan, Enander, and Stevens.</p>
   <p>The following persons will be asked to deliver speeches in English: Helinski, the censor of the Polish National Alliance, and Peter Kiolbassa, honorary president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union in America. Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek will deliver the main Polish speech, suitable to the occasion. Mrs. Helen Modrzejewski will be asked to give a speech or a recitation. Besides these, there will be presented the most important incidents in Kosciusko's life, namely, (1) Kosciusko's Oath at Crakow Square, (2) Battle of Raclawice, (3) Battle of Saratoga, in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0930.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The program will be diversified by three orchestra numbers and three choir numbers. The choir numbers will be rendered by the Polish Singers Alliance and the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish Choir, which will be invited by their representatives.</p>
   <p>At the end, a general protest against the partition of Poland, and a separate protest against the outrages committed by the Russians against the Poles at Kroze, Poland, will be made. Finally, Kosciusko's oath will be repeated and "God Save Poland" will be sung by all participants.</p>
   <p>The committee has decided to order ten thousand badges at three cents each. Five thousand of these badges will be sold to the public at ten cents each a week before the manifestation, and the other five thousand will be given free to those participants of the manifestation who contribute collectively, in groups or societies, the fifteen-cent special assessment for defraying the expenses of the manifestation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0931.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This program was accepted unanimously by the committee last night. We must admit that it is a very practical program. It will make our manifestation very imposing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
