<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-06-18">June 18, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">John Iii Sobieski Celebration at Pulaski Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0640</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0640.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-06-18">June 18, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN III SOBIESKI CELEBRATION AT PULASKI HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The two-hundredth anniversary of the death of King John III Sobieski was celebrated yesterday at Pulaski hall and attracted a large audience.</p>
   <p>J. Napieralski opened the celebration at nine o'clock in the evening, calling on Adam Blaszczynski and S. Bytonski to act as chairman and secretary respectively.</p>
   <p>When the curtain was raised, the first thing to meet the eye was a bust of our great hero-king, with black crepe decorations. Standing guard in the background were the Polish soldiers of several societies, namely, Soldiers of Saint Casimir, Saint George Krakus, Saint Onufry Group Number 322 of the Catholic Order of Foresters, and the Pulaski Volunteers of Saint Adalbert Parish.</p>
   <p>The Moniuszko Choir and the newly organized Paderewski Choral Society, directed <pb facs="5423968_9_0641.jpg" n="2"/>by Mr. Hensel, sang "John III."</p>
   <p>Then Casimir Zychlinski addressed the audience. After describing the geneology of the Zolkiewski, Danilowicz, and Sobieski families and their various branches, to which our famous hero and defender traced his ancestry, the speaker related the heroic deeds and historic background of King John III Sobieski.</p>
   <p>The speech, beautiful and all-embracing, was rewarded with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>Nine-year-old Joe Malkiewicz recited nicely. The two choirs combined to sing "Pamietne Lechity" (Famous Poles). Little Kurzawska--a seven-year-old girl--recited all alone and did it splendidly.</p>
   <p>Other speakers of the evening were Bobowski and Jarzebski, who spoke on the meaning of the celebration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0642.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the end, J. Napieralski appealed to the audience to make a donation for the crumbling Pulaski hall, and the women present collected $6.21.</p>
   <p>After the singing, a live tableau representing Sobieski was shown. At the end of the program, the audience sang "God Save Poland".</p>
   <p>Other speakers were to have appeared on the program, but they were unable to come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
