<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-18">July 18, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Centenary of the Battle at Dubienka</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1060</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1060.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-18">July 18, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">CENTENARY OF THE BATTLE AT DUBIENKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A service commemorating the centenary anniversary of the battle at Dubienka was held yesterday, July 17, at the Aurora Turner Hall. In the presence of a rather large audience, the meeting was opened by Mr. M. Osuch who called upon Judge M. A. La Buy to be chairman of the meeting. Mr. Osuch gave a short but beautiful speech; Judge La Buy presented the speakers. The following persons spoke: in English, Mr. Carter H. Harrison, who in an eloquent and lengthy speech gained the hearts of his listeners because he lauded the deeds of the national hero, Kosciusko, displaying an extraordinary sympathy and an amazing knowledge of the facts. In Polish, there was the editor of the Telegraf, Mr. H. Nagiel, who in a colorful and comprehensive manner presented the history of the Poles from the time of the declaration of the Constitution of May 3, until the end of the battle at Dubienka; again in English, Judge Richard S. Tuthill, who raised the Poles above <pb facs="5423968_9_1061.jpg" n="2"/>all others as lovers of freedom; he expressed the hope that they would regain their freedom and that even in Europe better conditions would be realized, and placing Kosciusko beside Washington, he asked that he be permitted to be present at the unveiling of the tomb of this hero. Finally, Dr. Casimer Midowicz spoke, encouraging unity and more solid action in the lines in our present struggle against our numerous enemies, a struggle which although bloodless, is no less important. All the speakers in closing urged us to contribute to the fund for the erection of a tomb for Kosciusko. It was then decided to hold a voluntary collection for that purpose from among those present. What did this contribution amount to--that was not announced; as far as we have heard, it brought about fifty-six dollars. The secretaries of the meeting were Messrs. W. Karlowski and M. Drzymala.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
