<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-10-22">Oct. 22, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Comments of the American Press on Our Participation in the Columbus Day Celebration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1031</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1031.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-10-22">Oct. 22, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">COMMENTS OF THE AMERICAN PRESS ON OUR PARTICIPATION IN THE COLUMBUS DAY CELEBRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the more important results of our participation in Columbus Day was the attention the Polish groups received from the American public at large.</p>
   <p>The local American newspapers, whose interests and principles are varied, recognized the part we played in the parade and devoted many interesting articles to the activities of the Polish groups during the celebration. Some of the articles are written in a friendly vein, even if the information they intend to convey is rather inaccurate at times. This lack of accuracy, of course, may be attributed to the fact that newspapers articles are written <pb facs="5423968_9_1032.jpg" n="2"/>in a hurry so that they may be ready before the deadline for publication. The main inaccuracies are in connection with the number of people that took part in the parade and with the route we followed. The split of the Polish societies contributed no small share toward getting the reporters confused. This explains why they failed to notice to what particular division our societies or organizations belonged. All in all, however, most of the newspapers, especially those supporting the Democratic platform, had a word of praise for the Poles, their vari-colored uniforms, and their ideals.</p>
   <p>The following are excerpts of articles that appeared in practically all of the Chicago newspapers in connection with our participation on Thursday's Columbus Day parade:</p>
   <p>The Evening News writes as follows about the sixth subdivision of the second <pb facs="5423968_9_1033.jpg" n="3"/>main division:</p>
   <p>"The Polish National Alliance was next in line. This was one of the largest organizations in the parade. It was formed of Polish societies and numbered five thousand persons. The dress was very simple, but the four-cornered caps of blue velvet and a strap of grey lambskin were an outstanding feature. Many were in full Polish regalia; the marshals astride horses wore beautiful colored trousers and caps. In the parade were seventeen [sic] bands, numbering three hundred men. The Polish division was headed by Marshal M. Budzinski, who was assisted by A. Lisztewnik and W. Wleklinski. Behind them followed the orchestras and later Polish soldiers in full uniform astride horses; these were followed by the officers of the societies and then the members."</p>
   <p>This same paper mentions Peter Kiolbassa, who was at the head of the Polish Catholic division:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1034.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"....The combined forces of the Polish Catholic adult societies, numbering eight thousand people, carried off the palm of precedence with their regalia and great effect."</p>
   <p>The Chicago Evening Post takes note of the second and third divisions of Polish societies and makes the following comment:</p>
   <p>"....The societies from the various Polish parishes were the most diversified groups of this great division. It is doubtful whether many persons, especially those outside the Polish parishes, know how many Polish people there are in Chicago. There were over eight thousand in the parade, according to estimates; but the proximity of the men as they marched abreast from one side of the sidewalk to the other, makes the number appear much greater. Societies from the great St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish formed along Lake and adjoining streets, and when they marched through Lake Street it seemed as if an army had arisen <pb facs="5423968_9_1035.jpg" n="5"/>out of nowhere.....This particular group marched twenty abreast with infinite exactness. These Polish societies were escorted from their parish by cadets, boys garbed in beautiful blue costumes of full military measures. There were two companies. Behind them marched the Polish Uhlans, who were also in full military regalia and marched like the best trained soldiers. The Knights of St. Martin and St. Joseph, the latter from Lake View, followed. They presented a picturesque sight in their semimilitary uniforms decked with gold. On the whole there were about sixty societies, and those that did not wear uniforms were also striking to the eyes in their satin caps, which were similar to university commencement caps."</p>
   <p>This paper was a bit confused as regards the societies of the Polish National Alliance and said that the number of their members in the parade was three hundred. As a matter of fact, the number was three thousand.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Evening Journal treated the Polish National Alliance and Polish <pb facs="5423968_9_1036.jpg" n="6"/>Roman Catholic Union societies as a whole.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's Herald followed along the same lines, except that it discussed the Polish National Alliance group in an editorial, as follows:</p>
   <p>"The sixth subdivision of the second division presented an unusual contrast alongside the Scotch group. The Polish group was composed of four thousand one hundred members of the Polish National Alliance. But this group, compared to the tall and stately Scotch, seemed dwarfed. However, from the military angle, the Poles surpassed the Scotchmen in number and in regalia. They presented themselves as ideal soldiers, especially those who were garbed in the impressive uniforms of the Uhlans. All those that participated in the parade, soldiers as well as civilians, wore the caps so famous the world over as a Polish national dress."</p>
   <p>The Republican mouthpiece, the Tribune, is less generous with its comment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1037.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>It compares the Polish sokols in an unpleasant way with the German and Czech gymnastic groups (the sokols marched with the Polish National Alliance group), and it does not mention the societies of the Polish National Alliance at all. As regards the Polish Catholic division, this is what the Tribune says: "All the members of Polish societies that did not wear uniforms wore special caps which were popular in the Polish army when Poland was free, independent, and fortunate."</p>
   <p>The Times treats the Polish groups in general.</p>
   <p>The German paper, Illinois Staats-Zeitung, considers the Polish participation truly outstanding. "The main Polish contingent," it says, "was formed of societies in uniform and was supported by groups wearing no uniform." The paper writes further:</p>
   <p>"All the members wore the same kind of Polish caps. These caps, made of <pb facs="5423968_9_1038.jpg" n="8"/>satin with a strap of grey lambskin, were of a four-cornered design and presented a splendid picture in the parade. Members of Polish military groups, especially, were present in large numbers....."</p>
   <p>In connection with the uniformed members of military societies belonging to the Polish National Alliance, the Illinois Staats-Zeitung goes on to say:"....in fact, the Poles conducted themselves nobly."</p>
   <p>Finally, the Inter Ocean mentions the Polish Catholic societies as follows:</p>
   <p>"....The Poles were led by a divisional marshal, Joseph Paszkiewicz. Eighteen marshals and twenty other leaders astride horses led the entire Polish division. All the marshals wore the American colors on their right arms.....They were followed by companies of Polish Cadets, Uhlans, and Guards [of the Queen of <pb facs="5423968_9_1039.jpg" n="9"/>Poland]. The Poles marched to their place on Lake Street; along the sidewalks, stairs, doors, and windows were throngs of people shouting and waving handkerchiefs at the passing Polish societies.....The cadets were spread out and carried rifles strapped to their shoulders. They occupied the entire width of the street and forced many people who were crowded along the curb to move back to the sidewalk. The people did not seem to mind the pushing, for they witnessed a magnificent sight....."</p>
   <p>Such were the comments made about the Poles who took part in the Columbus Day celebration, Thursday, October 20. Outside of some inaccurate statements, the articles as a whole bring honor to the Poles. It would have been a hundred times better, however, if the Polish societies had been represented by one solid group, as originally planned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
