<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1914-05-07">May 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Poles Launch Plans for Nation-Wide Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1914-05-07">May 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">POLES LAUNCH PLANS FOR NATION-WIDE CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Plans for a nation-wide celebration of the centennial of the congress of Vienna were launched in Chicago yesterday to include 1,500 Polish churches throughout the United States and various Polish organizations in the different states. The meeting, at which it was decided to make Chicago the center of the celebration, was held in the general assembly room of the Polish National Council of America, 984 Milwaukee Ave., which also is to be the central headquarters for the centennial committees which are to be named within the next ten days.</p>
   <p>The movement for the centennial celebration is launched by the Polish National Council of America, which represents the leading Polish fraternal organizations and various parishes and associations from all parts of the country. The Rt. Rev. Paul P. Rhode, D.D., auxiliary bishop and vicar general of the diocese of Chicago, and Rt. Rev. Edward Kojlowski, auxiliary bishop and vicar general of the diocese of Milwaukee, together with the Polish Catholic Priests' Association of America, will be asked to lead in the movement of the centennial celebration according to the action taken at yesterday's meeting.</p>
   <p>According to the plans discussed yesterday, celebrations in all the schools as well as monster mass-meetings and demonstrations of citizens in all the large <pb facs="5423968_9_0561.jpg" n="2"/>cities of the United States, are to be important factors of the celebration. According to the announcement of the officers of the various organizations which launched the centennial celebration, the demonstration is being arranged to remind the world of the broken pledges and acts in connection with the taking away from Poland of her independence, rights, language, freedom, and possessions which the powers of Europe had promised to respect, safeguard, and protect when they signed the acts of that congress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
