<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-10">Dec. 10, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">November Demonstration Staged at St. Casimir Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0742</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0742.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-10">Dec. 10, 1895</date>.
<title level="a"> NOVEMBER DEMONSTRATION STAGED AT ST. CASIMIR PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Although late in its arrival, we are printing the following article relative to the November demonstration staged by the parishioners of St. Casimir Parish on December 1.)</p>
   <p>As in other Polish parishes of Chicago, our parish [St. Casimir Parish] has also staged a November demonstration [a commemoration of the uprising in November, 1830, against Russian persecution]. Although our parish has been in existence a couple of years, this is our first occasion to celebrate this memorable event.</p>
   <p>On the very day marking the uprising, November 29, our pastor, the Reverend Furman, celebrated Requiem Mass for the souls of our valiant brothers who have made the supreme sacrifice for the liberation of their country. The exercise was staged Sunday, December 1.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0743.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The parish hall was filled to such an extent that many were turned away.</p>
   <p>Andrew Belinski, president of the program committee, opened the festivities. After a short speech he called upon the Reverend Albert Furman to preside as chairman. As Reverend Furman rose to take the stand the audience greeted him with great acclaim. Max Adamowicz was selected as recording secretary.</p>
   <p>The initial number on the program was the singing of national airs by the St. Casimir Parish Choir. That the audience was pleased with the renditions was evidenced by its response.</p>
   <p>The declamation delivered by young T. Bena was impressive. Songs by the children's group won generous applause, as well as the recitations of the students F. Pieczynski and C. Kosinski.</p>
   <p>Miss R. Durszlak and Miss B. Piotrowska gave charming declamations, followed <pb facs="5423968_9_0744.jpg" n="3"/>by more singing from the children's and parish choirs. F. Wojciechowski recited a beautiful Polish poem.</p>
   <p>All the above numbers were well received, as was the reading given by B. Klarkowski. This was followed by more singing by the two choirs mentioned above.</p>
   <p>Clement J. Belinski, president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, made a stirring speech appropriate to the occasion. He reviewed the accomplishments of Poland and recalled to the audience the duties of the Polish people to the fatherland, and the promises we made to the priests as we left for America, that we would be faithful to our religion and our country. He appealed to the people to retain in their hearts the spark for these two ideals.</p>
   <p>His speech was continually interrupted by warm applause.</p>
   <p>Once again the children's choir appeared on the stage, but this time to sing in <pb facs="5423968_9_0745.jpg" n="4"/>English. Then Albert Wachowski took the stand. He spoke about the losses of those that came to this country and urged everyone to work in behalf of the national cause. Generous applause was the speaker's award for his inspiring words. The songs of the children's choir and the declamation of Mr. Hojnacki were a pleasing interlude.</p>
   <p>The next speaker to take the stand was Mr. Marcinkowski, who urged the people to strive for unity and harmony. He was followed by more singing from the children's group, and then the Reverend A. Furman made a speech.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Furman's speech was the most impressive of the evening. Having heard some talk in opposition to parochial schools the other day, the pastor came strongly to the support of the parish school. Later he spoke about the duty of the Poles toward the fatherland. He said that we came to this country as strangers and, although we did not have much money, we survived. Not only that, but we have managed to procure work, save money, and carve out a place <pb facs="5423968_9_0746.jpg" n="5"/>for ourselves in this free country.</p>
   <p>"How have we done these things?" the priest asked. "Because we have stuck together and adhered to our religious principles. That is why we must continue the work, for with it victory will be ours. Do not listen to evil influences, be faithful to the God of our forefathers; work, strive to better your standing, and victory and not defeat will be ours," concluded Reverend Furman.</p>
   <p>The audience caught every word of this inspiring speech. Loud applause followed the speech as a tribute to the pastor.</p>
   <p>Before the speaker left the stand he brought up the problem of the Polish Immigration Home in New York City. A collection for its support netted $5.76. The money was sent to New York.</p>
   <p>In closing, Reverend Furman urged everyone to sing the well-known Polish hymn <pb facs="5423968_9_0747.jpg" n="6"/>"Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland), after which the audience left for home.</p>
   <p>The undersigned, in the name of the program committee, wishes to extend thanks to the Reverend Furman, the venerable sisters, school children, and guest speakers, namely, B. Klarkowski, C. J. Belinski, and A. Wachowski, and also all other speakers, performers, and singers, and the audience for their splendid co-operation and attendance.</p>
   <p>Max Adamowicz,</p>
   <p>recording secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
