<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-30">Dec. 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Voice of Theophilus Stan</title><title level="a" type="sub">Revision of the Books of the Central Committee of the Polish National Alliance Disproves the Assertions of Zgoda</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0242</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0242.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-30">Dec. 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE VOICE OF THEOPHILUS STAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Revision of the Books of the Central Committee of the Polish National Alliance Disproves the Assertions of Zgoda</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Editor:</p>
   <p>I am very sorry that I have to speak out publicly in a matter which should be settled within the organization of which I am a member and officer. It grieves me that I am forced to resort to having this matter, which has unfortunately been brought to public light and which should not have been discussed by Zgoda, brought before the public in the columns of Dziennik Chicagoski. Circumstances over which I have no control have compelled me to take this action.</p>
   <p>As one of the revisers of the Central Committee's books I discovered important inaccuracies in the books during my quarterly checkup. When I called attention <pb facs="5423968_9_0243.jpg" n="2"/>to this fact without any results, especially when my name was forged on the statement published in Zgoda, I felt it my duty to lay this matter before the Chicago delegates of the Ninth Diet, who, according to the constitution of the Polish National Alliance, Article 5, Section V, have a right to act on such matters until the next diet. A meeting of the Chicago delegates was called by me on December 22, and at that time I briefly brought up this matter. The meeting resulted in the creation of a committee which was directed to call a larger meeting of the delegates. As things stood, I awaited further developments.</p>
   <p>My waiting brought me unexpected results, namely, the attack against me by Zgoda. I feel obliged to reply to this assault, which twisted and distorted the facts. Harboring no hope of ever having this answer, even if it were of the utmost importance, placed in Zgoda, I turn beseechingly to the editorial department of Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0244.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following is my reply:</p>
   <p>Zgoda, in its issue of December 28, number 52, publicly accuses me of "secretive intrigues." This accusation was a result of my officially announcing to the delegates of the Ninth Diet at the meeting of December 22 that my signature on the third quarterly statement of this year was forged.</p>
   <p>S. Nicki; editor of Zgoda, attempts to make it appear that I permitted him to sign my name. I call any such assertions false. I am too careful a businessman to permit anyone to sign my name.</p>
   <p>At any rate, it was not on November 8, as Mr. Nicki asserts, but on Monday, November 7, 1892, at 10 A. M., that I entered the headquarters of the Polish National Alliance and said these words: "I have finished making an audit of <pb facs="5423968_9_0245.jpg" n="4"/>the books." I left shortly afterwards. As I was passing Sawicki's Dairy, which is a few steps from the offices of the Polish National Alliance, Mr. Nicki called after me. I stopped. From a distance, Mr. Nicki asked me: "Can the statement be published?" I told him: "This matter does not concern me," and I continued homeward.</p>
   <p>These are the actual facts. Was this permitting my name to be forged on the statement? Let any person give his opinion.</p>
   <p>It is not difficult to understand why I did not say the words which Mr. Nicki asserts I did. This can be confirmed by my six-page report, which definitely makes it clear that I could not have said the words in question. I cited twenty reasons in the report why I could not acknowledge it, for the books of the Polish National Alliance are not in order. This report was dated November 6 and sent to the censor, prior to any words with Mr. Nicki. These facts can be found in my records.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0246.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In order to give an understanding of why I did not affix my name to the quarterly statement, I will cite some of the discrepancies:</p>
   <p>1. Lack of proof that a receipt for $250 was received from Mr. Sajka, a beneficiary, of St. Paul, Minnesota.</p>
   <p>2. Lack of proof that S. Szymanski, a beneficiary, of Chicago, received $500.</p>
   <p>3. Walter Kucewicz received an a conto death benefit of $100 for Waclaw Kucewicz instead of Wladislaw Kucewicz.</p>
   <p>4. The $500 death benefit for the late Jacob Kowalik, alias Smith, was paid. I did not find any definite proof that Smith, who was found dead in the streets of Toledo, Ohio, was actually Kowalik.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0247.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>5. Some of the receipts for the payment of death benefits, namely, nos. 33, 35, 39, 40, 41, 42, 44, 45, 47, and 49 bear no date.</p>
   <p>6. There is lack of proof that the $5.00 paid to a committee for the purchase of wardrobes was ever received. Who had the right to pay out this money?</p>
   <p>8. (sic) The reserve fund from September 1888 to the end of May 1892, that is, for three and one-half years, amounts to $7,653.58. In May of 1889 there was no income for the reserve fund. Is this possible?</p>
   <p>On the whole, the condition of the funds is not very clear. In view of the incompetency of the present general secretary I am in no position to determine how much should be in the reserve fund, entrance fee fund, dues, death benefits, supplement, fees for Zgoda, badges, and other funds.</p>
   <p>The same holds true of the books of Zgoda. It is impossible to determine how <pb facs="5423968_9_0248.jpg" n="7"/>much was loaned, donated, paid out for work, earned from advertisements, etc. The same holds true for the Polish National Fund. How many postage stamps did it receive from the Polish National Alliance, including paper, circulars, etc., and how should this be balanced--as a donation or a loan?</p>
   <p>I have been asking for an inventory of the Polish National Alliance and the Zgoda and in every report my request was repeated, but thus far my requests have been to no avail. To this must be added the fact that the Central Committee does not want to recognize the members of the Revision Commission as officials and does not wish to divulge any of its transactions.</p>
   <p>S. F. Satalecki, president of the Polish National Alliance, has not responded to any of my letters or notices in the reports, and seems unwilling to supply the information I requested.</p>
   <p>A. Mallek, general secretary, has denied our right to revise all the books <pb facs="5423968_9_0249.jpg" n="8"/>and receipts. He expresses himself unpleasantly and demands that I leave his office whenever I appear. This fact can be substantiated by an incident that occurred at a meeting of the Central Committee on September 5, 1892. Mr. Mallek, in the presence of all the officers, virtually tore a book of his out of my hands and rudely forbade me to examine it--then walked away whistling. The Central Committee viewed this conduct calmly.</p>
   <p>To this I must add that, whenever I made quarterly statements for the first half of 1892, I found many errors which I noted in my reports, demanding better management of the books of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>The following is a list of some of the things I pointed out in the second quarterly report for 1892:</p>
   <p>1. I cited eight persons,with their addresses, who have advertisements of long <pb facs="5423968_9_0250.jpg" n="9"/>standing in Zgoda but are not accounted for in the books.</p>
   <p>2. There were several who have been suspended from the books, but despite this their advertisements have continued to appear in Zgoda</p>
   <p>3. How much money should actually be paid Zgoda for work, announcements and advertisements--no one knows!</p>
   <p>The following commissions were paid:</p>
   <p>4.
<table><row><cell>January 25, 1892</cell><cell>$0.50</cell></row><row><cell>January 27, 1892</cell><cell>1.15</cell></row><row><cell>February 3, 1892</cell><cell>.25</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>$1.90</cell></row></table>
</p>
   <p>Who received these amounts and for what? There were no receipts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0251.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>5. Some of the members of the Polish National Alliance pay $2 for announcements, while others pay $5, $6, and $8. Why?</p>
   <p>6. Receipt No. 25 for death benefit did not contain the signature of the president of the lodge; receipt No. 126 the signature of the secretary was missing, etc., etc.</p>
   <p>In the first quarter report I pointed out, among many other things, the following:</p>
   <p>1. Receipt no. 2 for a death benefit has not been signed by the secretary of the lodge.</p>
   <p>2. Receipt no. 3 for a death benefit has been signed by the beneficiary, but not by the president or secretary of the lodge.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0252.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>3. The books of Zgoda have been found to be in very poor order.</p>
   <p>To all these I must add one more thing. The statement for the first quarter of 1892 was signed by the revisers and balanced. After its publication I found that some of the amounts were changed; there was a difference of $300.30. I immediately went to the offices of the Polish National Alliance and brought this to the attention of Mr. Mallek, who said that it was not his fault, but that of Mr. Nicki, who rechecked the amounts--as it turned out, erroneously. I demanded a correction was announced.</p>
   <p>These are the facts that may be found in the reports, which are in the hands of the censor. These facts are the best evidence as to why I did not sign the third quarter report for 1892, which was not in accordance with the documents or accounts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0253.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>This matter, which casts a dark light upon the Polish National Alliance, has been in my mind for a long time and I have wanted to bring it to the attention of all the members. But I have been restrained by the hope of an improvement in the handling of the accounts--and the fear of the unpleasantness of publicity. Realizing that the improvement was not forthcoming, while in the meantime my name was deliberately signed to my report and published by the Central Committee, I called a meeting of the delegates in order to present to them the facts. This resulted in a public announcement by Zgoda about the situation. Under such circumstances there was nothing left for me to do but to make known the actual facts, for the good of the Polish National Alliance. This is what the undersigned has done.</p>
   <p>Theophilus Stan, Delegate of the Ninth Diet, and president of the Revision Commission</p>
   <p>(Note by the editor: These matters concerning the activity of the Central <pb facs="5423968_9_0254.jpg" n="13"/>Committee of the Polish National Alliance relative to T. Stan's statement were tactlessly made public by Zgoda yesterday. Zgoda was the first to speak in this situation. Although we have always believed and still believe in a just settlement of the internal affairs of the organizations, today, when this incident has been brought to light by Zgoda, journalistic duty does not permit us to deny an opportunity of speaking in this matter to T. Stan, president of the Revision Commission, which examines the books of the Polish National Alliance.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
