<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-09-19">Sept. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Celebration of the 209th Anniversary of the Siege of Vienna</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1053</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1053.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-09-19">Sept. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATION OF THE 209th ANNIVERSARY OF THE SIEGE OF VIENNA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 209th anniversary of the siege of Vienna [by Sobieski] was celebrated yesterday at the New Polish Hall, Bradley and Noble Streets, by the Poles of Chicago. The affair was arranged by the John III Sobieski Society Number 1. Although the audience was not as large as expected, the celebration was a success.</p>
   <p>The program was arranged in two parts--one devoted to speeches, songs, and declamations and the other to a drama.</p>
   <p>At the opening of the program, Mr. Szczesny Zahajkiewicz and Mr. L. Szopinski were appointed chairman and secretary respectively.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1054.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Zahajkiewicz explained to the audience that Peter Kiolbassa, the city treasurer, could not come because he had to attend a Democratic rally in Buffalo. In his stead, Mr. S. Zahajkiewicz made the opening address, in which he related the story of John III, one of Poland's greatest heroes. His description of the siege of Vienna by the former ruler of Poland was dramatic. He continued this historical sketch by stating that the siege of Vienna by the Polish troops was successful in safeguarding Christianity in Europe and that this should be our duty today. At the end of his speech, Mr. Zahajkiewicz praised the John III Sobieski Society for keeping alive the memory of this great Polish hero by arranging annual programs in his honor.</p>
   <p>The boys of St. Stanislaus Kostka School sang songs appropriate for the occasion after the chairman left the rostrum.</p>
   <p>Boleslaw Klarkowski was the second speaker of the evening. He also spoke of the life of John III. After a general resume of events during the earlier <pb facs="5423968_9_1055.jpg" n="3"/>years of the Polish nation, Mr. Klarkowski talked about the many battles this Polish king fought for his country. The verbal picture he painted of the siege of Vienna moved the audience. He ended his talk by urging his listeners to follow in the footsteps of this chivalrous king of Poland, saying that by so doing they would not only pay tribute to him but safeguard their religion and nationality.</p>
   <p>More songs by the children's choir followed. A verse, "John III," was recited by J. Kopczynski, one of the schoolboys.</p>
   <p>Reverend V. Barzynski, who was scheduled to talk at the close of the first part of the program, was unable to appear because of an unexpected trip to St. Louis. The gap left by his absence was filled with a second speech by the chairman.</p>
   <p>During the second part of the program the audience was entertained with an unusual village play, "King Sobek, Match-Maker," written by Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, the chairman. This musical comedy, which was the highlight of <pb facs="5423968_9_1056.jpg" n="4"/>the evening, was presented by Polish amateurs from the parish. Miss Zukowska and Miss Chlebowska played the leading roles, and the masculine talent was almost outmatched by these young ladies. The entire program was well received by the audience.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
