<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. IV, No. 46,
<date when="1930-11-13">Nov. 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A Voluntary Servitude</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_1631</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1631.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. IV, No. 46,
<date when="1930-11-13">Nov. 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A VOLUNTARY SERVITUDE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to the information given in the Roman papers, Prelate Kokoszny, the delegate of Bishop Hlond of Poland, came to the United States to investigate the religious status of our immigration, and also to uplift it spiritually. They called it "The Great Solicitude" of the cardinal for the souls of Polish immigrants.</p>
   <p>But we see it in a different light. The bishop's delegate did not come here to find out in what condition is the soul of our workingman, merchant or artisan, but to learn how fat is his pocketbook and how much can he squeeze out of it for the Vatican king, who must have lost heavily on the American stock market, just as any other worldly speculator. Someone must cover these losses; naturally no one else but the faithful subjects frightened by the Roman hell.</p>
   <p>One of those "spiritual delegates" of the Vatican, from Poland, Prelate Adamski, left America some time ago with a full pocketbook; for that he was made a bishop.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1632.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Hundreds of Polish workmen placed their savings in his hands and now they are cursing him, but the Vatican does not care.</p>
   <p>For their hundreds of dollars they may get enough to buy one meal or at the most to live one day in some cheap room full of bedbugs.</p>
   <p>The Vatican rewards very liberally its "spiritual collectors" of money, especially of American dollars, which have a special sanctifying power in the Vatican palace.</p>
   <p>However, Prelate Rakoszy must have another and very important mission. And that mission is to fix firmly the voluntary bondage of the Polish immigration under Irish and German spiritual masters, for the Vatican has learned that the Polish immigration in America is getting restless, in fact, it is opening its eyes and is beginning to see the truth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1633.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our immigration began to realize its degradation to which it was subjected by the "Roman hypnotizer" in cassocks, who have persuaded the Polish people to believe that they, the priests, are higher and better beings, who possess the exclusive rights to issue permits for admission to heaven or hell. They scoff at God and our honest people. The Irish and German agents of the Vatican, dressed in black cassocks, abuse our Polish people with impunity. What about it, Prelate Rokoszy?</p>
   <p>According to Dziennik Zwiazkowy, Prelate Rokoszy, in his speech at the celebration of "The miracle on the Vistula," advised our Polish immigrants to obey humbly the foreign bishops because "they would not obey their own, anyhow."</p>
   <p>In other words, Prelate Rokoszy encourages the Polish immigrants to submit themselves as servants and slaves of Irish and German lords and church tyrants. Will the Poles remain ignorant forever is a question.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_1634.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>More and more of them are casting away the fetters of bondage, and are enrolling under the banner of the Free Christian Polish National Church, whose bishops are Polish and the Poles obey and respect them. The Vatican tyrant who is playing the role of the representative of God is alarmed by such actions of the Poles in America; therefore he sends his agents here for the purpose us in keeping us in submission and draw profits for himself.</p>
   <p>Poles! It is high time to do away with the Roman religious hypocrisy and worship the Lord in our Polish National temples.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
