<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-18">May 18, 1918</date><title level="a">Beautiful Badges for Parade on June 2nd</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0406</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0406.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-18">May 18, 1918</date><title level="a">BEAUTIFUL BADGES FOR PARADE ON JUNE 2ND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Through the efforts of the committee in charge of arranging for a great parade to the Kosciusko monument [in Humboldt Park] on June 2, beautiful and effective badges have been made. These badges ought to be ordered now by [Polish National Alliance] Councils, societies, Polish Roman Catholic Union groups, Falcon nests, and other groups participating in the parade, in order to avoid later misunderstandings.</p>
   <p>There are badges of two kinds, one for men and one for women. The badges are made in the form of a butterfly, the wings of which consist of the American flag on one side and the Polish flag on the other. In the center are pictures of Wilson and Kosciusko, both fighters for the freedom of nations, and under these is the appropriate inscription, "For the freedom of nations".</p>
   <p>The badges may be purchased only for cash; this is the purpose of simplifying <pb facs="5423968_9_0407.jpg" n="2"/>accounts when the parade is over and avoiding many misunderstandings, complaints, and so on, which could arise later. Badges may be purchased from Edmund Misienkz, 1166 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>During the course of the celebration on June 2, the sale of badges will be conducted by girls wearing red arm bands on the sleeves of their dresses. The public is hereby asked not to purchase any sort of badges from anyone else.</p>
   <p>The income from the sale of badges has not yet been assigned to any particular cause, this will be decided upon at the next meeting of the committee in charge.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, it should be added that these beautiful badges were supplied by B. Majchrowkz, well-known member of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
