<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-27">Apr. 27, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">St. Stanislaus Kostka College Holds Exercises in Honor of Kosciusko</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0901</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0901.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-27">Apr. 27, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA COLLEGE HOLDS EXERCISES IN HONOR OF KOSCIUSKO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The St. Stanislaus Kostka College, which is directed by the Resurrection Fathers, held exercises in honor of Kosciusko last night at the school hall.</p>
   <p>The large hall was filled to capacity by school children from St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish. Many adults, mostly parents who desired to see the talents of the students of St. Stansilaus Kostka College, were also present.</p>
   <p>The program was interesting and diversified. The exercises were opened by "O Sanctisima," which was sung by the College's choir. A. Piasecki, one of the students, delivered the welcoming speech. He greeted the guests and exalted the significance of the exercises. This was followed by an orchestra number. Four boys--Edward Jarecki, J. Kopczynski, W. Zenger, and J. Mucha-- <pb facs="5423968_9_0902.jpg" n="2"/>recited a beautiful poem, "Tys' Niesmiertelna" (Thou Art Immortal). The recitation was so impressive that many persons were moved to tears. A little boy, J. Mucha, recited splendidly and with confidence a patriotic poem, "Syn Do Matki" (A Son to His Mother), following which the students sang "Na Wawel" (On to Wawel).</p>
   <p>S. Zahajkiewicz spoke to the young people. In very simple language, he explained to them who Kosciusko was and what his merits were. He pointed to our hero as an example of virtue and patriotism worthy of emulation. He explained in detail the warning given to the young Zelner by the immortal Kosciusko, and advised our youth to profit by it.</p>
   <p>The choir then sang "The Star-Spangled Banner," after which J. Sobieszczyk, one of the students, recited "A Grave on the Border of Siberia," a poem written by Garczynski. Then the choir sang "Mazurka of the Third of May."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0903.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Young T. Rekosiak spoke about Kosciusko's life. His voice was audible, clear, and full of enthusiasm and understanding. He prepared his speech on Kosciusko very well and created a very good impression.</p>
   <p>After the choir had sung "Gdzie Dusza Ojczyzny?" (Where is the Soul of the Motherland?), Mr. McEvoy, one of the professors at the College, delivered a speech in English. He spoke beautifully and with feeling, and praised the deeds of our heroes--Sobieski, Kosciusko, and Pulaski. He introduced himself as a sincere friend of oppressed Poland.</p>
   <p>The rendition of the choir numbers "Marsz Sokolow" (The March of the Falcons) and "O Columbia!" was a great success, and so was the English recitation given by two students, A. Bocian and A. Jeszke. Students M. Czajkowski and E. Gordon played and excellent piano and violin duet.</p>
   <p>After the song "Pozegnane" (The Farewell), rendered by the choir, Reverend V. <pb facs="5423968_9_0904.jpg" n="4"/>Barzynski, pastor of the parish delivered a lengthy speech. After greeting the students cordially and expressing joy at their progress, he gave a short history of the St. Stanislaus Kostka College and praised the consciencious and tireless work and devotion of Reverend J. Piechowski, rector of the College, and Professor McEvoy. Then he spoke about the misfortunes of our motherland and elucidated the meaning of real patriotism. He advised the young people to work and expressed the hope that young America-Polonia would have some day the spiritual leaders and men of deeds we need so much.</p>
   <p>The last number was very beautiful. After a short address by little W. Kwiat-kowski, who spoke with enthusiasm about love for one's motherland, there followed a very touching and thrilling scene. All students appeared on the stage and Kwiatkowski said:</p>
   <p>"Stand up, dear fellow students, and repeat after me, and let the echoes of <pb facs="5423968_9_0905.jpg" n="5"/>of our words be heard in our dear motherland."</p>
   <p>The students then repeated the following oath after him:</p>
   <p>"We, Polish children gathered here, promise today that we will love you, dear Poland, with heart and soul. We promise to help, and pray for you. We promise solemnly that we will guard the treasures entrusted to us--the Polish language and the faith of our forefathers. We promise that we will live in harmony, unity, and love. May God help us to fulfill these promises. Amen."</p>
   <p>This touching oath moved the audience to tears. The singing of "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland) concluded the exercises, the success of which proved that the students of St. Stanislaus College are making good progress and are being brought up in a patriotic spirit. It should be added that the stage was suitably decorated with a portrait of Kosciusko and a painting, "The Battle <pb facs="5423968_9_0906.jpg" n="6"/>at Raclawice." All numbers were applauded with great enthusiasm.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
