<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-22">Nov. 22, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Our Census</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-22">Nov. 22, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CENSUS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For over a week Dziennik Chicagoski and other papers have been publishing appeals from directors of various sub-committees appointed by the Polish Central Committee for the purpose of increasing attendance of Polish-Americans at the Lwow Exposition in 1894.</p>
   <p>The directors are appealing to our people to send samples of everything possible, and in addition to send information about the past and present conditions of our Polish-American parishes, schools, press, societies, and so forth.</p>
   <p>This work has just begun. We do not know whether the public and representatives of the schools, parishes, organizations, etc., will heed these appeals and will co-operate by gathering and sending in all of this necessary data.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0203.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We sincerely hope no person will refuse to co-operate. In any case, we wish hereby to emphasize the value of this correct information, gathered from all over the United States, not only for our own brethren in the old country and for the Lwow Exposition, but for us here also.</p>
   <p>Such information, gathered accurately and grouped accordingly, will be invaluable material on the history of the Polish immigrants in America. It will also correctly portray our present condition and will enable us to evaluate ourselves; it will show substantially the number of Poles in the United States of North America, how many and what kind of institutions, churches, schools, priests, nuns, and teachers we have, the number and kinds of benevolent, commercial, credit and other institutions, etc.</p>
   <p>So this gathering of information asked for by the directors of the Polish Central Committee represents almost a complete census of the Polish population <pb facs="5423968_9_0204.jpg" n="3"/>in America, and especially of their religious, educational and commercial lives. It is a tremendous effort to portray accurately Polish conditions and history in America.</p>
   <p>It is really not necessary to show how important it is to undertake such a census. Scattered as we are all over America, we know very little about each other. There has been no opportunity to tabulate our numbers and get acquainted with each other. The ties binding us--our organizations, newspapers, and clergy--are all so vague that we often have no record of colonies or Polish parishes that are practically in our midst.</p>
   <p>Now is the time to correct this sad situation. We cannot neglect this opportunity. If in union there is strength, then we should endeavor to unite and organize, so as to gain the most from it. But, is it possible to form a union without previously getting to know ourselves and our own numbers? No. These <pb facs="5423968_9_0205.jpg" n="4"/>are the main reasons why this gathering of information and grouping of same, are so important.</p>
   <p>We believe that what we have written above will suffice to call attention to the importance of this matter. So we end this article hoping that the representatives of American parishes, schools and organizations will kindly supply us with answers to the questions asked by the directors of the Polish Central Committee--and that they will give this information as early as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
