<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-02">Jan. 2, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">A Year of National Mourning</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0853</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0853.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-02">Jan. 2, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">A YEAR OF NATIONAL MOURNING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What should the national mourning in 1895 signify?</p>
   <p>Strictly speaking, this mourning cannot mean anything else than the gathering of strength for the national cause; recollection of previous hardships for the sake of Polish posterity, which is to live in a liberated Poland; revival of the spirit and a brighter awakening of the people upon the aspect of the century of fruitless efforts and struggles, which sadly terminated one after the other in greater sorrows and downfalls.</p>
   <p>Let us bespread our brows with ashes, do penance, be compassionate, in order to be resurrected.</p>
   <p>We have fallen through our own fault and the malediction of this fault, which, despite the numerous tests, is continuously with us. And today the candid patriotism of the Polish people is being replaced by a certain number of <pb facs="5423968_9_0854.jpg" n="2"/>compatriots who shield themselves under the guise of patriotism. This particular type of loyalty only arouses the enemies of our people to scoff at and to despise our Polish patriotism. The enemies assert that this patriotic shield tries to cover up the abominable discords, intrigues and treacheries among the Poles, which cannot be hidden by any front or disguise.</p>
   <p>Love for the fatherland became aroused--not in all, but in many--by an external formula, without quintessence and significance. And this formula was used to hide, from the most vile, the plans of those dealing with the downfall of the country [Poland]. Spies and enemies held no regard for the revered meaning of the words and began to use and abuse them, for they realized how frivolously and hypocritically the term of patriotism was expressed by the so-called "professional" pseudo-patriots.</p>
   <p>Alas, this is the sorrow of sorrows in Polish hearts where true patriotism beats. These are the hearts that hide themselves from this horrible infection by the strictest form of mourning.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0855.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Today--the year of mourning--in the presence of this contagious disease of falsehood, which comes from the miserly shams of stuffed patriotism, we should rise above it all through sorrow and penitence and awaken ourselves to the actual truth--a truth that is as clear as a drop of dew--and love for the fatherland.....By awakening ourselves and others to the realization of the danger of losing our national faith, we will avoid falling into an ambush and avoid developing into undesirable souls.</p>
   <p>Today the primary essential and absolute obligation of every true lover of Polish nationalism and the fatherland is the concentration of loyalty and unity, the consideration of the best method of co-operation in kindling the fire in the true-spirited Poles, and the stamping out of the loathsome disease which contaminates the life and health of the Polish nation.</p>
   <p>This year of mourning ought to be a year of our rebirth.</p>
   <p>It is of less importance how we are going to commemorate the century of our <pb facs="5423968_9_0856.jpg" n="4"/>subjection (no matter how evident and how impressive our outward demonstrations may be) than how we are going to remember this sad past in our hearts; what action we will take in reawakening the true feeling of patriotism is what is going to count.</p>
   <p>Let us cleanse ourselves of our faults, misery, selfishness! Let us stand as sentinels beside the banner of faith and ideal! Let us ennoble ourselves! Let us all be of good will!</p>
   <p>Where does this good will lie and who are its followers? Those are the ones who truly desire good for all, who are convinced by sound reasoning and basic facts, who recognize the truth and voluntarily adjust their opinions, judgments and outlooks according to the present incongruities; those are the ones who spread not hatred but love, those who have a desire for truth, and those who are compatriots.</p>
   <p>Our resurrection should guard against those who venture to bargain for the unity <pb facs="5423968_9_0857.jpg" n="5"/>of our fellow countrymen through sophism, misinterpretation or hypocritical stretching of facts, lies or calumnies, personal attacks or intrigues.</p>
   <p>Then, during this year of mourning, our watchword ought to be: true patriotism and good will.</p>
   <p>Upon this watchword, upon this alarm, every Polish heart in which there is still a glowing spark of faith in God, love of the people and the hopes of resurrection [of Poland] ought to awaken.</p>
   <p>Reverend Vincent Barzynski,</p>
   <p>pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
