<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-10">May 10, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Patriotic Celebration at St. Hedwig Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0797</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0797.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-10">May 10, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTIC CELEBRATION AT ST. HEDWIG PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Members of St. Hedwig Parish commemorated the 104th anniversary of the Constitution of the Third of May at Columbia Hall on Sunday, May 5. The exercise was opened by Mr. Losinski, who appointed J. Blaszka as chairman.</p>
   <p>The ladies choir opened the program with the song "The Leaves Are Falling from the Trees."</p>
   <p>F. H. Jablonski was the initial speaker of the evening. He spoke about the plans and purpose of the Rapperswyl National Fund, and urged the audience to support its cause.</p>
   <p>A declamation was rendered by Mrs. Losinska: "Where Is Poland."</p>
   <p>After a song by the mixed choir, C. Adamski and young Mandyk gave recitations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0798.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>S. Schmidt, commander of the Second Corps of Polish Soldiers of America, made a moving patriotic speech.</p>
   <p>At the request of the chairman Miss Poter and Miss Joket made a collection for the Rapperswyl Fund which netted $5.68. This was followed by the singing by the audience of "God Save Poland."</p>
   <p>Mr. Rudzinski was called from the audience to say a few words. He told the crowd that this was the finest patriotic manifestation ever staged at St. Hedwig Parish.</p>
   <p>"I see many good Poles among you, many good Cracovites [type of Polish soldiers] and young but great scythe-men [peasants who fought with Kosciuszko with scythes]," said Mr. Rudzinski. "Wear these uniforms, brandish the sword and scythe, and remember that these served Poland nobly. But it is not enough to wear these uniforms, one must also work for the fatherland. Your sword, my brothers, will not be needed so soon, and perhaps will never be so necessary as the rebuilding of our people in this country, the retention of our national <pb facs="5423968_9_0799.jpg" n="3"/>spirit and harmony, and our work for the Polish cause. This cause should not be supported halfheartedly, but with the entire soul; and only then will Poland arise.....The ashes of your forefathers will rest in peace, and Our Mother [the Holy Virgin], who has performed so many miracles in our country, will effect our resurrection," he concluded.</p>
   <p>As the speaker left the rostrum, he was given a great hand by the audience.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, the chairman thanked the audience for its warm support.</p>
   <p>signed, Swiatkowski, secretary</p>
   <p>[Although it is not stated, this affair was staged by one of the parish's military societies.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
