<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-29">Dec. 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">T. Stan's Charges against the Central Committee of the Polish National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-29">Dec. 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">T. STAN'S CHARGES AGAINST THE CENTRAL COMMITTEE OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Over a week ago we published a letter from M. Przybyszewski, censor of the Polish National Alliance, who is to prefer charges against the Central Committee of the Polish National Alliance and the editorial department of Zgoda on January 16, 1893, in Chicago. We have promised not to take sides in this matter. Thus far this promise has been kept to the letter--and this pledge will be kept until the matter is disposed of.</p>
   <p>One reservation, however, was set aside: Our silence would be broken if new facts or documents appeared. Such an incident occurred last Thursday. Although the matter became public last week, we made no mention of it until today. This silence was kept in order that we might not be accused of prying into <pb facs="5423968_9_0256.jpg" n="2"/>internal and private affairs of the Alliance, which are invariably damaging, and bringing them to public light. But since a one sided version of this matter was publicly announced in today's issue of Zgoda, journalistic duty demands that we speak out in this newly-risen situation.</p>
   <p>The fact is this: Theophilus Stan, a delegate of the Ninth Sejm (Diet) and president of the Revision Commission, which is in charge of auditing the books of the Central Committee, called a meeting of the delegates of the Ninth Diet on December 23 at Groenwald's hall relative to an "important matter." Only twelve delegates appeared when the meeting was called to order. F. Bieszka was chosen chairman and N. L. Piotrowski was made secretary. One of the members made a motion, since the question in hand concerned the internal affairs of the organization, to keep the proceedings private, but the majority agreed to make them public. Mr. Stan pointed out that the object of the meeting was his complaint against the Central Committee, which had falsely announced his quarterly statement. After a short discussion on the subject, a motion was made by Henry Nagiel, and carried, to postpone this assembly and appoint a <pb facs="5423968_9_0257.jpg" n="3"/>committee of five to call all the delegates to a meeting within a week. The following were chosen to act on the committee: R. Meclewski [Translator's note: According to a list of delegates of the Ninth Diet, this name appeared as Menclewski], T. Bieszka, M. Pikulski, M. Pikulski, M. Osuch, and Joseph Blociszewski. The meeting is to be held at the Central Committee's headquarters.</p>
   <p>The meeting was adjourned until the following week.</p>
   <p>We consider this matter serious and do not wish to treat it lightly. But the last number of Zgoda did not make much of the issue and only cast insinuations at T. Stan about the execution of his duties. It contended that his quarterly statement did not bear his signature and only appeared by the permission of Mr. S. Nicki, editor of Zgoda, as if it were a verbal authorization from Mr. Stan. At this time we do not wish to offer an opinion as to whether this was so or who is right in this matter, or whether it was at all possible to have someone who knew how affix a similar signature to the official quarterly document. No doubt this will be decided upon by the Polish National Alliance, <pb facs="5423968_9_0258.jpg" n="4"/>according to the dictates of its constitution. To just what extent this matter is going to be made public, judging from the present article in Zgoda, remains to be seen. The results will be announced.</p>
   <p>We only wanted to point out the facts, which are unfortunately unpleasant, and once more bring them to the attention of all the faithful members of the Alliance, who will have their own way of treating them.</p>
   <p>The question as it stands is of great importance. It concerns the honor of the Polish National Alliance. Mr. Stan, one of its officers, is accusing the other officers of forging his signature. This accusation should be examined; a verdict on one or the other side should be given. It is not right for Zgoda to revert to insinuations in a matter that concerns thousands of members of the Polish National Alliance. These insinuations will not cover up the matter. It must be examined thoroughly, and decided upon in the proper way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
