<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-25">Jan. 25, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">The First Step in Commemorating the One Hundred and Fiftieth Anniversary of the Birth of Thaddeus Kosciusko</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_9_0728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-25">Jan. 25, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST STEP IN COMMEMORATING THE ONE HUNDRED AND FIFTIETH ANNIVERSARY OF THE BIRTH OF THADDEUS KOSCIUSKO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[We have received the following correspondence with a request that it be published in the Dziennik Chicagoski.]</p>
   <p>The St. Casimir the Prince Young Men's Society of the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, at an extraordinary meeting held last night, decided to support most sincerely and most energetically the proposal made by the Dziennik Chicagoski to commemorate the one hundred and fiftieth anniversary of the birth of our ever-living "Hetman (leader) in peasant's dress".</p>
   <p>This Society proposes that one grand celebration be held by all the Poles in Chicago, which should take place in one of the largest halls in downtown Chicago. Our Chicago Polish societies should get busy with this project, and it can be accomplished.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0729.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If, however, the time should prove to be too short, then let us suggest that the grandest possible kind of a celebration be held in each Parish hall.</p>
   <p>The St. Casimir Society gave its officers full power to act, and it is ready to co-operate.</p>
   <p>The St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish Societies will meet tomorrow afternoon.</p>
   <p>In any event, it would be a shame if this second Polish capital, beyond the ocean, does not fittingly commemorate the memory of the hero of two worlds.</p>
   <p>This Society has adopted a resolution that, if there should appear to be any disinclination toward such an affair, it will arrange its own celebration in the hall on Bradley Street.</p>
   <p>Vincent J. Jozwiakowski,</p>
   <p>Secretary of the Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_9_0730.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>N.B. We call attention to the fact that, on this day, Americans will celebrate Abraham Lincoln's birthday, and many halls may already be engaged.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
