<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1931-11-20">Nov. 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Stephan Micuda Honored by a Banquet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0166</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0166.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1931-11-20">Nov. 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">STEPHAN MICUDA HONORED BY A BANQUET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our friend Mr. Stephan Micuda has just passed the examination of the Illinois Bar Association, which gives him the right to practice law in the state of Illinois. As a result of this, on November 7th, his relatives honored him with a surprise banquet in the hall of the Holy Rosary Parish. Knowing that it is kind of hard to fool a barrister, they were at a loss for a pretext to get Mr. Micuda to come to the hall for the surprise. However, the women were quick at thinking, so they called for assistance on Mr. Andrew Skotnicky, who is president of Mr. Micuda's lodge.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0167.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He immediately phoned Mr. Micuda and told the lodge was holding a special meeting, and that they were having trouble with several of the members on a certain matter, and his presence as an attorney would be influential in bringing the other brothers to a successful understanding. Not suspecting anything, Micuda at once left for the meeting.</p>
   <p>On opening the hall door and seeing all the Micudas there, he soon realized that something out of the ordinary was taking place. They all yelled, Surprise! and the band played the march "comrade from better times" (Mr. Micuda is an ex-member of the band). General congratulations took place. Following this, Mr. Skotnicky, acting as toastmaster, greeted those present and asked them to sit down.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0168.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Rev. M. Buc began with a prayer; the band played American and Slovak selections, after which followed the serving of appetizing food. Short but interesting remarks were made by some of those present. In conclusion, Mr. Micuda himself made a short speech stating that this was the first time in his life he was ever surprised. The rest of the evening was spent dancing. To Mr. Micuda we wish a lot of success in his chosen profession.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
