<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1929-06-29">June 29, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Our Slovak Student</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1929-06-29">June 29, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SLOVAK STUDENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last convention of the Federation of Slovak Catholic students it was decided to hold the next convention in the city of Detroit, Michigan. We do not know what preparation the student body of Detroit has made thus far; this being the first time that an annual meet was decided upon for the Middle West. Previous gatherings were always held in one of our larger eastern cities. In the East the Slovak Catholic students take great interest in the activities of their organization; by doing this they made definite progress. In the Middle West, however, the student body took things rather lightly, careing very little for the Federation until recently. Hence, the convention in the Middle West! In our own city of Chicago, conditions remain the same; lack of interest seems to prevail. The local student body should realize, that by keeping in touch with the Federation, and working in closer harmony, will contribute to the welfare and progress of our national and religious field.</p>
   <p>It was only the other day that I noticed an article in Osadne Hlasy, stating that the Slovak Catholic Student body of Milwaukee, Wisconsin, have taken steps toward bringing the annual convention to their fair city, which proves the faith and ambition of that organization. Should not this open our eyes, and remind the professional members of our student body, such as doctors and lawyers, to lend their assistance so that our youths of to-day will be leaders of tomorrow?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
