<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1934-12-21">Dec. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">News of the Slovaks in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1934-12-21">Dec. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS OF THE SLOVAKS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The economic crisis has brought suffering and want into many of our Slovak homes in this land. Many of our older Slovaks were preparing to retire to a less strenuous life when their plans were wrecked by their life savings being completely wiped out. Banks closed, industry collapsed, business institutions failed, even gold bonds became practically worthless in the financial market. Many of our people, with their life's savings invested in homes, lost everything through no fault of their own.</p>
   <p>At the present time, when it is difficult for a strong young person to secure employment, there is no work for an older person, whose only means of existence is charity through public relief. Many of these people were horrified to think that after they had worked and economized during all their lives, in their declining years they would have to become wards of the state or the Federal Government. Today in this country there is a movement to establish old age security. The measure was tabled at the last session of Congress, but is to be reintroduced at the coming session.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0156.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our various Slovak organizations of Chicago have a joint committee working in behalf of this human cause.</p>
   <p>This committee has called a meeting for Friday evening, December 28th, at 7:30 in Sokol Hall, 26th and Lawndale, the main object of which will be to explain the principles and facts of social security to the rank and file of our people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
