<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1933-01-13">Jan. 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Club Furdek Held Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0409</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0409.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1933-01-13">Jan. 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">CLUB FURDEK HELD MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Club Furdek held its regular monthly meeting, last Sunday, in the Saint Simon's parish hall. New officers for the coming year were elected. Rev. Charles Florek was chosen as spiritual adviser; Mr. Florian Tylka, president; Mr. John Dluhy, vice-president; Mayr Wargos, recording secretary; Cornelia Flaska, financial secretary; Mr. John Hlavacka, treasurer; Mr. George Galos, president of the entertainment committee; Mr. Joseph Steller, president of the membership committee and Dr. Peter Hletko, president of the literature committee.</p>
   <p>A letter from Mr. Fredrick Dvonc, member of the Club, who is continuing his violin studies, was read at the meeting. He wrote to the members about his progress, and also mentioned his desire to be present among them. His letter was enjoyed by all the members.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0410.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>
    Many serious matters were discussed at the meeting. It was decided that all future meetings will be held in the La Salle Hotel. In the early part of February, a banquet will be held, in the hotel, in honor of the newly elected officers. The Slovak public is invited to this banquet. The admission is $1.50, per person.
   </p>
   <p>The entertaining committee announced that a theatrical piece has been selected, called "The Last Husband." It will be shown in the near future.
   </p>
   <p>It was also decided that the Club's officers should publicly declare their support of the Slovaks, who resigned from the Czecho-Slovak World's Fair Committee, when they learned the name Czecho-Slovak was to be used without the hyphen.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0411.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>
    Much attention was given to the "Slovak Youths' Week." It will be held sometime during the period of the World's Fair. During that week, stage performances, concerts, dances, banquets, lectures, and other educational attractions will be held, and the entire Slovak youth will be cordially invited and welcomed. The purpose of the "Youth Week" is to awaken in our Slovak youth, Slovak consciousness and the love for their Slovak origin, and reveal to those youths, cultural achievements of the Slovak nation.
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
