<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1926-09-27">Sept. 27, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Father and Son as Pals</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0066</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0066.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1926-09-27">Sept. 27, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">FATHER AND SON AS PALS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A father laid aside his newspaper and turned his attention to the dirty little face, and tear-filled eyes before him. He had been disturbed in his few minutes of relaxation, before the evening meal, by having his son brought before him showing every indication of having been fighting with other boys in the street.</p>
   <p>"Well, young man, what have you to say for yourself?" questioned the father.</p>
   <p>The little fellow stood in silence, fidgeting, and finally said, "Father, you would have hit him too, had he called you names."</p>
   <p>At these remarks, the father immediately looked up. "Decent boys do not fight, and in the future, I will not tolerate it."</p>
   <p>Tears streaked the filthy little face, as the boy closed his fists in an effort <pb facs="5427331_0067.jpg" n="2"/>to gain his composure. "I'm too big a boy to be crying," he said to himself, and, stricken with remorse, he felt like an orphan who had been left all alone in the world with no one to care for him. This was what he got for hitting another little boy in an effort to protect his name and honor.</p>
   <p>"Didn't you ever get into a fight when you were a boy, Dad? Didn't you ever throw any old shoes, or break a window while you were playing ball or things of that sort?" questioned the boy, angrily.</p>
   <p>"Go and get cleaned up before you have supper," commanded the father. The boy left the room, wondering whether he really was as bad as his father tried to paint him, and if his father had really been a model boy when he was young.</p>
   <p>Raising children is a serious matter, and should be considered such. A father should make a pal of his son, should take him into his confidence, go out with him, play games with him, point out right from wrong, gain his confidence; <pb facs="5427331_0068.jpg" n="3"/>there would be less men in our penal institutions today if the fathers of a past generation had fulfilled their obligations to their sons.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
