<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rovnost Ludu</title> (Equality of the People) Chicago, Illinois,
            <date when="1910-03-30">March 30th, 1910</date> (monthly)
            <title level="a">Some Slavs on the Ballot.</title>
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0109</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0109.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rovnost Ludu</title> (Equality of the People) Chicago, Illinois,
            <date when="1910-03-30">March 30th, 1910</date> (monthly)
            <title level="a">Some Slavs on the Ballot.</title>.
        </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Tuesday, April 5th, the people of Chicago will be called upon to elect aldermen. Through them you will expect to better our system and conditions but we are going to enlighten you on the conditions that are existing at the present time.</p>
   <p>Right now Chicago politics are controlled by the Republicans who should first of all consider the people above everything. This we cannot say about the present faction; they cater to the rich corporations and to the Capitalists. At the present time there is not one in office who will take up the working man's cause, the same workers who put them where they are.</p>
   <p>Outside of Pittsburgh and Philadelphia there is not a more corrupt town then Chicago with its grafters and cheaters, and is blossoming forth under the guidance of the Republican Party.</p>
   <p>Checking the city's records it was found that One Hundred Thousand Dollars were stolen. City jobs were given without permission; contractors were paid for jobs they
    <pb facs="5427331_0110.jpg" n="2"/>
    never finished; and a lot of names on the payroll of people who never worked but received salaries, also orders for materials were given to friends of the politicians who in turn charged the city two and three times the actual value of the goods, and at that they would receive the worst grade of material, and on this account the city lost One Hundred Thousand Dollars. Also when some lawbreaker went before the judge he was freed provided he had the pull and the money.</p>
    <p>We are looking for men who are honest and fair but we wont find them on either the Republican or Democratic side. The Democrats today do not steal for the simple reason that they have not got the opportunity but in Milwaukee where they have power their stealing goes on just like the Republicans in Chicago.</p>
    <p>The Socialist Party is one which can curb dishonesty and the robbery of the city funds. They have candidates in every ward, men who will not be bought out, and who are honest and well deserving candidates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
