<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1934-04-13">Apr. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Meeting of the Executive Board of the First Slovak Catholic Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1934-04-13">Apr. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF THE EXECUTIVE BOARD OF THE FIRST SLOVAK CATHOLIC UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the executive board of the First Slovak Catholic Union, which was held in the Sherman Hotel, adjourned last Monday. The meeting was to have been held some time ago, but was postponed because of the illness of the president, Adam Podkricvacky. Monday morning the executive board and many other members of the Catholic Union attended services at the church of the Sacred Heart, Huron Street and Oakley Boulevard, where Reverend Dubos, chaplain of the First Slovak Catholic Union said Mass. After Mass a breakfast was served in the parish hall. From there the board members went to the Sherman Hotel, where the annual meeting began. The convention lasted a week. The chairman, Mr. Adam Podkrivacky, was assisted by the vice chariman, Mr. Joseph Vascak. On Tuesday the convention welcomed Reverend K. Mlynarovic, president of the Catholic Slovak Federation, and Dr. Peter P. Hletko, vice president, as guests.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0444.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Tuesday evening the members of the executive board were guests at a dinner in the Sherman Hotel, given by the president, Mr. Adam Podkrivacky. After the evening meal a sociable evening was spent, with a few timely remarks here and there. Those present were as follows: Rev. Dubosh, Joseph Vascak, John Sabol, E. W. Valko, Andrew Novak, Andrew Evdelyi, Michael Wangovic, John Hetsko, George Ruyak, Andrew Putka, M. L. Michuda, Edward Minarcak, Joseph Matasovsky, Joseph Husek, Dr. Michael Gaydos, Monsignor Victor Blahunka, Rev. K. Mlynarovic, John Mayer, Louis Severa and Michael Tremko. Dr. Peter P. Hletko, acted as toastmaster.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
