<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1931-06-19">June 19, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Catholic Sokols' Representation in National Gymnastic Tournament</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1931-06-19">June 19, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">CATHOLIC SOKOLS' REPRESENTATION IN NATIONAL GYMNASTIC TOURNAMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, June 21 of this year, the citizens of Chicago will have an opportunity to witness a gymnastic program under the name of "Chicagoland Sport Congress" to be held in Soldiers Field in Grant Park, sponsored by the Chicago Tribune.</p>
   <p>This is the first time in the history of Chicago that all nationalities have united in such a gigantic undertaking. There will be a representation of both sexes of Bohemian, Polish, Ukrainian, Hungarian, German, and Lithuanian. It was suggested by the Chicago Tribune, through the efforts of Michael S. Rehak, chief director of the Slovak Catholic Turners, and Dr. Peter P. Hletko their chief medical examiner that the Slovak Catholic Turners send a delegation representing our Chicago Slovaks to this gathering. Complete details of this</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0361.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>program appeared in the June 13th issue of the <hi>Chicago Tribune</hi>, which stated that the Slovak Catholic Sokols of Chicago and vicinity will have the largest representation at this meet, with about one hundred delegates of both sexes to be present. The <hi>Tribune</hi> also gives a brief history of the Slovak Catholic Sokol organization, which was very interesting, mentioning with the highest degree of regard the names of Michael Rehak, Dr. Peter P. Hletko, and Miss Veronika Kalafut, head overseer of this body.</p>
   <p>The program will consist of drilling by the sokols, folk-dances of the various nations represented. The music will be furnished by a on-hundred-piece band. This will all take place in Soldiers' Field, June 21st, commencing at 2 P.M. Admission will be twenty-five cents and proceeds will go to the public welfare fund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
