<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1930-07-18">July 18, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Slovak Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1930-07-18">July 18, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO SLOVAK DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Slovak Day, together with the celebration of the fiftieth birthday anniversary of General Milan R. Stefanik, is drawing near. On this coming Sunday, all Slovaks will congregate in the Coliseum, to testify before the public that the Slovak spirit is still alive, and rules the hearts of the Slovaks.</p>
   <p>Like all other enterprises, Slovak Day has met with both the approval and disapproval of the various individuals. We noticed from the beginning, that our organizations looked with disfavor on the project. These misunderstandings, however, were straightened out, to a certain extent, through the co-operation of different societies.</p>
   <p>We cannot however, predict the success or the failure of this national day. This coming Sunday will show whether we are competent to occupy ourselves with national affairs. If that day proves successful the glory and the good name of the Slovak nation will be known to all Americans. However, if the day is a failure, not only the committee, but the whole Slovak race will suffer moral defeat.</p>
   <p>All Slovaks, regardless of religious differences are expected to be present for the purpose of elevating our national spirit. Next Sunday will be a national holiday for all Slovaks, - a day when all troubles should be forgotten, when our time should be devoted to this cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0245.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Slovaks will also honor the memory of one of their greatest heroes, General M. R. Stefanik, who gave his all to his country. Due honor should be rendered to him. He is our Washington, who fought to gain freedom for the Slovaks. He may also be called our Lincoln because he freed our Slovak nation from a thousand years of slavery. We are so deeply indebted to him that we shall never be able to repay him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
