<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1935-03-15">Mar. 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Slovak Citizens' Club of Town of Lake</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1935-03-15">Mar. 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">SLOVAK CITIZENS' CLUB OF TOWN OF LAKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The political club of St. Michael's parish has always enjoyed a large membership, a goodly number of whom are Slovaks. Recently, however, the club has become known as the Slovak Civic Organization of Town of Lake, and it has set out to do for the citizens of this community greater things in the political field than anything which it has accomplished in the past. At a recent annual meeting the following officers were elected: John M. Kubina, president; Michael S. Rehak, vice-president; A. B. Tabola, recording secretary; Rudolph Rehak, financial secretary; and J. Trop, treasurer. The following committees were also selected: Executive Committee, - J. M. Kubina, Dr. Peter P. Hletko, John M. Dluhy, Adam Poliak, A. B. Tabola, J. Trop, M. S. Rehak, Peter Nemec, and John S. Dujmovic; Arrangement Committee, - John M. Nemec, Nicholas Palkovic, S. Cermak, Joseph Maxian, Ferdinand Culen, John Cermak, Joseph Koval, and Vendelin Paniak; Membership Committee, - A. B. Tabola, John Pavlik, John Dujmovic, William Hletko, John Sana, Rudolph Rehak, and John Kedzut; Legislative Committee, - John Dluhy, Michael Rehak, and Adam Poliak; Organization Committee, - Dr. Peter Hletko, J. Trop, and John Pavlik; and Naturalization Committee, - Peter Nemec, S. Cermak, Ferdinand Culen, and Nicholas Palkovic.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0114.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This civic organization has added several things to its program, such as the opening of South Damen Avenue, from 47th to 39th street; the opening of 47th street all the way to Harlem Avenue, and the routing of Western Avenue street-cars direct to the Loop. Other things necessary are warning signs to motorists for the protection of school children, the completion of the Verdi High School, at 56th and Rockwell Streets, and the universal transfer system on street-cars and buses. For the accomplishment of these and other purposes it is vitally necessary that every Slovak of this vicinity shall become a member of the Slovak Civic Organization of Town of Lake.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
