<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-22">July 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">From the Slovak Organizations</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-22">July 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE SLOVAK ORGANIZATIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Representatives of all the local Slovak clubs and associations are in conference now to decide upon the steps to be taken in case the majority of their enlisted members lose their lives on the battlefield, and the problem of how to pay death benefits should the need arise. Up to the present every organization has tried to meet its obligations individually. It was found, however, that co-operation and concerted action will bring forth more favorable results. For this reason a meeting of all presidents, auditors, and publicity men of the organizations was called. The organ of the Telocvicna Slovenska Jednota Sokol (Slovak Sokol Union) reports on the results of the sessions as follows: [Translator's note: Beginning here, the article is written in Slovak.]</p>
   <p>"It appears from the deliberations that the problem can be solved if all <pb facs="5427331_0418.jpg" n="2"/>the Slovak organizations will act as a unit. A joint committee has been appointed to represent all organizations. It will gather statistical data on the number of our young men expected to become soldiers. Each of these will be given a questionnaire to be filled out with information about the man's status in citizenship, his physical condition, etc. From this preliminary information our organizations will be able to estimate the obligations they will be called upon to meet when the sad tidings will be filing in from across the ocean, from the battlefields, where our boys will give their lives under the slogan "All for one, and one for all!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
