<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1933-03-24">Mar. 24, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Slovaks and Czechs Pay Tribute to the Late Mayor Cermak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5 (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1933-03-24">Mar. 24, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SLOVAKS AND CZECHS PAY TRIBUTE TO THE LATE MAYOR CERMAK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Slovaks and Bohemians gathered in large numbers last Sunday afternoon, in the Harrison Auditorium, to pay their last respects to their countryman, the late Mayor Anton J. Cermak.</p>
   <p>This solemn occasion was sponsored by the Bohemian and Slovak organizations of Chicago, to extend to those Slovaks and Bohemians who were not present at the regular funeral services for the dead Mayor, an opportunity to pay their last respects to this distinguished compatriot, whose name will go down in American history.</p>
   <p>The Auditorium was appropriately draped and the participants were deeply affected by this solemn occasion.</p>
   <p>The program was begun at three o'clock, when the curtain was drawn aside, to display a bust of Cermak, decorated with the American flag and draped in mourning. A large book, bearing the title History of Anton J. Cermak, 1873 - 1933, was also shown. Prominent men together with representatives <pb facs="5427331_0213.jpg" n="2"/>of various organizations were seated in a circle about the book, in the center of the stage.</p>
   <p>The services were opened with the National anthem, which was played by the Harrison orchestra; president of the committee, J. A. Cervenka, then addressed the audience and explained the purpose of the occasion requesting that they refrain from applause on this solemn occasion.</p>
   <p>The program proceeded according to schedule as follows: Hruska's quartet; a selection from Anton Dvorak; speeches: Cermak A Martyr, by Professor Zmrhala; Cermak as a Patriot, by Dr. Peter Hletko; "Cermak and the Homeland" by the Czecho-Slovak Consul General, Dr. Smetanka; Cermak as a Character, by Rev. J. Pelikan; Cermak as a Humanitarian, by John Straka; Cermak, a friend of the working people, by Dr. J. Vojan; songs by the choir Lyra concluded the service.</p>
   <p>All speakers performed their role excellently, depicting the entire life of Cermak; and all were of the same opinion; that, Anton Cermak was one of the greatest heroes. He lived for his people, loved them, worked for them, and sacrificed his life for them.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0214.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The death of this heroic man brought back, to the vast audience, who deeply mourn his loss, memories of his great work.</p>
   <p>The concluding number on the program, which was introduced by the Sokols and Legionnaires, was a drama portraying the life of Cermak. The drama was a historical play, beginning with the year of Cermak's birth until his death, when his last words to President Roosevelt were, "I am glad that it was me [Sic!] and not you." The audience, upon mention of these "last words" were deeply moved, in fact, many shed tears.</p>
   <p>The program concluded leaving the audience with the satisfied feeling of having performed their duty as citizens, toward their great political leader, the deceased Mayor Anton J. Cermak. Rest in Peace!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
