<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1934-08-10">Aug. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Jednota League News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0344</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0344.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1934-08-10">Aug. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">JEDNOTA LEAGUE NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As Napoleon met his Waterloo so Assumption met Nemcek and his mates last Sunday. The boys from So. Chicago played some smart baseball, defeating Assumption, 10 to 8.</p>
   <p>Bessemer Park was resounding with cheers and yells of St. Anthony's fans in the eighth when their boy collected six runs on seven hits, placing the game on ice. Manager Churilla in several instances outguessed his opponents and did the unexpected at the time. On the other hand, Manager Adamcik, of Assumption, could not keep his players under control. To a certain extent the loss may be attributed to the players' disregarding of their coaches.</p>
   <p>The double-header scheduled for Sunday was not played. St. Joseph chose to travel to St. John Saturday afternoon where they won, 8 to 5. The fans were more than surprised at the fielding of the St. John's outfielders. Apparently, Manager Oresky gave them a hot shot of "pepo." On account of St. Stephen's failure to furnish a playing field for their games with St. Andrew, the game was forfeited to St. Andrew's.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0345.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The game between St. Joseph and St. Stephen was a battle royal. Both of the teams were neck and neck for six innings, the tie finally was broken by St. Stephen who held a one run lead until the end. St. Joseph played very loose, causing three of St. Stephen runs to be unearned. Three times St. Joseph had the bags loaded but the batters could not deliver.</p>
   <p>Consequently the game went to St. Stephen by a score of 5 to 4. The regular league meeting ended in a near riot because the officers found it necessary to shorten the schedule in order to allow the Chicago champions to travel to Youngstown on the 19th of August. All the managers were in accord with the officers of the league, except Manager Churilla, who argued that he should play the regular scheduled game.</p>
   <p>On account of shortening the schedule, several teams who are not contenders for the championship voluntarily forfeited their games to the contestants. Consequently there is a three-way tie: Assumption, St. Joseph, and St. Stephen. To break this three-way tie and decide the champions of <pb facs="5427331_0346.jpg" n="3"/>this league there will be a double header played at Fernwood Park at 104th and Wallace Sts. There are plenty grandstand seats and room for all Jednota fans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
