<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1932-06-10">June 10, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Celebration of the Two-Hundredth Anniversary of the Birth of George Washington</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1932-06-10">June 10, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATION OF THE TWO-HUNDREDTH ANNIVERSARY OF THE BIRTH OF GEORGE WASHINGTON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This year celebrations are being held in all parts of the United States in commemoration of the two-hundredth anniversary of the birth of the immortal father of this country, George Washington.</p>
   <p>Not only statesmen and diplomats but all nationalities, churches, and organizations are making preparations for the celebration in every state and city of the land.</p>
   <p>We Slovaks, from the patriotic standpoint, also have our duties to perform for this country. We owe to it a large debt. Therefore we should render our respects to the greatest man in history, George Washington, for we also enjoy the right earned for us by Washington, the right of freedom under the protection of the Stars and Stripes.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0423.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the Slovak had been deprived by the Hapsburg reign of terror of his civic rights,--when all hope had been abandoned,--he left our native land with heavy heart and emigrated to Columbus's continent to procure a better living for his family and to rear his children in the land of liberty. In the short time of his residence here as a free Slovak he has made use of his opportunity to better himself, and with new hope and energy he has begun to establish large organizations, businesses, real-estate developments, schools, and churches. For this reason and for many others we are undeniably under obligation to take part in the celebration of the Washington anniversary.</p>
   <p>We are certain that the day will be properly observed by us if all Slovaks will unite with thousands of other American citizens to celebrate it. Let Slovaks with their clubs and other organizations assemble on July 17, 1932, in Pilsen Park, at 26th Street and Albany Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0424.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The celebration will be held under the direction of the American Slovak Citizens' League. Preparations are being made for making the affair a success, one of the greatest that Slovaks ever will witness. Many famous speakers will be present, and the public is assured of an interesting program.</p>
   <p>On all sides of this metropolis clubs and other organizations are displaying great interest in this anniversary; it may therefore be predicted that the affair will be a success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
