<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-12">Oct. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Slovak Priests under Our Flag</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary from the Headquarters of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-12">Oct. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SLOVAK PRIESTS UNDER OUR FLAG</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary from the Headquarters of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"What a beautiful sight is the unity of all the strata of our people now at the eleventh hour--a unity which may bring our nation life or death! We hope it will be life that will be given to it!</p>
   <p>"In this fateful hour our people will be able to state proudly: 'We have done everything in our power.' The Slovak Catholic clergy held a conference with Dr. Milan R. Stefanik in the Plaza Hotel in New York. As a result of this meeting, a telegram was sent to Albert Mamatey, president of the Slovak League. The clergymen assured the League of their loyalty to the cause of liberating the old homeland, and of their willingness to co-operate from now on.....The Slovak clergy had not taken an active part in the movement for liberation up to the present time.....The need for aid from that part of our <pb facs="5427331_0153.jpg" n="2"/>clergy has been long felt, for when some groups of an organization fail to respond, the efforts of the whole are badly hampered.....</p>
   <p>"The Catholic Sokol societies and the National Sokol (freethinking, nonsectarian) have removed old barriers that existed between them; they have forgotten old frictions.</p>
   <p>"What nobody would have thought possible only recently has become a reality. The two sides are united into one great organization as far as national patriotic effort is concerned. A gentlemen's agreement was reached between the leaders of the Catholic and the National organizations. They will work together under the name 'Slovak Sokols in America.'</p>
   <p>"The Slovak League registers great joy over this development....."</p>
   <p>[Note by the editor of the Denni Hlasatel: The preceding lines represent an excerpt translated from a report by the Slovak League which we offer to our readers without any comment.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
