<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-31">Jan. 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Slovak Bazaar</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-31">Jan. 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SLOVAK BAZAAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anyone who pays a visit to the pavilion in the Pilsen Brewery Park where the Slovak Bazaar is being held will hardly recognize the hall which is so familiar to most of us. The interior of the pavilion has undergone such a change that it looks almost as if it had been touched by a magic wand. It has been transformed into a colorful array of picturesque stands which lure the gaze with a wealth of desirable objects.....Smiling crowds are constantly milling through the hall. The mellow Slovak language predominates.</p>
   <p>This Bazaar is the largest enterprise upon which the Chicago-Slovak colony has yet ventured. Those who knew our Slovak brothers' willingness to sacrifice were certain that the Slovaks would not fail.....</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0260.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>...Anyone may try his good luck on one of the many wheels and win the beautiful prizes on display, consisting mostly of handwork, such as embroidery and woodcuts, which constitute the mainstay of Slovak home industry in the old country.</p>
   <p>There are twenty Chicago Slovak organizations represented. Each conducts business in its own tent....Service is supplied in the best way imaginable. Everyone is doing his utmost to help the most worthy of causes, the liberation of the land at the foot of the Tatra mountains from the Hapsburg's cruel reign.</p>
   <p>There is a cabaret similar to the one we had at the bazaar of the Czech National Alliance. It is one of the chief attractions and is connected with a delicatessen and refreshment counter which has been appropriately named "At Merry Annie's". All girls and married women wear native Slovak costumes.....The contest for the title "Queen of the Bazaar" is one of <pb facs="5427331_0261.jpg" n="3"/>the main centers of interest.....</p>
   <p>Besides Slovak organizations, there are individuals, and particularly businessmen, who work assiduously for the success of the Bazaar. Mr. Kubicek gave a building lot which will be raffled. It is located in Norwood Park and is valued at four hundred dollars. A gorgeous player piano was donated by the Tatranska Jednota (Tatra[mountains] Union).....</p>
   <p>Sokol and singing associations furnished the largest contingent of visitors yesterday. Catholic Slovak societies will gather in great numbers at the Bazaar today.....A mighty crowd of visitors is expected to throng the bazaar next Saturday, which has been designated as "Allies' Day". It is presumed that large delegations will appear on this day to represent the nations which are in the combat against the enemy of democracy and humanity. Authorities have promised that on that day the Marine Band from the Great Lakes Naval Training Station will be permitted to play at the Bazaar. The latter will close on Sunday with a masked ball.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0262.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This Slovak enterprise enjoys the favor of the metropolitan press, which sent a number of photographers who took pictures of the colorful scenes.</p>
   <p>The Czechs of Chicago should be the first to take a lively interest in this enterprise and so pay off in part at least, the debt they owe their brothers, the Slovaks. We regret to admit, however, that Czech attendance on the first Bazaar day was scant.</p>
   <p>The great wealth of embroidery exhibited at the Bazaar deserves special mention. A truly splendid piece of work of this kind is one showing the likeness of President Wilson. It is the product of the skill of Mrs. Mary Matusek, a resident of Pullman, Illinois. It is not for sale, because at the close of the Bazaar it is to be sent to the President as a token of the deep reverence which the Chicago Slovak colony harbors for the man who declared himself to be a protagonist of freedom for all small nations, regardless of their size. This is going to be a gift befitting the occasion <pb facs="5427331_0263.jpg" n="5"/>and will, doubtless, be accepted with gratitude.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
