<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1932-12-02">Dec. 2, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting Held by Slovak Catholic Charitable Organization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427331_0469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427331_0469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SLOVAK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Osadne Hlasy</title>,
<date when="1932-12-02">Dec. 2, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING HELD BY SLOVAK CATHOLIC CHARITABLE ORGANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An annual meeting was held last Sunday by the Slovak Catholic Charitable Organization in the Assumption parish hall. About sixty individuals, who are interested in the humanitarian work of this organization were present at the meeting. Three priests, Reverends Charles Florek, Joseph Rondzik, and Michael Buc, were also present.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by the president, Mrs. Julia Krajcovic and the prayer was said by Reverend Joseph Rondzik. After the prayer the president greeted the audience, and spoke about the work of the organization. She thanked everyone for the co-operation given her, and <pb facs="5427331_0470.jpg" n="2"/>plead for further assistance for the benefit of Slovak poor widows and orphans. Helping the poor is the purpose of the organization.</p>
   <p>Minutes and reports from the previous meeting were read by the secretary, and they were accepted. The by-laws were read and several changes were made. Among them, was that the directors will consist of two representatives from each parish, who will be elected every two years.</p>
   <p>The financial report was read by the secretary, Mrs. Anna Kocur.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0471.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In place of the treasurer, Mrs. Z. Kuna, who is ill, the report was read by her husband. The financial reports were itemized from the time of the organization's existence until the present. The income was $9,184.15; the expenses $4,430.14, and $4,754.10 is left in the treasury.</p>
   <p>The election of the directors followed the reading of the reports. The term expired for the following: Mr. Flaska, Mesdames Kuna, Kvacala, and Kocur, Mrs. Kvacala and Mrs. Kocur were re-elected. Mrs. Dvonc had succeeded Mrs. Kuna in office and the successor to Mr. Flaska has not yet been appointed.</p>
   <pb facs="5427331_0472.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>After all matters had been discussed regarding the organization, a question arose whether or not to hold a third Slovak Catholic Day, next year. It was decided that the Slovak Day should be held the following year in the same park where it had been held previously.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
