<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-21">Sept. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to the Child</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0087</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0087.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-21">Sept. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO THE CHILD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the Illinois conference of representatives of Zionist organizations, which was held last Sunday at the Chicago Hebrew Institute, Mr. David Schnaberg, secretary of the Young Judea, said a [few] words to the young boys and girls that penetrated the hearts of all his listeners. Mr. Schnaberg said nothing new. On the contrary, his description of the relationship between Jewish parents and their children, was familiar to every individual who had observed Jewish life in America. But because everyone recognized the truth of his statements--his speech was very impressive.</p>
   <p>Is there anyone who does not see the estrangement that is developing in America between Jewish parents and their children? Is there anyone who does not recognize that the connection between the old and the new generation is being broken? The children know very little about their parents; they have no conception of the spiritual heritage of generations which their parents possess.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0088.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Most of them grow up without the influence of either the parents or a home. Their school has the greatest influence upon them. They [the children] accept the superficial Americanism that they see, and look upon their parents with a certain contempt, because the children consider them foreigners, whereas they, the children, are Americans.</p>
   <p>Who is to blame for this lack of harmony? The parents blame America; they blame Columbus. America is that type of a country, they claim. There is some truth in this assertion. The American school system, which has so many extraordinary virtues, also possesses the vice of taking upon itself too many duties. In its concern for the rearing of children it usurps parental responsibility. The Americans themselves are beginning to notice this. Americans are beginning to realize that no good can come of leaving the rearing of children entirely up to the school. Americans who are busy with business or pleasure, seldom pay much attention to their children. The boy or girl is left to himself or herself. The father shows hardly any interest in the sorrow or joy of his children, in their pleasures or desires. He is seldom their friend, or their advisor, and the <pb facs="5423972_2_0089.jpg" n="3"/>sympathetic relationship which makes the life of children sweet, is missing.</p>
   <p>This situation exists in American homes. It is even truer of Jewish families because the parents are more absorbed in the search for a livelihood, and because the minds of the children are completely different from the parents. Jewish parents and children often lack the mutual understanding which should exist.</p>
   <p>This is not only the case among poor families, in which the parents cannot help themselves, or illiterate families, in which parents do not know any better. It is also true of rich and intelligent Jewish families. With the wealthy families it is very often worse because they think that money can provide everything, and that luxuries can take the place of a friendly and intimate relationship between parents and children. Since the parents do not know how to, or cannot develop a relationship which would make it possible for them to understand their children, would it not be possible to help the children educate the parents?</p>
   <p>On this point the remarks of Mr. Schnaberg about the activity of the Young Judea <pb facs="5423972_2_0090.jpg" n="4"/>were particularly interesting. He described the meetings of young boys and girls who entertain their parents at their meetings. The parents hear about what their children have already learned about Jewish matters, about Jewish songs and games, about the dramatization of Jewish historical events. He spoke of the satisfaction that the children reveal when they entertain their parents, and of the joy which is then reflected on the faces of the parents. In this way he vididly presented the work and mission of the Young Judea.</p>
   <p>Those present at the conference were aware of the truth of Mr. Schnaberg's remarks, and they applauded vociferously. But only a handful were present at the conference, and Mr. Schnaberg's remarks deserve to be heard by every Jewish parent.</p>
   <p>Young Judea is an attempt to solve the great problem of the estrangement of the young Jewish generation from their people. It is a movement that deserves the greatest encouragement and support.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
