<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-11-17">Nov. 17, 1905</date>, 3:2.
<title level="a">Ministers Aid Jews Congregationalists Heartily Indorse Work of Relief Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1352</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1352.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-11-17">Nov. 17, 1905</date>, 3:2.
<title level="a">MINISTERS AID JEWS CONGREGATIONALISTS HEARTILY INDORSE WORK OF RELIEF COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>JEWISH RELIEF FUND - PREVIOUSLY REPORTED $25,996.01</p>
   <p>YESTERDAY'S CONTRIBUTION 14,968.14</p>
   <p>Grand Total $40,966.05</p>
   <p>"Our prayer is that this last glorious martyrdom of the Jews, the bravest and most patient of people, the most loyal and devoted to their ideals, their faith, their institutions, their church and the various countries of their adoption, will stir up such a world of indignation, such a horror of the distempers and barbarities which are the inevitable outcome of race prejudice, that in the near days this vice of race prejudice will appear to all what it is even now to the thoughtful - a vice, odious and indefensible."</p>
   <p>This vigorous protest against the barbarities visited upon the Jews of the Russian provinces, sent as an expression of sympathy by the Congregational Ministers Association of Chicago, last night furnished the keynote of the meeting at the Standard <pb facs="5423972_2_1353.jpg" n="2"/>Club, where members of the central committee and with their auxiliary committees to discuss the progress of the movement to raise funds in Chicago for the aid of the oppressed Jews.</p>
   <p>Former Judge Philip Stein presented a resolution providing that the committees make no discrimination between Jew and Gentile in solicitation for the relief fund after hearing the letter from the congregational clergymen.</p>
   <p>President Kraus reported he had received a total of $5,700 from B'nai B'rith lodges in city and country and that he expected to forward $25,000 from that source. In order to make November 27 truly expressive of the profound sentiment of sympathy which the whole Jewish race feels, a west side committee suggested the propriety of exerting what influence they might to induce manufacturers and merchants to permit their Jewish employes to repair to their various synagogues on that afternoon to attend the memorial services. No formal action was taken on this by the committee.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's contributions ranged from $2000 to sixty-four cents.</p>
   <p>(A long tabulated list of individual contributions and from business firms followed.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
