<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-12-14">December 14, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Public Opinion</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-12-14">December 14, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC OPINION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>December 10, 1908</p>
   <p>Dear Editor:</p>
   <p>In the December 5th issue of the Chicago Israelite under the caption of News and Comments, Dr. Schoenforber requested all subscribers of the Associated Jewish Charities to return all tickets which they receive for balls or other affairs given for the benefit of welfare institutions and to inclose therein a printed leaflet sent to them by the Charities. In this they state they are already contributors of some organization, which actively participates in the maintenance of charitable institutions and which finds no need of collecting money through balls and bazaars.</p>
   <p>As this article appeared immediately after we sent out tickets for our ball to be held at the Coliseum, Saturday evening, December 26, also because a similar article, by the same writer, appeared in the March issue of the Chicago Israelite on the heels of our sending tickets for the bazaar, it is clearly an indication that the attitude of Dr. Schoenforber towards the Marks Nathan <pb facs="5423972_2_1274.jpg" n="2"/>Jewish Orphan Home is very unfriendly. Therefore, in all fairness, we should like to have an opportunity of answering this attack.</p>
   <p>The children who are at present at the Marks Nathan Home were taken from the very poorest homes, if they may be called homes, for in many instances they were found in stables and alleys. Only the very needy, who can positively find no aid elsewhere, apply to the Home. According to the statictics we now have one-hundred and fifty children in the Home. We were compelled to refuse hundreds of children for lack of facilities. Daily we reject children who are in desperate need of a home, and the Associated Jewish Charities intend to impress the public that they have provided sufficient comfort for the needy children and the institution. But have they done this? What about the one-hundred and fifty children who are with us? Have they come to us because they were well taken care of by the Associated Jewish Charities? Why are we beleagured by applications of children who were refused a home in other institutions, on the ground that there is no home for them "at present" and that they must "wait?" What is the reason when we refuse a child for lack of place that they come again and again and we are compelled to reject them?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1275.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Associated Jewish Charities is calling the Marks Nathan Jewish Orphan Home an orthodox institution, and as such they deem it unworthy of assistance......because orthodoxy is the wrong thing. Those who are in dire need are generally the persecuted from Russia, Rumania, Poland, etc. These refugees came to America, for they sought a place where they might have peace and be free to worship as they saw fit. Is it fair that these people, because of death and misfortune, should be compelled to accept Reformed Judaism and to place their children in institutions which are principally opposed to their views? Only in cases of total desperation would a father or mother of a half-orphaned child permit him to be in a place where the food is not in compliance with the dietary laws. Is not an orthodox training better for a child than one he may receive in the streets of Chicago? Is it not better that, instead of permitting a Jewish child to become a criminal or thief, he be trained to become a good orthodox citizen? A child will be a better American and Jew when he is taught to respect the laws and customs of his fathers instead of violating them.</p>
   <p>Above all, did you ever consider the tragedy which occurs when the parents and children are reunited and they find their children to be total strangers <pb facs="5423972_2_1276.jpg" n="4"/>because of religious differences? The aim of the Marks Nathan Jewish Orphan Home to avoid such tragedies is crystalized in the training of these children not only to love their parents, but also to respect the religion of their parents.</p>
   <p>The increase of Jewish institutions in Chicago has been instrumental in making the Associated Jewish Charities antagonistic towards the Marks Nathan Home, and unwilling to recognize that the West Side Jews have a right to their own thinking and are not compelled to accept reformed ideas.</p>
   <p>Briefly the Marks Nathan Home is a worthy institution. It is sad enough when we must have dances, balls and bazaars in order to maintain this Home, but it is more sad when the Associated Jewish Charities, instead of helping us, appeals to liberal-minded people to withdraw their assistance.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>Sol Drucker, Superintendent</p>
   <p>Marks Nathan Home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
