<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1918-08-01">August 1, 1918</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0988</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0988.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-08-01">August 1, 1918</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Peoples' Relief Committee of Chicago has put forth very little effort and it appears they will not do very much in the future because the atmosphere in which the committee finds it is very unfavorable for work and life.</p>
   <p>The Peoples' Relief is in alliance with the Central Relief, so to speak; it is the property of the prominent Jews of Orthodox Judaism. Being their stepchild, it is impossible for the relief committee to work independently and to win the full confidence and respect of the great masses. The officials of the Peoples' Relief Committee feel themselves in hypnotized surroundings, when they come together at a meeting with the prominent Jews, and on top of that, they don't get their equal rights, neither do they get the credit due them for their relief work.</p>
   <p>The Central Relief Committee always have the majority in all committees and get seventy percent credit for the money coming in, while the Peoples' Relief get only thirty percent credit for their work. In addition to this, the management of the office is entirely in the hands of the Central Relief Committee, centering in one person, who is the chief of that committee. Under such circumstances, the Peoples' Relief must be paralyzed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0989.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is time for the representatives of all organizations to present more independence in their dealings: they must demand equal credit for their work and a representative in the office with as much right as the representative of the Central Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>The representatives of the labor organizations must carry through the mandate given them at the labor conference and secure equal rights and equal credit. If that fails they must withdraw entirely, and work independently, as is done in other large cities, with great success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
