<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-08-28">Aug. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Germans in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1070.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-08-28">Aug. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMANS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The English-American newspapers provoked the German-Americans by showing their open sympathy for the German foes, in spite of the fact that the Germans have brought many good things to this country.</p>
   <p>The German-Americans forget, however, to mention that among the readers of the anti-German newspapers there are thousands whose fathers or forefathers came to America from Germany. Even many publishers and editors of the anti-German papers are of German and Austrian descent.</p>
   <p>The Germans are in many ways similar to the Jews, as Heine observed. They display the same abilities for adapting themselves to. their immediate surroundings; this at times brings great material success to the individual, but drastically weakens the further development of the national characteristics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1071.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Germans have worked themselves up nicely in America. The pioneers have handed down honor and wealth, to their children, but they have taken their German nationalism along to their graves.</p>
   <p>North America has remained an English-speaking country on account of the Germans. No one prohibited them from speaking their own language, from introducing into the United States their culture and the democratic order that prevails in Switzerland, where no language in particular is supreme.</p>
   <p>The Germans themselves helped to establish the English language and culture in the United States under the name of Americanism, and thereby raised their children as American patriots, and now they wonder why the American newspapers are against Germany - as if Americanism and English are not the same.</p>
   <p>England's poets are known to everybody here in America; English literature has a wide field here for its development; English journalists control the public opinion of the United States, and English publishers have a large market here for their publications.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1072.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But the grandchildren of the German patriots, who, at the beginning of the last century, fought for the survival of the German culture, now read their own classics in English translations. Modern German literature is foreign to them and they cannot understand a modern German poet unless his work is translated into English.</p>
   <p>The Germans are therefore wrong in protesting against the local English newspapers for expressing their sentiment in behalf of the mother country, England.</p>
   <p>Anybody who has been brought up and educated in the English language is an Englishman in spirit, and his heart throbs for England even if his forefathers came from Germany, Austria, or Scandinavia.</p>
   <p>German parents in America are responsible for this, and also their leaders, who think that someone can be a real German patriot even if his mother <pb facs="5423972_2_1073.jpg" n="4"/>tongue is English. They believe that an English-speaking American, in this melting pot of all nations, is as closely related to all other nations, as to England, the language of which country is spoken here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
