<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1890-02-14">February 14, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">Contrasts</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0343</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0343.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1890-02-14">February 14, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">CONTRASTS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Inter-Oceanic city, already very famous among the civilized nations, is also fast becoming a far famed co<gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>opolitan center. Let but Congress once declare Chicago to be the site for the World's Exhibition and presto, our houses of worship, temples and synagogues will be thrown open to the Jewish people from all climes and countries where they pay homage and devotion to their God according to their heart's desires. Unlike other large communities, as in foreign countries, we have the most complex variety of beliefs and forms of worship; a most singular contrast may be observed as follows: Let us take some of our English speaking brethren to Dr. Hirsch's Sinai Temple any Sunday morning. A solemn awe pervades the Moorish auditorium. The simple pulpit betokens no silken or embroidered table spread, but the illustrious orator sits alone contemplating beside it - not in the regulation costume and without the talith, but in plain broad-cloth modern fashioned clothes, his swarthy aspect infuses a consciousness that he will say some things that will instruct as well as admonish. The great organ <pb facs="5423972_2_0344.jpg" n="2"/>will ere long intone its voluntary, and the artistic quartette render in perfect unison, the hymns appropriate for the usual services. Order, quiet, and decorum reign supreme until the close of the services. Such is in brief the regime at this model temple. Jews and Gentiles fill the house to repletion and the orator discourses at times without bated breath for more than an hour; fettering his hearers with all that is philosophical, religious, historical or ethical and oft not without zest, sarcasm and infinite good humor - when he, himself, is not ruffled. By way of contrast, we will on the following Saturday go to the Beth Hamedrash Hagodol, or Kneseth Israel Temples, the first on Michigan avenue and the second on Canal street, and let us enter with hat on - otherwise the Shammes (Beadle) or some member will remind you that you are b'kales Rosh (bareheaded) which is heathenish. You must come at 9 a. m. for the Schachrith and Mussaf prayers are long. In both, a boys' choral accompanies the reader. The devotees reading with the Cantor, must stand up. No ladies accompany their gentlemen friends, fathers, husbands or brothers - they have a special quarter, usually in a gallery overhead - fenced off with wire gauze or wicker work, (an Oriental idea and possibly to avoid flirtation or "mashing") between the dusky worshippers). The male devotees in their Sabbath go-to-meeting garbs, are devout. They cover their heads with talithim (prayer shawls) <pb facs="5423972_2_0345.jpg" n="3"/>and shake their upper bodies quite lustily - some forward and backward, others from right to left. One - in a basso-profundo, others with sharp tenor voices. The edifice at times sounds like the convocation of some Mohammedan Dervishes or a meeting of Voodoo Africans, who all join in one general palaver. The prayers in themselves are in beautifully constructed sentences, fervent and soul inspiring, but these devotees believe that the Jewish Jehovah would not understand them unless the regular Nigan (melody) was sung with it, an evidence that they do not know what they are praying or saying. On extra holidays the Raf (Rabbi) may deliver a derasha (sermon), but these discourses are unintelligible to any except those who understand their jargon language. These are our Simon-pure orthodox Jews - their ritual is Minhag Polen - and no abatement is permitted. Thus if some of our Russo-Polish, Galician, Rumanian, and other Oriental brethren come, we can take them to thirty such Minyans in our great Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
