<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-06-13">June 13, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The American Flag</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Leopold Deutelbaum</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0415</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0415.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-06-13">June 13, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICAN FLAG</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Leopold Deutelbaum</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How many are there who have given deep thought to the true significance of the "Star and Stripes"? Alas! too few Americans appreciate its real meaning and the message it conveys. In speaking of the American Flag, the question of its origin very naturally arises. Not quite one year after the signing of the Declaration of Independence, Congress passed a resolution providing that the nation should have a national flag, consisting of thirteen alternating red and white stripes and a blue field with thirteen stars. A committee composed of George Washington and two others was appointed to have such a flag made.</p>
   <p>The design was carried to Betsy Ross in Philadelphia, and she made the first American flag. The flag was displayed for the first time June 14, 1777, and to commemorate the first appearance of our flag we now <pb facs="5423972_2_0416.jpg" n="2"/>celebrate Flag Day. Several changes were made in the flag during the first ten years after its birth, but they were all abolished. It was finally decided to observe the admission of a state by adding one new star for each state on the Fourth of July following its admission.</p>
   <p>The colors in our flag may be taken in a symbolic sense, the red representing the blood shed by our Revolutionary fathers and the ardent love of their country, the white symbolizing purity and the blue, truth. If we look into the past we see what great deeds the flag has inspired. The sight of our flag filled our soldiers with renewed hope and courage and has not infrequently changed seeming defeat into victory. How many thousands have laid down their lives that the flag might live?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0417.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The sight of our flag fills our hearts with emotion, but we rarely appreciate its deeper significance. It symbolizes the thirteen colonies, the struggle, trials, and successes of our nation; in short, its whole history. The flag should spur us on to emulate the examples of our noble ancestors by trying to become useful and productive citizens of our glorious country.</p>
   <p>The Jewish American, I am quite sure, experiences feelings of pride and patriotism on seeing the flag, only very much intensified. Reviled, hunted, and persecuted even to death for centuries by all the world, the Jew comes to America where he is accorded freedom, protection, and the same rights as are granted to people of other creeds. America has become the haven of refuge for cur persecuted co-religionists and has granted them an equal chance to rise in the world. The flag of the United States should awaken within his bosom, feelings of love, loyalty and devotion to the flag and to the country which it represents.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0418.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A great orator once said in speaking of the American flag, "The flag never did and I hope never may represent but one policy. That policy is individual manhood, the right to enjoy religious and civil liberty; the right to believe in and worship God according to the dictates of your own conscience; the right to stand protected equally before the law with every other man in the enjoyment of freedom, of personal rights, and of prosperity." This "Gorgeous Ensign of the Republic" symbolizes and protects the great ideas set forth so beautifully and graphically in our immortal Declaration of Independence and which lie at the very basis of our government, the enjoyment of life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness.</p>
   <p>This would be, if it is not already, the true message and significance of the flag to the Jewish American.</p>
   <p>What feelings of pride, patriotism, and loyalty, does the Jewish American feel when on returning from traveling in a foreign land he sees as he enters New York Harbor, the Statue of Liberty, holding aloft the eternal torch of freedom and he sees also the American flag floating everywhere?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
