<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-08">June 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">On the Community Stage</title><title level="a" type="sub">By J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0833</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.9"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.9"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.9"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.9"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.9"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.9"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0833.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 9 (Polish)</item>
     <item>II E 1 (Polish)</item>
     <item>III A (Polish)</item>
     <item>I F 4 (Polish)</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
     <item>IV (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-08">June 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE COMMUNITY STAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">By J. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jews in Douglas Park are in peril of health and life. Park Police and Park detectives do nothing to clear the place of gangs of Polish bandits who spit on old Jewish men and women, throw them off the benches, beat them and small Jewish children until the blood flows.</p>
   <p>Only when strong Jewish boys come to defend the weak and helpless, do the "order-keepers" appear, those of John P. Smulski, president of the West Park Board. Then they make arrests, arresting, of course, the Jewish boys, and for duty's sake, two or three Poles. Among those arrested last Monday evening was, as is now known, Dave Levitt. He was so badly beaten that the blood dripped over him, but this did not stop Smulski's "order-keepers" from taking him too with the Polish boys to the station.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0834.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following day, Tuesday, at the trial in Boys Court, Judge Trude freed Levitt, passing sentence on the other boys of three dollars each and costs, and a warning not to enter the Park for one month.</p>
   <p>Wednesday more Poles were arraigned before the Judge for attacks on Jews in the Park. The sentence was ten dollars each and costs. They were also put on probation for six months. Among those who received the same fate, was Charles Abrams, 1958 Kedzie Avenue, who defended himself when attacked, but the police gave testimony to the contrary, accusing him of being guilty.</p>
   <p>In passing sentence, Judge Trude remarked that the best thing to do to stop these occurrences would be to close the Park.</p>
   <p>It appears that Judge Trude knows little of the matter from his remarks. It is understood that he looks upon these occurrences as an "even fight"</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0835.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>between the two nationalities. But in this he is mistaken. Let someone translate for him one of the articles in the Polish newspapers, and he will see how Poles seek Jewish blood and endeavor to make the life of the Jew miserable. The attacks of Poles on Jews are not confined to the Park, but are also carried on in shops and in the streets.</p>
   <p>These attacks of Poles on Jews occur daily. It is for the authorities to see that an end be put to this. Today Judge Trude said the Park should be closed. Tomorrow another will say Jewish stores should be closed. Still another will, the following day say Jews should not walk in the streets at night to avoid attacks. Where and in which country do we live?</p>
   <p>We are not in Rumania and certainly not in Poland. We are in a country where our lives, property, and freedom are guaranteed by the Constitution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0836.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Poles in Chicago attack Jews, their newspapers advocate boycotting Jews, and public officials of Polish extraction permit, by their anti-Semitic statements, our order-keeping men to ignore action in the Park.</p>
   <p>It has already gone too far.</p>
   <p>We appeal, therefore, directly to the Honorable Frank A. Lowdon, governor of this state, for aid. Let Douglas Park be placed under care of the militia which will not permit gangs of your, Poles to have their way there.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
