<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-06-13">June 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Vigilance Committee to Combat Caricatures</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1201</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1201.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-06-13">June 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">VIGILANCE COMMITTEE TO COMBAT CARICATURES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The war on the ugly caricatures of Jewish life on the stage is being waged by Chicago Jewry, and all means will be applied to eradicate the clique, who make it their business to represent an ugly caricature of the Jew on the American stage.</p>
   <p>This ugliness is known as the "Stage Jew," and the fool who plays the "stage Jew" role becomes, very often, provoking not only to the Jews but also to the better class of our Gentile neighbors.</p>
   <p>In order to eradicate the stage Jew, a vigilance committee was formed. The committee held its first meeting last evening in the Sherman Hotel, where more than seventy-five societies were represented. Judge Hugo Pam was chairman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1202.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The object of this vigilance committee is to combat the "stage Jew" and at the meeting last evening a permanent Ways and Means Committee was appointed whose task will be to look out for these caricatures and report them to the committee who will apply all means to evacuate this infamy.</p>
   <p>It was also determined that not only will the Ways and Means Committee watch for the "stage Jew," but will also devote its attention to the scandalous post cards, newspapers, and magazines which print, from time to time, such pictures which are not very gratifying to the Jew.</p>
   <p>Among the prominent workers in eradicating this infamy are: Judge Pam, Mrs. Mollie Asherman, Dr. Schoenfarber, Mrs. I. Mandel, Mrs. Joseph Schiff, Prof. Ernst Freund, Adolph Crown, Mrs. Isadore Natkin, Mrs. H. N. Solomon, Jacob M. Loeb, Congressman Adolph J. Sabath, Mrs. A. I. Rice, I. Berzog, Mrs. M. L. Purvin, Karl Stanhill, and Mrs. B. M. Englehardt.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
