<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-11-25">Nov. 25, 1905</date>, 4:5.
<title level="a">America the Promised Land Rabbi Hirsch Says Jews Do Not Want Any Zionist Movement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-11-25">Nov. 25, 1905</date>, 4:5.
<title level="a">AMERICA THE PROMISED LAND RABBI HIRSCH SAYS JEWS DO NOT WANT ANY ZIONIST MOVEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jews alone of all other religious bodies in America have been the consistent backers of the public schools. This was one of the chief facts adduced to prove the pure Americanism of those members of the Jewish race who have made this country their home by Dr. Emil G. Hirsch in his address at Temple Israel, as the hall was packed to its capacity.</p>
   <p>"Americanism and Judaism are fundamentally the same" said Dr. Hirsch. "Americanism is the fulfillment of the principles for which Judaism has always stood. In America the Hebrew has come at last to the reality of his promised land. We as a race do not need any Zionist movement. We need not return to Palestine. We need no special flag. We have a flag of our own, the flag for which 6,000 Jews, twenty per cent of the Jewish population at that time, offered up their lives in the great combat against slavery.</p>
   <p>"The Jew is a standing rebuke to a narrow-minded hyphenated style of citizenship <pb facs="5423972_2_1338.jpg" n="2"/>which adds a foreign prefix to the glorious title of simple American. German Jews, Russian Jews, oriental Jews are all Americans, pure and simple. Our people alone have stood shoulder to shoulder with that sturdy type of citizenship which created and has maintained the public schools of this country. The Jew believes whole-heartedly in the public schools as a fundamental American civilization."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
