<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-13">July 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">On the Community Stage</title><title level="a" type="sub">By J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0785</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0785.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Polish)</item>
     <item>III B 2 (Polish)</item>
     <item>I G (Polish)</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-13">July 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE COMMUNITY STAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">By J. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Chicago, as we know, there can be found the main offices of the Anti-Defamation League, a body organized by the Order B'nai Brith for the purpose of curbing the spread of anti-Semitism in this country. It has succeeded in stopping many movies of anti-Semitic tendencies, and has driven from the stage many actors who ridicule Jews. We must admit to its credit that it was instrumental in influencing the Associated Press to omit all references to "so and so swindler or murderer, a Jew". It is even said that the Anti-Defamation League convinced the Associated Press not to attribute every unfavorable Bolshevik report and so-called Bolshevik murder to the Jew, Leon Trotsky, but to Nicolai Lenin. This, of course, we doubt very much because the Associated Press has of late been preoccupied with Leon Trotsky and even more so with Bela Kun of Hungary who is more of a Jew than the former.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0786.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whatever the result may be, the purpose of the League is a good one, and we must credit it with its various accomplishments. Yet it has done nothing, except in Detroit, to stop the Polish press from printing anti-Semitic cartoons and incendiary articles about Jews. Quite noteworthy in the light of their negligence is the published letter requesting individuals not to protest, just to leave it to the League, to depend on the League.</p>
   <p>There are Polish publications in Chicago which even in Bucharest would be suppressed by proper means and government measures. Yet here in a city in free America, they make their appearance unmolested, to the shame of decent Christians, the misfortune of Jews, and the weakness of the United States which circulates such matter, granting it the same privileges given to honorable, law-abiding and ethical publications.</p>
   <p>For several months now the local Polish press has worked havoc against Jews. Picturing them in the most hideous forms, it urges its readers to boycott <pb facs="5423972_2_0787.jpg" n="3"/>Jewish stores, and incites to pogroms. Thanks to the press, Poles of South Chicago pinned the "blood accusation" on the family of Cohen. Also due to it, Jews in Polish neighborhoods fear for their lives. The many tales about Poles being beaten and thrown out of Jewish shops are written to enforce the boycott.</p>
   <p>What has, and what is the Anti-Defamation League doing about this "plague" in Chicago? We ask this question, but no one seems to know the answer because the Anti-Defamation League here is run by Jews who avoid any honest, open criticism.</p>
   <p>In Detroit, on the other hand, the Anti-Defamation group is different. There too the Polish Daily News followed in the steps of its fellow papers in Chicago. Mr. Milton M. Alexander of Detroit's branch of the Anti-Defamation League set to work. In less than two weeks the editor, Mr. Kovalski, was ousted and the paper's stockholders printed a public apology. Since then the Polish Daily News is honorable and fair to Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0788.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Scoffers remark, "How could it happen unless the stockholders of Detroit's Polish daily newspaper were Jews?" They cannot conceive of the Anti-Defamation League advancing thus far in its field of battle, nor that Poles could become so big-hearted as to leave Jews alone. But the fact remains that the new editor declares himself to be in disagreement with Kovalski's policy and we have, therefore, in Detroit, less of a boycott and fewer broken heads.</p>
   <p>Let Chicago's office of the Anti-Defamation League awaken from its lethargic slumber and follow the example set by its Detroit branch. Local Poles are no longer satisfied with newspaper articles only, and have begun to print a series of brochures defending their acts of boycott and pogrom.</p>
   <p>The first brochure to appear these days was one by Mr. N. L. Piotrovski, former city attorney of Chicago, a leader of the Polish National Alliance. We do not know whether or not he was anti-Semitic during his term of office, but by his writings we know that he is now.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0789.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>He definitely denies [the existence of] pogroms in Poland, displaying ignorance of actual conditions there. His loyalty to that country must be greater than it is to America otherwise his official organ would not be permitted to incite one class of people against another. He is an artful person and a liar too.</p>
   <p>He tells, for instance, this: in the vote for the Russian Council, Russian Jews in Poland forced their candidate, an ignorant iron laborer to be elected as representative of Poland's first city, Warsaw; then he tauntingly declares that the Jews, and not the Poles, were leaders in Warsaw and that the country was not Poland but Judea Poland. Mr. Piotrovski, the ignorant iron laborer you refer to is a Pole named Yagello.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere in this brochure he speaks of "cities" of Jews existing in America. It was in these cities that Poles made pogroms. Jews in Poland died from various causes, and he adds questioningly, "What do Jews seek there? Perhaps they were caught stealing."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0790.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Braggingly he continues; had it not been for Poland the Turks would have overrun Europe. And thanks to them (Poles), Christianity and civilization were saved for mankind.</p>
   <p>He goes on to say: Poles were loyal to the Allies but the Jews and Bolsheviks were under German influence and spread German propaganda, thus undermining Poland's existence. He points out that in spite of everything Poles are very good to Jews, they respect them; for example, the Polish National Alliance has thirty Jewish directors, among whom prominently figures Nathan Kalman Zlotnizki (Corngold).</p>
   <p>We do not believe that the Polish National Alliance has thirty Jewish directors. But if it has, the Alliance is welcome to them. Even if his statement is false or deceptive we still thank Mr. Piotrovski, because acceptance of Jews as leaders or members in such an anti-Semitic institution is apparently a sign of deference to our people. It remains for the Anti-Defamation League, if it is <pb facs="5423972_2_0791.jpg" n="7"/>too inert for other tasks, at least to inform the American population that Jews in the Polish National Alliance are not Jews but traitors to their God and their people. In the end they will betray the Poles because a traitor to one country cannot possibly remain true to another.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
