<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1908-09-05">Sept. 5, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Health and Diet</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1908-09-05">Sept. 5, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">HEALTH AND DIET</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The writer has exceptional opportunities to observe and judge upon all matters pertaining to the dietary laws. Before he could be pronounced competent to fill a high and important office he would have to comply with the rules and regulations required for the training of one who is called upon, not only to obey, but also to expound the Mosaic Laws. In his endeavors to secure the proper observance of the dietary laws the writer has discovered how frequently those who ought to know better attempt to evade the requirements of the laws. How many young Jews disregard the commands regarding diet and eat all kinds of trefa! They appear to regard it as a sign of superior knowledge and feel proud and disdainful in the presence of those who would suffer hunger rather than eat unclean food. Yet when sickness and disease comes they change their attitude and wake up to the necessity of the dietary laws--when they discover that kosher food has kept the faithful from disease whilst they themselves <pb facs="5423972_2_0318.jpg" n="2"/>are under doctor's care because they ate meat which poisoned their blood and ruined their stomach.</p>
   <p>It is a well-known fact that when plagues have swept away the trefa-eating population of a whole city the faithful Jews have been spared from disease and death. It is important then that when huge letters on the windows of a restaurant announce it to be kosher, it should be so. Yet the writer has observed that the sign "kosher," whether in English or in Yiddish, is but a trap for the unwary. Even where signs of wealth and elegance and an elaborate menu appear, as in some downtown resturants, the visitor expecting to receive a kosher meal is chagrined to learn the prices are high but that the diet is nonkosher. From Halsted, Maxwell, and Twelfth Street, from the West Side to the South Side a lover of kosher food is in danger of being victimized by those who fail to cater honestly to the Jew who desires to adhere to the dietary laws.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
