<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-24">Aug. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Jewish Superstitions]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-24">Aug. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[JEWISH SUPERSTITIONS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Jews are really fine, likeable people, as fine and likeable as they were in the old country.....The Chicago Jews are not fanatics; on the contrary, they are very liberal people. For instance, a Jew who lives in the Lawndale district is a member of an Orthodox synagogue, but as soon as he moves to the North Side, he becomes a member of a Reform temple. Many Chicago Jews are not particular about their articles of faith, and they are not fanatical adherents of a certain set of principles. However, there are a few principles in which the Chicago Jews firmly believe. These principles are:</p>
   <p>1. That every dead body must be brought to the synagogue and a funeral oration must be delivered; otherwise the soul of the dead person will not go to heaven by express train.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0565.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>2. That weddings and wedding suppers must be held in a Down-Town hotel; otherwise the newlyweds will be unhappy.</p>
   <p>3. That the newly arrived immigrants, the greenhorns, have no brains, and that all wisdom is lodged in the Chicago Jews.</p>
   <p>4. That Shnevr Zalmen [J. Loebner] fights the world every Wednesday, with his Galician Jews.</p>
   <p>5. That during the rending of the Torah, one should chatter and gossip.</p>
   <p>6. That by giving to charity, one becomes poor.</p>
   <p>7. That every Reform rabbi is an educated man.</p>
   <p>8. That the editor of a Jewish newspaper is a public errand-boy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0566.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>9. That with his twenty-five or fifty-dollar donation to the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization], he [the Jew] is making the Jewish people happy, he is building Palestine, and fulfilling all of his Jewish duties; he thereby deserves a million dollars' worth of publicity and ten million dollars' worth of Paradise.</p>
   <p>10. That it is better [to have] money without a man than [to have] a man without money.</p>
   <p>If my dearly beloved Chicago Jews will ever get rid of these superstitions, they will really become civilized.</p>
   <p>Will we ever live to see that day?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
