<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-19">October 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Protest Extra. Chicago's Greatest Speakers Tell the Truth Regarding the Kiev Tragedy</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-19">October 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST EXTRA. CHICAGO'S GREATEST SPEAKERS TELL THE TRUTH REGARDING THE KIEV TRAGEDY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Over a hundred thousand Chicago citizens came to protest against the blood accusation. This accusation was today denounced by America's greatest and foremost personalities.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called for 2 P. M., but the crowd began to gather at eleven in the morning. The street cars and elevators were packed with thousands of people who were anxious to secure a seat for this historical occasion to which Chicago has added a well written chapter in the history of the fight for human justice and rights.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1153.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>About 12 o'clock noon, it was seen that the Grand Opera House was much too small to house even a small percentage of the large audience that responded so enthusiastically to the call of the committee sponsoring this meeting. The Garrick Theater was then pressed into use, but within half an hour this large theater was also filled. The thousands who were unable to gain admittance surrounded both theaters and stood patiently listening to the various speakers who expressed their opinions of Russia and her justice.</p>
   <p>The meeting at the Grand Opera House opened punctually at 2 o'clock. Judge Edward A. Brown of the Appellate Court was the chairman. He explained the purpose of the meeting and announced as the first speaker Miss Jane Addams of the Hull House. Other speakers were:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1154.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dr. E. G. Hirsch, Rabbi of the Sinai Congregation; Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, Superintendent of Chicago Schools; Rev. F. J. O'Kelloghan, Secretary of the Society of Paulist Fathers; Prof. George B. Foster, University of Chicago; and Prof. Booker T. Washington, Tuskegee Institute. Everytime Russia or Tsar Nicholas was mentioned the large audience expressed itself by hissing and whistling, just as the mention of the great efforts exerted for justice, such as was begun by Chicago citizens were greeted by thunderous applause which made the walls tremble.</p>
   <p>On the platform sat the committee of twenty-one which brought to this meeting members representing every nationality, leaders of various divisions both in politics and social life. The committee consisted of the following persons:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1155.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Miss Jane Addams, Hull House; T. W. Ellinson, Henry Booth House; Mrs. Louise Deck Bowen, President of Juvenile Protection; Mrs. George Bass, President of Chicago Women's Club; Alfred L. Baker, Vice President of National City Bank; Miss Sophrowisba Breckenridge, University of Chicago; Honorable Edward A. Brown, Judge of Illinois; Honorable John Gibbons, Judge of the Circuit Court; Honorable S. S. Gregory, American Bar Association; Dr. Abram W. Harris, President of Northwestern University; Dr. Jenkin Lloyd Johns, Lincoln Center; Honorable Julian W. Mack, United States Circuit Court; Mrs. John McMahan, Catholic Women's League; Prof. George Meade, University of Chicago; Mrs. M. L. Farwin, Chicago Women's Aid; Julius Rosenwald, Civic Federation; Honorable Cookham Skanlon, Judge of Circuit Court; Mrs. Hannah G. Solomon, Council of Jewish Women; Dr. Graham Taylor, Chicago Commons; Prof. I. W. Thomas, University of Chicago; and Mrs. Mary T. Wilmarte, Women's City Club.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1156.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Among those who were given honorary place on the platform were:</p>
   <p>Adolf Kraus, President of the B'nai B'rith; B. Horwich, President of Federated Charities; Booker T. Washington, Professor of Tuskegee Institute; and Harry A. Lipsky, of the Jewish Courier.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
