<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-09-01">September 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Cooperative Grocery Sells All Articles at Cost Price to Unemployed Union Members</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1635</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1635.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-09-01">September 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">COOPERATIVE GROCERY SELLS ALL ARTICLES AT COST PRICE TO UNEMPLOYED UNION MEMBERS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The members of trade unions who are unemployed will get everything which the cooperative grocery sells, and meals in cooperative restaurants for cost price only. This is the resolution adopted Monday evening at a meeting of the United Control Committee of both cooperative grocery stores and of the cooperative restaurant. After discussing what should be done for the unemployed members of trade unions, they adopted a resolution that every member who comes to the cooperative stores at 2733 W. Division street, and 3310 W. 15th street, with a note from the secretary stating that he is entitled to groceries for cost price, shall be granted such a service. The single man who will come to the cooperative restaurant, will be able to buy a meal ticket, whose regular price is $6, for $5, or a sixty cents meal for fifty cents.</p>
   <p>The Joint Committee believes that the union members who do not work, will be satisfied to save a few dollars a week for the necessities of life in order <pb facs="5423972_2_1636.jpg" n="2"/>to benefit from the cooperation which makes possible the organization of workers, during slack and in strike periods. Let all the trade unions whose members are unemployed get in touch with the manager of the cooperative grocery stores and arrangements will be made to save as much money as is possible for their members every week, through cooperation and brotherly solidarity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
