<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-11-08">November 8, 1930</date>. p.365.
<title level="a">Hatikvah and Reform</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-11-08">November 8, 1930</date>. p.365.
<title level="a">HATIKVAH AND REFORM</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is a well known rabbinic tradition that Jerusalem was destroyed nineteen-hundred years ago because of a trivial incident for which a certain Kamtzo "bar Kamtzo" was responsible. The result here, as so often in Jewish and general history, was certainly out of all proportion to its alleged occasion. A somewhat kindred consequence seems to threaten just now in the pending discussion about the inclusion of "Hatikvah" in the revised Union Hymnal about to be published by the Central Conference of American Rabbis. Doubtless prompted by some Freudian impulse in which the thought is fathered by the wish, certain of our Zionist friends have already triumphantly acclaimed the mere suggestion of such a thing as the final surrender of Reform Judaism to the nationalistic platform of Zionism. Rather gleefully and prematurely, they clap their hands in celebration of what they believe to be the complete capitulation of Reform, because of the latter's tolerant entertainment of the sheer idea that Zionism's theme song could possibly find its way into the Reform liturgy. The situation certainly calls for some clarification and restatement.</p>
   <p>What is the nature and content of "Hatikvah"? Its melody, as noted by the late Israel Abrahams ("By-paths in Hebraic Bookland," p.259 FF.), is reminiscent of <pb facs="5423972_2_0425.jpg" n="2"/>a Polish folk-tune and an old Sephardic hymn. It is certainly inviting and alluring enough to the ear, and is even sung at the table in Jewish homes on Sabbath and holidays, to the words of Psalm 126. A Reform Hymnal could readily enough, therefore, accept "Hatikvah's" melody without the slightest offense to non-Zionist ears. But what of its words? "Hatikvah" (The Hope) is the burden of its series of stanzas. So long as Israel continues to pilgrim to the tombs of the fathers, so long as a single eye is left to shed its tear over the temple ruins, so long as the waters of the Jordan roll on to the Sea of Kinnereth, so long as a drop of blood still courses through Jewish veins, so long as Israel continues to hold its national aspirations - so long shall we hope for the fulfillment of these aspirations, so long will Israel hope for the return to and the rebuilding of the land of our fathers. But as Abrahams has pointedly asked, what is to be the purpose and the end of this return and rebuilding; what is the ultimate ideal at which it aims? No suggestions of Messianism or universalism here. Purely a physical rebuilding and nationalistic restoration; Palestine as the end, and nothing more. This is "Hatikvah," the hope and the end of Israel.</p>
   <p>The futility, not to say ineptness of such a limited "hope" in the liturgical aspirations of Reform Judaism must be immediately obvious. For here is <pb facs="5423972_2_0426.jpg" n="3"/>expressed a decisive difference between Zionism and Reform in their respective interpretations of Jewish history and Jewish destiny. In the philosophy of Reform, Palestine can no longer be the end of Israel, either as a religion or a people. "On the day when the temple was destroyed," reads the well-known Talmudic dictum, "the Messiah was born (YER.BER-II)." At best, Palestine can be only a means - one of the many in the so-called Diaspora - to what Orthodoxy and Reform alike call Messianism. But whatever the interpretation of Orthodox Judaism, the Messiah, for Reform, is not an individual person, a royal dynasty nor a political movement. It is an era of universal justice, righteousness and peace, in the realization of which Israel will continue to enact the leading and exemplary role. That role, we maintain, is not nationalistic as that term is defined by Zionism - although the Jew today may be, and is, a thorough-going national of every land, including Palestine. It is primarily spiritual, ethical, social; it is religious.</p>
   <p>We may well concede that Israel today is something more than merely a religious community. It is a religion plus. A religious system which for numberless centuries has consistently indoctrinated the heart of, and life of its devotees, with certain spiritual, ethical, and social ideals, will inevitably inbreed <pb facs="5423972_2_0427.jpg" n="4"/>in those devotees what modern psychology calls a psyche - a specific psychologic consciousness - along the lines of those ideals; it is psyche which constitutes the plus in the Jew's distinctiveness among the peoples.</p>
   <p>But this plus, though distinctive, is still religious and not political in its aim, just as it is universalistic and not nationalistic in its scope. And in so far as Zionism can assist in the conversion and extension of this psychologic, religious consciousness. Reform certainly does not oppose nor resist it. On the contrary, it welcomes it. How genuine and effective that welcome is, has been amply demonstrated in the generous financial and moral support which the Reform synagogue has consistently given to the program of Palestinian agricultural, industrial, economic, and cultural rehabilitation throughout the postwar period.</p>
   <p>Certainly it should be ungrudgingly admitted that, except for such support, the plight of Palestinian Jewry were far less tolerable than current reports would indicate. But when Zionism insists on interpreting Judaism and Jewish history in terms of political nationalism, and would lay claim to Palestine as "the" national homeland instead of "a" national homeland, akin to many others of modern Israel, it proclaims a philosophy that not only runs counter to the <pb facs="5423972_2_0428.jpg" n="5"/>philosophy of Reform, but also jeopardizes the various hard won nationalisms of world-Israel, even as it unfortunately has already done in Palestine itself. Historically, it should not be forgotten, our modern Reform came into being concurrently with the growth of a newer conception of nationalism among civilized peoples. In spite of popular medieval conceptions still realistically current in lands where the Jew has become politically emancipated, this newer legal conception makes it not only possible but obligatory for the Jew to be a national of the land which is his home, in fullest consistency with the prophetic universalism of his ancestral faith.</p>
   <p>Despite the sophistries and protestations of political Zionists to the contrary, therefore, a particularistic Jewish nationalism is inevitably in conflict, not only with the universalism of his religion, but also with the nationalism of the land in which he claims citizenship. It is no doubt true that there are Reform Jews, in America and elsewhere, who can outscream the eagle in the raucousness of their new found nationalism. We have also known some political Zionists whose eagle-screaming are no less vociferous; who in fact, have been able, successfully, to capitalize this new-found nationalism to the extent of climbing to American nationalistic positions by persuading the other fellow, <pb facs="5423972_2_0429.jpg" n="6"/>if not themselves, of the utter "perishableness" of the thought that there could be such a thing as conflict between an American and a Palestinian nationalism.</p>
   <p>Accordingly, it may be true that there are some American Reform Jews who like to conceive of America as an isolated chauvinistic nationalism, just as there are some American Zionists who love to glorify the unquestioned idealism and courage of pioneer Chalutzim, in leaving their native habitat for a Palestinian Zion while the glorifiers themselves, prefer to "sit tight" in the political luxury and physical ease of their own American Zion. Reform Judaism, however, insists on a nationalism, whether in America or in Palestine, that is universalistic, and not merely chauvinistic. A distinctive Jewish nationalism in America is no more consistent in its philosophy than is the supposititious American nationalism of the Klu Klux Klan. Whatever the case in other nationalities, America, as Israel without a universalistic consciousness, is essentially un-Jewish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
