<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-02">Sept. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">It Is Dawning</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-02">Sept. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">IT IS DAWNING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After lengthy debates, heated discussions, and stormy exciting strifes and conflicts, dawn is beginning to break in the Jewish community in Chicago. The first lines and contours are already recognizable to the eye.</p>
   <p>Until now the Jewish community was left to its own fate. Everyone did as he pleased. Whoever so desired became a public officer. Whoever so wished became the founder of an institution. There was no authority in Chicago to regulate the public life or the religious life. Everything was simply left to fate, and it was a shame and a disgrace. The second largest Jewish community in the world was a desert, and is not an organized Kehilah (united Jewish congregations) even now. But already the first rays of light can be seen, and it is to be hoped that in a few weeks or months order will be restored in the city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0175.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is no Beth Din (Jewish religious court) yet, but there is an organized and conscientious corporation of Rabbis in the field of religious matters. At present, the Rabbis are occupied with the Shechitah (animal slaughtering), according to the Mosaic law. This is not an easy task, because there are about two hundred Shochets (animal slaughterers) in Chicago who, until now, have been indifferent as to the laws to be observed in the slaughtering of meat. But we hear that everything is now going on properly. The Rabbis are working steadily on the problem of placing the Shechitah on a proper basis. If they work in harmony they certainly will be successful in their endeavors. More important than the reorganization of the Shechitah is this co-operation of Rabbis. From it will arise a Beth Din, which will serve as the highest religious authority in the city in religious and social matters. The Rabbis realize now how important it is to have a Beth Din in the city, because they realize what could be accomplished if they work in unison. In the common work of unison lies their strength, and the strength of Orthodox Judaism.</p>
   <p>We are not too optimistic, but we believe that a Beth Din will soon rise in <pb facs="5423972_2_0176.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago. We do not have to explain to our readers what progress the establishment of such an institution must mean to the city. And, when there is a Beth Din in Chicago, then will come the communal problems which will demand immediate solution.</p>
   <p>A Beth Din must have a communal authority upon which it can depend for support. What can this authority be? Not the individual congregations nor even a number of congregations, but all congregations united. And that is a Kehilah. To place a Kehilah upon a solid foundation means hard work and great sacrifice. But the work will have to be done. The tendency of self-preservation in Chicago's Orthodox Jewry will compel the Chicago Jew to start the work. They can delay the task for a certain time, but sooner or later it will have to be done, because life itself will compel the Chicago Jews to do it.</p>
   <p>When the Chicago Jews begin the work they will find--of that they may be sure--a devoted coworker and a strong supporter in the Courier. If there is <pb facs="5423972_2_0177.jpg" n="4"/>anything within our power that will help in the constructive work and to assist in creating order out of the present chaos, we shall certainly be glad to do it.</p>
   <p>We are glad to see such a good start, and we shall be much happier when we see that from a small beginning something big and important has developed.</p>
   <p>A bright new dawn is coming soon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
