<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-07-10">July 10, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Religion and "Intelligentsia"</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. B. Komaiko</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0455</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0455.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-07-10">July 10, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">RELIGION AND "INTELLIGENTSIA"</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. B. Komaiko</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is not my intention to propagate religion; I am not concerned to debate: "Will Orthodoxy Prevail in the Jewish Community"? or "Has Reform any Substance"? or "Will Conservatism Over-balance the other two Wings of Jewry"?</p>
   <p>Our authority, also, for searching the depths of theology is limited, although heart and soul ever feel a spiritual satisfaction under the influence of faith.</p>
   <p>Faith always supplied an urge to accomplish material things for the good and welfare of humanity. If Christianity is more passive than our faith, and Buddhism is altogether opposed to materialism-that alone shows that all faiths are more or less concerned with the "material" in our existence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0456.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Touching the matter superficially, I will return to our own situation. It will be interesting to the reader, whether he believes or disbelieves, to know facts that will convince him that religion is a powerful influence, a marvelous influence upon the home and upon education. Let us hark back thirty years - when the Jewish community of Chicago began to grow great; when our peddlers, old-country tailors or "made" tailors, began to bring their families over, and to establish homes for themselves and their wives and children. Somewhat later, entire families came, among whom were found the "intelligentsia" of Russia.</p>
   <p>The peddlers, tailors, refined people from "home," "maskilim," all founded large congregations and small ones, which later grew into powerful organizations. The synagogues served as centers, wherein the Jewish life firmly imbedded itself in the new land. Later on there grew up Talmud Torahs, where the youth received a real Jewish up-bringing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0457.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The founding of mutual benefit societies is, in itself, a long chapter in the history of our community in Chicago. Then came Zionism - which not only received a dignified welcome in the synagogues, but also gained a large following among those who had cooled off in their attitude towards Jewish life. Zionism brought them back to the synagogue and the synagogue Jew raised children who had a feeling for Judaism.</p>
   <p>The Jewish "Intelligentsia" of Russia which, in the "old" country had avoided the synagogue, did not, in the new land, "walk a mile" for a mincha. Like all other classes of Jews, they had their hard times under the new circumstances. The younger element worked by day and studied by night. Many of them attained prominence in various professions. At the time, when <pb facs="5423972_2_0458.jpg" n="4"/>the synagogue Jew was enjoying the spiritual pleasure found in the synagogue and the lodge, where the orderliness of American life gradually penetrated, the "Intelligentsia" spent their time in their "circle" in an atmosphere into which Russia and its river Volga or Dnieper had been imported (mentally), where they chatted in Russian, and "chewed the rag," "kok-doma," like at home.</p>
   <p>When an "intellectual" entered a profession he was well content to settle, in the Jewish neighborhood where he might earn his bread, but to take part in Jewish affairs, that was against his principles.</p>
   <p>The average Jew raised a generation, who saw on the walls of their homes pictures of Reb Isaac Elchonon, of Moses Montefiore, and of others of the immortal Jewish great.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0459.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The "intellectual" brought up his young to see, on the walls of "papa's" house, the pictures of Tolstoi Pushkin, Gorki, and if a bit socialistically inclined, a small one of Karl Marx.</p>
   <p>We do not agree with the proverb that "time flies." Time is eternal but we run on, we grow older, we become aged. Those Jews of thirty years ago have grown old, the "intellectual" of that period was grown old, his responsibilities have been assumed by his children - by a new generation.</p>
   <p>Now let us consider which of the children of the new generation are socially useful, which of them feel and understand their duties to their own community, in particular, and to their people, in general.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0460.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It would be a difficult task to make a systematic canvass of the situation. It would be impossible to group all the children of such parents in order to show the actual effects of their activity and point of view.</p>
   <p>We, ourselves, have contacted the children who have graduated from higher schools, colleges, universities, or prepared for certain professions, such as medicine, law, engineering, and so forth. In other words, we have made a pencil calculation of a number of "new generation" children of "Shul" fathers, who have received a higher education, and a similar calculation of children of "Intelligentsia" parentage, and without any difficulty the following unassailable conclusions were drawn:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0461.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The young generation of the "Shul" fathers with diplomas on the wall, received religious training as children, grew up as sympathetic persons, Jews with heart and feeling - they can be met in all organized charity activities, in all Jewish movements; their personalities are effective not only in Jewish circles, but they gain glory for us in the general life of our freedom, blessed country.</p>
   <p>Quite otherwise, however, are the children of the "Intelligentsia." It is easy to understand that life in America has deprived them of the glory of a Tolstoi, and of a Gorki, not to mention "Kok-doma" like at home. But nothing else that concerns spirit or ideal has been substituted for that. They have remained materialistically inclined, passive to the interests not only of their brethren, but to everything that might alleviate the distress of humanity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0462.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Their lives are devoted to golf clubs and to other activities that satisfy the race-conscious Jew.</p>
   <p>Only then do they remind themselves that they are Jews, when father or mother pass away, and a stranger helps them say Kaddish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
