<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-06-13">June 13, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0419</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0419.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-06-13">June 13, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">EDITORIAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is presumed in these editorial columns that there is such a purpose as the serving of the Jewish cause, and it is further presumed that the service of this cause is higher than the service of any individual interest which mechanically is one of the instruments whereby the Jewish cause is served. That of course does not mean that the effectiveness of any one of the items is to be minimized, but rather that the value of any item is judged by the contribution of steadiness and achievement that it may make to the all embracing purpose of the Jewish cause. Readers who totally disagree with this preamble need not read any further, unless they just want to see what can be said in advocacy of something which they had long ago given up as hopeless. The two presumptions are, however, fundamentally necessary for the further development of the subject.</p>
   <p>American Judaism has taken on some of the methods of the business world. The theories under which men worked in the business world underlie also our religious constructions in this country. We certainly did lay stress on the individual prowess, and objected to any real pooling of the interests of all of the efforts and achievements of the individual person or organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0420.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A constitution of the Union of American Hebrew Congregations very zealously safeguards the autonomy of the congregations who were listed under the banners of the Union. Orthodox congregations without even the semblance of a union organized whenever any individual thought the time had come when he might organize a congregation and assume the presidency. Whether the Jewish cause was being served by having a thousand struggling associations - Chevroth - as in orthodoxy, or autonomous congregations as in Reform Judaism, few stopped to question. It is true that some people still had the memory of a "gemeinde" to which every Jew had to belong and by virtue of his adherence had certain rights and privileges and certain duties of support. These may also have had a memory of a community that supported all the rabbis as rabbis of the community, rather than of any one congregation and of schools that did not show wide difference as to purpose and methods. But such people were answered by the simple statement that this was America. And the answer meant that any plan of any other land was simply annihilated by the difference in geography.</p>
   <p>Fortunately for Judaism in America, there never were any serious financial difficulties that had to be faced. There was plenty of money to support the institutions in a small way. There were of course occasions when some of the smaller sections of the community had their difficulties; they faced them <pb facs="5423972_2_0421.jpg" n="3"/>alone. The larger organizations went their own way and rejoiced in their own success. The great cause of Israel was amply justified, so some congregations thought; if only they existed. They never dreamed of lending a helping hand to the pioneering and path-finding congregations. On the whole, however, the community went along. Occasionally a voice was raised in protest against the snugness of the large and the wealthy congregations, and point was made of the fact that pioneering congregations were subserving a purpose which the right congregations could not minimize.</p>
   <p>Those days are gone, the protests are louder and we are wondering if, in the congregational life of the Jewish community of America, we are learning quickly enough what the present duty is. We are not thinking of the smaller Jewish communities where there is one Reform Congregation - that is the community. But even in the smaller Jewish communities we address the question to the small "Orthodox" and "Semi-Orthodox," or "Modern Orthodox," or "Moderately Conservative" and ask whether the time has not come to form out of all the stunted and sickly Chevroth a substantial congregation, capable of maintaining itself in honor and doing its work with some proud satisfaction.</p>
   <p>Those days are gone. Judaism in its institutions has been hit as everything <pb facs="5423972_2_0422.jpg" n="4"/>else has been hit. The congregational life cannot be stronger than the surrounding financial condition will make it, and who shall say that when great financial institutions are being swept aside that huts will not be overthrown, and equally as true, that when the huts meet the storm and are blown over that sooner or later the storm will touch the larger and the prouder institutions of a decade ago. Congregations are all in the same kind of a boat just now and we are wondering how long it will take for the Jewish community to consider that it is suicidal in the face of a storm to let a boat-load in a leaky boat go out and fight the storm. One by one the boat-load in a leaky boats will come to grief. The Jewish cause is not being protected.</p>
   <p>In a time like this the spiritual values have to be maintained. Without these values there is no use going on. This is a time when men and women have to gather all the strength that they have; strength of patience and endurance, of right valuations, or else our civilization, completely identified with our money, will go to smash. Days of prosperity could not bring the congregations together. They could get along without each other. Perhaps days of adversity will bring congregations - all of them humbled, together.</p>
   <p>Out of days of trial we may emerge with a Jewish community really formed, with congregations allied and united, perhaps under the common board of management.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0423.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>At least the possibility of wresting this great achievement from these days of trial, we would suggest to the lay leaders of the community. We had once upon a time a Federation of Reform Synagogues. For years it has been inactive. A great emergency has arisen and it may stay with us for a while. In that emergency the Federation of Reform Synagogues ought to be called together, and the best brains and the best hearts should labor together to arrange for the continuance of the Jewish cause in its most effective fashion. If the Reform group can do it, then the Conservative group can do it and then the Orthodox group.</p>
   <p>But whoever begins the building - the purpose is the building of a real Jewish community.</p>
   <p>G. B. L.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
