<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1893-09-25">Sept. 25, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Universal Religion and Judaism</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1893-09-25">Sept. 25, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">UNIVERSAL RELIGION AND JUDAISM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Universal Religion and Judaism" was the subject of a sermon by the Rev. E. G. Hirsch of the Jewish Temple, Twenty-first Street and Indiana Avenue, yesterday morning. The theme was inspired by the speeches of the representatives of the various religious denominations of the world as delivered at the Congress of Religions.</p>
   <p>He spoke in part as follows: Religion is necessary to man. The ambition of to-day is not so much to rebuild the temple of our fathers as to create a religion that will be acceptable to all creeds and denominations. It is the "universal" idea that occupies the foreground of our religious hope.</p>
   <p>The typical Jew who goes into rapture when told he is one of the chosen people and blessed of God is egotistical and one with whom I have but little patience. However, as Jew, we have everything we need, but our Jewish Bible is proof of the fact that these historic conditions are not climatic. So the universal religion is after all but a tree. Judaism is conceited in that its prime belief is that it needs no further investigation. Some Jews labor under the belief that the best Christian boy is not good enough to marry the humblest Jewish girl. I <pb facs="5423972_2_1373.jpg" n="2"/>denounce such ideas and have no sympathy with such arrogant nonsense. The old Hebrew religions were the most sensual and self-destroying.</p>
   <p>Judaism has three times refused to make itself the universal religion. One of these occasions was when Christianity stepped out into the world. It was not taken up at this time, as it was correctly believed that Christianity would drift into creeds. When they give up their name, Christianity, we will give up that of Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
