<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-09-26">Sept. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Courier Publishes False Statement about the Cloakmakers Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0561</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0561.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-09-26">Sept. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">COURIER PUBLISHES FALSE STATEMENT ABOUT THE CLOAKMAKERS UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A bit of "news" appeared in the [Daily Jewish] Courier yesterday. It announced that a local of the Cloakmakers Union will hold a meeting stating, in the meantime, what will be discussed at the meeting and what will be determined--i.e., reporting everything in such a way that it will be detrimental to the Union and may result in destroying the Union. The Courier is up to its old tricks again.</p>
   <p>Comrade H. Schoolman, vice-president and district supervisor of the International [Ladies Garment Workers Union] submitted an explanation to the Forward upon being informed of the false accusations made by the Courier. He will, once and for all, nail the Courier to the wall. We know that his friends will support him in his campaign against those who attempt to sabotage the Union. Here is his statement:</p>
   <p>"Dear Editor of the Forward: I do not know who informs the Courier with what occurs in the Cloakmakers Union since I personally refuse to have anything to do with their "official labor editor" simply because he inserts additional <pb facs="5423972_2_0562.jpg" n="2"/>material regardless of what he is told. Very often his supplementary remarks are just lies. However, whoever wrote the last report about the Union certainly did not know what he was talking about.</p>
   <p>"The reporter probably heard that a special meeting was to be held by Local 5 at which certain clauses of the recent agreement and the resignation of the chairman were to be discussed. He then went ahead and wrote that the meeting would deal with Schoolman, although he knew that Schoolman was not concerned with the election for the new chairman since he represents, at present, not any particular local nor the Chicago Joint Board, but the whole International in the middle west. Moreover, he also stated that the Raincoat Makers Union, Local 5, was suspended because it opposed the movement to reorganize the Joint Board and to create the office of secretary. Did he know that the problem of reorganizing the Joint Board and of appointing a secretary was considered by the General Board before it was known that Local 5 did not favor the proposals? Thirdly, the reporter stated, 'wisely' so to speak, that the disturbances at the meetings of the Joint Board were caused by Schoolman because a majority of those <pb facs="5423972_2_0563.jpg" n="3"/>present were not his personal friends. He failed to state that because a majority were not Schoolman's friends four months have elapsed and no secretary has yet been appointed.....Lastly, the reporter also informs the readers of the Courier that no organizational work can be accomplished until a secretary of the Joint Board is appointed. The truth of the matter is that an organizer was appointed and that many preparations are being made. The work is being done as well as can be expected.</p>
   <p>"Altogether it seems as if many have united to destroy that which it took so much effort to build up. In that respect the conservative Courier marches side by side with the so-called 'reds'. It is nauseating to see these poisonous prevaricators create hatred among several innocent members in such an unprecedented manner. And who instigates this hatred? The Courier and the "left wingers" have united to destroy the organization which is so necessary and so important in our life."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
