<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1885-11-20">Nov. 20, 1885</date>.
<title level="a">"Auch Von Der Natur Beleckt."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0352</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0352.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1885-11-20">Nov. 20, 1885</date>.
<title level="a">"AUCH VON DER NATUR BELECKT."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The oldest Jewish congregation in Chicago, to wit: the K. K. Anshe Marriv, corner of 26th Street and Indiana Avenue, have at last awakened to a realization that there are some of its members whose vocation is such that they are precluded from attending services on Shabbes (Sabbath), wherefore the Rabbi of that congregation delivered a sermon in German last Saturday, the subject of which was to enable those that could not attend on Shabbes, to hear services on Sunday.</p>
   <p>Now the pillars of that congregation, many of whom wield their millions and who have kept Shabbes with a grain of salt in the morning, listening to the services, but in the afternoon attending to their banking and financial affairs, begin to realize something of the beauties of civilization, and as the Germans say von der Cultur beleckt, and inspiring them to doff a little of the Jerusalemic regime, seem now inclined to concede to the non-millionaire element in that congregation a little of <pb facs="5423972_2_0353.jpg" n="2"/>the divine inspiration which the millionaires have hitherto so complacently monopolized. Though the inception of Sunday services is but a straw in the great onward movement of Judaism for that congregation, it nevertheless shows that the Occident has had some influence to persuade the majority of that congregation to yield a tithe from its Jerusalemic dicta, and we are heartily glad at it. Rabbi Samuel Sale might be prone to be within the van of progress, and may now have an opportunity to march with his pious children of Israel and assume a position in modern Judaism, for, where there is wealth there should be also intelligence, and his congregation ought to be endowed with both. It were, indeed, singular if the prominent members of the congregation should persistently close their temple doors on Sunday, while their nearest offshoot, the Sinai congregation, have made such signal success of its Sunday Sabbath services. They can no longer be blind to the fact that a good portion of the Anshe Maariv members, and certainly nearly <pb facs="5423972_2_0354.jpg" n="3"/>all of the younger element of that congregation attend the Sinai services Sundays. Some three years since The Occident pointed out this ultimate result, which happily now takes its tread in the ordinary course of events. The Anshe Maariv congregation has been at a standstill for many years, because its most intelligent element withdrew from it, hence that congregation nearly died from inanition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
