<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-07-02">July 2, 1912</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1250</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1250.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-07-02">July 2, 1912</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are trades which the workers find hard to organize, and even if they are organized its difficult, for them, to control the shops.</p>
   <p>There are, however, trades where workers have a good opportunity to be organized, to control the trades, and yet the workers are in deep water.</p>
   <p>Take for instance the Building Trades, every worker in the Building Trade must, without exception, carry a union card as soon as he approaches the threshold of a new building.</p>
   <p>The Gentile workers are the real benefactors of this trade, but much to our regret the case is not so with the Jewish workers in the Building Trade. Perhaps you may share the opinion that union wages vary for Jews and Gentiles, or that Jews are worse tradesmen. No, the union wages are the same for everybody, <pb facs="5423972_2_1251.jpg" n="2"/>and the Jewish workers are as skilled as the Gentiles, and yet the Jewish worker is paid much less and is, on the whole, worse off.</p>
   <p>The readers of the Courier, are already acquainted with the differences between the Jewish carpenters, and the Gentiles, as well as painters and paper-hangers.</p>
   <p>A painter is paid $4.80 a day (60 cents an hour) according to the union scale. They get time and a half for over time, Sunday and holidays. The Gentile workers receive the true union wages, whereas the Jews do not receive half of this. In addition, the Jewish painters are not eligible for over time or work on holidays.</p>
   <p>Naturally they must belong to the union, and must pay dues in order to show a union card, otherwise they are barred from work. Most of the Jewish painters consider the union as a decree by which they are punished.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1252.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>No panaceas can be offered with the exception that the Jewish painters shall take action upon this themselves. We merely want to call attention to the Jewish workers of this trade that your season is in full swing now; work is plentiful and will be for some time to come. We do wish to say this: demand higher wages; do not return any money to the bosses. If all should demand union wages, you must get it, because if they put other workers in your place, they will demand union wages. Have no fear; work can not be done without you under any circumstances.</p>
   <p>Remember that no one can help you in this respect. It lies entirely in your hands alone. Be faithful union men and you will be better off.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
