<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-10-13">October 13, 1907</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-10-13">October 13, 1907</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Here and There. (Feature Column).</p>
   <p>Only recently the American German group held a national convention wherein they discussed many of the problems of their people in the United States. One of their most discussed problems was the question of language. It appears that the young German-Americans are ashamed of their mother-tongue and refuse to learn it. To combat this evil they resolved to further the German Language among their youth and redeem its honor. The Chicago Tribune in a well phrased editorial chastised German youth for their attitude to their mother language.</p>
   <p>This language problem is not apparently peculiar only to the Jews. For some time we have been noting the trend away from the Yiddish language. It has not merely been a trend. It comes in the nature of a shame. Ashamed to speak <pb facs="5423972_2_1305.jpg" n="2"/>or learn the Yiddish language, preferring to speak a "broken English" rather than a well developed "Jargon."</p>
   <p>Our mother-tongue- is a language, be it "Jargon" or a means of expression undesirable. It remains a language spoken by upwards of seven-million Jews and as such cannot be taken lightly nor is it something to be ashamed of.</p>
   <p>This general attitude slowly but surely gaining headway among our younger Jewish population has its tragic repercussions in quality of literary output. The "smear" all too present in American Journalism is being transplanted in Yiddish Journalism and literature, not for the same reasons we believe, but because writers realize that their efforts reach a constantly diminishing number of readers. Still more tragic is the exodus of Yiddish writers to more renumerative fields of journalism in other languages. We are pleased to see the expansion of Jewish efforts in business, industry and <pb facs="5423972_2_1306.jpg" n="3"/>labor, but we cannot afford to lose the molders of our culture.</p>
   <p>The German group could possibly afford to lose their literary following in this country, since they have a homeland which will continue to develop a culture, literary achievements, art and drama. But, we who have no land to continue our work if we fall by the wayside can ill afford to lose our literaries because more renumerative fields beckon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
