<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-06-23">June 23, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">Hilton-Seligman</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Editor of the Tribune:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1508</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1508.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-06-23">June 23, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">HILTON-SELIGMAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">To The Editor of The Tribune:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, June 22. - The Seligman-Hilton controversy seems to have created quite a stir among the Jewish population of our city, and, judging from the contributions in your paper, the smoke wafted by the wind threatens to increase. I am surprised that the Rev. Dr. Felsenthal, for whose learning and ability I entertain the highest respect, does not in a case of this kind counsel moderation, rather than incite his religious followers and believers, of whom there are about a million in this country, against this single individual, - Mr. Hilton. Much better would it be to treat this hostler's act with contempt. This innkeeper's individual act will not serve to resurrect the medieval days of barbarous persecution against the Jews. Far from it. Hilton's act will bring its own punishment. Let him at the end of the year balance his books, and compare the result with that of last year, and there will be a decided difference in favor of the latter. Added to this, there remains for each individual who feels himself slighted a la Seligman a civil remedy. The laws give the Jews, and protect them in the enjoyment of equal rights and liberties with all other sects. Why, then, make a national offense of what is private and special? I realize the feeling of those who have thus been insulted, but yet I cannot help feeling that there is some secret trouble and controversy which underlies this <pb facs="5423972_2_1509.jpg" n="2"/>sudden outburst, especially when we remember that but a short time ago these same parties were on the best of terms.</p>
   <p>Let the Jews be forgiving and relenting, and thus furnish examples for their Christian brethren, some of whom, as in the case of Judge Hilton the hostler, may be profited thereby. Such outbursts as this will in a short time be burried by the march of progress, and enlightenment, and refinement.</p>
   <p>A Jew.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
