<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-04-20">Apr. 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish "Wise-Guy" Who Pokes Fun at His Own People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0064</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0064.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-04-20">Apr. 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH "WISE-GUY" WHO POKES FUN AT HIS OWN PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The type of Jews that laugh at their own people is more scarce than it used to be. The growing anti-Semitism in America has brought about a new spirit among our American-born Jewish boys and girls. For, a Jew to make fun of Jews is anything but popular, nowadays.</p>
   <p>Yet, there are stray cases of Jewish young men and women who try to attract attention by flaunting a supreme contempt for their own fathers and mothers. Perhaps there are still enough lingering freaks to make up an audience for clowns of this type. At any rate, we have still among us some of those "wise-guys," who pretend to be above their brothers and sisters, but who are really inferior.</p>
   <p>They are not new, these "wise-guys." They were known to Jews thousands of years ago.</p>
   <p>The Hagodeh, for instance, the traditional Hebrew narrative of the redemption of the Jews from Egypt, tells of four varieties of sons the description of whom still retains fame. They are the proverbial quartette: -</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0065.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The wise son, the wicked son, the foolish son, and the one who does not know enough to inquire. (Call him in your modern language the greenhorn, the dunce, the numbskull, or plain idiot). Hagodeh's description of the foursome is the practically ancient conception of our contemporary rich man, poor man, beggar, and thief, especially in that the entire lot of the Hagodeh's boys seems objectionable. The wise boy persists in asking the same questions over and over again at each seder, and the wicked one, and the numbskull never did deserve any consideration.</p>
   <p>Our own Judo-American, 1924 - model of Hagodeh's boy, is the Hagodeh's quartette rolled into one. He retains all the objectionable traits of the four. For he is the "wise-guy" who does not ask questions about the Jews, or himself. He makes sport of it, mocks insultingly his own people. He is the so-called comedian who is in the habit of enjoying Hebrew stage jokes, considers it great sport to imitate the Jewish accent; which, by the way, is non-existent, except on the vaudeville stage.</p>
   <p>His hypersensitiveness as an observer of faults in anyone resembling a Jew is to be marvelled at. The faintest note of Jewish accent stirs him to ridicule.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0066.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He harps on such things.</p>
   <p>An orthodox Jew who passes the "wise-guy" on the street unobserved may consider himself fortunate indeed. The most decent thing the "wise-guy" can allow himself in such a case is to cringe his lips in and grin, with insinuation. This while others equally observant, no doubt, of the old-world Jew's outlandish appearance will look upon him with interest rather than scorn.</p>
   <p>In the subway and street cars, the "wise-guy"can be seen nudging his neighbor to draw attention to some old Jewess, unique in her Sheitel and her kerchief, who is worrying the conductor with questions for fear of passing her stop. The pathetic in the old woman's helpless flutter may be lost to the unsympathetic, but it certainly can inspire no one to ridicule, except our cherished product, the Americanized "wise-guy" of the Hagodeh. Most probably this inarticulate old woman, crushed by the alien surroundings, is on her way to feast her old eyes on her son or grandson, who is likewise potentially an Americanized Hagodeh's boy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0067.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>What is more, most likely this "wise-guy" parents are the very image of his objects of ridicule, and the only reasonable course for him would be to reassure the frightened old woman in Yiddish; - the Yiddish he hears at home, - and see to it that she gets off at the right stop. They may not be ornamental, - these antiquated-looking, inadaptable grandpas and grandmas of ours, - but they most certainly cannot be taken as butts for ridicule.</p>
   <p>To be sure, this obnoxious trait is not limited to the sons of the Hagodeh. The Hagodeh may have forgotten to mention them, but some of our daughters, too, seem to know this modern Chad-Gadyeh, the full text of supercilious mockery and spiteful public disrespect for anything that smacks of their own home-life. Their type is, unfortunately, too common to require a lengthy description. They are the kind who always boast of having been to places where "there was hardly a Jew," met people who told them that "no one would have guessed you were Jewish," and worked in stores and offices where "I was the first Jew employe they ever had."</p>
   <p>However, none of this variety is as objectionable as the comedian of breed, - he with the sneer and the ever-ready accent anecdote about "a Jew once took <pb facs="5423972_2_0068.jpg" n="5"/>out an insurance policy ... Listen to this one, Joe! Well, so he took out a policy .... ," etc.</p>
   <p>On Canal Street one afternoon recently I encountered a Cadillac full of this breed. A mass of Jewish shop workers were streaming from the needle shops east of the river. An open Cadillac, containing four Jewish youngsters, rushed up to the corner just as the traffic policeman gave the stop signal. They were a boisterous lot, and,with the car at a standstill, they directed their useless energy at the shopworn home-going pedestrians.</p>
   <p>"Hey, Moishele," yelled the "wise-guy" at the wheel. "How was your woik today, did you make a lot of money,ha?" supplemented another, and all laughed and jeered shamelessly.</p>
   <p>The scene lacked the bitterness of a pogrom in but that the hoodlum did not deign to descend from the automobile and tear Jewish beards.</p>
   <p>The traffic policeman, an Irishman, was the one who quieted them. "Hey, <pb facs="5423972_2_0069.jpg" n="6"/>you 'wise-guys', he warned them, "shut up, or I'll pull you in, so help me God. Where do you come from, I'd like to know?"</p>
   <p>And never was a more prophetic question uttered. The next morning, walking along in the thick of the Jewish district, I was struck by the sight of a touring Cadillac at the curb in front of an improvised store for the sale of Sacramental Kosher wines for the holidays. The car looked familiar. And then the unforgettable scene of the previous afternoon on Canal Street came to my mind. I recognized the car, and went into the store to investigate.</p>
   <p>A lanky young fellow with a pimpled face greeted me in the absence of the proprietor, who was out for a minute, as the young fellow explained. The proprietor, a middle-aged Jew with a trimmed beard, rushed in a minute later. The boy he had left in charge of the Sacramental stock was his son, and he was the hoodlum I had seen at the wheel the previous afternoon on Canal Street, slinging mud at Jewish pedestrians.</p>
   <p>Such is the status generally of these "wise-guys" of the Hagodeh. A more objectionable breed never was raised. He combines all the objectionable traits of all the four objectionable sons of the Hagodeh.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
