<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-09">June 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Poles Could Not Stage a Pogrom Yesterday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0816</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0816.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Polish)</item>
     <item>II E 1 (Polish)</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
     <item>I C (Lithuanian)</item>
     <item>I C (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-09">June 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO POLES COULD NOT STAGE A POGROM YESTERDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Yesterday, the five thousand Poles in Chicago," as the Daily News wrote Saturday," were prepared to stage a pogrom on the Jews in the Douglas Park District." They did not dare carry out their plans, but remained at home without ever showing up at the park.</p>
   <p>For this "quiet," on the part of the Poles, the local community has to thank the extra 250 police that Chief Garrity sent there; the muscular Jewish boys who stood guard from early morning to meet anyone who might seek to massacre local Jews here, as their brothers, no better than they, did in Lamberg, Wilna, Pinsk, and in smaller villages of Galicia, Poland, and Ukraine.</p>
   <p>Jewish boys who frequent the lunchrooms of Davie Miller, Pudi Anikster, <pb facs="5423972_2_0817.jpg" n="2"/>Raffleson, Balotin, Erhlich, Bartlestein and Bloom, and many more did not remain at home yesterday. They were in the streets and in the park. Some, on motorcycles and in automobiles, patrolled the park and the streets in the neighborhood of Twelfth Street and Kedzie Avenue where the Polish "crusaders" were to pass. The streets were literally packed with Jewish boys, one stronger than the other. Among them were many in military uniforms who have but just returned from across the seas where they fought so bravely for America, for Democracy, and for Peace.</p>
   <p>The audacity of these brave boys was enough to frighten even a greater number of Poles than we have in Chicago. The Jewish boys were unarmed but ready to fight with sinewy muscles to defend the Jewish population from those who sought Jewish blood.</p>
   <p>To their aid were to come the Irish, the Lithuanian, and the Bohemian boys whom the Poles also considered their enemies.</p>
   <p>The city police, noticing the brave Jewish boys, were admirably impressed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0818.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Chief Garrity, who arrived at the park in his automobile about three o'clock in the afternoon, shook his head and said: "There will be no trouble."</p>
   <p>But the park police did not like this. Most of them, that is, about eighty percent are Poles. During the last year they worked in the park under John P. Smulski, president of the West Park Board. Their support of the Poles has recently led to bloody attacks by Poles on Jews within the park. They certainly must have expected to take a hand as previously in the "fight against the 'Sheenies.'"</p>
   <p>About four o'clock, our boys disbanded and the Jewish people felt secure. They were certain that no Polish pogroms would occur.</p>
   <p>Davie Miller, in his lunchroom at 3216 W. Twelfth Street, was the most satisfied person yesterday.</p>
   <p>"Whatever comes up is ascribed to me," he told a Courier reporter. "If <pb facs="5423972_2_0819.jpg" n="4"/>they wish to point out a bad place, it's my lunchroom. Believe me, I do a legitimate business, have never cheated anyone, have always yielded to the other person, and am ready to aid in every Jewish undertaking.</p>
   <p>"I am more of a Jewish Jew than they think I am. I am proud of my nationality and feel deeply for those of us who are poor and persecuted. If it were not for me and all the boys that come here, Jews would be murdered in this neighborhood. We have eliminated the petty thieves, and hope in the future, to continue to live in peace and safety.</p>
   <p>"Believe me, the Poles will not dare to do to Jews what they would like to do."</p>
   <p>With great satisfaction he again attended to his cash register which was, yesterday, overloaded with money.</p>
   <p>But on the North Side yesterday, all did not fare so well. Two Polish bandits, at the corner of Ashland and Grand Avenue, stopped and attacked the junk dealer, Lieberman. Two policemen arrived just too late, thus permitting them to escape.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0820.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Polish newspapers were very busy yesterday denying [the fact] that Chicago Poles sought to make a pogrom, but their columns printed enough material to incite Poles against Jews. The individual attacks, as that upon Lieberman are a result of these incitements.</p>
   <p>In these provocations against the Jews the following newspapers are guilty: The Dziennik Chicagoski, "Potter" Gordon's organ; The Dziennik Narodovi, John F. Smulski's organ; and The Zgoda, the organ of the Polish National Alliance, of which the renegade, the scoundrelly Jewish traitor, Nathan Kalman Zlatnitski, is one of the leading officials.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
