<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-01">May 1, 1919</date><title level="a">Pentateuch Philosophies</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Paradox by Avrahemel</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0218</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.B"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0218.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>V B</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-01">May 1, 1919</date><title level="a">PENTATEUCH PHILOSOPHIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Paradox By Avrahemel</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Almighty had warned Jews that if they were not driven from the land, they would be put to death.</p>
   <p>The Translations of Avremel councils that this alternative from Heaven is an innuendo to the present day Jewish situation in Poland, where all Jews, except those killed naturally, will be forced to leave the country because of the troubled situation. As the Bible verse states, The earth will spit them forth, but the dead are never given up.</p>
   <p>From this we cannot infer that the Polish pogrom participants in Pinsk, for instance, who killed 37 Jews, have fulfilled the "positive command of the Torah." First, because Satan, excepting the evil <pb facs="5423972_2_0219.jpg" n="2"/>doctors, naturally hates partnerships; second, Poles do not believe in the precept of acquired citizenship. Satan treats all evils alike and would not favor the Poles, even if they were God's special good will messengers.</p>
   <p>In the Pentateuch is written: "When you will come to your land and grow a fruit tree, for three years its fruit must not be touched (uncircumcised), and we may not eat thereof."</p>
   <p>The Moskov Lavtzeem (Sessions of Jesters) remarks that even a piece of wood has more luck than a Jew. Trees may remain uncircumcised for three years; Jewish children for not more than seven days.</p>
   <p>Two are forbidden. The "no" in "no consolation" and the "no" that prohibits the cutting of beard and sideburns; one follows the other in this section of the Pentateuch.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0220.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Ask a "philosopher" of the "Hungarian School", "What relations have magic and card reading to beard shaving?"</p>
   <p>Answers the Translations of Avremel: "Only that it serves as a reminder of superstitions and imaginations for all intelligent Jewish actors, those that shave of course."</p>
   <p>"No consolation" says Rashi (ancient Bible commentary) means: To seek magic by experimentation, as taking notes on black cats, ducks, food fallen from the mouth etc.</p>
   <p>This, too, belongs to 'no consolation': the fear of a broken mirror, a play concerning the bed, sorcery in the prima donna's voice, copper money in the box office, etc. All those believing thus are worth many lashings, even if they should understand the art of a capable performance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0221.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Respect an aged person". This is covered by two paragraphs. It means: If he is a diplomat, a writer, let him publish novels; if he is a thief, help him crawl into someone's window; if an actor, take him into the union.</p>
   <p>In the Torah is the following: God at one time, in wishing to vent his anger on the Jews for their sins, would have annihilated them. But His good name and conscience prevented this. He did not wish to be put to shame by the nations of the earth before whose very eyes He had brought forth the Jews from Egypt.</p>
   <p>The question is: What miracles has the Almighty shown with His patience and greatness? Has He not in so acting protected His own reputation?</p>
   <p>The answer given is: that God, in this instance, demonstrated how much higher, more refined, and wiser He was than all the civilized nations <pb facs="5423972_2_0222.jpg" n="5"/>which persecute Jews in broad daylight without shame for God or peoples. Yet, they it is who must account for their lives to a higher tribunal and He, to none.</p>
   <p>In today's Pentateuch chapter, the word "Chassad," meaning "shame," is explained. Yes, there are two kinds of shame:</p>
   <p>That, for instance, which political powers use against Jews after a revolution is really worth mentioning; and that shame for which our intercessors must beg at the Paris Peace conference for British protection. This necessity of begging, that no more pogroms be made on us, 'tis a shame.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
