<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-08">Nov. 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Vaudevillians</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0718</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0718.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-08">Nov. 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH VAUDEVILLIANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago is busy amusing itself; there are at present four great Jewish entertainers in the city: Ed Wynn, whose real name is Israel Leopold, George White, Al Jolson, and Lester Allen. These entertainers are responsible for the amount of amusement that can be found in Chicago each night. What is more, there are any number of Jewish entertainers in the various vaudeville houses in the city, who are very talented and who make it their business to banish any spirit of despondency from Chicago audiences. However, Chicago is not the only great city where Jewish entertainers are to be found. There are a number of them in New York, Boston, Philadelphia, New Orleans, Frisco, and in all other theatrical centers in the United States. In all European countries, a similar state of affairs prevails. The vicissitudes of life are disheartening, and seeking an escape, men and women go to the theaters, both legitimate and vaudeville, to be amused by Jewish entertainers. Everywhere, it is the Jew who <pb facs="5423972_2_0719.jpg" n="2"/>is the great entertainer. The Jews completely dominate the sphere of comedy, although the life of the Jews is a tragedy. Few people ever ask themselves why it is that the Jews, the most persecuted and most oppressed race in the world, produce so many comedians. Of course, there are Jewish tragedians, too, and there are any number of them, but they are not pre-eminent in the field of tragedy, at least, not in America. The greatest tragedians of our time are non-Jews; the greatest entertainers, vaudevillians, and comedians are Jews. Is it not something of a riddle that a people that had endured as much martyrdom as the Jewish people, that is always the victim of suffering and oppression, should supply humanity with its principal comedians? To many it may seem that this is one of the paradoxes of life because at first it is nothing short of a paradox, but it seems to me that this phenomenon is by no means paradoxical, but can be explained by the very psychology of the Jewish people.</p>
   <p>I think it was Heinrich Heine who first used the expression "Galgen-humor": the humor of the gallows; the sort of humor that emanates from bitter despair. The <pb facs="5423972_2_0720.jpg" n="3"/>experienced sheriff could give many examples of this type of humor. It is produced only in extreme cases, where the person sentenced to die is either innocent or an archcriminal. Both of them often die, not only with a smile on their lips, a smile that cuts to the quick, but also with the most biting sarcasm on their lips. It is this sort of sarcasm, and this sort of humor, arising out of despair, that Heine called "Galgen-humor". People who live under normal conditions cannot possibly produce the volume and amount of humor that the Jews produce because this humor can only be understood and explained in terms of the various phases of Jewish life. Jewish life is so queer, so tragic, so abnormal, that it is often funny in its tragedy, and funny in its abnormality. The experienced vaudeville-goer is often aware of the fact that the humor of Jewish entertainers in vaudeville and musical comedy contains surprises, irrelevancies, and a certain type of inimitable bluff. It is neither the humor that arises from situations nor from dialogue--it is rather the humor of reverse logic. Ordinarily two and two make four. Some queer fellow may claim that two and two are seventeen, but the Jewish entertainer will surprise <pb facs="5423972_2_0721.jpg" n="4"/>you by claiming that two and two are neither four nor seventeen, but beet root. The main characteristic of the Jewish entertainer is the surprise element. You laugh at the unexpected; and this unexpected may not be funny at all, but it sounds so utterly funny because it is unexpected, because it is so contrary to all logic, so fantastic, so peculiar, and so queer. That is what fascinates the theater-going public and makes it applaud Jewish entertainers. It does not respond to the emotional appeals of Jewish tragedians or character actors with nearly as much gusto as it does to Jewish comedians. That is one of the reasons why Jewish entertainers are successful and dominate the vaudeville stage. A talented Jewish actor or actress cannot easily gain a prominent place on the legitimate stage, but Jewish actors are very successful on the vaudeville stage. The vaudeville stage has one main objective--to make the audience laugh, and the Jews are pre-eminently successful in this endeavor.</p>
   <p>The legitimate theater offers an artistic entity--a play with a plot and all the technical paraphernalia attached to the plot. The vaudeville stage doesn't <pb facs="5423972_2_0722.jpg" n="5"/>offer an artistic entity; it offers artistic varieties, a sort of artistic goulash. The legitimate theater may appeal to our intellect; if the play has a certain bias, it may arouse our emotions, it may appeal to our sense of humor; but in any case, it appeals to only one aspect of our personality. The vaudeville stage, however, which offers artistic variety instead of an artistic entity, appeals to the whole personality; it appeals to our eye through color and scenery, or through the movements of the dancers; it may appeal to our ear through good music, it may appeal to our emotions through dramatic skits or recitations; and it may appeal to our intellect through comedy. As a rule, it does all of these during one evening. In short vaudeville consists of an artistic goulash.</p>
   <p>Jewish life is not an entity. It is not an organic unit because it consists of fractions and parts, each of which is subject to the influence of others. The main feature of Jewish life is its variety. One can sum up the main features of American life in twenty or fifty words; one can sum up the features of French <pb facs="5423972_2_0723.jpg" n="6"/>or English or German life in twenty or fifty words; but one cannot describe the main features of Jewish life so briefly. Jewish life is one vast goulash; Jews live in thirty-six different countries, subject to the influences of thirty-six different civilization and cultures, and in each and every land they are divided in factions and parts. It is hard, therefore, to explain exactly what Jewish life in the Diaspora is, and what it consists of. This variety within Jewish life, with its many contradictions, with its many ups and downs, with its queerness, is in itself comic, and in America, the melting pot of all the Jews in the world, it is really very funny.</p>
   <p>On the corner of the street lives a Jew from Poland who still believes in the holiness of the Hasadic rabbi, and thinks in terms of the thirteenth century. On the other corner of the street lives a Russian Jew who is a "Red," and whose rabbi is Trotsky or Lenin. Both have a little in common--they are idealists; but both are Jews. And when they both meet, what do they say to each other? Isn't a meeting of two such Jews the height of comedy? Beneath <pb facs="5423972_2_0724.jpg" n="7"/>this comic situation is hidden the tragedy of our people, but to the naked eye such a meeting is too funny for words. A little further down [the street], lives a Jew who belongs to the nonveau riche. He doesn't believe in Trotsky or the Hasadic rabbi; he doesn't even believe in Moses or God. He believes only in money; and with these three types of Jews, a very humorous situation is created. A little further on lives a German Jew. He despises all three of these Jews, but still he is a Jew, and though he may not associate with them, he is a Jew too. In the eyes of the world, he is only a Jew, no better than the rest of them. Imagine a meeting of these four Jews. Vaudeville could not reproduce it. A little further down lives a Jew from Persia or a Sephardic Jew, who is so proud of his Spanish ancestry that he would not associate with either the German, the Russian, the Polish, or the Hasadic Jew. He despises them all in the depths of his heart. He is convinced that he is superior to all of them, just as the German Jew thinks himself superior to the Russian Jew, and the Bolshevik Jew thinks himself superior to the Orthodox Jew. But at some time or other, these five Jews will have to meet--and that will be a very funny meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0725.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Finally, there is the American-born Jew who, although he may be an American of only the second or third generation, is actually convinced that his ancestors came over on the Mayflower; he despises these other five types of Jews. He thinks himself superior to all of them, but sometimes he has to meet them, and that, too, is a very funny meeting.</p>
   <p>On the first floor, they mourn the death of a relative who died during the pogroms, somewhere in the Ukraine. On another floor, another Jewish family celebrates the third anniversary of the Bolshevik regime. On the top floor, another Jewish family celebrates the second anniversary of the Armistice. Consider the comedy and tragedy contained in one house! Art can only be a reflection of life. That which does not exist, cannot be imitated, and the Jewish vaudevillian simply imitates that which he has seen and observed as a Jew: varieties, contradictions, reverse logic, queerness, eccentricities, etc.</p>
   <p>It is a matter of general knowledge that the Jews are poor novelists, but great <pb facs="5423972_2_0726.jpg" n="9"/>short-story writers. I can't think of one great Jewish novel written by a Jew, but I can mention twenty great short stories, real masterpieces. A novel requires a certain harmony in the lives of its characters; it needs background and atmosphere. Jewish life is so broken, so full of variety and contradiction that it lacks the requirements needed to produce a great novel. On the other hand, Jewish life is full of amusements, full of incidents and surprises, full of one-act dramas, and since art must reflect life, the short story is a better medium of expression for the Jewish writer of fiction than the novel.</p>
   <p>The Jewish entertainer, like the short-story writer, can only offer tidbits, but in this he is absolute master. The non-Jewish entertainer usually specializes in one field. He is either a singer, a dancer, an actor, or a musician, but the Jewish entertainer is generally versatile and can do a bit of everything, and is often marvelous in his versatility. Ed Wynn is an accomplished actor and musician, playing many instruments, and in addition, he is a regular vaudeville comedian. Young Lester Allen is an actor, a dancer, <pb facs="5423972_2_0727.jpg" n="10"/>an acrobat, and in addition, a first-class vaudeville comedian. The two Dolly sisters took New York by surprise two years ago when they appeared on the legitimate stage. These two dainty dancers have proved to be accomplished actresses. Ivan Bankopf, the famous Russian dancer, whose real name is Goldberg and who is considered the best dancer on the American vaudeville stage, is in addition, a singer, an actor, and a producer. What is true of those great entertainers is true of persons like Nora Bayes, and to a certain extent, Al Jolson, George White, and many others.</p>
   <p>One can thus readily see that the type of amusement offered by the Jewish entertainer as well as his versatility are not accidents but are rooted in Jewish life and in its conditions, and that they reflect this life to a greater or lesser extent. It is because the type of humor offered by the Jewish entertainer is so original and unique; because the Jewish entertainer is versatile that the Jew on the American vaudeville stage has become such a prominent figure that he plays to capacity houses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
