<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-10-07">Oct. 7, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0555</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0555.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-10-07">Oct. 7, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The reactionary Courier showers the Cloak-Maker's Union with new prevarications. The Courier received a sharp and well earned answer to its lies, by Comrade Max Brodsky, secretary-treasurer of Local 100, International Ladies Garment Workers Union. The answer speaks for itself.</p>
   <p>Brodsky's Statement.</p>
   <p>"I deny all statements that were published in the Courier under my name. I am absolutely not responsible for yesterday's scribbling in this paper, in which an attempt was made to justify itself by using my name. I want to emphasize that whatever the Courier wrote about me is a lie.</p>
   <p>"First of all, the Courier wanted to show that I was a candidate for secretary-treasurer of the Joint Board on the left-wing ticket; the Courier also tortures itself in proving that in the Joint Board can be found two sections, a left-wing and a right-wing. I deny this.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0556.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"It is also said in the Courier that Schoolman and those who supported Rosen's candidates, compelled me to withdraw my candidacy as secretary-treasurer of the Joint Board. This is not true. The truth is as follows: Brother Fogel, manager of the labor department of the Joint Board, proposed that both candidates should withdraw in order to avoid certain misunderstandings. I immediately accepted Brother Fogel's proposal and resigned. When I was, later, renominated I refused to accept the nomination. However, Brother Rosen remained a candidate and the result was that Conefsky was elected. This is the truth, not as the Courier had written."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
