<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-10-08">Oct. 8, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A Democratic "Hanosein Tshuah"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0246</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0246.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-10-08">Oct. 8, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A DEMOCRATIC "HANOSEIN TSHUAH"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We do not know authentically who the author of "Hanosein Tshuah" (a prayer blessing the head, or heads of a government) was, but the motives which impelled the authorship of such a prayer and the reason for its being in the prayer book, are clearly understood by every Jew. The security of the Jews in the countries of Diaspora always depended upon the will or caprice of the sovereign in whose country they dwelled. The "Hanosein Tshuah," as a prayer, consists of two parts:</p>
   <p>1. A prayer beseeching God to prolong the years and strengthen the power of their sovereign, so that he may overcome his enemies.</p>
   <p>2. A prayer, regarding the Jewish people, that God should implant compassion in the hearts of their sovereign and his people, so that they may live harmoniously with the Jews; and, in conclusion, it states that during the reign of the sovereign, Judah should prosper, and Israel should live securely.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0247.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first part, apparently, is a pure political one and was never considered seriously. The reader chanted the prayer while worshipers' attention was centered upon something else. It is hard to believe that worshipers in a congregation in Russia once burst out into tears when asking the Lord to prolong the years and strengthen the power of such a sovereign as Alexander I, and such a servant as Ignatiev, or Plehve, in the time of the Kishenev pogroms. Nevertheless, the prayer is in the prayer book, and the cantor must read it regardless of whom it was aimed at. Were it ever made public that a synagogue purposely refrained from offering "Hanosein Tshuah" that synagogue would immediately be destroyed, and the rabbi, cantor, and president of the synagogue would be severely punished.</p>
   <p>The second part, which implies compassion, is characteristic of the Jewish groans in the countries of Diaspora. This part of the prayer is read with sincerity; the conclusion is a bit of Jewish irony. After the Jew got through praying for the health and happiness of his sovereign, and asking that compassion be implanted into his heart so that he may be merciful unto the Jews, he, in return, wants Judah to prosper and Israel to live secure.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0248.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The fact that all of Israel are not in that particular country, is evidence that it is a prayer alluding to a breaking away from that sovereign as soon as possible and then live securely in Palestine.</p>
   <p>In the prayer books which Europe exports to America, the "Hanosein Tshuah" is printed with the names of the Czar and Czarina, or Francis Joseph, or Kaiser Wilhelm. In the prayer books which are printed in America, the same "Hanosein Tshuah" is switched over to the President and his Cabinet, and is, therefore, absolutely not suited to American conditions.</p>
   <p>If the prayer be such in the American prayer books, because it was sanctified through the exiled traditions of many centuries, it ought to manifest the spirit of America; it should be a democratic prayer, not mentioning a sovereign or person, but asking for the prosperity of the country and for a clean, just, and intelligent government through representatives of the people. It should also manifest the spirit of Jewish traditions by not asking for mercy, but expressing sympathy for America. Such a prayer would be in harmony with the orbit of American principles. It was evident, that <pb facs="5423972_2_0249.jpg" n="4"/>at the out-break of the war in Europe, events took place which impressed the present administration in Washington to save Jews from gallows and made it possible to save thousands of others from starvation. Should our leaders in Washington not possess in their hearts broad-mindedness and great humanitarian ideas, the Jewish suffering in the various war-stricken countries would still be more horrifying than it is.</p>
   <p>A prayer asking for the spirit of human love, of noble sympathy for the afflictions of others, should amplify the hearts of the American representatives. Such a prayer also can not fall short of its educational influence upon those who pray. The reader can utter such a prayer with deep sincerity, and at the same time not feel the slightest iota of contradistinction, which is permitted in the "Hanosein Tshuah" of the present prayer books.</p>
   <p>And so such a "Hanosein Tshuah," that expresses both the American and Jewish spirit, the conclusion, "may Judah and Israel live secure in time of the President's rule", would be suited perfectly to American conditions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
