<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-01-10">January 10, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Gersoni to the Jews</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1312</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1312.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-01-10">January 10, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Gersoni to the Jews</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian-Jews revolutionist appeals to the Russian-Jews of Chicago and tells them that the only salvation for the Jews in Russia is the revolution. His speech made quite an impression on the public. Mr. Katz, Gersoni's host, requested actual cold cash instead of so much applause. More than 2,000 people attended the mass gathering in Orchestra Hall, to welcome Gregori Gersoni, a Jewish son who sacrificed his entire youth to the freedom of Russia.</p>
   <p>The reception tendered this exponent of freedom was overwhelming, volumes of applause greeted this great advocate of freedom. The chairman of the meeting, Mr. Peter Zuseman, delivered a short address and introduced Mr. Katz, the host of Gersoni. Mr. Katz spoke at great length, and, in introducing the hero of the evening, he stated that he was not here to praise <pb facs="5423972_2_1313.jpg" n="2"/>the greatness and personality of Gersoni, but, to endorse the cause of this hero who came to Chicago to enlist our moral and material assistance for the Russian nation and with our help to materialize the hopes that freedom will soon reign in the oppressed and smothered Czarist country. He also reminded the public of the dreadful hardships and persecutions that the Jewish people in Russia have endured.</p>
   <p>The Jews in Russia number six millions, and they are constantly in great danger of annihilation by the aristocracy of Czardom. In conclusion he stressed the need not for applause but for cash for the good of the cause.</p>
   <p>After Mr. Katz's address, the chairman introduced Gersoni. Before he began his speech the audience broke out with tremendous applause which lasted several minutes. Mr. Gersoni acknowledged the applause and then signaled for silence. During the long address of Mr. Gersoni, the audience was unusually quiet. Everyone was thoroughly engrossed in the speaker's words.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1314.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He made it known that he is a Jew and a Jewish patriot. He paid special respect to the Maccabees and mentioned the heroism and courage of King David who killed his enemy with a sling shot. The present Jewish generation is well fitted for today's civilization and instead of throwing stones at its enemy, it will destroy him with lead and dynamite. Gersoni also spoke in the Russian language as follows: "My dear sisters and brothers, my first words to you are the most heartfelt regards from our comrades who are suffering torture in the Russian jails: from our comrades who are on the battlefield and are fighting against tyranny. I also have a message for you from our suffering Jewish mothers in all parts of Russia." After concluding his talk in Russian, he resumed in Yiddish and said, "The Russian government was powerless to tear me away from my Jewish nation but it tore me away from my Jewish language." After these words, he pictured the hardships of the Jews in Russia. He urged the public to keep in mind the martyrs who fell struggling for the cause. The audience at this part of his speech arose <pb facs="5423972_2_1315.jpg" n="4"/>and stood in silence with bowed heads while the musicians played mournful Jewish tunes suitable for this occasion. Mr. Gersoni then spoke again, explaining that Russian today is the most unfortunate country in the world and it is a great humane act to fight for its freedom. He soon changed the subject and began to talk on the Jewish problems in Russia. "We Jews must make some great sacrifices to help the Jews in Russia in their struggle for freedom. I myself am a Jew, and I thoroughly understand the Jewish situation in the land of the Czars.</p>
   <p>The bloody attacks on Jews in Russia placed our Jewish nation in a discouraged and hopeless frame of mind, and it is my honest and sincere conviction that the revolution is Russia is the only salvation for our Jews in that country. Now as to myself, I was most fortunate, that the pogrom hoodlums did not get the chance at me to tear my body to pieces as they did with thousands <pb facs="5423972_2_1316.jpg" n="5"/>of my Jewish brothers and sisters. If I escaped with my life, it was entirely by accident. There is not the least doubt in my mind that the revolution is the only salvation for the Jews in Russia."</p>
   <p>Mr. Gersoni also spoke with regards to the Russian spies, some of whom, he was sure, were sitting in the audience listening to what he, the enemy of the Czar, had to say. As soon as the speech was over, the audience got busy with contributions for the cause by throwing five-dollar bills, dollar bills, one-half dollar and twenty-five cent pieces on the platform where the speaker stood. After the closing of this spirited meeting at 12 o'clock, the crowd left for the West Side Auditorium where a tea party was held in honor of Mr. Gersoni, at which he related his experiences in his Siberian exile.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
