<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-09-06">September 6, 1930</date>, Vol. 80, p.140.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0111</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0111.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-09-06">September 6, 1930</date>, Vol. 80, p.140.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The conservative school of Judaism was still unknown; it was before Dr. Schechter became the head of the Jewish Theological Seminary, of New York. But Dr. Deinard and Dr. Yudelson adopted the conservative methods of service in their congregation, i.e., services were conducted partly in Hebrew and partly in English. Men and women sat together. As the members of the congregation kept moving farther South, the House of Worship had to move as well. At the suggestion of Dr. Yudelson, the South Side Hebrew Congregation disposed of its Indiana Avenue property, acquired the Northeast corner of Michigan Avenue and 59th Street and proceeded to build a community center. This was of great significance in the cultural development of Chicago Jews.</p>
   <p>Dr. Yudelson was a Hebrew scholar, a real Maskil, endowed with a keen perception and an adherent to the cause of modern Zionism. He saw that the salvation of American Judaism lay in Jewish Nationalism, which could be effected amongst the Jewish youth of America only through Jewish education. He was one of the first to sponsor the universal teaching of the Hebrew language, not only for religious <pb facs="5423972_2_0112.jpg" n="2"/>purposes but for secular learning as well.</p>
   <p>The community center was erected with that point in view and it was constructed more as a modern school than a synagogue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
