<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-06-15">June 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Racial Caricatures</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-06-15">June 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">RACIAL CARICATURES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The movement which began a short time ago to combat caricatures of Jewish life on the stage and in the newspapers is certainly a worth while movement, although, in our opinion, it is a bit too theoretical.</p>
   <p>A few years ago the Order of B'nai B'rith urged newspapers not to mention, on each occasion that something happened to a Jew, the fact that the individual was a Jew. This was carried out without any meetings, without great publicity, and without any noise or commotion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1198.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is a fact that Jews are great theater-goers and many, if not the majority, theater stock companies are controlled by Jews. Therefore, a movement to abolish the noxious and ugly caricatures of Jewish life should be limited to Jews only. The submission of such reports to the general non-Jewish newspaper surely creates a very unpleasant effect on the Gentile people.</p>
   <p>Not only Jews, but all foreign peoples suffer from these noxious and ugly caricatures; the Italians as well as the Swedes; the Germans as well as the Irish. The Jew feels the bite more keenly than others, because he is persecuted more than others, because he is weaker than others, because thousands of years of persecution and affliction have made him submissive to those who ridicule him.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1199.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When a stage-joke is pulled on an Irishman at a social gathering, the Irishman will respond in such a manner that the joke will not be repeated. The Jew must bow his head and remain silent because he lacks the necessary strength, and consequently the joke is accepted as the truth.</p>
   <p>It is also a sad fact that the Jew accepts Gentile public opinion as truer than Jewish opinion. The Jew, himself, pretends that the disgraceful jokes are sacred. All the rotten jokes about Jewish incendiaries are repeated by Jews, and every insignificant Jew thinks that this will rid them of their faults, which by the way they do not have, but of which they are accused by the jokes.</p>
   <p>In every Jewish editorial office letters pour in daily from these moral preachers, whose conceptions of Jewish faults are created by seeing and hearing these ugly caricatures and rotten jokes, and instead of condemning such actors and theaters they decide to avoid such vulgar people, and attired in a preacher's cloak they proceed to repeat the jokes to whomever they contact.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1200.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There are many ways of approaching a Jew and requesting him to avoid these places which dispense hatred and envy. There are many methods for urging the individual Jew not to support with his money and influence those newspapers which spread lies through word and print.</p>
   <p>We need not resort to advertising in the general newspapers, regardless of the friendly manner in which the newspapers treat it.</p>
   <p>The movement should proceed to fight those who ridicule the Jews, but it should be a purely Jewish movement, among ourselves. The issue should not be that Gentiles should not ridicule the Jews. The issue should be that the Jews, themselves, should not do it, and that the Jews should avoid those who ridicule them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
