<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-17">Sept. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">At the First Slihoth</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0148</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0148.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-17">Sept. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AT THE FIRST SLIHOTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Autumn winds are beginning to blow and the leaves are falling from the trees. The air is chilly and the skies are cloudy. Summer is dying and the cold winds, the cloudy sky, the falling leaves are a sign of death and birth--the death of summer and the birth of winter.</p>
   <p>The Jew recollects his duties to God and to men on these days when Mother Nature herself stands at the parting of the ways. He too stands at a parting of the ways: the crossroads of his past and his future. He examines searchingly the days and months of the past year, to see whether they are clean; he tries to enter the future with a clear conscience and a cleansed heart.</p>
   <p>The Jew recollects his duty to God and to men when he stands at the <pb facs="5423972_2_0149.jpg" n="2"/>crossroads. The month of Elul and particularly the days of Slihoth [prayers of forgiveness recited before Rosh Hashanah] up to the Day of Atonement are, therefore, days of repentance and charity.</p>
   <p>Slihoth is a great and noble religious institution. No other religion has a similar institution that makes certain ethical and philanthropic demands upon the individual and society. The days of Slihoth are the days of an ethical and religious struggle, the days of a socio-ethical serenity. A poetic mood envelops those days when Mother Nature herself is at the cross-roads. These days are not only days of religious ecstasy and pure ethical strife, but they are also days of song, days which breathe a pure lyrical spirit.</p>
   <p>The Jew recollects, in these noble and uplifting days, not only his duties to God but also his duties to his people, to his fellow men because these are the days of repentance and prayer, these are the Yom Tovim, in the <pb facs="5423972_2_0150.jpg" n="3"/>ethical meaning of the word.</p>
   <p>On these Yom Tovim, the Jew should remember those whom fate persecutes, those whom life oppresses and neglects. He must remember the orphans and the helpless old people who are dependent upon the good will of others. He must remember the poor and the sick who need his help. He must remember the thousands of Jewish Halutzim who wander around European ports with their gaze focused on Palestine, where they want to go to help build the country. He must remember the poor immigrants of Eastern Europe who want to escape from the hell they are in at the present time, but who can do so only with our help. He must remember the poor students of the Torah, the young men who study in religious seminaries all over the world, who starve but do not cease studying. He must contribute to the Help the Torah Fund. His heart must be big enough to include all those who need help and he should seek ways to help them.</p>
   <p>Every Jewish community should naturally try to fulfill its own charity <pb facs="5423972_2_0151.jpg" n="4"/>requirements first. We, the Jews of Chicago, must not forget about the Home for the Orphans, where hundreds of poor Jewish orphans are being brought up to be good citizens and true children of their people. We have duties toward the orphan and we must try to bring a little joy into his cheerless life by providing him with whatever he needs. We must remember our Home for the Aged, where many old men and women are being taken care of, where the twilight of their lives is being made more beautiful. We must remember the neglected infants and babies who are wholly or partly orphaned and of whom the Daughters of Zion Infant Home and other nurseries take care.</p>
   <p>We must remember the Jewish Federation of Orthodox Charities which supports so many philanthropic, cultural, and social Jewish institutions in Chicago. The Federation is struggling hard to maintain its existence because the demands of the institutions are increasing while the income remains the same. We must not forget the Hebrew Theological College, which should become a center of the Torah in Chicago and which will <pb facs="5423972_2_0152.jpg" n="5"/>enable many young Jewish men to devote their whole time to the Torah. The Hebrew Theological College can become the pride of the Chicago Jews and can transform a spiritual wilderness into a spiritual garden. Anyone who wants to strengthen and perpetuate Judaism in Chicago must help the Hebrew Theological College. It is needless to point out that the Talmud Torahs must have our entire attention because they are the institutions which will raise the young Jewish generation.</p>
   <p>We must not forget the incurably sick Jews of Oak Forest, who lead a tortured and sad life, condemned by cruel fate to spend the rest of their days and years there. We must help maintain the kosher food kitchen set up for them. We must not forget the Mt. Sinai Hospital, which eases the pain of the sick and makes it possible for them to have kosher food while they are in the hospital. We must not forget those who are condemned by fate to suffer from the terrible white plague. We must help the Denver and the Los Angeles sanatoriums and the Chicago Consumptive Relief Society <pb facs="5423972_2_0153.jpg" n="6"/>to ease the pain of the sufferers. We must remember the Free Burial Society, which comes to the succor of the poor in the time of their greatest need. We must not forget the House of Shelter Society.</p>
   <p>We must not forget that besides those local charities there are in existence national charities such as the H. I. A. S. [Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society], the National Fund, the relief, and last, but not least, the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization], which must build Palestine.</p>
   <p>If Slihoth can bring to us that which we expect of it--serenity of heart and soul--then this serenity can come to us only if we do our duty to our people. Prayers and charity will bring us spiritual calm and happiness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
