<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1880-01-25">January 25th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Liberal Judaism</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1880-01-25">January 25th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">LIBERAL JUDAISM</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last meeting of the B' nai B' rith Grand Lodge, District 6, held in this city, the following was adopted:</p>
   <p>Resolved, that if a candidate applies for membership in a Lodge, of whom it is doubtful or disputed whether he is a Jew or not, such candidate shall declare in writing:</p>
   <p>1. That he confesses his belief in Judaism, and,</p>
   <p>2. That he does not belong to any non - Jewish church, or other non - Jewish religious organization.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Advance of yesterday comments on this innovation as follows:</p>
   <p>One resolution, adopted by this Grand Lodge promises to assume a historical importance of great magnitude. It is the resolution of admitting members into the Order on the simple declaration that they adhere to Judaism and without adhering to any ceremonial compliance with Jewish usages and customs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1470.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If on one side this resolution makes the Order eminent by Jewish in principle, it on the other hand, opens wide the doors for any outsider that may desire to join our ranks. It is an important sign of the time, the magnitude of which can hardly be estimated at present. While prejudices against the Jewish race prevail all over the world, and even representative Christian scholars are not ashamed to rouse the ghost of Judeophobia from its place of medevial confinement, - a Jewish corporation comes forth, generously and boldly saying: "You are all welcome in our midst, to share in our brotherly provisions, to take part in our public efforts, to work with us in behalf of the poor and needy. If you only declare that you are one with us in the belief of our God, you are our brother in spirit, and we desire no more."</p>
   <p>It was perhaps the most important day in the history of the Order B' nai B' rith, when this resolution was adopted by District Grand Lodge No. 6. It is certainly the grandest day of this district. All who have taken part in the passage of this resolution, may congratulate themselves of having aided in the accomplishment of a historical work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1471.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Occident, also an Israelite organ, gives its hearty support: The cause of Judaism can only be fostered and encouraged, and the pernicious preconceived antipathies against Jewish belief and philosophy materially abrogated, if we throw open the portals of our institutions and admit men of good morals and probity, of all mankind.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
