<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
            <date when="1919-03-15">March 15, 1919</date>.
            <title level="a">The Amalgamated a Victor in a large order Concern</title><title level="a">The Continental Tailoring Company signs union agreement grants a  hour week and all other demands. the workers are inspired.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
            <date when="1919-03-15">March 15, 1919</date>.
            <title level="a">The Amalgamated a Victor in a large order Concern</title><title level="a">The Continental Tailoring Company signs union agreement grants a <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> hour week and all other demands. The workers are inspired.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday morning, Mr. Samuels, the manager of the Continental Tailoring Company, one of the largest special order houses of Chicago, signed the union agreement with the amalgamated Clothing workers of America.</p>
   <p>The important points in the agreement are as follows: 1. Collective bargaining - for the purpose of coming to an understanding as to wages and working conditions and finding a system whereby grievances that arise during the life of the agreement can be ironed out. - 2 - 44 hours work a week. Time and half for overtime to week workers, and 50 percent more for piece workers. - 3 - During slack seasons the work shall be equally divided among the workers. - 4 - It is agreed that the principals of the Preferential Union shop shall exist and be recognized.  - 5 - Any controversies of the worker can, by a representative of the worker, by presented to one in charge of giving out the work or any one who is authorized by the firm to handle grievances.</p>
   <p>In case no agreement is reached, the case shall be left to an arbitration com-<pb facs="5423972_2_1576.jpg" n="2"/>mittee selected by both parties. Before the agreement was signed, a meeting of all the workers of the Continental Tailoring Company was in session, where one by one, these points were discussed. The workers approved the agreement. It was then that Mr. Samuels signed the agreement for the firm.</p>
   <p>Now this firm acknowledges the power of the Amalgamated and also the principles of collective bargaining.</p>
   <p>The other special order houses will soon follow the example of the Continental Tailors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
