<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-10-20">Oct. 20, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">The Jews and the Socialists</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Cri du Peuple.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1442</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1442.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-10-20">Oct. 20, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWS AND THE SOCIALISTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Cri du Peuple.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following letter which I have received, affords me the opportunity to give the Socialist Party's definition of the Jewish race.</p>
   <p>Citizen Lafargue!</p>
   <p>First of all I congratulate you upon your acquittal; the blow you have dealt the money barons was excellent, but I am curious to know why the prefix Jew was never missing when you mentioned their names? This is not done with any other religious sect. My business brings me in contact with many Jews and I wonder why you attack this class of our citizens which has produced some of the best Socialists. This is unjust and not at all within the doctrine of Socialist brotherhood, therefore, I raise my voice in protest. Will you kindly make a brief explanation in the Cri du Peuple?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1443.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The unknown writer of this letter is right. The Jewish question requires a profound study. Attempts at Jew-baiting have been made in Europe for years. The German Jews have to fight a hard battle against envy and jealousy, spread by Philisters and the clergy.</p>
   <p>National hatred or race hatred is unknown to socialism; I personally have the greatest admiration for this persecuted people, who were always subdued and who always have been bearing a yoke. These same people try now, by the use of their money to throw off their long endured enslavement.</p>
   <p>The history of the Jews is one of the greatest dramas the world has known.</p>
   <p>The attack on Rothschild by the Socialists is based on the grounds that he is the representative of modern finances. They also know that the capitalists, no matter whether Jew, Catholic, Protestant, Free-thinker or Atheist, worship one God only, and that is the capital.</p>
   <p>And they also know, that their conscience can easily be bought. German Socialists count among their most excellent members many comrades of Jewish <pb facs="5423972_2_1444.jpg" n="3"/>faith. Marx was a Jew, so was La Salle, Frankel, Bernstein, secretary of the Social Democrat; the Socialist Deputies Sabor, Kayser, and Singer are Jews, also. The Jewish race is endowed with intelligence, untiringness, faithfulness and ability.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
