<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-28">Feb. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Vigor of Jews</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0539</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0539.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-28">Feb. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE VIGOR OF JEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our report from Vienna regarding the almost incredible physical strength which a Russian Jew is demonstrating daily before thousands of people attending a circus there, has more than a local significance. Not only does this phenomenon confirm the ancient Biblical story of Samson's strength, it also explains many other things. Every anthropologist will asknowledge the fact that just as a mentally sound people can produce intellectual giants, so a physically strong and sound people can produce physical giants.</p>
   <p>Anti-Semitic scientists have sought for a number of years to convince the world that we [Jews], have not only degenerated intellectually as a people, but physically as well, and that we are even inferior, as compared to other peoples. When anti-Semites assert this, it is an accusation; when Jews <pb facs="5423972_2_0540.jpg" n="2"/>assert this, it is a superstition.</p>
   <p>The Jews are not physically inferior to other peoples; proportionately they are much stronger and healthier than any other race because our struggle for existence has always been so bitter that only the strongest could have endured it. A weak people would have fallen by the wayside. It is sheer superstition to assert that the Diaspora has weakened us physically. Only recently, hundreds of thousands of young Jewish men of Eastern Europe performed deeds of heroism on the battlefields. If the Jews were not such a strong and powerful race physically, they would have perished long ago.</p>
   <p>The fact is that the Jews are much stronger physically than is generally realized. If the story of Samson has a symbolic significance, that significance is that the Jews are a very strong race physically because the process of selection has been carried further among the Jews than among other peoples.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
