<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-24">Aug. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Who Is the Jew?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1037</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1037.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-24">Aug. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">WHO IS THE JEW?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Who is the Jew? He is musically inclined. He writes love poetry. He composes sweet songs and melodies, combining them in harmonious unison. His chords--oh, how wonderfully they speak; his bow is so sweet. Yet, his life is so inharmonious--is so broken up. He is the dramatic actor of the world. He is passionate in tragedy, romantic in melodrama. He is a hero [on the stage]. A world pays him respect. Yet, off the stage he is held in abomination and encounters contempt everywhere he goes.</p>
   <p>He is a reformer of society. Whatever affects mankind affects him. He weeps with all peoples. He sheds tears for their suffering. He spills his blood courageously for his fellow men; willingly, he sacrifices his life in every human struggle. Yet how little recognition is he given for all this.</p>
   <p>He is omnipresent. He is to be seen in all climates, in all parts of the <pb facs="5423972_2_1038.jpg" n="2"/>world. Yet, how little is he known. A single member of his kind--an individual--is often admired and loved by the whole world. Yet, his entirety--the whole--is despised and reviled.</p>
   <p>It is said that he is a practical creature. He is active and seeks reality. Where can there be found another such dreamer, such an unfortunate dreamer?</p>
   <p>He is a citizen of the world; the world is his home. He places himself every-where, adapts himself everywhere. He is rich, possessing Korah's treasures [fabulous wealth]. He is a banker and is at the apex of industrial and financial enterprises. He is a worker, a builder, an organizer. Yet, he is the poorest among paupers. He is dependent upon the will of someone else, the influence of someone else. The caprice of a despot, the change in the administration of a country, a word, a stroke of a pen--and he is ruined.</p>
   <p>We are told that he is a parasite, a leech; he does not want to work, He <pb facs="5423972_2_1039.jpg" n="3"/>lives off the sweat of others. Yet, who toils as laboriously as he and who is so underpaid? Just watch him at the sewing machine, at the shoe-repair machine, always bent over his work and always poorly paid.</p>
   <p>All cultures are his; he speaks all languages. Yet, not one is his own. He is a stranger unto himself. It is said that he is the same today as he was two thousand years ago in Jerusalem, in Alexandria. He does not change. Yet, what a capable organism he is! How he adapts himself, how he masters his surroundings. What an old type he is! According to the natural law, he should have vanished long ago. Yet, look at him--always young, always old. He still dreams of a new youth! What aspiration, what youthfulness!</p>
   <p>What a leader! There isn't an undertaking in which he could not become involved and receive distinction. What a dear leader, a successful leader. Yet, what a poor sorry leader he is for himself.</p>
   <p>It is his philosophy, which has so deeply penetrated the life of each <pb facs="5423972_2_1040.jpg" n="4"/>individual of the so-called civilized race. Whether good or bad--they cherish it. They press it to their breasts with love and great admiration. Yet he, himself, is exposed to every sort of humiliation and persecution just because of this.</p>
   <p>How wonderfully he is protected against many diseases--such tenacity of life. Yet, look at him; he is short of stature, wizened, pale and nervous. It is said that he is full of self-conceit, a regular bigwig. Yet, where can there be found another self-critique more severe, from Moses to Isaiah and Jerimiah down to La Salle and Heine of recent years.</p>
   <p>Recently, a Swedish professor made the remark that in his opinion a Swede is honest until he is proven to be dishonest and then it is hard to believe. At the moment, I thought of the Jew. Doesn't the world believe him to be dishonest until he is proven to be honest, and then it is hard to believe that?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1041.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Jew occupies a prominent niche in world literature; in the drama and essay he is the strongest character, the central figure. Yet, he is seldom portrayed in real art, but always in artistic reality. His twist, his look, his move, his sigh is imitated, but seldom his entire personality.</p>
   <p>He is a living enigma as complicated and intricate as his environment has made him. He is as hard as a rock, as sentimental as a young lass; he has the naivete of a child, is as puzzling as the Sphinx, as hard-hearted as a village trader. He is full of suspicion and is suspicious. He is the lover and the hater, the builder and destroyer, the friend and the enemy--the Jew.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
