<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1882-08-04">August 4, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">Slave Cunning</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1882-08-04">August 4, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">SLAVE CUNNING</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The incoming slaves, (Russian refugees), of which nearly five hundred are booked for this city, are coming in shipments of from seventy to one hundred. Many of them have some means, but most of them have large families with many children.</p>
   <p>The Aid Society's room is a veritable barrack. Superintendent Bartenstein, still holds sway and "Our Carter" (Mayor Carter Harrison,) has conferred police authority on him, and he is now a full fledged "Cop." Aside from expounding municipal laws, he does a deal of lecturing on moral philosophy. He has become thoroughly conversant with Russo-Judean humans, and can see right through them.</p>
   <p>Among leading citizens present at a levee held in examining the late arrivals were Mr. Treasurer B. Gradle, Secretary S. Rosenfels, Rev. Dr. E. G. Hirsch and Julius Silversmith, editor Occident.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1450.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The interrogations are pithy and piquant. The Russo-Israelite is a stubborn fellow, and will give any but the right answers. It is second nature with him. We can readily observe that having been constantly under surveillance of a despotic government; the neighbor of a fanatical and bigoted rabble; he becomes stolid and passive, and therefore, unwilling to convey the right answer.</p>
   <p>He will stare sideways; upward and downward; throw up his begrimed hands with palm outward; above his shoulders; and with the blandest mien ejaculate; "Ich verstei nischt," i. e., does not want to understand any question, and not until all subterfuges and contradictions are ferreted out, are there any truths eliminated from him.</p>
   <p>The "capping" scheme of boarding house keepers has been squelched. The committee has changed that policy by giving each grown person a certain sum per week. They have also resolved to send off into the interim towns a number, say about seventy, where our co-religionists will place them to become useful citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
