<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-12">Jan. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">From Sabbath Eve to Sabbath Eve</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0141</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0141.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-12">Jan. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FROM SABBATH EVE TO SABBATH EVE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What is the task of a rabbi? I have heard recently many answers to this question and, from these answers, I can understand how we are sinking deeper and deeper into an abyss. At a gathering of representatives from the different types of synagogues, these are some of the questions which arose. What is the task of a rabbi? What must a rabbi do in order to earn the name of a good rabbi, to be respected, and to fulfill his duties?</p>
   <p>"He must comfort broken hearts," was the answer of a president of a modern synagogue.</p>
   <p>"He must be a good organizer," was the answer of someone else.</p>
   <p>"He must be capable of raising money for charity," was the answer of a third.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0142.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"He must be capable of attracting the youth."</p>
   <p>"He must be capable of representing his community."</p>
   <p>"He must speak to the Gentiles in such a manner that they will respect us."</p>
   <p>"He must be capable of delivering fine sermons in English."</p>
   <p>"He must be concerned with Bible classes."</p>
   <p>"He must be a good mixer."</p>
   <p>"He must make the women interested in charity and in Judaism."</p>
   <p>"He must be a competent teacher."</p>
   <p>"He must have a faultless character in order to command respect."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0143.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"He must be an honest man."</p>
   <p>"He must be a good speaker."</p>
   <p>"He must be a highly educated man."</p>
   <p>"He must be a college man."</p>
   <p>"He must be a practical man with a business spirit."</p>
   <p>"He must be capable of entertaining people."</p>
   <p>"He must have an attractive personality."</p>
   <p>"He must fill the temple or synagogue."</p>
   <p>These are the answers as to the tasks and duties of a rabbi, as they are understood by the modern Jews of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0144.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>No one said that the rabbi must be a great Lamdan [the word Lamdan means a scholar]; that he must be a God-fearing man; that he must be engaged constantly in the study of the Torah; that he must preserve the great Jewish traditions; that he must disseminate the teachings of, and broaden [the understanding of] the Torah; and that morally and intellectually he must be the greatest man of his community.</p>
   <p>The task of comforting broken hearts belongs to a Catholic priest.</p>
   <p>The task of organizing belongs to an organizer.</p>
   <p>The task of raising funds for charity belongs to every welfare worker or civic leader.</p>
   <p>The task of attracting the youth belongs to a teacher, to an actor and, also, to a speaker on baseball.</p>
   <p>The president of a synagogue must be capable of representing his synagogue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0145.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Every educated Jew must be capable of speaking to Gentiles, so that they will respect us. A speaker who is no rabbi, can deliver a fine sermon in English. Young girls can conduct Bible classes, and they often do. To make women interested in charity and Judaism is the task of social workers. And in order to be a teacher one must have pedagogical ability and training, which has nothing to do with rabbinism. A junk dealer must also have a faultless and clean character, and we do not have to give him any credit for his honesty. A politician must also be a good speaker. Every person must have a certain degree of education, and, the fact that an individual has a college education does not entitle him to be a rabbi. A rabbi does not necessarily have to be a practical man. If he were a practical person, he would probably be in the suspender business and not a rabbi, because from a practical standpoint it does not pay to be a rabbi, especially in America. If a congregation seeks a rabbi who can entertain people, let it engage a vaudeville entertainer. These are not the tasks of a rabbi.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0146.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>A rabbi does not necessarily have to be a public mixer. A rabbi who is learned in the Torah need not be a great orator. If the congregation wants a great orator, let it engage a Magid (preacher). A rabbi need not be a Magid nor a college man. Rabbi Yehuda L. Gordon is no college man, yet, hundreds of college men can go to him for knowledge, even if it concerns secular knowledge. If it is the task of a rabbi to be an honest man, does it follow that the members of a congregation should not be honest? You know that this is absurd and foolish.</p>
   <p>I believe--and all of you know--that an old-fashioned rabbi, a rabbi like Yehuda L. Gordon, makes a greater impression on the American Jewish youth than a boy-rabbi, a toy-rabbi, or a goi rabbi; he will make an even greater impression on the Christians than will a modern rabbinical dude.</p>
   <p>But what? The American Jews have already forgotten the Jewish traditions. They do not know what the proper task of a rabbi is. They are somewhat misled. Their Jewish minds are a bit dulled, and that is why they utter so much foolishness when dealing with the question of the task of a rabbi.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
