<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-07-07">July 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Voice of the People - to the Parents -</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-07-07">July 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">VOICE OF THE PEOPLE - TO THE PARENTS -</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, after the children left our Sabbath school to go home, they were stopped and given pamphlets, distributed by missionaries. Some of the children returned to the school, showing us these pamphlets. Glancing through the latter, we explained to the children the nature and subject of these pamphlets and the children immediately destroyed them.</p>
   <p>Many of the parents of the West Side are not aware of the fact that the Jewish neighborhood is full of missionaries, whose sole purpose is to separate the Jewish children from Judaism, and convert them to Christianity. They have opened a number of schools, where their gospel is spread. Prominent Jews so far haven't done anything to combat this, and save the <pb facs="5423972_2_1058.jpg" n="2"/>Jewish children from the missionaries' grasp. Many mothers do not even know, where their youngsters spend their time; some are indifferent and the result is that many a Jewish child may be found in a mission home.</p>
   <p>A lot has been done to attract the children to the fold of Judaism, but much more must be done to draw them away from the Christian influence. For this purpose we opened three Sabbath schools, where the children are being taught Jewish history, religion and to read and write Jewish, also Jewish morality. These schools are doing all in their power to give the children a Jewish education and, therefore, deserve our thanks for performing their duty in bringing up our children in the Jewish tradition and guarding them from those, who are trying to separate them against their wish. Let the parents inform themselves as to where their children spend their time, to make sure that they will be an honor, instead of a curse among the Jewish people in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
