<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-22">Jan. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Public in Chicago in Uproar against the Nonkosher Butchers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0162</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0162.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-22">Jan. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH PUBLIC IN CHICAGO IN UPROAR AGAINST THE NONKOSHER BUTCHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, at the morning Services, the rabbis of the Chicago synagogues spoke about the scandal and the profanation of the Holy Name, caused by A. Wachovsky, a butcher at 1021 South Paulina Street. Last Thursday, Rabbi Azriel Epstein, together with a committee from the Kosher Food Council, came to inspect the meat that Wachovsky was selling to Jews. The butcher Wachovsky, as related Friday in the Courier, pointed a revolver at Rabbi Epstein and threatened to shoot him.</p>
   <p>The rabbis also spoke of J. Levin, a butcher at 1717 West Taylor Street, who said to the committee, when they came to visit his store: "Get out of my store. I am from Minsk and I am also a socialist. You cannot bluff me. You are the kind of people who cause the pogroms against the Jews. Take off your beards as I have, and go to ___".</p>
   <p>The people of the synagogues sympathized deeply with the rabbis and the <pb facs="5423972_2_0163.jpg" n="2"/>Kosher Food Council and became very angry at the butchers who are paid for kosher food, and sell nonkosher food.</p>
   <p>Everywhere that Jews assemble, in the synagogues, on the streets, in homes, people spoke of Thursday's incident, and great excitement prevailed.</p>
   <p>The Kosher Food Council called a meeting last night of the synagogue representatives and the rabbis. The meeting took place at the Congregation Anshe Kneseth Israel; Mr. M. Salk acted as chairman. The scandal was discussed and the Kosher Food Council was promised moral and financial support in its task of supervising the Kosher food in the city.</p>
   <p>The trial of the butcher A. Wachovsky, who is under a thirty-five hundred dollar bond, charged with an assault with a deadly weapon upon Rabbi Epstein, with malice aforethought, has been postponed. Attorney Samuel B. Epstein made this request last Friday. The trial will take place in a few weeks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0164.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Kosher Food Council will continue its work this week; it hopes that the butchers whom its committee will visit, will be willing to show the committee the meat they are selling, so that the Jewish public will not be cheated.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Klingman, 3231 Lexington Street, one of the Jewish women who have been appointed to assist the Kosher Food Council in its work, was attacked last night by Mrs. Wachovsky, in front of her butcher shop, because Mrs. Klingman told some Jewish women there that Wachovsky was the butcher who had pointed a revolver at Rabbi Epstein, and threatened to shoot him. Some women rescued Mrs. Klingman and Mrs. Wachovsky went back to the store to help her husband sell the meat that the rabbis wanted to examine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
