<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-10-24">October 24, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Priest Relates the Virtues of the Jew</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-10-24">October 24, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">PRIEST RELATES THE VIRTUES OF THE JEW</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Rev. Barger of the Maywood Congregational Church discussed and praised the Jews for their virtues. In his lecture last Saturday, at the Maywood Opera to an overcrowded Jewish mass meeting, he described the virtues of the Jewish people. The subject was "The Jew in America." This meeting was sponsored by the Marks Nathan Orphans Home, and all profits derived from the sale of tickets were turned over to that institution.</p>
   <p>In part of his address, he stated, "What is the use in arguing, whether or not we will recognize one another in heaven, when we have not as yet, learned to know each other in this earthly world?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1258.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The Jewish race, as a matter of history includes many warm-hearted philanthropists, who loved God and their fellowman and to exclude the Jew from the brotherhood of man, is just simply not Christianity, but un-Democratic and un-American.</p>
   <p>"The Jew in general is a law abiding citizen, honest and loyal, a home lover, respects honesty; when it comes to charity, he can boast of being the need on the list. There is never a case on record where a brother Jew was ever buried in Potter's field, for he takes a pride in taking an interest in his fellowman; of course, understand me, there are many bad Jews, also just like any other nationality, but as a whole the Jew is good at heart and makes a good citizen. Take the Jew away from the world, we lose Hayne for poetry, Halevi and Mendelsohn in music, and Jacobi in mathematics. The whole world without the Bible would look like a dark night, for the Jew is the one who created the Ten Commandments, and wrote the Bible, which is the greatest book since creation."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
