<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-09-26">September 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Employment Discrimination against the Jew</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0412</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0412.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-09-26">September 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">EMPLOYMENT DISCRIMINATION AGAINST THE JEW</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Nearly half of the Jews in America are subject to an economic and industrial boycott. There is a silent conspiracy of anti-Jewish employers." When such a statement can come from no less eminent an authority than Rabbi Stephen S. Wise, there can be no doubt in anybody's mind that employment discrimination against the Jew is a real problem. When it is almost the universal practice for Jewish graduates of normal schools to change their names in order to obtain jobs as teachers; when Jewish applicants at employment agencies are generally told to indicate their religious preference as that of some protestant denomination if they want to get a job, and when the heads of large business firms openly admit that they will not employ men with markedly Jewish characteristics, then it is high time that we pause and consider our position in "this land of liberty."</p>
   <p>We find that, although the political emancipation of the Jew is already more than a century old, curiously enough America has during the last decade registered an increase of anti-Semitic feeling, as the interests of the activities of America have, during this period, been predominantly commercial and industrial, so this new flood of prejudice has found economic expression in the form of widespread employment discrimination against the Jew. There are <pb facs="5423972_2_0413.jpg" n="2"/>tens of thousands of girls in New York City alone who are out of work for no other reason than that they are of the Jewish faith. And this condition is by no means confined to New York City or state. A prominent Gentile minister has declared, "In almost every land today, even though brutal forms of assault have ceased, the Jew suffers some sort of economic discrimination. In this respect America is no exception." In the face of this situation we may very well devote some of our thought to the problem of unemployment discrimination.</p>
   <p>However, we must recognize that, although this particular policy in its specific application is a comparitively recent development, it is, in its essence no whit different than all the multifarious manifestations of prejudice which have been directed at the Jews in ages past. To pretend to find distinct and therefore rational causes for unemployment discrimination that are not bound up soul and fibre with the whole problem of prejudice against the Jew, involves a very narrow and archaic view of the psychological basis of human actions. Policies are merely the expressions of attitudes. Employment discrimination against the Jew is merely one manifestation of the anti-Semitic attitude.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0414.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It will benefit no one for us to recite statistics, or narrate incidents, or classify kinds of discrimination. Neither the fact of employment discrimination against the Jew, nor the undesirableness of its existence can be questioned. But once we have diagnosed the disease, we are no longer interested in the symptons, but demand to know the causes and cures.</p>
   <p>However, the only way we can approach the causes of discrimination is to discover the causes of anti-Semitism; and the only hope that we can have of doing away with this policy must be in the possibility of changing the attitude that dictates it. So if our discussion is not to be a purely academic one, we must attempt to discover, if possible, a new approach to the age old problem of anti-Jewish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
