<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1881-08-12">August 12, 1881</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1881-08-12">August 12, 1881</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Russification? - Rumors are afloat that some influential American Israelites are afraid of the coming influx of Russian Jews into the United States, and that they fear in consequence thereof American Judaism would be Russified. In one regard, certainly, we have to look forward to the coming immigration with some anxiety and sad forebodings. Many poor Russian Jews will apply for aid and assistance, and but scanty means will be on hand to grant such aid.</p>
   <p>And suppose, half a million of these Russian Jews would come, and would in a few years out-number all the Sephardic and German Jews now living in America - how could they Russianize you, dear reader, and you, and you? Would you be compelled to wear Russo-Jewish Kaftans, because a future Russo-American Synod might decree that Malbush Nokhri (the manner of dressing as Gentiles do) would be 'Hukkath ha-boyim (an anti-Jewish custom)? Or would you have to give up your grammatical speaking, and would you be caused <pb facs="5423972_2_1461.jpg" n="2"/>to talk in the barbarous jargon of Podolia? The reform party may be out-numbered, and the new orthodox party of our Portuguese and English friends may be out-numbered by the old orthodox, culture-hating party, hailing from Volhynia and Bessarabia. But the minorities will have the rights and the means to remain uninfluenced by the Russian majority.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
