<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-06-21">June 21, 1877</date>, 3:3.
<title level="a">Seligman-Hilton</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Editor of the Tribune</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1511</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1511.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-06-21">June 21, 1877</date>, 3:3.
<title level="a">SELIGMAN-HILTON</title><title level="a" type="sub">To The Editor of The Tribune</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, June 20. - You are certainly right in saying that the action of Judge Hilton, in excluding Mr. Seligman from his hotel, should not be constructed as a signification of a prejudice prevailing against the Jews generally.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hilton, however, not only insulted Mr. Seligman, but, by giving instructions not to admit any Hebrew into his hotel, threw a deep offense into the face of the undersigned, and of every one confessing the Jewish faith and belonging to the Jewish race. What charges has this Mr. Hilton to bring against me and against my friends A, B, and C, by which to justify his vulgar insults against us?</p>
   <p>What charges has he to make against my said friends, whom he has never met before, and who undoubtedly stand mentally and morally on the same level with him, and very probably above him? One thing Mr. Hilton has certainly demonstrated. He was successful in showing that he is filled with a spirit of narrowness and of medieval fanaticism and that he would have shone brilliantly in a society of bygone ages. If now the Jewish merchants would not withdraw their custom and patronage from the various houses conducted by this Mr. Hilton, and if they would not thereby manfully <pb facs="5423972_2_1512.jpg" n="2"/>resent, in as far as possible, the insult they have experienced, they would show a lamentable lack of self-respect.</p>
   <p>I hope, however, and expect that the Jewish business men, without exception, will act in this case in accordance with their sense of honor and of dignity. And I furthermore expect that hundreds of Christian clergymen, and jurists, and merchants, and citizens generally, will powerfully aid the Israelites in their combating this spirit of fanaticism that dares to appear again in the fourth quarter of the nineteenth century. Respectfully,</p>
   <p>B. Felsenthal,</p>
   <p>Rabbi of the Zion Congregation</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
