<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-03-01">Mar. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Great Victory for Jewish Dietary Law in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-03-01">Mar. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT VICTORY FOR JEWISH DIETARY LAW IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sini Sausage Factory promises the rabbis that it will build a new factory where its production will be guarded with the most rigid inspection, as required by Jewish dietary law.</p>
   <p>The dietary law met with great victory yesterday in Chicago. The meeting, attended by many rabbis and a number of Jewish citizens, proved to be quiet a success.</p>
   <p>The demand of the rabbis that the Sini Sausage Factory conform to a strict observance of the dietary law in their new factory, was promptly accepted by the factory owners.</p>
   <p>Another demand was that the factory must sever its connection with the David Berg Factory, and build a special building on the West Side for the manufacture of Kosher sausage; that they shall not manufacture Kosher and non-Kosher sausage under one roof; that the building of the new factory must begin not later than May 15, 1916, and must be completed by the 15th of November, 1916, and that the Sini Company must furnish a ten thousand dollar bond to guarantee that the new <pb facs="5423972_2_0256.jpg" n="2"/>factory will be completed by the 15th of November, the bond to be forfeited for the benefit of Jewish charity in Chicago, should they fail. Many other demands were made on the Sini Sausage Factory which were accepted with the assurance that all demands by the rabbis will be carried out to the letter.</p>
   <p>The meeting was one of the most interesting in the history of orthodox Jewry in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
