<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-12-19">Dec. 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Force of a Language</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-12-19">Dec. 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE FORCE OF A LANGUAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the British Parliament, a few days ago, an interesting discussion took place concerning the Hebrew language. The government was asked why it has allowed, Hebrew, a dead language to become the official government-language in Palestine. To this question Mr. Bonar Law, the government's representative, replied that seventy per cent of all the Jews in Palestine understand Hebrew and speak Hebrew, and that the British government has promised the Zionists its assistance in making the Hebrew language the official language of Palestine.</p>
   <p>Neither the deputy, who proposed the question, nor the government's representative, who replied to this question, knew that, in the same British Parliament, two hundred years ago, a motion was made by a Mr. Johnson that <pb facs="5423972_2_0679.jpg" n="2"/>the British Parliament should make the Hebrew language the official language of parliament and government. In the same parliament, a deputy now declares that Hebrew is a dead language, and he is even angry that the Hebrew language is tolerated in Palestine.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, there are many Jews who think that Hebrew is not a dead language, but a language of prayers, a holy language, and at best a book language. It is true, that the Hebrew language is understood by only a select few, and is being employed by only a small number of Jews in their daily use; but this does not mean that Hebrew is a dead language. The fact is that the representatives of Hebrew culture have never ceased to think in Hebrew and to write in Hebrew. And a language is alive so long as it is a creative factor--so long as the life and the thoughts of a people are expressed in it. Whoever desires to have a clear picture of Jewish conditions in the Middle Ages, should read the works of the Middle Age sages, where the living conditions of our people are widely discussed. Whoever wishes to have <pb facs="5423972_2_0680.jpg" n="3"/>a picture of Jewish thoughts of the Middle Ages should read the works of our great Middle Age philosophers, and whoever wants to know how the literary genius of our people expressed itself in the Middle Ages, let him read our great Middle Age poets.</p>
   <p>So long as the entire creation in life, the rational and emotional world of a people are expressed in a single language, that language is a live one. Hebrew was never our native tongue, but our cultural language, and this fact makes Hebrew a live language. If the daily usage of a language makes it a live one, then Albanian is a language and Hebrew is not; Turkish then is a live language and Hebrew is not. Hundreds of tribes in Africa speak their own languages, and yet no one will assert that they are live languages; on the contrary, they are dead, because they are noncreative languages.</p>
   <p>The fact is that, since the Jews accepted Hebrew as their language--Hebrew <pb facs="5423972_2_0681.jpg" n="4"/>was also the language of many other Semitic peoples--the Jewish spirit never ceased to think in Hebrew, and the history of Hebrew literature since its beginning was an uninterrupted one, e. i. in the history of the Jewish people, there is no period where the Jews did not create Hebrew literature, and when the Jewish spirit did not express itself in Hebrew. How lively must a language be, that even though it is no more the tongue of a people it still remains the cultural medium of that people? Not only does Hebrew live, although it is not being used commonly now, but it has more of a living force than twenty other languages of small nationalities combined.</p>
   <p>No language in the world, even Latin and Greek, has had such a powerful influence upon the development of the great languages, as had Hebrew. What would English be without the translation of the Bible, the so-called King James version, and what would German be without the translation of the Bible by Martin Luther, who made a language out of German? One cannot <pb facs="5423972_2_0682.jpg" n="5"/>understand the English, when he has no profound knowledge of the Bible in English, and one cannot know German well, if he does not know the Lutheran translation of the Bible, and the Bible is, as it seems, written in Hebrew and not in Chinese or Turkish.</p>
   <p>Whatever the Jews have created in Hebrew has had an existence, and whatever the Jews have created in other languages have had and will have only a temporary value, because the language of the Jewish genius is not Jewish, nor any other dialect, but Hebrew. Upon that rests the power of Hebrew as a language.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
