<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1917-11-04">November 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The 70th Birthday of the Jewish Community of Chicago</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1020</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1020.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1917-11-04">November 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE 70th BIRTHDAY OF THE JEWISH COMMUNITY OF CHICAGO</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In 1838 the first Jewish settlers migrated here. The first Jewish pioneers were all German-Jews, mostly from Bavaria. They were chiefly occupied with peddling and upon meeting with success, became storekeepers. Several have also taken to agriculture. By November 4, 1847, they were already so densely populated that they were able to organize themselves into a Jewish community. On November 3, 1847, twenty-five Jews convened in a dry goods store at 155 Lake street, and determined to establish a synagogue under the name of "Kehiloth Anshe Mariv" (The Community of the West). The following day they adopted a constitution and it was signed by fourteen members - the fathers of our Chicago Jewry. The old Kehiloth Anshe Mariv stood in the shadow of the later millionaire congregation "Sinai." All the German-Jewish congregations became small bodies of water im comparison to the great stream of the Jewish speaking masses, which reached the height of hundreds of thousands. The Kehiloth Anshe Mariv and the later German- Jewish community distinguished themselves in the field of charity. They were the founders of the Michael Reese Hospital, the United Hebrew Charities and other charitable institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1021.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, they were not in need of these institutions themselves. Most of them became wealthy and foreign to the Jewish life. The reform religion, which they never sought to spread out of the boundaries of the wealthy classes, formed a wall between them and the common people. They have segregated themselves yet farther from the Jewish masses. Their sympathy is on the side of reaction. Their only connection with the Jewish race was through charity and mediations. The trade unions annihilated the necessity of beggary. They teach the worker to demand a higher standard of living with pride and not by humble beggary.</p>
   <p>The Community of the West has survived for seventy years and is now actually decrepit. It is not more than one of the many sects of America. It has no more connection with Jews and Judaism. Social justice and international peace is strange and fiendish to it. The Jewish masses of Chicago belong to the new "Community of the East." They are organized into trade unions, workmen's circles, and Socialist and radical orders. Karl Marx's prophecy that Judaism will be destroyed with the destruction of capitalism was aimed at the rich Jews of the Community of the West, - the worshippers of the Golden Calf. The Community of the East does not fear destruction. It struggles for the realization of Socialism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
