<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-25">July 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">South Chicago Poles Sentenced in Blood-Accusation Case</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0775</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0775.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II E 2 (Polish)</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-25">July 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SOUTH CHICAGO POLES SENTENCED IN BLOOD-ACCUSATION CASE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The case of H. Cohen, 8401 Buffalo Avenue, against Casimer Lota and seventeen other Poles ended yesterday with the conviction of the Poles. On July 4, as was printed at the time, exclusively in the Courier, the latter sought to instigate a pogrom against the Jews in South Chicago on the pretext that the elder Cohen had lured a Polish boy into his store in order to kill him and to use his blood for religious purposes.</p>
   <p>Judge Gemil, before whom the case was tried, fined the leader, Lota, one hundred dollars, and the others, ten dollars each. Their sentence would have been much greater had Cohen's witnesses appeared to tell how Lota, his accomplices and a mob of about three thousand Poles, paraded [up and down] Buffalo Avenue, where Jewish stores are located, yelling, "The Jews must be killed". But the witnesses were absent. One of them was H. B. Frank, a Jewish grocer on Buffalo Avenue, to whom Mr. Lota, a week before the Fourth, had boasted that he would, on that day, teach the Jews "respect".</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0776.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Frank's excuse was his fear of the Poles. Lota is one of his tenants.</p>
   <p>The courtroom in South Chicago was packed yesterday with Polish men and women. Present were the accused, their wives, children, relatives and friends; a Pole whose partner in the saloon business had his nose bitten off (sic) in a fight over money; an old Polish woman whose husband split her head open in a fight over a bottle of whiskey; a Pole and his wife who robbed another Pole of various articles in his house, and at the point of a revolver, threatened to shoot the policeman who caught him if he wasn't released. The policeman overpowered him, and yesterday he was held to the Grand Jury.</p>
   <p>Marcus and Laimus Cohen, the two sons of Mr. H. Cohen, appeared to testify against the accused. The father, because of his health, could not appear in court. The boys told of the blood accusation directed by Lota against them, and of how he had brought the rest of Buffalo Avenue's Poles to terrorize Jews on that street. They related too how Lota and other Poles, <pb facs="5423972_2_0777.jpg" n="3"/>escorted by police, entered the store and searched in the basement and in every corner. Though no child was found, police announcing this fact to those outside the store, yet he, Lota, still ran about yelling that the Cohens had killed a Polish boy and bribed the police to cover up the matter. Policemen Welden and McCarthy testified in favor of the plaintiffs.</p>
   <p>Casimer Lota, an undersized Pole whose face revealed little intelligence and a great deal of fury, was then called. Jews of South Chicago who know him say that Casimer Lota is somewhat of a "radical" of the Ignatz Doshinski school, and like his teacher, argues that in a Polish country, on Polish soil, one must speak, think and feel Polish.</p>
   <p>Casimer Lota spoke in broken English, whereupon Judge Gemil commented: "Goodness, what citizens we have". Lota completely denied the charges, adding that he tried to disperse the mob because he knew that the Cohens were fine people who have been unjustly accused. Policeman Lawrence Kobzo <pb facs="5423972_2_0778.jpg" n="4"/>(a Pole) came to his aid, giving the same testimony to the judge. Kobzo verified the fact that the defendant told the Poles: "If you are displeased with the Jews, do not buy at their stores".</p>
   <p>Assistant States Attorney John Kashin questioned Kobzo and proved him to be a liar. Assistant City Attorney Edward H. Lubek explained to the judge that Lota and the rest of them were rioters who deserved to be sentenced. Kashin and Lubek understood the blood accusation very well, and clarified it in their prosecution.</p>
   <p>Lota was the first to be sentenced; the others followed, one after another. The judge permitted no remarks to be made. Those who were sentenced all had [enough] money to pay their fines. It is said that some of them received the money from the Polish druggist Hofmann.</p>
   <p>Patrick Murphy, of the firm Piden, Cohen and Murphy, was the lawyer for <pb facs="5423972_2_0779.jpg" n="5"/>Mr. Cohen. He handled the case well.</p>
   <p>As the case closed and the court emptied, shouts were heard [coming] from the street. It was Casimer Lota quarreling with his lawyer, Billy O'Connor, demanding the twenty dollars which he had paid in order to be acquitted. The quarrel ended with O'Connor spitting at Lota and driving away in his automobile amid a burst of laughter from some Americans standing nearby.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
