<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-03-10">March 10, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Heard and Seen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-03-10">March 10, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">HEARD AND SEEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the most important things that the Jews of Chicago and elsewhere in the United States must not neglect is to register for election.</p>
   <p>The future success of the Jews in America depends upon the number of registered Jewish voters. It does not matter what political side you are on. You may be a Democrat, Republican, or Socialist, but you cannot vote for your party candidates unless you are a registered voter. Our youth is growing in numbers and the political field is big. There are possibilities of success for hundreds of thousands of Jewish young men, but they cannot possibly reach their goal unless they take advantage of the opportunity to register and thereby become a part of our free country.</p>
   <p>Next Tuesday the 12th of March is the only day of registration for the coming election. The polls will be open from 8 A. M. to 9 P. M. Do not <pb facs="5423972_2_1310.jpg" n="2"/>forget your duty to the country which gives you equal rights with all who live within its boundary.</p>
   <p>You are duty bound to the great city of Chicago in which you earn your livelihood. You are indebted to the friends who would like to represent you politically. You are also indebted to your children who wish to be recognized politically and socially.</p>
   <p>We would like very much to see each and every Jewish citizen's name on the registration book.</p>
   <p>The next campaign will be very interesting and important. The Street Car Settlement question is coming up for decision. A mayor is to be elected for the next four years. In the 9th ward a Jewish candidate is running for alderman. He will no doubt need every Jewish vote to be elected. By all means do your duty and register Tuesday, March 12.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
