<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-09-28">Sept. 28th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Converting the Jews</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">To the Editor of the Tribune, Chicago, September 22nd</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-09-28">Sept. 28th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">CONVERTING THE JEWS</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">To the Editor of The Tribune, Chicago, September 22nd</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago your paper contained a report concerning the "Conversion" of a Jewish boy of this city to Christianity.</p>
   <p>Referring to the report, I would respectfully ask a few questions, and I would be obliged for your kindly answering the same.</p>
   <p>1. Is it morally right and justifiable to enroll an ignorant Jewish boy, a minor, among the pupils of a Christian Sunday School, and to give him there, during a course of two or three years, a Christian training without the knowledge and consent of his parents?</p>
   <p>2. Is it morally right and justifiable to baptize an ignorant Jewish minor without the knowledge and consent of his parents? Is it morally right and justifiable to cause by such an act unspeakable grief to old parents, who look upon the denial of the one God of Israel by one of their children and upon their worshiping any human being as a deity as one of the greatest misfortunes that could befall them?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1474.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>3. Is it morally right and justifiableto encourage a Jewish boy, a minor, in his waywardness and in his continued transgressing of the Fifth Commandment, - to become an accomplice to him in his deceiving his parents by lies and double dealing.</p>
   <p>4. Is is legally permitted to anyone to baptize a Jewish boy, a minor, without the knowledge and consent of his parents? Would the Shaffner family have sufficient reason for commencing an action at law against the Revs. Reid, Goodwin, Pentecost and their "Christian" accomplices? If so, they ought to commence such a suit against the spiritual kidnapers and thereby create a precedent that might help to settle an important question, and might guard the community against the repetition of similar criminal acts.</p>
   <p>I do not expect that an enlightened and truly religious Christian community will indorse the action of the Rev. Goodwin and his accomplices. Such actions must be placed on the same level with the baptizing of the boy Edgar Mortana by the clergy of Rome some twenty years ago, - an act which then was denounced as a most shameful one, not only by Jews, but also by all the Protestant world <pb facs="5423972_2_1475.jpg" n="3"/>in Germany, England, United States and even by pious Catholics.</p>
   <p>A Jewish Father.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
