<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-14">May 14, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">World-Wide Congress</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. A. Margolin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0956</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0956.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-14">May 14, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WORLD-WIDE CONGRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. A. Margolin</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Finally, when the seas of blood of our pogrom victims in Poland, Lithuania, Galicia, Ukraine, Bessarabia, and Rumania had flooded every Jewish community until they reached the height of the throats of our London Judean and Palestinian representatives in Paris, then the old thoughts of Jewish National unity from organized Jewish political initiative and activity once more arose to the surface.</p>
   <p>The few Jewish Land Congresses in Poland, Ukraine, America, etc., which desired through their representatives and their programs and noble tendencies to impress and conquer the legitimate and active Polish, Czecho-Slovakian, or Rumanian delegations at the Paris World Court, became forcibly aware of their own weakness and imcompetence at the World's Peace Conference.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0957.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Like the irony of fate, there occurred the most inhuman, horrible pogroms on Jews in Poland, and Rumania. In the meanwhile, Jewish magnates of Zionist political representation quibbled, disputed, and arbitrated in Paris over "theoretical boundaries" and the interpretation of national minority rights concerning Jews, while the red devil in Warsaw, Pinsk, Keltz, and Bealistock took his toll as he roamed Jewish streets with bloody laughter and organized death reapers. Polish committees in Paris, London and Washington, as their excuse, used shaded statements about Jewish Bolshevists to blind the conscience of an awakening world democracy.</p>
   <p>Let us set aside the fact of our own chronic defeat. The dark western European destructive forces of assimilation defended in this High Court, even in the presence of Jewish delegates, the inciting Jew-hatred reaction and thereby partly influenced the Zionistic <pb facs="5423972_2_0958.jpg" n="3"/>mediators to sign away both Jewish National demands in the diaspora lands.</p>
   <p>At this opportunity let us by way of degradation and shame mention the names of these Neo-Zionistic heroes: Herman Landoi and Leopold Filichovsky, who recently, at a London protest meeting of Englishmen against pogroms in Poland, arrogantly defended the Poles, lauded their "tolerance" and appealed to the Jewish masses to establish friendly relations with Paderewski, Dmovski, and other executioners.</p>
   <p>Such scandalous occurrences in behalf of the Jewish self-defending masses, such salient aimlessness and incompetent official work of Jewish delegates for our national interests abroad, meaning at the World's Court, such an unexpected influence of conspiratory organized Jewish assimilationists <pb facs="5423972_2_0959.jpg" n="4"/>in diplomatic offices, all injured Jewish claims and was only possible because of the great disorganization and disharmony in international Judaism proper.</p>
   <p>The belated efforts and inquiries of Zionist demagogues to save something of the Jewish unity from the assimilators, at the price of degrading compromises and neglecting Jewish right claims, were crowned with a hard blow. First, because such chess politics with Jewish life problems were negotiated without the initiative of the Jewish masses. They were done secretly and dictatorially. Second, because Judaism proper was not organized well enough to back its representatives in Paris with collective folk-demands and with moral authority of a united Jewish political organ.</p>
   <p>And now historical necessity of itself calls forth on its agenda <pb facs="5423972_2_0960.jpg" n="5"/>the need of immediate political succor for an international, helpless, disorganized Judaism, thus extending the only helpful anchor to the troubled Jewish diaspora ship now floundering in the high inciting waves.</p>
   <p>Disunited Judaism at the International Tribunal felt very weak, lonely, and without authority. It sadly understood that only the backing of a strong representative folk body would suffice to defend its national interests in these critical moments of its existence.</p>
   <p>Again there arose the thought to call an immediate world-wide Jewish Congress, in which Jews from every land should participate and formulate their demands.</p>
   <p>If the Jewish representatives in Paris would take the noble initiative and organize this first Jewish International Assembly, they may certainly be successful. This then would be the sole and greatest work that our delegates could accomplish, who thus far have so miserably failed at the Peace Conference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
