<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-02">June 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Demonstrators Disappointed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0843</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0843.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-02">June 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DEMONSTRATORS DISAPPOINTED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The five thousand Poles who gathered yesterday afternoon around Kosdieshka's monument in Humboldt Park, where their demonstration closed with flags and banners, national costumes, soldiers, sailors, children, and other paraphernalia, were very much disappointed. The disappointment came when they had to wait and Senator Lodge did not come. He was advertised as the chief speaker but failed to appear. Therefore, their leaders took more time to speak, and among other things the Jew was mentioned at best.</p>
   <p>Professor Zwiderovski, for example, assured all of the 5,000 Poles that pogroms on Jews in Poland have never occurred,and that all reports of murders are no more than just so much slander. His Polish brothers, he almost swore, are all such good people that it wouldn't become them to <pb facs="5423972_2_0844.jpg" n="2"/>simply do such things as make pogroms. At that, he also assured the gathering that Jews in Poland do not seek equal rights. They want privileges which mean a government within a government, and neither he nor Paderewski will agree to such.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, with more heat and temperament spoke John Wleklinski, Commissioner of the Polish National Alliance. He said that he was not afraid to tell the truth even if he knew that he were surrounded by people who would feel the gist of his words. He assured them, in the name of the Polish hero Kosdieshka, "Jews will never receive what they want." Then he spoke in a lighter tone saying how the good-hearted man granted Polish Jews the advice of leaving Poland and going either to America or to Palestine. So ended yesterday's Polish demonstration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0845.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It all took place without disturbances. The police were extraordinarily well prepared to quell any action which, it was thought, might possibly be directed against the Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
