<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-17">Oct. 17, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Some Orthodox Men</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0189</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0189.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-17">Oct. 17, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">SOME ORTHODOX MEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish community in Chicago is considered one of the most conservative, one of the most Orthodox in the United States. It has proportionately more rabbis than any other community in the United States, and it spends more on Orthodox affairs than any other Jewish community in the United States. There are some one hundred Jewish congregations in the city of Chicago, and there are more than forty rabbis in Chicago. The Orthodox Jewish community in Chicago expends not less than a million dollars annually on Orthodox affairs. This million dollars, of course, includes the sums required to keep up the synagogues, the rent or mortgages of the synagogues, the services, rabbinical salaries, charities, various social and educational enterprises, etc. In short, Chicago is an Orthodox Jewish city. It is pious, God-fearing, and law-abiding.</p>
   <p>But still, this most Orthodox Jewish community in America has not one kosher restaurant, and an Orthodox newcomer in Chicago, without friends or relatives <pb facs="5423972_2_0190.jpg" n="2"/>in the city, must either starve or go and buy a trefa meal.</p>
   <p>A few months ago, the chief rabbi of Constantinople visited Chicago, in company of the president of the most Orthodox synagogue in the Turkish capital. Both gentlemen, it is needless to say, are very pious and observers of the dietary laws, and if not for the invitation extended to them by a well-known Jewish family on the West Side, both gentlemen would have had to leave Chicago without a meal, because there is not one kosher restaurant in the city of Chicago, where a true observer of the dietary laws could take his meals. There are any number of Jewish restaurants in the city, but not one of them is strictly kosher.</p>
   <p>Now, we have forty rabbis in the city of Chicago, one hundred Orthodox congregations in the city of Chicago, one hundred presidents and vice-presidents of one hundred congregations and ever so many thousands of Orthodox laymen, who are sometimes particular about Orthodoxy. But still none of them would deem it necessary to establish an Orthodox eating place in the city. The Orthodox <pb facs="5423972_2_0191.jpg" n="3"/>stranger must get a pretty notion of Chicago Orthodoxy, when upon his arrival in the city, he cannot even find a place to eat. Suppose some national Orthodox organization would decide to hold its annual conference in the city of Chicago. What would the members of the conference do, since they cannot all impose themselves on private Orthodox families, and since there is not one real Orthodox restaurant in the city of Chicago, not even on the West Side? Is not the Orthodox community in Chicago in honor bound to enable at least Orthodox strangers to buy somewhere a kosher meal? And what about the young men in the city of Chicago from outside, who would rather partake of a kosher meal than of a trefa, but who cannot do so because there is not a kosher restaurant in the city of Chicago? We suppose that there are plenty of wealthy Orthodox Jews in Chicago, who would be ready to invest some money in such an enterprise; but there is not one to organize it.</p>
   <p>What are the rabbis doing? Why should they not do something in the matter? If they do not devote their time to Talmudic learning, let them at least do something practical for Orthodoxy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0192.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>To us it seems that a kosher restaurant in the city of Chicago is just as important as a kosher hospital or any other kosher institution. But, while a kosher hospital or any other kosher charitable institution must depend on charity, a kosher restaurant can be self-supporting and can be made a paying concern. It is only necessary that those who seem to be so much concerned about Orthodoxy talk less and do more.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
