<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-11-19">November 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Hypocrisy</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-11-19">November 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">HYPOCRISY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We confess that when we reviewed the English newspapers of yesterday and found not one picture of the Marks Nathan Orphan Asylum, we were pleased, although we would have regretted it at another occasion.</p>
   <p>At the dedication of the Marks Nathan Orphanage, last Sunday, could be found Chicago's finest Jewry, prominent people who aside from being Jews, rank with the highest citizens of Chicago in the business world, as well as in all other fields of civil activity. They have earned the recognition of the general, not only Jewish, public. Taking into consideration the number of people that were present, there was sufficient material, from a newspapers standpoint, to make somewhat more than a usual everyday story. And yet not one English newspaper found it interesting enough to give it a few words, and <pb facs="5423972_2_1223.jpg" n="2"/>to the plain, ordinary man of everyday who well understands that a paper usually prints that which is interesting to its readers and when he sees that all newspapers have determined to absolutely limit the writeup of the dedication of the Marks Nathan Home, he must come to the conclusion that the entire event is not worthy of mention.</p>
   <p>The Publicity Committee of the Marks Nathan can not be accused of neglecting to inform the English newspapers of this great event in Chicago's Jewish community.</p>
   <p>Those present at the dedication saw the reporters and photographers of the English newspapers. And yet when the reporters submitted their reports and the photographers the photographs to the managing editors of the various newspapers, they, all, used their mighty blue pencils and transferred the reports and pictures to the editorial ash-barrel.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1224.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For the English press so to ignore the Jewish public is a crime; it is a slap in the face to the entire Jewish community; and it is an insult to every Jewish social leader and to the thousands of Jews who participated in bringing about that Chicago shall have one of the most modern and largest orphan asylums in America. Had this orphan home been a Christian one, had a priest made the benediction instead of Rabbi Katkoff, had "Very Reverends" spoken instead of Rabbis Epstein and Silver, then column after column would have filled the English press, editorials would have been written on "Christian Charities," and Christian civilization would have been praised and lauded unto heaven.</p>
   <p>The Publicity Committee can not be blamed. They approached every editor of every English newspaper. They sang hypocritically to every English reporter and at the dedication, we witnessed how our prominent Jews were flattering the English reporters, and passed out good cigars to them. The Publicity Committee was so eager to have the news written <pb facs="5423972_2_1225.jpg" n="4"/>up in the English newspapers, that they were afraid to give the news to the Jewish newspapers thinking the non-Jewish (papers) might resent it.</p>
   <p>And, therefore, the Publicity Committee can not be blamed. On the other hand the English papers can not be accused either. They attended the dedication and saw that those present were not English readers. They are not their customers, so the papers ignored them.</p>
   <p>We point out that the leaders of Jewish institutions, who aren't readers of the English press, force themselves into the various "societies". When they are shown that they are not welcome, they will no longer, in the future, approach places from which they are driven. They will wake up to the fact that they, who aid in building Jewish institutions, are readers of Jewish newspapers, and they will have to turn to them when in need of publicity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
