<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-12-25">December 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Business World</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-12-25">December 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Business World</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Schiff &amp; Co. is offering 3%-interest on savings deposits. This is the oldest and most popular bank on the west side. For Jews who own houses and are not satisfied with results, this bank operates a Bureau for Landlords which offers its services for the small sum of one dollar.</p>
   <p>The announcement that Schiff &amp; Co., 720--728 W. 12th Street would pay 3% on savings deposits was received by the Jewish element as a very pleasant welcome.</p>
   <p>Just as the Jewish population is constantly growing, so also is Jewish business growing from day to day by leaps and bounds. There is no doubt that the Jewish population on the West Side is progressing rapidly, and hence the offer of 3% interest by these Jewish bankers. The name "Schiff" signifies "reliability and honesty". It is one of the oldest Jewish business institutions in Chicago. Old and young, American or foreign-born, all know <pb facs="5423972_2_1730.jpg" n="2"/>the name of the Schiff Bank and its location. For many years the bank has been instrumental in bringing over thousands of immigrants to their loved ones here in the U.S.A. The Schiff bank is the first institution to which immigrants turned for advice,which was given with the greatest of pleasure. In other words, the bank was a Bureau for those who needed good counsel and advice. The success of the new 3%-interest-rate was instantaneous, for Jews began to bring their savings to the bank, not only from the west side and Douglas Park, but also from all other parts of the city.</p>
   <p>The bank is built and managed according to the latest methods of doing banking business and contains the best safety deposit vaults, consisting of 5,000 boxes, all large size and safe; as well as 20 rooms for the convenience of customers; a steamship-ticket and bank-drafts department, in addition to all the other departments of the bank.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
