<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-08">October 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Well</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0293</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0293.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-08">October 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WELL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The lack of knowledge shown in the English newspapers of America in their concepts of Jewish religious affairs, and the entangled mess they made of them have often served as the basis for puns or humorous themes for the Jewish newspapers. But lately this situation has improved since the English press discovered its error. In the last number of the American-Hebrew, Mr. Bernard G. Richard brings forth a sample idea of one English report which had, so to speak, made a "story" of the Jewish Rosh Hoshonah. Thus:</p>
   <p>"At sunrise this morning the Hebrews of this city began the celebration of the Orthodox New Year, which is the holiest holiday on their calendar and is called Rosh Ha Kippur. It lasts for two days. But the reformed Jews who celebrate the holiday a week later observe only one day. Not <pb facs="5423972_2_0294.jpg" n="2"/>a morsel to eat nor a drop to drink are pious people permitted from sunrise till evening during these two days. But at night there is a huge feast in every Jewish home. No pickled foods may be eaten on this occasion and instead of bread they use a sort of cracker that is called 'Machtser.' The feast itself is named 'Seder.' Eggs, which indicate that the year is round are first among the foods of the evening. After the repast, the family remains seated around the table. The head of the house puts on his 'Tallith and Tfillen,' and reseats himself to sing and read the 'Mcgillah,' which is a compilation of stories taken from the Talmud and the Holy Scroll that is termed the Mishnah.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0295.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"During prayers which are held in the synagogue, readings in the original Hebrew language are given from the Bible and the Talmud. An important portion of the ceremony is the blessing of 'Liliv' which consists of a lemon imported from Palestine, and the 'Esrog' which is a bundle of palm leaves. The two items are held over the head as you turn round and around several times, chanting thereby an ancient adage. This expresses the Jewish thanksgiving for the harvest of the New Year. In the end, a procession of the sponsors of the congregation march all around the synagogue carrying the 'Sofer Torah.' This ceremony is called 'Happiness derived from the Torah.' The cantor or rabbi blows a ram's horn as soon as twilight falls to indicate the end of the old year and to usher in the new.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0296.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Rosh Ha Kippur is one of a long string of festival occasions which include Chanicah, the holiday of St. Mordecal; Purim, the day of candles; and Pesach, which is in memory of the day when Jews received the Torah on Mt. Sinai. Four weeks after the New Year is Yom - Hashonah, a day of recalling and grieving for the destruction of their Beth Hamidrosh in Jerusalem. Everyone goes to the synagogue so that all the East Side theaters and amusement places are closed. In order that there may be enough room for all attending the services, meeting halls are pressed into service. For nine days afterwards no Jew eats meat. Then comes the holiday of the three weeks. Jews go to the rivers to say 'Tashlichi at the waters' edge thus to remind them of their passage across the Red Sea."</p>
   <p>Henry Spenser has been reared by the Illinois state government since babyhood, and this is the result.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
