<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-08">Sept. 8, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">How Much Is Two Times Two</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-08">Sept. 8, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">HOW MUCH IS TWO TIMES TWO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a letter to the editor of the Daily Jewish Courier, which the reader will find in another column of today's issue, Mr. S. B. Komaiko complains bitterly about the hostile and bitter opposition of the Courier toward Reform Rabbis and Reform Judaism. He does not seek to prove that Reform Judaism is a Jewish movement and a legitimate movement in Jewish religious and national life, but he is satisfied with the assertion, that among the Reform Rabbis there is nationalists and Hebraists, and for that reason we must be tolerant with them.</p>
   <p>There are among the Jesuits many fine and educated people, great scientists and eminent educators. Nevertheless, no rational person will change his opinion about Jesuits, and, in a collision with the Jesuit order, he will combat them to the last. He will disregard the fact that, in the Jesuit order, there are also honest, fine, and educated people. When it is required to fight against <pb facs="5423972_2_0169.jpg" n="2"/>an odious principle, against a hostile system, the struggle is carried on against the entire class that represents that system, and against the entire group that is trying to realize this principle. This, it seems, is as clear as two times two is four. Yet, to many Jews, two times two is not four, and also not seventeen, but leavened bread.</p>
   <p>We repeat once more that American Reform Judaism is the biggest fraud of the Jewish religion, Jewish history, and of the Jewish view of life, not since the era of the Karaites, ("Followers of the Bible"--a Jewish sect, professing, in its religious observances and opinions, to follow the Bible to the exclusion of Rabbinical traditions and laws), but since the era of Jeroboam, son of Nebat (ancient king of Israel).</p>
   <p>Reform Judaism ridiculed Judaism and wiped out every vestige of what is Jewish. We need not mention that Reform Judaism has sought, and is still seeking to destroy all the basic principles of religious Judaism, like the divine origin <pb facs="5423972_2_0170.jpg" n="3"/>of the Torah, the precepts, such as the Sabbath, holidays, Kashruth, Treifah, etc. This alone is the greatest impudence that one can imagine. If a Jew does not want to observe the Sabbath, it is his own business, but to make a principle out of the desecration of the Sabbath, abolish the Sabbath and substitute it for Sunday, and then state that it is a religious reform, is either charlatanry or idiocy, and for both things we have no sympathy.</p>
   <p>When a Jew does not want to observe Kashruth it is his affair, and nobody will compel him to observe it. But to abolish it officially, for Jewry at large, and claim that it is a reform, is simply to declare that chaos is order.</p>
   <p>Reform Judaism rests upon the loss of religious faith of its leaders; they have no religious faith, and people lacking such should not undertake the delicate task of reforming religious practices. Only those who stand upon the ground of religious Judaism can reform Jewish religious customs. And we are not ashamed to declare that the American Reform Rabbis, with very few exceptions, are religious charlatans and hypocrites; they know very well that what they are <pb facs="5423972_2_0171.jpg" n="4"/>preaching is not Jewish religion but a half-baked imitation of Christianity. Sunday, as a rest and prayer day, is Christian. The ministration of the Reform Rabbi and the philanthropic institution is Christian, and the entire work of the Reform Rabbi in organizing a congregation and enlarging its membership, is not the task of a representative of the Jewish religion, but that of a Christian clergyman.</p>
   <p>That which the Reform Rabbis call Jewish religion, is a derision upon the Jewish religion, and is a mockery and a farce. The Reform Rabbi does not believe and has no religious faith. At best, he is a philosophical scribe, and that is not Judaism nor Jewish religion. An educated Negro can also be a philosophical thinker, and yet, he is still not a Jew.</p>
   <p>It is not enough that the Reform Rabbis, representing the interests of ignorant parvenus, have abrogated for their group everything that is Jewish, but have sought and are still seeking to disrupt the unity of the Jewish people. For them, a Jewish race does not exist, but rather Polish Jews, German Jews, French <pb facs="5423972_2_0172.jpg" n="5"/>etc. Whosoever puts his finger on the unity of our nation, he is guilty of high treason, and among all civilized nations the penalty for high treason is death.</p>
   <p>What do the Irish do with their traitors? What does any other nation do with the elements who seek to undermine the unity of their nation? And among us the Reform Rabbis are Jews and leaders albeit day in and day out, they commit the vilest treason against the Jewish nation.</p>
   <p>The claim that the Reform Rabbis have saved many Jews from apostacy is a naive one, because Reform Rabbinism is in itself apostacy--and even far worse than apostacy. For one who is converted we are no longer responsible, because we are too cowardly to state that we have neither a portion nor an inheritance in either the God or the People of Israel. But this cowardice must not become a virtue, if two times two is four and not seventeen.</p>
   <p>Not because of piety, nor because we want to play the role of God's protectors <pb facs="5423972_2_0173.jpg" n="6"/>are we outspoken opponents of Reform, but because we think and conceive of Jewish history.</p>
   <p>Reform Judaism is a falsification of Judaism, and we must consider it an internal enemy with which we never can make peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
