<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-05-22">May 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Does Anti-Semitism Prevail in America?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1207</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1207.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-05-22">May 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">DOES ANTI-SEMITISM PREVAIL IN AMERICA?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This question has been discussed so many times without any result, that it is not worth repeating and is actually difficult or practically impossible to answer clearly. It cannot be determined either in the affirmative or negative because it depends largely upon the particular case with which it is concerned. Off-hand one desires to answer that there is no such thing as anti-Semitism, but the many apartments and districts in large cities barring Jews as tenants is a fact which gives the optimist very little encouragement and forces him to explain the restriction upon Jews. What is this if not anti-Semitism?</p>
   <p>It can be answered that the Jews, in this aspect, stand higher than the Italians. The Italians, seeking comfortable quarters, are even worse off than the Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1208.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Very true! Yet there is another class which is more discriminated against than even the Italians. I mean the Negroes. It is more difficult for them to get a decent home. Do you think that the Negroes are liked? Will you attempt to deny the fact that a severe ostracism exists against the Negroes? Can you fail to react to the atrocities, the humiliation, and the suppression of human rights to which the African race is exposed.</p>
   <p>However, I affirm that at present there is absolutely no anti-Semitism in this country. The case of landlords barring Jews is an exception only, an exceptions are contrary to the rule. Also the hotels and summer resorts, where there is a ban on Jews, are free from anti-Semitism, but there are various and perhaps just reasons for regulating their businesses.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1209.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is no anti-Semitism at present in America, but how long can this endure. Can we hope that this fortunate condition of the present will remain for ever? Unfortunately, no! Nothing is eternal, and a country certainly cannot continue without anti-Semitism.</p>
   <p>However, it would be absurd to be concerned with a condition that shall probably take place two hundred years from now without acknowledging the reasons that will bring this about.</p>
   <p>The first reason is the density of population. Jews are congregated in large cities and this is a fact which is repeated in every land. Anti-Semitism grows where Jews can be found in vast numbers, and it is hardly known where the Jewish populace is small. This is the chief reason. But I hereby want to point out to another reason, - a new, modern, artistic reason.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1210.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Before considering means for the abolition of the "stage Hebrew," the so-called "Jewish comedian," who pretends to represent Jewish types and characters which do not exist anywhere outside the mind of the author of comical scenes, and who thinks of nothing else but making the people laugh, we must consider a new evil which has grown up in America.</p>
   <p>By this we mean the statues depicting white slavery. In Europe the Jew is accused of slaying Gentile children and in America it is stated that Jews sell girls into white slavery.</p>
   <p>Miss Abastina Eberl, of Iowa, daughter of a United States army doctor, is a wealthy girl. She has a great love for art. She learned sculpture and evidently wants to acquire world fame. Seeing that the statues which she made of Indians, or something similar, did not get any publicity, she resorted to sensationalism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1211.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>White slavery is the topic of the day. Why not take advantage of it? And so a statue, the white slave, was created. This, the only statue of its kind, can harm the reputation of the Jewish people in America one hundred times more than all "stage Hebrews" put together.</p>
   <p>The statue depicts a girl being sold at auction. As old as the idea is, it could not attract any attention if it was not distinguished by two note worthy portrayals:</p>
   <p>1. The slave, a girl of the white race, appears in the nude on a platform. She stands there to be sold. This awakens great compassion for the unfortunate girl and evokes severe condemnation for her tormentor - the slave trader.</p>
   <p>2. The slave trader is the chief portrayal. He appears as a caricature of a typical Jew with a crooked nose, one hand stretched out and with the other hand holding his victim - a real "stage Hebrew."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1212.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>And this is a phenomenon of which we should have more fear than of all anti-Semitic books and theoreticians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
