<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-12-19">Dec. 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Theater Performances for Small Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-12-19">Dec. 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THEATER PERFORMANCES FOR SMALL CHILDREN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the schools are closed for the summer vacation and our children have nothing to do, the parents of these children must solve this problem [of leisure time]. Spending too much time outdoors is not healthy; staying inside the house all the time is not very good for the children either. So the family gets together and goes to see a theater performance. We Jews have a custom of taking our children to see a good show--not, however, always for the sake of the children. Gentile parents have a different approach to the matter: they go to the theater for the benefit of the children. That [practice], I think is a very good one. It is much more important for children to see a good theater performance than for grownups: a good performance impresses the child for it teaches him to be honest with his fellowmen and it builds up in the child's mind [a conception] of what is right so that when he thinks of the good things in life he will very likely be a good citizen and a good Jew.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0096.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To see a good performance in a theater means, most of the time, to see something which makes you laugh; when you laugh you are not angry; and when a person is not angry he is a good person. In other words, the theater teaches you how to laugh. The theater has many thousands of virtues; more than good books or a good environment. It is, therefore, a great pity that we have no children's theater in Chicago; not even a special performance for children. Of course, we Jews are not the only ones who have no theater for children in Chicago. The other nationalities have none either. Every city in the land lacks a children's theater. There is not even a special performance for the amusement of the children in any of our theaters.</p>
   <p>Our Jewish people in Chicago usually have special performances for the children on holidays. On Hanukah, in memory of the Maccabees, we Jews have a "Hanukah play". Also on Purim, when we celebrate the feast of Queen Esther, we have a "Purim play". This is all we Jews have to offer in the way of performances suitable for our young, Jewish generation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
