<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-04-20">Apr. 20, 1891</date>, 6:1.
<title level="a">Rabbi Hirsch's Address at the Ada Street M. E. Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-04-20">Apr. 20, 1891</date>, 6:1.
<title level="a">RABBI HIRSCH'S ADDRESS AT THE ADA STREET M. E. CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon at the Ada Street M. E. Church Rabbi Hirsch of the Sinai Congregation addressed a large audience on the duties of American Citizenship. He embraced under the head of patriotism something more than the mere love of country; it was that broader sentiment and inspiration that recognized the fatherhood of God and the brotherhood of humanity. He divided patriots into three classes - the noisy patriot of the Fourth of July; the professional patriot for revenue only; and the unostentatious citizen who is true to duty and principle.</p>
   <p>True Americanism is not, he said, all of native growth, but is the assimilation of all patriotic impulses. Races have congregated and solidified into one national whole. He denounced the system of politics which seeks to put everybody on a ticket except an American, and, although he was a foreigner himself, he hoped the time is coming when we will have Americans in office and get rid of professional officeholders and professional foreignism. He eulogized the public school as the most democratic institution in the world, and would have a law to compel the sons of the richest to sit on a stool beside the poorest. Referring to immigrants, he said: "Let them all come, for we are strong enough to digest even the worst elements of Europe."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1390.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For many of the evils which afflict our politics and communities the quiet, honest American citizen himself was to blame, for he neither attended primaries nor was he willing to serve on juries. Hence we have rascals in office and bribed jurors. The speaker was frequently applauded.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
