<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-27">Apr. 27, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0505</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0505.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-27">Apr. 27, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hebrew teachers of Chicago are very fine people and fine Hebraists, but they are not fine Jews. Otherwise, they would do something for the Keren Hayesod (exchequer of World Zionist Organization). All elements in the community, rabbis, laymen, scholars, welfare workers, and even children, are participating in the drive, but not the Hebrew teachers, even though they are always talking about Hebrew culture and Jewish nationalism. Who is a hotter nationalist than a Hebrew teacher? But when it comes to do national work, he tells someone else to do it and he himself evades the work. The Hebrew teachers of Chicago could have raised at least, a few thousand dollars for the Keren Hayesod. The all important thing is not the sum that they could have raised, but the example they could have set for the children whom they teach. But now? Nothing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0506.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When one has any suspicion on someone else, and if such suspicion afterwards proves groundless, one should have the courage to publicly admit it. I had suspected Rabbi Ephraim Epstein of doing nothing for the Keren Hayesod and I was pleasantly disappointed when I learned that he is active and is doing his duty. I had suspected Rabbi A. R. Mushkin of doing a great deal but found out that he is doing nothing, notwithstanding that he is at the head of the Misrachi (religious wing of the Zionist movement) in Chicago.</p>
   <p>According to the latest census, there are in all 120,000 Jews in Canada, i.e., less than one half the Jews of Chicago. But the 120,000 Jews in Canada are doing a great deal more constructive work than the Jews in the entire Middle West. In Canada there are well-organized Jewish communities. The Jewish children in Canada receive a good Jewish education, and Canada contributes to the Keren Hayesod exactly four times as much as Chicago, even though the Canadian Jews are not so well off as the Chicago Jews. They are, however, conscientious Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
