<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-06">June 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Spargo Says So Too</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0990</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0990.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-06">June 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SPARGO SAYS SO TOO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John Spargo is a scientific socialist. His books on economic problems are accepted as textbooks in many universities. He is also a man with a very clear head and great insight. And he is not a Jew. Therefore an argument presented by him that coincides with the ideas of a Jew apropos the Jews may be considered an irrefutable axiom.</p>
   <p>In his article on "Russia and the Universal Problem of the Jew", the Jewish translation of which was sent to the Courier this week in its entirety, Spargo expresses the following idea: That the Jewish religion is the reason why the Jew cannot adopt himself to a feudal (slave) system; and that brings misfortune upon him. The Jew (Spargo says) has to thank his religion for those spiritual gifts that raise him to his place among the nations of the world. The religion of the Jew came to him by way of a great cultural language of rate literary beauty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0991.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"No matter what country he (the Jew) may have lived in, he has always retained his religion through the medium of this great language (Hebrew) and the literature of this language--the literature that, we may say, more than any other excites and stimulates the imagination. A Jew without imagination is unusual. Now can we expect Jews with such active and sensitive dispositions to fit into a feudal [system] that demands in its labor-setup the stolidity of an ox and the patience of a burro?</p>
   <p>"And further there is in this literature of the Jews a revolutionary and democratic quality that we cannot ignore, and that explains why Jews are so often represented in revolutionary movements."</p>
   <p>Had Mr. Spargo been a Jew and a nationalist he could not have given a stronger argument then this one. If there exists anything of magnificence and greatness created by the Jew, which to this day influences Jewish life as well as that of the civilized world, then we must go back two thousand years in order to <pb facs="5423972_2_0992.jpg" n="3"/>praise the Jew for this achievement. For the magnificence and greatness of Jewish life has come down the ages from the time when Jews lived as a nation in their own land--the only circumstance under which a nation can create.</p>
   <p>Perhaps this will also explain why last winter at the Labor-Democratic convention in Minneapolis, John Spargo voted in favor of a Zionist resolution that was proposed there. It is always pleasant to find such an appropriate axiom as that of Mr. John Spargo.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
