<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-29">May 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A Black Border of Protest</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0859</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0859.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-29">May 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A BLACK BORDER OF PROTEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>My friends, publishers and editors of Jewish newspapers and various publications in all dispersed Israel:</p>
   <p>In a time when the world is being renewed, when the highest and most beautiful ideals break through on the path leading to the broadest circles and stratum of the nations, when innocent blood flows in streams while tens and hundreds of victims fall daily only because they are Jews, when no one can be found to remove the bloody knife from the hand of the murderer,--in such times the press has the added burden of a special task and debt.</p>
   <p>The Jewish press throughout the entire world, taken as a whole, <pb facs="5423972_2_0860.jpg" n="2"/>regardless of party or differences which each individual paper may represent, is the expression of the thought and sentiment of the Jewish people as a whole.</p>
   <p>The Jewish people cannot listen calmly to the persecutions that each new day brings. They cannot listen calmly and remain silent when it cuts into their living flesh, when their healthiest limbs are being cut away, and one Jewish center after another is being annihilated!</p>
   <p>Weak and helpless as we are, we have not yet tested all the means we possess. If we are deprived of the opportunity to face our foes with might, let us at least cast off the shame of silence when we are so hurt. Let us at least openly and publicly, so that all the <pb facs="5423972_2_0861.jpg" n="3"/>world know, express our sorrow and protest!</p>
   <p>Protest speeches at gatherings are of short duration and soon forgotten. Protest resolutions are, as time has proven, like the call of a voice in a desert, but a united outburst from the Jewish press throughout the world has not proven its strength.</p>
   <p>An effective, united protest and expression of mourning by all the Jewish press will indicate that we are not deaf to the voice that calls from the victims of our martyrs!</p>
   <p>Not against the hoodlums of this or that country are we protesting, and not against their accomplices; we raise only a protest which shall remain a constant shame to the cultured world that makes the Jew an <pb facs="5423972_2_0862.jpg" n="4"/>outcast and views in silence the pogroms, persecutions, and slaughters of the Jew.</p>
   <p>Not against this or that country, nor against this or that government would we direct our protest, but while the blood of our martyrs call to us, while the tears of widows and orphans move us, also the thousands of Jewish ruined existences, we, therefore, mourn and raise our just protest before an entire world!</p>
   <p>As the first united step to mark our grief and protests, let our publications appear with a black border of mourning so long as no definite tangible means are taken to stop these specific Jewish pogroms and organized Jewish persecutions in the various lands of the World, or let us all raise our voices for thirty days in succession!</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0863.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In this peaceful demonstration all Jewish presses of all our scattered Israel must unite, including all daily newspapers, weeklies, journals and periodicals, regardless of party or differences which each may possess and regardless of the language in which each may appear.</p>
   <p>Friends, let us unite in our grief and begin immediately that response which we owe our martyrs.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Dr. M. Brender (Copenhagen)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
