<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1909-02-26">2-26-1909</date>.
<title level="a">United Hebrew Trades</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1731</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1731.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1909-02-26">2-26-1909</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED HEBREW TRADES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United Hebrew Trades have reorganized. Hereafter, only trade unions will compose the organization, and only such workers will be accepted as delegates as are able to accomplish something for the Federation.</p>
   <p>If the reorganization will do good to the workers we are perfectly satisfied.</p>
   <p>When the Federation was reorganized we didn't have many unions, and if unions existed they were unknown to the workers. The first ones to affiliate with the Federation were a few small Jewish unions, the workmen's Circle branches, and Socialists, then the cap-makers, bakers, and garment workers joined, and within a short period there was a good deal of life put into the labor movement.</p>
   <p>Times were good, new organizations were born at the same time, many more progressive organizations paid monthly to help keep up an organizer. A strike of the bakers, attracted all the active Socialists and trade unionists. A vigorous agitation in favor of the union label was carried on, and within a short period it created a great demand for the label, <pb facs="5423972_2_1732.jpg" n="2"/>which was already pretty well spread. The meetings of the Federation became larger, the actors union then joined the Federation. They also had a strike that drew a few months of activity from the Federation.</p>
   <p>At that time the United Hebrew Trades had every indication of becoming a power for good, but the depression set in and a reaction occured in the Jewish movement. It was because of the differences in opinions among the delegates which was responsible, for their failure to do the required work, but the unions themselves turned weak and their members were left without work. The unions gradually disbanded. The progressive societies turned weak and all this effected the United Hebrew Trades.</p>
   <p>The press committee puts the entire blame on the divergence in opinion of the progressive delegates; this is wrong. It is possible that some of the delegates would like to introduce certain radical principles into the Jewish labor movement. They have a right to do so because the fundamental principles of the United Hebrew Trades is purely Socialistic. The delegate of the garment workers, in spite of the fact that he is not an outspoken radical, personally helped in the writing of the principle statements, together with the delegated of the cap-makers union, Brother <pb facs="5423972_2_1733.jpg" n="3"/>Schreiber, and a few other delegates. At a previous meeting it had been determined to stand by the Socialist principles, also to draw all the progressive Societies into the United Hebrew Trades.</p>
   <p>It is not true, as the press committee states, that the Jewish labor unions are not quite ready to go hand in hand with the radicals. Among all the Jewish unions one will find a strong radicalism. The cap -makers union has, in their fundamental principles, recognized socialism, the bakers 'union recognize socialism and these strong unions stand one hundred per cent with the United Hebrew Trades.</p>
   <p>The only union not recognizing socialist principles is the garment workers and when this union was investigated, it was found that instead of doing good, it was just the contrary, that it did a great deal of harm to the union by being conservative and following the program of all the American conservative unions.</p>
   <p>Let this reorganization of the United Hebrew Trades serve as the start of a new life in the trade unions and among the progressive elements.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
