<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-11-25">November 25, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Christmas in Schools</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1220</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1220.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-11-25">November 25, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CHRISTMAS IN SCHOOLS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It will be very interesting to the Jewish public to acknowledge that, according to the order of the Board of Education, Christmas, as a holiday, was abolished, and that the ceremonies prepared by various teachers, are on their own account without the knowledge and approval of the Superintendent of Chicago Public Schools. The order, by any teacher that the children should learn Christmas carols or anything else that is connected with Christmas is not legal, and it is being done by the teachers thinking that the Superintendent and the School Board will not become aware of this.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1221.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was recently discovered that a publisher published a book containing songs, among which are found Christmas carols, and the title page informs us that it is recommended by the Board of Education. Several teachers use these books and distribute them among the pupils in order that they may memorize the songs for the Christmas ceremonies, which they intend to perform in the schools. Therefore, an obligation confronts every Jewish mother and father to find out from every child if Christmas ceremonies are being prepared in his class room, and if so, to notify the Board of Education immediately.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harry M. Lipsky, as a member of the Board of Education, will accept, with pleasure, all notifications in order to terminate the compulsion of Jewish pupils to undergo any Christian ceremonies. The school should be free from religion, and it will be free, if Jews can only help it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
