<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Messenger</title>,
<date when="1909-11-01">November 1, 1909</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Messenger</title>,
<date when="1909-11-01">November 1, 1909</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Hebrew Institute. We need a bureau of Jewish statistics in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Any attempt to obtain statistical data to be used for guidance in social work among the Jews in Chicago is at once frustrated by the total lack of full and accurate information on any of the important cases of social endeavor. Each charitable and educational institution has records of its own, more or less complete, and satisfying to an extent, the practical needs of each organization. But what Chicago needs very much is a bureau of statistics at which shall be gathered all the statistical and other information regarding each activity, and such information as shall be obtained by the bureau itself. The bureau should make efforts to gather general information and data on broader lines and covering a greater range than can possibly be done by societies interested primarily in their own limited fields. Such information, full and accurate as it must be, would make possible a thorough study of the social conditions and needs of the community and would enable each organization to act more intelligently in its own particular field and secure it against encroachment on the territory of the others.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1265.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Institute is the logical place for such a bureau and will attempt its organization at the earliest moment feasible.</p>
   <p>Need of a directory of Jewish institutions of Chicago.</p>
   <p>In connection with the subject of a Jewish statistical bureau, mention should be made of the fact that there is immediate need of a complete list of Jewish charitable, educational, and religious institutions of Chicago. How soon this list can be compiled and by what organization will probably be decided at the same time that the question of the statistical bureau is taken up.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
