<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-07">Aug. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Frequent Phenomenon</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1181</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1181.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-07">Aug. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A FREQUENT PHENOMENON</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Times change and together with the changing times men's conceptions and actions also change. Jewish life of yesterday looked upon homicide and suicide with fear and astonishment. It was such an unusual and exceptional phenomenon. It stood in such glaring contradiction with all the traditional doctrines of life, and the entire community (Jewish) became disturbed whenever it occurred.</p>
   <p>Today it has become a frequent phenomenon, to which we give slight attention. We listen to the news of the occurrance, shrung our shoulders, and proceed to our daily tasks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1182.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Besides the pure, personally tragic moments which effect the person, who committed homicide or suicide, it also constitutes an act of general social significance, which effects the environment that produced these heroes.</p>
   <p>The old Jewish environment could not produce such figures because firm conceptions of life and obligations of men prevailed there. A firm tradition of thousands of years taught that homicide is the greatest crime; that a man is not allowed to rob another of something that he cannot return.</p>
   <p>Suicide was also considered as one of the greatest crimes. This opinion also originated in the Jewish doctrines which sanctified and revered life. Life was considered as one of the most beautiful gifts which God bestowed upon his creatures. The object of life was to <pb facs="5423972_2_1183.jpg" n="3"/>prolong, beautify, and glorify it, in order to draw it closer to the source of life, to divinity, of which the whole world, with all its men and creatures, is the reflex; but a reflex, having self initiative to throw rays to light upon the creator.</p>
   <p>When the independent basis of Jewish life became weaker, under the yoke of the foreign mode of living, when the ruling foreign environment became dominant, foreign influence and foreign views began to penetrate the Jewish life.</p>
   <p>The Christian view on life is very obscure. The world is nothing; man is nothing. The prolongation of human species is an impure sin.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1184.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The greatest accomplishment of the mind is not to exist. These views resulted in arrogance and crime, on a social and individual scale.</p>
   <p>Falling under this influence, the same phenomenon, which could hardly be seen before, began creeping into our life. Guns roar, victims of homicide and suicide fall. It has already become a frequent phenomenon among us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
