<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-11-08">November 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Heard and Seen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1288</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1288.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-11-08">November 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">HEARD AND SEEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish citizens of the West Side may congratulate themselves upon the manner in which the election of last Tuesday transpired, especially because they have made progress. Last Tuesday those who were noticeably absent were, the political workers, who habitually pester the people when they come to vote, telling them that they no doubt don't know how to vote, thereby offering their able assistance.</p>
   <p>The Jewish public went out en masse to vote, and everyone voted as he saw fit. The great number of "Split Ballots" was a clear indication that the Jewish public is not ignorant, and that every party politician who can barely sign his name wants to be a teacher of his. It was evident that the politicians are merely bluffing whenthey say that they can swing the election any way they please.</p>
   <p>We do not saythat a political organization is unnecessary, we do, however, say that if the politicians want to do the right thing they must be in contact with the workers in times other than that of election.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1289.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It should be the duty of the political workers to urge foreign workers to become citizens and help them obtain their citizenship.</p>
   <p>A world of gratitude is due the Jewish Circle League, who worked hard in order to clear the Jewish people of the accusation of selling their votes. Without any noise they have, through the assistance of the Election Commissioners, appointed judges and clerks in all the Jewish precincts, and thereby prevented the political sharks from doing the work they have been in a habit of doing.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that the Jewish Civic League is now in the right direction of upholding the Jewish pride and work for the good of the country. They need not succumb to the fear which so many politicians attempt to instill into them. They may rest assured that the Jewish public will always be able to distinguish right from wrong.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1290.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We believe that now is the time for the Jewish Civic League to do great and important work. In February of next year there will be primary elections for alderman and city officers, for which they will be elected next Spring. The importance of having a good alderman is so great, that Jewish Civic League give this matter precedence, although, other offices are also important. This issue is free of any nationalistic question, where Republicanism or Democracy play an important role.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Civic League should immediately begin investigating the capability and the fitness of the various persons, who desire to represent the wards in the Jewish Ghettos, impartially, honestly and fearlessly to tell the Jewish people who these persons are and who are anxious to represent them. It will be no accident if all right-thinking people will sympathize withthem and help them. As some have attempted to display Jewish wards as an example of mis-management, so will they in the near future present the Jewish wards as the very best examples.</p>
   <p>We have already remarked many times, that the fault of the Jewish institutions is not within the Jewish public or those who contribute to these institutions, but the difficulty, rather, is because the settlement of Jewish people is so young a movement, that they have not as yet, been able to produce any leadership for the common good.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1291.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The majority of the leaders of the Jewish institutions are working beyond their power, they sacrifice their time and their rewards are nil. It has always been our hope that as our population will grow, we will be able to set forth Jewish leaders who will labor for humanitarian causes and the common good. Until such time,however, we must be satisfied with such work as is being done at present in America.</p>
   <p>We, therefore, emphasize the fact that a certain Jew has decided to quit business and devote his time entirely to the good and welfare of all. As we know, Mr. Goldberg of the firm, Goldberg &amp; Bloom of 308 West 12th Street, is leaving business in order to work for the common good. Inasmuch as Mr. Goldberg is still a young person, we want to congratulate ourselves upon the noble spirit that prevails among the Jewish people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
