<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-25">Sept. 25, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The People of the Book</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Jonah Spivak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1030</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1030.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-25">Sept. 25, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE PEOPLE OF THE BOOK</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Jonah Spivak</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jews were designated by a Mohammedan caliphas Am Hasefer, "The People of the Book". This title is very appropriate. The Jew realized that neither by force nor my might, could be rule the world, but rather by intellect. The weapon used in Jewish life was not the slingshot, not the far-flung poisonous arrow, not the spear, and not the cannon, but rather the intellect, the achievement of the mind, of knowledge, and of science.</p>
   <p>With these weapons, the Jews have armed themselves against the deadliest enemy of human progress--ignorance. He [the Jew] has been armed with these weapons throughout the entire course of his history, and when the poisonous arrows of persecution, of hatred, and of envy were hurled at him, many a time they would, [like a boomerang], return to destroy the ignorant <pb facs="5423972_2_1031.jpg" n="2"/>enemies who had hurled them.</p>
   <p>When the Jews lived in Spain, they stood at the helm of all the sciences then known. They were the physicians, the astronomers, the geographers, the mathmeticians, the biologists, the ship captains, the engineers, the architects, the philologists, the financiers, and the political economists.</p>
   <p>While the Spanish knights spent many months practicing how to fence, the Jewish young man of Cordoba or Saragossa spent his time in the Yeshivoth (theological seminaries), and in academies where he studied the Torah and philosophy, specializing in various fields of science. The government would then seek his services in the field of industry, or commerce, as well as in state affairs.</p>
   <p>All historians give credit to the Jews for the greatness of Spain six hundred years ago. They were the most educated group within the country; <pb facs="5423972_2_1032.jpg" n="3"/>they were the ones who carried on all foreign and domestic affairs, intelligently and tactfully. The Jews had attained such prominent [governmental] positions there, that when the Inquisition broke out, in all its fury, the government was unable to find, in the entire country, a finance minister as able as the learned Jew, Don Isaac Abrabanel.</p>
   <p>When the hatred toward the Jews became so strong that they were driven out of the country, the commerce of Spain began to decline so rapidly that one political defeat followed another, until the country sank to the abyss of impotency in which she now finds herself.</p>
   <p>Later on, the expelled Jews of Spain, who settled in Holland, produced a great genius, the all-encompassing mind of Baruch Spinoza. The young Spinoza was raised in the Amsterdam ghetto. In the theological seminary of Amsterdam, he studied the Bible, the Talmud, and various scientific books. Later on, in a cellar, besides the light of a small candle, he <pb facs="5423972_2_1033.jpg" n="4"/>wrote his Ethics and his Tractatus Theologico-Politicus, which have been recognized by all learned men as the greatest [philosophic] studies ever written.</p>
   <p>How many other great minds, besides Spinoza, have we Jews produced? They are too numerous to count. We will merely mention the great Jewish philosopher, Moses Mendelssohn, who, in Germany, is looked upon not only as a Jewish philosopher and reformist of the Jewish religion, but also as one who was enriched the German language.</p>
   <p>Wherever the portals of education have been open to Jews, they have become the intellectual sovereigns, the great figures in literature, art, and science. And very often the enemies of the Jews would reluctantly enroll as students under Jewish teachers.</p>
   <p>Even in the half-civilized Russia, where the temples of education were <pb facs="5423972_2_1034.jpg" n="5"/>closed to Jews, where so many barriers were set up against, and restrictions imposed upon Jews, prohibiting them from gaining a higher education, they, nevertheless, broke through those barriers and became prominent in the legal and medical professions.</p>
   <p>The Jew possesses a native receptivity to education and it is, therefore, not surprising that he attends all the institutions of learning in this country, in our blessed and free America, just as soon as he arrives on her shores--from the elementary education offered in the free night school, to the [higher education in the] different universities and academies.</p>
   <p>This semester the free night school, is under the supervision of the Board of Education. It opens this evening. The schools will be opened from 4 P. M., Monday through Thursday. Adults, both men and women, will be taught to read, write, and speak English, as well as many other subjects.</p>
   <p>It is unnecessary to appeal to the Jewish youth of Chicago to begin their <pb facs="5423972_2_1035.jpg" n="6"/>studies this evening. Those who have not enrolled as yet, should do so this evening. Is there any Jewish young man or woman who does not seek an education? Among our youth, education is the greatest ideal in life, and they value knowledge higher than any other thing.</p>
   <p>In the ancient Jewish writings it is said that all crowns, except the crown of knowledge, can be inherited. Wealth can be handed down from parents to children. Nobility can be handed down, but not knowledge. One must exert effort, one must think, and one must study in order to gain knowledge.</p>
   <p>The majority of the Jewish youth of our country, who are unable to inherit the "crown of opulence," can hope for nothing but the "crown of knowledge," which cannot be inherited, but which can be procured through work and effort.</p>
   <p>Knowledge is not in heaven but in the schools, which invite you to study to <pb facs="5423972_2_1036.jpg" n="7"/>acquire knowledge, so that you may become useful and intelligent members of the great and free American society.</p>
   <p>We Jews are "the People of the Book". Tonight our youth will pick up their books and [begin to] study diligently.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
