<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-11-16">November 16, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Technical Schools for Children</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1284</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1284.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-11-16">November 16, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">TECHNICAL SCHOOLS FOR CHILDREN</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The many readers of the Courier, will see the resolutions, which the Chicago Association of Commerce has passed to encourage the Chicago Board of Education in a new undertaking. It was for a program of building new and special schools for technical training of children. Seeing this, they will compliment the Courier for its foresight, as to the spirit of the times.</p>
   <p>We may boast, without exaggeration, that we have been preaching for years to the parents about the necessity of training children to do things with their own hands, in addition to the theorethical knowledge which the children acquire in the ordinary schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1285.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Jews have a natural inclination and interest in theoretical learning. They are called "The People of the Book," and during the many centuries of their scholastic and educational backgrounds, have become accustomed to respect a learned man, regardless of his uselessness in any other respect. Therefore, there has developed among the Jewish people, a special class of scholars, who were totally unable to do any physical work, and were supported by their wives.</p>
   <p>This class of scholars has now disappeared, but the heritage to learn, for the sake of knowledge, has remained among the Jews. However, this is not study of the Talmud, but rather modern studies. Every Jew who sends his boy to school wants him to become a doctor or a lawyer. These are studies which require no technical experience or manual labor, and are, therefore, more closely related with the studies of yesterday.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1286.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Both the medical and law fields are already overcrowded, and many a young doctor and many a lawyer is compelled to seek employment in other fields. Therefore, we have been preaching to the Jewish people, to educate their children technically, if they are interested in the future of their children.</p>
   <p>We have forever been preaching, that a young man has a future, if he combines theoretical knowledge with practical experience, of how to do things with his own hands. The world requires improvement in all fields of human endeavor.</p>
   <p>The Chicago School Board, which is now beginning the establishment of technical schools, fulfills the requirement of the times. The Association of Commerce, which is so anxious to help in providing such schools, clearly indicates the demands in the business fields, for technically trained young men.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1287.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is our sincere hope, that Jewish young men will be among the first ones to enroll in the technical schools and take advantage of the opportunities offered them by these technical schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
