<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-01-10">Jan. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">In the Jewish World</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-01-10">Jan. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE JEWISH WORLD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish race is blessed with many people of great knowledge who are constantly on the look-out for new discoveries, new solution to the Jewish problem; especially do they seek ways to eliminate anti-Semitism from their midst.</p>
   <p>One of these outstanding scholars is Doctor Alexander Lyons, of the Eighth Avenue Temple in Brooklyn, N. Y. Reverend Doctor Lyons, you must know, is not only a Rabbi of the temple but also publisher and editor of a newspaper. The name of the paper is, The Supplement.</p>
   <p>In this newspaper, he declared a holy war against the Jewish beard. The Jewish beard is a victim of present circumstances. We have barely caught our breaths from the murderous attacks on the Jewish beards in Poland, and now a Rabbi, one of our own people steps out in the open with a declaration of war against the Jewish beards in America. But Rabbi Lyons by no means is an enemy of Israel; in fact, he is just the opposite.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0602.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is because of his sincere love for his Jewish brethren that he puts up this fight against the Jewish beards in America. He states the cause of anti-semitism in this country is due to the beard. The American looks upon the bearded Jew as a freak, and is suspicious of him. Just let the Jews shave their beards off, and you will soon see the dislikes and prejudices of the Americans against the Jew will disappear. There will be no more anti-semitism in America.</p>
   <p>No one else, heretofore, ever thought of such an easy way to get rid of anti-semitism in America; for one can think of no other faults that our enemies can hold against us. Mr. Ford and the other anti-semites, have no other complaints against the Jews except for their beards. So we see it very clearly, just as two and two make four, that all we have to do to protect ourselves against anti-semitism is to get after the old fashioned Jews and induce them to make the small sacrifice of shaving their beards off.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
