<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-17">Mar. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Spiritual Poverty in Lawndale District</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1092</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1092.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-17">Mar. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">SPIRITUAL POVERTY IN LAWNDALE DISTRICT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is not in Chicago a Jewish district so spiritually impoverished as the one that extends from Douglas Park to Independence Blvd. Even though the residents on the two boulevards decorate their beautiful homes with flower gardens, the symbol of refinement and appreciation of the beautiful that we are wont to see among the parvenues, yet it seems that this people believe in nothing but sham mockery, which is no more than a thin powder on a putrid surface and springs from the same source as does the Jewish Christmas trees which last winter shone from the wealthly Jewish homes on Independence and Douglas Blvds. How can people like this possibly live without the least urge for culture?</p>
   <p>In the Lawndale District, where thousands of Jews live, among them many of the wealthy and professional, there is not a single cultural center.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1093.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the entire neighborhood there isn't even a library, Yiddish or English; no folk schools to teach Yiddish or Hebrew, no dramatic clubs; no literary circles nor any organization embracing moral and cultural objectives. This is why the Lawndale District is well-stocked with pool-rooms, saloons, and gambling dens. Apart from this, the wealthy and professional men possess a beautiful edifice which serves as a card club, where their women organize not infrequently whist games. The movies are overfilled with children who gain such knowledge there as even their card-playing parents would not wish to acquire. Children who ought not to have any money on their persons, can be found gambling on street corners and near public schools. This is the district which is erroneously referred to as Little Germany, for the most poverty-striken Balkan country can justifiably feel offended should one assert that its culture is the same as that of the Jews in Lawndale District, which thrives culturally only by the charity it receives from other Jewish districts of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
