<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1908-07-26">July 26, 1908</date>, 3:6.
<title level="a">Jews to Shun Primary Held on Their Sabbath</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1908-07-26">July 26, 1908</date>, 3:6.
<title level="a">JEWS TO SHUN PRIMARY HELD ON THEIR SABBATH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is estimated that 20,000 orthodox Jewish voters will not take part in the primary because it is held on their Sabbath. Whether this loss will be an injury to the Republican or the Democratic candidates is a matter of conjecture, but the Democrats are apparently more concerned about it.</p>
   <p>"It does not make much difference what the reason and explanation is for the observation of the law by the orthodox," said Judge Mack yesterday. "The orthodox are prohibited from writing or marking a ballot or doing any kind of business on the Sabbath. And that means that the laws are observed. Perhaps the voting is a phase of attending to community business, but the fact remains that they won't vote.'</p>
   <p>"I do not expect there will be a score of votes by the orthodox Jews," said Henry M. Shabad, Democratic candidate for municipal judge and a believer in the orthodox church, although liberal in his views." The people of that church do not quibble to relieve themselves of the duties imposed and whether a law is obsolete or not will make no difference with their action on primary day."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0320.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The matter came up yesterday at a conference in the headquarters of Maclay Hoyne, Democratic candidate for State's Attorney. Apparently the framers of the law overlooked the orthodox Jew when the date of the primary was fixed for Saturday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
