<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-09-11">Sept. 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Street before Rosh Hashanah</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Jonah Spivak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0193</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0193.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-09-11">Sept. 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH STREET BEFORE ROSH HASHANAH</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Jonah Spivak</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Vacation is over and many Jewish people have returned to the city. A cold wind is blowing and the leaves are falling from the trees. Flowers are withering away and the Jew is becoming lonesome--his heart is growing very heavy. "Who knows what can happen to us?" the Jew thinks. "We are no more than sheep guided by the god of fate." This is the philosophy of the New Year.</p>
   <p>Before the New Year arrives the Jew becomes unusually serious. He stops to think about the higher purposes and aims of life. He runs to the synagogue and buys a ticket for the holidays. Once this "business" is done he feels free once more from all moral obligations: by purchasing a ticket all his problems and philosophical questionings are answered. This occurs in every Jewish city as well as in Chicago. And once Jews start to buy tickets, all <pb facs="5423972_2_0194.jpg" n="2"/>the seats in all the synagogues are quickly filled. The synagogue then become crowded. "Mushroom" synagogues are organized on every street: in barns, shops, etc. Even motion picture houses and theaters are transformed into synagogues. Very high prices are charged [in these "mushroom" synagogues]. It is a good business. The day after Yom Kipur these "synagogues" are reconverted into barns, shops, motion picture houses, theaters, etc. Business is business--even when it concerns the Master of the Universe!</p>
   <p>During these Holy Days cantors are scarce. Synagogues look for cantors everywhere. Then some Jews put away their scissors and their presses and others forget that they are potato peddlers and expressmen. They put red bandannas around their necks and announce to the public that they are cantors. It even pays to become a cantor in one of the "mushroom" synagogues which were barns and shops.</p>
   <p>Soom the "officers" of the so-called synagogues begin to peddle tickets. One "president" sits in front of the "synagogue" behind a table piled up with red <pb facs="5423972_2_0195.jpg" n="3"/>and yellow tickets. A second "president" is a "puller". He pulls people going by on the street to the table. "Mister," shouts the puller grabbing an elderly Jew by the lapel, "please come to the table and look. We will charge you nothing to see our place." "And who is the cantor here," asks the Jew. The "president" who is seated at the table gives the Jew a circular in which is printed the picture of the cantor. "What?" cries the Jew, "your cantor comes from Odessa? It is a lie! He is a Lithuanian and he has been my potato peddler for the past six years!" The Jew goes away excited and angry. The "puller president" runs after an old Jewish woman (carrying a freshly slaughtered chicken in her hand). And he yells: "Missus, Missus--please come and see our synagogue." The woman approaches the table and buys a ticket while the "table president" shouts: "Cheap, ladies, cheap!"</p>
   <p>The motion picture houses and the theaters plan the synagogue business on a grand scale. They print circulars with pictures of the cantor and the choir. The cantor is pictured in his long, black robe and his head is covered with a <pb facs="5423972_2_0196.jpg" n="4"/>huge, round skull cap. He is the star. Before the holidays the future synagogues advertise the cantor between the acts--on the stage and screen. The cantor is usually an old actor in the theater. The management released him for two weeks to grow a beard. Upon the big poster the picture of this actor is, however, painted with a long, black beard and the advertisement underneath reads: "The celebrated cantor, E___B____from P____ will sing choral melodies in our Temple!" [Sacrilegious, isn't it?]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
