<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-07">Jan. 7, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Fear</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0549</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0549.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-07">Jan. 7, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FEAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Unless you appreciate the state of mind, the background of prejudice, the subconscious influences that enter into the making of an obstinate dogma, you cannot understand the continued opposition to Zionism by the small group of American reform Jews who go ahead protesting that they cannot join in building the Jewish National Home in Palestine. They say: "Build houses or establish banks, create industries, make it a center of religious life, make it a home; but do not, for God's sake, make it the Jewish National Home." If you will only do this, they may eventually come along and help, but still with reservations, denying the thought behind the building.</p>
   <p>It is a strange attitude.</p>
   <p>The anti-Zionist reform Jews are not strangers to Jewish interests. They <pb facs="5423972_2_0550.jpg" n="2"/>are part and parcel of that stream of Jewish life that maintained during the Goluth [Diaspora] all the institutions that Jewish life could maintain in the face of the oppression and persecution. Within the limits of what they regard as being Jewish, they are generous and self-sacrificing. They are what is called good Jews. They have been the founders of orphan asylums, homes for the aged and hospitals; they have established charity organizations; they have joined with zeal in every Jewish defense or apologia. They understand the domestic features of Jewish life pretty well. There (sic) desire to Americanize the new immigrants--the immigrants themselves have gone far ahead of their teachers now--came from an interest in the immediate comfort and well being of those new comers. If they were moving toward assimilation they did not know it. They were trying to make Jewish life harmonize with what they thought was American life. They adapted themselves to new conditions, probably not out of a feeling of servility, but because they thought adaptation to be the way to harmony and comfort. They wanted all Jews in America to be comfortable, the new comer included.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0551.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What they lacked was imagination, the sense of historic relations. They saw not the whole of Jewish life, but the fragment in which they happened to be lodged at that time. A decade of instruction and guidance in adjustment--a period of shrinking and accommodation--had dried up their feeling of universal solidarity and assertiveness. The obligation close at hand, the one thing that could be touched, they appreciated, they sympathized with, they gave generously to. But speak to them of the complicated, far-reaching influences of Jewish life, the future that could be created for the whole Jewish people, and they wondered at you for going so far afield when there was so much to be done right around the corner. They not only did not see the far-off, but they resented its intrusion. They regard past Jewish history as a book that had been closed. They could not see in what way they were connected with Jewish historical processes.</p>
   <p>The basis of their attitude was fear. They understood remedies, making the best of things. They knew the meaning of orphan asylums, homes for the aged, hospitals, charities. They understood, a little more vaguely, learning <pb facs="5423972_2_0552.jpg" n="4"/>literature, the thing that had to be done to certain Jewish rights. But when you reached conceptions of Jewish life that embraced the whole of the Jewish people, that involved strife and struggle, the assertion of rights, conflict to attain it, the new forms, new ideas, they could not understand why these things were necessary for the retention the (sic) comforts of the moment. Their eye-sight was to (sic) weak. Their vision became blurred. They were afraid of the unknown and the unborn.</p>
   <p>You know children who are afraid of the dark. They have fears that are born out of pre-natal influences. There are adults who carry with them inherited fears. They cannot understand why certain things frighten them. They do not know why certain signs weaken (sic) in them distrust or suspicion. The dark is full of hobgoblins in whom they do not believe, yet fear.</p>
   <p>The anti-Zionist reform Jews have inherited a fear of what the development of a strong Jewish life may create. All the distrust of past Jewish life goes into the making of that fear. All the complications of past Jewish <pb facs="5423972_2_0553.jpg" n="5"/>life, its tragedies, its difficulties, its extensive wretchedness, its ups and downs, have instilled a feeling of horror when thinking of the Jewish people again resuming functions that they have once possessed. They have gotten out of the habit of thinking of Jews in this connection. All the greatness of the past is submerged in this subconscious fear of the consequences. Life has lost a residuum in their souls of the darkness of the past. It is this fear that animates their opposition to Zionism. It is fear of the complications that may be created, the dangers involved. It is fear of struggles that are not now forseen but are sensed in advance, atavistically, in the establishment of a National Home for the Jewish people in Palestine.</p>
   <p>That is why our efforts to argue with our brethren of this group have proven to be of no avail. The controversy has been carried on for over twenty years. On every point logic and truth seem to have been with us. All the questions raised have been dissipated. Have we a national language? Are we a people? Is Palestine large enough to hold the Jewish people? Can the Jewish people <pb facs="5423972_2_0554.jpg" n="6"/>be organized? Is Zionism a practical movement? Can Jews actually build a National Home? Will governments give us recognition? All of this is settled. What was controversial material has been established as fact. The world recognizes us as a people. It has given us the opportunity, long desired and long expressed, to establish ourselves once more in our own land. The world recognizes all the claims that we have made and has opened the doors of Palestine to our practical efforts. All of this is real. The fringes of the unknown are gradually disappearing. Palestine has entered into our consciousness, and this contact with reality should dissipate all fear, but the anti-Zionist reform Jews hold to their opinion and oppose our rhyme or reason because they cannot dislodge the fear that is the basis of their opposition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
