<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-02">Feb. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Our Synagogues</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Anna Goldberg</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0265</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0265.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-02">Feb. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SYNAGOGUES</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Anna Goldberg</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Permit me to take up with our elderly Jews, the question of our synagogues. In Chicago we have many beautiful and large synagogues. More beautiful synagogues are being erected each year. But, unfortunately, for whom? Upon entering a synagogue on the Sabbath, a holiday, or any day throughout the year, how many people do we find there? A few elderly Jews, but very few young people. I will admit that the elderly Jews cling devoutly to Judaism. I believe that when an elderly Jew dies a branch of Judaism simultaneously dies, but the question remains: What will become of the young generation? What sort of Jewish future can we expect from them? The future of the present generation lies in the hands of our parents.</p>
   <p>We construct colossal synagogues for a handful of Jews, but why aren't the <pb facs="5423972_2_0266.jpg" n="2"/>synagogues designed with some attractive features for the youth? Every synagogue should have a modern Talmud Torah (School of Religious lore), as well as a Sabbath school. Every synagogue should open its doors to the young children.. Let them even be a bit boisterous. Something should be done about the children who are not getting a Jewish education at home!</p>
   <p>Around Douglas Park where the Jewish population is so dense, there is not one Jewish school for girls. The education of our children in this country, rests mostly upon the women, the mothers. If you neglect the Jewish education of your daughters, you will have no Jewish future. Could we ask for a better place to open a school for girls than in the large, beautiful, and new synagogue, the Anshe Kneses Israel, Douglas Blvd., and Homan Ave.</p>
   <p>But the synagogues were established only for praying and studying the <pb facs="5423972_2_0267.jpg" n="3"/>Talmud. You, older Jews, already know enough. Start teaching the youth. Your synagogues are externally beautiful. The internal beauty should be mantled with the work of small children. There are Sabbath schools in a couple of synagogues where small children can secure a good Jewish education. But how are they treated by the majority of elderly Jews? They are reproached and kicked out of the synagogue for being a bit too boisterous. You, parents, were spoiled when you were small children! If you were driven from the synagogues when you were young, you would now be ignorant of Judaism. If something interesting is introduced in a synagogue for the benefit of small children, a revolt immediately takes place. The adults are ready to take up arms against the children. The only synagogue, where approximately 250 children assemble every Saturday and Sunday to study Jewish history and Judaism, is the Beth Medrash Hagodol, on Maxwell St., There the children are treated splendidly; the members do not interfere. On the contrary, they are highly pleased with the progress the children are making in their studies. If <pb facs="5423972_2_0268.jpg" n="4"/>we only had a few more schools and synagogues like that, we could certainly do much for the good of Judaism. Let the synagogues be open for the young children, just as they are for the older people; let us establish schools and arrange lectures to attract the youth; let every synagogue provide the children with ample space to enable them to study Judaism!</p>
   <p>If you will not rear Jews for the future you will have no synagogues, a few decades from now.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
