<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sinai Congregation, Board of Directors, Minutes</title>,
<date when="1872-07-28">July 28, 1872</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0384</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0384.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sinai Congregation, Board of Directors, Minutes</title>,
<date when="1872-07-28">July 28, 1872</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>.....the report of the Committee on Funeral Regulations (was) acted upon, section by section. Report was then read and adopted as follows:</p>
   <p>1. In the event of death of a member of this congregation, it shall be the duty of the family of the deceased, or one of their relatives, to inform as soon as possible the president or vice-president of the congregation, or any member of the Committee on Funerals, of such an event, and the person receiving such information shall without delay inform the Committee on Funerals of such death, and shall notify the minister, and through the Sexton the members of the congregation to attend the funeral.</p>
   <p>2. It shall be the duty of one or more of the Committee on Funerals to repair at once to the house of mourning, and offer their services for the arrangements necessary to perform the funeral services.</p>
   <p>3. Although, it is no part of the duties of the congregation to furnish <pb facs="5423972_2_0385.jpg" n="2"/>carriages, it shall be left to the discretion of the Committee on Funerals to furnish in exceptional cases not exceeding three (3) carriages, for the accomodation of the funeral Committee and such members as desire to attend the funeral, at the expense of the congregation.</p>
   <p>4. The Funeral Committee shall also see to it that the sexton notifies those members living nearest to the house of mourning to attend the customary evening prayers for the three evenings following the day of the funeral.</p>
   <p>5. Not less than two members of the Committee on Funerals shall attend funerals in person.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
