<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-04">Feb. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Better Methods</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1588</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1588.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-04">Feb. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">BETTER METHODS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The English capitalists and the labor unions are holding a series of conferences, the object of which is to shorten working hours. These conferences are the result of new methods introduced in the factories. Scientific management enables the capitalist to realize that just as it is necessary for him to introduce the finest type of machines and the most modern means of production, so it is equally imperative for him to have the best kind of workers.</p>
   <p>And here is where capitalism arrived at the question of what sort of worker is the best. England's labor statistics have come to their aid by showing that long working hours drive the best and most able worker down to a level of in-competency, because long hours sap energy, health, and ability. It is a fact that not long hours but interest in one's work is what really counts for an increase in production. Besides the physical damage wrought by long working <pb facs="5423972_2_1589.jpg" n="2"/>hours, the spiritual and moral degradation of the worker should also be taken into account.</p>
   <p>The father who spends twelve hours at monotonous work is torn asunder from his home, his wife, and children, thus weaning himself from them to such an extent that they appear strange to him.</p>
   <p>This makes family life burdensome and the worker resorts to liquor to drown his troubles. This condition prevails in England more so than in any other country, with the result that industrial development suffers greatly. Shorter working hours or a five-day working week would improve this condition. The reason for this move, however, is to be found in the desire for practical things characteristic of English capitalism. Having the most extensive experience in this matter, they know that shorter working hours result in greater industrial efficacy.</p>
   <p>They know well that besides an increase in production, shorter hours will preclude the necessity of strikes, which at best are disadvantageous to both labor and capital.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
