<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-10">May 10, 1910</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1669</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1669.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-10">May 10, 1910</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Worker's Ghetto. (Column of Local Labor News).</p>
   <p>Women and children who work in factories - How they work and live - A scandalous sweat shop system - A dangerous system and a dangerous occupation - Jewish workers are most affected - Declaration of principles of the National Workers Verband - A branch of the verband is being organized in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Often in strolling through the streets of the West and Northwest Side, one can see women and children walking in the streets carrying heavy bundles of wearing apparel or material of which to make wearing apparel, carrying these heavy weights, with large beads of perspiration rolling from their faces, and with a troubled and emaciated look in their eyes.</p>
   <p>Is it not shameful to countenance such scandalous goings on? These children are no more that 13 and 14 years of age, lean faced, undernourished, fatigued because of inadequate sleep, all this before they are full grown. If you know <pb facs="5423972_2_1670.jpg" n="2"/>the reason for this disgraceful state of affairs, it is the sweat shop system at its worst. It is this sweat shop system which breeds tuberculosis and premature death. This undermines the existence of the worker and causes him to compete with his own children. It is this system which denies the worker to better his economic circumstances.</p>
   <p>In the streets we see only a small phase of the sweat shop system. Let us enter the homes and shops where these heavy bundles of wearing apparel materials find their way. There we can see the real horrors of the system. Let us enter a model home at midnight. All is quiet in the dismal, small apartment, occupants sleeping fully clad upon poorly "homed" beds. But at four o'clock, the mother is up and with her, her children, candles are lit and work begins. Children, ages 7 to 14, begin their days work. The hand-sewing machines begin to turn. At eight o'clock they stop. Children must go to school, and then, after school, again the machines begin to turn, until far into the night.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1671.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is a double sorrow; Firstly, the children work about 16 hours a day, at school and at home, and in spite of this labor, their income is a mere pittance and insufficient for them to be properly nourished and properly clad, not including of course, the unhealthy environment of young children, our future leaders. They grow up sickly and weak, tubercular, and cripples for life. Secondly, they harm the workers in the shops. They compete in prices and hours of work. Workers cannot get better conditions so long as they have to compete with cheap family labor.</p>
   <p>The Trade Unions are fighting this evil with all their might. Much has been done to abolish this system, but it is still prevalent. This plagues not only the Tailoring trades but other trades as well.</p>
   <p>The Jewish worker is greatly affected by this system and the only way to remedy it is for workers to organize into strong and sturdy trade unions and fight against the sweating system. It will be a hard battle, but the system must be abolished.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
