<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-07-31">July 31st, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Corbins and the Jews</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1488</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1488.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-07-31">July 31st, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE CORBINS AND THE JEWS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Editor of the Tribune, Chicago, July 30th. -</p>
   <p>It appears to me that the Jews and their friends, and the Corbins and their friends are alike very unjust to the Corbins, Judge Hilton, and all other landlords who choose to keep hotels for Gentiles. Their reasons for excluding Jews from their houses are certainly good and sufficient, and such as should be recognized as void of offense.</p>
   <p>The case stands thus: A Jew will not eat pork or anything into which it enters as an ingredient. This peculiarity creates confusion at table, occasions very great loss to the proprietor of the house, and annoyance to his other guests. And he certainly has a right to say that he will not incur that loss and subject them to that annoyance.</p>
   <p>The food ordered and rejected, on account of the discovery or suspicion of lard or bacon, would of course be lost. Then as the estimates for a hotel are made on the basis of lard as a lubricant, no one has a right to demand olive oil as a substitute.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1489.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The trouble lies in a nutshell. Shall the Corbins and Judge Hilton sell olive oil and butter at five cents a pound, and have their table linen greased without compensation for the laundress?</p>
   <p>According to the financial policy of the original Jacob, a Jew will of course get all he can for his money. But for this a Christian should rather do him honor, since that policy is a part of our divine revelation. If God "loved Jacob," who was the sharpest man in bargains, of whom history gives any account, and "hated Esau," who was a generous, large-hearted gentleman, why should not we honor the descendants of Jacob for following the example of their ancestor who was the especial favorite of the Deity?</p>
   <p>Our modern ideas of finance would say that Jew guests and all other guests should pay according to the cost of entertaining them, and that when a host does not choose to establish a Jew department in his culinary establishment, he acts in accordance with that freedom of choice which leads one man to deal in hardware and another in dry goods.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1490.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To insist that he shall submit to having the time of his servants taken up in cooking and carrying food to be rejected and so lost, that he shall furnish butter and olive oil at the price of lard, is doing him a gross injustice.</p>
   <p>To make a case of religious or race persecution out of this affair, is simply ridiculous; and if it should lead to the establishment of hotels and tables, where dead pig would not be served in any form, there are more people than Jews, who would have reason to rejoice. I, for one, should always want to go to the Jew hotel if to any.</p>
   <p>As it now is, I avoid a hotel and boarding house as I do a pesthouse, not only on account of the swill mixed up in two-thirds of the dishes, but of the dough served as bread. If there were as many anti-dough eaters in this country as there are Jews, hotels would be obliged in self-defense to promulgate orders against entertaining them, for they would be almost as troublesome as anti-pork eaters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
