<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-24">Apr. 24, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Forward Boosts Paderewski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0507</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0507.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-24">Apr. 24, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FORWARD BOOSTS PADEREWSKI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In last Friday's, April 20; issue of the New York Forward, an announcement to this effect appeared in the theatre section: "Paderewski's Four Concerts".</p>
   <p>Under this caption, it is told that Paderewski will conduct a concert Sunday evening at Carnegie Hall, New York. Then three concerts will follow in Brooklyn, New Jersey and Boston.</p>
   <p>We need not tell the Jewish reader who Paderewski is. He is the former Polish premier under whose administration pogroms broke out in Pinsk, Wilno, and Chenstekov. In 1912 Paderewski founded in Warsaw the hooligan newspaper Dva Groshe, which is still instigating pogroms on Jews. Paderewski founded in Warsaw another reactionary newspaper, Jest Paspolita, a large newspaper which is doing much harm to the Jews.</p>
   <p>It is a shameful betrayal for a Jewish newspaper to boost the former Polish premier at a time when the Polish Jews are carrying on a bitter struggle against <pb facs="5423972_2_0508.jpg" n="2"/>Paderewski's Party, the Narodovtzes, against the pogroms instigated by Paderewski's newspapers.</p>
   <p>Now, when on the streets of Warsaw Jews blood is flowing, when Jewish refugees are crying unto Heaven that the Polish government has driven them from the land so cruelly, it is a disgraceful conspiracy to boost the former Polish premier, whose party is in power in Poland and whose newspapers are continuing their reactionary work.</p>
   <p>One may hold many points of view on Paderewski as a pianist, but since 1912 a Jewish newspaper has never given Paderewski any publicity--Paderewski who publishes pogrom-sheets with the money he makes on concerts. The Forward has done this.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
