<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-12">Feb. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">In Newspapers and Journals</title><title level="a" type="sub">Renaissance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-12">Feb. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">IN NEWSPAPERS AND JOURNALS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Renaissance</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great number of Jewish writers and civic leaders are wont to designate the present, in which is to be detected a revival of Jewish literature and Jewish life, as the Jewish Renaissance, as the solstice of rebirth and rejuvenation.</p>
   <p>In a letter to a friend, published in Life, S. Garelik thinks that for the present our generation has not deserved the name of "Renaissance." Our Renaissance, he opines, has not introduced anything new; not one idea, not one great important publication. For the present we have reproduced nothing, and the best Jewish writers have completed their creative circle. "Even the new courses of the modern Diaspora nationalists, are nothing but a continuation of the ideas with which Echodam and Dubnov wrangled over long before the Renaissance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1128.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"We live in exclusion. Each day we create new Ghettos. We strengthen those which we already have. If not a bit cynical, at any rate, we act indifferent toward the concepts of life upheld by others. We know nothing about this, nor do we wish that our press should write about it.</p>
   <p>"I am a nationalist, but even in the most fiery years of my nationalism, I longed to see wide open doors and gateways. Whither? Into the world, my dear friends! To visit freely here and there, taking from there narrations, translations, and concepts of life, and then bring everything into our beehive. We should fly over every field and garden, and cast anchor on all the flowers, imbibing their fragrance. Go out my friend, some summer day, to some garden and listen to the humming; the humming of the bees sounds so pleasant! You shall see how they work and build. This is renaissance. As a reader, I am thankful for the memoirs of Ezikail Katik, yet, at the same time, I should like to know what goes on beyond our respective boundaries. I am eager to know what new dramas were written by Bernard <pb facs="5423972_2_1129.jpg" n="3"/>Shaw and Hoffman; I want to know what all this talk about the 'Futurists' is, what is the significance of it; I want to learn about the fourth edition of Chekhov's correspondence, and about the lectures of the French poet Rishpen. I am a human being living among people, and I do not wish to appear like a barbarian; do not wish to be segregated. My parents, as educators, should not discriminate against the material I read or whatever language I read it in. We must provide channels that will convey to us the cultural values of other peoples. On the day when a complete Jewish rendition of Tolstoi, Dickens, Shakespeare and Goethe will be made possible, on that day our spiritual world will be multifariously enriched. It will be honey in the Jewish beehive, and then we shall be able to speak of renaissance.</p>
   <p>Pan-Yiddishism</p>
   <p>"Zionism, as a powerful national movement, was already fortunate enough, like all great movements, to effloresce streams which branched out into <pb facs="5423972_2_1130.jpg" n="4"/>many opposite directions. At the time when Mr. Zabotinsky came from Zionism to Pan-Hebrewism, annuling the Diaspora with its daily troubles and afflictions, others drifted from Zionism to Pan-Yiddishism with a tender love for the Diaspora and for everything that Diaspora had created. Yiddishism was centered around a group of national-Zionists in Germany. This group publishes its monthly journal, Die Freistaat. In the latest edition of the Freistaat, there appears an article written by a certain Juris, entitled 'Kultur or Fetish' which defends Pan-Yiddishism.</p>
   <p>" 'For the neo-Hebrewists,' says Herr Juris, 'exists only the Jewish culture, which was created in a short time when Jews inhabited Palestine; the residue is Diaspora culture, bondage and misfortune. The young Jewish culture also belongs to misfortune, but if we annul the Diaspora and everything fashioned by Diaspora, we thereby cut Jewish history into two parts and simultaneously cut the Hebrew language and its culture. If the production of and struggle for the Jewish spirit in the course of 2000 years is no more than Diaspora, it follows then that Zionism, the Hastodroth, <pb facs="5423972_2_1131.jpg" n="5"/>and the modern life in Palestine itself are nothing but Diaspora, which means that Diaspora can achieve something. I believe, moreover, that the Hebrew culture first became an animated and real culture in Diaspora. In Palestine, the Hebrew language was only limited to the high priests and writers. The broad masses knew little of it. Only in Diaspora have the Jews become a race and the Hebrew language nationalized.'</p>
   <p>"The writer proceeds further in his deliberations and comes to the conclusion that 'land and language are no more than means and forms to serve the people. They become sacred to the people when the spirit and essence of the people have found in them an image, but they change as the style of clothing changes, and they are dependent upon mere accident...., if we should impose a new culture upon them, it would only be inane, a national crime.</p>
   <p>" 'If the revival of Hebrew,' continues Herr Juris, 'leads to the construction <pb facs="5423972_2_1132.jpg" n="6"/>of a barrier between the intelligentsia and the broad masses of people, then it divides the people, which can become dangerous for the culture and posterity of the people.'</p>
   <p>"In conclusion, the writer says that 'only Yiddish, which nine million Jewish people speak, can be, and it is at present, the bearer of Jewish culture to Jewish posterity.'</p>
   <p>"This sort of Pan-Yiddishism is even a bit too logical, and it can be answered by Zabotinsky's reverted formula, 'The national problems are not decided upon through logical evidences.' "</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
