<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1881-10-14">Oct. 14, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Suspension</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1881-10-14">Oct. 14, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">SUSPENSION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On account of momentary financial embarrassment we are compelled to suspend the publication of the Jewish Advance for a term of three months. If but a third part of the monies due us from subscribers were collected, we would be free from this embarrassment.</p>
   <p>The causes by which we were driven into our present difficulties are obvious and will not tire our readers with an elaborate account thereof. We will only state that the delinquency of our subscribers, although it is directly the cause of our suspending publication, is in itself the effect of other causes. It is, for instance, contrary to the material interests of our Rabbis that a Jewish Journal should exist which will not yield to their influence, which is able to meet them on their own grounds in a conflict of opinions, which would not make "stars" of such men as are anything but shining lights in the pulpit. Some of our Rabbis have cause to be afraid of honest, unbiased and boldly expressed truths, others again are faint-hearted <pb facs="5423972_2_1457.jpg" n="2"/>and stand in friendly relation to their unworthy colleagues. The former, therefore must undermine the interests of every independent publications; the latter must deny it their countenance and support. Our congregations, too, in as much as they are composed of men who live on and by old impressions in matters of religion and who have no time to think for themselves, must naturally rely on the thinking and actions of the Rabbis, right or wrong. Thus it comes to pass that whatever is contrary to the interests of Rabbinism (which is in every respect synonomous with Priestcraft) is maligned and held low. And the conscience of the fraternity of the cloth is pliant and means can easily be formed to impose on the people.</p>
   <p>The constantly increasing circulation of the Jewish Advance has been watched with anxiety by the Rabbis; the confiding nature and "impracticalness" of the editor were taken advantage of; the willing ear and influence of those who are slow to appreciate any truly ideal pursuit, were prejudiced; the ready tools of scheming individuals were set to work in the press, in the pulpit, and in meaner ways to prejudice the minds of the people against the Jewish <pb facs="5423972_2_1458.jpg" n="3"/>Advance--delinquency of subscribers in paying their bills was the immediate cause, the suspension of publication ensued.</p>
   <p>There is perhaps a tone in the last sentences which we should not have given to them, but who will judge us harshly at this moment and in the position we are now? For nearly four years we have toiled hard, literally by day and night, our eye-sight became impaired, our health almost ruined. We have worked to gain the ear of our brethren for the cause of "Truth and Justice," and after we had gained an audience (our subscription list can compare favorably with that of any Jewish Publication in this country) we see our work turned almost into naught, by dishonest scheming.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
