<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1909-02-13">Feb. 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Hospitals and Orphan Asylums Must Be Conducted in Accordance with Jewish Requirements</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0313</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0313.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1909-02-13">Feb. 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">HOSPITALS AND ORPHAN ASYLUMS MUST BE CONDUCTED IN ACCORDANCE WITH JEWISH REQUIREMENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of delegates of the Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations was held on Wednesday evening in the Beth Hamedrosh of the 85th Street Synagogue, of which Dr. Drachman is rabbi. There were few out of town rabbis.</p>
   <p>A large variety of subjects were discussed, but few resolutions were adopted. Dr. Mendes praised the Albert Lucas classes and deplored the meager support given to the religious centers started by Dr. Lucas. Mr. Hirshfield criticized the downtown orthodox Jews for their indifference to Talmud Torahs. These Talmud Torahs cannot draw sufficient funds for their maintenance. Mr. Hirshfield was appointed a committee of one to investigate the subject.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0314.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The high vitality of the Jewish race," said Dr. Mendes speaking on Kachrus, "is due to the fact that our laws are stricter than the state laws as regards the care and slaying of animals. It is suggested that a special sign be issued to those keepers of restaurants who will consent to be visited by inspectors appointed by a board of ministers so that a genuine kosher restaurant can be distinguished from the imposter.</p>
   <p>"We have discovered that the marriage and divorce laws of certain states are being infringed upon, particularly by rabbis newly arrived from Russia. In different parts of the United States, for example, cousins are allowed to be married; under Jewish law this is permitted. No rabbi may grant a divorce unless it has been previously sanctioned by the state, and some of our rabbis are ignorant of this fact. We have a movement on foot to enable them to cope with present conditions.</p>
   <p>"Unless our hospitals and asylums are conducted in accordance with <pb facs="5423972_2_0315.jpg" n="3"/>Jewish requirements there is no reason for their separate existence and for their posing as Jewish. To do so is living a falsehood. This is a matter demanding vigorous action."</p>
   <p>A survey of all the activities of the Union was then indulged in, with explanations by Dr. Mendes. It was a late hour when the meeting arrived at the consideration of the internal affairs of the Union, but the hour for adjournment had arrived.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
