<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-10">May 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S.M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0494</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0494.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-10">May 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S.M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The missionaries are complaining of poor business. Jews are not converting themselves, leaving them without a stitch of work, and if the missionaries are unable to prove to their bread givers--the Missionary Society--that they are rescuing a certain quota of souls each year, they risk the chance of losing their jobs. For that reason, to them the question of saving more Jewish souls is really a bread and butter question. The missionaries want to earn a living. One earns a living from stealing horses, another from white slavery, a third from saving souls for Christianity. The thing that counts is to earn a living.</p>
   <p>My friend, Dr. David Neimark, the noted Hebrew philosopher, whom ugly fate has driven to Cincinnati as professor of that rabbinical factory, writes to me that Dr. Mann, successor to Dr. Emil G. Hirsch, is not only a rabbi but a man who has already written essays on Bergson's philosophy and its relationship to Judaism. Therefore, he is a Jewish scholar. I must say that to write <pb facs="5423972_2_0495.jpg" n="2"/>such essays is not one of the most difficult tasks, and I will find in the local Hebrew Theological College at least five boys who can write them. Yet, that still doesn't make them Jewish scholars. I remember that my first literary assignment was to write an essay on Shakespeare as a statesman. Yet I have never believed that I am a Shakespearian critic. Whatever a young student may write is of little consequence! It may be true that Dr. Mann is a great physicist, mathematician, or biologist, but he is not a Jewish scholar, because the Cincinnati seminary does not produce any Jewish scholars. No one knew that better than the late Dr. Emil G. Hirsch, who was the first to call the Hebrew Union College a rabbinical factory. Not only the students of the Hebrew Theological College but even the professors themselves are not well posted in Hebrew literature. This does not mean, however, that Dr. Mann cannot be the desirable rabbi.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
