<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-10-13">October 13, 1907</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-10-13">October 13, 1907</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Seen and Heard. (Local Column).</p>
   <p>And now, to add to our many Jewish problems has arisen the "Mezuzah" problem. Very often, little things lead to big fights. As the Gemorah says, "because of "Kamzah" and "Bar Kamzah" Jerusalem was destroyed. (The Hebrew equivalent of "From little acorns, oak trees grow"). World History says that the French Revolution arose as a result of Louis XVI eating a bowl of soup at an Inn. Now the little "Mezuzah" has caused a small revolution at the Chicago Hebrew Institute. And so that those who will sometimes write the history of the Jews of Chicago, will not be deprived of information on this important dispute we write you of it now and suggest that those who seek further, attend the Institute.</p>
   <p>As is well known, the Chicago Hebrew Institute has two goals to achieve; firstly to teach Jewish immigrants to become Americans, to teach them of American institutions and the American spirit; secondly to inform American Jewish youth who are fast losing contact with our past, of their glorious past, our history, our literature and our ethics. The founders and leaders <pb facs="5423972_2_1302.jpg" n="2"/>of the Chicago Hebrew Institute fall into two different categories, "Jewish Americans" and"American Jews." Or firstly those who believe that one should first of all be a good Jew and he will per se be a good American whereas the second group feels that we ought to first be Americans and if because of accident of birth one is a Jew he should therefore be informed of his people's past.</p>
   <p>Now, and Heaven knows whence they come, the traditional "Mazuzah" has been placed in its traditional place on all doors of the Institute. Now who could have had the audacity to place these "old style" "Mazuzoth" on the doors of the modern Hebrew Institute? Some say the Jewish janitor was afraid to sleep in his quarters, and others say that the president himself who stems from an old orthodox family and who never saw a house without the traditional "Mazuzoth" in their proper places, could not imagine a structure of any kind without "Mazuzoth" and therefore had them placed in the Institute.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1303.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As it were, the "American Jews" discovered the sad state of affairs and the revolution is on. An investigation was immediately made to find the culprit and expose him. However, the "Mazuzah" supporters are not without voice. They maintain that such as do not crave the protection of the "Mazuzah" are not bound to practice the customary ritual and honor accorded a "Mazuzah". They suggest that opponents of the "Mazuzah" would find a greater field of activity elsewhere - rather than concentrating their efforts against the "Mazuzah."</p>
   <p>It is hoped that the "Mazuzah Party" will invoke the powers of the "Mazuzah" and bring peace upon us and upon the Institute.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
