<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-24">July 24, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Undesirable Community Worker</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-24">July 24, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNDESIRABLE COMMUNITY WORKER</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Rev. Charles Beard Mitchell, president of the Methodist preachers meeting, shared his opinion on the art productions that are found in the Chicago Art Institute, and when a Reverend speaks about art, it is taken for granted that he condemns it.</p>
   <p>"The Art Institute should be blamed by the public for covering their walls with such vulgar paintings as would not be permitted to hang on the walls of the lowest saloon in town" - was the "learned" criticism of Dr. Mitchell.</p>
   <p>It would be useless to argue with the spiritual leaders, or preachers about art and morals.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1186.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Their constant criticism on everything that is considered by the world beautiful, clean and desirable does not originate from any deep moral sentiment which could not under any circumstances be injured by artistic paintings. The true source of the clergy's utterances is their narrow-minded view of ethics and anesthetics, and the inherited and ignorant opinion that everything satisfying the human body and soul, whether it directly concerns religion or not, is vulgar and obscene.</p>
   <p>The second reason is the great desire for publicity.</p>
   <p>The clergy (Gentile) interfere too much in social life. They stick their noses in places where they are not wanted, and they always find enough believers to follow them and adhere to their commands.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1187.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This does not only involve morals and art. They interfere in politics, city management, and social life directly or indirectly, from the pulpit or at public gatherings - the spirited leader is seen everywhere sowing the seeds of the religious self-seeking individual.</p>
   <p>Religion was excluded from politics and citizenship in this country. But the laws are weak against the increasing toll of fanatics, whether they be Catholics or any other type of Christian.</p>
   <p>The only solace is that when the spiritual leader become too arrogant, the nation probably will realize its danger, and they will introduce a new reform that will again sharply divide the broad and rich social life from the narrow religious domain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
