<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-02-07">Feb. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">In the Jewish World</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0594</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0594.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-02-07">Feb. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE JEWISH WORLD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In an article on Ford, in the World, the opinion is expressed that Ford started his anti-Semitic propaganda not because he is an anti-Semitic at heart, but because he believed that he would ride into the White House on the horse of anti-Semitism. He is just like many other self-made millionaires.</p>
   <p>The article says Ford is suffering from the malady of "Presidentism," and that to be president of the United States is his life's ambition. With this in view, he always comes out with new ideas and projects on how to make our country, and particularly the whole world, happy.</p>
   <p>He does not care how much his fanatical plans will cost him; he does not care if his plans are simply empty dreams. His purpose is to gain popularity, to be a successful great man and a friend of the nation. When he reaches this aim, he will be ready for his life's ambition, i,e., to become president of the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0595.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He believes that his anti-Semitic propaganda will help a great deal in making him beloved by the American people. It is a maxim of the Talmud, that whosoever persecutes or troubles the Jews, rises to fame. So, of course, Ford's figures are right, but here in America, in the land of the Free, Jew-bating does not click. With his anti-Semitic propaganda, Ford failed to acquire the friendship of, or the followers among, the American masses.</p>
   <p>Most of the American newspapers resented his anti-Semitic propaganda, lies, and false accusations, with condemnation and contempt, and he was compelled to abondon it.</p>
   <p>If there ever was a remote possibility of his achieving his life's-ambition, it has now disappeared forever. Instead of making him a great man, his lies and false accusations towards Jews show that every intelligent citizen realizes how common, ignorant, and uneducated he is.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0596.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And the result is that those who thought of him as being an outstanding, high-class gentlemen of high ideals, look upon him now as a demagogue and egoist, and who is always ready to commit any sort of wrong or vicious act in order to achieve his selfish aim.</p>
   <p>It would appear that every Jew should be quite pleased now that Ford was forced to abandon his anti-Semitic propaganda, but his is not altogether the case. There are many Jews who cry and mourn because Ford, in his Dearborn Independent, has discontinued his writings on Jew-bating. no sensationalism would prove unprofitable to some people. There are many small weekly publications scattered all over the land which have very few readers on account of their very little importance. The publishers of these small weekly papers had to put up a continual struggle in order to make ends meet until the Dearborn Independent came out with Ford's Anti-Semitic propaganda.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0597.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The appearance of the Dearborn Independent, with its Jew-bating, was just like a godsend to these small weekly newspapers. They immediately began a counter-attack in their weeklies against Ford's lies and false accusations, and the patronage of readers began to grow by leaps and bounds. Great success was in store for them, so it seemed. But when Ford stopped his Jew-bating in his Dearborn Independent, these small weeklies had to resume the struggle again, for the patronage had fallen off immediately, as they has no one to fight with through their columns.</p>
   <p>It appears now that the stopping of Ford's Jew-bating in his publication, is in itself a new form of anti-Semitism. Ford could not stand to see the small weekly papers thriving and carrying on such a successful agitation against him, so he decided to stop his anti-Semitic propaganda. This thing should have been investigated. If Ford's motive was to take away the livelihood of these Jewish publications, it is the duty of the Jewish people to look out for the interest of these publishers, for they stand the sacrifices of anti-Semitism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
