<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-23">May 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">John Smulski Cannot Endure the Fact That Jews Protest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0922</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0922.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV (Polish)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-23">May 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN SMULSKI CANNOT ENDURE THE FACT THAT JEWS PROTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>New York, May 22. John P. Smulski, the well-known Polish leader of Chicago, who is president of the Polish National Department of America, made a statement yesterday regarding the large protest meeting here against horrible pogroms in Pinsk and Wilno, saying that the Polish nation has suffered for the last two years from the calumny of Jewish leaders.</p>
   <p>In the course of his statement he also asserts that the Polish Committee had generously given space for a thousand tons of food which was sent to Poland by the Jewish Relief Committee, and although the Poles contributed the greater sum of the money for it, instructions were given to distribute the food equally among Jews and Christians.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0923.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Such demonstrations, as these held in New York," says Smulski, "make cooperative work impossible."</p>
   <p>The transport ship Westward has made its second trip this week to Danzig, laden with food for Poland. The Jewish Relief Committee has sent via this ship $600,000 worth of Kosher food (smoked), 500 tons of oil, 500 tons of condensed milk, 19,000 pairs of shoes for women and children, and many other articles.</p>
   <p>Smulski's statement, it appears, refers to this second shipment of food. The first time, food was sent worth $2,200,000, for which the Jewish Committee contributed $1,100,000, besides $25,000 for shoes. The lard (pig fat) sent for the Poles amounted to $160,000, more than the cost of oil sent for the Jews and Poles. The Jews really contributed more than the Poles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
