<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-07-09">July 9, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Christians Want to Reform Gehenna. Editorial</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-07-09">July 9, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHRISTIANS WANT TO REFORM GEHENNA. EDITORIAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The International Bible Students Association unanimously adopted a resolution, at its convention which it held this week in Washington, denying the belief of a Gehenna. The purpose of this resolution is to strengthen the Christian faith. The Christian intellectual youth shows more and more indifference to the faith of their fathers, because they find too much nonsense in it; but if such a great convention, which represents thousands of Prostestant Congregations in America, declares itself publicly, against the stupidities of the New Testament, then the intellectual youth will have no ground on which to run away from it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1245.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Good Christians will certainly share sympathy with the members of the convention which had undertaken to cleanse the New Testament of its stupidities. A strong objection will, however, be made against them for beginning their program with the Gehenna. Every person who possesses a little knowledge of the New Testament, knows that there are greater stupidities in it than the belief in Gehenna.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, we do note this: we merely wish to call attention, that progress is not only entering politics but also religion, that not only politicians are now divided into progressive and stand-patters, but the Christian clergy are also dividing themselves into these two classes.</p>
   <p>Besides, this reform-work is beginning to meet with huge obstacles. Hundreds of Catholics and other spirituals throughout the United States are strongly protesting against the resolution of the above mentioned convention. They not only want to listen to the denial of a Gehenna for the wicked but are also against the reform of Gehenna.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1246.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Evidently, the conservatives have the power among the Christian clergy and will not permit any attacks upon the old traditional Gehenna.</p>
   <p>This, however, should not cause the reformers any heart aches. Their devotion to the condemnation of Gehenna is not cleansing the New Testament of stupidities. This, apparently, is a thing out side of the possibility of a common effort.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
