<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1890-03-21">March 21, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to Radical Israelites</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1421</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1421.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1890-03-21">March 21, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO RADICAL ISRAELITES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whatever may be implied with the term "radical" in so far as it relates to the Jewish cult, seems but an empty and meaningless word when applied to the present status of that class of men who advocate and desire to adhere to reforms and progress. Its most erudite Rabbis have not yet stepped out of all the old beaten ruts, though many of the heretofore accepted religious and formalistic notions, such as the "divine revelation theory," belief in a personal deity, circumcision, etc., are eschewed by them and that Sunday may be as good a day to rest and worship as Saturdays, were in their day, deep incisions to the orthodox Shulchan Aruch Jews. A greater and more decisive evolution seems to be impending for the intelligent Jewish masses, if the Ethical Culture Society shall not usurp the field for making itself a universal moral cult in which all religious bodies may be engulfed in the near future. There were those who had advanced the notion of transferring the traditional Jewish holidays to the nearest general days of rest, but the most radical of all were not willing to listen to this proposition. The intermarriage problem is deemed <pb facs="5423972_2_1422.jpg" n="2"/>inexpedient even among our so called radicals and are only consummated by contracting parties outside of the Jewish congregation. The Occident has always inclined toward a consistent progress for the Jewish people and we move along with the current of philosophy and logic. The dogmatic religion must sooner or later be consigned to a dark past, while a moral and ethical training alone will suffice for the good citizen, no matter what country, birth or race he may spring from.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
