<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
            <date when="1919-03-16">March 16, 1919</date><title level="a">Opening of the Community State Bank</title>.
        
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1643</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1643.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
            <date when="1919-03-16">March 16, 1919</date><title level="a">Opening of the Community State Bank</title>.
        </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thew new bank is opening the same place where the 12th Street Bank formerly was at - 1637 West 12 Street.</p>
   <p>A few remarks about the officers:</p>
   <p>The West side is one of the most important business centers of the city, and business is progressing. With pride and joy we should welcome this large State bank. The Community state bank, that was just organized to replace the 12th Street Bank at 1637 West 12 Street. This is proof that the west side is progressing.</p>
   <p>This bank is taking over all accounts from the 12th Street Bank and is a new money exchange for the west side business center and will help the community in all cases.</p>
   <p>A good help for the Community Bank is Mr. Samuel D. Wexler, one of the former officials of the 12th St. Bank.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1644.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Wexler is a gifted young business man with an honorable reputation. Through his own merit he attained the point where he is now considered one of the most successful manufacturers and financiers. While Mr. Wexler was managing the 12th Street Bank he won a reputation for that institution so that it became popularily known for its success and confidence. That is the reason Mr. Wexler, at the first stockholders meeting, of the new Community State Bank, was elected as President of the bank, because they <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> him best fit for the banking business. He is well liked by everyone who comes in contact with him.</p>
   <p>A second person who helped much in organizing the new Community Bank is Mr. Jacob Gurwitz, a rich business man with many years of business experience. He is also one of the stockholders who was elected as Vice-President of the Community State Bank. He is widely known in business and financial circles for over thirty years. You need speak to him only once and you will have the impression that you have a man before you with a big heart and a well established responsibility. Mr. Gurwitz, for over twenty years controlled cotton plantations in Mississippi. He is now with his brother Michael Gurwitz and Chas. Cohen in The <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Corrugated Paper Box Co. on Morgan and 21st St. It is certain that Mr. Gurwitz will make a good Vice-President.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1645.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Community State Bank is organized under the supervision of the state of Illinois, with a charter and capital and surplus of $130,000.00 and will operate in their own bank building at 1637 West 12th Street, just half block from Paulina Street. It will open formally Saturday night March 22nd.</p>
   <p>
    <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
