<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-09-09">September 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Many Thanks, Chicago Tribune</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-09-09">September 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">MANY THANKS, CHICAGO TRIBUNE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>No one will suspect us of being overwhelmed with enthusiasm when informed that non-Jewish circles are dishing out great compliments to Jews. Just as we do not feel depressed whenever some one makes it his business to step out openly and magnify Jewish faults, neither do we swell with pride when accredited with pleasing characteristics.</p>
   <p>Yet, we were exceedingly pleased when we read, in last Sunday's edition of the Chicago Tribune, an article concerning Chicago Jewry which is as close to the truth as any newspaper article written about Jews can be.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1175.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our satisfaction is great because recently - speaking in a diplomatic sense - the Jewish people became highly strung whenever speaking of the Tribune.</p>
   <p>The Jewish public had two strong complaints against the Tribune:</p>
   <p>1. Because it published articles on the Jewish Ghetto which were remote from the truth and which cast an obscure shadow on Jewish activities.</p>
   <p>2. A representative of the Tribune stepped over the boundaries of journalism in the campaign which the Tribune is carrying on against gambling in Chicago, and this had actually occurred in the Jewish neighborhood.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1176.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Jewish public, although aware that both the writer of the undesirable articles and the investigator were Jews, and that therefore it could not be a matter of anti-semitism, had, nevertheless, felt offended by these occurrances. The Chicago Tribune is a progressive newspaper. It is permeated throughout with the American spirit, or as the Americans call it, "a square deal", and it was the general opinion of Chicago Jewry that in these two instances the Tribune did not act in accord with its usual manner. It had forgotten that it speaks to, and wants to be active among newly migrated citizens from a land where citizenship is understood entirely differently and that it is a physical impossibility to change one hundred men in the course of only thirty years, regardless of the circumstances.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1177.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Daily Jewish Courier voiced the resentment of Chicago Jewry in its editorial columns and it was unpleasant for us to see that the Tribune construed it in such a wrong manner that it had, in order to justify itself against uncharged accusations, falsely accused the Courier, thinking that its guilt would be wiped out by smearing the accuser. This is certainly not in harmony with the ethics of journalism to which a paper like the Tribune should live up.</p>
   <p>Within the two distinct worlds, in which the Tribune and the Courier prevail, a compromise between both was impossible. The Leviathan and the Messianic bull have no neutral grounds upon which to debate or to fight. Nevertheless, we were of the opinion that the Tribune remained morally indebted to the Chicago Jewish populace, and we were sure that the Chicago Tribune would sooner or later liquidate this debt.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1178.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The article in the last Sunday's edition of the Chicago Tribune, by Mr. Hied was first payment on this debt. And we believe that if this experienced writer shall visit the Jewish district more frequently he will find enough material to continue along these lines. This will give the vast number of non-Jewish people a better and truer conception of Jewish activities and it will also encourage the Jewish public to continue their good work. We therefore express our gratitude to the Tribune.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
