<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-02-07">Feb. 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Vain Promises to Jews</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-02-07">Feb. 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE VAIN PROMISES TO JEWS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The politicians and publishers of far and wide are busy discussing with speech and pen the ironical question, "To whom shall we cling? Who has more sympathy for us Jews?" Not only in our native lands where every Jew has the opportunity of being a patriot, but even in the neutral countries, as for instance, the United States, Jewish public opinion is discussing whom shall we favor.</p>
   <p>Who is being deceived? Deception is undoubtedly involved here. Whom do they want to impress in certain countries. The Jews suddenly have become such patriots that they permit themselves to be slaughtered, robbed, and ruined in boundless measure.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1060.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the war broke out they were left in a trap, all the gates were closed to them. They had no alternative, but to defend the land of their birth.</p>
   <p>We contributed to each individual country the maximum amount of effort, wealth, and blood that we possessed, but when have we ever before been so oppressed in the Disapora as at present?</p>
   <p>They have scattered our people in innumerable camps where they destroy one another. Our wives, mothers, and children were driven from their homes, then their poor small houses were fired.</p>
   <p>We are ruined, our people, all our hopes, our ideals destroyed, and who knows whether we can escape the present Gehenna with healthy organism - and here we are discussing, "To whom we shall adhere?"</p>
   <p>Let us ask ourselves, "Who helped us when we were in need of help?"</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1061.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Why shall we deceive ourselves and not openly state to the entire world, that the Jewish people, the entire united Jewish people want to remain neutral. It was always our fate to kiss the rod of our oppressors. Oh yes! I almost forgot, we will be highly rewarded for our present efforts, we will be given privileges, we will be permitted to go from one city to another, our children will no more be driven, from the synagogues. For our victims and our blood we will be rewarded with - our rights, iron crosses, and official positions. This will be our reward.</p>
   <p>Oh yes! there is another thing we will gain. From now on we Jews will be acknowledged as a courageous people, because we fought tirelessly, the Jewish pride will thereby gain considerably because everyone will realize that we deserve the honor of making use of a sword.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1062.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Hereafter the anti-Semitic students will not object to duel with a Jewish student by claiming that we don't deserve such honor. The world will know that "on the field of honor," we have left many, very many of our young brothers to die. Due to this the Jewish pride will grow considerably, in the eyes of the nations.</p>
   <p>Ha - Ha - Ha! The Jewish people may also get an iron cross.</p>
   <p>And we will take pride, great pride in our heroism and dexterity. And that is not all - we will also get back our land. The European diplomats have nothing else on their mind than to take Palestine away from the Turks and give it back to the Jews. This is very humane.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1063.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It would be a still better idea if it did not originate from diplomats. As you see it is possible, that with the will of God and the help of the newspapers, we may be able to get Palestine back.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
