<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1921-10-02">Oct. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">What Is the American Plan</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Morris Ziskind</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <!-- 5423972_2_0610 omitted, duplicate of 5423972_2_0611 -->
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1921-10-02">Oct. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS THE AMERICAN PLAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Morris Ziskind</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Which truthfully is the open shop? No need of a better explanation, than was given by the capitalistic defender of this plan. We therefore submit a resolution adopted at the National Conference of state manufacturers held January 21, 1921, in Chicago, when the national campaign started for the open shop.</p>
   <p>Whereas a fundamental principle in this country recognizes that all law abiding citizens, or inhabitants have the right to work when they please, and for whom they please, and at whatever conditions arranged between them and the one giving them the work, without anyone else to try and arrange things better for them, therefore, be it resolved that we declare our aim to defend the fundamental principles of the American plan of employing throughout the life of the open shops.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0612.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Be it further resolved that we urge our members to receive through discussion and education, the active help of the workers, business men, bankers, professional people and all other elements for the American ideals of the open shop.</p>
   <p>Here we have, clearly and concisely, the fundamental concepts of the open shop as it was expressed by a representative of the manufacturers organization of this country. One of the delegates claimed that he has no trouble with his factory workers. He has signs in every department, which read: This is an American shop, operating on an American plan, by Americans. In these twelve words are expressed the ideal or the open shop on the true American plan. You can readily see where our manufacturers stand or what they think of collective bargaining or the closed shop, industrial democracy, and other nice phrases which are being used to influence the American people.</p>
   <p>In its statement of principles, the Manufacturers Association of San Diego <pb facs="5423972_2_0613.jpg" n="3"/>gives a clear idea as to what the open shop is, and what it means for the workers. 1. Employ workers, men and women, whether they are members of a union or not. 2. Protect the wages of these workers, according to their ability and experience in the industry. 3. Pay your workers wages as high as circumstances will permit, 4. Give them regular working hours, and have the best working conditions. 5. Expect from each worker an honest day's work, according to his best ability. 6. Protect the rights of each worker and the right to earn enough to live. 7. Recognize the rights of each worker to bring his complaints, grievances, and questions regarding wages, individually or in groups, through a committee. 8. Refuse the right of any outsider or union representative to interfere in questions between the employer and employee. 9. Justice and square deal for every one and special privileges for no one. 10. Help every organization, capitalist or workers, which stands for law and order and for the rights of the American citizen.</p>
   <p>From these ten commandments, we deduce that the open shops are similar <pb facs="5423972_2_0614.jpg" n="4"/>to those shops in which the workers are not organized. Each individual worker arranges his own conditions with his boss or his representative. This is the contrary of collective bargaining. The worker has no voice in the matter of wages, hours or conditions. The boss is the dictator; he operates his business to satisfy and benefit himself. The employers, with their natural false phrases, claim that in their open shops, union men can work as well as non-union men; but the truth is that a union man cannot work there unless it is kept a secret, so that no one will know that there are any union people in the shop.</p>
   <p>What is the aim and idea of a union? A trade union is an organization of men and women working in the same trade who organize themselves of their own free will, in a common interest. They pay dues, conduct meetings, accept their constitution and laws, and regulate all the laws by which they are governed. They elect officers and accept their policies. A trade union is the most democratic organization in existence. further more <pb facs="5423972_2_0615.jpg" n="5"/>a trade union makes all efforts to let the public know of all its policies and aims. The aim of a union is to take in as members all persons working for a living, the great majority of the people, because the workers must be organized in unions, if they want to defend their interests against the great organized combines of capital who control all the large industries.</p>
   <p>Here we see the vast difference between a union and a manufacturers association. A trade union which is 100% organized has the greater majority of people, speaks for itself, and is American through and through. The main purpose of a trade union is to tabulate union shops. This means to make an agreement with the employers, as to the conditions under which the members of the union shall work. The union claims that such dealings with the boss is just, right and American.</p>
   <p>Now let us see. What do we derive from the name American? We mean one who is born in or is a citizen of the United States and does his share in building American Institutions and principles. He is a citizen, a member <pb facs="5423972_2_0616.jpg" n="6"/>of society, and accepts the benefits of living in America. He must also assume the responsibilities, pay taxes, and obey the laws. What does the union say?</p>
   <p>The union says, that every person working in a shop, where the working conditions, hours and wages have been rectified by the efforts of the union, shall become a member of the union, pay the dues and share the responsibility with the members. If he receives the benefits of the union won for him, he should become a member. The non-union man is an industrial alien.</p>
   <p>What is the main object of a union? Just this - to bring about greater comforts, better pay, shorter hours, better conditions, and a longer life to all that work. Does not all this conform with the idea advanced by the American government, to provide for the general welfare? Can all these objectives be attained by the workers through competing with one another? No. The non-union man in the non-union shop is not American.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0617.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The trade union and the union shop are the true guides for Americanism.</p>
   <p>Why blame America, when the non-union man or woman work for themselves and stand alone in the non-union or open shop? What new lesson have we workers learned in the open shops? None. They are against Americanizing, they are outside the labor movement, they do not organize, they do not unite with their co-workers, and they are of no help to their co-workers.</p>
   <p>It is the trade unions that have developed the American ideal, that all must stand united and carry out the will of the entire membership. It is the trade union that puts life into the idea that while doing good for yourself you can do it for all the others.</p>
   <p>The open shop movement is directed against all of us, whether union members or not. It is the aim of the capitalists and employers to reduce wages, to make conditions miserable, to take away the rights that the union has won for us. It means to reduce the workers to such an extent that <pb facs="5423972_2_0618.jpg" n="8"/>we will be looked upon as slaves, under the disguise of Americanism and an American plan that is not American, and is the very reverse of true American traditions and principles of citizenship and democracy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
