<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1916-05-20">May 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Assistance for the Jews and Lessons for the Jews</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1045</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1045.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1916-05-20">May 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">ASSISTANCE FOR THE JEWS AND LESSONS FOR THE JEWS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A call went forth from Jewish citizens of Chicago; to their fellow citizens and as a result the immense Chicago Auditorium was packed to the limit. Their willingness for sacrifice should be recognized, although it may not be an extraordinary service to give money, especially so, if there is a fine surplus there, and even more so, when one is made spellbound by irresistible speeches, that are regular pocket-openers.</p>
   <p>The misery of the Jewish people in eastern Europe is well known to us, although the war increased their misery a hundred fold. That the Jewish people are persecuted, insulted and murdered, that women and girls are dishonored has long been the custom in cultured Russia, a civilization that now is joining hands with England's culture in a common defence against German "barbarism."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1046.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But money alone cannot solve this problem. Yet it is easier to give than to think and reflect upon some real fundamental, permanent assistance, some eternal solution to the problem. For anyone in the audience who was capable of consecrating himself to serious thinking for the benefit of the unspeakable suffering of the Jewish people in eastern Europe, certainly must have been inspired by the wonderful musical revelations of the singer, Ernestine Schumann-Heink, who sang Schubert's "Allmacht," and the touching Wolf's "Heimweh." The longing for home, in her song "Heimweh," trembled, wailed, fairly was wept out of the singer's great heart, bringing the hopeless situation of the Jewish people in all its horror to the feeling, thinking listener.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1047.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Those unfortunates in Russia are longing for home; since the Deaspora (exile). when the denationalization took place of the Jewish people, the longing for their home has not only became a passion with them, but it is actually consuming them.</p>
   <p>They have longed to return to that native country because they have felt the pressure of a set-back in their moral and spiritual heritage was impossible for them, because they would finally be equals among equals.</p>
   <p>Zionism is not a religious movement: it is a spiritual, economic, and also a national movement, warmly supported by both Gentiles and Jews alike.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1048.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Dr. Theodore Herzl and his collaborator, Dr. Max Nordan, the famous Paris essayist, have tried to find a field for labor in America in which to plant Zionism. We now find that these very same American Jews, who are now lamenting over the Russian Jews and are most liberal with their money, would know nothing of Herzl and the cause of the Russian Jew. Even if political and human equality were granted the Jew in Russia and Roumania, their problems could not be regarded as solved. Laws permit us to ask or demand our rights, and their safe-guarding, but prejudices cannot be met in this way, while hatred is the most dangerous of enemies to a progressive idea. Civilized society owes these seven million Jews a plain duty, for they have the human right to live and grow and remain human.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1049.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Russia's persecution of her own subjects is according to Dr. Magnes the blackest page in the history of mankind.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
