<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-30">May 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Regarding Zokan Godol's Feuilleton</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0856</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0856.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-30">May 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">REGARDING ZOKAN GODOL'S FEUILLETON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Worthy Editor:</p>
   <p>Reading in your paper, the Courier of May 19, the article "A Glance and a Thought," by Zokan Godol, brought back to my mind a similar story that happened to me in Lodz.</p>
   <p>A friend of mine and I entered Gitkin's Book Publishing establishment to buy some works of Jewish authors. Glancing over the volumes of Mendele Mocher Svorim, Sholom-Alechim, Peretz, Tseitlin, and others, there immediately came to my mind thoughts of each one's writings: The Nag (Mare), Fishke The Wry One, Tuvia of The Dairy Diet, Stempeniv, Menochem Mendel of Yehupetz, and many of Sholom Alechim's heroes, etc. When I expressed my thoughts to my friend, the salesman spoke up (I <pb facs="5423972_2_0857.jpg" n="2"/>do not know whether he was Mr. Gitkin himself or one of his clerks.)</p>
   <p>"Would that we did not know them!"</p>
   <p>We were enraged at the man's audacity and I replied:</p>
   <p>"Yes, you publishers and distributors desire the author's work, their creations into which they have put their hearts and their souls, so that you may get money for them."</p>
   <p>"No,"said the salesman,"you have not understood me correctly. I meant to say; would that we had not known the authors personally, because the farther we are from them, the more revered they remain <pb facs="5423972_2_0858.jpg" n="3"/>with us, and the more respect we retain for them."</p>
   <p>Transposing his words according to Zokan Godol's article, we must confess that we imagine the author to be other than he actually is. Yet, after all, he too is only mortal, having caprices and peculiarities of his own. The expression "Simple reflections of the wise scholar are necessary lessons," may imply that the sayer probably did not know the wise man face to face. But in truth, the authors are as human as you and I. If we appreciate them, it is for their work, because in creating this work they are as angels.</p>
   <p>Your devoted reader,</p>
   <p>Kalman Bailes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
