<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-25">May 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Cable from Chicago Jewish Leaders to the President in Answer to John F. Smulski's Denial of Pogroms</title><title level="a" type="sub">Gigantic Protest Meeting Called for June 8</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0886</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0886.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 1 (Polish)</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
     <item>IV (Polish)</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-25">May 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CABLE FROM CHICAGO JEWISH LEADERS TO THE PRESIDENT IN ANSWER TO JOHN F. SMULSKI'S DENIAL OF POGROMS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Gigantic Protest Meeting Called for June 8</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jewish leaders of Chicago answered yesterday to the ungainly cable that the Polish leader John F. Smulski, Paderewski's representative in America, sent to President Wilson, in which he asked that demonstrations in America against Polish pogroms be stopped, mentioning that pogrom reports are false. The following cable was sent yesterday to President Wilson, signed by Adolph Kroiz, president of the B'nai B'rith and Julius Rosenwald, vice-president of the American Jewish Committee.</p>
   <p>"To his excellency Woodrow Wilson, President of the United States, Paris.</p>
   <p>"John F. Smulski published his cable to you, and therefore we send this <pb facs="5423972_2_0887.jpg" n="2"/>in reply:</p>
   <p>"Mr. Smulski, in the name of the American citizens of Polish blood and descent, says, in regard to accusations of his kinfolks murdering Jews, 'We know that these stories are false,for the people being accused are our brothers and fathers.'</p>
   <p>"Those are his own assertions, but he gave no proof. On the other hand, we are in possession of the names of many victims who were slaughtered.</p>
   <p>"We received reliable reports stating that hundreds of Jews were put to death and burned alive in Poland; that thousands were wounded and hundreds of thousands were plundered, their homes ruined. It is feared that an annihilation war is being planned.</p>
   <p>"Lord Parmour, of the English House of Lords, addressed, on April 11, 1919, <pb facs="5423972_2_0888.jpg" n="3"/>a meeting concerning the slaughter of Jews in Poland. He stated that this is a blot on the face of civilization; a problem not only related to Jews but to the entire civilized world. All of civilized mankind must immediately protest against such outrages.</p>
   <p>"American citizens, regardless of their religion, who are horrified at the brutalities committed against Polish Jews, do not desire revenge. They wish only that the slaughter of Jews cease; and that the same justice administered to their neighbors should be extended to the Jews in those countries where it is now denied them.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Adolph Kroiz</p>
   <p>Julius Rosenwald."</p>
   <p>The cable was sent from the conference of prominent Jewish leaders held <pb facs="5423972_2_0889.jpg" n="4"/>here yesterday. Present at this conference were Adolph Kroiz, Julius Rosenwald, Max Adler, James Davis, Rabbi Silver, Judge Horner, and Judge Harry M. Fisher.</p>
   <p>At this conference it was also decided to call a huge mass-meeting in one of the largest halls of Chicago for a deeply impressive protest against pogroms in Poland.</p>
   <p>It is to be held Sunday, June 8. The most prominent speakers of the country, Jews and non-Jews, will address this mass-meeting.</p>
   <p>This Wednesday evening, in the Chicago Hebrew Institute, there will be an important conference which extends an invitation to all the rabbis of Chicago, all the synagogue presidents, and to presidents of lodges and societies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
