<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1918-03-13">March, 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Toman - Courier League</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1011</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1011.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish World</title>,
<date when="1918-03-13">March, 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE TOMAN - COURIER LEAGUE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The good and bad qualities of people are exposed in every campaign. The masses are then distinguished by their idealism; the scabs by the sale and prostitution of their votes; the politicians by the boodleness and certain Jewish social workers and "reverends" have their masked removed.</p>
   <p>In peaceful times - not speaking of campaign times - we know that the former "ists," who today call themselves Zionists, are ordinary nothings, who change their "ism" in accordance with the market prices. They also do the same with their political convictions and proclaim themselves Republicans or Democratics as it best suits their business.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1012.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, in time of a campaign, these very people must look upon the mob - the Jewish masses - with contempt, for they remove the "Zionist" masks from themselves and proclaim the country in which they reside as the true Jewish home. In time of a campaign these very people must also drop their "we are the chosen people" melodies and reverse the "tunes" of "hypocrisy" according to the dictates of the candidates of the powerful money-interests.</p>
   <p>Alderman Toman is well known to the Jewish masses through his glorous record, which was exposed in Saturday's Courier. He is well known as a loyal supporter of the wealthy money - bags, as a defender of everything that the wealthy exploiting corporations and companies demand. He is also known as an enemy of free speech and peaceful assemblage, and as a friend of everything that is hated and condemned by the nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1013.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>His poor record in the City Council has compelled even the Capitalistic Municipal League to condemn him and to praise Comrade Alderman Rodinges because he had courageously combated the reactionary plans of Alderman Toman.</p>
   <p>All this, however, does not make him unsympathetic to the Courier, that pretends to be the organ of the Chicago "Zionist leaders."</p>
   <p>The Courier stated in its yesterday's issue that a group of "prominent Jewish personalities" of the 34th Ward, Democrats and Republicans, have organized a "Toman Non-Partisan League" for his re-election.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1014.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The "Zionist" editor of the Republican, Democratic and "all around " Courier also remarked that Toman is known for his "good work?" in the City Council, that he completes his term with a good record ?, and always has proven himself a devoted friend ? to the Jews.</p>
   <p>We, Socialists, are international, and a good Gentile is closer to us than a wicked Jew, a Democratic or a Republican politician. The "Zionist" editors and publishers of the Courier should consider Comrade Yretz, the Jew, to be an honor to the Jewish community. Why is it then that the Courier the organ of "Judaism" should be on the side of a Gentile against a Jew?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1015.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This difficult question increases in difficulty when we observe the names of the officers of the "Toman Non - Partisan League," whom the Courier advertises as "well-known social workers." The secretary, Max M. Korshak, is the Courier's lawyer; the vice chairman, Samuel J. Rosenblatt, in the Courier's headman.</p>
   <p>The Jewish community is too well acquainted with the Courier and its lies, and will never receive a better reception by the Jewish masses than its honorable friend, Judge Fisher, got.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
