<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-24">Nov. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Race and Nationality</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-24">Nov. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">RACE AND NATIONALITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In America there is a city called Cincinnati, and in Cincinnati there is a newspaper called the Israelite, and the Israelite has an editor called Dr. David Phillipson. This Dr. Phillipson is not only a rabbi, but also a publicist, and as a publicist, he is the spokesman of all the anti-Zionist and assimilation elements in America.</p>
   <p>He is an anti-Zionist not because he has any fault to find with Zionism, but because he is a typical assimilationist and is constitutionally opposed to Zionism. Since Zionism is a living movement, which develops politically and organizationally, it cannot be fought by any one [fixed] argument. Therefore, David Phillipson, like any other enemy of Zionism, must always change his position and stand toward Zionism and must always seek to find new faults <pb facs="5423972_2_0708.jpg" n="2"/>with Zionism.</p>
   <p>At one time, his best argument was that Zionism is a dream and cannot be realized. Well, thank God, Zionism is no longer a dream, but a reality. Nor can the argument that Zionism is treason to America be used, for the greatest American statesmen, from President Wilson down, have declared themselves to be in favor of Zionism, and the American government has done everything [it could] to help Zionism become a reality. Therefore, David Phillipson must present brand-new arguments against Zionism--in order to remain a significant enemy of Zionism.</p>
   <p>His newest argument is that the Jews are a race, but not a nationality. He makes this statement in an editorial in his newspaper, the Israelite.</p>
   <p>Race--declares the sage of Cincinnati--is physical and ethnical, and has to do with descent. On the contrary, nationality is purely subjective and is <pb facs="5423972_2_0709.jpg" n="3"/>entirely a psychic matter. A human being is, so far as nationality is concerned, what he is and what he wants to be; he can change his nationality at will, and, consequently, there is no Jewish nation; therefore, national Zionism is a swindle.</p>
   <p>This is a new Torah from Cincinnati. Whether or not this new Torah is a valid one, we shall soon see. The racial theory is ancient and at the same time new, because no two anthropologists have the same definition of race. Some anthropologists claim that there are only four different races, while others contend that there are hundreds of races. Race has not yet been defined, and race psychology has proven to be the greatest sophistry, so far as the attempt to build it on a purely physical basis is concerned.</p>
   <p>Whether or not the Jews are a race, and a pure race at that, as many assert, it is difficult to say. For the last two thousand years, we have been living in the environment of the white race in Europe, and we have lived in <pb facs="5423972_2_0710.jpg" n="4"/>America since it was discovered. Whether or not we were at one time a race, or only a part of the Semitic race, has never been finally settled. The whole racial question, as far as it concerns nations, is obscure, and is not only difficult to solve, but is also hard to define. At any rate, it is purely an academic question. For the past few decades, the racial question has become a whip in the hands of anti-Semites, and all the accusations against our people are now being made against the Jewish race. For this reason, it is not particularly good tactics for a rabbi to play off race against nationality in regard to Zionism because it means the employment of anti-Semitic methods against Zionism.</p>
   <p>For the past two thousand years, the civilized world has referred to us not as a race, but as a nationality, and in the consciousness of the nations, we are a nationality. This fact alone makes us a nationality.</p>
   <p>The question is not whether we are actually a nationality, or merely a <pb facs="5423972_2_0711.jpg" n="5"/>religious community; the question is rather, what do the nations of the earth think of us? Even if we were not actually a nationality, as long as the nations of the world consider us a nationality, we are a nationality.</p>
   <p>Therefore, when Dr. Phillipson says that a human being, which naturally includes a Jew, can, on the question of nationality, be whatever he wants to be: a Russian today, a German tomorrow, a Frenchman the day after tomorrow, he shows not only a pitiful lack of political understanding, but also a lack of historical knowledge. A Jew cannot become a Russian today, a German tomorrow, or a Frenchman the day after tomorrow. Wherever he is, he is loyal to his country, but he always remains a Jew. We Jews are not a people of actors, who perform a different role every day and change our faces daily. Wherever we are, we are Jews and members of the Jewish nationality. The world considers us a nationality; in the literature of all civilized nations, we are characterized as a nationality, and our entire existence in the Diaspora countries for the past two thousand years <pb facs="5423972_2_0712.jpg" n="6"/>proves that the world made no mistake when it considered us a separate nationality.</p>
   <p>When Dr. Phillipson says that a Jew can change his nationality, just as a man changes his coat, that he can be a Russian today, a German tomorrow, a Frenchman the day after tomorrow, etc., he himself is making a severe indictment of us because he is characterizing us as a people of actors, who can change their faces daily. This also has always been the argument of the anti-Semites. The truth is, and it is proven by the fact that we still exist as Jews, that we cannot change our faces, that we are loyal, that we are conservative as a people.</p>
   <p>If we were a race and not a nationality, as Dr. Phillipson states, the nations would never have given us Palestine because a race is not limited to one country and is not entitled to a country. On the contrary, a nation is entitled to a country. Since the nations of the earth know that we are <pb facs="5423972_2_0713.jpg" n="7"/>a nation, they have recognized our right to our national home and have given us Palestine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
