<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-11-06">Nov. 6, 1905</date>, 6:3.
<title level="a">Dr. Hirsch's Irritating Speech</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1358</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1358.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-11-06">Nov. 6, 1905</date>, 6:3.
<title level="a">DR. HIRSCH'S IRRITATING SPEECH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the course of an address on the Russian disorders on Friday evening Rev. Dr. Hirsch gave expression to some opinions which, though he may honestly entertain them, he would better have kept to himself.</p>
   <p>It is rather late in the evolution of civilization for any man, leading the thought of even a small part of the world, to be saying anything calculated to fan the flame of enmity, religious or any other, but religious especially.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch has made no little reputation by such questioning and answering as are reported of that address.</p>
   <p>"Does Christianity fail to civilize or has it never been taught?" This is one of the questions he asked, and it carries the unmistakable implication that whether Christians have or have not been taught they are, in the reverend gentleman's judgment not civilized - at the least, that Christianity does not imply civilization. He answered his own question by avowing belief that "it has never been taught."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1359.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch should know that religious wars and religious persecutions, really as such, have been little known in the world for many years. None knows better than he the spirit and the teachings of the Christian religion - not of this or that denomination or this or that people avowing the religion but of the source and fountain head of the religion, and none knows better than he that nothing in that spirit of those teachings is inconsistent with the highest civilization of which man has known anything. He knows that a higher civilization has never been developed under or along with any other religion.</p>
   <p>He knows, too, that though the religion of the Jew has been more or less involved in the outrageous persecutions his people have endured, yet the real, controlling element in them all has been not religious but racial and personal antagonism. The modern name for the whole anti-Jewish feeling - anti-Semitism - is alone conclusive proof that it is racial and not religious in basis.</p>
   <p>No matter how much a Jew may become a professing Christian, he never wholly loses his blood fellowship with his people, though they execrate his religious apostasy, and he rarely attains to full fellowship of any kind with non-Semitic peoples, largely because he cannot rid himself of his own race identity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1360.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>None should know better than Dr. Hirsch that, whatsoever may be Russian or other persecution of Jews, it is not because Russians are Christian but that, in so far as they indulge in cruelty and persecution, even for racial reasons, they are not Christian in spirit or motive.</p>
   <p>Least of all is it becoming in any Jewish teacher in this country to ascribe to religious difference cruelties that are inconsistent with any true religion.</p>
   <p>From the hour this nation was born the Jew within its borders has enjoyed as large a measure of civil and religious liberty as any other of its people. He has had no reason to complain of any abridgment of either. He has been free to worship, to think, to vote, to have his voice in government, on precisely the same terms with other native or foreign born citizens.</p>
   <p>Within a very few years this country has become the refuge of many thousands of the race who have suffered wrong elsewhere, nor have they here encountered political or religious proscription.</p>
   <p>Racial antagonisms do not rest at all on religious profession, and no people have <pb facs="5423972_2_1361.jpg" n="4"/>better reason to know that fact than the Jew in America. It is the blood, not the religion, that makes them and sustains them.</p>
   <p>There was reason to hope that American silence and forbearance, met by the Jew in like spirit, might in time wear out even the rooted antagonism of race, but utterances such as those ascribed to Dr. Hirsch threaten to increase it.</p>
   <p>Wholly apart from religion, no American can fail to deprecate most earnestly anything that tends towards blowing into flame the anti-Semitic feeling latent here precisely as similar racial antagonisms yet dwell in every people of the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
