<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Forward</title>
      <date when="1919-05-21">May 21, 1919</date>
      <title level="a">Countrymen</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0945</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0945.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Forward</title>
     <date when="1919-05-21">May 21, 1919</date>
     <title level="a">Countrymen</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A terrible desolation has come upon our brethren and sisters in our old home. The Pole, who yesterday fought for his freedom, is today celebrating his victory in Jewish blood. He washed the flag of victory in the blood of our children and parents. Under the pretense of fighting Bolshevism, they violate our daughters, our brides, our sisters and our wives. They robbed us of all we had, and then murdered our fathers and our brothers. Our despair is complete! No one in this civilized world notes what is taking place, and no one responds to our cries, our groans, all are blind and deaf to the slaughter which is being committed against us. Therefore - we demand that you cease work, come out on the street and join in a protest. Join in our pleas that this Powerful Country of ours should use its influence to stop the murder of children and adults simply because they are Jewish.</p>
   <p>Not one mother should send her child to school today. Women and mothers - leave your work! Dress in black! Bring your husband and children, and come to join the protest.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0946.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(The following organization signed the above appeal) Perissian Progressive Aid Society, Rovner Lodge, Progressive Order of the West, Bendin Verein, Denewitz Podolian Verein, Vilna Independent Aid Society; Unity Lodge 41 Order of the Nights of Joseph, Brusillove Aid Society, First Alexandrousky Aid Society, Dwinsh Progressive Aid Society, Independent Polchin Sick Benefit Society; Starodnov and Vicinity Aid Society, Staradnov Ladies Aid Society; First Krinik Aid Society; Kilso Progressive Aid Society; Nierzin Progressive Aid Society, Clothing Peddlers Protective Association, Krementchuk Aid Society, Stashov Sick and Aid Society; Chersin Aid Society; Winitz Aid Society; Poltizner Independent Aid Society; First Chernigov Aid Society; Independent Posen Aid Society; All immigrant Jews, all lodges and societies are summoned to appear at Winchester Ave. and 12th St. at 2:30 P.M.</p>
   <p>Pinsk &amp; Vicinity</p>
   <p>The latest news from our former home is so terrible that it must arouse the emotions of every countrymen. A great mass meeting will take place on the day of mourning. Today at 7:30 P.M. a special meeting will be held in the West Side Auditorium, Taylor St. &amp; Racine Ave. All our countrymen are cordially invited to meet at about 1:30 P.M. at corner of Wood and 12th St. from where we will join with the procession of mourning. Executive of Pinsk &amp; vicinity society for the War Victims.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0947.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To all members of the Jewish National Worker's Alliance.</p>
   <p>Dear Comrades!</p>
   <p>Today, Wednesday is the day which the Jewish people of America have chosen to voice their strongist protest against the horrible, brutal and inhuman pogroms upon our brethren and sisters across the ocean. The air will be filled with our pain and our condemnation of a society which permits and encourages such bestiality as the pogroms in Pinsk Lemberg and other provinces and towns in Poland, Ukrainia, Galicia and Roumania. Society must be horrffied by the brutality of the pogrom inciters, to say nothing of the organized and planned systematic murder of a nation, all this under the guise of anti-Bolshevism.</p>
   <p>to be continued</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
