<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-01">July 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Protestants and Catholics</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1194</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1194.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-01">July 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">PROTESTANTS AND CATHOLICS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We often hear that the Protestants are a more liberal element than the Catholics. Everybody recalls the conflagration in Salem, which branded the Protestants as unjust and impious people. Since there were neither Jews nor heretics to burn, they were satisfied with "witches."</p>
   <p>It has occurred in times of yore that Catholics have burned both Protestants and Jews. Now in France, where the Catholics have long since abrogated the out-moded Christian divorce laws, the Protestants are not even conservatives, and they are always roaring about clamping down the divorce laws tighter, although they know that it results in bad consequences.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1195.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Protestants aren't, in any degree less fanatical than the Catholics, and if their spiritual leaders could attain everything they want, they would introduce the dogma of the Protestant religion in public schools and turn every public institution into missionary houses.</p>
   <p>An incident, which occurred recently in Texas, illustrates this. The Protestant spiritual leaders of Texas succeeded in ejecting, from public schools, the study of Darwin - a textbook on the development of the species. They (these spiritual leaders) are not prudent enough to know that the only way to make peace between science and religion is by not interfering with either and that to prohibit scientific teachings will ultimately cause children to drop religion, when they become acquainted with science. However the spiritual leaders do not look beyond the present and treat it as they did the divorce question.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1196.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is no reason, under any circumstances, to consider the Protestants higher than the Catholics. Neither one is better nor worse than the other.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
