<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-12-09">Dec. 9, 1905</date>, 6:3.
<title level="a">Opposes a Jewish Federation President Kraus of the B'nai B'rith Says it is Unnecessary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1330</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1330.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-12-09">Dec. 9, 1905</date>, 6:3.
<title level="a">OPPOSES A JEWISH FEDERATION President Kraus of The B'nai B'rith Says It is Unnecessary</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Pittsburg, Dec. 10. - Adolf Kraus of Chicago, international president of B'nai B'rith, to-day declared against the plan for a universal central organization of Jews saying his order stood for all the proposed organizations wants to accomplish. Mr. Kraus was here to initiate 112 candidates into his order. He expressed the hope that Witte, if he remained premier of Russia, would accomplish much for the good of the Jews. He said that the B'nai B'rith is preparing to appoint committees all over the world to take care of homeless Jews from Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1331.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>cloud on the horizon of the nation. It is growing in magnitude and soon will become a burning question, unless foresight and judgment are exercised in an effort to provide for its solution. I refer to the problem of immigration, and especially to that phase of it which presents itself in the enormous influx of Russian Jews which will flood this country as a result of the barbarities in Russia....we must expect that hundreds of thousands of them will seek refuge in America.</p>
   <p>"The danger is that, twenty-five years hence, when the oppressed of other countries present themselves at our gates they will be met with an extensive and rigid system of restrictions which will make it very difficult for them to enter the country and become citizens of the republic. It is our duty, immigrants and descendants of immigrants as we are, to hold the door open that others may enjoy the same privileges of which we and our ancestors availed themselves as long as our country is able to contain the millions of souls who arrive here yearly and seek to make homes for themselves."</p>
   <p>Dr. Hirsh also appealed to the Jews to meet the problem and shoulder the obligation of the care of their unfortunate brothers who are left homeless and seek an asylum in the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1332.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"I believe," said he, "that Count De Witte's influence in the present crisis in Russia is not sufficient to carry out the policy of emancipation of the Jews. We may expect to see the Jews flock to America from Russia and Roumania and we must, as Judge Mack has said, face the problem which will present itself. We have had a share in the making of the nation at the mine and in the mill, in the counting-room and on the seas.</p>
   <p>"I myself am an immigrant; I am not a native-born American citizen, and I can sympathize with those who are seeking life and liberty in this land. Let us give of our brains and our money to care for these people and help to make of them citizens who will become a prop instead of a burden upon the nation."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
