<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-05-22">May 22, 1919</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0924</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0924.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-05-22">May 22, 1919</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was a great privilege to be able to observe Chicago Jewry as it mourned and protested, cried for the unfortunate, - their panegyrics for the dead, their demand for rights for the living. Chicago Jewry did not beg but demanded their rights from that world which the Jews, with their flesh and blood, had helped make free, safe, and secure for democracy.</p>
   <p>The Rabbis and their henchman and the politician of the Courier, did not come to join the Jewish masses in their day of mourning, did not join with those Jews who demanded that the world should not allow Poland to continue to bathe in Jewish blood. On that day the first named parties stayed at home; they were afraid to show themselves in public, at the march or in the Auditorium as opposed to the protest of the masses against the misery inflicted upon them.</p>
   <p>The Courier in its publication said yesterday that the mourning procession and the protest mass meeting was the work of the radicals. Never was the Courier so truthful. Yes, it was the work of the radicals, who are the most intelligent <pb facs="5423972_2_0925.jpg" n="2"/>and the best of the Jewish nation and who are giving of their intelligence through the Forward. The radicals knew that they were protesting in unison with the Jewish of New York, Detroit, and several other cities.</p>
   <p>The Jews of the other cities combined with Chicago Jewry and rank and file Jews of all types from lodges, synagogues and societies against the opposition of their leaders, protested and thus helped to awaken the conscience of the world. They opened the eyes of the world to the brutality and savagery which the Poles are displaying against the Jews, wherever they may be, from Lemberg to Pinsk.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
