<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-09">June 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanians Demand Recognition; Desire No Ties with Poland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0811</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0811.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1 (Lithuanian)</item>
     <item>III H (Lithuanian)</item>
     <item>I G (Lithuanian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-09">June 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIANS DEMAND RECOGNITION; DESIRE NO TIES WITH POLAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More than 5,000 voices of American-Lithuanians were raised yesterday evening, at the opening of the Lithuanian convention in the Auditorium, in a prolonged "no" when one of their leaders, V. F. Yankus, asked if Lithuania should be united with Poland.</p>
   <p>Representing the 800,000 Lithuanians in America, was the unanimous expression of those assembled to demand that the Peace Conference give recognition to Lithuania as an independent republic, such as other small nations have already received. For Lithuania, no less than the others, helped carry the burden of the War, fighting <pb facs="5423972_2_0812.jpg" n="2"/>courageously against the Germans.</p>
   <p>A touching scene was presented when the curtain rose and before the eyes of the Auditorium's 5,000 people stood a young woman personifying America, and she, Miss Columbia, with stirring words presented Miss Lithuania, a second young woman wearing a Lithuanian National costume, with the symbol of America's freedom,--a large bell, a Liberty Bell.</p>
   <p>Lithuanians in American Army uniforms stood at attention as the assembly sang The Star Spangled Banner and the national anthem of the Lithuanian Republic. This created a deep impression on all present.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0813.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Congressman "Billie" Mason told of his presenting a resolution, last week, in Congress that America send an embassy and diplomatic corps to Ireland. He will demand that the same be done for Lithuania.</p>
   <p>In this same vein of great sympathy for Lithuania's independence and recognition also spoke Congressman Adolph J. Sabath, who among other things said: "We favor the independence of all small nations such as Lithuania, Czechoslovakia, Jugoslavia, Poland, etc., but, these small nations must in turn guarantee that they will be no less tolerant to the minorities on their soil than they expect us, the democracies of large nations, to be in extending that attitude toward them."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0814.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Some of the other speakers were Judge J. F. Barrett, Chief Justice of the Circuit Court, and S. J. Lapata, who but recently returned from Lithuania bringing news of the terrible state of poverty in which the country now finds itself. He dwelt especially on the horrible calamities of Jews in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>On the motion of one of the speakers, all present, as one man, stood up in tribute to the memory of the Polish pogrom victims in Wilno. The entire assembly stood for fully three minutes. This silent demonstration left a deep impression.</p>
   <p>The convention will today open its meeting at the Morrison Hotel, <pb facs="5423972_2_0815.jpg" n="5"/>and according to the statement of Dr. K. Drangelis, a resolution of protest against pogroms in Poland will definitely be presented.</p>
   <p>Dr. Drangelis, chairman of the Lithuanian Defense Fund, explained that the Lithuanian government distributes the contributed money among all factions of its population, giving its Jewish sufferers the same as received by the Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>In general, it appears that the ruling opinion among the Lithuanians is strongly against Polish pogrom-makers and in full sympathy with the Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
