<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-28">Mar. 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Hasty President of Mount Sinai Hospital</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-28">Mar. 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE HASTY PRESIDENT OF MOUNT SINAI HOSPITAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Morris Kurtzon, the hasty president of the Mount Sinai Hospital, an institution which shows that it regards the poor people as of minor importance by renting out its beds to the rich, is busy now issuing wild statements to justify the acts of the hospital in Berger's case.</p>
   <p>Max Berger, possessing letters of recommendation from a newspaperman and a physician, was brought to the hospital for the treatment of a swollen foot. The swelling started on a toe which rubbed against the shoe. He waited in the hospital a few hours. A girl then came up to him and told him to go home, that there was no place for him. If Berger had been at least taken into the dispensary, his toe washed, treated, and bandaged, he would not have died in pain at the County Hospital. This proves that there is neither pity nor <pb facs="5423972_2_0466.jpg" n="2"/>service at the Mount Sinai Hospital.</p>
   <p>The Berger case is not the first incident in the annals of the Mount Sinai Hospital. Premature graves at Waldheim tell of other terrible mistreatments at the hospital.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kurtzon now claims that Berger would have died anyway, because he was suffering from diabetes. Some pseudo labor leaders support his contention. Mr. Kurtzon explains the Courier's protest as a personal attack upon him. Collectors and emissaries of the hospital back him up in this statement.</p>
   <p>The writer of these lines, who sent Berger to the hospital and who was the first one to take up his case, has never had any transactions with Mr. Kurtzon and hopes not to have any in the future. Dr. [S. M.] Melamed, the editor of the Courier, gave space on the English page of the Courier to Mr. Kurtzon's Mount Sinai Hospital report. Dr. Melamed did not make any comments on this <pb facs="5423972_2_0467.jpg" n="3"/>report, though it contains vague and misleading statements. This proves that Dr. Melamed has nothing against Mr. Kurtzon personally.</p>
   <p>All this blustering will not help Mr. Kurtzon. He must leave the Mount Sinai Hospital. He made a botch of his presidency of that institution. He does not know how a hospital should be managed and he will never know it because his spiritual equipment is much smaller than his great desire to be a public worker.</p>
   <p>A hospital supported by charity must, first of all, make space for poor patients. It should be headed by wise people, with a sense of responsibility to the community, with a sense of mercy.</p>
   <p>The Mount Sinai Hospital must have a different management and Mr. Kurtzon, its hasty president, must make room for it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
