<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-04">Mar. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Massmeeting Without Masses</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-04">Mar. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A MASSMEETING WITHOUT MASSES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a bitter fight against the West Side in general, and particularly against the Jewish District, Chicago's "World's Largest Newspaper" widely publicized that the Jewish people calls a massmeeting to organize an official opposition to Congressman Adolph Sabath. The massmeeting was to have taken place yesterday.</p>
   <p>And this massmeeting was held. What this greatest "nonantisemitic" newspaper did not calculate, is that there are no masses to oppose the Jewish congressman. True, there are in the 5th Congressional District a number of people who are dissatisfied with the politics in which congressman Sabath is engrossed. Congressman Sabath is a Democrat, clinging to the Harrison faction, and this renders him nil in the eyes of the Republicans and in the eyes of the Democrats, who are of another faction. But this short coming is only a political defect with which the masses do not interest themselves. Congressman Adolph Sabath has no adversaries, and therefore, when the widely <pb facs="5423972_2_1111.jpg" n="2"/>advertised meeting was held the most important was lacking, that is, the masses.</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabath was sent to Washington as a representative of a district comprising foreign nationalities. His political position is not taken into consideration when performing his duties from this point of view. His fight against immigration laws made him for a national figure, and he has become recognized as an authority on immigration problems. In this respect he has in due time become not only the representative of the 5th Illinois District, but also the representative of all foreign nationalities in America.</p>
   <p>The so-called American Nationalism, which the Chicago Tribune has now taken to defend, is no more than the old gossiper differently garbed. It is a new impression of the erstwhile A. P. Aers in a modern form. It is the desire of the so-called American, who had the good fortune of having his great grandfather migrate to this country to rule over the American, who is an immigrant, or who is of immigrant parents. This is against the basic <pb facs="5423972_2_1112.jpg" n="3"/>principle of Americanism. It is against all accepted truths.</p>
   <p>The broad masses of America, in general, and especially those of the 5th Illinois Congressional District, realize, understand, and feel this. They will not yeild to a self-crowned aristocracy, of which the Chicago Tribune and its like are the organs. Therefore, when a massmeeting was called for the purpose of building up an opposition to the true American patriot, as is understood by the masses, the masses were absent. It was a meeting without masses, and masses without a meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
