<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-06-08">June 8, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Repudiating Alleged Interviews the United Hebrew Charities Not Antagonistic to Russian Refugees</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1384</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1384.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-06-08">June 8, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">REPUDIATING ALLEGED INTERVIEWS THE UNITED HEBREW CHARITIES NOT ANTAGONISTIC TO RUSSIAN REFUGEES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Board of Directors of the United Hebrew Charities repudiates the alleged interviews in which officers of that body are quoted as saying that the society is unfavorably disposed to the location of Russian refugee Jews in Chicago. This resolution was approved at a special meeting of the Board at the Standard Club yesterday.</p>
   <p>It having come to our knowledge that certain pretended interviews were published in one of the daily papers of Chicago, and thence copied into the press of the country generally, representing that the officers of the United Hebrew Charities of Chicago were hostile to the Russian refugees, the Board of Directors of the United Hebrew Charities declares that the interviews do not represent the sentiments or views of the gentlemen said to have uttered them,nor of the Board as a whole; that the figures on our books show that the United Hebrew Charities has, as always heretofore, taken charge, even contrary to the rules of the work, of such applicants as have come before it, whether recent arrivals or not.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1385.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The officers who were said to have expressed sentiments antagonistic to the refugee Jews were President Isaac Greenfelder and Francis Kiss, Superintendent of the Charities. These were said also to be the sentiments of Dr. E. G. Hirsch. These three attended and are said to have indorsed the resolution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
