<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-06-25">June 25, 1877</date>, 4:6.
<title level="a">Seligman-Hilton</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1505</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1505.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-06-25">June 25, 1877</date>, 4:6.
<title level="a">SELIGMAN-HILTON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Seligman's tardiness in bringing his suit against Judge Hilton suggests the inference that he prefers leaving his vengeance to be worked out by the members of the ten tribes. In the outset the banker's position was an excellent one. A survey of all the facts shows him to have been shamefully abused, and, had he acted on his own responsibility, he would have vindicated himself and his religious predilections, and become a second Moses to the Israelites all over the world. The stated reason for his rejection from Hilton's hotel was a fine ground on which to establish a fight, wherein he was certain of victory and laurels. But Mr. Seligman chose an ill-advised course, and by casting his personality into the contest robbed it of its broader principles, and left the general public to select between two individuals in bestowing their sympathies. In his statements and correspondence, he has assumed that he was insulted, and, collaterally, his religion, assigning to the more important a secondary place. It is characteristic of the American people to pay little regard to individuals, and profound respect to representatives of classes; and had the banker sunk his personal feelings in this unfortunate matter, and held up the fact that he had been ostracized for certain peculiar methods the class to which he belongs follows in the worship of God, the instinctive love of religious liberty on which every American prides himself had sprung to his defense, and Hilton had been crushed by an overwhelming expression <pb facs="5423972_2_1506.jpg" n="2"/>of public opinion. But with that self-esteem attached to all wealthy men who have secured position through their wealth, Mr. Seligman assumed that he, and not so much his religion, was the Gen. Boum from whose head the cocked hat of his dignity had been snatched by the suddenly famous Fritz, who unites the diverse functions of running a hotel and keeping a dry-goods shop. The first thing Seligman did was to show that he and Hilton had had business transactions before, not altogether pleasant, as appears from the misty admissions of both, and the public regards this circumstance as suspicious, and are inclined to let the gladiators fight the battle without intervention.</p>
   <p>The crafty method adopted by Seligman and his counsel to induce Jews to withdraw their patronage from Hilton counts for nothing. It is an element of the Jewish faith to purchase goods at the lowest possible rates, and if Hilton commanded a large and influential Israelitish custom, it was because that custom found it to the interest of its constituents to patronize his establishment, and, if they did, they are not to be driven to any quarter in which those interests would suffer. So that wing of Mr. Seligman's attack is not of much avail. If a few of the more susceptible among the Jews have withdrawn their trade from A. T. Stewart &amp; Co., it will find its way back.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1507.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The argument that there are many of his own religion whom Mr. Seligman would not entertain at his home is without force. The grounds upon which he would exclude them would be purely personal, and it was in intruding his personal rights into the present controversy that he made his grave mistake.</p>
   <p>There was one course for Mr. Seligman to take, - a dignified course, - and that an appeal to the courts, and a placid acceptance of the decision. This he failed to do, and an opportunity was lost.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
