<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-14">Mar. 14, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-14">Mar. 14, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish Theological College is the one great cultural institution which the Orthodox Jews of Chicago have built. The growth and development of this institution will be accepted as a proof that the Orthodoxy grows and develops. Conversely, if the Jewish Theological College stands still, it will be taken that Chicago Orthodoxy is standing still too. He who wants Orthodoxy to progress and not to retrogress must first of all participate in the membership drive of the Jewish Theological College. I think that the rabbis should be the first ones to desire that Orthodoxy should grow and they should deem it their prime duty as rabbis, as representatives of the Torah, as the leaders of Orthodoxy, to help the Jewish Theological College, to work for it, to take part now in the membership drive. When the Jewish Theological College will have three thousand members in good standing, it will be financially independent; otherwise it will always have financial troubles. The rabbis <pb facs="5423972_2_0481.jpg" n="2"/>should be the first ones to see to it that the institution becomes financially independent, but what have the rabbis done up to now for the membership drive? How many hundreds of new members have they enrolled? No synagogue member will refuse to give his rabbi five or ten dollars as membership fee in the Jewish Theological College. There are in Chicago about thirty rabbis. Were these thirty rabbis to devote two days to the purpose of enrolling new members in the Jewish Theological College, they could easily enroll about a thousand new members. The institution would then know that it has a yearly income of ten to fifteen thousand dollars a year, its struggle for existence would ease up, and its leaders, instead of worrying about the budget, would be able to devote all their energies toward the intellectual development of the institution.</p>
   <p>Now, my dear rabbis, permit me to ask you these questions: You claim that you are the representatives of the Torah, why then don't you throw yourselves, heart and soul, into the work for an institution which is devoted to the Torah only? If you rabbis would not work for such an institution, how can you expect the lay citizen to work for it? However, the sad truth is that the laymen who <pb facs="5423972_2_0482.jpg" n="3"/>are connected with the institution work for it, out you rabbis, with the exception of one, are not doing anything for it. Excepting the chairman, there was not a single rabbi present at the last meeting of the board of directors of that institution.</p>
   <p>Ought it to be this way?</p>
   <p>A few of the citizens who are connected with the institution are doing their duty, but many citizens who, out of the kindness of their hearts, let themselves be elected directors, are not doing anything. They are never seen at the institution, they do not come to meetings, they do not help, they do not do anything, but they are directors. What for do we need forty-five directors who are not doing anything? Let the board of directors consists of ten or fifteen people who are doing something. We must not throw sand into the eyes of the people. A director who does not come to a meeting, who is not doing anything for the institution, should be given his walking papers, and the sooner he gets them the better it will be for the institution. Every director <pb facs="5423972_2_0483.jpg" n="4"/>of the Jewish Theological College should enroll at least twenty-five new members. If he cannot do it, he has no right to be a director. He is then simply a "mister," without influence, without friends. Not only the Jewish Theological College but many other Jewish institutions should do a house cleaning in their boards of directors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
