<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1925-12-25">December 25, 1925</date>. Vol. 7, p.4.
<title level="a">Jewish Prisoners Are Neglected</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0125</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0125.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Chronicle</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1925-12-25">December 25, 1925</date>. Vol. 7, p.4.
<title level="a">JEWISH PRISONERS ARE NEGLECTED</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There was published recently, in one of our local Yiddish dailies, a letter from a Jewish prisoner in a nearby state institution, crying out against the shameful way the Jewish prisoners are being neglected. The writer of this letter points out that while Christian prisoners receive regularly the consolation and encouragement which go with religious services and sermons, with gifts and visits, the Jewish prisoners are left to eat out their hearts in desolation and despair. He implores the Jews of Chicago to send a word of cheer, a glint of hope to these erring sons of Israel.</p>
   <p>In the same Yiddish daily there appeared sometime later, an article giving in detail the history of Chicago's Jewry provision for the Jewish prisoners in institutions in the city and its vicinity. And from that account it appears that whatever special care or help the Jewish prisoners have received has been due almost wholly to the efforts of some thoughtful and generous individual. It was only recently that the community, through the medium of a Jewish chaplain, for the first time made any organized effort whatsoever to help the prisoners, and now it appears that even that has been given up.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0126.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is high time that the Jewish community of Chicago make some permanent and definite provision for supplying the Jewish prisoners in institutions of the vicinity, with religious services and the consolation that comes from sympathetic understanding.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
