<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-02">July 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Corporal Brings a Scroll of the Torah from Metz to Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-02">July 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH CORPORAL BRINGS A SCROLL OF THE TORAH FROM METZ TO CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Corporal Harry Fon, 1535 Central Park Avenue, has recently returned from Paris, France, where he participated in the various battles near Metz. He brought back with him a Sepher Torah (Scroll of the Torah) which he saved from the ruins in Tiakaot, a village not far from Metz.</p>
   <p>It was at the height of the battle, when thousands of shells from German cannons fell on all sides, that the Corporal learned that there was a synagogue near by and decided to risk his life to save any holy scrolls that might possibly be found there.</p>
   <p>He was not mistaken. When he entered the synagogue, the Orin Kodish (special closet in the wall where scrolls are kept) was already shot to pieces and two scrolls lay on the floor. Because both of them were much too heavy to carry, he took but one, removing its two heavy wooden handle bars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0205.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For the two months during which Corporal Fon remained in the war, he carried the scroll with him. Upon his return, he presented it to the synagogue Agudos Sphord Anshe Mariv.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Please note custom of considering the Torah, or the "Book" as it is sometimes called, more valuable than life itself. Orthodox Jews will go to great lengths to save the Book in a crisis, for without it the community considers its very life lost. The receiving of a scroll in a synagogue is a very high honor that is generally attended with great ceremony.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
