<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-09-16">September 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">'Tis a Difference</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1170</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1170.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-09-16">September 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">'TIS A DIFFERENCE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his column, "News Plus Observations", in the Chicago Israelite, Rabbi Tobias Schoenfarber wonders "why we Jews feel it necessary to invite city officials to participate in the consecration of a synagogue."</p>
   <p>"The Mayor of the city," said the honored rabbi, "can even be a religious man, but it is not in place to invite him to speak at the consecration of a synagogue, or even of a church."</p>
   <p>We agree with the honored rabbi that at a consecration of a synagogue, further even, at the consecration of any specific Jewish institution, non-Jewish speakers are not in place. We too are of the opinion that at the consecration, especially of a synagogue, only speakers who believe in, or are at least in sympathy with the dogmas, ceremonies, and traditions of the concerned synagogue should be invited.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1171.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, we are of the opinion that an exception should be made when it is the question of a mayor of the city, a governor of the state, or a president of the United States.</p>
   <p>It is true that when these people come to address a Jewish audience at such a consecration, they speak of the Jews as "good citizens, charitable people, and other such compliments," and perhaps, it is just as the honored rabbi states that they pass compliments in order to profit by them. "They bear in mind re-election," says Rabbi Schoenfarber, "and they attempt to get it by the 'sacred services' of consecrating a synagogue." But this is still no reason for not inviting the highest executive official of the city, state, or country when consecrating a synagogue or any other community building.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1172.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The construction of a synagogue, and a consecration of a synagogue carry no piety from an orthodox standpoint. The construction of a synagogue only shows that in a certain part of a city, state, or country the population increased; a consecration of a large, beautiful and magnificent synagogue is merely a sign that this division of the population has become wealthier, is living more comfortably, and wants to have a more comfortable place of worship.</p>
   <p>From a religious standpoint, it doesn't make any difference whether we pray on the balcony, or in the basement, or in a palace. The Jewish God accepts Jewish prayers from anywhere. The Prophet Isaiah stressed that point. If we want more beautiful and larger synagogues, it is because we want to have more enjoyment and because we want to show those who are outside of our limits that we are on equal footing with them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1173.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The possession of a beautiful synagogue is a symbol that we are rich and well-off. Just as we attire ourselves in beautiful clothes and jewels so do we decorate our synagogues and community institutions.</p>
   <p>We suspect that Rabbi Schoenfarber wrote his editorial, bearing in mind the consecration of the Anshe Knesseth Israel Synagogue, which will be held in the near future, and to which, we understand, the Mayor is invited and only orthodox rabbis besides him.</p>
   <p>We wish to say that from our standpoint, the Congregation Anshe Knesseth Israel is right in every sense of the word and we hope that in the near future all the synagogues and institutions will follow this example.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
