<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1919-12-12">Dec. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Iii (ed)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0747</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0747.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1919-12-12">Dec. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">III (ed)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Genuine orthodox views are now becoming fashionable among Jewish Young-America. The hopes for a national restauration of Israel are now widely fostered...."A Jewish nationality:" is now the cry....</p>
   <p>We are ba' avonoth harabbim, in galuth, but we hope soon to return to Palestine where we shall regain our national independence; where we shall take our place as an organic member among the other nations, and where we shall be governed by our own political and ecclesiastical authorities. But, friends, are you aware of what is implied by the terms Jewish Nationality, Restauration, our Own Authorities? Do not play with the word "Nationality," and do not say that you have no desire for a "Restauration." Your "Nationality" leads logically to "Restauration."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0748.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The temple in Jerusalem will be built, and this temple will be the temple, and the sacrificial worship there will be the worship, and the Palestinian Judaism, as represented by the Polish, Roumanian, Turkish, and other eastern Jews flocking there, will be the official Judaism, and your "temples" in New York, Cincinnati, Chicago, and elsewhere, and your Minhag America and your Olath Tamid will be declared to be irreligious, heretical, you yourself may be put in Herem, or you may be forced out altogether by your own "ecclesiastical authorities." This will be the outcome of your declaration: "We stand upon the platform of Jewish "Nationality.'"</p>
   <p>We admit that thus far, Israel was standing upon the nationality-platform. But we are now standing before the threshold of a new period in our history. Judaism must now become elevated to a higher plane; Judaism <pb facs="5423972_2_0749.jpg" n="3"/>must be emancipated from national and racial narrowness; it must become a Religion, - a religion having the power and potency to enter upon its true, prophetic mission to redeem all the world.</p>
   <p>An American Israel ought to be the first in the field to carry on the flag of a New Judaism to triumph and final victory.</p>
   <p>Caeterum censeo, it is time that Judaism becomes a religion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
