<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Chronicle</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1923-03-02">March 2, 1923</date>. Vol. 4, p.4.
<title level="a">Editorial. a University Club</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Chronicle</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1923-03-02">March 2, 1923</date>. Vol. 4, p.4.
<title level="a">EDITORIAL. A UNIVERSITY CLUB</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For a long time in Chicago, there were many places and many neighborhoods from which Jews were barred. Jews were not admitted to certain clubs; were not allowed to buy property in certain sections of the city; were refused admission to rent apartments, etc. Gradually, however, a more broad-minded attitude is beginning to spread itself among those who were intolerant of the proximity of the Jew. Whether it is because of the Jew's increasing wealth, or because of the spirit of the times, we can not say.</p>
   <p>There is, however, still one institution in Chicago where the fear of being besmirched by a contact, however distant, with the Jew, is still rampant. This is the University Club of Chicago, composed of graduates of universities the country over. However, we have no quarrel with the University Club. We turn to a much more serious need of Chicago Jewry. This is a university club for Jews, where graduates from different universities of the country may come together to exchange views and experiences; where young men of the community, fresh from the universities, may be inducted into communal work, for their own good, and for everyone's good. This may seem a rather large order, but a club like this is needed; and a club like this will come. And the sooner it comes, the better Chicago will be.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
