<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-11">May 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">On the Community Stage by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0977</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0977.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-11">May 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE COMMUNITY STAGE BY J. LEIBNER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have an Anti-Defamation League established by the B'nai Brith, whose purpose is to remove from screen and stage types or persons who ridicule the Jew. They protest against newspapers and journals which foster a stimulus in anti-Semitism and create thereby a far reaching hatred.</p>
   <p>Thus far, this body has done very good work, especially in the field of screen and stage. It is said that the reason why the Associated Press does not bring from Russia so many Bolshevik murder stories attributed to the Jew Leon Trotsky, is due to the work of the Anti-Defamation League. If this is true, they have deservedly earned our hearty gratitude.</p>
   <p>We wish to call to the attention of the Anti-Defamation League some foul work done by an anti-Semitic reporter in the Chicago Herald Examiner.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0978.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For the second time in the last few weeks the above mentioned paper published stories of incriminating plans against the government in Washington, and in the local areas, listing Jewish names as instigators.</p>
   <p>Their first article, a sensational one, stated that the sub-treasury would be seized as well as all other public places, the stockyards, and various food warehouses. They gave the name of a young Jewish man, a habitual gossiper, as the leader thereof. We think the young man boasted to the reporter: "Bolshevism is very near America; all branches of government will be taken over by our Bolshevikis," with the same ease that he lectures on Kent and the more or less influence of Latin psychology on modern Jewish literature, and so on and so forth. We believe the reporter took "stock" in the young man and spread a "story" that has no relation with us Jews in this community or in any other that it may have reached.</p>
   <p>Yesterday we read in the same paper a second sensation, that the I. W. W. will hold a revolutionary gathering in the West Side Auditorium, and that <pb facs="5423972_2_0979.jpg" n="3"/>Jews have organized the affair.</p>
   <p>In this case we are certain that no one made any boasting speeches to the reporter, but we take it that his purpose was to place the Jews in a bad light, showing that they seek to create a disturbance throughout the country.</p>
   <p>This is anti-Semitic provocation in the Chicago Herald Examiner, and the Anti-Defamation League should not remain indifferent to it. Let them send a protest to Mr. Arthur Brisbane, editor of the newspaper, or to Mr. William Randolph Hearst himself, the publisher. Both are liberal men and when necessary defend the Jew in their many influential newspapers which they control in most states of the Union.</p>
   <p>The phrase "Bolshevism is a Jewish product" is the label given us by England, which feels so correct in this assumption as she felt when she discontinued Mr. Hearst's cable services in Europe during the War.</p>
   <p>It is hard to give an impartial interpretation of Bolshevism, which in itself <pb facs="5423972_2_0980.jpg" n="4"/>is quite a new problem, that can not so readily be solved unless the world treads another path than that which it follows now. Bolshevism is the result of autocracy, oppression, and hunger. But you cannot hold Jews responsible for these things.</p>
   <p>The peasants of Russia support Bolshevism and workers in America are I. W. W. But a small percentage of Jews are connected in this movement and would be the last to foment trouble. Bolshevism in Russia is also the result of the disorganized, interrupted system of huge industries in which Jews played but a very small part, if any. Jewish workers were almost altogether excluded from large factories up to the time of the Revolution, which completely closed them.</p>
   <p>"Russian Bolshevism," relates a writer, acquainted with the situation there, swept the country in two huge waves, rural and urban. Peasants participated in the rural wave massacring farmers, burning their homes, and securing their lands. Jews certainly took no part in this. In the urban wave of Bolshevism, <pb facs="5423972_2_0981.jpg" n="5"/>Jews, without a doubt, participated.</p>
   <p>But the proportion of Jewish Bolshevists everywhere is very small. Of those Jewish Bolsheviks who have created for themselves a name in Europe, there are only two: Trotsky and Yafe; the founder and leader is still the Russian, Nicholai Lenin, and his former exponent in London, the Russian George Tshitsherin, and in America, a third Russian, Ludwig Martens. The expounder of the Bolshevistic war court in Russia is Zshukov, an ardent Russian who had spent sometime in London.</p>
   <p>Among the Bolshevistic preachers in this land are the Americans John Reid, Colonel Thompson, Louisa Bryant, Albert Rhes Williams, Professor Scott Nearing, Eugene Debs, the priest Irving St. John Toker, Max Eastman, the Tribune's shareholders William Bros Lloyd, Seymore Steadman, and in sympathy with them the reformers Raymond Robins, Jane Addams, Ellis Stone Blackwell, Frank P. Walsh, John Fitzpatrick, Dudley Field Malone, Frederick Hoe and more and more men and women whose names we do not have on hand.</p>
   <p>We believe that in America Bolshevism will never take root. It has no foundation <pb facs="5423972_2_0982.jpg" n="6"/>here and the above mentioned brave and honest women are merely dreaming. But that it will indirectly bring changes here in our political and economic life is not to be doubted. These changes will come from our leaders. Our political leaders and big capitalists are discreet and liberal enough to do something in this matter. Ford, the automobile manufacturer, set a small example that is being followed by other manufacturers.</p>
   <p>Bolshevism is not a Jewish product. Only anti-Semites, among whom may be counted prominent Poles, at present the Jews greatest enemies, will label us so.</p>
   <p>The Anti-Defamation League has before it a great task, to discredit reports of Jewish Bolshevism and to influence the English press to refrain under this category from inciting people against the Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
