<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-11-12">Nov. 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">In Whose Name Does the Jewish Committee Intend to Bow before the Queen?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-11-12">Nov. 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">IN WHOSE NAME DOES THE JEWISH COMMITTEE INTEND TO BOW BEFORE THE QUEEN?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The days are finally drawing near when Chicago will also have the "great" privilege of meeting the Rumanian Queen who is visiting many cities in the United States accompanied by her Imperial suite. Chicago has been in a turmoil for the past few weeks about the manner in which Her Majesty should be greeted. The mayor of Chicago has announced that he will greet the Queen in a very simple and very plain manner. He will not only not bow down before her and kiss her hand but he will also not even dress formally for the occasion. There were some persons in the City Hall who ridiculed the entire affair. One remarked, for example, that he had tickets to a football game the same day, and that he would not give up the game to meet the Queen!</p>
   <p>One can readily see, therefore, that to many Americans, and especially to those who occupy official positions, the entire performance is no more than a nuisance which must take place and which should be forgotten. We certainly <pb facs="5423972_2_0445.jpg" n="2"/>would not have taken up our valuable time to write an article about this nonsense if something hadn't occurred that deserves the undivided attention of our readers--that must be brought to light.</p>
   <p>We mean, of course, the formation of a so-called Jewish committee which plans to prepare a special Jewish reception for the Rumanian Queen during her visit to Chicago. We do not know who authorized this committee to give a special Jewish reception for the Queen. We know that the committee is composed of Rumanian Jews. Still in all, we are not sure that even all the Rumanian Jews of Chicago are filled with so hypocritical a spirit that they are prepared to humble themselves by bowing before, and kissing the hand of, the Queen of that country which is the scene of so much Jewish bloodshed. We are more than certain that there is but a small and insignigicant number among the Rumanian Jews of Chicago that is qualified to act so hypocritically. The Jewish committee probably consists of the common sort of mediator and politician who has no right to carry on such a scene in the name of the Rumanian Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0446.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Yet this is not all. The so-called Jewish committee, according to a rumor, intends to represent not only the Rumanian Jews of Chicago and Illinois, but also the entire Jewish community. Among the members of the committee appear the names of several prominent Jews who are present at every public affair that concerns only important Jewish matters. Their names were mentioned very often during the great relief campaign. Moreover, if we are not mistaken, these very same individuals also participated in the gigantic demonstrations held by the American Jews to protest against the atrocities and bloody outrages committed against other Jews.</p>
   <p>How such people are able to join a committee which plans to pay tribute to a Queen of a country whose Jewish policy they condemned so bitterly, is a thing that it is very hard to understand unless one considers the act as pure hypocrisy. Or maybe these people think that Jewish public opinion has fallen so low as to permit such arrogance and irresponsibility in people who have the nerve and the insolence to do such a thing in the name of all the Jews?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0447.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The people of the Jewish committee should have hidden their faces in shame when they heard the words of that proud Jewish judge, Joseph David of Chicago, as he explicitly refused to act as a member of their committee because, as an American and as a Jew he could not bow before an imperial woman in whose land Jews are being so horribly persecuted. We are positive that the action of Judge David has more beautifully and more proudly expressed the opinion of the Jewish population of Chicago than that of the so-called Jewish committee which thought that it would do the Jews in Rumania a favor by bowing before the Queen and kissing her hand.</p>
   <p>The people on the committee should have understood long ago the uselessness of this type of Jewish mediation. It has never amounted to anything and has always ended with disgrace for the mediators and for those whom they represented. We say this because we believe that there are individuals on the Jewish committee who probably let their names be used out of pure and honest motives. They <pb facs="5423972_2_0448.jpg" n="5"/>probably thought that by giving a reception they would soften the Queen's heart and help the Jews in Rumania in this manner. However sincere their motives may have been, the nature of their action, permeated as it is with the ugly spirit of hypocrisy--from which our Jewish mediators should free themselves now--remains unchanged.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
