<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-08-30">August 30, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Jews Shall Not Perish So Soon. Editorial</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1226</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1226.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-08-30">August 30, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">JEWS SHALL NOT PERISH SO SOON. EDITORIAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Emil G. Hirsch, the honored rabbi of Sinai Temple, in a n interview to reporters, expressed his opinion that Jews - through intermarriage and assimilation - will be wiped out as soon as all nations will remove the chains of suppression and persecution from them.</p>
   <p>The honored rabbi points out that the French Jews are losing the physical features of their ancestors and he also quotes, from a New York anthropologist, that the Jewish physiognomy is changing rapidly in America according to the environment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1227.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We can understand his point; if the honored rabbi means that if the physiognomy of a race is changed due to conditions the race will no longer exist. But then the Jews should have perished long ago. It is irrational to think that if the American Jews acquire a different physiognomy they shall perish, the German Jews did not perish, although the German Jews of today do not have the same physiognomy of the ancient Teutons.</p>
   <p>Not the physiognomy, not the physique makes a race. Moral traditions, spiritual intelligence, which is deeply innoculated into the blood of a separate group, makes a race and nation. And all the distinctions do not show that the Jew is retrogressing physically and morally.</p>
   <p>Therefore the Jews shall not perish, because their existence does not hang upon - as the prophet says - the sword, but upon spirit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
