<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-27">Feb. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Thou Shalt Not Kill</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-27">Feb. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THOU SHALT NOT KILL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A well-known Jewish legend is to the effect that thousands of years ago, when the spirit of the Torah [Law] was still poising in mid-air seeking a national entity in which to become corporeal, it was rejected by all nations. One group of people declared that they could not get along without theft; another declared that they could not get along without murder, and so on. But one nation, which was still as pure and honest as an innocent child, came out openly and answered that they would accept it and combine their fate with the spirit of the Torah.</p>
   <p>Jewish life in reality was still more beautiful than the legend. In times when the whole world was full of rape and the earth was drenched with blood, the Jewish race was counted among the sanctified and godlike, and not among the murders and plunderers. And whenever the enemy have sought to pollute the Jewish name or have accused the Jewish race of bloodshed, he <pb facs="5423972_2_1114.jpg" n="2"/>attributes his libelous accusation to a religious motive. In accusing the Jewish people of all sorts of crimes, why was the most vile anti-Semite unable to say that the Jews will shed blood on account of money or any other motive?</p>
   <p>The proud Jewish spirit is strongly exemplified in the history of an expatriated Spanish Jew, whose whole family starved to death and who himself was in danger of losing his life. Yet, in such plight he turned to heaven, crying out, "you can take my life, but you can't make me a non-Jew." This spirit forced the martyrs of those Jewish communities to commit sucide rather than fall into the hands of the enemy, and only this motive could move the Jewish hand to shed human blood, their own blood.</p>
   <p>All this, however, is past history. Conditions have changed now. Our pseudo-prophets, the prophets of Baal, are forever preaching in the temples <pb facs="5423972_2_1115.jpg" n="3"/>of the golden calf that we should become similar to our neighbors, not a nation on equal footing with other nationalities, having our own homeland and language. This is scarcely fit to be uttered in the halls of the indigent, much less among the leaders of the rich Jews, who are Americans first and then Jews.</p>
   <p>And they have triumphed. A Jewish young man of Chicago slew cold-bloodedly the father of a family, who was twice his age, because the "foreign" Jew dared to insult him, the "Americanized" criminal. Americanized Jewish young men of New York even offer their services of killing someone against whom they may have no grievance. And the list of Jewish murderers can still be extended further.</p>
   <p>The retractation of "Thou Shalt Not Kill" among Jews might be pleasing to those who preach our extinction as a race. But the Jews who do not feel proud of Jewish murderers, and who wish to uphold in our midst the true <pb facs="5423972_2_1116.jpg" n="4"/>Jewish spirit, which gave the commandment of "Thou Shalt Not Kill" to the world thousands of years ago, for these Jews only one thing remains, and it is to acquaint our youth with the everflowing well from which our prophets and servants, martyrs and saints drank.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
