<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-28">Feb. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0536</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0536.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-28">Feb. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Professor Horace Kallen, Henry Hurwitz, and other learned students of Judaism, have undertaken to ferret out the causes of anti-Semitism existing throughout the world in general and America in particular. They claim that Christianity and Christian religious instructions are responsible for anti-Semitism. They claim that hatred toward the Jews and toward everything pertaining to Judaism is implanted in the Christian child from the time he is a small child. Anti-Semitism will exist as long as this is true.</p>
   <p>What, then, shall we do? Can we abolish Christianity? Can we abolish instruction in the Christian religion? I would like to ask these men who know so much about Judaism a few puzzling questions.</p>
   <p>If it is true, as they claim, that Christianity alone is responsible for anti- <pb facs="5423972_2_0537.jpg" n="2"/>Semitism, why did the Greeks and the Romans, who were not Christians, hate the Jews? Apparently, there weren't any fewer anti-Semitic propagandists in ancient Rome than there are today in Germany and France. The Romans knew nothing about Christianity, and yet, they hated the Jews. Later, when they became aware of Christianity, their hatred toward the Jews increased because they believed that Christianity was a Jewish religion. The same holds true of the Greeks.</p>
   <p>If it is true that the Christian catechism is responsible for anti-Semitism, then why are there so many anti-Semites in France where the youth are not reared as Christians? Why are there so many anti-Semites who know no more about Christianity than they do about Buddhism?</p>
   <p>True, the Christian religion and Christian mythology have contributed a great deal to the dissemination and encouragement of anti-Semitism. But it is historically false and sociologically fallacious to assert that hatred toward the Jews originates from Christianity alone. Do the Mohammedans love us?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0538.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Didn't Mohammed himself cast aspersions upon us, and haven't contemporary Arabian pogromists the same psychology and the same ideology as the Christian pogromists in all the countries of Europe and America?</p>
   <p>The truth is that we are hated because we have no national home, because we are a people in the Diaspora. We are not trusted anywhere because people are inclined to mistrust anyone who has no home. People are inclined to regard tramps with suspicion. As a people, we are tramps because we have no permanent address. How does the world look upon an individual who has no permanent address? So long as we, as a people, have no permanent address, we will be mistrusted, suspected, and hated, and we will be made the scapegoat for every crime in the history of the world. When Jews have a homeland, they will probably not be loved, but they won't be regarded with suspicion. There is only one way to destroy anti-Semitism: A Jewish Homeland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
