<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-03-16">March 16, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Nationality</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-03-16">March 16, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH NATIONALITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recent reproduction of an article from the London Saturday Review upon "Jewish Nationality," with some local application of its statements, in The Chicago Tribune, has called forth some replies from Jewish citizens, who seem to apprehend that The Tribune may have some suspicion of Jewish patriotism. The most important of these communications is that of Dr. Kohler, printed in our last issue, which covers the ground so completely that a publication of the others is unnecessary. The Tribune has no exceptions to take to Dr. Kohler's eloquent declaration of the patriotism of the Jews; on the other hand, it is glad to receive the assurance from so competent an authority that, "should Daniel Deronda or Sir Moses Montefiore, the noble Jewish philanthropist, who, I am sure, sat to George Eliot for a portrait of her hero, even venture to call upon the Jews, either of America or of England, France, or Germany, to help him in restoring a Jewish Kingdom in Palestine, he would hardly find ten men to follow him." And again: "for a cosmopolitan freedom and true humanity, the Jews have ever since longed and prayed, whether believing in a personal Messiah, as the conservative English Jews, or adhering only to the kernel of the Messianic hope, disengaged from its national form, as Reformed Judaism in America most decidedly does."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1521.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These two extracts state the case perhaps as strongly as it can be done, and they convey in a positive statement what was meant to be implied in the summary of the Review article and its application. The idea meant to be conveyed was, that while the Jews hold offices of honor and trust, while they are patriotic, as a reference to our late war will show, while they are good citizens and perform all the duties of citizens, and while they are stricter observers of the law and figure less frequently in criminal records than almost any other nationality, still they are not so completely absorbed into the body politic as to be unrecognizable.</p>
   <p>They retain their nationality. It stands out clearly and distinctly. In becoming part and parcel of the American nation, they are still the Jewish people or Jewish nation. They suffer no loss of identity or character. This is the historical phenomenon, and it is as a phenomenon that we are disposed to regard it. Probably no other people of equal numbers could accept a citizenship and perform all its duties with the same patriotism and faith that characterizes those to the manner born, and not lose its identity altogether. If our critics, therefore, are disposed to discuss this as a phenomenon, it might not be unprofitable; but, so far as Jewish patriotism is concerned, we have no discussion to make with them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1522.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The whole case seems to be in Dr. Kohler's nutshell of "cosmopolitan freedom." At the same time there can be no doubt that it was this very idea that some day the Jewish people would migrate to the Holy Land and set up an independent nation that has given people the general impression of their being "sojourners," - a feeling which has been emphasized by the reluctance of the Jews to becoming landholders. All this has now changed, especially in this country, and we are glad to have Dr. Kohler's emphatic indorsement of the fact.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
