<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-03">June 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Gang of Polish Youths Attack Jews in Douglas Park</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0840</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0840.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
     <item>II E 2 (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-03">June 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GANG OF POLISH YOUTHS ATTACK JEWS IN DOUGLAS PARK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Gangs of young Poles wander in Douglas Park, spit on the Jews, throw them off the benches, and beat them within an inch of their lives.</p>
   <p>Such was the case Sunday and also yesterday.</p>
   <p>There were no arrests made Sunday. The park police and detectives who receive salaries so that they guard and protect the lives of those who come to the parks for a bit of fresh air, were nowhere around. If they were, they ignored everything.</p>
   <p>Yesterday, the outrages committed by the young Poles reached its <pb facs="5423972_2_0841.jpg" n="2"/>climax. They went around simply murdering Jews. They beat up David Levitt of 3331 Levitt St. He lay on the grass. They pounded upon him and left him lying there unconscious. A Jewish couple, whose name and address we do not have on hand, met a similar fate. Many more Jews fared no better.</p>
   <p>Instead of taking Levitt to a hospital, the park detectives took him and two Jewish boys, Morris Welner and Isadore Zevin, to the Fillmore Avenue Police Station.</p>
   <p>The Poles brought to the same station were Walter Tarzos, John Auskizski, Edward Makos, and Frank Latorski.</p>
   <p>An officer of the Fillmore Station explained yesterday to a Courier <pb facs="5423972_2_0842.jpg" n="3"/>reporter that he would not be surprised if Poles murdered anyone in the Park, so enraged are they against the Jews.</p>
   <p>Those arrested, ranging in age from 17 to 21, will be arraigned in the Boys Court today.</p>
   <p>Appeals to the Captain of the Park Police to give protection to Jews in Douglas Park will be madentoday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
