<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
            <date when="1919-09-27">September 27, 1919</date>.
            <title level="a">The Trades and the Jewish Labor Movement
            by H. Schneid</title>
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1688</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1688.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
            <date when="1919-09-27">September 27, 1919</date>.
            <title level="a">The Trades and the Jewish Labor Movement
            by H. Schneid</title>
        </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United Jewish Trades is in its second decade of existence. It was organized 18 years ago when the Jewish labor movement was still in the process of birth. At that time, according to the old timers, the Trades Council consisted mainly of delegates from radical clubs, Workmen's Circle branches, the "Bund", and other progressive organizations. The few unions adhering to the council were the tailors and cloakmakers, bakers, and no more. And this "great list" of Unions were finding existence most difficult.</p>
   <p>The Trades Council has had in its 18 years of existence several years of variation. In the years 1906 to 1910 no Council existed. To a great extent it was the depressing effect of the defeat of the 1905 Russian Revolution. It is interesting to note the effect of Russian life upon the local Jewish trade union movement.</p>
   <p>Since 1910, however, the Council has existed continuously. During the past ten <pb facs="5423972_2_1689.jpg" n="2"/> years the Trades Council has done wonders in organizing the Jewish working man, and to organize on radical socialist principles.</p>
   <p>First and most important the Council has 32 local unions, and none but unions represented in its ranks........</p>
   <p>The unions which developed during the past ten years are the Furriers, Mattress Makers, Butchers and Schochtem, Rain Coat Makers and many others.</p>
   <p>The Council, despite its being a pure trade union body, has never lost its interest in general Jewish life, in both its social and economic aspects. It aided in the creation of the weekly Jewish Labor newspaper, "The Jewish Worker's World", and afterwards it aided in the transformation of the paper into a daily. They have participated in such general activities as protests against programs, they have voiced their opinions on general Jewish problems of the day, and so forth.........</p>
   <p>Another talk of the Council is to protest against discrimination of the Jewish workman by Gentile unions. The Gentile workers do not understand the immigrant, they regard him as an alien, and the Council has much to do in this regard.</p><pb facs="5423972_2_1690.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Trades Council has organized the Cleaners and Dryers, the Paper Box Makers, the Junk laborers, the Furriers and many other trades. What is the percentage of Jews in these trades? Among the cleaners and dyers 20%, among the paper box workers 15%, and the junk workers 15% etc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
