<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-06">Apr. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Gentlemen of the North Side</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-06">Apr. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE GENTLEMEN OF THE NORTH SIDE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are many Jews on the North Side of Chicago, wealthy and rich Jews, who seem to have forgotten that the North Side is a part of the City of Chicago, and that the North Side Jews are members of the Chicago Jewish community, although not members in good standing. The gentlemen of the North Side seem to have forgotten that they, too, have some duties and obligations to perform, we mean of course Jewish duties and Jewish obligations. The gentlemen of the North Side must not imagine for one single moment that making money and playing pinochle are the only two objects of life. They must bear in mind that a man is not a money-making machine and not a pinochle hyena. They must not always think of themselves and of their pleasures. Being men of wealth, they must also help to carry the financial burdens of the community, and must from time to time think of the fate and future of their people abroad.</p>
   <p>We have a new Ghetto on the North Side, and a wealthy Ghetto too. Jews who <pb facs="5423972_2_0580.jpg" n="2"/>have been living for years on the West Side have suddenly discovered that they can no longer live in the Ghetto and must move North. They are moving North, they are moving by the score and by the hundreds, and settling on the North Side they free themselves from their Jewish duties and Jewish obligations. Not only do they not pay any attention to the Jewish education of their children, but they get out of touch with Jewish life as well, and the more modern and fashionable among them, even join Reform Temples, although in the heart (sic) of their hearts they hate Reformed Judaism and all that goes with it, but they believe it to be their duty to be fashionable and to be up-to-date. In many cases they become ex-Jews altogether, as soon as they reach the North Side. This is of course altogether ungentlemanly. This is upstart life. Men of good taste, good education, and good breeding, do not do it.</p>
   <p>There must be at least from fifty to sixty thousand Jews on the North Side of Chicago. Unlike the West Side Jews, who are not all well to do, the gentlemen on the North Side are all well to do, or they could not afford to live on the North Side. How many modern Jewish schools are there on the North Side of Chicago? Is there any Jewish cultural center on the North Side of Chicago? To our knowledge there is not <pb facs="5423972_2_0581.jpg" n="3"/>even a Zionist district on the North Side. As far as we are informed, the Zionist district is just now in the stage of formation, thanks to the efforts of Rabbis Langh and Lassen, and Messrs. Phillipson and Mann. If not for their efforts, the North Side of Chicago would to the present day be a Zionist wilderness, and to be sure, many of the Jews on the North Side have Jewish tradition and know something about matters Jewish, and cannot claim that they are not Zionists because they know nothing about it.</p>
   <p>The North Side of Chicago has, as a unit, not contributed one single cent for the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization]. Tonight an attempt will be made to induce a group of North Side Jews to do something for the Keren Hayesod. Whether the attempt will be successful or not is hard to foretell. We dare say that the Jews on the North Side of Chicago can give ten times as much for the Keren Hayesod as can the Jews on the West Side, because the gentlemen of the North Side are all economically settled, are all wealthy or rich, and they could well afford to enrich the Keren Hayesod with one hundred or two hundred thousand dollars, but to be sure they won't do it. If everything goes well tonight, ten or fifteen thousand dollars will be collected from a small group of <pb facs="5423972_2_0582.jpg" n="4"/>people whose heart is on the West Side. The bulk of the North Side Jewry is not interested in the Keren Hayesod, because it is not interested in anything Jewish. It is only interested in good times, in making money, in pinochle, and in pleasures, and all these things combined cannot restore Palestine. Most of the North Side Jews pay a visit to the Almighty once a year, visit the Temple on Yom Kippur, and pay a definite sum to either charity and are through with their Jewish duties, and God knows that the North Side Jews alone could finance twenty new colonies in Palestine and could finance ten up-to-date modern Hebrew schools in their neighborhood, but what is the use talking. They are all busy making money or losing money--most of them can even afford this pleasure and still be wealthy people--they are all enjoying the movies and the pinochle games, joy-rides, parties, etc., and as to their Jewish duties, they wait for the next Yom Kippur. They probably think that since the Almighty Lord's profession is forgiveness, he will forgive them anyhow--a very cheap conception of God.</p>
   <p>Is there nobody on the North Side to stir up those pinochle playing gentlemen and joyriding dames, and to arouse them to their consciousness of their duties as Jews and Jewesses? What do you say Rabbi Langh, and what do you think Rabbi Lassen?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
