<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1906-04-26">April 26, 1906</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1325</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1325.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1906-04-26">April 26, 1906</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Jews, Why Do You Sit Back?</p>
   <p>The terrible San Francisco earthquakes have caused untold misery to twenty-thousand Jewish people who were made homeless, and their belongings destroyed by this terrible experience. This catastrophe has opened the hearts of every one. These must be supplied with immediate food and clothing.</p>
   <p>And what are we Chicago Jews doing? We who best know what it is to suffer and endure. To what extent have we helped those upon whose God's wrath hath fallen and who have been made homeless within a period of five minutes?</p>
   <p>How many people will we help? How many people without clothes will we clothe? We have read in the papers that Germans, Poles, and even Chinese have set a goal for fund raising activities for the stricken areas, but we Jews have not yet stated our position.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1326.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the name of Jewish Honor we implore you to start raising funds for the relief of the unfortunate victims of the Frisco earthquakes.</p>
   <p>Let this Saturday be declared "San Francisco Sabbath" in all synagogues, and let every president of every synagogue be responsible for an appeal to their audiences. Presidents of societies, clubs, and lodges! Unite! Do your share! Chicago Jewry: We who often call upon others for aid of our brothers in other lands, shall we stand aside and see people in our own country suffer from want and deprivation? The eyes of twenty-million Americans are upon us. Let us show the world by doing our share.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
