<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-08-03">Aug. 3rd, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Ostracism</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">The Jewish Advance</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1479</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1479.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-08-03">Aug. 3rd, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">OSTRACISM</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">The Jewish Advance</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We owe a debt of gratitude to such worthy and estimably personages like Hilton, Corbin and others of the genus, who have the courage and honesty to express the prejudice which dwell in the hearts of many against our race. If it were not for such persons, we might become forgetful of what we are, what the world owes to us, and what we owe to the world. We might indeed be rocked into a sweet slumber with the dreams of a Christian civilization, of brotherhood of the human family, of peace, love and harmony, advancement and enlightenment floating before our deluded fancy, and making us forget the real state of affairs in this world. Hilton, Corbin and others, when expressing the sentiments nourished by many others against our race, remind us that we are Jews, that we are still proscribed by the descendants of those generations which have burned our ancestors at the stake, which hunted and persecuted them, because they have been Jews. Such persons as Hilton and Corbin teach us to remember that notwithstanding our endeavor to imitate and outdo our neighbors in the worship of fashion and in the neglect of our religious duties; notwithstanding our professed liberality and hyper-philosophical tendencies; notwithstanding we isolate ourselves from each other and form societies in which we eschew everything <pb facs="5423972_2_1480.jpg" n="2"/>specifically Jewish - we are nothing more or less than Jews.</p>
   <p>But it is a shame to the civilization of our time to have such prejudices and to make such distinctions.</p>
   <p>A shame, is it? Is Mr. Shoddy, who professes to be a true Israelite, is he ashamed to make discriminations against his brother Israelites who have not been born in the same country with him? Is there no ostracism against the Polacks by the Germans; against the Germans by the Alsatians; against the Ashkenazim by the Sephardic Jews? And if we nourish and maintain such prejudices against one another, if in our midst classes and grades are formed entirely distinct and unable to mingle with each other, why should those whom Hilton and Corbin represent, be branded for ostracising the Jews in general?</p>
   <p>One of our French contemporaries remarked a few weeks ago that every Christian who expresses animosity toward the Jews as a class, always makes an exception <pb facs="5423972_2_1481.jpg" n="3"/>of one or more individual Israelites. Therefore, our contemporary said, it would be safe to let the enemies of our race do all they please against us, if only every one of them should pick out his favorite Jew and accord him all the rights of a man. It would soon be found that there would not be Jews enough for all the prejudiced Christians to respect. If the same rule is applied to the Jews, who are prejudiced against each other, it is hard to tell how many Polacks our enlightened German friends would have to treat with respect. Hilton and Corbin Jews can be found in every society, and, before, their Christian brethen are roughly dealt with, they should be given what they deserve.</p>
   <p>The Christian Hiltons and Corbins deserve our gratitude for reminding us that we are Jews, for rousing us from the lethargy in which we are apt to sink by dint of our excessive "enlightenment" or by the pride of riches, or by the pursuit of fashion. They deserve our thanks for showing us our true friends - the friends of humanity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1482.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>For if it were not for them, we would have no occasion to see how the entire press is against Jewish ostracism, and how we lack yet a great deal of liberality in our own midst to become just toward the spirit of the time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
