<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-03-22">March 22, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Nationality</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1517</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1517.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-03-22">March 22, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH NATIONALITY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Publisher of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung:</p>
   <p>The 19th century's blissful cultural progress of greet inventions and discoveries, had a special influence upon the Jewish people. The results of this powerful change are of such significance that the history of nations and states can not disregard it. The common ties which unified the Jewish people ever since their first national suffering up to and including this century, are being loosened through progress and the spirit of humanity.</p>
   <p>The Jew has a keen instinct to take care of his own benefits and a great ability in shaking off the demon as soon as there is no opposition to this tendency. How much of a success there was, is shown plainly in the assimilation of the Jews and various religious sects. The statement of the Chicago Tribune, that the American Jew as well as the Jews of other countries, do not profess any patriotism for their adopted country, is greatly incorrect.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1518.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Both, the Chicago Tribune and the London Saturday Review, point out that the Jew is especially gifted in some of the arts and sciences, but this does not mean that capability can be considered as a characteristic inclination of the race, but is a natural outcome of conditions. It is not surprising that, for instance, the cleverest physicians can be found among the Jews, because students of the Mosaic confession previous to the year of 1848, were not allowed to enter into the pedagogical or legal profession.</p>
   <p>The Jewish student could choose only between the doctor or rabbi. No Jew was a farmer until recently, for they were considered people without a country and for the most part, were regarded and suffered as people with a right for settlement, but forbidden to call mother earth their own.</p>
   <p>The absolute equality of the Jew with believers of other faiths will tend to lessen the apparent differences and then the time may come when the old Jewish prophecy will be fulfilled! "Bajomim hahen jihehe Addanai echot," meaning, (Some day all of us will have one cloak and one God.)</p>
   <p>A.C.Lebell</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1519.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>(Here are two of the many comments, which could be made:)</p>
   <p>1. Disinclination of the Jew for agriculture, even in the countries where they enjoy over a long period of time, all the privileges of the rightful citizen.</p>
   <p>2. The Jews of only six countries regard themselves as nationally attached, this is the case in Germany, France, England, Italy, Denmark, The United States, and possibly in Portugal.</p>
   <p>In East-Europe, Asia and Africa, they consider themselves as a special nation. Their complaint of being regarded a special race is groundless as long as they are proud of the purity of the race. Such distinctions can be wiped out by centuries only, and then not through laws, but through intermarriage. Into this race question, the Jewish religion has mistakingly been drawn, but has nothing whatsoever to do with it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
