<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-27">July 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">On the Community Stage</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II E 2 (Polish)</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-27">July 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE COMMUNITY STAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the Courier printed the news that Poles in South Chicago had framed the "blood accusation" on the Jewish shopkeeper, H. Cohen, 8401 Buffalo Avenue, and that its instigator and seventeen of his friends had been arrested for trying to start a pogrom there against the Jews, Jewish newspapers of New York and Cleveland staged definitely: "It is not difficult to prophesy the outcome of the trail. Judge Gemmil will tell the hooligan Poles that America is not Poland; America will not tolerate such wild, vicious, shameful, and dark lies. Such creatures as Casimer Lota, the instigator, and his seventeen companions are a disgrace to mankind and to America; if it were within his (the judge's) power he would send these 'bandits' out of the country for at least twenty-four hours."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0772.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We refrained from printing our opinion of the trial; first, out of respect to the court, and second, so as not to afford the local Polish leaders, who translate our articles regarding the case, an opportunity to say that we were seeking to influence the court. We relied on the [sense of] righteousness and justice of Judge Gemmil. As a result he saw to it that eighteen Poles were not just arrested; he sentenced them to pay a fine.</p>
   <p>Judge Gemmil did not state his reasons for fining the prisoners. Poles are under the impression that sentence was passed because they gathered en masse on Buffalo Avenue, which action seemed to constitute a threat. Such an action is against the law.</p>
   <p>Judge Gemmil did not take into consideration the "blood accusation". Had he done so he would have followed the advice of Assistant States Attorney Kashin who argued at the trial thus: "This Casimer Lota is a troublemaker, a disturber of the peace, a man who seeks to discredit the honor of a people, to <pb facs="5423972_2_0773.jpg" n="3"/>plant the bitter seeds of hatred, and to instill in the hearts of ignorant Poles the illusion that Jews use Christian blood to bake matzoth for Passover. He deserves, therefore, a sentence of six months in the House of Correction." The attorney also recommended imprisonment for the accomplices. This would serve as a lesson to all who seek to spread the "historical lie" which America must condemn at every opportunity.</p>
   <p>The writer was in court during the proceedings of the trial to record its results for the Courier. On one side were two Jewish young men, Marcus and Laimus Cohen; on the other, Casimer Lota and his accomplices, and before them, the Judge. Marcus and Laimus, Americans in every sense of the word, each described the pathetic portrait of the Diaspora Jew, who is humiliated and insulted, whose life is always in danger; opposite them stood Casimer Lota, a Pole, a murderer, a disgusting creature, who appeared to be even more moronic than his accomplices. Before them sat a Judge, whose task it is to mete out justice, and to prevent people from wrongdoing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0774.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Judge Gemmil, we say this publicly, did not show any great interest in the very essence of the case [the blood accusation]. The sentence, therefore, was much milder than everyone expected. Furthermore, as we learned later, Lota's $100 fine was reduced by half, and Lota paid only $50.</p>
   <p>Under all circumstances Jews are in the Diaspora, not only where Poles are concerned, but also at times where an American Judge is concerned. Like good fellows we cheerfully accepted the Judge's sentence. At any rate, the verdict will still be something of a lesson to the pogromists of South Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
