<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1906-06-20">June 20, 1906</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1906-06-20">June 20, 1906</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Terrors in Biyalistok Continue.</p>
   <p>The news headlines of the past week have been screaming with the outrages upon Jews in Biyalistok, Russia. Jews, once again atrocities are being committed against us. Bodies which were not destroyed by fire bear all the marks of mutilation by bayonets of the Russian government soldiers.</p>
   <p>Jews, we must help our brethren over the seas. Attend our meeting in the rooms of the Hebrew Literary Group and help us form a plan for aiding our fellow Jews. Once again we hear a voice calling. This time from Biyalistok, that great and beautiful city which has produced so many outstanding Jewish scholars, and men and women of outstanding achievement. This is not the cry of dispossessed Jews of former means, but of poor Jews now completely denuded of the bare necessities of life and literally robbed and plundered of their elementary needs of existence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1318.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We ask you, not to help former people of means, but to contribute and make possible the holding together of body and soul of our poor unfortunate brethren. These people to whom the bare necessities were luxuries, are now in dire need of bread. We Jews of America, fortunate in having left that land of persecution, czarist Russia, should do all within our means to lighten their burden.</p>
   <p>Chicago Jews! Tonight you are expected to be at 47 Johnson street at 8 o'clock. There, ways and means of helping these poor unfortunate Jews of Biyalistok will be discussed. Remember! Jews of Biyalistok are calling to you! They will tell you of the atrocities committed. That great and internationally famous Jewish scholar, Epstien, found tied, gagged,and three inch nails through his eyes. The feet of his ten year old son hacked off by a hatchet, and thousands upon thousands of children forced into a jail and shot one at a time. Hundreds lie nude in the streets and the cry is, Bread! Tonight at 8 o'clock. We have only begun to tell you what is happening. Our account of the massacre will make you hair stand up. Come tonight! Realize you own fortunate positions and help the unfortunate in Biyalistok.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
