<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-03-12">Mar. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Task and Aim of the Mothers' League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0073</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0073.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-03-12">Mar. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE TASK AND AIM OF THE MOTHERS' LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Never before has the existence of the Mothers' League been so important. When it was first organized in Chicago, it had to face many important problems.</p>
   <p>The founders of this League discovered that the women of the present social order were not organized or prepared to defend and protect their interests.</p>
   <p>The Jewish woman of the working class spends her life raising children, without having the slightest conception of child training. She is sold to her household, - to the kitchen and pot, - and has not the least possibility of participating in political or social life.</p>
   <p>She is, therefore, lagging behind in organizational activities; even more so than is the case with women of other national groups. This class of Jewish women is very retrogressive in matters of organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0074.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Gentile women are organized in various fields. You can find them in fraternal organizations, in mothers' societies, in auxiliaries, in unions of their husbands, etc. But it is not so with our Jewish women. When you think of the problems which our Jewish women have to face, you can readily see that it is not only a duty, but an absolute necessity that they organize.</p>
   <p>Join the Mothers' League, whose aim is to show the vital necessity of organization and whose main task is the training of women. This League gives lectures intended to acquaint women with all the vital problems they are facing.</p>
   <p>Under present conditions, with the great changes and new discoveries which lighten the tasks of the housewife, it is possible for women to enjoy a freer life and be able to take part in the social and political life of the nation.</p>
   <p>The Mothers' League is trying to make their undertaking a success. Its purpose, <pb facs="5423972_2_0075.jpg" n="3"/>teaching the housewife, depends mostly on the progressiveness and enlightenment of women convinced of the necessity of organization.</p>
   <p>Come to the League, become a member, and help carry on the good work of training women by assisting in the constructive work which is facing the Mothers' League.</p>
   <p>Every working-class woman knows and feels the problem of high rent, for rent is continually rising; she feels the heavy burden of the high cost of living and the hardship of paying bills, such as gas, electricity, laundry, and other things which she cannot do without under present conditions.</p>
   <p>Women of the working class are the ones who suffer the most when there is unemployment. There are a few questions which the women should consider. How many of them take an interest in their problems as workers and citizens? How many take an interest in the question of high rents, high cost of commodities, and unemployment?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0076.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The average working woman feels the hardships caused by unemployment, high rent, and shortage of household necessities. She speaks individually of her grievances, is dissatisfied, criticizes the landlord, the butcher, the baker, and the laundry collector, curses those who take away her last cent, but she does nothing to better her condition, which she could do by becoming an organized worker, a member of the united working class. This is the principal aim of the Mothers' League. It tries to bring all women of the working class into one organization and to enlighten and educate them so that they become powerful. It is worthwhile for all women to join the Mothers' League. They must find time to attend the meeting of the Mothers' League and acquaint themselves with the activities and problems that come up for consideration. The organization, then, will look after the interests of the working-class women, as human beings, as women, and as members of the working class.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
