<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-08">July 8, 1913</date><title level="a">A Common Event</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1192</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1192.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-08">July 8, 1913</date><title level="a">A COMMON EVENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our colleagues are still occupied with the Alpha-Delta-Phi Fraternity which does not want to have any Jews within its ranks. Our colleagues speak about this as if it were something unusual and surprising. They dissect the event thoroughly and reveal the outstanding fact that this treatment was only due to the fact that there are too many Jews in college. We do not deny the truth of this, and yet we ask: what is so surprising about this? They question whether such a thing should happen in America?</p>
   <p>The secret of their surprise is hidden in their protest. They forget that America is a country which can be compared to any other country in the world. The Americans are the same as all other people in other countries. What is possible in other countries, among other nations, is also possible in the United States of America.</p>
   <p>If they would adhere to this adage, they would save themselves many surprises and would not need to be deceived by superficial appearances when meeting with unpleasant phenomena.</p>
   <p>It is true that the American Constitution garuantees equal rights to all men without discrimination because of color, race or creed, and every citizen is <pb facs="5423972_2_1193.jpg" n="2"/>equal before the law. But there is something in the life of a society which is much more powerful than written law. There are inherited views and sentiments which the law cannot uproot. Besides the "written law" there is an "oral law" which is handed down from parents to children and puts a mark on the soul of the present student and the future citizen and law giver. According to the oral law there are differences as to race, color, and creed.</p>
   <p>Both laws affect life. They affect and influence people in their relations to those whom they consider their own, and to those whom they consider remote and strange.</p>
   <p>According to the written law we are all equal, but according to the oral law we are considered as being different and we must never forget this maxim. There probably will come a time when the oral law will agree with the written law. The best thing we can do is to forget about the great honor of belonging to the fraternities which reject us.</p>
   <p>The Jewish nationalistic youth in colleges began to organize Menorah (light) Societies. We do not see why the name Menorah is worse that Alpha Delta Phi. If Jewish youths will be organized in their own societies where they shall be free, they can grow into a great progressive force, which will be able to perform great things for Jewish life. Being surprised cannot help us - only self-activity can.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
