<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-22">May 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's March of Mourning</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_0929</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0929.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-22">May 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S MARCH OF MOURNING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yes, very large was that march of mourning in the streets of Chicago arranged by radical Jewish elements in this city, protesting Polish pogroms. Also very large was the audience in the Auditorium and downtown, where speeches were held against the outrages committed by the Poles and Rumanians.</p>
   <p>It is estimated that thirty or thirty-five thousand persons participated in the march; in the Auditorium there were several shifts of audiences. After some speakers performed, the audience was asked to leave and others who had been waiting outside took their seats.</p>
   <p>The principal speaker in the Auditorium was Dr. I. L. Magness, of New York.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0930.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Among other things, he said:</p>
   <p>"After years of persecutions, the Polish people have again secured freedom and the first thing they did was to baptize this freedom in Jewish blood. Drunk of their new rebirth they cast themselves like wild beasts upon the Jews.</p>
   <p>"Poland cannot justify these pogroms and is, therefore, not entitled to her freedom."</p>
   <p>Dr. Magness read yesterday a list of violences and abuses that Poland heaped upon the Jews in most of its villages and states since the Peace Conference granted and recognized her self-independence.</p>
   <p>"We do not ask," Dr. Magness cried, "but demand of Poland justice, freedom, <pb facs="5423972_2_0931.jpg" n="3"/>and protection for our sisters and brothers who live there! We demand of the Peace Conference, the World Powers, to do likewise for our present unfortunates in Poland!"</p>
   <p>After Dr. Magness, spoke Clarence Darrow, Reverend Brushingham, Rabbi Julius Rapaport, City Prosecuting Attorney Harry Miller, and Rabbi Budzinsky. The last mentioned drew many tears when he rent part of his coat and dramatically tore it (ancient custom of mourning when person dies) for Jewish victims of the pogroms.</p>
   <p>Bishop Falaus said in his address:</p>
   <p>"When I was called upon to pray for the Polish Nation that they might receive their freedom, when we sent our soldiers to fight for the Polish Nation, I did not doubt for a moment that the Poles would establish true freedom." He expressed great indignation against injustices and outrages <pb facs="5423972_2_0932.jpg" n="4"/>committed by Poles against Jews.</p>
   <p>Clarence Darrow stated in his speech that Jews are not solely oppressed in Europe but also here in America.</p>
   <p>"I have seen it myself in the courtroom, where judges pass sentence against the Jew," he said, and ended by stating that Poland must be forced to treat the Jew with justice.</p>
   <p>Harry Miller, in the name of Mayor Thompson, declared his sympathy with Jewish demands to stop Polish outrages, and expressed the hope that the Americans will line up with the Jews in their call for defense.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hyman Cohen was the chairman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_0933.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Similar protest demonstrations were held yesterday in New York and other cities.</p>
   <p>In New York over ten thousand Jewish soldiers marched in the March of Mourning to protest Polish pogroms.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
