<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-09">Mar. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Frank's Condemnation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1100</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1100.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-09">Mar. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">FRANK'S CONDEMNATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A court of criminal jurisdiction in Atlanta, Georgia, has reaffirmed for the second time the death sentence imposed upon Leo Frank, and unless he is granted a pardon by the Governor or the President, the young Jew will be hung on his 30th birthday, the seventh day of Passover.</p>
   <p>Frank's Judaism is no evidence of his innocence. Since long ago, the Jewish people have ceased to be a people of high priests. We are a people like all other peoples, possessing our virtues and faults; our good and bad. For the present day Jew to commit such a crime as the one in which Frank is involved, is not out of the ordinary. All circumstances, however, point to the innocence of the young Jew, not to mention his good reputation in the past.</p>
   <p>Frank is a Jew and the slain girl was a Gentile. He was the employer, and the girl his employee. This is a case, in which a Jewish employer is <pb facs="5423972_2_1101.jpg" n="2"/>accused of murdering a harmless, innocent working girl who attempted to defend her honor, the only possession she had left. It must also be remembered that the accused is more than twice as old as his victim. The facts considered, it is easy to imagine just why the colorful fantasy of the children of the South burst into a mighty explosion which has even engulfed the consciousness of the intelligent circles. Since everybody regards this Jew, who happens to be a boss at that, as the real criminal, no one has paid any attention to others also under suspicion.</p>
   <p>The demonstrations on the streets and in the courthouse, the thunderous ovation given the prosecutor, and the threats against Frank, go only to show how ferocious the entire populace was toward him. The jurymen, who used to intermingle with the enraged masses, were influenced by their prejudiced attitude and by the threats hurled against Frank.</p>
   <p>There was no justice to be found in the tribunal. The judge conducted himself properly, but the trial was beyond the mark so as to win the approval of the prejudiced infuriated masses. The police and detectives had also <pb facs="5423972_2_1102.jpg" n="3"/>trodden on false grounds by permitting themselves, due to the "sacred objective" of convicting Frank, to fabricate evidence wherever such evidence could not be traced.</p>
   <p>The death sentence has been passed. Frank's days are limited. But it is hoped that those who are in a position to exercise justice will diligently weigh all ascertained circumstances, and delay the execution of that death sentence until after a thorough investigation has been made.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
