<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-05">Mar. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Jews in Moving Pictures</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_2_1106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-05">Mar. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">JEWS IN MOVING PICTURES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Universal Moving Picture Company, one of the largest moving picture companies in America, is at present set against the Assistant Police Deputy, M. L. S. Pankhauser, and for this fracas are to be blamed the Jews.</p>
   <p>There is a law which specifies that, if moving pictures which are shown to the public are immoral, repugnant, or depict wild riots, indecent or illegal scenes, or are prone to disturb the peace, let it be the duty of the general superintendent of the police to bar such pictures from the public.</p>
   <p>This law is certainly a good law. Men, women, and children of all classes, of different nationalities and religions, and of diverse inclinations and propensities, attend the moving picture houses. There is much in moving pictures that affect the thought and sentiments of the theatregoers. When <pb facs="5423972_2_1107.jpg" n="2"/>pleasant and tranquil pictures are shown to the public, they have a tendency to make the masses better and more sublime. There is no reason why moving picture producers should have to appeal to the worst and ugliest in human nature. There is no excuse for showing a group of men, women, and children the most repulsive and ugliest platitudes of any sort of man.</p>
   <p>There was a time when so-called actors, in their hunt to earn a few pennies more, would seek, in comic or tragic manner, to expose the peculiarities of a certain class of people. Ridiculing the Irish, Swedes, Jews or other nationalities was to them the stock from which they drew dividends. This had naturally worked detrimentally to those who were ridiculed, and this also impeded the peaceful coalition of the various nationalities.</p>
   <p>In the course of time, however, the various nationalities have put a stop to this. The Irish and other Gentiles were ready to take up arms against this. They would stone such an actor to death. The Jews agitated and protested against these clowns until they were forced to give up their business.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_2_1108.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This sham mockery is now being revived in the moving pictures, and it is no more than natural to begin with the character of a comical Jew, thinking that the "voice of Jacob" need not be feared.</p>
   <p>The Assistant Police Deputy, Pankhauser, does not permit the showing of this picture. As a man of common sense, he deems it logical that the only suitable and real judge, to understand what an insult is to any class of people, is one belonging to the class being ridiculed. It then follows that if the question arises to ban moving pictures which portray Jews in silly roles, Jews should act as censors of such pictures. And if they opine that any character will interfere with the friendly relations among their neighbors, such characters should not be presented. Hence, when the Universal Moving Picture Company wanted to show a comedy in which the Jew plays a despicible role, the result was that the comedy was forbidden a public showing.</p>
   <p>The Universal Moving Picture Company is fighting against this ban, attacking <pb facs="5423972_2_1109.jpg" n="4"/>the Assistant Deputy of Police in large, paid advertisements in newspapers, accusing him of acceding to Jewish obstinacies, while disregarding the sentiments of non-Jews.</p>
   <p>It is needless to say that every right-thinking person should encourage the Assistant Deputy of Police in his position to maintain peace among the various nationalities in this large cosmopolitan city. The Universal Moving Picture Company can produce plenty of comedies without such characters, which puts the Jew to shame and ridicule.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
