<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1919-12-21">Dec. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Italian Chamber of Commerce and the Death of Cleofonte Campanini</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1100</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1100.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1919-12-21">Dec. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE ITALIAN CHAMBER OF COMMERCE AND THE DEATH OF CLEOFONTE CAMPANINI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, at St. Luke's Hospital, Maestro Cleofonte Campanini died. Maestro Campanini was a celebrated interpreter of the Italian music and he deserves all the credit for the Chicago Opera Company becoming in a few years one of the most famous organizations of its kind.</p>
   <p>The death of Maestro Campanini deprives the world of one of the greatest directors of orchestra and of one of the renowned and genuine interpreters of the lyric operas of the past and present generations.</p>
   <p>The Italian Chamber of Commerce of Chicago, at the request of F. Bragno, president; J. Cannini and V. Formusa, vice-presidents; Comm. A. Lagoria, A. Ferrari, Dr. S. Monaco, U. Muggia, S. Gillette, L. Caravetta, trustees, held a special meeting and resolved to close the Chamber of Commerce's offices next Saturday, as a token of respect for the beloved Maestro Campanini, who was one of the greatest personalities of modern Italy.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1101.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Ario Flamma said a few words of eulogy and grief, and concluded by stating that Maestro Campanini, although dead, will always be remembered by the present and future generations for his musical genius, which will place him on the Olympus of the Great.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
