<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-08-30">Aug. 30, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Important Reunion of Italian Socialist Party in Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-08-30">Aug. 30, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">IMPORTANT REUNION OF ITALIAN SOCIALIST PARTY IN CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, the representatives of the various Italian Socialist Branches in Chicago met at the Chicago Commons Hall in order to clear up several important questions. Comrade Molinari presided, with Pellegrini as secretary.</p>
   <p>The first question on the order of the day concerned the Co-operative Publishing Co. After the meeting opened,comrade Lucidi took the floor. He enumerated the advantages the organization would derive from having its own publishing company, and the obstacles still to be surmounted before the Federation decision to print its own paper could be carried out.</p>
   <p>Comrade Taurchini presented an estimate of the sum necessary to initiate the enterprise.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0460.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He thought $700 would be sufficient. Comrade Ruffino felt that it would be inadvisable to rush into something without sufficient financial backing. Others spoke pro ad con. The vote on the question was unanimously in favor of buying the necessary printing equipment. It was also decided to accelerate the drive for funds through the scale of shares.</p>
   <p>We wish to correct a statement made in a previous issue of"La Parola," to the effect that the Cooperative "will be incorporated." The Co-operative has already been incorporated.</p>
   <p>The entertainment committee, composed of Comrades Ruffino, Bragia, Pellici, Vanellini and Morini, proposed that the profit derived from the Socialist picnic to be held Aug.31, at Riverview Park,should be distributed among the branches of the Italian Socialist Federation and " La Parola."</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0461.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Comrade Ruffino then read a letter from the County Committee of the Socialist Party. The letter invited all branches to send delegates to the general meeting and pointed out that branches failing to do so would be excluded from certain benefits. The following delegates were chosen: Gustaferri, Cappetta, Braglia, Pellegrini, Ruffino and Venaglia.</p>
   <p>The meeting was then adjourned.</p>
   <p>Everyone is enthusiastic over the prospects of a bright future for the Italian Workers of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
