<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1909-04-10">April 10, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Italian Lecturer at Hull House</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1909-04-10">April 10, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">ITALIAN LECTURER AT HULL HOUSE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At Hull House, last Monday night, Mr. Edoardo Pecoraro lectured on the far Western states. After an introduction in which he referred to his audience as real Italians, and said that he had a greeting and message from those far West colonist, he went on to say that to compare California with Southern Italy was unjust, and hinted that the stories of His Excellency, the Italian ambassador, Mayor De Plandes, and of Adolph Rossi, publisher, now consul in Denver, to that effect, were not to be entirely depended upon since they traveled in luxury and therefore did not come into direct contact with the actual conditions under which the Italian laborer works. He then went on to say that his knowledge of California was first hand since he had covered the entire state on foot. He spoke of California as being mostly desert, with here and there an oasis, and that the pressing need was for irrigation, over which the government should concern itself. He gave a picture of the Italian Colony at Asti, and of the conditions of the vineyard workers in that locality, which one gathered, were hardly pleasant. He counselled any one who has in mind moving to <pb facs="5425702_1_1461.jpg" n="2"/>California, to reconsider, asserting that California would feel the effects of the San Francisco disaster for another twenty-five years.</p>
   <p>Of Oregon, he was less enthusiastic, referring to the hop-pickers as "Italians of the beer," and the mines of Washington state he defined as the scourge of the working man. He concluded with the statement that the East is preferable to the West.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
