<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1931-06">June 1931</date>, p. 24.
<title level="a">Cady, Janet B., "Signor Giuseppe Sirignano,"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1075</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1075.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1931-06">June 1931</date>, p. 24.
<title level="a">CADY, JANET B., "SIGNOR GIUSEPPE SIRIGNANO,"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the occasion of the celebration of the 10th Anniversary of the St.John Presbyterian Church, which has been the first year in its own building at 2101 W. Harrison St., Signor Giuseppe Sirignano, a member, presented to his church and friends of the church an excellent musical program. The rendition of this program aroused such an enthusiastic and interested response, and so many inquiries about Signor Giuseppe Sirignano that the writer, Mrs. Janet B. Cady, was requested to secure an interview with the director.</p>
   <p>Signor Giuseppe Sirignano was born in the city of Nola, Italy, a city 700 years older than Rome, and a city of a musical genius. Signor Sirignano is the fourth generation of musical Maestros. He states that Italy is full of musicians.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1076.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Said he, "if you upturn a stone in Italy you will find a musician."</p>
   <p>At eight years of age Signor Sirignano started directing a group of boys with instruments made of paper and wood. He received his musical education in Naples under Chev. Paolo Savoia, who is noted for his skill in instrumentation and who was at the time the Director of the Conservatory of Music in Naples.</p>
   <p>He studied harmony under Signor Francesco Panzetta, Director of the Bellini Opera House at Naples.</p>
   <p>After graduating, he was appointed musical director of the foremost municipal band in Italy. Having distinguished himself as a most capable director. In response to an offer from one of America's biggest summer resorts, Sirignano came to America and brought with him the foundation of his present day band.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1077.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In addition to his orchestra work Signor Sirignano is now teaching an orchestra of 48 pieces at the Graham High School.</p>
   <p>There is an attractive quality which Signor Sirignano personifies and that is humanitarianism - the soul of the poet alive to the needs of his fellowmen. It is a well known fact that men who have spent their lives in attaining perfection in music are facing a situation that is very serious.</p>
   <p>There is a choice supply of musicians at hand with no market for the supply.</p>
   <p>The Musicians's Union at 175 W. Washington Blvd., has as its president, Mr. James C. Petrillo. Mr. Petrillo has been instrumental in promoting many movements for the benefit of the members. Signor Sirignano, who is a member of the visitation Committee, explained that the Union pays to the families from $7.00 to as high as $15.00 a week, according to the size and need of the family.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1078.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Within the next week the president, Mr. Petrillo, authorized the withdrawal of $30,000 to be used in giving concerts to our city and county institutions gratis thus covering two purposes, employment for the musicians, and bringing cheer and joy into the hearts of those who are almost forgotten by the outside world.</p>
   <p>Signor Sirignano was most eager to speak of his work, rather than of himself, but the writer wanted to know about his family. He has two sons, one Albert, is the general Musical Director of the Metro Goldwyn Corporation for the entire United States, and the other son, Felix, is Director of the San Antonio Symphony Orchestra at San Antonio, Texas.</p>
   <p>Picked them from his band of eighty or more members, Signor Sirignano brought the following noted musicians who presented the program:</p>
   <p>Thomas D'Onogrio - First Cornet in the Opera,</p>
   <p>Mattew Manna - Second Cornet in the Opera,</p>
   <p>Tony Rizzo - First Violinist for several years in Opera,</p>
   <p>F. Dante - Nephew of Signor Sirignano, Trombonre, several years a musical director <pb facs="5425702_1_1079.jpg" n="5"/>who studied in Naples.</p>
   <p>Gabriel Tose - Clarinet, graduated from Conservatory of Music in Bologna, Italy.</p>
   <p>Von Beulipz, First Violin, graduated in Berlin, Germany.</p>
   <p>Arthur Domminici, First and Second Violinist.</p>
   <p>James Tedeschi - String Bass in Opera</p>
   <p>Victor Wurms, Flutist, Prague, Bohemia</p>
   <p>F. Christenbeck, Drum from Opera.</p>
   <p>A. Tufigno, Cello from Opera.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
