<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-09-13">Sept. 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Co-Operative Publishing House</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0335</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0335.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-09-13">Sept. 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE CO-OPERATIVE PUBLISHING HOUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The local is open. The equipment has been acquired. This week marks the beginning of work on the printing jobs which are already flowing in abundantly. The contract calls for the linotype to be in operation by Sept. 15. If it is possible,the second number will be composed entirely by the Co-operative.</p>
   <p>By working harmoniously and making sacrifices, we have overcome every obstacle. The Co-operative will be a great success. As successful as the sale of shares is at the present time.</p>
   <p>In due time a report will be issued to the shareholders of our co-operative publishing house (The Italian Labor Publishing Co.), giving a detailed account of the tasks accomplished in these last two weeks in order to carry out the order of the Chicago branches of the Italian Federation of the Socialist Party, regarding the immediate establishment of the Co-operative.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0336.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For the present we merely wish to state that the Co-operative is located in a store at 1144 W.Taylor St., in the center of the Italian colony. The concern which is supplying the linotype has promised to have it set up and in operation by Sept. 13, in which case there is a possibility that issue No. 272 of the Parola will be published in our own place.</p>
   <p>The printing presses are already in operation and quite a number of printing orders are waiting to be filled. Comrades of Chicago and the United States should take notice of this fact, and set themselves to the task of procuring work for the Co-operative. Constitutions, books, pamphlets, newspapers, announcements, calling cards, letterheads, and raffle tickets can be printed at prices with which others cannot compete. From near or far, comrades can in this way render much help to our entire enterprise.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
