<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1923-08-04">Aug. 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Reorganization of the Fascists of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0376</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0376.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1923-08-04">Aug. 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE REORGANIZATION OF THE FASCISTS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are informed by the newspaper L'Idea, a weekly, promoter of "Americanism" among Italians, that the Italian Fascist branch of Chicago is reorganizing. The great colonial event took place in the offices of the Italian Chamber of Commerce of Chicago. The place was well chosen!</p>
   <p>The followers of the castor-oil administration are organized in an active group for the purpose of spreading the fascist ideas among our colonies.</p>
   <p>The outstanding members are: Mr. Enrico Barbera, Dr. A. Carfora, Miss Mabel Cesari, Dr. Ugo, M. Galli, Atty. Italo Gallo, Prof. A. Nobili, and Prof. V. Oppedisano.</p>
   <p>Chev. Atty. Mario Lauro was unanimously elected as political secretary.</p>
   <p>The program of the Fascio is vast. It is enough to say that our "civilizers" intend to strengthen the Italian-American friendship through the honest and carnivalesque (sic) activities of the Italians, and the active propaganda in favor of the Fascist Government.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0377.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To spread such propaganda, it is necessary to explain to the public, the means with which the Fascist Government acquired power, and how it intends to consolidate it. It is necessary to inform the Americans of the danger of being compelled to drink a large dose of castor-oil, as they are compelling any one in Italy who does not bow to the wish of Mussolini.</p>
   <p>The public must be informed also, that while in America there exists the freedom of the secret ballot, in Italy one must openly vote the Fascist ballot - or drink a dose of castor-oil - and if one refuses, he is flogged. Only in that way may the friendship of the Americans with the worst element of our colony be strengthened.</p>
   <p>We do not think that the Americans are willing to be in contact with the representative of a government which consists of organized criminals, capable only of arresting the forward march of the working class.</p>
   <p>But we know that we are not entitled to make statements if we cannot prove them. We are ready to prove our statements in the presence of the gentlemen <pb facs="5425702_1_0378.jpg" n="3"/>who have assumed the task of defending the acts of Mussolini and his followers. Almost every night, we hold meetings all over the city in order to unmask Fascism.</p>
   <p>Why don't the gentlemen of the reorganized Fascio contradict us? Do they desire a public debate or one through the newspaper? We are ready for the civil duel with words or with the pen. Refusing to defend their own political idea certainly does not call for respect.</p>
   <p>Whoever has the courage of his convictions must be willing to discuss them with his opponents, he must measure his with the convictions of someone else. Are the Italian Fascist gentlemen of Chicago sure of the goodness of the fascist program? Well then, accept the challenge.</p>
   <p>We Socialists discuss the Fascist program among ourselves because we believe it unjust, barbarous, uncivil, and we consider it a dishonor to our good name, and to the history and tradition of the Italian people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
