<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Vol. 6, No. 3, <date when="1913">1913</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1005</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1005.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Vol. 6, No. 3, <date when="1913">1913</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I. The Chamber supplies Italian exporters with a list of American, particularly Chicago, firms that might buy articles manufactured by said exporters. It also finds agents and representatives for the latter, and furnishes them with information as to the commercial custom, mode of payment, duties, etc. to be obtained in this country.</p>
   <p>II. The Chamber supplies similar information to American exporters desirous of establishing relations with Italy.</p>
   <p>III. The Chamber supplies all members or public institutions or Italian Chambers of Commerce with information as to the reputation and financial standing of any given concern.</p>
   <p>IV. It advises and assists members, on request, in any dispute with the Custom House authorities, railway companies, etc. and settles on a friendly bases or by arbitration any commercial controversy or dispute in which a member of the Chamber is involved.</p>
   <p>V. The Chamber has on exhibition in its offices a collection of samples of Italian products and furnishes visitors with the fullest possible information <pb facs="5425702_1_1006.jpg" n="2"/>on the origin of each article, its prices, the name of the manufacturer and of the American agent, etc. and in any other way open to it. Within the limits of its finances, it spreads the knowledge of Italian products among Americans.</p>
   <p>VI. It publishes in the Bulletin under the heading "Exchange Column" all inquiries for agents and offers to act in that capacity, as well as for commercial addresses, goods, etc.</p>
   <p>VII. Dues: The initiation fee is $10.00, and the annual dues $20.00, payable in two half-yearly payments of $10.00 each.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
