<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1933-08">August 1933</date>,
<title level="a">Columbus Monument in Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1933-08">August 1933</date>,
<title level="a">COLUMBUS MONUMENT IN CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are glad to inform our readers that the Committee for the Columbus Monument, which is to be erected in Grant Park, is working assiduously. Chev. Brioschi has completed the model of the Statue of Columbus which is being sent to Italy to be cast in bronze.</p>
   <p>The sculptor has also completed the model of the four symbolic figures representing: faith, courage, science, and desire for knowledge; which guided and sustained Columbus on his dangerous journey. Those four big figures will adorn the base of the monument together with four medallions representing: the Caravel Santa Maria; the emblem of the City of Genoa; and the profiles of Paolo Taselli, Columbus's teacher and Amerigo Vespucci, Columbus's pupil.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1491.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Judge Francis Borrelli, president of the Committee on July 16 went to St. Paul, Minn., with the Italian Consul General to inspect Chev. Brioschi's work and both were well pleased. The model of the base also is ready to be shipped to Italy to be carved out of Boveno grante.</p>
   <p>On July 20, Judge Borrelli with Hon. P. Colianni, Chev, Brioschi and the Italian Consul, attended a meeting of the South Park Commissioners and after a discussion with the Hon. Igoe, Kelly and others, they had a formal promise that the location of the monument would be in Grant Park, north of the Field Museum at the corner of the Inner Drive, the best spot in the park.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1492.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The commissioners also resolved to approve the changing of the name of Inner Drive to Columbus Drive, and this change will be formally made on the same day of dedication - August 3, 1933 has been designated as Italian Day at the World Exposition.</p>
   <p>The National Broadcasting Company on that day will grant free the use of the radio waves from Rome to Chicago and the Italian Consul expects that His Holiness, the Pope, His Excellency Mussolini and His Excellency Marconi, to broadcast a message to Chicago to the World's Fair Exposition, and to the Italian colony.</p>
   <p>The Knights of Columbus have promised spiritual and financial cooperation. At the dedication honored guest will be: His Excellency, the Cardinal Mundulein; His Eminence Bishop Sheild; General Parker, commander of the Great Lakes Naval Station; the Mayor of Chicago; His Excellency, the Ambassador of Italy, and many prominent Italians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
