<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1908-07-25">July 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Arturo Caroti Arrested</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1908-07-25">July 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">ARTURO CAROTI ARRESTED</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On July 18th, at 9:30 p. m.,while Arturo Caroti was addressing a gathering at the corner of Jefferson and Ewing streets, he was illegally arrested by two policemen of the twenty-first police district.</p>
   <p>However, thanks to the efficiency of the Socialist party's headquarters for Cook County, whose secretary is the excellent G. T. Fraenkel, our comrade was promptly released under bond of $800. In compliance with his request a jury trial, set for July 29th, has been granted to Caroti.</p>
   <p>Although night visitors are not allowed, I was successful in penetrating the underground detention room of the Maxwell street police station, where I interviewed Arturo Caroti. The atmosphere reminded me of a menagerie of wild animals. In a large and poorly-lighted room there are several rows of eight cages each.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0500.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These are real cages, built in cement as hard as granite, with iron bars, much thicker than those which are used for elephants in zoological gardens. The cages are three steps square, and each contains two benches two feet wide and of the same length as the cell. At the farther end a stream of water runs incessantly, roaring at high pressure. The water fulfills two purposes, hygienic and disciplinary. While it removes excrement and noxious smells, it also prevents the inmates from speaking to each other in a low voice.</p>
   <p>Moreover, water is extensively employed in disciplining these jails. Thus in front of every rowof cells there are fire-extinguishers. Their powerful spouts can be used by the jailers to calm any excitement among the inmates.</p>
   <p>I found Comrade Caroti lying at full length on his bench. Perhaps he was dozing and entertaining thoughts of home.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0501.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"How are you?" I inquired. "Ah!" replied Caroti with a Florentine oath. "It is hard!"</p>
   <p>Evidently he was referring to the wood of the bench.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
