<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-08-23">Aug. 23, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Co-Operative Printing Shop</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-08-23">Aug. 23, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE CO-OPERATIVE PRINTING SHOP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Comrades:</p>
   <p>In order to speed up the development of our Federation and to give a solid financial basis to our official organ, Parola Dei Socialisti, we have taken the initiative and are setting up a Co-operative Printing Shop.</p>
   <p>Our reasons for concluding that we need this co-operative are as follows: The Co-operative Print Shop will publish the Parola Dei Socialisti, as pamphlets, and will accept other jobs solicited from outsiders.</p>
   <p>The venture can be capitalized by issuing shares at the rate of $5.00, which shares can be offered for sale to non-members as well as members of the Federation.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0338.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As soon as the profits realized from the Co-operative make it advisable, the shares can be redeemed entirely, and the social patrimony will accrue to the Italian Federation of the Socialist Party, and can be applied towards expansion of the newspaper, distribution of pamphlets, etc.</p>
   <p>The co-operative will be incorporated and begin to function when the capital reaches the sum of $1500.</p>
   <p>The seat of the co-operative will be Chicago and the executive council will be elected by referendum from the members of the Federation.</p>
   <p>These rules, we think, are sufficient to sketch the purpose of the enterprise and the benefits that can be assured when it is in operation.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0339.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We beg of you, therefore, to vigorously interest yourselves and to nominate a committee in your Socialist branch to work for the co-operation of all members and sympathizers. Let us know whether you intend to co-operate with us and to what extent.</p>
   <p>We faithfully await your worthy support.</p>
   <p>Address all requests for imformation to the Italian Editing Co-operation, 111 N. Market St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
