<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1927-06">June, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Activities of Garibaldi Institute</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1927-06">June, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE ACTIVITIES OF GARIBALDI INSTITUTE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If every man should strive to do one-fourth of his duty, human misfortunes would not be numerous. Moral and social evils, physical as well as spiritual, are the result of a lack of energy at the moment when it is most needed. If I accidentally hurt my hand, I must medicate and bandage it to avoid contact with dust or germs, which often cause the worst consequences. The criminal was not born a criminal. He became such because he lacked moral energy. He disregarded the small things and adapted himself to the evil until he lost all conception of right and wrong.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1627.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is necessary to cure human evil. Rivers of ink are used to demonstrate the urgent necessity of doing something for the people. But is anyone moving a finger? Who is making even a small sacrifice to soften the wounds of our many brothers? It is time that we awake, ourselves, and do our duty if we want to be called Christians. He is a gentleman who achieves some good every day in proportion to its possibility.</p>
   <p>This is the duty of all but especially for a Christian. The follower of Christ must carry in his heart the wonderful words of his Divine Master, "Love thy neighbor as thy self."</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1628.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Garibaldi Institute is a part of this duty performed by a few Christians. Still many benefits for the people are derived from the activities of this institute. If other Christians performed their duty in the same way as those who made possible the opening of the Garibaldi Institute, more institutions of the same kind could be erected everywhere. To give to the Italian readers an idea of the activities performed by the Garibaldi Institute in favor of their people, I will quote some accurate data:</p>
   <p>1. Every Sunday, at 11 A. M. and every Thursday at 7:30 P. M. religious culture is given in the St. John's Church annexed to the institute.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1629.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>2. Christian instruction by Sunday School; Biblical class in Italian, Sunday Evening Club.</p>
   <p>3. For the children - kindergarten every morning. In the evening recreation in the hall of the institute.</p>
   <p>4. For boys and young men - gymnasium classes, basketball, baseball, social clubs, athletics, drama, manual training, Wolf Cub, and Boy Scout training.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1630.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>5. For girls and young ladies - gymnasium classes, volley ball, folk dancing, drama, sewing, and Camp Fire Girls training.</p>
   <p>6. For adults - Mother's Club training, drama, English language classes, preparatory and classes for citizenship.</p>
   <p>7. Music - choir, piano, violin and singing lessons.</p>
   <p>8. Health- Diet classes, lectures, publicity, medical and dental services in cooperation with hospitals and clinics.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1631.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>9. Family service - Friendship calls, advice, on family problems, assistance for the needy, emergency service day and night.</p>
   <p>10. Summer activities - Vacation at Camp Gray, Sangatuck, Mich., and for the Boys Scouts at Owassippi, street play, excursions, daily vocation Bible school.</p>
   <p>Is this not a program?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
