<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1894-11-03">Nov. 3-4, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">The Two Parties Contrasted</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0617</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0617.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1894-11-03">Nov. 3-4, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">THE TWO PARTIES CONTRASTED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When American citizens of foreign birth refuse to ally themselves with the Republican Party, they make war upon their own welfare. The Republican Party stands for all that the people fight for in the old world. It is the champion of freedom, progress, order and law. It is the steadfast foe of monarchical class rule.</p>
   <p>It contains the bulk of the intelligence of the nation. That part of the republic in which the Republican Party is the strongest is that part of the republic which is the most prosperous.</p>
   <p>The brightest names in American History during the last forty years are those of men who followed the Republican banner, - Lincoln, Seward, Sumner, Greeley, Grant, Garfield, Blaine, and a host of others.</p>
   <p>Look at the achievements of the Republican Party since it sprang into existence. It saved the republic from disunion and destruction.</p>
   <p>It crushed the mightiest rebellion of modern times.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0618.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It wiped out the foul stain of slavery. It brought the nation back to honest money and specie payments. It has persistently defended the national credit. It has cut down the national debt until that burden is no longer felt.</p>
   <p>It has removed a multitude of war taxes. It has built up American industries. It has opened a thousand new avenues for the employment of labor. It has made every citizen, no matter of what complexion, race, or creed, equal before the law.</p>
   <p>Under Republican rule the United States reached its highest degree of civilization, liberty and prosperity. Under Republican rule the American flag became honored and feared abroad as never before.</p>
   <p>The record of the Democratic Party is directly the reverse. That Party steadily upheld and defended slavery. The leaders of the Southern rebellion were Democratic leaders. It was the Democratic Party that pronounced the war a "failure". It was that Party that attempted to flood the country with worthless and cheap money.</p>
   <p>It is the Democratic Party that has assailed repeatedly the national credit. It is the Democratic Party that has robbed the voter of the ballot by <pb facs="5425702_1_0619.jpg" n="3"/>shotguns and fraud. It is the Democratic Party that is now bent upon tearing down American industries, beggaring workingmen and covering the land with ruin.</p>
   <p>Every traitor to the nation, from Aaron Burr down to Jefferson Davis, has belonged to the Democratic Party. Where the greatest amount of ignorance and lawlessness exists in the United States today, the Democratic Party will be found the strongest.</p>
   <p>The adopted citizens of the republic should not be misled by the noisy, promises and falsehoods of Democratic demagogues and bosses. On every great question that has come before the people for the last two generations, the Democratic Party has been on the wrong side.</p>
   <p>Every great act of legislation that has gone on the statute books of the Nation for the last two generations has been put there through the aid of the Republican Party.</p>
   <p>It is because the Democratic Party is undoing the work of the Republican Party that the country is now in the depths of calamity and want.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0620.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Foreign-born citizens should become thoroughly posted in the history of the Republican and the Democratic Party.</p>
   <p>These citizens are here to found a home and to rear their children. They cannot afford to support a Party which proposes to make such a home impossible and to drive them back to their native land. A Party like the Democratic Party, which for half-a-century was the backbone of slavery, is not a Party from which the escaped victims of foreign tyranny need expect sympathy or help.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
