<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy of Illinois</title>, Vol. IX, No. 1.
<title level="a">Defend Thy Glories</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By Franco D'amico</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1482</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1482.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy of Illinois</title>, Vol. IX, No. 1.
<title level="a">DEFEND THY GLORIES</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By Franco D'Amico</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The inspiring love for the Italian community-at-large which, with our leader Cav. George J. Spatuzza, has assumed the apostolicity of a mission, needs no further illustrations. It has become a truism and it is accepted as a matter of fact by the Italians in Chicago.</p>
   <p>What we wish, however, to convey to our members at the outset of this article, is the idea that that love does not blindly direct him to start a controversy nor to enter into an argument unless there is a specific and important reason for it. The "school boy with a chip on the shoulder" defiant attitude is as alien to him, as there is no trace of pettiness in his character. It is also to be remembered that these actions, which form part of the routine work of the Grand Lodge, have been taken with no intention of deriving from them any personal glory and have been tenaciously conducted until results have been attained.</p>
   <p>It is not amiss to repeat once more therefore, that the Grand Venerable and the Grand Lodge, fully conscious of the responsibilities that weigh on them, have never let an occasion pass by to uphold the Italian name and the Italian <pb facs="5425702_1_1483.jpg" n="2"/>prestige. And this has been done in silence.</p>
   <p>Having of late been informed of the precarious conditions in which was to be found a replica of Columbus flagship - Santa Maria - reported neglected in a lagoon in Jackson Park; attaching great historical and racial significance to the relic which stands as a memento to the discovery of America, the Grand Venerable directed the Grand Recording Secretary, Mr. Paul A. Lonero, to immediately take proper steps to secure the preservation of the caravel.</p>
   <p>We take great pleasure in publishing the letters in which Mr. Lonero addressed Mr. R. Dunham, President of the Park District Board, and the answer that the former received from the latter.</p>
   <p>Mr. Robert Dunham, President</p>
   <p>Park District Board, Administration Building</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>Sir:</p>
   <p>It has been brought to our attention that a replica of Columbus' flagship - Santa Maria - lies neglected in one of the lagoons of Jackson Park, and that <pb facs="5425702_1_1484.jpg" n="3"/>the effects of time are rather noticeable on it.</p>
   <p>While we believe that the report is exaggerated, in as much as it is not conceivable that even a reproduction of a relic of such paramount importance could be left to waste, we respectfully ask of you to use your authority to have the above mentioned replica removed to a more conspicuous place and to provide that it is taken care of at all times if it is possible and if you deem it fit.</p>
   <p>If the task of making such a request has fallen on us because we are the largest organization of Americans of Italian extraction, the request, however, is made in the spirit of civicism which is characteristically American and which bosoms all those principles and ideals meant for the greater glory and prestige of America. With the utmost consideration, we remain, dear president,</p>
   <p>Sincerely</p>
   <p>Paul A. Lonero, Grand Recording</p>
   <p>Secretary.</p>
   <p>As this letter, written on October 29, 1936, was not answered as promptly as Mr. Lonero expected, the Grand Recording Secretary wrote another one on November <pb facs="5425702_1_1485.jpg" n="4"/>15, 1936.</p>
   <p>Mr. Robert Dunham, President</p>
   <p>Park District Board, Administration Building</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>Sir:</p>
   <p>On October 29, we wrote you, in your official capacity, a letter begging of you to give us some information as to the condition of Columbus' caravel lying in a lagoon of Jackson Park. As we have not been favored so far with an acknowledgment from you and as the request was made in behalf of many a Chicagoan, we respectfully ask of you to please oblige us with an answer so that we, in turn, may reply to the many inquiries we have received in regard.</p>
   <p>With the greatest consideration, we remain, sir,</p>
   <p>Yours very truly</p>
   <p>Paul A. Lonero, Grand Recording Secretary.</p>
   <p>On December 30, 1936, Mr. Lonero received the following letter from the Chicago Park District:</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1486.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Mr. Paul A. Lonero</p>
   <p>Grand Recording Secretary</p>
   <p>201 N. Wells Street</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>Dear Mr. Lonero:</p>
   <p>You wrote, under the date of October 29, and November 25, relative to the Santa Maria, the Columbus caravel which is anchored in the Jackson Park Lagoon.</p>
   <p>I have referred your letters to our repair and construction division and they advise me that they have done quite a lot of repair work on the Santa Maria, during the past season.</p>
   <p>This ship is not in any very bad condition and has been kept up fairly well for many years. We had contemplated painting the Santa Maria this year, but were unable to do so because of the discontinuance of a great portion of our W. P. A. painters. However, it is possible that we may be able to take care of the painting next year.</p>
   <p>Trusting that this information will serve your purpose, I am</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1487.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Yours very truly</p>
   <p>Geo. T. Donoghue, General Superintendent.</p>
   <p>We hope that one of these days the "Santa Maria" restored in all its glory shall occupy a very prominent place alongside the statue of the genius who directed her course.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
