<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1922-05-13">May 13, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of Men's Tailors in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The Fifth Convention)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1922-05-13">May 13, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF MEN'S TAILORS IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The Fifth Convention)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The representatives of the young and powerful organization of men's tailors, The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, were reunited in a Convention Monday, May 8. The work of this fifth convention will last for ten days. Grave and urgent problems face the delegates. The future, whether flourishing or not, will depend on the resolution taken.</p>
   <p>In its nine years of existence, the Amalgamated has recorded truly triumphal successes. From stage to stage it has gone forward to the point of becoming a formidable advance-guard in the workers' movement in America. Its successes, aside from the ability of its directors and the spirit of abnegation with which it has inculcated its members, are based on a main principle to which it has constantly recurred in all its acts: the principle of intensive unity and action.</p>
   <p>In the four preceding conventions none dared to present proposals which would to any extent damage this sacred principle, which is the key to the success of all the proletarian organisms, and the structure of the ever-growing organization remained as solid as a granite rock, a safe guarantee of other and major successes.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0257.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In this convention, they said to us, something will emanate which will disturb the serenity of unionistic atmosphere. The electrifying spirit, which in other conventions amalgamated the enthusiasms and intellectual energies of all, at this convention shall be substituted by the spirit of sedition.</p>
   <p>We mean to allude to the proposal which will be made for adhesion to Moscow. Whenever a similar proposal crept in, it produced nothing but discord and confusion in the ranks of the working masses and contentment and jubilation in the camp of the enemy, which knew how to profit to its advantage in its reactionary aims. In remembering this truth, we have no intention of giving advice to, or imposing our views on anyone. We do not belong to that category of subversive "self appointed saviours of the world" who cry, "Moscow is the truth, the just, the infallible, he who does not follow Moscow is a traitor, a counter-revolutionary and with the seal of approval of the Holy Apostolic Inquisition of horrible memory."</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0258.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We do not consider the comrades of the Amalgamated to be so imbecile as to need advice or that of the "Fighting Leaders," for the solution of their problems. We, without meaning any offense to the intelligence of the comrade delegates, make this simple statement of fact which has already been stated by certain leaders of the same Amalgamated, as for example: Poftosky on his return from Europe.</p>
   <p>Whether or not the Moscow proposal is accepted or rejected, one thing leaps into our mind, over and above the immediate or remote ends of the proposers and the opposers of the project. The moment in which a group is formed within the Amalgamated that prefers to win a tactical point, despite the desire of the others and without any regard for what may result, from that instant, the Amalgamated parts from the road of unity for which it has fought, in order to travel the tortuous road of disunity, where 50 % of its energies previously dedicated to the increment and perfectioning of its organisms will be wasted in frictions and diatribes.</p>
   <p>We merely authenticate, not predict. We base our statement on what has happened in France, what is happening in America and what is happening to the International Ladies Garment Workers' Union and the Furriers Union, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0259.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Perhaps it was fatal for the Amalgamated, equally with other advance-guard organizations, to soak itself in the tepid baths, disturbed by the obstinacy of that group that could have used the motive force issuing from the greatest revolution for the general advantage of the world movement of the working class, instead of abusing it in order to expel this last in the mazes of this Bakunistic confusion.</p>
   <p>And so be it! And we hope that it will escape soon, and that the lesson served to replace on the old and good way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
