<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Vol. IV, p.1. <date when="1911-11-05">1911, Nov. 5</date>.
<title level="a">Report of the President</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1028</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1028.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Vol. IV, p.1. <date when="1911-11-05">1911, Nov. 5</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF THE PRESIDENT</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>The time that has lapsed since the last assembly is relatively brief and I have very little to add about the work accomplished by this chamber during 1911.</p>
   <p>The work has continued regularly giving proof that our institution is going through a quiet period at the present time. The modification of the chamber's constitution, which was approved by the chamber has proven very useful to the development of a practical, calm and intensive activity in the chamber. Thus the division of the offices between the secretary of finance and the secretary of the chamber has worked out to the desire of all. Our "bulletin" has been changed from a fortnightly, to a monthly publication.</p>
   <p>This new bulletin's form, which if it is not as elegant as the preceding ones, at least, is superior to the Italian bulletin issued abroad.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1029.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Beginning with this "new year," you will receive a monthly bulletin regularly. Certificates and folders containing identification cards with further additional regulations to the constitution which the committee found necessary to reprint, have been distributed. The propaganda made in Italy, about which I have reported previously, has already given good results. I am happy to announce to you that about ten Italian Chambers of Commerce have joined our institution, and many others will probably follow suit. We also have received the affiliation of the Banco of Napoli, Banco of Roma, and various other Italian firms in the United States.</p>
   <p>The Consul has asked of the Italian Government, an augumented subsidy and is confident that this will be given without any objection. While the chamber is conscientiously fulfilling its duties, it is also interested in the development of the Italian commercial institutions abroad. Thus the Consul gave his support to the Italian Chamber of Commerce's delegates to the International Convention, convoked by the co-sister Italian Chamber of Commerce of Paris, last November; as representatives, delegates were Louis Solari and Dr. Albert Bonaschi, of New York, representing the Italian Chamber of Commerce of New York.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1030.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our chamber was given recently the task of representing the Italian Chamber of Commerce of (Padua) Italy, at the convention of the National Irrigation Congress, held in Chicago. The various commissions worked normally.</p>
   <p>I would like to refer to the new industrial section's aims and scope which are clearly explained in the last issue of the chamber's bulletin. The industrial section has been engaged in a discussion about the best means to effect its own mission with the best results.</p>
   <p>The financial situation of the chamber is very satisfactory, especially if we consider the money spent for the constitution, certificates, etc. The chamber has sustained this year more expenses than the previous years. Following is the list of expenditures:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance of January, 1911</cell>
     <cell>$590.29</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Government subsidy, lira 2,000</cell>
     <cell>380.86</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Members' annual dues</cell>
     <cell>1,093.54</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1031.jpg" n="4"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Admission fees</cell>
     <cell>$ 70.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Printing expenses</cell>
     <cell>642.70</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mostra Campionaria</cell>
     <cell>21.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Miscellaneous</cell>
     <cell>12.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$2,820.39</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Expenses:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Rent and electric light</cell>
     <cell>473.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Postage for the bulletin</cell>
     <cell>561.40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Salaries</cell>
     <cell>1,226.62</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Telephone</cell>
     <cell>56.72</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Certificates, and identification cards</cell>
     <cell>172.25</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Cancellations and miscellaneous</cell>
     <cell>186.21</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>2,676.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance in Cash</cell>
     <cell>$ 144.19</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1032.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>To this amount we must add $380.00 which was remitted by the Minister of Agriculture for the second half of the 1911-1912 subsidy.</p>
   <p>Results of the election: Reelected Cav. Frank Cunio, Frank Bragno, Vincenzo Formusa, John Garibaldi, Joe Malato, Modestino Mastrogiovonni, Alessandrio Mastrovalerio, Giacomo Ozello, and Andrea Russo. On a proposition submitted by Stephen Malato, the assembly unanimously approved a resolution expressing confidence in Mr. John Revere, the police inspector, who was suspended by the service, on the grounds of neglecting his duty.</p>
   <p>Stephen Malato, in the name of the Unione Siciliana, invited the people present to participate in a banquet given by the Unione Siciliana in honor of Wm. Randolph Hearst, who defended the Italian army against the accusations of barbarianism and cruelties. The assembly accepted the invitation and drew up a draft of a circular extending the invitation to those members who were not present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
