<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1921-09-03">Sept. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Volini and Oscar Durante</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1921-09-03">Sept. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">DR. VOLINI AND OSCAR DURANTE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I would like to take to task the Cavalier and Commendatore, Dr. Camillo Volini, who for the long period of twenty-two years was my greatest and most favored friend. Now we are separated through the entire fault of the Royal Italian Consul. That friendship might better be called brotherhood.</p>
   <p>Mr. Volini and I always nurtured great respect and affection for each other--and woe to the person who would have taken the liberty to speak of him disparagingly or unjustly in my presence! What might seem a mere threat is a well-known fact, which can be fully attested by Cav. A. Ferrari, an intimate friend of the above-mentioned Royal Italian Consul. One evening, in the studio of the Cannata brothers, Mr. Ferrari had the nerve to call Dr. Volini a swindler. What then escaped my lips I do not remember, but I can now say that I knew mighty well both Dr. Volini and Cav. Ferrari.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1320.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The latter made no reply, but only gazed at my feet, fearing perhaps that I might introduce him to them.</p>
   <p>Dr. Volini surely has many good qualities, but he also has many faults - some of these detracting from his honesty, or better, from any possible consistency he might have had in politics or religion.</p>
   <p>In fact, Dr. Volini has been in turn Democrat, Republican, Progressive, Independent, Non-Partisan, Monarchical, Socialist, Garibaldinian, Mazzinian, Clerical, Anti-Clerical, Atheist, Believer, etc.</p>
   <p>He lost his common sense when he began to criticize my humble work of protecting our poor countrymen against the many clerical and monarchical rackets.</p>
   <p>Then he sailed into me because I dared to criticize the Italian Consul's patriotic(?) actions. He threatened to break up our friendship unless I <pb facs="5425702_1_1321.jpg" n="3"/>stopped writing to the said Consul and then, turning to a third party, he said these very words "You see, after this poor man [the Consul]has spent $1,000, they also want to chase him out of office. This crazy fellow is picking on me because I am not capable to make him shut up."</p>
   <p>This means that Dr. Volini considers insane all those who do not favor the present capitalistic regime--even if the guilty one should happen to be honest and educated.</p>
   <p>From what I have said, it is evident that the Italian Consul is entirely to blame for the breach between me and Dr. Volini.</p>
   <p>What grieves and disgusts me the most is that my former friend has made peace with Paolo Parisi: This Parisi founded in Chicago the newspaper IL Movimento, which was soon rumored as being a blackmailer. The truth was revealed after the paper had been published for a few weeks when Dr. Volini was asked to contribute two or three hundred dollars toward the recovery of the dying Movimento. The doctor wisely replied that he was sorry, but that he could not afford it. A few more weeks <pb facs="5425702_1_1322.jpg" n="4"/>passed, and Dr. Volini was attacked not only bodily, but also professionally[?], right in the sanctuary of his respectable home.</p>
   <p>Oscar Durante, owner and editor of L'Italia, also blackened and vilified by the Movimento, is now friendly again with the blackmailer--although L'Italia had called Parisi's paper "the Sewer of Chicago."</p>
   <p>Giuseppe Orrico</p>
   <p>807 Garibaldi Place</p>
   <p>Chicago, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
