<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title level="a">A Book That Clamors to be Read</title>," <title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy</title> in America (Monthly),
<date when="1937-06">June 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1370</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1370.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title level="a">A Book That Clamors to be Read</title>," <title>Bulletin Order Sons of of Italy in America</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1937-06">June 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The book titled Personal Reminiscences came to light or, to be more precise, came into life, to bring more light in the history of Italian immigration in America.</p>
   <p>Its author, Prof. Francesco Ventresca, who has been a silent but a powerful factor in moulding such a history, in this autobiography not only has weaved a magnificent tapestry of facts and events of which he was a spectator and participant, but has poured into this work his whole heart and his vast culture, so as to make it one of the outstanding literary creations of the season.</p>
   <p>And the book not only is a classic, as far as the English language <pb facs="5425702_1_1371.jpg" n="2"/>is concerned, but it is also a hymn of thanksgiving to life by a man who has learned through faith and work how to appreciate it and how to use it to his and humanity's best advantage.</p>
   <p>J. G. Fucilla, professor of Romance languages at Northwestern University, in complimenting Professor Ventresca on his wonderful achievement, among other things, wrote: "Among the other admirable traits that you display, I have been struck by your militant idealism and your patriotism. You have demonstrated to a skeptical world that it is possible to be at once a good American citizen and a lover of the land of glorious achievements, the land of your forefathers, Italy.</p>
   <p>For too many young people of Italian extraction, especially in their misguided zeal to become quickly assimilated, have not only deliberately <pb facs="5425702_1_1372.jpg" n="3"/>blotted out the brilliant traditions which belong to them, but what is worse, they have come, in some cases, to nourish a strange and implacable hatred toward them; gaining nothing tangible by such an attitude, they have deprived themselves at the same time of that element that would contribute most to make their cultured life richer and more worthwhile."</p>
   <p>As a scholar, teacher, traveler and gentleman, Prof. Francesco Ventresca has contributed very much to elevate the prestige of the Italians in America, and in recognition of his contribution to the common cause, the Italians in America should read his book which, after all, is their book.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
