<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Avanti</title>,
<date when="1921-08-06">Aug. 6, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Chicago Commons Has No Use for Socialists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Avanti</title>,
<date when="1921-08-06">Aug. 6, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHICAGO COMMONS HAS NO USE FOR SOCIALISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Commons is a bourgeois institution, having as part of its program the education and amusement of the many thousands of Italians who inhabit that district. Every Friday evening, an entertainment is given consisting of an orchestra, singing, dancing, and lectures in Italian.</p>
   <p>Often in the past, socialists have been invited to speak at the Commons: for instance, Valenti, Buttis, Pollacchioli, and others.</p>
   <p>Last Friday, July 29, an Italian member of the Commons' committee asked our juvenile section for a socialist speaker.</p>
   <p>Comrade Culla was asked by telephone and he immediately went to the Commons. There he was surprised to hear that "other speakers had been already engaged." However, through the good offices of another committeeman, a <pb facs="5425702_1_0430.jpg" n="2"/>ten-minute talk was finally granted to our comrade.</p>
   <p>The large Auditorium was crowded with men and women, all eager to hear a socialist speaker. Comrade Culla spoke on Socialism for about twenty minutes and was applauded indiscriminately. Then the president, peeved perhaps at the enthusiasm produced by the talk on Socialism, approached comrade Culla and volunteered the information that the Commons wanted speakers on the labor movement and not on Socialism(!) So! They seem to want conservative orations of every variety, as long as they advise the laborers to submit to their tribulations and to pray their merciful god to throw down from an imaginary paradise some manna for their empty stomachs.</p>
   <p>Workingmen, organize and acquire an education! So that, by means of your strength and class consciousness, you may secure a better life, <pb facs="5425702_1_0431.jpg" n="3"/>Even if a brief one. Remember that divided, we are the rabble - united, we are powerful. The master wolf will always devour the laboring lamb.</p>
   <p>Attend every evening the Local of the Italian Socialist Section, 920 West Grand Avenue.</p>
   <p>[Signed] The Courier</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
