<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-08-08">Aug. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Horrible War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0750</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0750.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-08-08">Aug. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE HORRIBLE WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The war is going on. A terrible event, an armed conflict among all the European people, has already begun.</p>
   <p>The great slaughter, such as never before happened in human history is inevitable.</p>
   <p>The suicidal collision of the Teutons against the Celtic and Slavic people, will stain the old Europe with blood. Four hundred million human beings are trembling and crying in this tragic hour. Mothers and wives, sisters and children, will have their hearts broken and will live in anguish and fear.</p>
   <p>Grief and misery, people massacred and cities destroyed; follies, cruelties and heroisms; all the blind powers of the wicked varnished by Christian pity - will inveigh against humanity with volcanic impetus, to accomplish the infamous work of of devastation and death.</p>
   <p>An why all this?</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0751.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Because an old Emperor, who was born and has lived in blood, wants to [open] his ravenous eyes to the red glare of new carnage. Because another mad and criminal Emperor, worshipping the murderous sword, wants, in God's name to renew the barbarous exploits of his fathers, and to impose-- on the civilized part of Europe --the brutal domination of the Krupp cannons.</p>
   <p>Germany and Austria are the instigators and provokers of the war.</p>
   <p>The assault against Serbia was ordered by the two brigand rulers, in order to force Russia to intervene; and, even though Russia has been very prudent, her mobilization of the Russian army was pretext enough for Germany to hurl its army on French and Russian soil, in violation, also, of the neutrality of smaller independent nations, extraneous to the conflict, such as Belgium, Switzerland, and the Granduchy of Luxemburg.</p>
   <p>Now that war is begun, now that nothing can be done to stop the bloodshed, we have only one desire: that Germany and Austria, the nations responsible for this brutal butchery, should be beaten. Thus their respective peoples, <pb facs="5425702_1_0752.jpg" n="3"/>after the bitter [taste] of defeat, will throw out the monarchies, and largely influenced by the Socialist workers, will organize themselves into democratic republics.</p>
   <p>If such a wish, which is almost pre-visualization, comes true - the great sacrifice of lives shall not have been useless - and the great disaster may turn out to be a good deed, if it accomplishes quickly, that which would otherwise take long years of struggle to gain.</p>
   <p>But if the two Kaisers should come out victorious?</p>
   <p>Then, would begin a new period of military waste, and the future of Europe would be very dark for democracy and socialism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
