<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1929-01">January 1929</date><title level="a">The Italian Consul Chev. Castruccio, Member of Our Organization</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1550</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1550.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1929-01">January 1929</date><title level="a">THE ITALIAN CONSUL CHEV. CASTRUCCIO, MEMBER OF OUR ORGANIZATION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the early afternoon of January 10, 1929, the Italian Consul, Gen. Castruccio, visited the new offices of the Italo-American National Union. He was surprised on finding the records of the society, verified two months ago by the State Examiner, well kept in a neat systematic manner.</p>
   <p>The Consul commented highly upon the growth of membership, and upon the sum of money which the organization had contributed to various charitable and patriotic causes. He made an application for a $1,500 policy.</p>
   <p>The Supreme Council ended the day at the Vesuvio Restaurant where a dinner was given in honor of the Italian Consul. During the course of the dinner the Supreme Council unanimously voted Consul Castruccio Honorary President of the society. Then the Hon. B. P. Barasa spoke upon the betterment and success of the union.</p>
   <p>Prof. J. F. Militello, co-editor of the I. A. N. U. Bulletin; and V. E. Ferrara, assistant cashier of the old established North Avenue Bank, and treasurer of the organization, also spoke upon the future program of the union.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1551.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Vice-President Vitello, whose time and energy have always been devoted to the organization, who has visions of a national order, who strives daily to increase the ranks of the union, in a brilliant oration explained the reason for a greater and stronger organization.</p>
   <p>Telegrams were sent to His Majesty the Kind and His Excellency Mussolini and Ambassador De Martini at Washington.</p>
   <p>The Italian Consul always before the public eye, a man worthy of the office, right, just, ever helpful to the Italian colony, patriotic, is now a regular member of our organization.</p>
   <p>The Italo-American National union is proud to accept such a man within its ranks and his membership opens the new year for us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
