<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1918-07-07">July 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">An Italian Organization to Support the Candidacy of Medill McCormick as Senator</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1918-07-07">July 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AN ITALIAN ORGANIZATION TO SUPPORT THE CANDIDACY OF MEDILL McCORMICK AS SENATOR</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italian-American citizens of Illinois are getting together to give their support to Mr. Medill McCormick, a candidate for United States Senator, on the Republican ticket. A club has just been formed which will soon be incorporated under the state laws of Illinois. Committees have been formed in all the counties of the State of Illinois where Italians live in order to give Mr. McCormick their full support this coming election. Every district will be represented by a committeeman and towards the middle of July a meeting will be held in Springfield, Illinois, to proceed with the selection of a permanent committee.</p>
   <p>Besides thirty electors they have also sent their adherents to the initiated movement and it is certain that the Italians will enthusiastically support Mr. Medill McCormick's candidacy. The temporary officers are as follows: Mr. Joseph N. Nicolai, president and Mr. M. J. Donna, secretary. In the name of the organization a proclamation has been issued by the Italians of this state. The Italians of Illinois are greatly interested in electing a <pb facs="5425702_1_0567.jpg" n="2"/>man who has a clear conception of the present situation, and we urge every Italian to support the candidacy of Honorable Medill McCormick. It was Mr. McCormick who brought a message to us from Italy, and through him we learned the situations that confronted our countrymen at the front. From Mr. McCormick we also learned the needs of our people, and in this way we have had the courage to intensify our efforts in battle for liberty and democracy. That is why we are supporting Honorable Medill McCormick for Senator of the United States and we promise to do as much as possible toward his election.</p>
   <p>(Signers). Mr. Joseph N. Nicolai, Springfield; Paul Perona, Ladd; J. Rancilio, Herrin; Nunzio Di Lorenzo, Joliet; Bob Querio, Collinsville; and M. J. Donna, Braidwood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
