<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1927-04">April, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Approval and Disapproval of Vita Nuova Program</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0363</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0363.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1927-04">April, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">APPROVAL AND DISAPPROVAL OF VITA NUOVA PROGRAM</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is impossible to please everybody because opinions of people are often so diametrically opposed. But if it is impossible it is even immoral, because many opinions are butting against the most elementary rules of justice and common sense.</p>
   <p>Who does not know that many human judgments are subjective and not objective? The Communist sees everything with the lens of Communism, the Socialist with those of Socialism and so on. They are slaves of their own opinions and can not distinguish the good from the evil. They condemn everyone and everything. They and only they, themselves, are the supermen, the infallible judges......</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0364.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program of Vita Nuova is to diffuse culture and state the truth confirming the facts. No human power can force us to deviate from our program. We do not belong to any sect. We are independent and impartial. We praise the right and the good, wherever we see it. We reprint two letters which express approval and disapproval for our program.</p>
   <p>The Rev. P. R. De Carlo,</p>
   <p>Dear Friend:- It is my duty to thank you for the kind words you wrote about me in your esteemed review. We are living in a time where there is danger of illness if we attempt to pass judgment on men and things. Your periodical is worthy of praise because it fulfills its program completely, free from partisan servitude.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0365.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Your articles are inspired by a pure sentiment of Italianism and do not endure the malefic influence by self appointed supermen.</p>
   <p>With my praises and best wishes for more success.</p>
   <p>(Signed) A. N. Gualano.</p>
   <p>Rev. P. R. De Carlo,</p>
   <p>Dear Pastor:- I subscribed to your review, Vita Nuova, believing that your mission was to propagate the faith of God, who met martyrdom for the sake of humanity, and not to defend the thieves, brigands and murderers of the Italian people. I prefer to Fascism and its chief brigand, Mussolini, and the hangman, Victor Emanuel, the Third. Whoever defends such governments is ignorant or a rascal and nothing else. I beg you to stop the delivery of your newspaper to me.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Joe Orrico.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
