<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1920-10-31">October 31, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Recommendations by L'italia</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0673</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0673.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1920-10-31">October 31, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">RECOMMENDATIONS BY L'ITALIA</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>L'Italia wants to make clear to all its readers that, because of the inviolable rights of citizenship, they have the privilege of concurring with the vote in the selection of the political and administrative offices and to take advantage of this privilege without being disloyal. All American citizens of Italian birth, men and women, are asked to go to the polls for the purpose of exercising this right, which is their duty. It is the one opportunity which the citizen has of assuring himself of a good administration.</p>
   <p>Our recommendation is that you vote for the entire Republican Ticket, not only as a duty to the party, but because the Republican candidates from the presidency down to the most humble offices have proved to be faithful and devoted to the public.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0674.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To vote the Republican Ticket you must make a cross (X) in the circle next to Senator Harding's name, that is in the circle which is above the second column of candidates on the ballot, which will be given to you when you go to vote. A simple error would give your vote to the Democrats, who are a menace to the nation, and who have in their program the continuation of the harmful policies of Wilson.</p>
   <p>You are recommended to vote for Francis Borrelli, candidate for Judge of the Municipal Court on the Democratic Ticket; for Charles Cola, Democratic candidate for the House of Representatives from the 19th Ward; and for D. Parriello, Republican candidate for the House of Representatives from the 18th Ward. Borrelli's name is on the small ballot, which you will receive with the larger one. Whatever you political tendency, your duty is to vote for him and other candidates, because they are Italian candidates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
