<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'avanti</title>,
<date when="1919-02">Feb. 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Convention Protesting Liebknecht and Luxemburg Slayings</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0434</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0434.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Avanti</title>,
<date when="1919-02">Feb. 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION PROTESTING LIEBKNECHT AND LUXEMBURG SLAYINGS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On February 3, as announced by the Italian Socialist Section, this convention took place at the Hod Carriers' Hall, to protest against the slayings of Karl Liebknecht and Rosa Luxemburg. It was attended by a large crowd of radical sympathizers of every denomination. Its solemnity, as required by the occasion, was not marred by any incident.</p>
   <p>Our comrade J. La Duca acted as chairman. He opened the convention with an appropriate and impassioned speech, and then gave the floor to comrade L. Bellandi, of the Juvenile Club Karl Marx, who described admirably the lives of the two German comrades, martyrs for a common cause.</p>
   <p>After the chairman had explained the absence of two Americans who had been scheduled to speak, comrade G. Valenti, editor of this newspaper, <pb facs="5425702_1_0435.jpg" n="2"/>emphasized the courage and "loyalty-to-an-ideal" displayed by the two Socialist leaders - who so strenuously fought the Kaiser and the social democratic plutocracy - that they were slaughtered in Berlin within the same hour; one by the police, the other by the rabble.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Molinari followed with a speech which was enthusiastically applauded, particularly, when Dr. Molinari compared the Italian government (after its seizure of Trento and Trieste and its aims on Fiume and Dalmatia), to a greedy boy who is seized with indigestion after gorging himself with food.</p>
   <p>Comrade La Duca closed the convention by recalling the names and actions of political prisoners - including Eugene Debs - from whose magnificent defence he read a passage.</p>
   <p>A collection for the Socialist Party netted $32.10.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
