<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Pei, Mario A., "<title level="a">Italians in America</title>," <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1929-10">Oct. 1929</date>, p. 10.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1375</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1375.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Pei, Mario A., "<title level="a">Italians in America</title>," <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1929-10">Oct. 1929</date>, p. 10.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Director:</p>
   <p>Several days ago one of the accredited newspapers of New York City in one of its leading articles entitled "Columbus and Erickson," contained the following quotation:</p>
   <p>"In America there is a need for a campaign of Italian propaganda for the purpose of acquainting the people with the contribution of Italy to the discovery and development of this great republic. We have not one organization in this country which is in a position to give the American public a clear idea of that which our pioneers have done for this country. From the mass of our people not one voice has succeeded in making itself heard; that history's pages might record these forgotten names - Mazzei, Beltrami, Vigo, Maroncelli, Tonti, Bellini, Foresti, Conte di Cesuola, Brumidi, and a hundred others which have a sacred right to be known to posterity."</p>
   <p>It is precisely to remedy this state of affairs that the Historical Research Society, located in the Woolworth Building, New York City, proposes to publish a book in English entitled Italians in America. The book will narrate to the American public all the epic of Italian emigration to this country, from Columbus <pb facs="5425702_1_1376.jpg" n="2"/>to the present moment; and it will describe minutely, with the support of statistical reports, all the immense contribution brought by Italians to the progress, civilization and development of this, our adopted country. This book, which the Society intends to place in every library, university and high school of this country, will aim to rectify the false impressions of those who, in their ignorance, have not as yet learned to appreciate the worth of our race and the gigantic contribution of the Italians to America. It aims to render justice to our nationality, which for too long a period has been unjustly scorned and underestimated by those who seek favor from the people who are our hosts; and to arouse a justifiable sense of pride of race among the young Italo-Americans who were born and raised in America.</p>
   <p>It is the patriotic duty of the Italo-American press to give its support and cooperation to this noble initiative, from which will result an elevation of prestige and respect for the Italian in America. A campaign launched by the Italo-American press in favor of this plan will serve to make known to the Italians in America the efforts which this organization is making in their favor, and to draw the attention and interest of the readers to this important <pb facs="5425702_1_1377.jpg" n="3"/>and necessary work of propaganda among the American element in order to do justice to the Italian in America. It is for this reason that we address this plea, that you should collaborate in this noble enterprise.</p>
   <p>We enclose a list with the names of the Executive Council, among them being many prominent and influential Americans and Italians in America.</p>
   <p>Should you decide to cooperate in making this work a success by publishing an article in your periodical, we beg you to send us a copy of the issue containing the article.</p>
   <p>With the assurance that you will not fail to take advantage of this opportunity of promoting the prestige of the Italian in America, we thank you in advance, and remain</p>
   <p>Devotedly,</p>
   <p>Historical Research Society,</p>
   <p>(Signed) Mario A. Pei, Editor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
