<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1922-01-28">Jan. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Battistoni in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0412</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0412.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1922-01-28">Jan. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">BATTISTONI IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The comrades of Chicago have had the beautiful opportunity of a two day visit by our dear comrade Battistoni.</p>
   <p>Battistoni is always an immovable, immutable fervent asserter of our principles, one of the dignified leaders of the Italian Socialists in America.</p>
   <p>His presence and his fervent words have infused a new enthusiasm into the local comrades, who respect him much. On his departure, he declared himself happy at having found our local movement solid as a rock, with all the old comrades at their old places on the fighting line. And we, on our part, feel invigorated by his message of <pb facs="5425702_1_0413.jpg" n="2"/>faith and by his promises of solidarity from our conrades in the East.</p>
   <p>The comrades of the ever growing 9th Ward Branch, who had the first opportunity to hear him last Sunday afternoon, admire him the more - and are anxious to see him again; the comrades of the 11th and 17th Ward Branches were likewise impressed.</p>
   <p>"We are and shall remain Socialists," Battistoni said in his lecture at the Chicago Commons, "because we have the responsibility of restoring Socialism, and because those who at different times changed name and tactics - with the aim of doing a better and bigger job than us - not only failed to go ahead of us but failed and failed miserably, falling behind us."</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0414.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the public celebration given by the comrades of the 11th Ward Branch, the words of Battistoni, which followed those of Valenti and Bellandi, will be a spur - and at the same time a comfort - in that they succeeded in convincing us, once again, of the excellence of our methods of fighting and of the justice of our attitude in this last period of extreme aberration.</p>
   <p>He promised to work for our good in Italy, and we promised to do our part here in America. We then wished our comrade bon voyage to Italy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
