<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anderson, Madge, C. P., "<title level="a">What Garibaldi Institute Has Meant to Me</title>," <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly), <date when="1929-10">October 1929</date>, p. 18.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0045</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0045.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anderson, Madge, C. P., "<title level="a">What Garibaldi Institute Has Meant to Me</title>," <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly), <date when="1929-10">October 1929</date>, p. 18.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two very vital experiences have come to me through my contact with the work of Garibaldi Institute.</p>
   <p>First, I have realized as a fact that one finds the only real joy and satisfaction in life from service, and second, that the majority of our foreign neighbors are glad to learn anything that will make for better homes, lives and citizenship.</p>
   <p>When the Italian Christian Institute was carrying on its mission and institutional work at 567 W. Taylor St., a Sunday class of girls of about sixteen years of age, from the Lagrange Presbyterian Church, went in for a short time on Saturday mornings to help in the sewing <pb facs="5425702_1_0046.jpg" n="2"/>classes. My only daughter was one of these. Just on the verge of her eighteenth birthday she passed away. I felt that I should seek in some way to occupy my thoughts to make life worth living, and so found myself wandering to the place she had talked of and to which she had given a small part of her time.</p>
   <p>After feeling around as to where I was most needed and being told by one of the kindergarten teachers that volunteer help was not very successful because it couldn't be depended on, my interest turned to the Woman's Auxiliary which was then new and small. It was an active group, however, and furnished great assistance and inspiration to the institute workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0047.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As that neighborhood changed from a residential district to a factory district, the people moving west, there was a period of unrest and inactivity for the auxiliary. A few held together, however, until a larger field was opened to them at 1200 W. Taylor St., and the first task was to get back the old members and to interest the new members.</p>
   <p>As president of the auxiliary I found ample work to occupy my thoughts and time. We stood ready to back the institute staff in many ways, such as furnishing living quarters, collecting equipment for the institute gymnasium, library, club rooms, kitchen, etc., and raising funds to be used towards our work and neighborhood relief. After five years of this work I began "volunteer service" among the girls of twelve and fourteen years of age, in spite of my lack of encouragement <pb facs="5425702_1_0048.jpg" n="4"/>along those lines a few years before! The management evidently felt I could "be depended on."</p>
   <p>I worked with the girls in their sewing classes and in their scout work, and then with the mothers in their club, calling on them at their homes, and occasionally visiting the other departments, i. e., the kindergarten, church, and Sunday school. Also having seen works of handicraft completed by both boys and girls, and having noticed great changes, for the better, in the character, living and outlook, among the women and children who have attended the institute for some time, I feel that I am in a position to realize what a splendid and far-reaching influence Garibalid Institute has over the individuals who participate in the activities. It is three-fold in its benefit. First, to the people it is giving service, second, to these who serve it, third, to Chicago and the world, by turning out better citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0049.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Anderson, "What Garibaldi Institute ...., "Vita Nuova, October 1919.</p>
   <p>I have real friends among the members of the Mothers' Club. For several years I interested myself in the activities of the Mothers' Club and am thankful that I began at the Italian Christian Institute when I did, for this institute has greatly developed me, and I am sure if I had waited, as so many did and not joined when I did, I would have missed a great joy in life.</p>
   <p>After all, humanity is the same the world over, and, as I said in the beginning, it is a big thing to prove it to oneself.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
