<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Volume IV, <date when="1911">1911</date>, No. 4.
<title level="a">Our New Industrial Section</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1034</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1034.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Volume IV, <date when="1911">1911</date>, No. 4.
<title level="a">OUR NEW INDUSTRIAL SECTION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For some time past, the officers of our organization have observed a growing demand for some convenient, connecting link between manufacturers and others interested in industrial matters in Italy and those in the United States, whereby accurate and reliable information can be supplied relating to industrial matters in general.</p>
   <p>We have observed with satisfaction a steadily increasing desire on the part of manufacturers in one country to secure information relative to products, opportunities, methods, and requirements in another country, with the intention apparently of instituting business connections.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1035.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Inquiries at our office, and those referred to us by other members and by the respective Consular Officers include almost all lines of industrial activity as well as questions relating to patents, and the law governing the securing of patents and other industrial protection.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time, these questions, covering such technical matters and requiring replies from experts, have been very difficult for us to handle. Our only course has been, wherever possible, to secure the assistance of our friends or members who were able to provide the necessary information. One of our members, Mr. C. Barbieri, a consulting mechanical engineer of experience in both countries, has been of great assistance to us in these matters and finally suggested the formation of an industrial section to look after all questions of this kind. This appears to offer a complete solution of the problem and will no doubt make our organization of inestimably greater value to our entire membership.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1036.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In establishing this section, the necessity of securing the best information possible has made it desirable that the work be divided almost equally between persons thoroughly conversant with the products, methods and conditions as they exist in Italy, and others having broad knowledge and experience in relation to conditions in the United States. With this object in view, a mixed committee of seven, four native Italians and three Americans, has therefore been selected to take over the immediate supervision of this section.</p>
   <p>Under the present arrangement, this committee will meet as nearly as possible once each month to consider the industrial interests of Italian importers and the American exporters, and to endeavor to devise means for bringing the various industrial establishments into closer commercial contact. The committee will harmonize the various underlying interests which bear such an important relation to the industrial welfare of each country.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1037.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The committee will also endeavor to get in touch with all available sources of information and act in the capacity of an exchange medium or clearing house of information for the membership of our organization in both countries. It is hoped that our members will co-operate with this committee as much as possible, each member rendering such assistance as he can, especially by providing all available industrial data for its use and verification. In return the committee expects, with such cooperation, to be able to enhance the value of our organization and make it a worthy adjunct to the business of everyone who may be commercially interested in the interchange of industrial products between Italy and America.</p>
   <p>C. Barbieri, M. E., president; S. Spagiari, C. E; N. S. Amstutz, Ch. E; B. U. Hills, M. E., Attorney; W. F. Herzberg. E. E; Davia, Mfgr; G. Mastrovalio, E. E.</p>
   <p>Industrial Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
