<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1933-01">Jan., 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Italo-American National Union Is Now a Legal Reserve Fraternal, Insurance Society</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1544</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1544.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1933-01">Jan., 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE ITALO-AMERICAN NATIONAL UNION IS NOW A LEGAL RESERVE FRATERNAL, INSURANCE SOCIETY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On January 1, 1933, our Society passed from the Assessment Plan to the Legal Reserve Basis. The issuance of the old plan certificates, known as Class A, has been discontinued as of the above date and our Society now issues three new forms of legal reserve rate policies namely, Ordinary Life; Twenty Payment Life; and Old Age Benefit at the age of 70.</p>
   <p>By legal reserve plan it is meant that the rates paid are sufficiently adequate to permit the society to guarantee all benefits under the certificates issued by it, whether at death of the member or surrender of the certificate, by the maintenance of the tabular reserve for the policies on the basis of the American Experience Table of Mortality at 31/2 per cent.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1545.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As stated in our last issue of the Bulletin the non-forfeiture values make the new policies very desirable at the new rates. The beneficial features in these new certificates completely dissipate the old saying that "one must die to beat it" due to the fact that the policy holder, in case of need, may make various arrangements with the Society to meet certain difficulties that may confront him.</p>
   <p>While insurance is primarily purchased to create an estate, unforeseen needs may arise while living, and in that case provisions are made in the policies which allow the member a number of highly protective features.</p>
   <p>The new policies will be written on the several tables provided by the society in the amounts of $100 and in multiples thereof up to $2,000 on all accepted applicants.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1546.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>wives of members and unmarried women may also obtain a policy or policies up to $2,000 except that where a man and wife cannot obtain insurance for a greater amount than that of the husband.</p>
   <p>The new policies provide for guaranteed non-forfeiture values and participate in the divisible surplus of the society. Provision is made also for the payment of the amount of insurance of the certificate to the beneficiary in equal monthly installments for a fixed period of years instead of in a lump sum.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
