<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1910-05-21">May 21, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">National Socialist Congress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1910-05-21">May 21, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">NATIONAL SOCIALIST CONGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Delegates representing seventy thousand Socialists of twenty different nationalities and various races, scattered throughout North America, are now gathered in the Masonic Temple in Chicago. Never before has the Socialist Party of America held so impressive a congress. Never before has so great a number of comrades gathered for the purpose of solving problems so momentous for the laboring masses: the problems of industrial accidents, immigration, proletarian farmers, and others.</p>
   <p>The thorny question of Asiatic immigration was debated on May 16. For the last decade American capitalism has attempted to introduce into the United States thousands of Chinese coolies for the purpose of hindering organization in unions and wage increases among the white laborers. This colossal scabbing project could break any union or strike.</p>
   <p>A commission of experts, comprising some of our most cultured comrades, - such as Wanhope, Berger, and Spargo, - has been studying this problem for the last three years.</p>
   <p>Both in the commission and in the congress two opposing trends are discernible. One is the theory that all men should be absolutely free to go wherever they wish.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0479.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The other, which is supported by the mass of unskilled laborers, is the idea that employers should not be allowed to starve out the masses by importing scabs. Likewise, yellow scabs should not be permitted to replace white union men.</p>
   <p>Two Italian comrades are attending every session of this congress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
