<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-07-24">July 24, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Parade by Court Order</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0149</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0149.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-07-24">July 24, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">PARADE BY COURT ORDER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual parade and picnic of the Italian church of Melrose Park in honor of the Virgin Saint on Mount Carmel took place yesterday and proved to be most orderly. Few arrests were made and no serious disorders occurred. The unusual good order was due to the urgent appeals of Father Petillo, pastor of the church.</p>
   <p>The crowd, numbering about 10,000 persons, was one of the largest which ever attended the festivities. Italians began surging into the village early in the morning. Police were stationed at intervals all along the car lines from the Desplaines River, as many disturbances have formerly occurred before the crowds reached Melrose Park. A dozen special police were added to the regular force of Melrose Park and most of the policemen were stationed along Twenty-fifth Ave., the village limits. Most of the places of amusement were located in the vacant ground in Proviso, which lies across the street.</p>
   <p>All kinds of gambling games from roulette wheels to faro-bank, for the benefit of the sight-seers who were there to see the parade, were in operation in full view of the police, who were powerless to stop them. These games were the most popular forms of amusement and great crowds were gathered around them all day until late in the afternoon, when three deputy sheriffs arrived from <pb facs="5425702_1_0150.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago and stopped their operation.</p>
   <p>The religious ceremonies began at eight o'clock, when the first mass was held, Father Petillo officiating. Following this was another mass at nine o'clock, celebrated by Father Senese of St. Louis. High mass was held at ten o'clock, after which the procession formed in the street, headed by a figure representing the Virgin.</p>
   <p>Before the figure was taken out into the street, it had been decked with paper money which had been contributed by the worshipers, several hundred dollars being pinned on the robes of the Virgin, completely hiding the fabric. Many zealous worshipers had thrown their jewelry at the feet of the figure,and watches and rings were also pinned over the bills.</p>
   <p>The privilege of carrying the figure was auctioned off to the highest bidder, as high as $110 being paid by one Italian for the honor. Following the statue were many women and children, chanting, and bearing large candles.</p>
   <p>The procession wound slowly through the streets, followed by several thousands of worshipers with bared heads. Two bands accompanied the procession. Three hours were consumed in the procession, which finally returned to the church <pb facs="5425702_1_0151.jpg" n="3"/>about three o'clock in the afternoon. Before the figure of the Virgin was taken into the church, it was placed upon the steps for a few minutes where all could see it and another large sum of money was laid at its feet.</p>
   <p>Services were held at intervals during the rest of the afternoon and evening, great crowds moving in and out of the church.</p>
   <p>During the masses in the morning, a number of Italians formed a procession and with a band at its head, marched down First St., and had turned into Nineteenth Ave., when they were stopped by Marshal Evans of the Melrose Park police and turned back; as this was a violation of the sanction which the church had obtained from Judge Healy, which stated that the parade should not march down any street east of Twenty-first Ave.</p>
   <p>In the evening a display of fireworks was given. This closed the ceremonies for the day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
