<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1924-11-01">Nov. 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Political Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0370</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0370.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1924-11-01">Nov. 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the evening of Monday, Oct. 27, in the hall of Italian Cooperative of the West side, a political meeting was held.</p>
   <p>Comrade Bellandi, acting president, opened the meeting and after explaining its purpose, gave the floor to the American comrades, Johnson and Meade, and to the Italian comrade, Buttis.</p>
   <p>The speakers explained the importance of the present electoral campaign and the reason why the Socialist Party has decided to indorse the candidacy of La Follette, because on the program of the Progressive party, accepted by La Follette, are included a good share of the postulates of our minimum program, while the maximum program of our party will remain intact, with all power.</p>
   <p>In this struggle we are pursuing the current of our Socalist International <pb facs="5425702_1_0371.jpg" n="2"/>which is in sympathy with the creation of the Labor Party.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the American Socialists are allied in this struggle, with the Progressists, because with them they are in company with the working class, with all unions of the American Federation, railroad men, miners, tailors, etc.</p>
   <p>Reactionary people are scared by our enthusiasm in this campaign, which will bring about greater success next January, when the Labor Party of America will be organized.</p>
   <p>What we Socialist wish, is a delineation of the class struggle in such a way as to knock down the two big parties of America, which for the last 63 years have deceived the people of this great nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
