<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Il Corriere Italico</title>,
<date when="1937-08-01">Aug. 1, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">For an Italian Day</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1234</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1234.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Il Corriere Italico</title>,
<date when="1937-08-01">Aug. 1, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">FOR AN ITALIAN DAY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4. - This great metropolis, which because of its leadership in commerce and industry and its cultural and artistic development has become one of the principal centers of the world, is celebrating its jubilee this year.</p>
   <p>Many groups, representing various nationalities, have already participated in the great event with superb exhibitions worthy of admiration for the solidarity and discipline displayed.</p>
   <p>Can we Italians be indifferent to the general celebration and lag behind people of other nationalities, who neglect no opportunity to increase their prestige and to show their attachment to this great country?</p>
   <p>We Italians are also part of the cosmopolitan population of Chicago, and now is the time for us to do our duty by participating in this solemn celebration, and by so doing we shall gain recognition.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1235.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Italian community will make its contribution to the Chicago Jubilee on Sunday, September 5, in the Lagoon Theatre, in Grant Park,and that day will be called Italian Day.</p>
   <p>This day of faith, unity, and harmony, which will strengthen the spiritual bonds between our people and people of other nationalities, will be under the high patronage of the mayor of Chicago, the honorable E. J. Kelly, and the Italian consul general, Dr. F. Fontana.</p>
   <p>The large and attractive program will include instrumental and vocal concerts, folk-dances, a Venetian carnival, and lavish display of fireworks.</p>
   <p>A Roman column will be dedicated to the transatlantic flight of the Balbo squadron.</p>
   <p>All together, it will be a demonstration worthy of the occasion and of the Italian name.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1236.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The executive committee which will work for the success of the day and direct the program is as follows: the honorable P. V. Colianni, honorary chairman, Mr. Philip L. D'Andrea, chairman, Attorney G. Spatuzza, vice-chairman, Dr. G. O. Quattrone, director of the Bank of Naples, treasurer, and Mr. V. Ferrara, secretary.</p>
   <p>The Italian community and all the Italian societies will participate, and we are sure that on that day another wonderful page will be added to the history of the Italian colony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
