<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1933-04">April 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Our Supreme President Candidate for Mayor of Melrose Park, Illinois</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0655</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0655.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1933-04">April 1933</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SUPREME PRESIDENT CANDIDATE FOR MAYOR OF MELROSE PARK, ILLINOIS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Surpeme President, Joseph Imburgio, has been recently designated as candidate for mayor of Melrose Park, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Mr. Imburgio, who for the last five years has been trustee of that beautiful village was nominated to the important office by the Civic Welfare Party, which has been the guiding spirit for many years, in the village's civic affairs. Other Italian candidates on the ticket headed by Imburgic are: Sorvillo, for trustee of the town and Carl Montino for trustee of the library. Judge Louis Senese Jr. is a candidate for reelection as police magistrate.</p>
   <p>We print in brief an item published in the weekly Suburban Advertiser of Maywood: "Joseph Imburgio, a financial genius and one of the largest property owners in Melrose Park, has worked hard as trustee for his village. The residents have many things to thank him for. Through his hard work he made it possible to have Lake street paved and secured the street car extension to 25th avenue. He had the measure put through reducing the vehicle tax from <pb facs="5425702_1_0656.jpg" n="2"/>$5 to $2.50, which saved thousands of dollars to the heavily burdened car-owners of the village.</p>
   <p>"Mr. Imburgio is married and is the happy father of two boys, Joseph Jr., 14 years old, and Robert, 9 years old. He has resided in Melrose Park for more than fifteen years.</p>
   <p>"The popular candidate for mayor of Melrose Park, besides being an energetic Supreme President of the Italo-American National Union, is an advisor for the Western Mortgage and Finance Co. He is a member of the Melrose Park Chamber of Commerce, the Oak Park Elks Lodge, the Maywood Real Estate Board, and the American Institute of Appraisers.</p>
   <p>"Knowing the good qualities and aptness of the candidate, who has proven himself a man of action and initiative, we congratulate the Civic Welfare Party for its fortunate choice."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
