<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1920-08-01">August 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Judge Barasa against Prohibition</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0679</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0679.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1920-08-01">August 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">JUDGE BARASA AGAINST PROHIBITION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judge B. Barasa has announced his candidacy for State's Attorney as an independent Republican candidate. In his statement Judge Barasa confirmed the fact that the prohibition league has imposed upon the Republicans through Brundage and Deneen, the responsibility of eliminating his name from the list of candidates supported by the said faction in the coming primary elections.</p>
   <p>"For more than twenty years," declared Judge Barasa, "I have been loyal to the Republican organization, and I am firmly convinced that the best results can only be obtained through organization.</p>
   <p>"About a year ago, I vainly tried to have my candidacy for State's Attorney supported by my organization, but the fanaticism and false prejudices did not permit my election to this high office.</p>
   <p>"I am convinced that I was deprived of the support of the Republican organization because of threats made by the Anti-Saloon League, that I would be <pb facs="5425702_1_0680.jpg" n="2"/>strongly opposed in the Primary Election, because I have never hesitated to declare myself for a law which allows men and women the full right to enjoy their personal liberty, as long as they do not trespass on the rights and privileges of others.</p>
   <p>When an organization like the Anti-Saloon League, short-sighted and intolerant to an extreme, attempts to invade the political fields with appeals and unreasonable prejudices, and with the offer of votes only for a one-sided program, then such an organization becomes a public menace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
