<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1900-06-09">June 9, 1900</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1900-06-09">June 9, 1900</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italian Language.</p>
   <p>Mr. E. Durante</p>
   <p>L'Italia Editor</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>I have been at your office to confer with you but you were not in. A resolution has been placed before the Board of Education to give the Italians privileges like those they have given to other nationalities. To get these privileges we should have every ones cooperation.</p>
   <p>The Board of Education records show that there is a majority of Italians in the Polk, Jones, and Kinzie Street Schools, which give them the right to form classes of their own, to teach the Italian language to anyone who wishes to learn the language.</p>
   <p>I believe that in a cosmopolitan city like Chicago where our schools are supported by means of general taxes, everyone should be treated alike. By that I <pb facs="5425702_1_0098.jpg" n="2"/>mean, if it is alright to teach German in Elementary Schools, it is alright to teach Polish, Swedish or Italian as well. These legal rights apply to everyone and they should be enjoyed by everybody in this country. There is no such thing as special privileges for anyone. The Bohemians, Polish, Swedish, and Norwegians are working hard to get these privileges and I would also like to see the Italians receive these privileges.</p>
   <p>We urge all English-speaking Italians to attend the meeting which is to be held by the Board of Education, June 13, regarding this matter. If possible the Board of Education Committee would like to receive a large number of Italians with ready suggestions on how necessary the teaching of a foreign language is. Form a committee and transmit a copy of your suggestions to the Superintendent of the Board of Education, on important facts of the teaching of the Italian language in the Elementary Schools.</p>
   <p>The Board of Education spends $150,000 to $175,000 yearly for the teaching of the German language in the Elementary Schools of this city. Therefore they <pb facs="5425702_1_0099.jpg" n="3"/>must show some consideration for the Italians and teach their language in the schools where it is needed.</p>
   <p>Sincerely yours</p>
   <p>C. R. Walleck. (A member of the Board of Education Committee)</p>
   <p>Editor's Note:</p>
   <p>Mr. C. R. Walleck, member of the Board of Education Committee, warns the Italians to be powerful and courageous and to fight for their rights. The teaching of their native language is necessary in the Elementary Schools as well as in the High Schools, so that students will not forget their parent's language and will have the advantage of knowing more than one language. Every one in this city is forced to pay taxes, therefore, they should all enjoy equal opportunities. The advantage we are now looking forward to is the teaching of foreign languages. Mr. Walleck also thinks that it is our duty to take advantage of the privileges given us.</p>
   <p>The Board of Education is ready to spend any sum of money for an education, <pb facs="5425702_1_0100.jpg" n="4"/>but only on condition that the people enjoy such an education as the teaching of the foreign language. Mr. Walleck gave us a list of names and addresses to whom to write for such information. They are as follows: Daniel R. Cameron, 73 Lake St. - Mrs. Caroline K. Sherman, 1538 Monroe St. - Bernard F. Rogers, 154 La Salle - Graham H. Harris, Room 1018, 59 Clark St. - Mrs. Isabelle O'Keefe, 4857 Michigan Ave. - C. R. Walleck, 544 Blue Island Ave. and Joseph Stolz, 157 42nd Place.</p>
   <p>June 13, the committee will hold the great mass meeting to decide this important issue, and on this day the different committees should be present. It is necessary that the Italian Workers Societies should hold a meeting tomorrow to nominate a committee to represent the Italians of this city. We should thank each member of the Board of Education Committee individually and give special thanks to Mr. Walleck for his patience in writing to the L'Italia Editor and for the interest they have shown towards the teaching of the Italian language in the Elementary Schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
