<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>
(Monthly), <date when="1929-05">May 1929</date>, p. 25.
<title level="a">"Italians in America"</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0242</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0242.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>
(Monthly), <date when="1929-05">May 1929</date>, p. 25.
<title level="a">"ITALIANS IN AMERICA"</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When, as a young man, Michele Carrozzo left Avellino, his native city, he had in his mind, already accustomed to the hardship of life, a single thought. to struggle and to get ahead.</p>
   <p>He came to Chicago in 1904 with the firm resolution of making a place for himself in the social and economical life of this great country, which for millions of people turns out to be only a mirage of opportunity and wealth.</p>
   <p>At first he was compelled to work as a laborer in the factories. During this period he acquired a knowledge of the customs and the labor system in America.</p>
   <p>Metropolitan life, instead of stunning him, moulded in him a stern character which he used to advance the cause of his countrymen.</p>
   <p>Michele Carrazzo, better known as "Mike", is today thirty-eight years old and is the powerful President and Treasurer of the "Street Sweepers and Cleaners Union, Local 361, of Chicago and Vicinity" with offices at 11 S. La Salle St.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0243.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He is held in high esteem by the thousands of workingmen, in majority Italians, because he knows how to defend their rights.</p>
   <p>Recently he gained a brilliant victory for the street sweepers by winning for them a raise in their salary of $1.20 per day.</p>
   <p>"Mike" is married and is the happy father of a boy. After twenty-five years of life in America, he plans to go back to Italy for a visit to his home town, Avellino.</p>
   <p>Carrozzo raised himself from a laborer to an enviable social position through his own efforts, and owes only to himself his success in the labor union field, a position of leadership which is a credit to his intelligence and energy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
