<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1925-06">June, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Luigi Carnovale, Benefactor of Humanity</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1925-06">June, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">LUIGI CARNOVALE, BENEFACTOR OF HUMANITY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>War is humanity's most terrible calamity! It is a monster which devours anything it meets in its destructive path, sowing over all humanity, desolation, tears, and death.</p>
   <p>Who is not frightened by such a terrible monster? Ask the mother whose son was snatched away and torn to pieces. Ask the wife who was tragically robbed of her husband. Ask the boys and girls who were orphaned in youth, deprived of the smile and love of their parents. Ask the thousands of women and children, who suffered mutilation of arms, legs, ears, and the terrorizing spasms of a slow, merciless, atrocious death.</p>
   <p>War, in reality, is the most terrible of calamities. Anyone, who has human sentiment and love for the human species, must hate and help to destroy such a terrifying spectre.</p>
   <p>We note with joy that those who have the sentiment of love for humanity, raised <pb facs="5425702_1_1390.jpg" n="2"/>their voices condemning war and its promoters, trying to establish harmony and universal peace among all people. For that purpose various societies were organized, such as: "The League of Nations," "The World Court," and "Alliance Negotiations."</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, all these beautiful organizations do not influence the hearts of those who are fomenting war. Dissension between peoples or nations pursue its way undisturbed and often culminates in armed conflict, violent and ruinous. The blood of our brothers has flowed like streams until now, despite the numerous formulas and remedies devised to obtain universal peace. It is necessary, then, to try other means and formulas.</p>
   <p>Luigi Carnovale, a rare genius, dedicated himself to the humanitarian cause and worked out a formula for abolishing war which seems astonishingly good. The basic principle of his formula, the theory proposed by him and treated thoroughly in his pamphlet How America Can Easily And Quickly Prevent Wars Forever, is as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1391.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The elimination of neutrality, only, can quickly and forever stop war. What is the elimination of neutrality? It is 'human solidarity' against neutrality, which is an act of cruel collective egotism which perpetually encourages war. Human solidarity is a 'strong spiritual alliance' of all peoples. It means to establish as a basic principle, that when a controversy which arises between two nations is resolved into a war, every nation not involved must intervene with its army in favor of the oppressed nation, which stands on the side of reason in accordance with the judgment of the people, free of prejudice."</p>
   <p>But somebody might object."Can the people decide and put into execution this human solidarity?" "Certainly," says Mr. Carnovale. "The masses of the people are free and powerful. They are impartial and generous. They can impose their will on the government."</p>
   <p>This is profound truth and worthy of much consideration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
