<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mens Italica</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1928-10">Oct. 1928</date>, pp. 235-236
<title level="a">Pei, A. Mario. "Italian Language in the High Schools"</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mens Italica</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1928-10">Oct. 1928</date>, pp. 235-236
<title level="a">PEI, A. MARIO. "ITALIAN LANGUAGE IN THE HIGH SCHOOLS"</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Through the efforts of Chev. Oscar Durante, editor of the daily newspaper L'Italia, and member of the Board of Education of this city, the Italian language is finally being taught in our high schools. At present, a course of instruction in the Italian language has been instituted at McKinley and Austin high schools.</p>
   <p>It is important that the youth of Italian descent enroll in the courses in large numbers. To reach that goal it is necessary that Italian parents urge their children to use, as second to English, the beautiful language of our ancestors, rather than any other language.</p>
   <p>What are the benefits that the young student can derive from this study?</p>
   <p>In the fiscal year 1921-1922, the commercial exchange between Italy and the United States amounted to $200,000,000. In 1925-1926, the amount was more <pb facs="5425702_1_0084.jpg" n="2"/>than $260,000,000. This shows not only that an active trade exists between the two nations but that this commerce is always increasing.</p>
   <p>Anyone who knows the Italian language can actively share in the benefits derived from this commerce. Of greater importance yet is the domestic commerce in the Italo-American communities of the United States. We do not have any statistical data on this commerce, but, considering that in the United States there are more than four million Italians, many of whom can speak or read only Italian, it is logical to conclude that it is necessary to know the language in order to do any business with the large mass of Italo-Americans. And that reason applies in a special way, to the professional field.</p>
   <p>Moreover, the cultural advantages of our language certainly are equal to those of any other language.</p>
   <p>Italian is the most direct in descent from Latin, and Italian culture is the <pb facs="5425702_1_0085.jpg" n="3"/>direct heir of Roman historical traditions. The influence exerted by Italy upon the history of the world, even after the fall of the Roman Empire, for a long time surpassed that of any other nation.</p>
   <p>Italy's contributions to the world in the field of arts, and scientific discoveries and culture, and inventions, is unsurpassed. The beauty of the Italian language, which is free of hard sounds, and is very easy to pronounce and read, is universally recognized. Therefore, we can affirm, without any doubt, that the student who is interested in culture and the arts should select, above all others, the Italian language. For, besides being the key to a vast and important culture, to a rich fund of literature, and to a school of art and music which is a lasting glory to Italian genius, the Italian language has notable scientific merits and has the distinction of being the simplest, sweetest, and most harmonious of all languages.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0086.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In studying Italian, students of Italian descent would have the opportunity to understand and appreciate the enormous contribution of their race to the civilization of the world. Then they will not feel ashamed, but will be proud of being Italians.</p>
   <p>They will place themselves in a position to impart to their American colleagues the heritage that Italy has and always will have.</p>
   <p>It is only in such a way, and on that basis, that the Americanization of the younger generation can be accomplished.</p>
   <p>Americanization does not mean to forget the best and noblest traditions of our motherland; it means, instead, to jealously retain the best and sanest of the Italian tradition, and at the same time to absorb the best of the life of our adopted motherland.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0087.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Thus, it is necessary for our students to enroll in the courses of Italian. In doing so, they will acquire a knowledge that can be of advantage to them, they will make Italy and the Italians better known to the great American people, and they will strengthen still more the friendship which already binds the two nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
