<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy of Illinois</title>,
Vol. 8 No. 11, <date when="1936">1936</date>.
<title level="a">Nordic Myths</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Franco D'amico</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0757</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0757.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy of Illinois</title>,
Vol. 8 No. 11, <date when="1936">1936</date>.
<title level="a">NORDIC MYTHS</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Franco D'Amico</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>They arose as a joke but managed somehow to be recognized as realities - those Nordic myths.</p>
   <p>Because someone could easily flash a monocle or strut nonchalantly in spats, while others boasted an achromatic skin or crop of blend hair, the Nordic people labled themselves "a superior race" and under false pretenses acquired a false reputation.</p>
   <p>And it so happened that in due course of time, a genius, to be acknowledged as such, had to bear the Nordic trade mark. "Made in the Nord" was the clearence paper that allowed the Nordic intellectual wares to travel unquestioned and reverenced from continent to continent. This, since the "Nordic Superiority Theory" had been advanced and ingeniously advertised; for those geniuses who had been born long before, bespectacled professors with bushy beard and lion's mane like hair, painstakingly traced their origin to some Nordic horde which in unrecorded times settled outside of its primitive habitat.</p>
   <p>Although never thoroughly explained, the world was let to understand that for some mysterious reasons, art, literature, and science had forsaken the sunny <pb facs="5425702_1_0758.jpg" n="2"/>shores of the Mediterranean Sea and migrated to the desolate and bleak lands of the North. May be they had gone there for a bleaching cure. What is sure, however, is that in spite of the strict watch of the austere professor, art, literature, and science, constantly went on a spree and with much gusto deserted the "Nord" for the South in order to enjoy a Summer vacation and acquire a coat of tan.</p>
   <p>But the imposing and elaborate structure erected to screen the emptiness within, lacked the "sine qua non" of its very existence. The foundations could not withstand the mere ripple of a laugh to be flattened and when the people of the South learned to laugh at it, the idol of the North became a myth and merrily relegated to mythology.</p>
   <p>In order to "save their face" the Nordic people clamorously appealed to their oracle - the bespectacled professor - to find a new idol on which to pin their hope to regain the lost prestige, and the oracle trained his eyes to pierce the remote past and in the hazy distance beheld a mirific vision. "Behold" he cried in a trance, "behold your hero, ye sons and daughters of the Northlands." "Behold the precourser to the discovery of America - Leif Erickson." "Although uncertain are his outlines, and his deeds are legendary, I proclaim him the prototype of our race and the discoverer of America, let's <pb facs="5425702_1_0759.jpg" n="3"/>say at the end of the tenth century."</p>
   <p>Even born out of the fervent desire of the worshippers, the worshippers were not however, so blind as to clearly perceive that their idol lacked historical bases upon which to stand. Those bases had to be created also in order to prevent the possibility that the hasty concocted fetich, whose magic power had to restore the lost prestige, should not resolve itself into another Nordic myth. And a group of the most fanatic among the believers intrigued to have their idol sanctified through an official recognition. This happened in America and in the year 1936.</p>
   <p>Blessed ingenuity; as if a proclamation, even by the president, is all that is necessary to create an imaginary hero in juxtaposition to historical being, greatness, and of value of Washington or Lincoln. The news of such a request and that the favor had been granted by the governor of Illinois and the mayor of Chicago, appeared in a lengthy article dedicated to the occasion, in the October 7 issue of the local newspaper Chicago Evening American.</p>
   <p>The Grand Venerable, Cav. George Spatuzza, having been appraised of the fact, charged the office of the Grand Lodge to write to the governor and the mayor to learn the truth in regard. We transcribe herewith the letter that our <pb facs="5425702_1_0760.jpg" n="4"/>Grand Recording Secretary, Mr. Paolo A. Lonero, addressed to the governor. A similar one was addressed to the mayor.</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>October 26, 1936</p>
   <p>Hon. Henry Horner</p>
   <p>Governor, State of Illinois</p>
   <p>Springfield, Illinois</p>
   <p>Your Excellency:</p>
   <p>Many lodges of our Order and numerous societies of Americans of Italian descent have insistently asked us to ascertain the veracity of a statement which appeared in the Chicago Evening American of October 7, and which was credited to your excellency and the mayor of Chicago.</p>
   <p>We are told that an article under the caption "Norwegians to Honor Erickson as the Real Discoverer of America" published by the above mention newspaper, among other things was said that, "Interest in the Leif Erickson celebration was accentuated this week, since official recognition was given it by Governor Horner and Mayor Kelly. With a tribute to the citizens of Norwegian descent, Governor Horner proclaimed October 9, as Leif Erickson Day."</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0761.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The above statement has been regretfully construed by the many inquirers, that your excellency in your official capacity has substantiated and convalidated the strange and fantastic assumption advanced by a local group of Norwegians that America was discovered by Leif Erickson instead of Columbus.</p>
   <p>Believing that the statement is untrue, or at its best, it is a distorted interpretation of our thought in regard, inasmuch as incontrovertible, historical facts cannot be changed or denied to suit chauvinistic idealogies, we respectfully ask your excellency to give us your version of the truth in the matter in order to assuage the painful impression created among the Italian constituency.</p>
   <p>With the utmost consideration for your excellency, we remain</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours</p>
   <p>Paolo A. Loreno</p>
   <p>Grand Recording Secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0762.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Mayor Kelly answered with the following letter:</p>
   <p>October 23, 1936.</p>
   <p>Mr. Paolo A. Lonero</p>
   <p>Recording Secretary, Grand Lodge of Illinois</p>
   <p>Order Sons of Italy</p>
   <p>201 N. Wells Street</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>Dear Mr. Lonero:</p>
   <p>This will acknowledge your letter of October 26, in reference to the recent Leif Erickson celebration conducted by Chicago citizens of Norwegian descent. I am very glad to give you the facts in connection with the matter. The Norwegian National League, through its president Mr. Erwin Larsen, on September 23, requested that I issue a proclamation to set aside the week of October 5, to 11, as Leif Erickson Week. Since this organization is a reputable one and is composed of citizens of Chicago, I complied with their request by issuing a proclamation - a copy of which is attached, for your information.</p>
   <p>You will note that no reference is made in the proclamation to the discovery of America, also I have before me, a copy of the Chicago American clipping of <pb facs="5425702_1_0763.jpg" n="7"/>October 7, referred to in your letter, and I find that the only paragraph which refers to my proclamation reads as follows: "Interest in the Leif Erickson celebration was accentuated this week, since official recognition has been given it by Governor Horner and Mayor Kelly."</p>
   <p>The official recognition referred to was simply the attached proclamation. Needless to say, I am always happy, as Mayor of Chicago to recognize the courage and enterprise of any person regardless of nationality.</p>
   <p>Your organization will understand, I feel sure, that as Mayor of Chicago I am given no official authority to enter into any controversy pertaining to historical claims or to act as a judge in such a matter.</p>
   <p>Please assure the members of your splendid organization that I have only the friendliest of feelings toward your group and the Italian people in general - a race which I am proud to have the privilege of honoring at any time, for their valor and outstanding achievements,</p>
   <p>With kindest regards and very best wishes, I am,</p>
   <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
   <p>Edward J. Kelly, Mayor.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0764.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The secretary to the governor answered with the following letter:</p>
   <p>Mr. Paolo A. Lonero</p>
   <p>Grand Recording Secretary</p>
   <p>Order Sons of Italy</p>
   <p>201 N. Wells St. Suite 702</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>Dear Mr. Lonero</p>
   <p>This is to acknowledge your letter of October 26, to Governor Horner, which has been received in his abscence from Springfield. As you know, the governor is in Chicago at the present time, winding up his campaign but I am enclosing for your information, a copy of the proclamation issued by the governor, designating October 9, as Leif Erickson Day. I shall call your letter to the governor's attention upon his return to Springfield.</p>
   <p>Very truly yours</p>
   <p>Arthur P. O'Brien</p>
   <p>Secretary to the Governor.</p>
   <p>Both the mayor and the secretary enclosed in their respective letters, copies of the proclamations from which, clearly appears that neither the governor <pb facs="5425702_1_0765.jpg" n="9"/>nor the mayor make any allusion that Leif Erickson was the discoverer of America. The proclamations are too lengthy to be reproduced but they are extant in the office of the Grand Lodge to be read by anybody who cares to.</p>
   <p>To our brothers in "The Melting Pot" the Norwegians, we put squarely this question: "Conceding hypothetically that Leif Erickson at the end of the tenth century, his nutshell buffeted by a tempest, scrambled for life upon the coast of America, what did the world gain by his accidental discovery, if there was any?" None whatsoever! It took Christopher Columbus to triumphantly reveal the existence of a new continent to the people of the earth and the existence of a said continent has been known only since 1492, and never before.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
