<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title level="a">St. John Vocation School Program</title>", <title>Vita Nuova</title>, (Monthly),
<date when="1930-08">July-August 1930</date>, p. 23.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1408</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1408.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title level="a">St. John Vocation School Program</title>", <title>Vita Nuova</title>, (Monthly),
<date when="1930-08">July-August 1930</date>, p. 23.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Thursday evening, July 24th, 1930, the St. John Vocation School held its closing program in the new basement of the Church. The sixty-five members present marched in, to the stirring strains of "Stand Up, Stand Up for Jesus", and took their places. After the invocation by the Reverend P. R. DeCarlo, the entire school repeated its motto, "Let my words and my meditations be acceptable in Thy sight, O Lord, my Strength and my Redeemer." The next half hour consisted of Worship Service by the Beginners and Primary Departments, and a program of songs and rhythmic orchestra selections and a memory contest of Bible Verses by the Primary children. The next part of the program was devoted to the Junior and Intermediate boys and girls, who sang a group of four songs and gave some memory work. After introducing Miss Marnise Nickerbocker, Director of Garibaldi Institute, 1208 W. Taylor St., who gave a short talk, the Rev. De Carlo gave an address in Italian and one in English, and then he presented each member with a tooth-brush, a means of helping to promote good health. After the offering salutes were given to the American and Christian flags and the program closed with the Mizpah Benediction, "The Lord watch between me and thee, while we are <pb facs="5425702_1_1409.jpg" n="2"/>absent from one another".</p>
   <p>There was a display of handiwork by the children, which the parents and friends enjoyed.</p>
   <p>The offerings of the four weeks and Thursday evening amounted to $15.50. Of this sum $5.00 has been given to the Presbyterian Hospital.</p>
   <p>The staff of the school included the Reverend P. R. DeCarlo, Pastor; Reverend F. A. Walker, Superintendent; Mrs. F. A.Walker, Primary Director; Miss Lucy Fanello, Assistant; Marie Matarrese and Anna Cucciardi, Beginners' Teachers; Miss Helen Bailey, Musical Director; Miss Susan Jenks, Director of Junior and Intermediate Girls with Mrs. DeCarlo, Mrs. O. C. Belcher and Miss Ruth Chittick, Assistants; Mr. F. A. Walker, Director of Junior and Intermediate Boys, with Mr. Phillip Sorce, Mr. Vincent Console, and Mr. Pacifico C'Anselmo, Assistants.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1410.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>CHURCH SCHOOL PROGRAM.</p>
   <p>The Reverend P. R. DeCarlo royally entertained the St. John Presbyterian Vocation School Staff to a six course Italian dinner at Amato's Restaurant, 914 S. Halsted Street, Friday noon, July 25th. The fifteen people present had a time partaking of Italian food and hospitality, such as no one can offer like the esteemed Pastor, Pasquale Ricciardi De Carlo.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
