<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1901-08-16">Aug. 16, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Sicilians Celebrate the Assumption of the Virgin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-V.B"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>V B</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1901-08-16">Aug. 16, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">SICILIANS CELEBRATE THE ASSUMPTION OF THE VIRGIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Altars to the madonna are erected in the open street and hundreds worship at brilliantly lighted shrines.</p>
   <p>The Sicilians of the Nineteenth Ward celebrated the assumption of the virgin last night. On Polk St. near Halsted, the largest of the altars was built. Five large arches were erected, covered with green branches and vines, and Sicilian and American flags were swung above the arches. At the end of the bower-like avenue was the altar in a high, broad inclosure. Tiers of lighted candles flickered and flared in front of the image of the virgin, which had been brought from Sicily and set up in the open air according to the old custom.</p>
   <p>Two blocks of Ewing St. were hung with lanterns suspended above the sidewalks on green-covered lines; while on Jefferson St., the green arches were so close together that they made almost a perfect bower.</p>
   <p>There are at least 1,100 Sicilians in Chicago, and with few exceptions, they live in the Nineteenth Ward. They were all out, wearing the national costumes and full of the spirit of the holiday. The Italian headdresses and scarfs, <pb facs="5425702_1_0153.jpg" n="2"/>and the soft Italian voices made this religious ceremony as foreign in appearance as though it had been celebrated in Sicily itself. Tonight and tomorrow night the candles will be lit again before the altars, and the crowds will fill the streets. On Sunday there will be a parade.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
