<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Il Bollettino Sociale</title>,
<date when="1929-08-15">Aug. 15, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Plaudite Omnes (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Il Bollettino Sociale</title>,
<date when="1929-08-15">Aug. 15, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">PLAUDITE OMNES (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Honorable mention is due to the splendid efforts of Jimmy Petrillo, the indefatigable and capable pilot of the Chicago Federation of Musicians' fateful ship.</p>
   <p>To wit, Mr. Petrillo has lately promoted the organization of thirty free public concerts to be given by a one hundred piece band, and the expenses will be defrayed by private contributions.</p>
   <p>It is a fine step on the right path of progress, a movement toward the rehabilitation of real musical art, so much neglected and misrepresented of late with the advent of the charlatanic era of jazz.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, it will add somewhat to the depleted financial resources of the real musical profession. The enthusiastic response of the general public in contributing to this worthy cause and to the Chicago World's Fair Band contest fund and the tremendous attendance at the late concerts held at the Daily News Plaza prove convincingly that the mass of the people are in favor of real music and not of the savage- <pb facs="5425702_1_1084.jpg" n="2"/>like, rhythmic, tasteless, monotonous, lascivious cacophony known as jazz.</p>
   <p>It is about time for a Christ to appear to lash the unscrupulous and sordid money changers from the temple of art! For if art reveals the character of a race, jazz would certainly indicate an advanced stage of degeneracy among civilized people. Good for you, Mr. Petrillo!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
