<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1924-04">April, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Modus Vivendi of the New Financial Program</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1924-04">April, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">MODUS VIVENDI OF THE NEW FINANCIAL PROGRAM</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new plan of financing our association is based on practical application and in a way that will not cause any financial difficulty to the brethren.</p>
   <p>This plan consists of assessing every member for a loan of $20 to be paid in at once, or in twenty monthly payments of $1 each, or in any other way as long as the payment is done within twenty months.</p>
   <p>When the loan of $20 is completed each member will receive a certificate for this amount, which will be attached to the insurance policy the value of which, consequently, will be increased by $20, and for which the Executive Council will pay the annual interest of 3 per cent rate.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1566.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The loan, so made, will be paid after five years from the date of the issuance of the certificate. In case of the holder's death the amount will be paid, with the insurance premium to his or her heirs.</p>
   <p>This assessment was planned to raise the necessary guaranty funds requested by the state of Illinois. The institution of this reserve fund will affirm the economic soundness of our association, which will advance and ascend to a higher plane, after twenty-eight years of efficient and patriotic existence in which it has participated in many activities for Italians in America and in the mother country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
