<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1937-02">February 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Directory of Italian-Americans in Commerce and Professions</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1937-02">February 1937</date>.
<title level="a">DIRECTORY OF ITALIAN-AMERICANS IN COMMERCE AND PROFESSIONS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Continental Press of Chicago will in the near future publish a complete commercial guide in order to unify and stimulate the business of the Italian people throughout the United States, Canada, and Italy. This directory will demonstrate the tremendous progress made in this country by the people who bear Italian cognomens.</p>
   <p>Every Italian, big or small, must be proud to belong to this race. The many Italian concerns are scattered and the number of them appears limited, but this publication will show, prominently, the great number of our people successfully engaged in business, commerce and professions.</p>
   <p>In the first edition will be listed over 25,000 names including about 2,000 firms in Italy which are organized to export to the United States and Canada. These names were sent and recommended to the Continental Press by the Istituto Nazionale Fascista Per Il Commercio Estero of Rome.</p>
   <p>The publication received much encouragement from many Italian authorities of Rome and America and from the better business people, banks, professionals, <pb facs="5425702_1_1349.jpg" n="2"/>etc., of the United States and Canada.</p>
   <p>The majority of the best and largest Italian concerns have reserved space in the directory and many more of them are considering advertising in it. The directory will have a large circulation in the United States, Canada, and Italy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
