<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1933-05">May 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Our Supreme President Elected Mayor of Melrose Park</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1933-05">May 1933</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SUPREME PRESIDENT ELECTED MAYOR OF MELROSE PARK</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On April 18th, Melrose Park, by the greatest majority of votes ever recorded in the history of the elections of the village, elected Joseph Imburgio to the presidency of its Board of Trustees.</p>
   <p>This registers the first election in Cook County of an Italo-American to the presidency of any sizable community and the victory becomes a more signal one because Mr. Imburgio's wonderful achievement was not due to a preponderance of an Italo-American voting strength but to the popularity of the candidate himself, whose amiable nature, sense of fairness and justice for everybody, efficient record as public official, success in business, and a sterling character have won for him the confidence, esteem, and admiration of the citizenry of his town and of all those who have been privileged to associate with him, or who even have a speaking acquaintance with him.</p>
   <p>Mr. Imburgio is a red-blooded, two-fisted, self-made man. He is the son of Italian immigrant parents; he knows people and their needs; he loves Melrose Park and his constituents. He will discharge his duties with honor and <pb facs="5425702_1_0658.jpg" n="2"/>distinction to himself, and satisfaction to the people. He will prove the greatest single factor Melrose Park has ever had and the community will be exceedingly glad to return him to office indefinitely. Joe will not have to he be remained that the people elected him. He will know how to serve them. Joe comes from the school of experience, from that Italo-American Stock that is daily enriching America with valuable material for public office. With an unsurpassed historical heritage, combining the innate political acumen of their forbears, the Romans, inured to the pioneering hardships of the latest arrivals to these shores; with American education and experience, which has given them a thorough knowledge of American institutions, these young Italo-Americans like Joe, will cleave their way into American politics and as their kinred have done thus far, will give an honorable account of themselves. They will make America feel proud of these new children.</p>
   <p>Imburgio's victory is a victory of the Italians in America; it should serve as a great incentive for good to the young, Italo-Americans in Chicago. The names of other Americans of Italian extraction, who have served and are now serving creditably in public offices all over the United States, should spur them on to greater achievements.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0659.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Young Italo-Americans, who now fill the public schools and colleges, should emblazon the ideal of dedicating the best that is in them to the future greatness of America whose needs they should serve with honor to themselves, their families, and the land of their origin of which they should be justly and legitimately proud.</p>
   <p>We of the I. A. N. U. are extremely proud, that our Supreme President has been elected president of Melrose Park.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
