<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1915-09-28">Sept. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">An Announcement to All Italian Tailors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0293</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0293.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1915-09-28">Sept. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">AN ANNOUNCEMENT TO ALL ITALIAN TAILORS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America has issued the following proclamation to the Italian tailors:</p>
   <p>"Italian tailors of Chicago, our condition in factories have become unbearable. We work many hours and wages are very low. The system basis of fines, black book, contract work, and dismissals by caprice, has slowly transformed the useful and productive category of tailors into a class of slaves. This cannot and must not continue.</p>
   <p>"Fifteen thousand tailors have organized committees and have sent representatives to each employer asking for decent work and for more reasonable wages.</p>
   <p>"If the employers do not give their answer before next Monday there will be a general strike among tailors to fight until victory is theirs.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0294.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Never has such a strike occurred in the history of Chicago.</p>
   <p>"We shall win!</p>
   <p>"Italian tailors! We should not follow in the footsteps of other nationalities. We should prove that existing conditions must be improved in the interest of the public and of the Italian workers.</p>
   <p>"Sunday, September 26, 1915, at 10:00 A. M., a large mass meeting of the Italian Tailors' Union will take place at Bowen Hall, Hull House, on Polk and Halsted streets, regarding this general strike.</p>
   <p>"The president of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, Mr. Sidney Hillman, and Miss Bessie Abramovitz, representative of the women tailors, will be present at this meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0295.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The president of the Joint Board of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, Anziuno Moreimpietro, will preside. Italian speakers are Mr. Emilio Grandinetti and Mr. Joseph Bertini.</p>
   <p>"Be sure to attend this meeting for the interest of your job and the raising of wages. Do not fail to attend this meeting."</p>
   <p>Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
