<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'avanti</title>,
<date when="1920-05-08">May 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Fifteenth Congress of the International Ladies' Garment Workers Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Avanti</title>,
<date when="1920-05-08">May 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FIFTEENTH CONGRESS OF THE INTERNATIONAL LADIES' GARMENT WORKERS UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This Congress convened on May 3rd, at the Carmen's Hall.</p>
   <p>Over 6000 unionists paraded, with music, flags, and flower wreaths offered by several locals of Chicago. At the Hall, they were welcomed by the City Attorney, who represented the mayor.</p>
   <p>Vibrant speeches were made on international labor problems. Revolutionary anthems were played, and were clamorously applauded by the audience.</p>
   <p>The chairman received several telegrams from all parts of the United States, containing good wishes. One came from Paris, signed by Pierre Dumas, general secretary of the French Garment Workers Union; and another from Berlin, signed by H. Stuhmer, general secretary of the German union.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0265.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There were seventeen delegates of Italian blood, among whom were our friend Ninfo, and our comrades Cottone and Antonini.</p>
   <p>On of the most important resolutions passed was the one calling for the formation of a single, compact union of garment workers, with all its ramifications. This resolution will be presented to the next congress of the Amalgamated Garment Workers of America.</p>
   <p>The delegates were highly satisfied with the cordial welcome received, and also with the unmistakable solidarity shown by their Jewish comrades.</p>
   <p>The Chicago locals, moreover, held a great banquet, in which more than 800 of the unionists participated. Each delegate received a statuette representing that liberty which is no more, and the chairman of the Congress was given a magnificent cup.</p>
   <p>We regret that our secretary, La Duca, being out of town, was unable to attend the Congress as a brother delegate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
