<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Lauro, M., "<title level="a">Open Letter to the Chicago Tribune</title>",
<title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly), <date when="1929-01">January, 1929</date>, pp. 20-21.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0172</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0172.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Lauro, M., "<title level="a">Open Letter to the Chicago Tribune</title>",
<title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly), <date when="1929-01">January, 1929</date>, pp. 20-21.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Managing Editor of the Chicago Tribune</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>In the Tribune of Jan. 2nd, news from Nice, France was published under the caption "Chicago Tribune Press Service".</p>
   <p>It claimed that President Yrioyen of Argentina had signed a decree prohibiting Italian ships from entering the port of Buenos Aires until certain Mussolini regulations on military service affecting Italians who were naturalized Argentinians had been removed. The story stated that Mussolini bowed to the ultimatum from Argentina, removing said regulations.</p>
   <p>Strangely enough, the news of an ultimatum from Argentina to Italy does not arrive at your desk from correspondents in Buenos Aires or Rome, but just from Nice, France, which is not the capital of Argentina, or Italy, but only the capital of western European subservient forces distinguished as anti-Fascist.</p>
   <p>Stranger yet, not one of the other Chicago newspapers printed such news, although <pb facs="5425702_1_0173.jpg" n="2"/>they have a foreign service as good as yours.</p>
   <p>From a very authoritative source, I have been informed that said news is absolutely unfounded in every respect.</p>
   <p>Your editorial staff with the article, "International Nationalism", published in the Tribune of Jan. 3rd, has shown ignorance of the most elementary principles of international law ruling citizenship and sovereignty among civilized countries, and, profiting by the same ignorance of the largest majority of the public in this matter, it has fully misrepresented things, only to write "Un mucchio di fesserie" (A mass of lies).</p>
   <p>The writer of said article states that "under the terms of Mussolini's edict, children born of Italians on foreign soil are still Italians, and Italians of foreign citizenship returning to their native land are still Italian, subject in some cases, to military service". He sees in it "an insulting imperialistic practice" of Mussolini.</p>
   <p>No Mussolini edict could modify the Italian codes and laws, unless enacted according to the provisions of the Italian constitution.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0174.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The law ruling Italian citizenship is an Act of Parliament of 1912, (at that time Mussolini was not the premier of Italy) which absorbed some of the old regulations of the Italian legislation, adding to them more liberal and modern ones.</p>
   <p>According to said Act of 1912, which is still in force, children of Italian citizens born and residing in a foreign country maintain the Italian citizenship; but when of full age, or emancipated, they can renounce it. In this case, which is of election of nationality and not of naturalization, they are exempt from any military duty in Italy. (Art. 7 combined with the last part of Art. 8.)</p>
   <p>This is very logical and not imperialistic. In fact, the United States is doing the same thing with its laws on citizenship, by declaring that children born in foreign countries of American citizens are Americans. (Section 1993 U. S. Revised Statutes)</p>
   <p>In case an Italian naturalized American again obtains the Italian citizenship, his minor children born in America become Italian; but if they continue to reside <pb facs="5425702_1_0175.jpg" n="4"/>in America, where they are considered Americans, they do not acquire Italian citizenship according to regulations of Art. 12 of said Act.</p>
   <p>Making a comparison of Italian and American citizenship laws, it appears that they have almost similar regulations inspired by the same judicial principles, and both countries are very careful not to diminish their sovereignty and independence before possible pretensions of other nations.</p>
   <p>Concerning military service, the Italian law on conscription makes this service compulsory for every male citizen able to bear arms. The Act of 1912 on citizenship, repeating old regulations of former laws and codes, decrees that an Italian who has lost Italian citizenship through naturalization in a foreign country, is not excused from military service.</p>
   <p>The reason for such disposition of law is a very logical and moral one. In fact, the military service is a burden on the citizen and many people would prefer to stay at home than to go to the colors.</p>
   <p>If the status of a newly acquired citizenship had been a reason for exemption, <pb facs="5425702_1_0176.jpg" n="5"/>it would have been very easy for wealthy people, particularly those living near the boundary line, to take the citizenship of a bordering country and exempt themselves from the military service, while people with less money would have sustained alone the burden of the conscription law.</p>
   <p>The writer of the editorial in question vehemently accuses Italy and, particularly, Mussolini and Fascism, of imperialism; but he ignores, or at least it seems that he ignores that every European country has almost the same regulations as Italy in this particular case.</p>
   <p>In fact, the United States Department of the Interior published a pamphlet "Notice to Bearers of Passports" informing naturalized citizens of their possible military liability in the countries of their origin.</p>
   <p>According to the pamphlet, Belgium, Bulgaria, Denmark, Norway, Portugal, Sweden, France, Greece, The Netherlands, Poland, Rumania, Switzerland, Turkey, without having an imperialistic Mussolini, have compulsory military service and in these countries, American naturalized citizens also in some particular cases, are drafted for military service upon their return to the country of their origin <pb facs="5425702_1_0177.jpg" n="6"/>and possibly sentenced to serve a term in jail, if they have committed an offense against the conscription law.</p>
   <p>Countries with the government of which the United States has concluded naturalization treaties, consider if such an offense has been committed before or after American naturalization; but the others, which are in the majority, do not make this distinction.</p>
   <p>The imperialism of Italy is then in good company!</p>
   <p>If, in the United States there were a compulsory military service law, they also would consider as subject to it the children of Americancitizens who were born American in foreign countries, this would be in perfect accord with the general principles of international law.</p>
   <p>Mussolini is not "attempting to appropriate citizens of foreign nations", as the writer of the article states; but, if anyone with many years of Italian government has reduced the burden of military service to Italians living abroad, naturalized or not, this surely is Mussolini. In fact, his government has been instrumental in having a law enacted which practically exempts all Italians living <pb facs="5425702_1_0178.jpg" n="7"/>in foreign countries from actual service in the army, and gives them permission of returning to Italy for periods of six months, without being compelled into military service.</p>
   <p>With a previous law, Italian naturalized Americans, who, during the war had served under the American colors, were exempt from military service and penalties under the Italian conscription law which applied to those who had served less than one year under the American colors. A new regulation of law, enacted under the leadership of Mussolini, has reduced the time of one year to that of only one day.</p>
   <p>In conclusion it is very sad to realize that a man belonging to the editorial staff of the "world's greatest newspaper", in his heart and mentality is so little able to take pretext from a logically unfounded news to insult all the Italians in this country stating with sarcasm, that the Italian immigrants need to be fed and sweetened on the prairies of America; but they gave back to the United States a California, one of the richest states in the world.</p>
   <p>And when life was hard and dangerous in the trenches of France, the dark Italians <pb facs="5425702_1_0179.jpg" n="8"/>of America, if not yet naturalized citizens, were also there representing twenty-five per cent of all American forces, to fight for the honor of the red, white and blue.</p>
   <p>At that time the writer of "International Nationalism", was, perhaps, sitting at his desk in the Chicago Tribune office, puffing at a good cigar.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
