<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Grand Lodge of the State of Illinois</title>,
Volume 8, No. 11, <date when="1936-11">November, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Order Sons of Italy. "Always Patronize Your Own Institution," Is Plea to Italians</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0863</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0863.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Grand Lodge of the State of Illinois</title>,
Volume 8, No. 11, <date when="1936-11">November, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">ORDER SONS OF ITALY. "ALWAYS PATRONIZE YOUR OWN INSTITUTION," IS PLEA TO ITALIANS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the world began every man has done everything possible to get more power, for his tribe, family and country. So it is the duty of every Italian to enforce his Italian institution, directly or indirectly, to enforce andserve his great nation, the Italian. This Italian institution, which has gone through many years of experience is the Banco di Napoli.</p>
   <p>The Banco di Napoli Trust Company of Chicago has developed, within a short time, a banking institution of structure of steel, and the progress of this bank is positively astonishing, and that not mentioning its reserves which have accumulated into a superior social capital. Its beautiful building on the corner of Roosevelt Road &amp; Ashland Avenue, is a monument for the Italian <pb facs="5425702_1_0864.jpg" n="2"/>people of the Middlewest, and for the people who patronize this bank, which bares the name of our "Italian Institution." The service is perfect, especially the remittance of Italian money.</p>
   <p>It is absurd to patronize other banks when you can patronize the foundation of every bank, which is the Banco di Napoli Trust Company of Chicago.</p>
   <p>It is estimated that if all the Italians in Chicago place their banking business in charge of the Banco di Napoli and give their deposits to this institution they will then have a backing of $200,000,000.</p>
   <p>When the Italian colony realizes the indisputable fact that union makes strength, and that the prestige of the Italians in Chicago grows in proportion to <pb facs="5425702_1_0865.jpg" n="3"/>their power of cohesion. Italians, observe what is happening in Italy and the reaction of the whole world which is paying everyday the tribute of honor to a solidly united Italy. Stop and think for a few moments of the force of the Italian colonies in Chicago, and what results can occur if all the colonies should combine and make one force. It is absurd to deal with other banks when you have your own bank, where you can speak your own language and use your own dialect.</p>
   <p>In the Banco di Napoli you will find the utmost courtesy and efficiency. The President is always at your disposition, without waiting one minute for an interview with him. The purpose of Banco di Napoli is to serve all the Italian people. I am hoping that every Italian understands this plea.</p>
   <p>Note:- Dr. Joseph P. Ouathone, president of Banco di Napoli.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
