<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy in America - Illinois Lodge</title>,
<date when="1934-06-15">June 15, 1934</date>, p.4.
<title level="a">To Our Boys and Girls</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Francis La Piana</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy In America - Illinois Lodge</title>,
<date when="1934-06-15">June 15, 1934</date>, p.4.
<title level="a">TO OUR BOYS AND GIRLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Francis La Piana</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>No doubt several times during your attendance of the high school classes you have wondered and asked why you were required to study the Latin language, a language for which you were to have no use in the latter years of your life. You perhaps felt that the time and effort spent in that study could have been better employed in acquiring knowledge of more practical value.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0078.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But in this reasoning you left out the very important consideration, that in the study of a language it is not so much the learning to repeat a few words in more or less meaningless way that counts, but that its real value lays in the understanding of the life, the spirit of the people, who use the language as their means of expression.</p>
   <p>When you boys and girls study Latin it is not that you might know how this or that other thing was designated by the Romans, but that you know and become imbued with the spirit of old Rome. The spirit upon which, as a solid basis, has been built the civilization of today.</p>
   <p>You boys and girls of Italian parentage, conscious of the nobility of your race, should feel rightly proud when you realize that the knowledge of the language of your forefathers is one of the basic requirements in the education <pb facs="5425702_1_0079.jpg" n="3"/>of every young man and woman in this land, and in any other civilized land on the globe.</p>
   <p>And this spirit of greatness, of achievements, of progress irradiating from Rome, we, of the Order of Sons of Italy in this new fatherland of ours, deem it our duty to awaken and keep alive in your tender hearts, so you may in time become for honesty, ability, obedience to law, for love of country and of humanity worthy citizens of this land of your birth, "America."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
