<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1917-01-21">January 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Worthy Persons of the Bazaar for the Italian Section</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1266</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1266.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1917-01-21">January 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORTHY PERSONS OF THE BAZAAR FOR THE ITALIAN SECTION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although we have not yet been given the final results of the Allied Bazaar, we are sure that it will be a great success from all indications. The receipts, according to the members of the executive committee, will pass the half million mark, and this shows that the sympathy of the majority of the people of Chicago is for the allied nations fighting a titanic struggle for the defense of modern civilization in danger of falling at the hands of the barbaric teutons.</p>
   <p>For the convenience of those who have not as yet attended the Coliseum, it will be open Saturday from 10 A. M., to 11 P. M.</p>
   <p>We hope everything will come up to our expectations, and we are pleased to announce with a sense of pride that the Italian section responded as was anticipated.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1267.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The success of the Italian Day, was due to the patriotism shown by the colony, and also to the untiring activity of the people, who assumed the task of urging contributions and the selling of objects placed on exhibition.</p>
   <p>The Italian Consul Conte Bolognesi, the Italian Civil Engineer Barbieri, and the Italian Red Cross delegates, Cavalieri Dr. Volini, and Dr. Lagorio, deserve much praise for having prepared a demonstration in keeping with Italian traditions. But the reward for the success of the day, is to the gentle set, who worked with much alacrity in inducing the visitors to pour out money for the benefit of our soldiers in war.</p>
   <p>In this work of charity, the Italian women have acted with feeling for their fatherland. Under the direction of Mrs. Herman H. Kohisaal, the Italian kiosk, functioned so well that it is expected to raise another 100,000 lire.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1268.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mrs. Eva Campanini-Tetrazzini, and Mrs. Jean Durante, deserve much admiration for the work done. Mrs. V. Volini, Countess Bolognesi, Mrs. Garibaldi, Mrs. M. Bruno, Mrs. Ettore Titta Ruffo, Mrs. Canepa Bono, Mrs. Rigali, Mrs. Mirabella, Mrs. Fumasoh, Miss Adeline Durante, Miss Volini, Miss Conforti and many others deserve to be congratulated.</p>
   <p>A BENEFIT PERFORMANCE FOR THE OLDIERS AT THE AUDITORIUM.</p>
   <p>Through the initiative of that worthy person, Mr. Cleofonte Campanini, there will be given a performance at the Auditorium Theatre Sunday night for the benefit of the Italian and French soldiers at war. Our colony has never failed to support all charity movements for the fatherland. A great number, we are sure, will attend the show to see the best that the opera company has to offer. The Ambassador and his wife, will come here from Washington, inorder to be present at the benefit.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Bryan Lathrop, Mrs. Arthur Ryerson and Mrs. Joseph Coleman, are the honorary presidents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
