<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-05-24">May 24, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Oddino Morgari at Hull House</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1454</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.9"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1454.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II D 9</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-05-24">May 24, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ODDINO MORGARI AT HULL HOUSE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On last Sunday Bowen Hall in Hull House was filled to overflowing with an audience composed mainly of Italians, who had come to hear a lecture by by Oddino Morgari, Socialist member of the Italian Chamber of Deputies.</p>
   <p>The program was opened with a talk by Dr. Molinari, who chose as his subject Cesare Lombroso, the Italian scientist and criminologist. His lecture was accompanied by illustrated lantern slides.</p>
   <p>After the playing of the Internationale,Morgari delivered his address.</p>
   <p>He spoke of the situation existing in Japan and the United States. He expressed the hope that the Italians would protest against the insult to Japan in the proposed act excluding members of the yellow race from entry into America.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1455.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He further stated that the Italian consul in Chicago had refused to attend the Lybian peace banquet sponsored by the Italian colony of this city, because the chairman in charge of the banquet is the head of the Black Hand in Chicago. At this point the editor of Movimento, a local weekly, attempted to interrupt the lecture but with no success, for the few anarchists present drowned him out with shouts and hoots.</p>
   <p>As to Morgari's statement about the consul and the peace banquet, we can vouch for its veracity. The president of that banquet is an ex-priest and an ex-inmate of Joliet penitentiary and was recently pointed out by the American press of Chicago as the head of the Black Hand.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1456.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In making that statement Morgari did not imply that all those connected with the banquet are members of the Black Hand. It is useless for the editor of Movimento to deny the fact that the chairman is just what Morgari called him.</p>
   <p>Morgari's lecture was followed by the playing of a Socialist hymn.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
