<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1930-04">April 1930</date>, p. 23.
<title level="a">"Ruth Hanna McCormick, Candidate to the Senate."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0606</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0606.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1930-04">April 1930</date>, p. 23.
<title level="a">"RUTH HANNA McCORMICK, CANDIDATE TO THE SENATE."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Congressman-at-large, Ruth Hanna McCormick, one of the most intelligent woman of America, is more than capable to hold the office of U.S.Senator.</p>
   <p>She is a courageous and able citizen with wide experience. She is an untiring worker endowed with enthusiasm and energy.</p>
   <p>Mrs. McCormick is an expert and elegant speaker and has much political talent. She is capable of competing with the best American Statesmen and consequently she is the logical choice to represent the State of Illinois in the Senate.</p>
   <p>She is a good mother who has reared a splendid family.</p>
   <p>Mrs. McCormick has a wide knowledge and experience of national and international affairs because she spent most of her life in Washington as Secretary to her father, <pb facs="5425702_1_0607.jpg" n="2"/>the late Mark Hanna who was U.S.Senator, and because she is the widow of the late Medill McCormick, Congressman-at-large and Senator for the State of Illinois.</p>
   <p>Mrs. McCormick has traveled and studied conditions in foreign countries as well as those of America, and she is very well informed and in a position to know national or international problems as no other women does.</p>
   <p>During the Presidential campaign of William McKinley, she worked with her father, Senator Mark Hanna and spent her vacationsamong the coal miner's foundries and among the industrial workers to study their living conditions.</p>
   <p>Her recommendations have been adopted and approved as laws. Regulation of the hours of work, increases in salary and better living conditions or the workers were some of the recommendations.</p>
   <p>Mrs. McCormick aspires to be a U.S.Senator not for personal advantage but to be useful and helpful to the people of Illinois.</p>
   <p>We are against those who do not pay any attention to our protest against the <pb facs="5425702_1_0608.jpg" n="3"/>abnormal law of the immigration quota.</p>
   <p>This law is unjust and against the best interests of the people of our race but it is favorable to other nations.</p>
   <p>We need an able representative who will speak for the interest of the people of Illinois disregarding creed, affiliation or race.</p>
   <p>We recommend that the Italian voters support Ruth Hanna McCormick.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
