<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy of Illinois</title>,
Vol. VIII, No. 8.
<title level="a">Wake Up</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By George Spatuzza</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy of Illinois</title>,
Vol. VIII, No. 8.
<title level="a">WAKE UP</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By George Spatuzza</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last issue of our Bulletin there appeared an article under my signature, in which I stated in substance, that while it is true that our organization is not political in character, yet our organization is interested in the advancement of our people in the political field, because the more of our people in public office, the better our prestige rises. I stated of the necessity of the existence of an organization in Illinois that would count tens of thousands - for the existence alone of such an organization would cause the political "bosses" to think twice and more before acting on a list of candidates or appointments.</p>
   <p>I am moved to continue to write along these lines, because I received numerous favorable comments, not only from our members, but from the press as well.</p>
   <p>I have known our people never to ask for too much - even timed for asking their just share - this is because the Italian rewards faithful service without the asking, and gives unto others what they deserve without solicitation; such being their trait, they naturally expect others to do likewise.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0627.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But the experience in the political field has taught us otherwise, hence the necessity of deviating from those traits and to prepare to go after the very things that ought to be ours.</p>
   <p>Our people, in Chicago especially, have been the subject of unfair treatment in the political field. Here, where thousands upon thousands of our people reside and where a good percentage of the voting strength lies, we have been the recipients of a small portion of political benefits. The fault may be in those of our people who now occupy political positions. Still the fault may not be charged to them because in demanding, they have been unable to point out a single unity of Italians that would count tens of thousands.</p>
   <p>We need not make such a careful study to correctly conclude that our representation in the various public offices of our city, county, and state, falls very short of our just share. Take for instance the Board of Education, whose members direct the destinies of the education of the children of today, who will be the men and women of tomorrow. Here our people have no representation of any kind - although we have thousands upon thousands of our children attending public schools. We could take practically any department of our city, <pb facs="5425702_1_0628.jpg" n="3"/>county, and state, and we find conditions about the same.</p>
   <p>But the most humiliating thing that I had to suffer was this; One bright morning I received a communication from the Grand Lodge of Pennsylvania asking me to send immediately the names and addresses of the delegates of Italian birth or extraction of the State of Illinois, who would attend the National Political Convention at Philadelphia, as the Grand Lodge wanted to welcome them and have festivities in their honor. I set myself immediately to the task and after careful search I found that none of our people were on the list of delegates, except one and he was an alternate. What a political situation for our people in the great commonwealth of Illinois!</p>
   <p>But the worst of all is the fact that we are sleeping - sleeping a tranquil and sound sleep. And our children are growing, thinking possibly, that we as in duty bound, are preparing a splendid path for them.</p>
   <p>To my people I say: "Arise from the slumber and organize yourselves into a unity that will assert itself for the present and future generations."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
