<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1915-01-30">Jan. 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation of the Unemployed to the Citizens of Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0347</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0347.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1915-01-30">Jan. 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION OF THE UNEMPLOYED TO THE CITIZENS OF CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>These unemployed persons wish to protest against the incidents which took place after the mass-meeting held at Hull House on January 17, when unarmed men and women were brutally beaten by the police.</p>
   <p>Exercising our constitutional rights of speech and assembly, we had gathered in order to discuss our deplorable condition. We had passed a resolution to make a public demonstration on the streets, thus showing to the world our wretched situation, which was forced upon us through no fault of our own.</p>
   <p>We unemployed consider it to be a crime attributable to the present civic order that millions of unemployed must die of starvation while they are surrounded by so much wealth, especially since we ourselves have contributed to the production of that wealth.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0348.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The politicians, taking advantage of our destitution, are replying with charity to our cry for bread and work. We want a home, and they give us the municipal night-shelters, which are not ample anough to harbor one-tenth of the homeless in this city.</p>
   <p>Formerly self-respecting American citizens are now undergoing the humiliation of bread-lines and public kitchens. Hungry and shivering with cold, they wait in line for hours until a piece of bread is thrown to them!</p>
   <p>We unemployed, who have not lost our human dignity, demand work, and we shall carry on our efforts in meetings, in parades, or in any other appropriate way.</p>
   <p>It is useless to speak of police permits for public parading because they will never be issued to hungry people. However, the police are mistaken if they believe that the power is theirs to subdue hungry people with clubs, black-jacks, or revolvers.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0349.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Hunger knows but one law, which is the right to live.</p>
   <p>Violence attracts violence!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
