<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1925-11">November, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The Locarno Pact. Actual Triumph of Carnovale's Original Conception</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1383</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1383.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1925-11">November, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE LOCARNO PACT. ACTUAL TRIUMPH OF CARNOVALE'S ORIGINAL CONCEPTION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Luigi Carnovale, resident of Chicago for about sixteen years, presented his original "abolition of neutrality" conception for the first time in the chapter entitled "Human Solidarity" of his famous historical book Why Italy Entered Into The Great War, published in Chicago during July, 1917.</p>
   <p>The people must have facts. They must, without distinction, create among themselves a solid spiritual alliance (product of their universal political unison), and establish, as a fundamental principle of justice - inviolate and invincible - that when a controversy between two nations degenerates into war, each of the peoples not involved in the controversy so fostered, must impose upon their own government an armed intervention in favor of the nation which one finds in the right. In the right, according to the judgment that springs free from preconceived ideas and passions, from free intelligence, from the candid conscience of the people themselves, and above all, according to the natural guide of life which makes the cause of the oppressed seem always beautiful, sacred, and worthy of victory.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1384.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Only in such a manner, for the present, can one curb the aggressive mania of the stronger. Only in such a manner can war be prevented.</p>
   <p>In April, 1920, Luigi Carnovale republished the same chapter "Human Solidarity" in a separate pamphlet, under the title, Only By The Abolition Of Neutrality Can War Be Quickly And Forever Prevented, with preliminary and complimentary notes to further develop and clarify the conception against neutrality. Other editions followed in May, 1920, in Italian; in November, 1921, and in May, 1922, in English. Both pamphlets were published in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Then in March, 1924, Luigi Carnovale again republished his conception against neutrality in another pamphlet, in catechistical form (questions and answers) under the title, How America Can Easily And Quickly Prevent War Forever. In this edition he set forth his conception in still clearer and more precise terms, in the following three questions and answers:</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1385.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>(1). How can the United States abolish neutrality?</p>
   <p>The President of the United States should officially proclaim the principle itself in the form of an appropriate article in the American Constitution.</p>
   <p>The United States Government should invite all the other nations of the world to do the same; that is, to proclaim officially the principle of the abolition of neutrality, and to introduce the relative article into their own constitutions.</p>
   <p>(2). How must the article establishing the abolition of neutrality be formulated?</p>
   <p>It must be formulated in these terms: When in a part of the world a controversy (in words) arises between two nations, the United States and all the other nations not involved in the controversy, instead of remaining indifferent, which means neutral, must immediately and officially sympathize <pb facs="5425702_1_1386.jpg" n="4"/>with the nation which is in the right and at the same time stigmatize the nation which is in the wrong.</p>
   <p>If the two nations in controversy pass from words to acts, which means war, the United States and all the other neutral nations must immediately intervene in the war in defense of the nation which is in the right, and intervene with economic and armed forces of land, sea, and air, instantly, to defeat and annihilate the insolent nation which is in the wrong and has provoked the war.</p>
   <p>It is understood, of course, that in all cases the stronger nation must intervene against the nation which is in the wrong and has provoked the war. But the weaker nation must necessarily be in the right, it being impossible, excepting in case of insanity, that the weaker should insolently attack the stronger. The lamb cannot insolently attack the wolf!</p>
   <p>At any rate, the neutral nations must always intervene in favor of the nation which is in the right, whether this nation be the weaker or the stronger.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1387.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The principle of intervention of the neutral in favor of the side which is right, and against the side which is wrong, is also applicable to civil wars.</p>
   <p>The article establishing the abolition of neutrality to be introduced into the Constitution of the United States must be identical to the one to be introduced into the constitutions of all the other nations because the object of the United States and that of all the other nations of the world is identical. It is the end of war and the practical advent of universal, permanent peace.</p>
   <p>(3). What is the Locarno Security Pact?</p>
   <p>In substance it is the official recognition and proclamation on the part of the great European nations of Luigi Carnovale's original conception, "the abolition of neutrality."</p>
   <p>It is true the objection might be raised that the Locarno Pact covers only a <pb facs="5425702_1_1388.jpg" n="6"/>few nations, whereas Luigi Carnovale's plan covers all the nations of the world; but, it is also true that the Locarno Pact is the decisive step toward universal permanent peace and which will certainly be followed sooner or later by all the other nations of the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
