<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1921-12-17">Dec. 17, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Colonial Chronicles</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0426</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0426.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1921-12-17">Dec. 17, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">COLONIAL CHRONICLES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are glad to publish the following letter:</p>
   <p>Dear Editor:</p>
   <p>In reading your honest and pugnacious newspaper, I cannot but notice your noble and sacred crusade in behalf of the interests and rights of the common people, and that you are in the habit of calling an ace an ace.</p>
   <p>For these very reasons, I am asking you to grant me a little space in your paper, so that I may be able to continue my interrupted campaign against all sordidness found in the Italian colony of Chicago. For six long years I fought this campaign in the former Socialist paper L'Avanti, for the purpose of unmasking the banditry which is nestling within our colony. A small group of these crooks, aided by the Italian consular authorities, are cheating the large population of our Chicago immigrants.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0427.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now, with the collaboration of your worthy newspaper, I shall be able to expose grave matters which our Italian comrades and laborers ought to know. I will leave the grammatical and orthographical rules, of which I am ignorant, to those rascals of the colonial press; that is, to the editors of L'Italia, L'Idea, and La Tribuna Transatlantica.</p>
   <p>With your permission, I shall first describe the person, the character and the professional achievements of one of those weather-vanes, Attorney Giogliotti.</p>
   <p>My campaign would open in your next number with an article regarding the visit to Chicago of Generalissimo Armando Diaz.</p>
   <p>Hoping for a favorable reply, I remain your devoted reader,</p>
   <p>Giuseppe Orrico</p>
   <p>807 Garibaldi Place</p>
   <p>Chicago, III.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0428.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Editor's Note. - Our newspaper is intended to be a free platform for the discussion of all the problems which concern the Italian colonies in America. We believe that the problem of colonial "worms" is of the utmost importance.</p>
   <p>These colonies are afflicted by a cancerous sore formed by prominent, but vulgar, co-nationals, who are dishonest and filthy exploiters. Every citizen desiring the welfare of our poor immigrants-- who are such easy victims -- should favor any honest initiative bent on pointing out and curing said cancerous sore.</p>
   <p>Therefore, our friend Orrico, if capable, is welcome to space in our newspaper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
