<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Tribuna Italiana</title>,
<date when="1908-02-08">February 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Italian Banks</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Tribuna Italiana</title>,
<date when="1908-02-08">February 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">ITALIAN BANKS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Seven Italians banks in New York which, until now, were believed to be strong and solid, have failed. Approximately $3,000,000 were lost by Italians, and the bad news has stirred the public's opinion, Italians as well as Americans.</p>
   <p>Our esteemed sister, L'Italia of Chicago, a newspaper read from the Atlantic to the Pacific, from Canada to the Gulf of Mexico, had to handle the subject of the banks for the Italian Press of Chicago.</p>
   <p>It should not have been done since it offended so many Italian bankers that they held a meeting at which they decided to answer L'Italia with an article written by Mr. Michelangelo Freda, of the banking house, V. Renzino and Company, 418-420 South Clark Street. This article will be published prepaid in our Tribuna as a defiant gesture against L'Italia for its article.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1044.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The bankers decided to withdraw their advertisements and also those of navigation lines, and to refuse to pay their back subscriptions.</p>
   <p>We learned of these dicisions from Mr. Freda himself, last Monday in his office, when he paid us for his subscription. We advised Mr. Freda to visit the publisher of L'Italia, Mr Durante. We, in fact, immediately visited him and agreed that Mr. Freda should have written his article directly to L'Italia instead of sending it to the Tribuna for publication.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time neither L'Italia nor La Tribuna have received this article. The bankers of Chicago can do as they please, but as long as they do not put a gag on the honest press in Chicago, by threatening to furnish them, by refusing to pay the subscriptions, and by withdrawing not only their own advertisements, but also that of others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
