<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1936-07">July 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Our Association Sponsors the Study of the Italian Language in Kensington</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1402</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1402.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1936-07">July 1936</date>.
<title level="a">OUR ASSOCIATION SPONSORS THE STUDY OF THE ITALIAN LANGUAGE IN KENSINGTON</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the evening of June 10, in the Venetian Hall, Kensington, the Italian colony celebrated the end of the school period for the Italian classes, taught during the year in the school of St. Anthony Church, through the efforts of our association.</p>
   <p>Among those present were: Royal Consul General Dr. Mario Carosi; Supreme President Philip D'Andrea; Director of Italian Study, Prof. Pomante; Chevalier V. E. Ferrara, and Dr. Ingrao. The Italians of Kensington attended in large numbers, thus showing their interest and appreciation for the study of our language.</p>
   <p>The scholastic test in Italian passed by the pupils was very successful, and they demonstrated their skill in the declamation of Italian.</p>
   <p>A selected musical program was rendered by a band directed by Prof. A. J. <pb facs="5425702_1_1403.jpg" n="2"/>De Grazia. Commendatore Dr. Carosi, Royal Consul General, in distributing medals awarded to the pupils who had distinguished themselves in these Italian classes, praised all the rewarded pupils. The Rev. G. Chiminello of Kensington introduced Miss Lina Panozzo, instructor, who thanked everybody for the kindly aid given to her students, and Mr. G. Favario, teacher of the evening class, made a brief speech.</p>
   <p>The Rev. O. D'Andrea, founder of St. Anthony church and school, expressed his satisfaction at the achievement of the school.</p>
   <p>Prof. Pomante, Director of Italian Study, in his speech praised the Italo-American National Union, which had given its moral and financial support in order to make possible the teaching of the Italian language to the children of our race, who through knowing the language may appreciate more fully the glorious land of their fathers.</p>
   <p>In supporting financially the Italian schools in Kensington and in Rockford, Illinois, the Italo-American National Union has added another glorious page to its history.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
