<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title level="a">"Justifiable Protest of Attorney John De Grazia,"</title><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title> (Monthly), <date when="1935-03">Mar. 1935</date>, p. 1440

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0162</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0162.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title level="a">"Justifiable Protest of Attorney John De Grazia,"</title><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title> (Monthly), <date when="1935-03">Mar. 1935</date>, p. 1440
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Attorney John De Grazia, founder and first president of the Justinian Society of Advocates (members must be of Italian birth or descent), as well as one of the oldest members of Lodge La Masa, member lodge of our organization, sent us the following letter which we, recognizing the value of the concept that inspired it, gladly publish.</p>
   <p>For many years, whenever Italian periodicals published in America and certain orators feel the need of criticizing the morals or conduct of their countrymen living in America, they unfailingly write or say something of the customs of the country which offers us hospitality.</p>
   <p>In my forty years of residence in America, I have never felt nor considered myself the guest of anyone, because history, as I have learned it, taught me that this country does not belong to any definite group but indisputable to all who have come here to earn an honest living and have established themselves as good citizens. To say, as is said in general of Italians, that we are guests creates the impression that we are here by the good grace of certain individuals or groups, who are the owners <pb facs="5425702_1_0163.jpg" n="2"/>of this land. Puerile mentality and conception because if we Italians could establish our claims to this continent on the basis of discovery, we would be the masters and the others the guests. Therefore it is an injustice on the part of that section of Italian orators and the Italian press in America to sow harmful seeds that only tend to create an inferiority complex in our people.</p>
   <p>Even disregarding our claim by right of discovery and of the name given to this country, I feel that our contribution to its development places us on a par, if not above, the best element here established. One needs but to read the story of the growth of the two Americas, and our most rabid critic is forced to admit that to omit the contribution of the people of our race would leave an immense void.</p>
   <p>It should be known that the Italian has had few equal to him in the work of developing this nation. Every railroad, mine and skyscraper is indebted to the Italian manual laborer; every industry is familiar with the good work and ability of the Italian.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0164.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It would be better for the Italian orators and the Italian press to change their attitude and take the point of view that we Italians are not guests but masters of the house.</p>
   <p>With distinct regards,</p>
   <p>John De Grazia, Attorney.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
