<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1923-03-24">Mar. 24, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Socialist Campaign Is Worrying the Bourgeoisie</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0388</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0388.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1923-03-24">Mar. 24, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOCIALIST CAMPAIGN IS WORRYING THE BOURGEOISIE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From reading what the newspapers of the bourgeois parties are publishing about the Socialist election campaign, it seems that those gentlemen are alarmed by the sentiment aroused among the voters of Chicago, especially among the workers.</p>
   <p>Mr. Oscar Hewitt, who is conducting a straw vote for the Tribune, said, in commenting on the results, that the Socialist vote at the next city election will be an important factor.</p>
   <p>According to Mr. Hewitt's straw vote, the Socialist candidate, Mr. Cunnea, will draw not less than 62,000 votes. Never before in the history of Chicago has a Socialist candidate for mayor received more than 25,000 votes. However, Mr. Hewitt said that Mr. Cunnea is a Socialist candidate who is very different from the others; he is an outstanding influential personality.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0389.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1912, as Socialist candidate for District Attorney, Mr. Cunnea drew 107,647 votes. This campaign is more energetic than the preceding one. Cunnea and Debs speak every night, and even though there is a charge for admission, their meetings are crowded. The people are paying to listen to these two speakers. The money is used for campaign expenses.</p>
   <p>It is not improbable that Mr. Cunnea will carry more than 100,000 votes, which can become the deciding factor between the Democratic and Republican candidates.</p>
   <p>We reported Mr. Hewitt's comments, as published by the Tribune, in order to let the Italian comrades know of the splendid opportunity our Party has for a beautiful Socialist affirmation at the coming election.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
