<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1922-06-03">June 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Patriotic "Thieves" and High-Placed Protectors</title><title level="a" type="sub">Where Is Justice?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0401</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0401.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1922-06-03">June 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTIC "THIEVES" AND HIGH-PLACED PROTECTORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Where Is Justice?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Senate of the United States they are talking about speculations and the huge frauds committed during the war by individuals who supplied war materials to the government. They speak of specific cases in regard to frauds amounting to the handsome sum of $192,000,000.</p>
   <p>The gentlemen who have enriched themselves at the expense of the state, that is to say, our country, in time of war, belong to that category of so-called 100% patriots and leaders of the people.</p>
   <p>The Attorney-General has requested and obtained an assignment of $500,000 in order to unearth the facts and bring the guilty before the law. Mr. Daugherty has need for other funds, other graft, in order to discover and punish the grafting of the "patriots." Accused of not having done so before now, he justifies himself with saying that the famous Palmer, of the famous democracy of Wilson, left nothing prepared for the need. That Palmer may <pb facs="5425702_1_0402.jpg" n="2"/>be guilty of negligence, we are well aware. In fact he was much too occupied with the search for "Reds" to give a thought to the yellow-gloved thieves. But this excuse does not justify the inertia of the present Attorney-General.</p>
   <p>It seems that there are in the Senate certain "gentlemen" Senators who think as we do in that respect. There are some, for example, who accuse Daugherty of something like complicity. Senator Caraway, for example, reveals that His Excellency Attorney-General Daugherty made an agreement involving $25,000 with Col. Felder, to promote the release of a certain Morse, one of the many "patriotic" war thieves who had been imprisoned for fraud committed against the State. Furthermore, says Caraway, the same Morse was counselled by His Excellency Daugherty, as to the part he was to play in order to facilitate his release from prison, counsels which Morse followed and which procured him his freedom.</p>
   <p>These little things, of course, do not surprise us. Who does not know that in America justice serves the thieves while it keeps imprisoned unfortunate subversives whose only crime is that they think.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0403.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But there is more to it. His Excellency has been criticized by senators and newspapers for his inability and unwillingness to prosecute the war thieves. How can you expect Daugherty to agitate against the capitalistic corporations, say his critics, when this same Daugherty is ex-legal consultant for various capitalistic corporations?</p>
   <p>And who would try to make us believe that among these war thieves there is not one corporation which should be brought before the law?</p>
   <p>So that summed up we have: Thieves who profess themselves to be one hundred percent patriots and highly placed accomplices who should punish them. But a wolf does not eat a wolf. It is for the people who vote to think before putting into power wolves from the packs of wolves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
