<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1915-04-04">April 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Favored Candidate Who Is the Advance Guard of Prosperity Is William Hale Thompson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0548</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0548.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1915-04-04">April 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE FAVORED CANDIDATE WHO IS THE ADVANCE GUARD OF PROSPERITY IS WILLIAM HALE THOMPSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tuesday, April 6th is Election Day. Every Italian voter will not only vote the way he thinks is right, but also will show whether or not he wants to continue under a Democratic administration and continue the depression by voting Democratic.</p>
   <p>Tuesday is the opportune day to show whether you desire the return of prosperity.</p>
   <p>The victory of the Republicans, next Tuesday, will mean the reopening of factories and work for the unemployed. A "Full Dinner Pail" is the slogan. Work for whoever needs it and big wages. Don't let employers or politics betray you Tuesday, and when you vote look for the Republican column. Vote Republican and assure yourself that you have voted for the return of prosperity.</p>
   <p>William Hale Thompson for Mayor.</p>
   <p>To our countrymen, the most important thing in this election for Chicago citizens is to have a good city administration. You need security and a guarantee <pb facs="5425702_1_0549.jpg" n="2"/>that you will have it for yourself, your family, and your property.</p>
   <p>You need personal liberties within the limits of the law and you need work.</p>
   <p>If you are a laborer and desire to take good care of your family, you need work. Or, you need it for others, in case you have your own business, because we depend on one another, and few are those who can live a comfortable life without hope of prosperity.</p>
   <p>You have a need that Chicago develops.</p>
   <p>You need a city governed by an honest and competent administration for the good of all.</p>
   <p>A Mayor is needed who knows and loves Chicago.</p>
   <p>You need a man who has no fear and who is independent in action.</p>
   <p>You will find such a man by voting for William Hale Thompson!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
