<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1908-03-12">Mar. 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">A Pleasing Denial</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.9"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 9</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1908-03-12">Mar. 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">A PLEASING DENIAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last week American and Italian newspapers have been printing news which has brought sorrow to all members of Italian colonies in North America who are concerned for our reputation.</p>
   <p>It was stated that following the murders perpetrated by Averbuch and Alio, the White Hand of Chicago had furnished the police with a list of fifteen names of dangerous Italian anarchists who would be soon jailed and deported.</p>
   <p>How can such things be? How could a society founded with the praiseworthy object of quenching attacks on the good reputation of Italians stoop so low as to become a political spy on radicals, and a free reference bureau for the American police?</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1665.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have interviewed Dr. Camillo Volini, president of the White Hand of Chicago.</p>
   <p>We take pleasure in declaring that Dr. Volini authorizes a categorical denial of such reports. He begs us to state publicly that the White Hand did not furnish the police with the names of any Italians, and that it is not an organization of private detectives but a society of which the purpose is to fight with whatever means are most convenient, the Camorra, the Mafia, and other Italian criminals in this colony. Mr. Volini added that the press reports were also false: that he had been threatened with death by the Black Hand, and that he kept a kind of bodyguard--that these were all the vagaries of American reporters.</p>
   <p>When will these journalists learn that inventing is not reporting?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
