<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
The Copist, "<title level="a">Choosing a Profession</title>" <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly), <date when="1929-03">Mar., 1929</date>, p. 18.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0823</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0823.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
The Copist, "<title level="a">Choosing A Profession</title>" <title>Vita Nuova</title> (Monthly), <date when="1929-03">Mar., 1929</date>, p. 18.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the ever increasing number of Italian-Americans, who are venturing out into the world, the question of choosing a profession which shall be both remunerative and consistent with their likes and dislikes is a very difficult one. The problem is made more acute because of an inadequate comprehension of just what the word "profession" embraces, and just what other fields are open in addition to the over-crowded field of law and medicine. Time has brought no abatement in the number of young men seeking to become doctors or lawyers, while other and oftentimes more attractive, if not more lucrative professions, are sadly in need of new talent.</p>
   <p>Perhaps the principal reason for the glamour surrounding the professions of law and medecine is the legendary respect inculcated in the hearts of our immigrants for those professions in Italy. In the small communities of the old country, where most of our immigrants come from, the lawyers and the doctors represented the highest leadership and commanded the greatest respect. The business man, on the other hand, was considered a lower order in the social scale, until recently young men in Italy, who could afford an education, invariably entered these professions.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0824.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The immigrant seeks to do for his child in America what for lack of means he could not do for himself in Italy; make him a lawyer or a doctor in keeping with tradition.</p>
   <p>Much of this that might be called sentimental attachment for the two professions, the only professions in the minds of many, is still noticeable and many mothers and fathers doggedly insist that their boy shall be a "dottore" or an "avvocato". The result has been an influx into those fields that has created some rather unfortunate conditions. Thousands of them earn little more, if as much as the average man with a good trade, and many more earn appreciably less than the go-getting business man. Many have impelled themselves only half trained into the practice of law or medicine and, along with the others of other nationalities, have induced a lowering of the standards all along the line. A reaction has been in the stiffening of requirements and qualifications and the tightening of bar and medical board examinations. Some of the applicants inadequately prepared and over-anxious to break through, fail and attribute their failure to prejudice against them on account of race. There may be some grounds to this charge, but it can not be made generally applicable.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0825.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Later phases of psychology, dealing especially with vocational guidance, promise to help a great deal in pointing out to the ambitious young man the right road; but science must first have a tilt with superstition if the historical glamour of medicine and law, as it affects the Italian, is to be destroyed. Of course, we need new talent coming into these professions, but it must be regulated in proportion to its value. The multiplicity of American life, its variegated industrial and business activities, offer many interesting and remunerative lines of endeavor to young men.</p>
   <p>There is need of more Italians in the field of journalism, social service, engineering, and the various commercial fields. These fields have been elevated to the dignity of a profession and, after all, the greatest profession in America is neither law nor medicine, but business.</p>
   <p>The great majority of American young men is going into business. Our Italian youth should follow their example.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
