<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1924-05-01">May 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Socialist Federation to the Italian Workers of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1924-05-01">May 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOCIALIST FEDERATION TO THE ITALIAN WORKERS OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>May First, the universal holiday of workers, finds us this year in our ranks, inspired with undiminished enthusiasm and faith in our incessant struggle for the conquest of a better future for the working class.</p>
   <p>Our appeal on this occasion is not an invitation to you to celebrate victories; instead, we urge you to profound meditation, active meditation on the way that we have traversed, in order that we may acquire a stronger will to struggle for the inevitable conquest of the morrow.</p>
   <p>Capitalism is not disarming but is speculating on our errors and dissensions; it is returning to the attack with renewed vigor, to take away from the working class the hard-earned conquests of the past.</p>
   <p>It appears that the workers are not excessively worried by the chains welded <pb facs="5425702_1_0373.jpg" n="2"/>on their wrists, nor are they trying to marshal themselves in one solid political organization to combat the reactionary bourgeoisie. Upon you workers rests the task of stirring up the masses, who are still the slaves of prejudice and are still chained to the bourgeoisie's wagon. The Socialist party, our mother organization, has been marching forward for years and is getting ready to inspire new life in the solid, united proletarian class of America, preparing it to meet in pitched battle the two capitalistic parties of the United States, which are using political power to consolidate their class predominance to the absolute detriment of the populous ranks of the producers.</p>
   <p>Comrades, respond to our party's appeal; do not hesitate to bring it to the attention of your co-workers; convince them of its virtue, and persuade them to accept it! The criminal indifference of the American working class must come to an end; it is the duty of the Socialist party to lead the masses to victory. This should be your resolve as you celebrate the historic date of the First of May. What we have heretofore accomplished is nothing in <pb facs="5425702_1_0374.jpg" n="3"/>comparison with what is still to be accomplished, for the emancipation of the working class is a long and arduous task, which requires perseverance and will power.</p>
   <p>Capitalism has produced a state of chaos; it has impoverished nations and is unable to solve the peace problem after a five years' war which was supposed to put an end to armed conflict. Instead of promoting peace, capitalism, not bound by international solidarity but urged by greed to competition for the conquest of markets, is throwing all its force in to the mad race to increase the armaments which will lead us into a new war, a war more disastrous than the last to the nations involved in it.</p>
   <p>When will the abused populace learn to resist? Taught by experience, the proletarians of the world will some day be wise enough to unite and put an end to the capitalistic regime, and such a day must come because it is absurd to believe otherwise. And we must endeavor to hasten the event with incessantly <pb facs="5425702_1_0375.jpg" n="4"/>persistent propaganda, penetrating everywhere, including the household, the factory, and the farm.</p>
   <p>Remember this our comrades and workers, on this first day of May, and let us remind other workers of it.</p>
   <p>If the red flags may not circulate in the streets of Italian towns today, or in certain other countries, and the masses of the workers may not meet there to proclaim their faith, remember that in the streets of London and before the Kremlin of Moscow the cry of hosanna will mount heavenward and magnify the new sun of our redemption, socialism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
