<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Il Bollettino Sociale</title>,
<date when="1929-09-15">Sep. 15, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">For a Monument to Columbus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Il Bollettino Sociale</title>,
<date when="1929-09-15">Sep. 15, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">FOR A MONUMENT TO COLUMBUS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following circular letter has been sent to the presidents of all Italian associations, inviting them to join the Lega Colombiana, with the object of erecting a permanent memorial to Christopher Columbus and of unveiling it on the occasion of the World's Fair in 1933:</p>
   <p>"Mr. President: A great enterprise, born of pure Italian patriotism, is about to increase our prestige in this great city. Together we shall consummate an honorable achievement worthy of real Italians if we participate in this project, which will affirm the triumph of our Italian civilization and the historic importance of the discovery of this continent of America by our glorious fellow-countryman Christopher Columbus.</p>
   <p>You undoubtedly know that a great international exposition will be held in Chicago in 1933, in which all the nations of the world will participate.</p>
   <p>We Italians desire in that year to erect a monument to our Columbus and to give it to the city.</p>
   <p>When we have erected this permanent memorial of Italian civilization by honoring the <pb facs="5425702_1_1500.jpg" n="2"/>noble Columbus, the people of this city will feel higher admiration and respect for us in remembering that he who first discovered this new world was a great Italian.</p>
   <p>The monument made by us and erected at our expense will be an honor to Columbus and a rebuke to all our adversaries who are trying falsely to deprive Columbus of credit for priority of discovery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
