<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-05-24">May 24, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Co-Operative Publishing Firm Established</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0342</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0342.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-05-24">May 24, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">CO-OPERATIVE PUBLISHING FIRM ESTABLISHED</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The co-operative publishing company which is to print La Parola has been incorporated under the name of the Italian Labor Publishing Company.</p>
   <p>Last week we received our certificate of incorporation from the State of Illinois. The certificate has been registered in the recorder's office in Cook County.</p>
   <p>The administrative council, which will function for the term of one year, is composed of Dr. A. Molinari, president, C. Pellegrini, secretary, E. Matteoni, C. Bartalini, A. Ruffino, B. Ronchetta and G. Corti. It met last Thursday and passed a resolution to print five thousand copies of the corporation's charter. These are to be circulated among the readers of La Parola.</p>
   <p>It was also decided to issue five thousand shares of stock to sell to readers. It was further resolved to bond the cashier and the other officials, thus assuring the shareholders of the security of their funds.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0343.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have arrived at the point at which we operate without a deficit, and thanks to the coming picnic and the favorable financial results expected of it, it may be possible to have an operating fund in the treasury. We can therefore direct all our energies to propaganda instead of using our space for appeals for funds.</p>
   <p>Our paper has improved beyond all expectations in this last year.</p>
   <p>What it most needs at present is a salaried manager who can give all his time to the fight, which at present is carried on by a few part-time workers.</p>
   <p>Therefore, comrades, you are hereby advised that the co-operative is an accomplished fact and needs only capital in order to function. Forward!</p>
   <p>Corti.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
