<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1928-09">Sept. 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Answer to the Circular of the Royal Minister of National Economy of Italy</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0895</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0895.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1928-09">Sept. 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ANSWER TO THE CIRCULAR OF THE ROYAL MINISTER OF NATIONAL ECONOMY OF ITALY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 1st, 1928, the Chamber had 107 active members residing in Chicago; 20 associat members in the United States; 15 associate members in Italy. Altogether 143 members.</p>
   <p>The active members residing in Chicago at the end of 1927 were 123, but by a decision of the Executive Council, February 28th, it was resolved to drop from the list of active members fifteen who were not in good standing with the treasury.</p>
   <p>For the same reason, some associate members, residing in Italy, were cancelled.</p>
   <p>The number of the associate members in Italy, is supposed to be greater and we believe that the Italian exporters, who are doing business with the United States and are being benefited by the activities of the Chamber, should be encouraged to become regular members, paying the regular dues.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0896.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From a recent estimate made by the Accounting Commission it appeared, that the income from social dues for 1928 was about $2,500.00; the Italian Government subsidy for the past year was $1,080.00, a total of $3,580.00. The expenses for the present year were computed at $4,400.00 which will leave a deficit of $20.00. We are depending on the income from our advertising, celebrations or banquets to clear up that deficit. Our income does not allow us to employ the help needed to take care of the various activities of this Chamber, which with the coming International Exposition of Chicago, will be enlarged.</p>
   <p>Chevalier Italo Emilio Canini, born in Venice, came to the United States in 1876 when very young. He became an American citizen in 1884. He was Secretary of the Royal Italian Consulate of Philadelphia from 1877 to 1882. Then he established himself in the importing business. His first imports from Italy were articles of industrial art. He was the first man to introduce Venetian glassware in America and to represent the Venice-Murano firm of glassware and the mosaics of Dr. Antonio Salvati of Venice.</p>
   <p>As a representative of leading Italian firms he took part in every International Exposition in the United States from Boston in 1883 to that of St. Louis in 1904.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0897.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the Exposition of San Francisco, in 1897, he was Vice-President of the Exporters Association. In 1897 he established himself definitely in Chicago. He is an importer of artistic furniture from Italy and is an agent for many Italian manufacturers.</p>
   <p>He has been a member of this Chamber since 1913 and a councilor, a Vice-President for many years, and President since 1926.</p>
   <p>In his fifty-two years of American life he always protected the rights and interests of Italy with his articles published in many newspapers of which one that deserves to be mentioned is: "What Italians Have Done for the United States", written at the request of the Illinois Manufacturers' Association in 1924.</p>
   <p>John Del Lungo was born in Florence. He took his degree as Doctor of Law at the Royal University of Pisa.</p>
   <p>In 1909 he passed the test for the Consular service. He served as Captain <pb facs="5425702_1_0898.jpg" n="4"/>during the World War and was dangerously wounded. He came to America in 1918, for the first time, as a member of the Propaganda Commission sent here by the Italian Government.</p>
   <p>From 1920 to 1922 he was an agent for a number of American firms in Italy and France. From 1923 to 1925 he was serving on the "General Commissary of Emigration" as an interstate delegate.</p>
   <p>In 1925 he came back to the United States and was Vice-Director of a newspaper, The New Journal, published in San Francisco.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
