<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1923-07-28">July 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">To the Trial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1634</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1634.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1923-07-28">July 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE TRIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last Congress of the Italian Federation, a new project was undertaken. That project, planned and explained in every detail by a group of active comrades, was understood by our comrades, and was immediately accepted - after being studied and scrutinized.</p>
   <p>Its utility of the project and the opportunities it presents were readily recognized, and we are grateful to the comrades of the congress who advanced it.</p>
   <p>Cooperation by all was immediate, and the undertaking from a mere project stage - become a concise idea, easy to realize, an indispensable enterprise on a firm base -.</p>
   <p>The urgent needs of our organization, and the hope for greater advancement, has developed in us the desire to accomplish the establishment of this now necessary enterprise.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1635.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our comrades are convinced of those needs, and that conviction has instilled in them renewed enthusiasm. The work is progressing in an admirable way; the possibility of realization is the air; it is developing in long strides; we [may not] achieve it this time, but -. There is a "but" in it, comrades!</p>
   <p>We need your help, your every effort. No one can refuse; we must be ambitious enough to be the first, because that project which we want to realize, and which is indispensable - is: The House of the People, our home, the house of the Socialists.</p>
   <p>The appeal is cast. It is for their own interest that the comrades must give it serious consideration, with all their will. They can not play deaf, because that would kill our aspiration, that aspiration that is our and their pride.</p>
   <p>There are many good, clever, and humble comrades who already have bought their shares. We expect the same from the others - also good, clever, and <pb facs="5425702_1_1636.jpg" n="3"/>well known comrades - who, as yet, have not performed their duty. But we are sure that they will give their valuable co-operation by buying many shares and selling many others.</p>
   <p>We will explain our project to them in detail, in the columns of this paper. We will ring the alarm-bell to awaken the sleepers. They will awaken, and will help us, because the House of the People, our home, the house of the Socialists, must be built, without any delay - and at whatever cost.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
