<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title><date when="1914-09-13">September 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Result of the Primaries</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title><date when="1914-09-13">September 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE RESULT OF THE PRIMARIES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Interest in the World War has kept a large number of votes away from the polls.</p>
   <p>The election however, proceeded with much strong feeling between the various factions that contended for victory and the fraudulent work combined with the absence of so many from the polls caused many unhappy surprises to some who thought victory an assured thing.</p>
   <p>The Italian candidates--we are sorry to say--did not make the showing that they hoped to make on the basis of the personal regard and esteem in which many are held by the Italian voters.</p>
   <p>The defeat of De Stefano can be understood when one realizes that one of his opponents among the numerous democratic candidates for municipal judge, was Judge Owens, who by legitimate or illegitimate means was able to stop many from voting in the first and second wards.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0637.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>De Stefano lost by a few hundred votes, so that victory might have been his if the disbarred voters in those two wards had been allowed to vote. Other Italians who met defeat were Fred Alonzo, Antonio D'Andrea and Paul Dasso, all three running for County Commissioners. Another Italian defeated in the election was Guiseppe Pirofalo, a candidate for member of Board of Assessors.</p>
   <p>In the 29th Senatorial District, John Durso, candidate for state senator and Guiseppe Farina and D. Cafferata, candidates for state representative were defeated. But it was in the 17th District that the mushroom growth of candidates resulted in the Italian vote being split into many small parts so that no good was done with it whereas fewer candidates might have shown some results.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0638.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In that district the six Italians candidates for representative or senator, were Tony Trinaco, W. A. Navigato, W. Pacelli, A. Fortoriello, Mick Foste and M. A Gioscio.</p>
   <p>The only Italian who had some measure of success was Albert N. Gualano, who won the nomination for Municipal Judge on the Progressive ticket.</p>
   <p>The results in this primary election should be an admonition for the Italians in future elections. They should understand that to win with the Italian vote, it must be concentrated on one candidate alone and not uselessly scattered on many.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
