<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1915-05">May, 1915</date><title level="a">An Old Subject</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0966</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0966.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1915-05">May, 1915</date><title level="a">AN OLD SUBJECT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the June 3rd issue of the commercial newspaper I1 Sole, published in Milan, there appeared an article written by Mr. Emilio Guarini, which I would like to reprint because it expresses the same views published by me in this Bulletin.</p>
   <p>The writer states, "It is a general error for the Italian exporting firms to think that if we have need of them and their products, it is necessary for us to go to Italy." It is really a serious error.</p>
   <p>We think that foreign firms which are in need of our merchandise should come to Italy to buy it, and our exporters wait idly for business to come to them. It is pitiful that even the more important firms remain inert and are doing nothing to expand their commerce and take advantage of the opportunity offered them a few months ago, soon after the start of the war.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0967.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I know that in the the United States, the Americans buy only such products which cannot be found elsewhere, and we are sure that they always prefer the products of any other nation but Italy not excluding Japan, which, in the last few years, has absorbed some of the Italian business in the United States.</p>
   <p>It is wrong to believe that it is only necessary to have a good salesman to do a large business. It means nothing if the business is not repeated because the customer was not satisfied with the quality or price of the products sold. They must know the needs and the Customs of every country and the psychology of its people to establish a permanent success.</p>
   <p>Our industrialists have produced different articles suitable for the European and South American markets but absolutely unfitted for the United States because of the different economic conditions of this country and <pb facs="5425702_1_0968.jpg" n="3"/>because the Americans are accustomed to paying cash and buying what they want instead of accepting what is, offered them.</p>
   <p>The old saying "When in Rome, do as the Romans do" should be the slogan of our exporters if they intend to penetrate and establish their commercial connections in this market.</p>
   <p>Our exporters must study seriously the various markets and send their best products at the best prices with convenient terms for payment. We should also initiate an advertising campaign, sending catalogues and correspondence in the language of the country with which they are dealing.</p>
   <p>In the United States, advertising must be done on a large scale, because when you try to sell products to the Americans, they do not ask: How good are they, but how well are they advertised?</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0969.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>They also expect well-packed articles because they believe in the attractive appearance of the package.</p>
   <p>Thus we recommend to exporters good products, well-packed, at convenient terms, and well advertised to insure the success and stability of their products.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
