<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1922-01-28">Jan. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Communists and Semi-Communists in Our Federation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0415</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0415.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1922-01-28">Jan. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">COMMUNISTS AND SEMI-COMMUNISTS IN OUR FEDERATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italian Socialist Federation, which cost a small group of comrades much labor and many sacrifices, and which is on a par with other organizations, has had to submit to the attacks of its many enemies, who, united in recent times with the Communists, tried in vain to defeat the Federation. The Communist Labor Party News, during the convention in Chicago, carried among the list of delegates, the representatives of the Italian Socialist Federation, whose membership was reported as one thousand. It is to be noted that at the time, our Federation accounted for that number of members, and that it had sent its delegate, John La Soca, to the Convention of the Socialist Party.</p>
   <p>When the fashion was to go with the "left wingers," a member here,and one there, would, in good faith, join the "left wingers," and then voices would insidicusly <pb facs="5425702_1_0416.jpg" n="2"/>try to impress the people with the assertion that the majority of the Italian Socialists in America were deserting the Socialist Party. Some self-styled Socialists and various subversive elements then bellowed with all their strength into that flame with the hope of seeing the Italian Federation reduced to ashes.</p>
   <p>Later, others donned the communistic red, and declared themselves ready to battle the bull of capitalism which they felt themselves ready to drag into the dust. And so, other internal struggles, other arguments, other misunderstandings resulted; and the small raft of the Federation, assailed on all sides by waves that attempted to submerge it, fought against them with tenacity-and did not perish.</p>
   <p>Calm followed the storm, and at the Convention of Oct., 1919, after a heated discussion, an Order of the Day was voted upon and accepted by all-whether middle, left or right "wingers." And to-day, with a membership of one thousand, to which it has held on since 1914, it is the only organization that has been capable of putting up a front against the revolutionary hurricane from the East. A hurricane <pb facs="5425702_1_0417.jpg" n="3"/>which proposed to destroy capitalism, but instead served only to strenghten it, thus weakening the Socialist movement in America.</p>
   <p>Although every now and then a member would leave us for the Communist Party, we still held on to our one thousand members, and it seemed as though we would now live in peace and direct our efforts to the propagation of our ideals, and the struggle against the enemies of suffering humanity. But we again deceived ourselves because a small group of semi-Communists has arisen in New York, under the leadership of Negri, and with calumnies and rank stones, initiated another fight against the Socialist Party and the Federation.</p>
   <p>I call them semi-Communists, because I know them, and because I remember their discussion at the National Convention of the Federation, and at the banquet in West Hoboken given in honor of the delegates.</p>
   <p>Some time ago, a Communistic paper of New York, to prove that one should desert</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0418.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>the Party, published Lazzari's speech at the convention in Milan, as an indication of the right way.</p>
   <p>In America, at one time, the Protestant minister, Bugelli, used the same system of reasoning-instead of arguments. In his lectures, he would say: "God exists because Dante, Mazzini, Colombo, Carducci, etc., believed in him."</p>
   <p>Knowing Lazzari, and also knowing that there are hundreds in Italy equal to him who do not think as he does, I would like to point out that Lazzari still belongs to the Party and submits to the decrees of the majority.</p>
   <p>In their letters, articles and circulars, the neo-Communists speak of the fact that the Socialist Party has failed to join the Third International; of the expulsion of members; of the 50,000 members in the new party-which actually has a membership of less than 5,000; and the ex-secretary of the Socialist Party, who <pb facs="5425702_1_0419.jpg" n="5"/>is very active in the new Party; and of the obligation which the Federation failed to meet-meaning, of course,-the Order of the Day voted upon at the convention of the Italian Socialist Federation.</p>
   <p>They say that the failure of the Socialist Party to join the Third International is childish and worse. There is only one war for the F.I.S. to affiliate itself with the Third International, and that is to enter the Communist Party. Why do they hold back from taking such a step?</p>
   <p>Forward, by God! Have courage and join; put into action the programs which you have trumpeted, and, above all, remember to be consistent because our eye is upon you. We have a right to except you to be consistent, because, just as you attacked the Socialist Party for not joining the Third International, you should also, if sincere, attack and accuse the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, which is not an affiliate of the Red International, branch of the Third International.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0420.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>And as to the expulsions, who can dispute the right of a Party to expel the element that insists on having its own way?</p>
   <p>The First International, of which Marx was the leader, expelled Bakunin-yet you do not attack Marx.</p>
   <p>The Russian Communist Party recently expelled 20 per cent of its members. The Fourth International, according to its manifesto, said that the Third International had expelled the "left wing" element. Why do you not attack the Third International?</p>
   <p>The Order of the Day approved at the National Convention of Oct., 1919, did not stipulate that the Federation would be justified in leaving the Socialist Party if it did not affiliate itself with the Third International.</p>
   <p>The Second International betrayed all the principles of International Socialism.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0421.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The Italian Socialist Federation always has been in accord-in the main-with the program of the Socialist Party of America, and is now and always has been with the "left wing."</p>
   <p>If someone in New York signed a promissory note, that is, an Order of the Day that we did not see, that is an affair that does not concern us; only the semi-Communists are the debtors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
