<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1913-03-23">Mar. 23, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[Criminal Activities of Black Hand]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1659</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.9"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1659.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 9</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1913-03-23">Mar. 23, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[CRIMINAL ACTIVITIES OF BLACK HAND]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An Accomplice's Confessiom Bears the Identity of the Chief of the "Black-Hand" Organization in This City.</p>
   <p>The serious depositions made by the recluse, Chick Nunn, is already known to the public. His confession explains innumerable horrible crimes that happened in the last couple of years among the Italians of this city.</p>
   <p>The treacherous fire on Wentworth Avenue of last Tuesday night, destroying a building at 2359 Wentworth Avenue, causing the death of three persons, victims of the flames, is attributed, without any doubt to the criminal machinations of that mob that strikes in the dark.</p>
   <p>After the authoritative words of the Chicago Tribune in last Wednesday's issue in which it occupied itself largely with the compromising confession <pb facs="5425702_1_1660.jpg" n="2"/>of Chick Nunn, Thursday's issue of the Record Herald also loads its pages, and without any preamble it makes you understand that the police are well informed on that organization.</p>
   <p>We produce Chick Nunn's confession from Thursday's edition of the Record Herald March 20, 1913, which gives the police a good clue to the criminal organization and is as follows:</p>
   <p>The Confession of a Penman.</p>
   <p>The Record Herald giving Chick Nunn's confession in substance, is said to have been as follows:</p>
   <p>That a thoroughly organized Sicilian Mafiusi exists in Chicago and has headquarters in the West Twenty-third Street Station. It has enlisted a score of male and female criminals of other nationalities and has branched out from <pb facs="5425702_1_1661.jpg" n="3"/>ordinary "Black Hand" letter operations to the field of forgery and arson. That a man, ostensibly an excommunicated Italian priest, master of fourteen languages, owner of a macaroni factory, of several disreputable houses and interested in two banks and who poses as a notary and professional bondsman, is head of the band. That in reality the leader is a man well known in Italian circles, but who attends no Camorrist meetings and attempts to dictate only in international relations with the "Black Hand" of other countries.</p>
   <p>That the excommunicated priest leader of the band was convicted of counterfeiting dimes some-time ago and was sent to Joliet. At the expiration of his term he returned to Chicago and sought out his betrayer, killing him with a "sawed-off shot gun." This is said to be the origin of the use of the death-dealing weapon.</p>
   <p>That murders and cutthroats are trained by this leader in the ways of exacting tribute and are dispatched to New Orleans, Kansas City, St. Louis, Washington, Toledo and Cleveland to operate. They do not enter the New York City <pb facs="5425702_1_1662.jpg" n="4"/>field, through an agreement with the Mafia of that city.</p>
   <p>These are succinctly the main accusations based on the depositions of the recluse, Chick Nunn. If the truth of the charges in the deposition can be substantiated, it will be possible to send more than one to jail.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
