<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'avanti</title>,
<date when="1919-03-01">Mar. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Propaganda and Amusement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Avanti</title>,
<date when="1919-03-01">Mar. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">PROPAGANDA AND AMUSEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, February 23, a dramatic performance was given at the Hull House Theatre by the Italian Socialist Section of the 19th ward.</p>
   <p>The sketch "Intimate Drama," by comrade Serafino Lami, and the satirical comedy "The Colonial Revival," by the excellent author T. Lucidi, were presented.</p>
   <p>"Intimate Drama" justly condemns the barbarous custom, the pitiless tradition of binding the heart of a maiden to the first ruffian who comes along, cynically (sic) displaying those financial requirements which will purchase her father's consent to the marriage. No consideration whatsoever is allowed the poor victim, who in many instances will succumb prematurely to such a calamity.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1217.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Among the customs and traditions of the barbarous ages, that of the conventional marriage is perhaps the most barbarous - inasmuch as it extinguishes in a virgin that vivifying spark called love - which has ever been the sage and gentle promoter of human development.</p>
   <p>Against this remnant of savagery, our comrade Lami has directed his keen criticism, analyzing the errors of modern life and employing a witty and flowing style.</p>
   <p>Our friend, T. Lucidi, in his "Colonial Revival," endeared himself greatly to all those who have at heart the real colonial interests of Italy.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1218.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>His eloquent satire mercilessly flays prominent, but ignorant and conceited citizens; political racketeers; dishonest bankers; haughty, foolish ladies.</p>
   <p>Both playwrights were called to the front of the stage several times and their ideas were interpreted faithfully by the actors.</p>
   <p>Comrades Meucci and Rossi were excellent - the one, in portraying the lover who is entitled to spontaneous, non-purchasable love, the kind that flows from a passionate heart - the second, in playing the role of the husband, who acquired his barbarous rights over the heart and body of the maiden through the connivance of the no less barbarous laws on marriage.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1219.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mrs. Ester Lami, the noted artist was also warmly applauded.</p>
   <p>Financially, the show was quite a failure.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
