<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1894-09-08">September 8, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">To Young Italian Voters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0621</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0621.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1894-09-08">September 8, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">To Young Italian Voters</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italia has a word for young Italian voters who will cast their ballots for the first time this year. Begin your career as American citizens should. The Democratic Party is not the party for intelligent and progressive young men. It is not the party for men who love free institutions and demand a chance to use their abilities to the best advantage. It is the party which, for years, upheld slavery. It is the party that plunged the Nation into a bloody and needless War. It is the Party that attempted to flood the country with worthless money. It is the Party that maintains its rules at the South by means of shotgun terrorism, and in the North by means of fraud. It is the Party of Jeff. Davis, and Boss Tweed. It is the Party that has brought the Republic to its present deplorable condition.</p>
   <p>The Republican Party, on the other hand, has a record which is part of all that is splendid in the history of the Western hemisphere. It saved the Republic from dis-Union. It freed the colored-race. It gave Abraham Lincoln to mankind. It has been the bulwark of American honor at home and abroad. It has built up American Industries and settled the Western deserts. It contains a vast majority of the decent and intelligent citizens of the country. It is the champion of public <pb facs="5425702_1_0622.jpg" n="2"/>schools and free education. It is the friend of the oppressed people of the Old World.</p>
   <p>In a word, the Republican Party is a Party of the People, by the People, and for the People. In the coming election it is the Party that is bound to win. Let young Italian voters flock around the Republican banner; a banner under which the noblest Italian patriots would have felt it an honor to serve. Let these voters commence their career as American Citizens, under an American Party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
