<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1928-09">September, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Answer to the Circular of the Royal Minister of National Economy of Italy</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0899</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0899.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
<date when="1928-09">September, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ANSWER TO THE CIRCULAR OF THE ROYAL MINISTER OF NATIONAL ECONOMY OF ITALY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We publish in its entirety a report which we sent to the Minister of National Economy at its request.</p>
   <p>It is deduced from official data, furnished to us by the office of the Custom House of Chicago, a prospectus giving synthetically and clearly the movement of imports from Italy in the Chicago District.</p>
   <p>This report of ours edited carefully and laboriously, is a real example of the activities of our Chamber for a greater development of the commercial relation between Italy and the United States, despite of limited financial means at her disposition, and in spite of the apathy of some Italians residing here, who for personal reasons refuse to give their support and cooperation to our institution which has twenty-one years of existence behind it.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0900.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>HISTORICAL SKETCH OF THE CHAMBER AND ITS ACTIVITIES.</p>
   <p>The Italian Chamber of Commerce was established in 1907 through the initiative of the Royal Consul Chevalier Guido Sabetta, and with the assistance of Italian merchants of this city.</p>
   <p>October 5, of that year, the first general meeting was held, in the presence of Chevalier Montagna representing the Royal Embassy, and the first Executive Council was elected.</p>
   <p>The Italian Chamber of Commerce of Chicago is operating under the laws of the State of Illinois and was incorporated with a charter of the Secretary of State in October 12, 1907, and officially recognized by the Italian Government in 1912.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0901.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Through the efforts of various succeeding administrations since its foundation, the Chamber has always kept to the rules established in its constitution when promoting facilitating and protecting the Commercial relations between Italy and the United States, and by cooperating in every way to strengthen the friendship between the two peoples.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Tribune, a newspaper which generally shows very little sympathy for the Italians living here, or in Italy; in an article published January 18, 1914, gave the following account of the undertaking of our Association:</p>
   <p>"In Chicago there exists an association which is strongly and effectively working to tie more securely the relations between the two nations. The organization is looking into the future, not forgetting the past, and tries by every means to increase the commerce between Italy and the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0902.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Italian Chamber of Commerce of Chicago has inspired much confidence in the business men for its capacity and cleverness in trying to increase not only the commerce of its members, but of every one else who asks for advice and needs its help without cost.</p>
   <p>The attachment which this institution, composed of Italian-born members, naturalized American citizens, has for the mother country is proved by various activities accomplished, among which we mention the following:- On the immigration question it has supported and still supports the necessity of eliminating race discrimination. During the World War it cooperated with the Royal Consul General in making well known the merits and rights of Italy. It entertained every special commission which came to Chicago; took part in Italian Day at the pro-Allied Bazaar; gave money to the Italian and American Red Cross, and bought Italian and American war loan bonds. In the Fiume question it started a campaign to present President Wilson with a petition, signed by 150,000 persons of Italian origin, in which he was asked to support the annexation of that city to the Italian Kingdom.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0903.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Our institution celebrated the victory of our armies with the intervention of civil and military officials of the Nation, the State, and the City, and the diplomatic representative of the allied nations.</p>
   <p>THE COMMEMORATION OF THE VI CENTENNIAL OF DANTE.</p>
   <p>It established an Italian section at the Pageant Exposition of Chicago in 1922, where our exhibit made a rich showing of Italian products.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0904.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The assistance sent through the Italian Government to the victims of the Calabria, Messina, Toscana and Avezzano earthquake.</p>
   <p>THE CAMPAIGN AGAINST THE FORDNEY BILL FOR THE CUSTOM TARIFF.</p>
   <p>The campaign against the restriction of immigration. The campaign in favor of the law, which authorized the Secretary of the Treasury to refund importers the money, which they paid in excess for duty on merchandise received before September 22, 1922.</p>
   <p>The protest to President Harding against the American "Cotton Seed Trustees Association" which asked the Government to increase the duty on Olive Oil imported from Italy.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0905.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>In 1926, when the Senate in Washington was discussing the agreement on Italian war debts to the United States, this Chamber accomplished much that was favorable to Italy.</p>
   <p>This Chamber receives daily a great number of requests for commercial information, and so forth, to which the Secretary answers promptly and satisfactorily.</p>
   <p>The Chamber, since its first existence, established an agricultural section to investigate all the propositions made to the Italians with the ideas of forming new colonies.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0906.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The presidents of this Chamber since its foundation have been as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Chev. Francesco Cuneo</cell>
     <cell>1907 - 1910</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Chev. Andrea Russo</cell>
     <cell>1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Chev. Francesco Cuneo</cell>
     <cell>1913 - 1915</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mr. Emilio Longhi</cell>
     <cell>1916 - 1917</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Chev. Francesco Bragno</cell>
     <cell>1918 - 1921</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mr. Emilio Longhi</cell>
     <cell>1922</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Chev. Uff Giovanni Rigoli</cell>
     <cell>1923 - 1925</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Chev. Italo Emilio Canini, still in office.</p>
   <p>(To be continued)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
