<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Farinacci, M. G., "<title level="a">The Italian Language in our Public Schools</title>,"
<title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title> (Monthly), <date when="1928-09">September 1928</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Farinacci, M. G., "<title level="a">The Italian Language in our Public Schools</title>,"
<title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title> (Monthly), <date when="1928-09">September 1928</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are pleased to note that the Board of Education of this city after having named three new schools in memory of Verdi, Volta and Tonti, has through the untiring efforts of the Chevalier Oscar Durante, a member of the Board and one of our prominent leaders, added to the curriculum of McKinley and Austin High schools the study of the Italian language. This is only an experiment and we hope that it will be taken seriously by the young students of Italian birth.</p>
   <p>Statistics show that throughout the country the universities and secondary schools offering courses in Italian grammar and literature have enrolled in this branch of study only twenty-two per cent students of Italian parentage and, that the highest awards are received by students <pb facs="5425702_1_0091.jpg" n="2"/>who have never before heard or come in contact with the language. The reason for this low average can be attributed to the fact that many Italians are so confident of their knowing the language that in class they pay little or no attention to the trying efforts of the professors and teachers.</p>
   <p>But do they really know the Italian language? The rythmic, romantic, euphonic language of Dante, Ariosto, Tasso, Carducci? No. They can only speak and at that very poorly, the rough dialect which has come to them through their parents, or the Americanized Italian phrases which they have coined.</p>
   <p>They will be surprised to find a great difference both in tone and <pb facs="5425702_1_0092.jpg" n="3"/>structure, if they apply their minds to its study rather than take the subject lightly and in a haphazard fashion. They will note how the charming words intermingle into rythmic phrases forming sentences of exceptional tone, clear and concise. They will discover the ease of pronunciation, the graceful and simple method of enunciating which is found in very few other languages. They will find treasures of love, romance and adventure throughout the epic and lyric poems and the swaying prose of the many writers which Italy has given to the world. In all, they will find it a language of rare beauty, simple but majestic, clear, bright, unobscured, unparalleled by any other.</p>
   <p>We anxiously await the outcome of this experiment and hope that the many students of Italian birth will be proud of this opportunity offered them and take advantage of it, conscientiously and appreciatively.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
