<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1922-08-05">Aug. 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">25,000 Chicago and Elevated Workers on Strike</title><title level="a" type="sub">Whose Is the Blame?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0272</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0272.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Del Popolo</title>,
<date when="1922-08-05">Aug. 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">25,000 CHICAGO AND ELEVATED WORKERS ON STRIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Whose Is the Blame?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Surface and Elevated workers of Chicago, numbering 25, 000, have refused to submit to a wage cut and are out on strike.</p>
   <p>They voted to strike only when they realized the impossibility of coming to an agreement with the transportation companies over their impossible demands.</p>
   <p>For twelve days union officials worked towards a just compromise with company officials, local authorities, and commercial assocations in order to avoid a strike. The union officials had conceded many points in the controversy, one of which was an agreement to accept a ten percent cut in wages, but the companies, which are trying to regain the income lost when the State Commission decreed a one cent cut in fares, would not listen to reason.</p>
   <p>They insisted on the wage reduction to the extent which they had proposed. This would place the workers in the position of making up to the companies the total loss which they suffered when the Commission decreed a cut in fares from eight to seven cents.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0273.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The strike, therefore, is the result of the insatiable greed of the companies. Now the bourgeois newspapers will not fail to bemoan the suffering of "Poor Public" (poor public in truth when it is served by a bourgeous press subservient to capitalism), but no citizen of Chicago who has followed the trend of this contest between capital and labor will miss the opportunity of convincing himself that the blame for the suffering resulting from the strike is to be given entirely to the transportation companies.</p>
   <p>We, convinced of the justice of the worker's cause, express our most unconditional support for their complete and immediate victory, inviting comrades and readers to assist the strikers even at the cost of individual financial sacrifices until the workers' rights are recognized.</p>
   <p>The most efficacious medium for assisting the strikers is to boycott the "scab" transportation service in case the companies should go to that extreme.</p>
   <p>The duration of the strike depends not only on the solidarity of the workers, but also on the attitude of the public towards this just cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
