<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy</title>,
Vol. VIII, No. 8. <date when="1930-05">May, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">True to His Mission</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy</title>,
Vol. VIII, No. 8. <date when="1930-05">May, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">TRUE TO HIS MISSION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When last November we welcomed Comm. Dr. Mario Carosi in Chicago, we, from the pages of the Bulletin, formulated the hope that, true to his mission and to the fame that preceded him, he would perform fully, indiscriminately and courageously, all the acts that would defend and uphold the cause and the prestige of the Italian colony in our state. Cuddled in the belief that our honest efforts to become an integral part of and to identify ourselves with the life of this country and that our unchallengeable record of the moral and material contribution to the greater glory of America had silenced the biased propaganda of unfriendly newspapers and irresponsible petty office-holders, we hoped also that the Royal Italian Consul General should never be forced to remind certain peoples, who owe to an Italian genius, and to the Italian initiative, the privilege of being today citizens of a great and free country, the primary principle of hospitality and a sense of justice.</p>
   <p>But what we thought had become a carcass, whose only claims to remembrance were due to its pestiferous exhalation, from time to time gives spasmodic symptoms of life, and stung by truth - untrammeled facts and statistical figures - spits falsehoods as a reptile spits poison.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0166.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Actuated by resentment for the progress made by the Italians here and abroad, and fearing that the average, basking in the sunshine of a fictitious and superimposed equality is destined to be eliminated by the excellent, certain newspapers have represented a vulgar campaign of vilification against our race. To them have forcefully answered the Italian newspapers.</p>
   <p>But when some members of the police force slurred the honorable reputation of a section of the Italian people, calling them a bunch of criminals, to them answered the Royal Italian Consul General. We are glad to publish the letter that Comm. Carosi addressed to the Chief of Police of Chicago and to heartily congratulate him for the dignified and firm protest against accusation directed to hurt the peoples he represents.</p>
   <p>F. D.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
