<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Tribuna Italiana</title>,
<date when="1904-06-18">June 18, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Laud the Church Enemies</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0228</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0228.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Tribuna Italiana</title>,
<date when="1904-06-18">June 18, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">LAUD THE CHURCH ENEMIES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is the title of an editorial which appeared in last week's edition of the New World, the organ of the Arch Diocese of Chicago. In this article our newspaper is referred to as follows:</p>
   <p>"If we must believe our eyes, an Italian Catholic weekly newspaper is needed in our colony. We believe it to be an absolute necessity. What will the Catholic world think of a newspaper that pretends to be secular and that persistently praises the plunderer of the church? What will be thought of the impartiality of a newspaper that perpetually sings to the so-called glory of Garibaldi? We do not know, but we know that in Chicago there are many thousands of Italian Catholics that need an aggressive Catholic weekly newspaper, published in their own language and not afraid to tell the truth."</p>
   <p>We thank, very heartily, our colleague for the praise conferred on the Tribuna Italiana, but we refute the insinuation that this paper occasionally attacks the doctrines of the church because it is not the truth. If the <pb facs="5425702_1_0229.jpg" n="2"/>New World believes that they have doped the patriotism of the Italian colony of Chicago with saints, madonnas, societies, cliques, confraternities, parochial schools, etc., we assure them that they are greatly deceived.</p>
   <p>The monument of Garibaldi, in Lincoln Park, the Dante Aleghieri Society of Chicago, the celebration of the historic date of September 20, and other patriotic dates, and the protest to the Board of Education, are demonstrations of our nationalism. The Italian Catholic newspaper, which the New World suggests, shows the editor to be a fanatic Irishman and only he could write it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
