<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1927-05">May 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A Lecture by Dr. Comba</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1436</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1436.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1927-05">May 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A LECTURE BY DR. COMBA</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On March 20, sponsored by the Valdesian Society of Chicago, a lecture was delivered at Garibaldi Institute by the distinguished Valdesian, Dr. Guido Comba.</p>
   <p>People in large numbers attended especially the members of the society. A selected musical program was rendered and the choir of Samaritan House, of which Rev. Melardi is the pastor, sang with the distinguished singer, Mrs. Peterson of the Garibaldi Institute Choir.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1437.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Alfred Barr and Mr. Goodman said a few words, both manifesting their sympathy and esteem for Italy and the Italians. The Rev. P. R. De Carlo, pastor of St. John Presbyterian Church, operating in conjunction with the Garibaldi Institute, was the chairman for the evening and introduced Dr. Comba with appropriate words.</p>
   <p>Dr. Comba then addressed the audience. He said that more than giving a lecture he would try to inform the public of the activities and the civic, religious and moral efforts made by the Valdesian Church among the Italian people. He spoke of the persecutions the Valdesian church suffered, and of the sacrifices made by the Valdesians to spread the Voice of the Gospel among the mountainers of the Italian Alps.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1438.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He related the vast program which the Valdesians are accomplishing in Italy. The aim of the lecture was to raise funds to finance the extended civil, religious, and moral program made by the Valdesians for needy Italians.</p>
   <p>Those present responded generously and contributed to the collection made by the Rev. P. R. De Carlo and the Rev. Merlandi.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
