<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Volume IV, <date when="1911">1911</date>, No. 4.
<title level="a">(Report of the President)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1038</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1038.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Volume IV, <date when="1911">1911</date>, No. 4.
<title level="a">(REPORT OF THE PRESIDENT)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>I am glad to announce to you our progress from the time of the last assembly until today. During these last months, we thought it necessary to increase the membership to intensify the propaganda in Italy so that the Italian commercialists will contribute more generously to the chamber's existence. If it is a useful institution for the prestige of the Italian Colony of Chicago and, in a direct or indirect way, contributes to intensify and facilitate commerce between America and Italy, it should also be worthy of consideration by the Italian exporters and producers.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1039.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A great number of letters have been sent by Italian private commercialists, commercial institutions, and governmentofficials requiring information, lists of addresses, samples, and so forth, which shows that they understand the importance of the Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce. It must also be announced that the Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce was worthy represented at the Congress of the Italian Chambers of Commerce of Foreign Countries, held in Rome last June by Prof. Ausonio Franzoni, who also represented the New York and Buenos Aires Chambers of Commerce.</p>
   <p>This makes us feel that our chamber has gained considerable moral advantages. Our Bulletin has made satisfactory progress. Since January three copies have been issued. It can be compared with any other Bulletin abroad. We have noticed with pleasure, that some American papers have <pb facs="5425702_1_1040.jpg" n="3"/>expressed good opinions of the Bulletin. The Association of Chicago, an official organ newspaper, has reproduced one of our articles and its editor has declared in a letter that our Bulletin helps greatly to facilitate commerce between America and Italy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
