<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1933-08">August, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Echoes of the Dedication of the Monument to Christopher Columbus</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1488</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1488.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo American National Union</title>,
<date when="1933-08">August, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">ECHOES OF THE DEDICATION OF THE MONUMENT TO CHRISTOPHER COLUMBUS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The gigantic monument erected to the honor and glory of Christopher Columbus was solemnly dedicated on August 3, which was also Italian Day, at A Century of Progress Exposition of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Most noted among the speakers were His Excellency Augusto Russo, Italian Ambassador to Washington, Governor Olson of Minnesota, and Gold Medal Hero, Dr. Giuseppe Castruccio, Italian Consul in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The greatness of the spectacle was due to the untiring efforts of our president Joseph Imburgio, who as chairman of the Italian societies and sodalities in Chicago was able to gather and keep united with discipline, hundreds of societies and thousands of flags and standards, followed by a parade of more than 30,000 members. The 55 lodges of the Italo-American National with 110 flags and 55 standards were at the head of the interminable cortege which paraded from Grand Park to the Hall of Science within the Exposition grounds.</p>
   <p>After a short talk by Chevalier Paul Colliani, His Excellency Augusto Russo was handed the scissors with which he severed the tri-colored ribbon, thereby officially opening to traffic, Columbus Drive.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1489.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Following the inauguration of the Columbus monument and Columbus Drive, the program was continued with a program of vocal music, in which John Paul-Gasar sang "Giovinezza" and the "Star Spangled Banner."</p>
   <p>Messages were received from Mussolini, President Roosevelt, and Mayor Kelly. Mayor La Guardia of New York City sent a message over the radio.</p>
   <p>To Paul-Gasar, Chicago Italian tenor, goes the credit for the presentation of the opera "Aida" on an improvised stage of the Hall of Science. Others in the cast besides Paul-Gasar, were Anna Roselle, Ada Paggi, Carl Formes, and Mantorani Gennaro Papi conducted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
