<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy</title> in America - State of Illinois,
<date when="1936-03">March 1936</date>.
<title level="a">A Banquet in Recognition of Their Efforts</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0037</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0037.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy In America - State of Illinois</title>,
<date when="1936-03">March 1936</date>.
<title level="a">A BANQUET IN RECOGNITION OF THEIR EFFORTS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A banquet, the first of a series, which promises to become an annual event, will be given under auspices of the Order Sons of Italy in America in the State of Illinois, October 12, to all the young men and young women of Italian birth, or descent, who will receive in 1936 a diploma from any university in America, providing they are residents of this State, Illinois.</p>
   <p>The Grand Venerable, Chevalier George J. Spatuzza, having performed well and thoroughly the fundamental duty of assuring to the Order its financial stability, conceived the idea of the banquet and submitted it to the approval of the Grand Council at its meeting last February 24.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0038.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>By it, in an unmistakable way, he gave expression to the high cconception in which he holds the Order and for which he has coined a slogan: "The duties are reserved for the members. The benefits are extended to all the Italian community".</p>
   <p>In prospecting his idea the Grand Venerable added: "It is my earnest desire that the day to be fixed for the banquet should coincide with the epoch-making one of the discovery of America: With that memorable day, which for us Italians is an inexhaustible source of pride, and for the rest of the valuable benefits that have been reaped from the inspired act of this, our great Italian genius. It will be our privilege and our cherished wish to affirm on that occasion, in the most solemn and befitting manner, that the solidarity of our race, cemented by adversities and triumphs, remains still unchanged as it has been unchangeable throughout the centuries.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0039.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And we wish to assert it on that day when, in the simplicity of his soul, the immigrant, recalling the memory of the greatest explorer of all times, through him perceives the numberless glories that are ours, and that no hostile and base propaganda can efface or contaminate.</p>
   <p>And while the immigrant rejoices, hopes and prays that his Italy may always achieve everlasting glory, we, who have espoused his cause, will initiate with a symbolic send-off, his son or daughter into the social and political life of the country.</p>
   <p>We also mean by this noble gesture inspired by a disinterested principle of brotherhood, to confer deserved value on that conspicuous contribution of Latin intelligence and initiative, that the offspring of the immigrant is ready to offer to this land so dear to us, because it is the land of Columbus, <pb facs="5425702_1_0040.jpg" n="4"/>Vespecci, Verrazzano, Toriti, Vigo, Meucci, and many others, who are too numerous to be mentioned. The suggestion was unanimously approved by the Grand Council which resolved to accept also, in that connection, another important suggestion made by the Grand Venerable which completes and enhances the previous one. It was resolved that on that occasion funds be raised for the endowment of one or more scholarships to be assigned to those students of Italian birth or extraction, who during the year have obtained the best average in their study at any high school of the state.</p>
   <p>Of its own initiative and with the purpose of encouraging the study of the Italian language in our schools, the Grand Council also approved the conferring of prizes, (the nature of which is to be determined), to those boys or girls irrespective of their nationality, who have, during the year, obtained the best average in the study of Italian.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
