<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title>,
<date when="1932-11">Oct. Nov. 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Our Duty Towards the Italian Candidates</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0630</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0630.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Bulletin Italo American National Union</title>,
<date when="1932-11">Oct. Nov. 1932</date>.
<title level="a">OUR DUTY TOWARDS THE ITALIAN CANDIDATES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the April issue of our Bulletin we wrote as follows: "Our Association is not political for the sake of politics, but for that spirit of unity that should exist among our countrymen. Whenever the occasion presents itself, it gives recommendations as to the type of candidate, in order to familiarize our members and their families with the necessity for a solid political front."</p>
   <p>Our duty is to support all candidates who are members of our organization, and at the same time vote for all other Italian candidates who, although not brother members, are entitled to our confidence and support. Our stand in this respect follows the principle that it is much better to help an Italian gain a political administrative position always assuming of course that he is deserving of the honor, than to assist a stranger who might be hostile to us.</p>
   <p>It is necessary that we do this to gain the position in America to which we are entitled. This we can obtain gradually by constantly persevering with the weapon of the vote. One does not need to know, personally, every Italian candidate in order to vote for him; to know him by reputation is sufficient.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0631.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We recommend the following candidates: Judge John A. Sbarbaro, Republican candidate for Judge of the Municipal Court; Hon. N. J. Bonnelli, Democrat, candidate for Judge of the Municipal Court; Judge Francis Allegretti, Democrat, candidate for Judge of the Supreme Court; Peter Granata, Republican, candidate for Congressman of the 8th Congressional District; and Joseph E. Larina, Republican candidate for State Representative from the 29th District.</p>
   <p>All other Italian candidates are equally recommended.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
