<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-09-27">Sept. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Statute and Regulations of the Italian Labor Publishing Company</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0329</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0329.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1913-09-27">Sept. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">STATUTE AND REGULATIONS OF THE ITALIAN LABOR PUBLISHING COMPANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Article 1.</p>
   <p>Title</p>
   <p>Section 1. A society has been formed with unlimited capital acquired by the sale of shares, to be located in Chicago, Illinois, and incorporated under the name of the Italian Labor Publishing Co.</p>
   <p>Purpose</p>
   <p>Section 2. The purpose of I. L. P. C., shall be to provide the Italian Federation of the Socialist Party of America with a printing establishment for the publishing of newspapers, books, pamphlets, etc., which publications are to be used to educate in the principals of International Socialism the Italian immigrants in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0330.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Capital and Shares:</p>
   <p>Section 3. The capital of the I. L. P. C., shall consist of shares at a value of five dollars each, without interest, and redeemable one year from the date of functioning of the enterprise.</p>
   <p>The shares, however, can be paid back after the first year, at the written request of the shareholder, with six years subscription to the Parola Dei Socialisti, or with books to the value of six dollars; these books to be chosen from the library of the Italian Federation of the Socialist Party.</p>
   <p>All shares for which payment is made become the property of the Italian Federation of the Socialist Party until the dissolving of the Society.</p>
   <p>Article Two.</p>
   <p>Administration</p>
   <p>Section 1. The I. L. P. C. shall be administered by an Executive Council consisting of a president, secretary, treasurer and four councilmen elected <pb facs="5425702_1_0331.jpg" n="3"/>every year at a general meeting.</p>
   <p>All officers of the council are eligible for re-election.</p>
   <p>Powers of the Council.</p>
   <p>Section 2. The Executive Council shall have the power to buy and sell, to redeem shares which it thinks best to redeem before or after five years, from the date of functioning of the enterprise, as well as all powers relative to the operation of the enterprise, such as hiring and firing of employes, etc. It cannot in any way modify or add to the present statute, that being the prerogative of the members when called to a special or ordinary meeting.</p>
   <p>Duties of the Officers.</p>
   <p>Section 3. The president shall preside at all meetings of the Council and it shall be his duty to attend regularly and assure efficient administration.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0332.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>He shall sign all official reports as well as the shares which are released.</p>
   <p>No share shall be valid without the signature of the president.</p>
   <p>Section 4. The secretary shall handle all correspondence, write all reports of the meetings of the Council and the extraordinary sessions of the members, and he shall also call general meetings of the members.</p>
   <p>Section 5. The treasurer shall have handling of all moneys; he shall be keeper of all unsold shares. All moneys which he receives is to be deposited in a bank designated by the Council in the name of the I. L. P. C. He shall not at any time have more than fifty dollars in his possession. At each meeting of the Council he shall give a verbal or written report of all moneys received from the sale of shares, to whom sold, and the amounts on deposit and on hand. The shares, to be valid, <pb facs="5425702_1_0333.jpg" n="5"/>must carry the signature of the treasurer as well as that of the president.</p>
   <p>The treasurer shall also furnish bond. The expenses he incurs in the course of his duties shall be paid by the I. L. P. C., from the treasury.</p>
   <p>Section 6. General assembly shall be called once a year and the agenda shall be sent to all members one month before the day of the meeting.</p>
   <p>Any member shall have the right to be represented by another member merely by giving him a written mandate to that effect. All members have a right to vote for officers of the Executive Council. Members who live too far away to attend the meeting, may vote by sending a list containing the names of candidates for whom they wish to vote.</p>
   <p>The list containing the names of the candidates shall be mailed to the members one month before the meeting, with the notice of the meeting enclosed.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0334.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Article Three.</p>
   <p>Section 1. When the society has accomplished its mission, and all shares have either been paid for or have become the property of the Italian Federation of the Socialist Party, the Executive Council may dissolve the Society and all the capital will become the property of the Federation.</p>
   <p>Section 2. If within a reasonable length of time it should become evident that the funds collected are not sufficient for proper functioning of the society, the members by a majority vote at an extraordinary session shall decide as to the best way of disposing of the money on hand.</p>
   <p>Section 3. The present statute may be amended, modified or corrected only by a majority vote of the members called to an extraordinary session, or by referendum. But for no reason or condition can Sec 2, Article 1, be modified or changed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
