<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1931-04">April 1931</date>, p. 29.
<title level="a">"The Inauguration of the New Offices of the Banco Di Napoli Trust Company."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0884</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0884.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1931-04">April 1931</date>, p. 29.
<title level="a">"THE INAUGURATION OF THE NEW OFFICES OF THE BANCO DI NAPOLI TRUST COMPANY."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The inauguration of the renovated premises of the Banco di Napoli Trust Company of Chicago turned out to be quite an event of Italianism for the number and class of people who attended.</p>
   <p>The premises was decorated with flowers and banners. The Italian Consul General Dr Castruccio always present at every demonstration which is to the interest of the Italian people delivered a speech which elicited much enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>Chev. Eduardo Maglione, Director of the Banco di Napoli, gave a talk.</p>
   <p>All countrymen were urged to support morally and financially the only bank in Chicago which is Italian in name, interest and character.</p>
   <p>The press was represented by our colleagues Chev. Rossi, Chev. Mastrovalerio, N. Lofranco, C. Meola, D. Stefani, C. Catalano and our co-editor, Bellaria.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0885.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We print the following letter sent to us by Chev. Magliane:</p>
   <p>To our clients and friends: We are glad to inform you that the Trust Department of the Banco di Napoli Trust Company of Chicago is organized and ready to offer you the following services:</p>
   <p>1. To act as Executive Trustee in care of a will, where inheritance is concerned and the beneficiary named in the will.</p>
   <p>2. After legal appointment has been made, by a competent court, to act as administrator of inheritance of the people who died interstate and who have not appointed an executor.</p>
   <p>3. Administer titles and real estate of private individuals or of corporations. This is a convenient service for those who travel or for the businessmen who have no time to attend to these matters personally.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0886.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>4. Act as a Trustee for those tho want to save a specified amount of money, titles or anything else and administer it for their benefit or for one or more relatives. This service is very convenient for those who want to insure the future of the wife or want to accumulate a dowry for the daughter or insure the education of the children.</p>
   <p>5. Act as a guardian and Trustee for the real estate pertaining to minors, the mentally incompetent, or to people who are legally incapable of administering their property.</p>
   <p>6. Collect, from the insurance company, after the death of the insured, the premium and keep it in trust for the beneficiary, and apportion to the same the capital as well as the interest in accordance with the instruction received.</p>
   <p>Our Trust Department is at your disposal in furnishing you all necessary information and advice.</p>
   <p>We guarantee discretion for any question or advices desired.</p>
   <p>(Signed) E. Magliane, Director."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
