<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1915-06-27">June 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">[Club Contributes to Red Cross]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0742</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0742.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1915-06-27">June 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">[CLUB CONTRIBUTES TO RED CROSS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italian Alpine Gun Club held a meeting last Wednesday in Vittoria Hall on Western Ave. and Madison St. at 2 P. M., to raise funds by subscription for the Italian Red Cross. The Italian Consul Conte Bolegnesi was also present.</p>
   <p>At the opening of the meeting the following order of the day was approved:</p>
   <p>"We, Italian American citizens of Chicago, and of all Italian provinces, and elements of the Italian Colony of Chicago, must support our great and noble King Victor Emmanuel III, his people, and their intrepid, loyal and honorable acts, in declaring war on Austria. The purpose of this war is to redeem from slavery the provinces of Trento and Trieste, and the City of Dalmazia - all Italian.</p>
   <p>"We, in our hearts, profoundly deplore a war that menaces the lives of our Italian soldiers, many of whom will never return to their homes, while many will return wounded and maimed for life.</p>
   <p>"We Italian American citizens of Chicago, wish to show our most warm feelings and profound sympathy for our fatherland, and solemnly promise to do all <pb facs="5425702_1_0743.jpg" n="2"/>in our power to alleviate the sufferings of our country, men who are fighting at the front, their families, widows and orphans.</p>
   <p>"For such a purpose we donate to the Delegation of the Italian Red Cross of Chicago the sum of $1,500., which has been raised by the members of the Italian Alpine Gun Club among their friends (besides another sum of $1,500. presented by other members of the said club).</p>
   <p>"Finally, we approve a vote of thanks to the American press for the impartial items published concerning Italy in the war and its story, eulogizing the Italian Minister of Foreign Affairs for his publication of Libro Verde (Green Book) in which he declares that our fatherland did not go to war for the purpose of acquiring more territory, but to redeem our brethren tyrannized and oppressed by Austria against the most elementary laws of justice of right, and of nationality.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Barto Chiappe</p>
   <p>Italian Alpine Gun Club President of Chicago, 1658 West VanBuren St."</p>
   <p>At the end of the session it was unanimously decided to send the following despatch to the King of Italy:</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0744.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"To his Majesty,</p>
   <p>Victor Emanuel III,</p>
   <p>King of Italy.</p>
   <p>Italian American citizens of Chicago united today at a mass-meeting in the Vittoria Hall, and expressed to your Majesty that for intelligence and valour you have earned the veneration and admiration of all Italians scattered throughout the world, and our eternal love and support.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Barto Chiappe</p>
   <p>Italian Alpini Gun Club Pres. of Chicago</p>
   <p>1658 W. Van Buren Street"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
