<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Il Corriere Italico</title>,
<date when="1927-03-20">Mar. 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A Friendly Appeal for a Weekly Newspaper</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Il Corriere Italico</title>,
<date when="1927-03-20">Mar. 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A FRIENDLY APPEAL FOR A WEEKLY NEWSPAPER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This monthly paper is maintained by its friends. Its very success is positive proof that it has friends in abundance. Except for our friends our little journal might have gone the way of other monthly publications. For the loyalty of our friends and for the support which they have given us we render due gratitude and appreciation.</p>
   <p>The popularity of a newspaper depends upon the interest which it creates among its friends and readers. The character of its editorials is most important. Each issue must offer editorial comment of particular interest on some subject. It must have special articles by competent writers to increase its power and its attractiveness. It must offer cuts and illustrations of matters of the moment.</p>
   <p>The circulation of this paper is growing by leaps and bounds. It is essentially a family newspaper, read by every member of the family. Its success has endured because we have tried to instill into its pages a "punch," a fearlessness not found in daily newspapers.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1311.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our paper goes to family people, to the people whom advertisers want to reach with their strongest appeal, and they cannot be reached anywhere except at home. Our readers constitute a great purchasing agency of high-grade articles and of the necessities of life.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, this is a sincere appeal for help to achieve one of our foremost aims, which is to establish a weekly newspaper for the interest and the welfare of our community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
