<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>L'italia</title>,
<date when="1893-09-16">September 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[A Dishonored Colony]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>L'Italia</title>,
<date when="1893-09-16">September 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[A DISHONORED COLONY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Italians are wicked and cowards" a statement made by two of our prominent co-nationals, E. Ronga and J. E. Garibaldi.</p>
   <p>Citizens of the Italian Colony are being dishonored by American citizens for not cooperating with the Board of Education in sending their children to school. This ignoble characteristic lowers our social position in Chicago into a very unfavorable light in comparison with Americans. We should send our children to school, and make them good American citizens. We, therefore have asked the cooperation of all Italian Societies in bettering our social standing among Americans.</p>
   <p>A letter was sent to the Board of Education stating:</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0059.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>September 12, 1893</p>
   <p>To the Board of Education of the</p>
   <p>Chicago Public Schools:</p>
   <p>September 3, A. D. 1893, at the Gazzolo Hall in a regular meeting of the Committee of the United Italian Societies composed of the presidents and two delegates from each of the following societies: C. Colombo, Umberto I, Court Italian, Court Gen. Garibaldi, Court Liguria, Trinacria Siciliana, Stella d'Italia, Court Assunta, Aquila Abruszzi, Red 'Italia, Legiene Garibaldi, Victtorio Emanuele, Aiutanti Mosaicisti, Margherita di Savoia, San Michele Arcangelo, Genova Carrallena, Agricola di Rieighano, and Court Asppromente.</p>
   <p>Said committee of the United Italian Societies, having in view the welfare</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0060.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>and bettering of the Italian children of Chicago who are kept out of school by their parents and deprived of the essential elements of an education, passed unanimously the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>Whereas: A certain Oscar Durante has been for some years past in the employ of the Board of Education in the capacity of Truant Officer, and is at present an applicant for the same position for the ensuing year.</p>
   <p>Whereas: The said Oscar Durante was elected to said office only because he was considered to be one of the prominent and most deserving individuals of the Italian Colony of Chicago, and the one to shower the most favors upon the said Italian Colony.</p>
   <p>Whereas: If the said Oscar Durante is re-elected to the same position, he <pb facs="5425702_1_0061.jpg" n="4"/>would offer no more advantages to the Italian children than he gave last year, for during that time he never attended to duties properly.</p>
   <p>Resolved: To notify the Board of Education that said Oscar Durante does not deserve the position of Truant Officer, and to give full force and effect to the above resolution the Committee through its chairman appointed a Sub-Committee to wait on the Board of Education, consisting of the following persons: J. G. Garibaldi, Paul Dasso, Dr. C. Volini, Dr. G. Ronga, G. D. Raggio, R. Puccini, G. Cozzi, F. De Rosa, V. Giannatiempo. E. Libinati, V. Ginocchio.</p>
   <p>Dr. G. Ronga, Secretary; John G. Garibaldi, Chairman Timbro.</p>
   <p>Societa Italiane Unite, Feste Colombiane.</p>
   <p>October 12, 1893, Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0062.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Traitors."</p>
   <p>Statement made by Oscar Durante.</p>
   <p>The infamy brought upon us by these two men, Garibaldi and Ronga, is beyond any doubt the most disgraceful under which our Colony has labored and furthermore these two prominent men, as we call them, should be branded with a red hot iron as traitors to our Colony. They took advantage of the good deeds of our societies which are always trying to help the Italians and with the ignorance of others, misled them into committing a prejudice so vulgar and treacherous to our Colony.</p>
   <p>Garibaldi and Ronga thought, by scandalizing us and by taking away the bread we have honestly earned for four years, would ruin us, but whether in defeat or victory, we will still be honest and loyal to our public.</p>
   <p>We advise our public to scorn them and spit in their face, which is the way gentlemen treat such villainous traitors.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0063.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Friends and enemies judge for yourselves the unworthy character of these two men.</p>
   <p>It is to be regretted that these two men hold such honorable positions as president and secretary of the Columbian Exposition, which they do not deserve.</p>
   <p>And to the Board of Education, I send you my sincere apologies if I have caused any trouble, because all this was only a fraud on the part of these two men who have a personal revenge on me.</p>
   <p>And to our Colony, let us hope that the disgrace brought upon us by these two men will soon vanish, and let us all cooperate in being good American citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
