<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-07-25">July 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Banquet in Honor of Arturo Caroti</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0447</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0447.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Parola Dei Socialisti</title>,
<date when="1914-07-25">July 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">BANQUET IN HONOR OF ARTURO CAROTI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hon. Arturo Caroti, Deputy in the Italian Parliament, was the guest of honor at the banquet held on the evening of July 10th, at the Roma restaurant. The banquet was under the auspices of the Italian Socialist Party of Chicago.</p>
   <p>More than eighty outstanding Socialists attended - in comradely spirit.</p>
   <p>Needless to say, the banquet turned out to be a meeting full of cordiality and enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The American comrade, Brais, representing the Industrial Tailor's Union of America, was also present.</p>
   <p>The director of our newspaper, Mr. Vacirca, delivered a speech, in which he praised the exceptional qualities - of heart and mind - of the old fighter for the socialist cause, who is the idol of the working class of Italy.</p>
   <p>He gave a resume of the ten years that the Hon. Deputy spent in America <pb facs="5425702_1_0448.jpg" n="2"/>before his election to the Italian Parliament.</p>
   <p>The orator recalled Mr. Caroti's life of struggle in America; how he adapted himself to the humblest and most difficult jobs, suffering distress and poverty in order to remain faithful to his ideals and to earn a piece of honest bread for his wife and children.</p>
   <p>Hon. Arturo Caroti, in thanking all his friends for the splendid reception bestowed upon him, recalled the time he spent in Chicago years ago, and was glad to see that his old friends and comrades of yesterday, are still the same friends and comrades.</p>
   <p>He promised to return to Chicago, to fight by our side with the same spirit and zeal, in order to destroy capitalistic society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
