<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title level="a">The Champion Boxers of the Order Sons of Italy Defeat the Jewish All Star</title>," <title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy</title> in America (Monthly),
<date when="1937-05">May 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title level="a">The Champion Boxers of the Order Sons of Italy Defeat the Jewish All Star</title>," <title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy in America</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1937-05">May 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Tuesday, May 11th, at the Madison Athletic Club, 4711 W. Madison St., the boxing team of the Order Sons of Italy Youth Organization met a team composed of the Jewish All Stars and came through in good fashion.</p>
   <p>Much credit for the fine showing of our boys in due to Paul Pantaleo, Leo Raineri and Joe Demarco, whose untiring efforts and general training supervision of the team was reflected in the final result.</p>
   <p>It was the team's first match since its selection at the tournament held last Jan. 28 and 29th.</p>
   <p>The boys representing the order were Jim Scorza, Al. Angelo, Frank Salerno, Vince Pellegrini, Charles Manna, Roy Atherton and Frank Speciale. The team was victorious in all but the heavyweight division, where Frank Speciale was defeated by a knockout, and the 150 division in which Frank <pb facs="5425702_1_1475.jpg" n="2"/>Salerno dropped a close decision in what was one of the finest bouts of the evening. The others won comparatively easy victories over their opponents.</p>
   <p>The Order Sons of Italy, in furtherance of its plans to promote the activities of its youth movement, is sponsoring a soft ball league, entries for which will close June 6th. All lodges or members of the order who desire to enter a team should communicate with their respective Venerables or the office of the Grand Lodge for information and entry blanks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
