<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 9-10, Sept., <date when="1913-10">Oct., 1913</date>,- Page 9.
<title level="a">At a Meeting of the Directive Council, Sept. 29th</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0985</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0985.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Italian Chamber of Commerce</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 9-10, Sept., <date when="1913-10">Oct., 1913</date>,- Page 9.
<title level="a">AT A MEETING OF THE DIRECTIVE COUNCIL, SEPT. 29th</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Vice-President Barbieri officiated and the following were present: - G. Malato, Spagiari, Davia, Barasa, Merando, Chiostri, Maestro-Giovanni and Maestro-Valerio.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the last meeting were read and approved.</p>
   <p>Motions were accepted by the Councillors to induce members who had resigned to withdraw their resignations. Dr. Vincenzo Guagliato was accepted as an active member.</p>
   <p>In credit to the practice of the Commission on Imports and Exports, concerning the article which appeared in the periodical "The Midland Druggist and Pharmaceutical Review" of Columbus, Ohio, which purported to be a dispatch sent by the Italian Government to the Associated Press, to the effect that the olive oil exported is not pure. Mr. Barasa, legal counsel for the Chamber, read correspondence from the Associated Press, which gives the lie to the article. The Italian Government <pb facs="5425702_1_0986.jpg" n="2"/>never sent it to the Associated Press. It claimed that such false rumors were circulated for the purpose of damaging the good reputation of our olive oil.</p>
   <p>Mr. Barasa also reports that he had an interview with the States Attorney, who advised that some action be brought to discover the sources of these lies.</p>
   <p>Maestro Valerio one of the Councillors, and members of the Agriculture Section also spoke in detail on the colonization plan proposed by the Federal Representative in the State of Texas, a plan which is guaranteed and would be under the protection of the Government. In acknowledgment of this, the Councillor decided that printed material in which would be given all information on soil, selling conditions, etc., should be obtained from the Government representative.</p>
   <p>It was discussed whether all matters referred to the Chamber, should be turned over directly to the president or secretary of each section or commission, that these might give the necessary information. The meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
