<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1928-08">August, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">For the Sub-Editor of Vita Nuova</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1356</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1356.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vita Nuova</title>,
<date when="1928-08">August, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE SUB-EDITOR OF VITA NUOVA</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italian newspapers, which are published in the United States and in Chicago, have written flattering articles on Charles Bellavia, recently appointed sub-editor of Vita Nuova.</p>
   <p>We reprint some remarks made by the most important newspapers to whom our sub-editor sends his kindest expressions of gratitude. From L'Italia, daily of Chicago:</p>
   <p>"From the last edition of Vita Nuova, the interesting monthly review, directed by the Rev. Dr. P. R De Carlo, we learned that Charles Bellavia has been appointed sub-editor. We congratulate the Rev. De Carlo for his choice, knowing the journalistic ability of Mr. Bellavia."</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1357.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From the same newspaper, L'Italia, we learned that the owners and workers of the Italian printing shop, Christiano and Catenacci, gave a banquet to Mr. Bellavia on his recent appointment as sub-editor of Vita Nuova, in the restaurant of Mr. Villani on Blue Island Avenue.</p>
   <p>From the Tribuna Transatlantica:</p>
   <p>"We have learned, with pleasure, that our dear friend, Charles Bellavia, has been appointed sub-editor and secretary of the review, Vita Nuova, which has been published in Chicago for the last fourteen years. Dr. Rev. P. R. De Carlo, director of the review, could not have made a better choice because Mr. Bellavia, besides being a well-known publisher, is an expert organizer. Congratulations to the dear colleague and best wishes for a great success."</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1358.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From the Progresso Italo-Americano, which is published in New York for all the United States:</p>
   <p>"Dr. P. R. De Carlo, director of the popular Italian review, Vita Nuova, which is published in Chicago, has appointed Charles Bellavia as secretary and sub-editor of the review. Vita Nuova, publishes very important articles by illustrious Italians such as Professors Acocella and Lanzalone, of Naples. The choice of the popular Bellavia, who is well-known as an organizer, could not be improved upon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
