<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title level="a">Festival of Italian Art at De Paul University</title>,"
<title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy</title>, Illinois Lodge (Monthly), <date when="1937-04">Apr. 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_0158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title level="a">Festival of Italian Art at De Paul University</title>,"
<title>Bulletin Order Sons of Italy, Illinois Lodge</title> (Monthly), <date when="1937-04">Apr. 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the invitation of the Art League Club of De Paul University, Grand Venerable Chevalier George Spatuzza proposed a program of art and Italianism by members of the Order Sons of Italy. The program was presented in the Little Theatre at the university on the evening of March 30th before an audience composed of the leading officers of the order, De Paul University, the Italo-American National Union, and prominent members of civic and educational bodies of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Maestro Berardinelli of the Berardinelli School of Music presented the third act of "La Traviata," with Miss La Placa in the role of "Violetta." Miss Myrtle Stolt sang two arias from "I1 Trovatore."</p>
   <p>Judge Louis Senese of Melrose Park showed films of Italy which he took while traveling through that country.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_0159.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are especially grateful to Mrs. Doetch, who acted as mistress of ceremonies.</p>
   <p>Before introducing the Italian consul-general for Chicago and the Grand Venerable of the order, she spoke a few words in favor of Italy and the Italians. The Italian consul, in a short talk thanked the De Paul University representatives for giving the Order Sons of Italy this opportunity, one for which it was very grateful. He said that he was happy to find himself again among members of that order, which in America is the strongest supporter of Italian ideals.</p>
   <p>Chevalier Spatuzza, in a few words, sketched the accomplishments of the order in the past and its hopes and aims for the future.</p>
   <p>In closing we cannot fail to mention Mr. O'Shaughnessy, who has showed <pb facs="5425702_1_0160.jpg" n="3"/>himself very favorable to Italy and was also intrumental in having Columbus Day declared a legal holiday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
