<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title>Italo-American Youth Organization Awards Boxing Prizes</title>," <title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1937-03">March 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425702_1_1595</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1595.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title>Italo-American Youth Organization Awards Boxing Prizes</title>," <title>Bulletin Italo-American National Union</title> (Monthly),
<date when="1937-03">March 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Italo-American Youth Organization entertained the champions and runners-up of the recent boxing tournament at the new Capri Restaurant, Thursday evening, March 11th. Gold and silver medals were awarded the following champions and runners-up, respectively:</p>
   <p>James La Rocco, Vito Benigno, Lawrence Ciaccia, Ben Taglia, Nick Castiglione, Louis Zito, Bob Furey, Sam Benigno, Sebastiano Ognibene, Frank Tinaglia, Ted Bianchi, Tony Scimeca, James Caruso, Nunzio Raimondi, Louis Regani, and Angelo Bragalone.</p>
   <p>A large silver trophy was presented to the Owl Indians (boys) for gaining the most points as a team in the tournament. The group greatly enjoyed the dinner, which included, of course, the traditional spaghetti.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1596.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Philip D'Andrea, Supreme President of the Italo-American National Union, together with the chairman and executive committee of the Italo-American Youth Organization, gave the boys a message of inspiration and good will, assuring all that the Italo-American National Union is indeed proud to sponsor the activities of the Italo-American Youth Organization. County Commissioner, Mrs. Lucy Palermo, who acted as toastmaster, gave the boys many encouraging words and a wonderfully hopeful picture of the future of the organization.</p>
   <p>Brief speeches full of enthusiasm and hope for a radiant future for the organization were made by vice-presidents Ross Ceffalio, Pat Petrone, Jack Nardulli, Sam Pecoraro, Louis and James Tortorelli, Carlo Boscia, James Pacente, Jack London, and secretary Sam T. Valenti and others.</p>
   <pb facs="5425702_1_1597.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A. J. De Julio, athletic director, explained plans for the coming tournaments. The speech which brought out the full inspirational vigor was given by V. E. Ferrara, treasurer of the Italo-American National Union and of the Italo-American Youth Organization.</p>
   <p>It should be very gratifying to every Italian in Chicagoland to know of the work that the officers of the Italo-American National Union are doing for every group in the city and its environs to affiliate with their union, in order to make it the greatest youth organization representative of the Italian people in social and athletic activities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
