<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-04-06">Apr. 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Use of the Donations</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-06">Apr. 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE USE OF THE DONATIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. A. Thompson of Herscher, Illinois, has written us as follows:</p>
   <p>"It is indeed a pleasure to read that money is being sent continuously from America for the benefit of the widows and children of the fishermen who died in the October storm on the coast of Northern Norway. But some of us who have contributed have been surprised to learn how widely opinions differ as to the use of the money sent. We appreciate greatly the work done by Skandinaven in connection with the gathering and forwarding of the gifts, and we have had no doubts as to the honesty of the Department of the Interior in Norway as regards the distribution of the funds received. Yet it appears that there is considerable misunderstanding between the donors and those who determine how the gifts are to be applied.</p>
   <p>"As one of those who have had something to do in connection with the collection <pb facs="5423969_4_0250.jpg" n="2"/>of the funds for the unfortunate in this case, many complaints have reached me. From several people I have also had statements such as, 'if only we knew that the money would be given to those for whom it was intended, but--'</p>
   <p>"In our simplicity we actually thought that when we sent $150 to three widows they would each get $50. Never did the thought occur to us that some kind of a community chest was to be established out of the money explicitly given to those widows and children in Rovar, Norway, who had lost their supporters. It did not occur to us that a gift sent by many in common, might not have the same standing under the law as if the amounts had been sent as private gifts to definitely indicated persons.....</p>
   <p>"It was a pleasure to note how readily people were giving to those unfortunate ones over in Norway, but we, the donors, want proof that the gifts went into the hands of those concerned. Some people may think it all right to use the money as a fund to provide aid in future cases of need, but it was not for such a purpose that the money was given by the people I have met."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0251.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>So much for our contributor. He has misunderstood the situation somewhat. It has not been decided in Norway to use part of the gifts contributed for the foundation of a permanent fund for the aid of future widows of drowned fishermen, although the matter has been up for discussion in Norway. As our contributor will remember, the Rev. Hersleb Sverdrup said in a letter to this paper that if it were to appear that more money had been collected than was required for the needy widows and children of the deceased fishermen from Rovar, then it would seem suitable to use the surplus money for a fund as mentioned. In his opinion, the collection would bring a surplus beyond the amounts required to relieve present need, and he desired the opinion of the donors in America as to the feasibility of such a plan.</p>
   <p>Much might be said in favor of the idea mentioned by Rev. Sverdrup, but Skandinaven will not enter the discussion of the plan at present. We do wish, however, to reassure the many contributors to the sufferers from the storm at Rovar, who sent their gifts through this paper, that Mr. Thompson is correct in his statement that the gifts are the property of the widows and children in question. Calling attention to this fact, Skandinaven has informed the Department of the Interior in Norway that <pb facs="5423969_4_0252.jpg" n="4"/>the money transmitted by the paper must be distributed respectively to the widows of the Northern district, the widows in Rovar, and to the children of Engel Olsen. The editors have called the attention of the members of the distributing committee to the fact that the gifts are the property of the people in question; that the powers of the committee are limited to acts in conformity with this right, and that the gifts must be distributed in conformity with the mandate given the committee by this paper. The editors have further demanded detailed accounts of the funds sent through Skandinaven, with a full list of recipients and amounts given to each. We have no reason to doubt that these instructions will be complied with.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
