<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-10">Oct. 10, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Home for the Aged</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0124</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0124.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-10">Oct. 10, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN HOME FOR THE AGED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Humboldt Park Branch of the Society for the Norwegian Home for the Aged held its monthly meeting last Monday evening at the Home in Norwood Park. A large number of the members of the Society arrived at Norwood Park by train at nine-thirty, and together marched to the Norwegian Home for the Aged. Also a number of friends of the Home, not yet members, came to attend this regular monthly meeting, which was held in the office of the Home. Mrs. Marie Holland, the superintendent, acted as hostess.</p>
   <p>Reverend A. C. Anda opened the meeting with a reading from the scriptures and with prayer.</p>
   <p>After the routine business matters were transacted, Mr. A. B. Swanson was received as a member, so that the Branch now has sixty-six active members and two honorary members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0125.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The most important business taken up for consideration was the preparation for the annual bazaar, which also this year, is to be held at Schoenhofen's Hall. The bazaar will open on November 5 and continue until the end of the week.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Thyr reported how the ladies' aid committee had planned the affair. She distributed subscription lists for gifts to the bazaar and tickets for the members to sell. On her motion, an auxiliary committee consisting of Mrs. Louise Nilsen, Mrs. C. G. Nilsen, and Mrs. Rikka Gunderson was elected to assist during the Branch evening at the bazaar and during the preparation for same. The Branch will have charge of the bazaar on Tuesday, November 6 (Election Day; election returns will be displayed free).</p>
   <p>The other evenings of the bazaar week will be in charge of various branches of the Society for the Home for the Aged: Monday, Bethlehem Branch; Wednesday, Trinity Branch; Thursday, Concordia Branch; Friday, Wicker Park Branch; <pb facs="5423969_4_0126.jpg" n="3"/>Saturday, Moreland and Humboldt Park Branches, assisted by all the rest.</p>
   <p>Mr. Olaf Anda reported from the meeting of the board of directors that three new guests had been received at the Home, one of these, Mrs. Johnson, being present at the meeting.</p>
   <p>The business meeting over, all those present were invited downstairs to sit around the long dining table and there to be served with coffee and cake. The food was enjoyed by all, and afterward the Reverends Anda and Harrisville and their wives sang several numbers which were greatly appreciated, and then the guests, in the glittering moonlight, marched over to the railroad station to take the train home. Mrs. Henry Olsen, president of the Ladies' Board was present and gave information concerning the bazaar, etc.</p>
   <p>The meeting seemed to cheer the aged ones who were present; it was evidently a welcome variation from their daily routine. At the table, Reverend Anda <pb facs="5423969_4_0127.jpg" n="4"/>expressed the thanks of all those present to Mrs. Holland for having given the younger people a chance to inspect the attractive Home with its beautiful surroundings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
