<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-11-14">Nov. 14, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian National Association</title><title level="a" type="sub">Resolutions Concerning the Income of Next Seventeenth of May Festival</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1706</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1706.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-14">Nov. 14, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN NATIONAL ASSOCIATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Resolutions Concerning the Income of Next Seventeenth of May Festival</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian National Association held a special meeting last Monday evening at Wicker Park Hall. A communication from the Leif Ericson Monument Society in which application was made that the income from the next Seventeenth of May celebration to be held under the auspices of the Norwegian National Association be donated to the Monument Association.</p>
   <p>After a lively debate it was moved that the matter be placed before the respective societies under the Association for discussion before action be taken. This motion was rejected.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lars Johansen, a member of the Leif Ericson Monument Society moved that the surplus from the coming Seventeenth of May festival be donated to the Monument Society after the statutory $1,000 has been collected for the treasury.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1707.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Olaf E. Ray said that he would agree to aid the Monument Society, but he did not feel inclined to work for the proposed sketch by Mr. Asbjornsen as accepted by the Monument Society. Messrs. Hans Hansen, L. E. Olsen, G. Martin, and Mrs. Broon favored the donation of any eventual surplus from the Festival to the monument Society; they were eager to see the monument erected as speedily as possible. The motion by Mr. Lars Johansen was adopted by overwhelming majority.</p>
   <p>The board of directors was authorized to rent at an early date a suitable hall or park for the celebration of the next Seventeenth of May.</p>
   <p>The president, Dr. K. Sandberg, expressed his approval of the resolution concerning the monument matter. The adopted motion was the only manner in which the National Association, in accordance with its laws, could aid the monument.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
