<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-06-18">June 18, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Norse Aid Is Pledged</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-06-18">June 18, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">NORSE AID IS PLEDGED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Accompanied by wild cheering resolutions pledging the material and moral support of those present to the new Norwegian government and asking President Roosevelt to recognize the separate government of Norway were adopted at the mass meeting of Norwegian-American residents of Chicago at the Auditorium last night. While in no sense a demonstration against Sweden or King Oscar, the gathering cheered the speeches which told of the greatness of Norway and the justice and right of her cause.</p>
   <p>Chairman Paul O. Stensland, president of the Milwaukee State Bank, started the enthusiasm by expressing the hope "that Norway may succeed and that peace and liberty may continue there for many years". The meeting closed with vociferous applause for the statements by Attorney Johan Waage, that "though we have from 25,000 to 50,000 sons of Norway in Chicago, if we count the Swedes and Danes who sympathize with Norway's cause, there would be 100,000 names on the appeal to President Roosevelt to recognize the Norwegian government".</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1536.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Ormund Harveland, president of the Norwegian National League, called the meeting to order. After prayer by Rev. John Z. Torgerson he introduced Paul O. Stensland as chairman. The latter made a brief speech, eulogistic of Norway, and then introduced Dr. Anders Doe, who spoke in Norwegian.</p>
   <p>Praise for Norway</p>
   <p>"We are here tonight in sympathy with Norway and the storthing", he began. "This is not a demonstration against King Oscar nor Sweden. It is only in support of Norway. The man who has been king of our country thirty years was behind the times, and while we loved him, Norway was progressive and was forced to take the step she did unless she wanted to drop back with Sweden".</p>
   <p>Attorney Oscar M. Torrison, who made in English the chief speech of the evening, declared that "the consular question is not the cause; it is only the occasion of this struggle between Norway and Sweden". Continuing, he gave the history of the two countries from the treaty of Kiel, in January, 1814, discussing the Norwegian constitution and the act of union and explaining the rights of each country under each. In closing he spoke in part as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1537.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Let us hope that the king and the Swedish people will decide wisely and well, and abide by a peaceable dissolution which shall remove all causes of friction between brother peoples and bind more strongly the natural ties between them, and lead to most cordial relations in the future.</p>
   <p>Text of Resolutions</p>
   <p>Birger Osland followed Mr. Torrison and presented the resolutions which were cabled last night to the Norwegian storthing. They were adopted with a thundering, "ja". They were as follows: Whereas; We, citizens of the United States of America of Norwegian birth or parentage, follow the destinies of our ancient father-land with constant sympathy and solicitude; and</p>
   <p>Whereas; The Norwegian nation under the leadership of able and trusted men have been compelled to make great and far-reaching changes in its government in order to maintain its right to be the master of its own destiny; and <pb facs="5423969_4_1538.jpg" n="4"/>Whereas; These changes have been effected in a dignified, deliberate manner, increasing our own respect and that of all men, for the Norwegian nation, its storthing and its provisional government; now, therefore, be it.</p>
   <p>Resolved: That we, Norwegian-Americans of Chicago in mass meeting assembled at the Auditorium this 17th day of June, 1905, under the auspices of the Norwegian National League, hereby express our unqualified approval of the steps which were taken by the Norwegian storthing on June 7, 1905, and also our pride in, and deep appreciation of the manner in which these changes have been brought about; be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we express our firm belief in the necessity of the measures that have been adopted; and, with the hope and conviction that this change in the international status of Norway will make the ties between Norway and Sweden stronger than they were under the union which has been dissolved, and will lead to lasting cordial relations among the three norhtern nations, we hereby solemnly pledge the Norwegian people our full sympathy and material support in their efforts to defend the proud heritage of Harold, Olaf, Svens, and Haakon.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1539.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Plea to Roosevelt</p>
   <p>Ormund Harveland was recognized by Chairman Stensland and presented the resolutions to be sent to President Roosevelt. It is probable Mr. Stensland, John Anderson, publisher of the Skandinaven, and Mr. Harveland will be the committee to take them to Washington. The resolutions were in substance as follows;</p>
   <p>Whereas, We regard the said action of the storthing as a necessary step for the vindications of the soverign and constitution of Norway in a contest between the people and the crown of Norway; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, In our judgment, prompt recognition of the new government of Norway by the United States would be in line with American traditions and also tend to strengthen the ties of mutual good will and friendship between the people of Norway and the rank and file of the people of Sweden.</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we respectfully petition the President of the United States to recognize the government of Norway at the earliest opportunity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1540.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>In presenting the resolutions Mr. Harveland eulogized President Roosevelt, whose name was an occasion for renewed cheering, and declared Norway entitled to representation at Washington by sons of her own blood.</p>
   <p>Between the speeches the numbers of the allied Norwegian singing societies under the direction of Emil Blorn, sang various Norwegian airs, and after the adoption of the resolutions sang the Norwegian national air, "Ja, vi Elsker Dette Landet."</p>
   <p>Besides the Norwegian pastors there were present on the stage all of the presidents of Norwegian societies and the delegates to the national league.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
