<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-07-13">July 13, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Home for the Aged Holds Quarterly Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-07-13">July 13, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN HOME FOR THE AGED HOLDS QUARTERLY MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Society for the Home for the Aged held its quarterly meeting on July 10 at Zion Church, corner of Potomac and Artesian Avenues. Dr. N. T. Quales was elected chairman of the meeting, and Mr. J. Blegen acted as secretary.</p>
   <p>The meeting opened with a prayer by the Reverend J. H. Meyer. A report from the previous meeting was read and accepted, after which the president of the Society, Dr. Quales, presented the following report:</p>
   <p>"The constitution of the Society does not require of the officials of the board of directors to present an account of the condition of the Society every quarter. It is simply stated in the constitution that at the quarterly meetings such business is to be transacted as may be placed before these meetings. This, in my opinion, is a mistake, and I think the constitution ought to be amended on this point.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0137.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"So far we have followed the safe rule that both the board of directors and the officials of the various branches of the Society have to present reports. This rule has contributed considerably to make the quarterly meetings interesting.</p>
   <p>"The motion has been made to abolish the quarterly meetings, and perhaps it may seem unnecessary to have the members of the Society convene so often, while the affairs are in good hands and the board of directors fulfills its duties. It cannot be denied, however, that these meetings are of considerable practical importance for the promotion of the undertaking.</p>
   <p>"Our frequent meetings serve to increase the interest. The individual members get a chance, through the meetings, to become better acquainted with the work that is going on; they find opportunity to exchange opinions and propose new plans. These are factors which ought not to be lost sight of in a society such as the present, in which the objective does not consist in self-interest <pb facs="5423969_4_0138.jpg" n="3"/>but solely in the efforts to promote a noble undertaking.</p>
   <p>"The directors were instructed to see to it that programs were arranged for these meetings, of a nature to ensure large attendance. The directors may not have succeeded in this as well as might have been desirable, but we hope to attain better results in the future.</p>
   <p>"The board of directors is glad to be able to inform the Society that the Home is in good condition, and all is well there; that good feeling and harmony prevail throughout.</p>
   <p>"Details concerning the activities at the Home will be shown in the reports of the secretary and the treasurer, so I shall not attempt to touch on these. There are, however, matters of importance, matters of special interest for the Society, which I shall take the opportunity to mention: First, that the board of directors has acquired a burial place for the aged at Union Ridge Cemetery, <pb facs="5423969_4_0139.jpg" n="4"/>about fifteen minutes' walk from the Home. The lot is estimated to hold about one hundred graves. The cost of the burial lot was $450.</p>
   <p>"The Home needed some repairs, as we know, externally, and this has been taken care of since our last meeting. The sidewalk, also, needed repairs, and this has been done.</p>
   <p>"It is now several years since the building was painted, and the work of painting ought to be done this summer, since otherwise damage will result. The painting will probably cost about two hundred dollars, and it causes some inconvenience this summer, since there are several extra expenses which must be met this year. There is the insurance premium of $200; the cost of the burial place, $450; Erie Street is to be paved, and the cost of this will amount to about $200. Altogether, our extra expenses will amount to more than one thousand dollars. This is a heavy extra load. It can be taken care of, however, if the board of directors be given a free hand; but this they must have.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0140.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Since our last meeting, one of the aged--Mrs. Martha Nelson--has passed away. She died on the third of March and was buried in the burial space of the Home, on March 7. Most of the aged at the Home followed the casket to the cemetery. Mrs. Nelson was born in Romsdalen, Norway, on October 14, 1833. She was one of the first to be received at the Home. For several years she suffered from heart disease, and this, in connection with her age, caused her death.</p>
   <p>"For the rest, the state of health at the Home is about as good as one could expect. A certain amount of frailty is the common accompaniment of old age.</p>
   <p>"From a report of the Ladies' Aid Committee, it appears that the income from the festival at Wicker Park amounted to $267.30; the expenses to $49.40; the net income to $218.10. This result was beyond our expectations, very satisfactory.</p>
   <p>"On June 23, many of the members of the Society, and also some invited guests, <pb facs="5423969_4_0141.jpg" n="6"/>took the trip out to the Home and spent some pleasant hours in the beautiful surroundings of the Home. The Ladies' Aid Committee, with its usual tact and foresight, took care of the well-being of the guests.</p>
   <p>"On this occasion, we had the pleasure of receiving as a gift a selection of books from Mr. John Anderson, publisher of the Skandinaven. The books are highly treasured by the aged ones, and the gift deserves the fullest gratitude of the Society.</p>
   <p>"The annual picnic of the Home has been decided on for August 25, and the railroad company has promised to arrange for special trains on the occasion.</p>
   <p>"Our annual bazaar will be held at Schoenhofen's Hall, from November the fifth till November the tenth. We are hoping that the income this year may be as satisfactory as was the case the preceding year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0142.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"The report I have given now intends, then, to give you a brief account of the main activities at the Home since our last meeting. The board of directors once more takes the opportunity to thank most heartily all those who have stood by during the period, and we express the hope that they will continue to assist in carrying the work forward."</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Blegen, the secretary, reported that the board of directors of the Society has held three regular meetings during the past quarter. In addition to the meetings of the executive committee, there have been held two general meetings of the committee on arrangements for the picnic to be held [on August 25], and for various other activities in the interest of the Home.</p>
   <p>One new guest has been admitted to the Home, the widow Ida Amalie Johnson, 717 North Maplewood Avenue. She was born in Kongsberg, Norway, on September 24, 1832.</p>
   <p>The Secretary's report from the branches is as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0143.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Bethlehem Branch: Mr. George Olsen, secretary.</p>
   <p>Number of members, as of June 30, 57; membership fees paid, $27.25.</p>
   <p>Trinity Branch: Mrs. T. Johnson, secretary.</p>
   <p>Number of members, as of June 30, 54; fees paid, $25.25.</p>
   <p>Concordia Branch: Miss Camilla M. Wium, secretary.</p>
   <p>Membership, as of June 30, 97; fees paid, $32.75.</p>
   <p>Humboldt Park Branch: Mrs. Getta Johnson, secretary.</p>
   <p>Membership, as of June 30, 66; fees paid, $34.75.</p>
   <p>Wicker Park Branch: Mr. Theodore Wangen, secretary.</p>
   <p>Membership, as of June 30, 114; fees paid, $70.01.</p>
   <p>The activities of the Society have proceeded under the warmest interest for <pb facs="5423969_4_0144.jpg" n="9"/>the cause and under the heartiest harmony and good will among the members.</p>
   <p>On a motion by Mr. Jersin, seconded by Mr. Ray, Mr. Anton Petersen, chairman of the committee for the picnic, was requested to approach the Northwestern Railroad Company with the request, that on the day of the picnic all the local trains be made to stop at Maplewood Station. The secretary was requested to send a letter of thanks to Mr. John Anderson, publisher of the Skandinaven, for his valuable gift of two hundred finely bound volumes, which he recently sent to the Home.</p>
   <p>On a motion by Mr. John M. Pedersen, seconded by Mr. Jersin, the board of directors was requested to consider the advisability of the creation of a reserve fund for the Society, by means of small monthly contributions.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Harrisville, of Hauge's Synod, expressed his pleasure at the fine <pb facs="5423969_4_0145.jpg" n="10"/>progress of the Home for the Aged. He hoped that the spiritual nurture at the Home would find active support in the good will and willingness to make sacrifices on the part of the Norwegian ministers.</p>
   <p>The meeting was concluded with a prayer by the Reverend George T. Rejgh.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
