<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1911-10-06">Oct. 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Investments</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0724</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0724.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-10-06">Oct. 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE INVESTMENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following Scandinavians bought or sold real estate in Chicago recently:</p>
   <p>August E. Gustafson to Samuel Clark:  53rd Avenue and Superior Street. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Anna L. Johnson to Jennie M. Armstrong: 507 La Salle ["North" or "South" not specified.] Price, $8,400.</p>
   <p>Otto F. Erickson to Edward J. Johnson: German and Southport Avenues. Price, $7,500.</p>
   <p>Chicago Title &amp; Trust Company to Oscar A. Johnson: Sacramento and Sunnyside Avenues. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0725.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Edward J. Walsh to Catherine L. Benson: Western and Lawrence Avenues. Price, $20,000.</p>
   <p>Ole J. Olesen to Morris Janosky: Maplewood Avenue and Division Street. Price, $6,000.</p>
   <p>Harold W. Dyer to Julius Petersen: Lincoln Avenue and Byron Street. Price, $10.</p>
   <p>Christine Bruse to John C. Petersen: Richwood Avenue and Sheriden Road. Price, $10.</p>
   <p>Christian L. Benson to G. W. De Smet: Pratt and Newgard Avenues. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Reynert Reynertson to Bernhard Magnuson: Springfield and Belden Avenues.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0726.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Price, $5,400.</p>
   <p>Reynert Reynertson to Karl H. Olsen: Springfield and Belden Avenue. Price, $3,500.</p>
   <p>Henry C. King to Henry F. Swanson: Flournoy Street and Central Park Avenue. Price, $950.</p>
   <p>Charles H. Reynolds to Harry J. Johnson: Morton Street and Phillips Avenue. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>Louis M. Nelson to Nicolas Zepp: Bernice and 52nd Avenues. Price, $2,400.</p>
   <p>Lina M. Sandahl to Louis M. Nelson: Dakin Street and 52nd Avenue. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>Geo. J. Johnson to Sam Arado: Grand and 48th Avenues. Price, $2,700.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0727.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mathilde Davidson to Peter O. Lind: Carmen and Ashland Avenues. Price, $7,500.</p>
   <p>George K. Spoor to Johanna M. Nelson: Margate Terrace and Sheridan Road. Price, $5,400.</p>
   <p>G. H. Spoor to Axel E. Olesen: Margate Terrace and Sheridan Road. Price, $5,400.</p>
   <p>N. W. T. Christensen to L. M. Weaver: Paulina and Byron Streets. Price, $2,200.</p>
   <p>Lena H. Petersen to M. Gratch: Artesian and Montrose Avenues. Price, $7,300.</p>
   <p>Adolph Schmidt to Annie C. Hattstrom: Christiana Avenue and Byron Street. Price, $2,200.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0728.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Theodor Voss to Henry S. Bauer: Eberly and Sunnyside Avenues. Price, $4,000.</p>
   <p>Sofig Gustafson to Adelof J. Nelson: Fullerton and Lowell Avenues. Price, $6,500.</p>
   <p>Mathilde Davidson to Peter E. Lind: Monticello and Leland Avenues. Price, $1,155.</p>
   <p>Ira M. Cobe to Nels N. Johnson: Ridgeway Avenue and Grace Street. Price, $1,600.</p>
   <p>Adelof J. Nelson to Sofie Gustafson: Tripp and North Avenues. Price, $900.</p>
   <p>A.A. Rogalla to Kristian A. Jacobsen: Frances Place and Point Street. Price, $3,100.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0729.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>William O. Larsen to Ditlef Holmeide: Edgewood and Sacramento Avenues. Price, $1,650.</p>
   <p>Jens J. Nielsen to Lonneth Nielsen: Johnston and Sacramento Avenues. Price, $1,900.</p>
   <p>Ira M. Cobe to Rasmus Jensen: Whipple Street and Bloomingdale Avenue. Price, $2,450.</p>
   <p>Sofie E. Anderson to Joseph A. Klein: Hoyne Avenue and Berlin Street. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <p>Gustav A. Gunderson to W. Goelinowski: 2117 Thomas Street. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>John Nelson to Louis Carlson: Beach and Spaulding Avenues. Price, $2,200.</p>
   <p>Olga Carlson to Sofie Gustafson: Christiana Avenue and Division Street. Price, <pb facs="5423969_4_0730.jpg" n="7"/>$7.50.</p>
   <p>J. Winterbottom to Aneus Sorenson: 40th Place and Potomac Avenue. Price, $6,500.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
