<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-06">Jan. 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian National Association</title><title level="a" type="sub">The New Board of Directors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1662</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1662.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-06">Jan. 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN NATIONAL ASSOCIATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">The New Board of Directors</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The election of Attorney [John J.] Sonsteby as the new president of the Norwegian National Association has caused a certain stir among the Norwegians of Chicago. It is the first time that an American-born Norwegian has been so honored. Everybody agrees that Mr. Sonsteby will have his hands full if he is to keep his administration on a level with those of Messrs. [Birger] Osland and [A.] Abrahamsen. It will be no easy task. Mr. Sonsteby is known as a great worker, however, and from his activities as a member of the Board of Education it has been learned that he can stand his ground, not losing courage even though one battle may be lost. Among the Norwegians in Chicago the approval of his election is general.</p>
   <p>Mr. John Malmstrom, who was elected corresponding secretary, is possibly the <pb facs="5423969_4_1663.jpg" n="2"/>strongest man on the new board of directors. His re-election was unanimous and he was the only one among the retiring officials who did not meet opposition. This is the second time that Mr. Malmstrom has been unanimously chosen for the office of corresponding secretary. The general assembly is to continue its work next Monday. At that time three new members of the board of directors of the employment office are to be elected. Messrs. Osland, Sonsteby, Fossum, and Backer retire. As the president of the Association, Mr. Sonsteby occupies the place held by Mr. Osland. The other three places are to be filled through election. In addition there will be elected an auditing committee, a visiting commitee, seven members of the Seventeenth of May committee, and a member of the lecture committee (the children's Seventeenth of May committee). A motion has been presented concerning the distribution of aid to the needy.</p>
   <p>The Employment Office</p>
   <p>Among the reports presented to the National Association the most interesting <pb facs="5423969_4_1664.jpg" n="3"/>was the one from the employment office. Mr. Anderson, the superintendent, and the members of the board of directors have accomplished much. The office is still in the red but the deficit is decreasing every month. The auditing committee consists of Olaf E. Ray, Otto Berg, and Oscar Amundsen. The committee has audited the books of the employment office and found them in order. The report of the finances of the National Association follows:</p>
   <p>Income</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Song festival at Orchestra Hall</cell>
     <cell>$1,515.58</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Seventeenth of May festival at Brand's Park</cell>
     <cell>3,810.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest (to November 30)</cell>
     <cell>39.58</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total income</cell>
     <cell>$5,365,36</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance in treasury from 1907</cell>
     <cell>1,723.15</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total gross cash in trensury</cell>
     <cell>$7,088.51</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1665.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Expenses</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Bills from 1907</cell>
     <cell>$59.32</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Current expenses</cell>
     <cell>105.98</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Employment office</cell>
     <cell>711.29</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Benevolences</cell>
     <cell>221.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Deficit at banquet</cell>
     <cell>30.85</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Printing of laws</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Seal and emblem</cell>
     <cell>39.29</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Contribution to North-West Improvement Association</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Contribution to Chicago Relief and Aid Society</cell>
     <cell>100.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Contritution to Norwegian Orphange building fund</cell>
     <cell>500.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses of concert at Orchestra Hall</cell>
     <cell>561.43</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1666.jpg" n="5"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Net income of the concert at Orchestra Hall, to the Orphanage building fund</cell>
     <cell>$954.15</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Contribution to John Sverdrup monument</cell>
     <cell>100.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses of Seventeenth of May festival</cell>
     <cell>1,180.95</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Contribution to policemen's burial fund</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Contribution to reserve fund of the Home for the Aged</cell>
     <cell>500.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Contribution to reserve fund of the Orphanage</cell>
     <cell>150.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Christmas presents to Orphanage</cell>
     <cell>50,00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Advance to Seventeenth of May festival, 1909</cell>
     <cell>125.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total expenses</cell>
     <cell>$5,469.86 [sic]</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total net cash in treasury</cell>
     <cell>1,618.65 [sic]</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>The following is a report from the employment office of the Norwegian National Association for the period of December 1, 1907 to November 30, 1908:</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1667.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The previous superintendent of the office, Mr. Lars Bergan, resigned in March, 1908, as he intended to start his own business outside of Chicago. Mr. Andrew Anderson was appointed his successor.</p>
   <p>The efforts of the office during the past year have mainly been to provide jobs for the unemployed in the country, away from Chicago, and for this reason the office has advertised in several out-of-town papers. This was necessary also for the reason that factory activity in Chicago was at low ebb and consequently it was unusually difficult to find employment within the city. During April, 1908, unquestionably the best month for securing jobs on the farm, the employment office sent fifty-five men out to work in the country. The board of directors of the employment office decided to demand a registration fee of twenty-five cents from every applicant, the amount to be returned on request if no work is found. This step was taken because a number of applicants failed to pay the very reasonable fee that the employment office asks--one fourth of one week's pay.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1668.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>In the course of the year the office has received 1,447 applications for work from 1,055 men and 392 women.</p>
   <p>Employment Provided</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>In Chicago, men</cell>
     <cell>279</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Outside Chicago, men</cell>
     <cell>186</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>In Chicago, women</cell>
     <cell>202</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Outside Chicago, women</cell>
     <cell>34</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>701</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Employment Office Income</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Application fees</cell>
     <cell>$198.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Fees refunded</cell>
     <cell>26.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$167.75 [sic]</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1669.jpg" n="8"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Employment fees</cell>
     <cell>$492.93</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Refunded</cell>
     <cell>26.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$466.18</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Special income</cell>
     <cell>4.85</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Grand Total</cell>
     <cell>$638.78</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>From farmers a total of $550.66 was received to cover traveling expenses for people employed on the farms during the period of April 1, 1908 to November 30 of the same year. The superintendent of the office bought the tickets for those employed.</p>
   <p>During the month of December, 1908, forty-five men and forty women were provided with employment through the efforts of the employment office. The income for December, 1908, was $83.50.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1670.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>The Visiting Committee</p>
   <p>In the course of the year the visiting committee investigated several applications for assistance. In twelve cases it was recommended that assistance be given. The total amount recommended by the committee is $227. Of this amount $221 was appropriated by the Association....The visiting committee has only acted on request, and its decisions have been made by a simple majority of votes....</p>
   <p>The committee on the historical lecture to be delivered in English to the children at the Seventeenth of May celebration held its first meeting on September 29. Dr. S. H. Nannestad was elected chairman; Miss J. E. Olsen, secretary; Mr. Edward Hansen, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
