<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1910-11-25">Nov. 25, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0937</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0937.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-11-25">Nov. 25, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following Scandinavians bought or sold real estate in Chicago recently:</p>
   <p>I. H. Cobe to Edward T. Carlson: Monticello Avenue and Grace Street. Price, $900.</p>
   <p>Anna R. Kjeld to Gustaf Tideman: Richmond Street and Berteau Avenue. Price, $2,275.</p>
   <p>Samuel Brown to Erick Ericksen: Tripp and Belden Avenues. Price, $1,811.</p>
   <p>Emil Rudolph to Lars K. Lindberg: Berwyn and Oakley Avenues. Price, 2,367.</p>
   <p>Hilda C. Nelson to C. L. Miller: Indiana Avenue and 53rd Street. Price $15,000.</p>
   <p>C. O. Gustafson to Alfred Aronsen: Fifth Avenue and Garfield Boulevard. Price, $6,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0938.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Gustav W. Halbom to Inga E. Johnson: Lyndale Avenue and Ballou Street. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>Paul Pedersen to Elizabeth Franne: Cottage Grove Avenue and 115th Street. Price, $1,400.</p>
   <p>Anton Johnson to Georg Thomeson: Augusta and Willow Streets. Price, $3,300.</p>
   <p>Carl O. Olsen to Nels Johnson: Irving Avenue and 22nd Street. Price, $4,500.</p>
   <p>Nellie B. Smith to Burton Hansen: Pratt and Wayne Avenues. Price, $1,500.</p>
   <p>John B. Olsen to W. Petersen: Foster and Southport Avenues. Price, $6,900.</p>
   <p>John M. Hansen to C. R. Nielsen: Victoria and Clark Streets. Price, $4,200.</p>
   <p>Hannah Johnson to Emil A. Thoresen: Kedzie and Schubert Avenues. Price, $1,260.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0939.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Carl H. Petersen to M. B. Edgerton: Berwyn, Andrews &amp; P. Addition, lots 41 and 42. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>Carl H. Peterson to John Anderson: property in Andrews &amp; P. Addition. Price, $4,500.</p>
   <p>Olaf Anderson to Charles Colberg: Farragut Avenue and Clark Street. Price, $8,400.</p>
   <p>Emma Johnson to Per C. Nordmark: Grove and Racine Avenues. Price, $3,600.</p>
   <p>C. C. Knight to Reynert J. Renertsen: Avers and Belden Avenues. Price, $2,500.</p>
   <p>Henry M. Pedersen to Charles M. Andersen: Homer Street and North Ninth Avenue. Price, $600.</p>
   <p>Emma C. Anderson to Alfred A. Anderson: North and Lawndale Avenues. Price, $1,300.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0940.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Max L. Teich to T. Hora and C. M. Manson: 613-613 Lincoln Park Avenue. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <p>C. Ecklunp to Marcus Well: Huron Street and Spaulding Avenue. Price, $10.</p>
   <p>Helene M. Nelson to Katherine Risevig: Sacramento and Schubert Avenues. Price, $4,000.</p>
   <p>Clara Olsen to Fred Wamstedt:: 810-8120816 Prias Place. Price, $17,150.</p>
   <p>Martin Weick to Aug. E. Anderson: Harding and North Avenues. Price, $1,100.</p>
   <p>Theodore Jacobs to Wm. H. Nelson: Milwaukee Avenue and Logan Square. Price, $5,625.</p>
   <p>George Noer to Andrew Nelson: Avers Avenue and Hirsch Street. Price, $4,200.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0941.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>M. Nelson to F. Natucki: Ohio Street and Centre Avenue. Price, $2,500.</p>
   <p>S. Harstrom to L. E. Lund: North Park Avenue and Center Street. Price, $5,200.</p>
   <p>Jens Jensen to G. J. Williams: Division and Wedder Streets. Price, $15,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
