<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1911-10-24">Oct. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0676</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0676.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-10-24">Oct. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following Scandinavians bought or sold real estate in Chicago recently:</p>
   <p>Peter Tyser to Oscar E. Anderson: Wentworth Avenue and 106th Street. Price, $2,200.</p>
   <p>Herman S. Petersen to Mary Andrews: Carrey's Subdivision, lots 19, 20, 42, block 1. Price, $1,600.</p>
   <p>F. Schroeder to Nils Buck: Barry Avenue and Clark Street. Price, $10,000.</p>
   <p>F. Babage to J. Frederik Lundgren: Winnemac and Southport Avenues. Price, $2,400.</p>
   <p>John Brem to Andrew G. Andersen: Armitage Avenue and 40th Court. Price, $4,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0677.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Frank M. Butler to Jens C. Hansen: Medill Avenue and 49th Street. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>H. C. Nichols Lumber Company to Charles E. Knudsen: Springfield and Belden Avenues. Price, $2,300.</p>
   <p>Hannah L. Olesen to Andrew W. Nelson: Hirsch Street and Homan Avenue. Price, $5,700.</p>
   <p>Andrew G. Anderson to Dudrik C. Voss: North and Talman Avenues. Price, $20,000.</p>
   <p>John Dahlberg to Maren Lundberg: Ridgeway Avenue and Hirsch Street. Price, $600.</p>
   <p>Adelaide Jacobsen to Emmett E. Mame: Huron Street and 49th Avenue. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>John Dahlberg to Maren Lundberg: Ridgeway Avenue and Hirsch Street. Price, $600.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0678.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Anton Johnson to Joseph L. Hammel: Superior Street and Franklin Avenue. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <p>Abraham J. Jacobsen to H. Edelman: Fairfield Avenue and Howard Street. Price, $10.</p>
   <p>Kristine Sorkness to Ed. Petersen: Lawndale Avenue and Huron Street. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <p>Augusta Hansen to Annie Nathanson: Leavitt and Augusta Streets. Price, $4,500.</p>
   <p>Carrie Carlson to Emil Youngreen: Foster and Ashland Avenues. Price, $950.</p>
   <p>Mary Owens to James Williamson: Winnemac Avenue and Clark Street. Price, $1,175.</p>
   <p>Carl F. Carlson to Emil Carlson: Central Park Avenue and Grace Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0679.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Price, $900.</p>
   <p>Charles S. Neross to J. L. Traverkamp: Springfield Avenue and Thomas Street. Price, $5,000.</p>
   <p>Andrew Ringman to Oscar E. Erickson: Calborn Avenue and 106th Street. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <p>Frank C. Doherty to Carrie W. Davidson: Ogelsby Avenue and 68th Street. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <p>John H. Helvig to Nels K. Anderson: South Park Avenue and 71st Street. Price, $800.</p>
   <p>R. O. Dolls to Knute Anderson: Evergreen and Spaulding Avenues. Price, $2,500.</p>
   <p>Hans E. Anderson to M. S. C. Churchhill: Lee and Francisco Avenues.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0680.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Paulina Rasmussen to Christ P. Petersen: Washtenaw Avenue and Bloomingdale Road. Price, $2,800.</p>
   <p>Joseph Elger to Jens C. Hansen: Milwaukee and Armitage Avenues. Price, $80,000.</p>
   <p>Chicago Title &amp; Trust Company to Lena H. Petersen: Maplewood and Sunnyside Avenues. Price, $900.</p>
   <p>Josephine Roob to Gustaf Gustafson: Halsted Street and Grand Avenue. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>W. E. Hagworth to Harry O. Johnson: Clark Street and Evanston Avenue. Price. $1.</p>
   <p>M. Momson to Simon Swanson: Lakewood and Iowa Avenues. Price, $1.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0681.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Adelaide J. Jacobsen to Lona Hoge: Bingham and Cornelia Streets. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>Adolph Weber to Gustav Nelson: Elston and Maplewood Avenues. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>Henriette Weber to Gustav Nelson: Elston and Armitage Avenues. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>S. P. Samuelson to J. W. Westcliff: Lawndale Avenue and Thomas Street. Price, $8.25.</p>
   <p>N. H. Weaver to Albert E. Amundsen: Maplewood Avenue and LeMoyne Street. [Price not specified.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
