<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-01-27">Jan. 27, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Lynch Law-- Roots and Remedies</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0331</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0331.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-01-27">Jan. 27, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">LYNCH LAW-- ROOTS AND REMEDIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whether or not lynching is "strictly an American institution," as the keenwitted Chinese minister puts it, mob law is certainly not one of those institutions Americans cherish, though we have received it as an inheritance from our forefathers.</p>
   <p>In the closing days of the eighteenth century the good people of Boston, shocked by the burning of a negro culprit at the stake, expressed the hope and belief that their grandchildren a hundred years hence would class such occurrences among the barbarities of a past age. In the course of time these grandchildren moved west. Some of them now live with their children in Colorado and Kansas, where the twentieth century was ushered in amid agonizing groans of a negro rapist roasting at the stake, while hundreds of people of Boston blood were counted among their executors and tormentors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0332.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The unspeakable horrors occasioned a burst of indignation; but it soon passed away. Moreover, public sentiment was plainly divided, not only in Colorado and Kansas, but also in other northern states, let alone the South. It cannot be denied that the lynching of a human brute caught red-handed is regarded by a large number of people not as a crime,but as an act of justice. The law may brand it as a crime, as wilful murder punishable by death, but it cannot change the human heart. The fact remains that lynch law and public law have a common root: the sense of justice that is implanted in human nature. The purpose of a mob of lynchers is not to commit a crime but to avenge a crime committed and protect the community. When men are face to face with a monstrous wrong they do not stop to consider the numerous fine theories and doctrines of crime and its punishment. The old law, "An eye for an eye, a life for a life," is written in their hearts, and that is the source and controlling force of their action. They apply it because they want to see justice done and rid society of a dangerous wild beast in human form.</p>
   <p>The true cause of lynchings is found in the law's delay and the uncertainties <pb facs="5423969_4_0333.jpg" n="3"/>and frequent slips of criminal justice. While once upon a time such unauthorized executions of dangerous criminals were necessary on account of lack of public law, lynchings are now resorted to for the very opposite reason--a surfeit of law. In our desire to protect the "defendant" we have robbed honest people and society at large of due protection. The criminal is hedged about by such safeguards and "the people" are handicapped by such an intricate net of technicalities that the crime is forgotten before a verdict is reached--only to be followed by appeals without number.</p>
   <p>If he be blessed with wealth and powerful friends, a man may celebrate his majority by committing some atrocious crime and yet reach a ripe old age before the law is ready to send him to the gallows; and should it overtake him this side of the grave, there is always a governor ready to commute his sentence, and a successor to grant a full pardon. Meanwhile,the felon has been fawned upon and lionized by sentimental and hysterical women, who have made his cell an ever-blooming bower of roses, while a lot of more or less learned cranks have taught him to believe that he is the victim, and society <pb facs="5423969_4_0334.jpg" n="4"/>the criminal. Is it any wonder if he, upon regaining his liberty, concludes a fresh rape or murder?</p>
   <p>It is such judicial farces and disgusting spectacles that prompt resolute men with a healthy sense of justice to take the law into their own hands. If they were like some of our "sociologists," or women, or professional jurors--if their minds were warped by foolish notions--they would not shoulder the trouble and responsibility of taking a human life. But they are determined to see justice done and they administer it because they think, or know, that society is not likely to do it in an adequate and effective manner.</p>
   <p>The remedy for lynchings is not to pass more stringent laws against lynchers or to mulct counties where such occur, etc. A radical reform of the law of criminal procedure is the true and only remedy. We must go back to the just principles. And we have something to learn from lynch law. In some respects, lynch law comes nearer to the accepted ideal system of criminal justice than does our present system as it operates in many communities. It is an axiomatic <pb facs="5423969_4_0335.jpg" n="5"/>truth that in order to attain its purpose, punishment must be sure, swift, and adequate. The punishment administered at the hands of "Judge Lynch" is swift, sure, and adequate. Nor will it be denied that executions by virtue of his decrees are more deterrent in their efforts than are those conducted under the public hangman--because in the former instance the punishment is sure, swift, and efficient, and is administered while the crime is fresh in the public mind, whereas in the latter instance,the public has partly forgotten why the wretch is to hang anyway.</p>
   <p>It is high time to abolish the "American institution which has moved Minister Wu to give vent to his sarcasm. It is a disgrace to our civilization. And it can be done, but not by hurling anathemas from the pulpit, nor by sermonizing in presidential and gubernatorial messages, nor by filling the air with lamentations about mob law. It can be done only by adopting a practical, common-sense system of criminal law that will visit upon criminals a punishment that is just, swift, sure, and adequate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0336.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Our lawyers will have to do the work, but they will not move until the people compel them to. Nearly all states are in need of a simpler and better system of criminal justice, and the more uniform the system of the various states, the better for the country.....</p>
   <p>The National Civic Federation would be a proper leader of a popular, uniform system of criminal law and procedure.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
