<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-06-11">June 11, 1905</date><title level="a">Norse to Roosevelt Chicago Leaders Prepare a Plea for Recognition of New Government</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1541</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1541.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-06-11">June 11, 1905</date><title level="a">NORSE TO ROOSEVELT CHICAGO LEADERS PREPARE A PLEA FOR RECOGNITION OF NEW GOVERNMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The sentiment of Chicago Norwegians regarding their mother country's eventual independence has crystallized into a movement to obtain the influence of President Roosevelt in behalf of the recognition by the United States of the provisional government. This movement took two forms yesterday. Prominent Norwegian American citizens prepared a petition asking the President to recognize the new government. Besides, Ommund Harveland, president of the Norwegian National League, issued a call for a meeting of the delegates of the organization to adopt resolutions relative to the new situation.</p>
   <p>The appeal,which is printed in full in another column, was formulated after several conferences, in which prominent Norwegian-Americans took part. Among them were: F. Herman Gade, Mayor of Lake Forest; John Anderson, publisher of the Skandinaven: Nicolay Grevstad, editor of the Skandinaven; Paul O. Stensland, president of the <pb facs="5423969_4_1542.jpg" n="2"/>Milwaukee Avenue Savings Bank; Hilge A. Haugan, president of the state bank of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Sermons on Norway</p>
   <p>The document was drawn up by Mr. Gade and has been distributed widely through-out the city, in Norwegian communities and to the various Norse societies and churches. Through the religious bodies, it is expected, a large number of the signatures will be secured. Norwegian pastors, will preach on Norway's new government today, and at the close of the service the worshippers will be requested to sign the appeal.</p>
   <p>"We expect at least 20,000 signatures said Mr. Gade yesterday. We believe the action of all the world powers regarding the recognition of Norway depends upon that of this country, as President Roosevelt from the beginning has been looked up to as a great leader in the affairs of the world. Should he signify his recognition of the present provisional government as such, and later of the permanent government yet to be established, the other powers cannot but fall into line".</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1543.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Starts in other Cities</p>
   <p>A petition, worded in practically the same terms as the one issued yesterday, was started some time ago in Boston. Other cities, including Minneapolis and St.Paul, have followed suit with success gratifying to the leaders of the movement. On Tuesday the Chicago petitions with their signatures, will be collected and bound for transmission to the President. A delegation from Chicago will have the plea in charge. A rumor that a representative of Norway already had arrived to assist the movement, could not be verified yesterday.</p>
   <p>The meeting of the Norwegian National League's delegates, fifty in number, will be open to the public. It will be held tomorrow night at Schoenhofen's Hall, Ashland and Milwaukee Avenues, at 8:30 o'clock. The league is composed of twenty-five societies, representing 10,000 persons.</p>
   <p>A resolution said to have been somewhat inflamatory and socialistic in its nature, was handed late last week to one of the officers of the league, and its presentation <pb facs="5423969_4_1544.jpg" n="4"/>at the meeting tomorrow night was urged strongly. As there was doubt about the propriety of risking the publicity that would attend its introduction, a copy was sent to the national officers for consideration, and late last night word was received by President Harveland advising that it be suppresed.</p>
   <p>The officers of the league are: President, Ommund Harveland; Vice Presidents, Andrew Anderson, John Wold and Mrs. Walberg Lund; Recording Secretary, Carl J. Baker; Corresponding Secretary, F. Asche; Treasurer, Ole Gullickson.</p>
   <p>The allied Norwegian singing societies of Chicago will meet Tuesday night at Schoenhofen's Hall to take action similar to that of the National League. On Wednesday night, the Norwegian student singers from the University of Christiania, will give their farewell concert at the Auditorium.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
