<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-08-28">Aug. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Club of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-08-28">Aug. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN CLUB OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Club of Chicago held a membership meeting last Friday. The club debated as to whether there should be a ladies auxilary. The question arose several months ago through a written request from the ladies for authorization of the aid society. There were so many opinions within the Board in regard to the matter, that it was thought safest to leave the decision to the membership meeting.</p>
   <p>The debate became lively. The opponents of the proposal declared that if the ladies gained entrance as accepted members by having a branch club they would soon rule the club; the whole result would be a skirt-regime they felt, and the club would lose its status as a happy retreat for males.</p>
   <p>It was soon evident, however, that the ladies would win, and the vote, when taken showed forty-four in favor of admitting the ladies, to twenty against. There were, however, several who refrained from voting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1580.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was announced that the world renowned Norwegian tennis player, Miss Malla Bjorstedt would be a guest of the club during her stay in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It was also announced that an arrangement has been reached with the Swedish Club of Chicago, through which the members of the two clubs (Norwegian and Swedish) will mutually enjoy the privileges of members whenever visiting each other as members or collectively.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
