<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-01-17">Jan. 17, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Societies, Clubs, Lodges</title><title level="a" type="sub">Athletic Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II D 1 (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-01-17">Jan. 17, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN SOCIETIES, CLUBS, LODGES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Athletic Societies</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norge Ski Club meets on the first and third Tuesdays of each month in Jacobsen's Hall, Wabansia and Washtenaw Avenues.</p>
   <p>The Sleipner Athletic Club meets on the first and third Wednesdays of each month in Sleipner Hall, 1620 North Fairfield Avenue.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian Turner Society meets in Casino Hall, California Avenue and Division Street. Business meetings are held on the first Thursday of each month; men's class, Thursdays and Fridays; women's class, Mondays; boy's class Monday and Fridays.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1499.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Benevolent Societies</p>
   <p>The Bethlehem Sick and Death Benefit meets on the first Monday of each month in the Bethlehem Church, Huron Street and Center Avenue [sic].</p>
   <p>The Norwegian Lutheran Sick Benefit and Aid Society meets in the Church every Tuesday.</p>
   <p>The New Norway Sick Benefit and Aid Society meets in Lagoni's Hall, North and Western Avenues, on the first Monday of each month.</p>
   <p>The Genoveda Norwegian Women's Sick Benefit and Aid Society meets at 491 West Ohio Street, every second Monday.</p>
   <p>The Thora Scandinavian Women's Society meets every second and fourth Thursday at the Danish Brotherhood Hall, 315-17 Hirsch Street.</p>
   <p>The Danish Workers' Sick Benefit Society meets on the first and third <pb facs="5423969_4_1500.jpg" n="3"/>Wednesdays of each month at Jacobsen's Hall, Wabansia and Washtenaw Avenues.</p>
   <p>The Danish Mutual Aid Society meets in Schoenhofen Hall, 880 Milwaukee Avenue, every second and fourth Wednesday.</p>
   <p>The Martha Sick Benefit Society meets every third Thursday in Wicker Park Hall, North and Milwaukee Avenues.</p>
   <p>The Schleswig Aid Society meets every second Wednesday at 949 North Avenue.</p>
   <p>The First Norwegian-American Male Burial Society meets every first and third Tuesday at 208 West North Avenue.</p>
   <p>Haabets Anker (Hope's Anchor) Burial Society meets every first Monday in Jacobsen's Hall, Washtenaw and Wabansia Avenues.</p>
   <p>The Scandia Women's Benefit Society meets every first and third Monday in the <pb facs="5423969_4_1501.jpg" n="4"/>Brotherhood Hall, Hirsch Street and Fairfield Avenue.</p>
   <p>The First Scandinavian Death Benefit Society meets twice each month in Lagoni's Hall, North and Western Avenues.</p>
   <p>The Minde (Remembrance) Women's Benefit Society meets every first and third Thursday at Wicker Park Hall.</p>
   <p>The White Star Death Benefit Society meets every fourth Tuesday at 949 West North Avenue.</p>
   <p>Labor Organizations</p>
   <p>The Scandinavian Painters Union No. 194 meets at 730 North Maplewood Avenue every Friday.</p>
   <p>The Scandinaven Shoemaker's Association meets every fourth Sunday at 907 [now 1707] California Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1502.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Temperance Societies</p>
   <p>The Ilinois Norwegian Prohibition Society meets irregularly.</p>
   <p>The Haabet (Hope) Women's Christian Prohibition Society meets every Friday at 76 North Center Avenue [sic].</p>
   <p>The Minnehaha Temperance Club meets every Tuesday at 876 [now 2416] North Avenue.</p>
   <p>The Blue Cross Christian Temperance Club meets every first and third Monday at 915 North Avenue.</p>
   <p>The Nordkap (North Cape) Temperance Club meets every first and third Wednesday in Rockwell Hall, Rockwell Street and Bloomingdale Road (now Bloomingdale Avenue).</p>
   <p>The First Scandinavian Women's Christian Temperance Club meets every Sunday in <pb facs="5423969_4_1503.jpg" n="6"/>the Hope Mission, corner of Noble and Ohio Streets.</p>
   <p>Tordenskjold Lodge No. 15, R. H. K. [Royal Order of the Knights of the White Cross], meets every second and fourth Friday in North West Hall, 690 [now 2400] West North Avenue.</p>
   <p>Wergeland Lodge No. 24 meets at 48th Avenue and Superior Street.</p>
   <p>Dovre Lodge No. 18 meets every first and third Thursday at 1375 West North Avenue.</p>
   <p>Nora Lodge No. 1 meets every second and fourth Wednesday at Lagoni's Hall, North and Western Avenues.</p>
   <p>Leif Ericson Lodge No. 9 meets every first and third Thursday at Schoenhofen Hall, Milwaukee and Ashland Avenues.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1504.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>other Societies</p>
   <p>The Ulabrand Youth Society meets every Thursday in Wabansia Hall, California and Wabansia Avenues.</p>
   <p>The Scandinavian Young Men's Christian Association meets every Sunday at 317 West Erie Street.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian National Committee meets at 859 [now 1609] North Fairfield Avenue on the first Monday in January.</p>
   <p>The Bethlehem Branch of the Norwegian Society for a Home for the Aged meets on the second Monday of each month.</p>
   <p>The Sondre Norge (Southern Norway) Youth Society meets every Sunday at 1203 [now 3303] West North Avenue.</p>
   <p>Nordfalles Supreme Lodge meets every second and fourth Wednesday at Hirsch Street and Talman Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
