<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-07-17">July 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Homecoming Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">Festival for the Superintendent of the Home for the Aged</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-17">July 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">HOMECOMING FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Festival for the Superintendent of the Home for the Aged</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The residents of the Norwegian Home for the Aged, in Norwood Park, gave a reception yesterday in honor of the superintendent of the Home, Mrs. Anna Christiansen, who recently returned from her vacation in Norway. At two o'clock in the afternoon, the people assembled in the dining room of the Home. The aged men and women were dressed for a festive occasion, and were animated with festive anticipation. The tables were loaded with delicious foods and decorated with beautiful flowers. The aged people acted as waiters.</p>
   <p>After everyone had been served, the speeches began. The superintendent expressed her joy and gratitude at the love and good will shown her by the aged people. She spoke of the pleasant experiences that had been hers during her visit to Norway; yet, she said, the Home and the friends dwelling there had always been in her thoughts, and now she was most happy to be back again among her own.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0044.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Brief speeches were also made by Reverend Wolstead, the rector of the Home, and by Dr. N. T. Quales. The aged inmates also desired to be heard on this occasion, and brief speeches were given by Mrs. Pernelle Gundersen, Mrs. Caroline Nilsen, Mrs. Julia Ross, and Mr. Christian Anderson. All of these speakers praised the attendants for faithful and capable work. The aged had not suffered at the Home, they said; on the contrary, they had enjoyed a pleasant and cozy home. Yet, as one of the aged people put it, "when the head is off, it seems as though something is lacking."</p>
   <p>So the residents of the Home were happy that the superintendent had returned, and they were happy to be present to bid her welcome.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
