<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1921-01-15">Jan. 15, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Life--The Chicago Norwegian Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1921-01-15">Jan. 15, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">LIFE--THE CHICAGO NORWEGIAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We want to tell the reader simply and in a few words something about the social life of the Norwegian colony in C. [Chicago]. The names are fictitious, but the persons are real.</p>
   <p>Let us begin with Dr. Darre, who is considered the socialite par excellence in the colony. He studied in Christiania [Oslo] and was considered one of the happiest of the happy student fraternity. After his graduation he packed his diplomas, his social talents, and his happy humor and decided to settle in the midwestern metropolis of C., where he was welcomed with open arms and soon became one of the "prominent" and worked up a profitable "praxis" [practice]. He soon became the colony's recognized social leader and a member of the most prominent clique, in which nothing could be accomplished unless he was active in the work, both propaganda and practical. [Dr. Darre--Dr. Anders Doe.]</p>
   <p>Another member of the elite was the banker Kamstrup [Oscar H. Haugan], who was <pb facs="5423969_4_1462.jpg" n="2"/>born in western Norway more than forty years ago. At an early age he signed on as cabin boy on a ship out of Bergen. He "jumped ship" in the U.S.A. and decided to try the "Northland" of America, and about twenty years ago he settled in Chicago, where he soon became a leading banker. Kamstrup was a born humorist, and because of this virtue, or vice, as the case may be, he soon became the bosom friend of Dr. Darre.</p>
   <p>The colony in C. had two papers, a daily, Dagbladet [Skandinaven] and a weekly, Torden [Thunder--Scandia]. We will not speak of Dagbladet, for obvious reasons, but we must say a few words about Torden, whose editor's and owner's name was Olsen [L. H. Lund]. We mention Olsen because he was a member of the clique to which the author of these "confessions" belonged. Olsen was a young and hand-some man who had tried to make a living in various ways and by various methods but had found that his proper function was that of editor. Olsen was a good-natured fellow who would not harm a soul unless that soul doubted his ability as a journalist; if any one was careless enough to do that, he was sure to be hauled over the coals in the columns of Torden.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1463.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Olsen gave the impression of being a cross between an academy student and a university student, which was probably correct, for he had attended schools and colleges of all sorts back in old Norway but has never graduated from any of them; so he naturally felt like an intellectual lost sheep. He had read a great number of books and was still reading, we are certain, altogether too many more; he never could have digested them all. While Kamstrup was quiet and reserved, not so Olsen. He has, among other things, a great idea of his own wisdom, and he never lost an opportunity to show the world how much he really knew. He tried to shine as an orator, but here as in his writing he failed miserably because he always used a lot of foreign words, especially Latin, that no one understood, and sometimes we doubt whether he himself understood them, for he often used these words in the wrong places. Olsen was likewise very critical of everything [and everybody]; he even criticized his two bosom friends, Dr. Darre and the banker Kamstrup.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
