<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-10-17">Oct. 17, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0682</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0682.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-10-17">Oct. 17, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following Scandinavians bought or sold real estate in Chicago recently:</p>
   <p>Charles F. Swanson to Oscar Helmert: Sheffield Avenue and Grace Street. Price, $16,000.</p>
   <p>Charles A. Anderson to Clark Artner: Victoria and Clark Streets. Price, $2,500.</p>
   <p>M. Pottinger to Nicolaus J. Davidsen: Central Park and Waveland Avenues. Price, $1,200.</p>
   <p>Ira M. Cole to Charles E. Opdahl: Ridgeway Avenue and Byron Street. Price, $800.</p>
   <p>E. H. Castle to Marie Carlson: Morton Park, Hawthorne Addition, lot 22, block 5. Price, $675.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0683.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Charles H. Serum to Hans Lund: Kedzie Avenue and Ohio Street. Price, $6,500.</p>
   <p>A. J. Jacobsen to Julia Lieberman: Robey and Thomas Streets. Price, $1,200.</p>
   <p>Soren Eske to Mandel Arnolff: Western and Potomac Avenues. Price, $2,775.</p>
   <p>Axel Nordlund to S. Czacrynski: Monticello and North Avenues. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>David Nelson to M. K. Arkiball: Clark Street and Greenleaf Avenue. Price, $20,000.</p>
   <p>C. H. Elmberg to Nellie Carlson: St. Anthony Court and Lawrence Avenue. Price, $4,200.</p>
   <p>Joseph Enslo to Jeanette D. Franzen: Balmoral and Ashland Avenues. Price, $1,444.</p>
   <p>John K. Schmidt to Anna Thronstrom: Catalpa Avenue and Clark Street. Price, <pb facs="5423969_4_0684.jpg" n="3"/>$1,200.</p>
   <p>H. Weldenhoefer to Andreas A. Nelson: Washtenaw and Greenwood Avenues. Price, $800.</p>
   <p>William Ghan to William Nelson: Western Avenue and Clara Place. Price, $5,000.</p>
   <p>Lars Jensen to F. Pawlowski: Huron and Noble Streets. Price, $4,600.</p>
   <p>Claus E. Anderson to Wm. B. Waldrath: 47th Court and Le Moyne Avenue. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>Anna Clinton to Laura J. Johnson: Hamlin and North Avenues. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>Gustav E. Carlson to John Sandberg: Hermitage Avenue and Ainslie Street. Price, $10,000.</p>
   <p>John Sandberg to Christofa Carlson: West Ravenswood Park and Winona Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0685.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Price, $4,000.</p>
   <p>Peter Petersen to Wm. Schneider: 1814 Kimball Avenue. Price, $2,600.</p>
   <p>N. T. Reynertson to Hans E. Wold: Springfield and Belden Avenues. Price, $5,400.</p>
   <p>Isabella Anderson to Wm. Engel: Troy Street and Diversey Avenue. Price, $4,200.</p>
   <p>B. Anderson to Martin O'Malley: Augusta Street and 49th Avenue. Price, $2,400.</p>
   <p>Peter A. Petersen to James J. Smith: West Erie Street and North Lincoln Street. Price, $2,900.</p>
   <p>B. C. Johanson to H. B. Hatwald: Superior Street and Austin Avenue. Price, $7,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
