<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1910-12-07">Dec. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0930</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0930.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-12-07">Dec. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following Scandinavians bought or sold real estate in Chicago recently:</p>
   <p>Carl C. Olesen to Wm. Warneman: State and Ninth Street. Price, $18,500.</p>
   <p>Martin Werk to Aug. O. Anderson: Harding and Armitage Avenues. Price, $1,100.</p>
   <p>Wm. Jacobs to Harald Nielsen: Albany and Milwaukee Avenues. Price, $6,250.</p>
   <p>Georg Nar to Andrew Nielsen: Avers Avenue and Thomas Street. Price, $5,100.</p>
   <p>Anna M. Nelson to Frank Natti: Ohio Street and Central Park Avenue. Price, $2,100.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0931.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>G. Harstrom to A. C. Lundegaard: North Park and Webster Avenues. Price, $5,600.</p>
   <p>Jens Jensen to G. I. Willamson: Division and Vedder Streets. Price, $16,000.</p>
   <p>L. C. Zettewall to Ernie P. Nelson: Farragut and Southport Avenues. Price, $1,600.</p>
   <p>Emma Nelson to Reuben Doherty: Lafayette Avenue and 73nd Street. Price, $6,500.</p>
   <p>William Henriksen to H. W. Austin: The Highland, lot 220. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>L. S. Hill to Carl A. Carlson: Short's Addition, lots 45 and 46, block 5. Price, $1.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0932.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>P. R. Boylan to Albert Carlson: Vincennes Avenue and 32nd Street. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <p>Paul C. Petersen to G. De Maies: 112th and Fulton Streets. Price, $1,600.</p>
   <p>Andrew Nelson to Sophia Martens: Ashland and Foster Avenues. Price, $6,000.</p>
   <p>Andrew Sorenson to Gustav Hallborn: Berteau and 51st Avenues. Price, $4,300.</p>
   <p>Arthur Krueger to Georg T. A. Larsen: 42nd Avenue and Addison Street. Price, $600.</p>
   <p>Charles Bostrom to Carl G. Lund: Sawyer and Balmoral Avenues. Price, $2,800.</p>
   <p>C. K. Wendel to Frederik Johnson: Kamerling and 40th Avenues. Price, $5,300.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0933.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Emil Rudolph to Nils Anderson: Bowmanville Avenue and Leavitt Street. Price, $2,635.</p>
   <p>Robert C. Petersen to J. H. Cobe: Central Park and Waveland Avenues. Price, $2,600.</p>
   <p>C. K. Butler to Olaf C. Ray: Milwaukee and Lawrence Avenues. Price, $8,000.</p>
   <p>Andrew Ringman to Nels Ed. Christianson: Avenue J and Ninety-ninth Street. Price, $7,000.</p>
   <p>John Peterse to Adolph Nielsen: Leavitt and Hirsch Streets. Price, $2,600.</p>
   <p>Christian Iversen to Charles Lind: Western Avenue and Pleasant Place. Price, $6,500.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0934.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Jacob Levy to Michael Johnson: Sawyer Avenue and 13th Street. Price, $11,300.</p>
   <p>Cate E. Allport to Adolph Petersen: Kimball and Lyndale Avenue. Price, $1,200.</p>
   <p>Olaf E. Ray to Oscar H. Haugan: Wilwaukee and Lawrence Avenues. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Olof Petersen to Augusta H. Hart: Curtis Avenue and 110th Street. Price, $2,100.</p>
   <p>Garfield Anderson to Harriet Allstedt: Indiana Avenue and 63rd Street. Price, $9,750.</p>
   <p>August Tidholm to C. W. Frederiksen: Emerald Avenue and 51st Street. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0935.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Alma Lind to Rudolph Gruenke: Southport and Balmoral Avenues. Price, $13,000.</p>
   <p>Hans M. Olsen to John Meiner: 1012 South wells Street. Price, $9,000.</p>
   <p>Sophia Johnson to Ellen Johnson: La Salle and 35th Streets. Price, $970.</p>
   <p>John B. Olsen to Ester Simon: Belle Plaine and 52nd Avenues. Price, $1,500.</p>
   <p>Ira M. Cobe to John Wicklund: Winchester Avenue and 51st Street. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <p>A. Sylvander to Ragnar C. Olsen: Morgan and 60th Streets. Price, $1,800.</p>
   <p>Alfred Eckstrom to Abel Troberg: Oak Park, Reynold's Addition, lot 12, block 12. Price, $3,750.</p>
   <p>Victor A. Larson to Oscar R. Anderson: 110th Street and Princeton Avenue. Price, $2,900.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0936.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Martin A. Carlson to Otto Erlandson: 112th Street and Perry Avenue. Price, $3,650.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
