<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-07-13">July 13, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0753</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0753.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-07-13">July 13, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following Scandinavians bought or sold real estate in Chicago recently:</p>
   <p>Jacob C. Jacobsen to Martin Johnson: Lincoln Street and Cullom Avenue. Price, $2,500.</p>
   <p>Jens P. Nilson to James P. Hansen: Eberly and Leland Avenues. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>John F. Petersen to Helmar Hagenson: 48th and North Avenues. Price, $5,500.</p>
   <p>M. Cobe to Charles E. Opdahl: Lawndale Avenue and Greenwood Terrace. Price, $1,800.</p>
   <p>Edw. Haugan to L. D. Glanz: Rockwell Street and Fullerton Avenue. Price, $1,100.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Title and Trust Company to Hans H. Lund: Chicago and Oakley Avenues.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0754.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Price, $5,000.</p>
   <p>Selma C. Anderson to Ellen L. Farwell: Rhodes Avenue and 62nd Street. Price, $9,000.</p>
   <p>Christian Olsen to Chas. G. Anderson: Evergreen and Washtenaw Avenues. Price, $2,200.</p>
   <p>Helmar Haagenson to John F. Petersen: 48th Avenue and LeMoyne Street. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>F. H. Gedtner to Robert W. Christiansen: Carmen and Ravenswood Avenues. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <p>Frank Lundquist to M. Olesen: Robey Street and Belle Plaine Avenue. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>M. Olsen to Mary Lund: Robey and Frankfurt Streets. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0755.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>D. M. Christiansen to Magnus Holm: Winchester Avenue and Roscoe Street. Price, $3,500.</p>
   <p>Anton Petersen to P. G. Jensen: Fairfield Avenue and Cortland Street. Price, $9,000.</p>
   <p>Anna K. Nielsen to Augusta Miller: Lincoln Street and Evergreen Avenue. Price, $2,400.</p>
   <p>Augusta Miller to Albert Lindman: Lincoln and Thomas Streets. Price, $3,900.</p>
   <p>Nils Ellestad to John Lilleskan: Ballou Street and Greenwood Terrace. Price, $6,100.</p>
   <p>Louisa Strom to Carl A. Carlson: O'Brien Street and Wabansia Avenue. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0756.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Marie Carlson to Catherine Horvak: Morton Park, Hawthorne Addition, lot 8, block 2. Price, $3,500.</p>
   <p>C. M. Fergusen to Ferdinand Petersen: Ferguson's Birchwood Addition, lot 5, block 6. Price, $2,225.</p>
   <p>N. J. Reynertson to Oscar Bergstrom: Avers and Belden Avenues. Price, $5,850.</p>
   <p>David Hansen to Johan Schmidt: 50th and Fullerton Avenues. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>John M. Andersen to John Sontag: Halsted Street and Webster Avenue. Price, $9,200.</p>
   <p>Alma Ecklund to Louis Levy: Huron Street and Sawyer Avenue. Price, $5,850.</p>
   <p>Ernest Lauge to Oscar Johnson: Fairfield and Wabansia Avenues. Price, $1,200.</p>
   <p>John Higgins to P. A. Poulsen: Kedzie Avenue and Thomas Street. Price, $2,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
