<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-09-13">Sept. 13, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Home for the Aged</title><title level="a" type="sub">Humboldt Park Branch Holds its Monthly Meeting in Norwood Park</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-09-13">Sept. 13, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN HOME FOR THE AGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Humboldt Park Branch Holds its Monthly Meeting in Norwood Park</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The last meeting of the Humboldt Park Branch of the Norwegian Society for the Home for the Aged was held at the home of Mr. and Mrs. Olai Anda in Norwood Park. The meeting was opened with prayer by Reverend A. C. Anda of Goshen, Indiana, after the Chicago members had arrived. They came on the half-past-eight train.</p>
   <p>As usual, satisfactory reports were given of progress made; yet Mrs. Thye stated that the income from the restaurant at the picnic held this summer was less than last year. The explanation offered was that the storm of the preceding night kept many of the people away until the afternoon. Mrs. Thye proclaimed the results satisfactory in all other respects, however. Attention was called to the fact that there now were only about eight weeks left <pb facs="5423969_4_0131.jpg" n="2"/>before the bazaar, which is to open at the beginning of November. It was stressed that the necessity for early preparations was urgent.</p>
   <p>Mr. and Mrs. Nels Sampson of Norwood Park were received as members and Mr. Sampson explained that he had moved to the Park twenty years ago on account of failing health, but has since regained it. He considers Norwood Park one of the most beautiful suburbs of Chicago and it is for this reason he did his utmost to have the Home for the Aged located there at the time when the board of directors visited various localities in search of a suitable place. He expressed his pleasure that Norwegians had started moving into Norwood Park. For many years he was the only one of Norwegian nationality living in the place.</p>
   <p>Reverend L. Harrisville concluded the meeting with prayer, after which the lady of the house, assisted by a number of young ladies, began to take care of the guests, bringing them coffee, sandwiches, and cakes. The committee on arrangements had not made up any regular program to be followed, since the <pb facs="5423969_4_0132.jpg" n="3"/>members were aware that Reverend Harrisville was bringing his wife with him. The minister and his wife also sang several songs, and later were joined by Reverend Anda and his wife, and by Mrs. Minnie Anda. These ladies and gentlemen entertained with songs till the hour of leaving.</p>
   <p>The meeting was very pleasant and cozy. The large rooms in the house also contributed considerably to this end. Mrs. Helland said that she too had plenty of space, and on her request it was decided to hold the next meeting of the Branch of the Home for the Aged at her home in Norwood Park on October 8.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
