<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1902-03-06">Mar. 6, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Salvation Army</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0242</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0242.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1902-03-06">Mar. 6, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">SALVATION ARMY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Scandinavian Branch of the Salvation Army has just completed its annual report for 1901. The report is published in a book that contains much interesting material, of which we give the following highlights:</p>
   <p>The executive staff in Chicago consists of Colonel and Mrs. Charles Soroton; provincial officers are Brigadier and Mrs. A. N. Damon; general secretaries, Major and Mrs. John Bovill; staff captains, Lena Lindstrom and Sven Wiborg; division officers for the Scandinavian work, Adjutant Evelyn Olsen, Adjutant Louie Smith, Elizabeth Ludworth, Ensign Fletcher Agnew, Ensign Christine Sandgren, and Captain Grace Gegan.</p>
   <p>The headquarters for the Scandinavian department is at 84 west Adams Street. The Branch fed 10,000 people Christmas Day; in addition to the thousands that were fed in Tatterfalls Hall, hundreds of baskets were given to needy families; not one hungry man, woman, or child was turned away.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0243.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Scandinavian department's posts in the slums are numerous; there the assigned officers live permanently, visiting the sick and dying, and caring for the children. The report shows that these officers spent 5,194 hours in the streets, 893 hours visiting the sick, and 17,612 visits to saloons.</p>
   <p>The department operates a bureau to find missing persons. The department operates four homes for men, where six hundred men can sleep every night. In two of these institutions the unfortunate men are supplied with clean beds, lockers, showers, needles, thread, buttons, a place in which to do their laundry, and papers and books; coffee and buns are served every morning for ten cents.</p>
   <p>At 73 Lincoln Avenue the Salvation Army has a "House for Fallen Women", with room for twenty-five women. It is estimated that eighty-five per cent of the women that pass through this institution are saved.</p>
   <p>At 394 North Dearborn Street there is a hotel for working women, where board <pb facs="5423969_4_0244.jpg" n="3"/>and room can be had for seventy cents per week, there is room for sixty-five women.</p>
   <p>Over five thousand open-air meetings were held during the year; ten thousand mothers with their children were given picnics last summer; fifteen thousand people attended the indoor meetings every were; over two thousand dollars is paid in rent.</p>
   <p>There are in Chicago eleven English speaking corps, seven Swedish, one Norwegian, and one German. There is one maternity hospital, one day nursery, and a number of other institutions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
