<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-08-25">Aug. 25, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">A Plea for Norwegian</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-08-25">Aug. 25, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">A PLEA FOR NORWEGIAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor of Skandinaven.</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>Being raised and educated in a large city of the United States, I had, in common with most young people in like circumstances, a sort of pitying contempt for everything not American--the Norwegian language included. I am afraid some of our public school teachers had something to do with bringing about that state of mind.</p>
   <p>The first one to open my eyes to the truth, was the late Dr. Poole, librarian of the Chicago Public Library. In the course of a conversation, he asked me the meaning of our family name, which ended in "vig". I was fortunate enough to be able to explain it to him. He then asked me if I read and spoke the <pb facs="5423969_4_1523.jpg" n="2"/>Norwegian language. "Not well," I answered.</p>
   <p>"Why not?"</p>
   <p>"Oh, I had never been made to learn it." (The truth must be told, however, I'm not proud of it.)</p>
   <p>"There is no honor in doing anything one is made to do," he said, and advised me to learn it as soon as possible. From that he went on to say that he had notice that the Norwegians learned English quicker than other nationalities, his observations being taken, in large part, from servant girls at his home.</p>
   <p>Later on I had the good fortune to visit Norway. How great that advantage was: I have been better able to appreciate it later. I found a much higher standard of culture there among the people of my circle than in America (this refers to Chicago and the West). Then and there I became acquainted with the literature 
    <pb facs="5423969_4_1524.jpg" n="3"/>of Norway and found in it a charm with which I fell deeply in love. I felt like the heathen who heard the story of Christ and exclaimed: "Oh! why has someone not told us this before!"</p>
   <p>Why not start reading clubs everywhere to study the Norwegian language, its saga, its politics, its wealth of beautiful literature; in short, Norway and its people. It is a country one need not be ashamed of, but ought to feel intensely proud of. I think such clubs would do more to foster that quality which so many say we are lacking--loyalty to our own people.</p>
   <p>Organize, buy a good map of Norway; subscribe to a good newspaper direct from Norway; learn to sing the songs, recite the poetry, read fine literature; study the biography and history; interest yourselves in the topics of the times on a large or small as circumstances dictate.</p>
   <p>Don't let the Norwegian die; at least don't hasten its death. The English is better able to take care of itself.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
