<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-04-04">Apr. 4, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian National Association Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1711</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1711.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-04">Apr. 4, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN NATIONAL ASSOCIATION MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian National Association met in quarterly session last Monday evening at Wicker Park Hall. Twenty societies were represented at the meeting. Mr. C. H. Lee, the treasurer, reported that the total income from the festival given at the Auditorium amounted to $1,980.27; the total expenses were 761.04, leaving a net balance of $1,219.25. The amount sent through Skandinaven to the Norwegian Department of the Interior in aid of the destitute widows and children of Norwegian fishermen killed during the great storm was 1,076.25, leaving cash in the treasury to the amount of $142.98.</p>
   <p>The auditors reported that they had examined Treasurer C. H. Lee's account and found it to be correct.</p>
   <p>The committee for the Seventeenth of May celebration reported having been in negotiation with Bjornstjarne Bjornson, trying to prevail upon him to come to Chicago to deliver the Seventeenth of May oration, but that a few days ago <pb facs="5423969_4_1712.jpg" n="2"/>the message had come from Norway that Mr. Bjornson had been ill, and that for this reason he did not dare to expose himself to the rigors of the voyage across the Atlantic. The committee reported having met several times, and that its program for the Seventeenth of May festival will be presented to the public as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>The Association accepted the various reports. Dr. Karl Sandberg, the president, expressed surprise that the committee did not have tickets printed for the Seventeenth of May celebration. Dr. Olaf E. Ray, the chairman of the committee, answered that since the price of the tickets would have been greater if Mr. Bjornson had come to speak, the committee had found it necessary to await word from him before deciding what price to charge. He promised that the tickets would be ready for distribution to the various societies within a few days.</p>
   <p>Mr. E. C. Christensen spoke in favor of having the Association's statutes printed. After extended discussion it was decided to appoint a committee <pb facs="5423969_4_1713.jpg" n="3"/>for the revision of the statutes and to have the committee report at the next quarterly meeting of the Association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
