<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-12">Apr. 12, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Society for the Norwegian Home for Aged</title><title level="a" type="sub">Meeting of Humboldt Park Branch</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-12">Apr. 12, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOCIETY FOR THE NORWEGIAN HOME FOR AGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Meeting of Humboldt Park Branch</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Humboldt Park Branch of the Society for the Norwegian Home for Aged held a very pleasant meeting last Monday evening at the home of Mr. and Mrs. John Anda, 901 North Albany Avenue. The president, Mr. Ludvig Monsen, opened the meeting by reading a chapter from the Bible. The reports received concerning the conditions at the Home were very satisfactory. Hardly a single case of illness has occurred, and la grippe has been avoided by the aged.</p>
   <p>From the last meeting of the board of directors, Mr. Olaf Anda reported that the Schoenhofen Hall had been secured once more for the bazaar which will be held during the week from November 4 to November 10. He also informed the Branch that several applications for acceptance at the Home had been received, but the Home is full and has no room at present for additional guests.</p>
   <p>The financial secretary reported that membership fees received during the <pb facs="5423969_4_0160.jpg" n="2"/>first quarter amounted to $54.75. Ten new members were received into the Branch.</p>
   <p>After the business meeting, Mrs. Anda attended to her duties as hostess, while Miss Minnie Colberg, Mrs. Anda [wife of Dr. Anda], Miss Jorgenson, and Miss Taft diverted the group with music, singing, and readings. The next meeting will be held at the home of Mrs. Jennie Thye, 817 North Fairfield Avenue. The date of the meeting will be May 14.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
