<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-02-23">Feb. 23, 1909</date><title level="a">The Norwegian National Association Banquet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1652</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1652.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-02-23">Feb. 23, 1909</date><title level="a">The Norwegian National Association Banquet</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Mutual admiration" is once more gaining the upper hand in the Norwegian National Association, with the sole difference that the mutual admiration society within the Association seems to be more select, more exclusive; it does not include the whole board of directors, as was formerly the case.</p>
   <p>All of this was clearly revealed at the banquet given yesterday by the Association. The banquet, with the exception of the speeches, was a success; the good, which was served by the Kaffistova (Coffee Hut), was first class, the very best that has ever been offered at any Norwegian-American banquet at the price charged. The assistance rendered by Miss Bergliot Allruds, the organist Christopher Ursins, and the Lawson Orchestra served to add a touch of festivity to the whole. Bjorgvins beautiful hall was tastefully decorated....There is no question that the committee on arrangements had performed its task well.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1653.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At about nine o'clock the guests were seated, and were welcomed by Mr. S. Husoby, chairman of the committee on refreshments. He also introduced the toastmaster for the evening. The foremost task of the toast-master is to enliven the proceedings, and to be successful in this, one must have a reasonably good command of the language. This requisite, however, was not possessed by the toastmaster of the evening, and inasmuch as some of the other speakers of the evening also did their best to murder the Norwegian language, one need not wonder that some of those who were present felt that Norwegianism did not receive its due at the evening's banquet.</p>
   <p>Mr. Birger Osland spoke on the objectives and the activities of the Norwegian National Association. He outlined the growth of the Association from its humble beginnings as a ten-man committee, of which Dr. Marl Sandberg was the president and the speaker the secretary. He lauded the administration of Attorney Hummeland and Ommund Harveland. Nothing, however, was said at any time about the administration of A. Abrahamson and that of Mr. Osland himself, and yet these two administrations must be considered the best in the history <pb facs="5423969_4_1654.jpg" n="3"/>of the Association.</p>
   <p>Mr. Martin Clausen spoke in honor of America, while Mr. John Borge's speech in honor of Norway was the best delivered speech of the evening. C. Gilbert spoke about business life in Chicago, and Mr. John Jersin brought the speechmaking to a close with a speech in honor of Norwegian benevolent endeavors. At the close of his address he proposed a toast to the ladies.</p>
   <p>The solos offered by Miss Allrud were rewarded with enthusiastic applause. The regular program having reached its end, the toastmaster hurried to conclude the banquet. The attendance was quite large.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
