<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-04-19">Apr. 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[International Norwegian League Activities]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1599</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1599.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-04-19">Apr. 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[INTERNATIONAL NORWEGIAN LEAGUE ACTIVITIES]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We wonder just how many members of Chicago's great Norwegian colony realize what a strong organization Nordmands Forbundet (International Norwegian League) is, or have any idea as to its future strength. The League is now only six years old; yet it already has a membership of 40,000 scattered throughout the world. Each year adds thousands of members, and by the time the festivities start next year (1914), we expect to have 100,000.</p>
   <p>The year 1914 (centennial year for Norway) will be the big year for the League as well. Then it expects to attract Norsemen from all over the world for the festival. They are already advised of the home-coming of Norsemen from China, India, Australia, South America, South Africa, America, and the Arctic countries. And what a traveled gathering that will be! Norway is justly proud of her representative children found in every corner of the world, and the rate in which the membership is increasing is ample proof of the pride <pb facs="5423969_4_1600.jpg" n="2"/>in their mother country of the horde of scattered Norsemen everywhere. In order that we Norwegian-Americans may have a broader Knowledge of Norway, her advancement, and the celebration of her centennial, she is sending us the secretary of the world-wide league, Mr. C. J. Hambro, who delivered a fine lecture on Norway at Bjorgvin Hall last Monday night.</p>
   <p>We know of no better messenger of good will than C. J. Hambro. This man is a veritable eternal spring of information on any subject one cares to mention concerning Norway and her people. "The secret of the success of Norsemen wherever they are found," said Mr. Hambro, "is their outstanding individualism." Through many years this trait had hindered concentrated action but 1905 conquered this individualism to an undreamed of degree. The result of this is the wonderful cooperation between Norway and Norsemen in foreign lands, who are all working toward one goal - a successful centenary festival in 1914. The Norwegian pictures, with which Mr. Hambro accompanied his lecture, were a revelation of the progress of a country of which comparatively little is known <pb facs="5423969_4_1601.jpg" n="3"/>in other countries, the widespread idea being that Norway is only a land of fish and goat cheese.</p>
   <p>Norway is today's miracle of achievement and advancement. She does not yield the palm, even to our own United States of America in the excellence of her road building, telephone service, dairy industries, etc., and in the utilization of her water power to produce electricity she is far in advance of any other country in the world, especially when size is considered. Norway is now the land of the future as much as she formerly was the land of saga and song.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
