<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-11-12">Nov. 12, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A Salutary Verdict</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0339</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0339.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-11-12">Nov. 12, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A SALUTARY VERDICT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"We the jury find Harry H. Hammond not guilty." Before this finding was announced, another verdict had been rendered by a larger jury sitting upon the same case. It reads as follows: "We the people of Chicago find Harry H. Hammond not guilty." The finding of the jury merely gave the force of law to the verdict rendered by the conscience of the community.</p>
   <p>On March 21, Harry H. Hammond shot John T. Shayne with intent to kill. This was the charge of the indictment. But in the language of the attorney for the prosecuting witness, "It was not Harry H. Hammond who was on trial in this case, but his client, John T. Shayne." The jury evidently was in perfect agreement with the attorney upon this point.</p>
   <p>Says James O'Leary, foreman of the jury: "All that I will say is that we went according to the law and the evidence in the case as we saw it. We followed out <pb facs="5423969_4_0340.jpg" n="2"/>the instructions of the court, and I believe that our result is correct."</p>
   <p>Another juror says: "It was a question whether a rich man could go into the home of a poor man and steal his wife, and I would have stayed there a hundred years before I would have voted to convict Harry Hammond."</p>
   <p>The attorneys for the defendant take the same view. "The case was common decency against money," says Attorney Miller, "and decency won. I believe this is one of the most important cases ever tried in Cook County. If Shayne had won, what home would be safe against the attacks of unprincipled men with money and position to back them up? The verdict of the jury was just in accordance with the evidence."</p>
   <p>Attorney Scanlan voices the same sentiment: "We have established a man's right to be poor and retain the sanctity of his home against a rich suitor for his wife's affections. We have vindicated his honor, and now we propose to see the child he loves restored to him."</p>
   <p>The verdict may or may not be open to certain objections of a technical character.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0341.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But it voices the all but unanimous sentiment of the community. No other verdict would have been regarded as just. It will undoubtedly serve as a precedent for the future. After this day Chicago will not be a safe place for rich wife thieves. A rich man who undertakes to steal a poor man's wife and children will know that the job may cost him his life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
