<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-06-29">June 29, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0763</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0763.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-06-29">June 29, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following Scandinavians bought or sold real estate in Chicago recently:</p>
   <p>Axel W. Ostrand to Henry Palmer: Robey Street [now Damen Avenue] and Berwyn Avenue. Price, $8,000.</p>
   <p>Charles M. Storey to Nils P. Wickstrom: Southport Avenue and Grace Street. Price, $8,600.</p>
   <p>Nils Wickstrom to Charles M. Storey: Southport and Newport Avenues. Price, $14,000.</p>
   <p>Harry Korak to Max and Louis Paulson: Leavitt and Le Moyne Streets. Price, $14,000.</p>
   <p>Fannie C. Stella to John M. Carlson: Columbia and Lakewood Avenues. Price, <pb facs="5423969_4_0764.jpg" n="2"/>$5,500.</p>
   <p>John M. Carlson to Fannie E. Stella: Pratt Avenue and Sheridan Road. Price, $11,000.</p>
   <p>John L. Bobo to John M. Carlson: Sherwin Avenue and Perry Street. Price, $5,000.</p>
   <p>Albert Halvorsen to A. Bohnenberger: Armitage and 40th Avenues. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Charles S. Neeros to R. J. Renertson: Avers and Belden Avenues. Price, $650.</p>
   <p>Ida A. Arbogast to Emma L. Hansen: Byron Street and 40th Avenue. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>Arnold Nilson to Ole Nilson: Fullerton and Spaulding Avenues. Price, $10.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0765.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Max Friend to Abraham Nelsen: Chicago Avenue and Robey Street. Price, $50,000.</p>
   <p>Oscar Erickson to Chas. G. Erickson: Cortez and Willow Streets. Price, $3,500.</p>
   <p>Mathilda Nelson to John J. Corbett: Haddon and Western Avenues. Price, $1,325.</p>
   <p>Annie Peterson to David Getiebter: Leavitt and Le Moyne Streets. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>John F. Amberg to H. C. Johnson: North Avenue and 41st Court. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <p>Mads Christensen to Annie M. Quinn: Ridgeway Avenue and Le Moyne Street. Price, $1.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0766.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Haral F. Hibbard to Carl Johan Nelson: 51st Avenue and Ontario Street. Price, $4,112.</p>
   <p>A. Kleinbinzen to Morris Arnesen: Hastings and Wood Streets. Price, $5,000.</p>
   <p>C. A. Erickson to Ph. R. Nelson: Evanston and Balmoral Avenues. Price, $1,675.</p>
   <p>Emma L. Hansen to Ida A. Arbogast: Lincoln Street and Hood Avenue. Price, $1.</p>
   <p>Emanuel Osterholm to Carl Fritz: Lakeside Place and Sheridan Road. Price, $29,000.</p>
   <p>John S. Benson to Otto Peters. School Street and 41st Avenue. Price, $1,800.</p>
   <p>Jacob Nissen to Herman Anderson: Magnolia Street and Rosemont Avenue. Price, <pb facs="5423969_4_0767.jpg" n="5"/>$12,500.</p>
   <p>H. T. Anderson to Jacob Nissen: Winthrop and Balmoral Avenues. Price, $27,000.</p>
   <p>Ingeborg Wold to D. E. Meyer: Drake and Schubert Avenues. Price, $10,800.</p>
   <p>M. O. Halloran to Catrina Olsen: Monticello and Armitage Avenues. Price, $4,050.</p>
   <p>Niels J. Nielsen to Georg Frost: Kedzie and Belmont Avenues. Price, $5,175.</p>
   <p>Martin M. Serum to W. Hendricksen: Huron Street and 50th Avenue. Price, $6,500.</p>
   <p>George Carlson to August Emerick: Artesian Avenue and Hirsch Street. Price, <pb facs="5423969_4_0768.jpg" n="6"/>$7,000.</p>
   <p>Joshua Jackson to Louise Jacobsen: Edgemont and Ashland Avenues. Price, $6,000.</p>
   <p>Andrew Johnson to Alfred Norton: Oregon Avenue and Loomis Street. Price, $5,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
