<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-10-02">Oct. 2, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Stensland Bank Scandal Comes to an End</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-10-02">Oct. 2, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">STENSLAND BANK SCANDAL COMES TO AN END</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Stensland case is one that cannot but set people thinking about banking systems, banker embezzlers and forgers, from the president down to the newest teller.</p>
   <p>On Monday, September 24, the steamer "Prince Adelbert" arrived in New York, from Tangier, Morocco, with Paul O. Stensland, president of the bankrupt Milwaukee Avenue State Bank, on board. At the quarantine station they were met by a sloop carrying federal guards to protect Harry Olson and James J. Kelly, Stensland, the prisoner, attorneys who sought an opportunity to serve Stensland, detectives, photographers and Theodore Stensland, son of Paul O. Stensland. The first night ashore was spent by Stensland in the Mulberry Street Station where he was questioned, photographed for the rogues' gallery, and measured by the Bertillon system. He did not know what a mattress or pillow felt like that night, but he did know what the "third degree" of the New York Police department meant.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0288.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Theodore Stensland had been in New York several days and stood ready to put his father in touch with the best lawyers in the city at a moment's notice, but the father was not interested; he preferred to get to Chicago as soon as possible and face the music here. In compliance with Stensland's desire, they left New York on Tuesday, arriving in Chicago on Wednesday morning.</p>
   <p>At the LaSalle Street Station, he was met by an inquisitive throng who greeted him with scornful and insulting remarks. He was well guarded by a police detachment and he was taken directly to the Criminal Court building. Here, in a three hour examination, Paul O. Stensland made a complete confession implicating several co-workers who, until now, had not been suspected. The names of the new guilty ones are, for the present, withheld from publication.</p>
   <p>After making his confession, Mr. Stensland, pale, weak and shaking, was brought before Judge Kersting, accompanied by State's Attorney Healy and his two assistants, Harry Olson, and James Barbour. Harry Olson presented the case before the judge and stated that Stensland desired to plead guilty. The first charge read dealt with the misappropriation or defalcation of one million <pb facs="5423969_4_0289.jpg" n="3"/>dollars. Stensland admitted that he was responsible for $400,000 and stated that he could, had he so desired, taken the entire amount.</p>
   <p>The judge rebuked Stensland severely before sentencing him to from one to ten years in prison, and a $120 fine. The formerly proud and important"king" of Milwaukee Avenue was now left lonely and deserted; neither lawyer, friend nor relative seemed to know that he still existed or stood at his side to cheer or console him. From court he was taken to a restaurant, and from there to the train bound for Joliet.</p>
   <p>Stensland's daughter, Mrs. Inga Sandberg, accompanied him, while Theodore, the son, seemed to have vanished completely. Arriving in Chicago and then in Joliet on the same day, Paul O. Stensland had become number 9902 and the following day he was assigned to work in the broom factory where the recently sentenced J. A. Linn, absconding Chicago court clerk, is serving his time. On his first day at prison labor, Stensland was visited by his son Theodore; the visiting time allowed seemed too short for both.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
