<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-09-25">Sept. 25, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">[The Stensland Bank Scandal]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-09-25">Sept. 25, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">[THE STENSLAND BANK SCANDAL]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several important details are mentioned regarding the Milwaukee Avenue State Bank Crash (Stensland Bank Scandal) during the last week. On Tuesday, September 18, Judge Windes postponed the hearing of the controversy between Attorney General Stead and receiver Fetzer until this week.</p>
   <p>The establishment of a new bank in the old location is about settled, as a charter has been issued to George Packard, John J. Packman and John F. Hagey who represent several of the large down-town banks. It is possible that the new bank may direct the affairs of the collapsed Stensland Bank thereby making it possible to return some money to the stricken depositors.</p>
   <p>Walter Franzen, accused of stealing large sums from the bank a number of years ago has posted a $5000 bond for his appearance in court when the case is called. Reporters who approached Franzen were given the cold shoulder while <pb facs="5423969_4_0291.jpg" n="2"/>State's Attorney Barbour drew a complete confession from him, in which Franzen places the entire blame on cashier Hering, whom he characterizes as an arch-thief of today in whose presence Paul O. Stensland was utterly helpless.</p>
   <p>The rumor that Theodore Stensland had betrayed his father's whereabouts is still traveling, in spite of the sincerity he showed in defending his absent father. Theodore went to New York with the intention of engaging lawyers there who could hold his father in New York and prevent him from being brought to Chicago.</p>
   <p>In reference to the audit by bank inspector Jones, there is a seemingly well-founded report that Jones is not as reliable as he might be; the receiver will show, before Judge Brentano, that there are $340,000 more on hand than Jones reported. This additional balance on hand consists of $81,000 in cash; the balance consists of real estate values which Jones had reported <pb facs="5423969_4_0292.jpg" n="3"/>worthless. Mr. Fetzer has reported the possibility of turning over to the depositors eighty-five cents on the dollar or $132,600. Other values were actually owned by the bank, but were held under other names. These are notes for $52,579 and bank property valued at $75,000. These make possible a much larger reimbursement than was possible according to the audit by inspector Jones. The pleasing phase of the receiver's report is the fact that he could easily have backed the report of Jones and put what he found in his own pocket with no one being the wiser.</p>
   <p>The search for resources has revealed the fact that Stensland had committed forgeries as far back as 1896, using, among other names, that of Sheriff C. R. Matson. A few days ago Mr. Fetzer found bonds, covering bank employees, amounting to $23,000. These bonds were issued by the American Surety Company. These had also been included in the "worthless" list turned in by Jones, though Mr. Fetzer plans on holding the Surety Company to its contracts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0293.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Another detail unearthed by Fetzer is:--the employees who have been indicted were old members of a gambling syndicate with headquarters at Gus Anderson's saloon, 225-227 Milwaukee Avenue, where the police department unearthed a bank book that proves to be indisputable evidence as to where the bulk of stolen funds went.</p>
   <p>Regarding the "Prinz Adelbert," the boat on which Paul O. Stensland is being brought from Tangiers, Morocco, had been sighted off Fire Island and will reach the quarantine station at four this afternoon. Nothing definite is published as to what is on the program in the transportation of Stensland to Chicago by his captors Olson and Keeley.</p>
   <p>According to our information nothing will be permitted to hinder the landing of Stensland and his immediate transportation to Chicago. The commission issued by the president to Harry Olson, will hardly be opposed by New York authorities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
