<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-06">Apr. 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Home for the Aged</title><title level="a" type="sub">Fourth Anniversary Celebrated</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-06">Apr. 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN HOME FOR THE AGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Fourth Anniversary Celebrated</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Society for the Norwegian Home for the Aged celebrated its fourth anniversary at Wicker Park Hall last Wednesday evening. A large audience was present, filling all the seats on the main floor and in the gallery.</p>
   <p>The program opened with a piano solo by Miss Lucille Fitzgerald, after which the president of the Society, Dr. N. T. Quales, welcomed the visitors and introduced Mr. H. A. Hangan as the speaker. Mr. Hangan in his speech traced the history of the Norwegians in Chicago during the past fifty years, with special reference to their activities for benevolent purposes. Miss Ragnhild Johnson rendered "Salveig's Song" very attractively and received much applause.</p>
   <p>The Rev. J. Z. Torgerson was the next speaker....."The early settlers," he <pb facs="5423969_4_0165.jpg" n="2"/>said, "coming to America fifty years ago, started by building little homes for themselves; their next important task was to build a church. Having finished the church, they started erecting schools and about 1870 the thought of founding charitable institutions, such as hospitals, orphanages, and homes for the aged took root. Here in Chicago the work for benevolent institutions did not gain momentum until about ten years ago, but the work done in this line during the past ten years is astonishing. Money has been collected for hospitals,for orphanages, and for homes for the aged, as well as for other benevolent institutions, and in accomplishing this, our people have displayed a degree of persistency and energy--somewhat like the Boers in South Africa against the English--in their endeavor to make these institutions as excellent as possible. The Home for the Aged has accomplished much during the four years since it was founded. The Society is working for a noble purpose, and it deserves the support of all."</p>
   <p>After the speech, Miss Fitzgerald and Miss Charlotte Jones gave a piano duet, after which the Reverend Austin D. Crile was introduced to the audience. In <pb facs="5423969_4_0166.jpg" n="3"/>his speech he dwelt on the rich opportunities he had had during the past year of associating with the Norwegians, and the pleasure he had derived from this association. He has visited the Norwegian Home for the Aged, he stated, and rejoiced that the Home was conducted in the Christian spirit. He warmly congratulated those who had been active in the work for the Home and reminded them that it is ever more blessed to give than to receive. He closed with an exhortation not to let the good work lag.</p>
   <p>Professor T. Beresina gave a violin solo. There was warmth in his playing, and both his "Concerto" by Ole Bull and his "Phantasie" by Bariot were received with storms of applause. Two encores were necessary to satisfy the people. The Wicker Park Quartet sang the "Hunters' Song" and "To My Country". The songs were loudly applauded. The festival concluded with a piano solo by Arthur N. Granquist. In the dining hall the ladies served coffee and cakes.</p>
   <p>Secretary John Blegen distributed the fourth annual report of the Society. The report was printed by Alderman A. W. Beilfuss, Mr. P. Halgersen has provided <pb facs="5423969_4_0167.jpg" n="4"/>the photos to illustrate the book, and Blomgren Bros. &amp; Co. developed the plates, all of this being done free of charge. The annual report appeared in Skandinaven some time ago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
