<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-06-24">June 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Norwegian National League]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-06-24">June 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[NORWEGIAN NATIONAL LEAGUE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.3...............The Norwegian National League met in extraordinary session at Kedzie Hall on Monday June 19. The session was called to discuss the advisability of rendering financial aid for further research as to the value and authenticity of the now famous Kensington stone. Dr. Boe's demand that the aid be given was met by protests from Mr. Svendsen, who rather recommended financial aid to needy countrymen in the colony. This proposition brought on a lengthy talk by Mr. Molmstrom who vigorously pointed out that the "League" was not a charitable institution. He warned the league against becoming involved in charitable activities as it could be so easily victimized (due to its inexperience), calling attention to the ease with which frauds had been perpretated on a man of such wide experience as our country agent; $40,000.00 having been grafted during the past year.</p>
   <p>The question of the Kensington stone brought on quite a discussion and the immediate outlay in its behalf was voted down. Instead, the league decided that upon being advised by the faculty of the University of Christiania that the stone, in their opinion, is genuine they would appropriate $50.00 toward the traveling <pb facs="5423969_4_1637.jpg" n="2"/>expenses of Mr. Haaland (custodian of the stone) who is to display the stone at Europe's greatest universities and give the faculties of these an opportunity to voice their opinions as to the genuineness of the Kensington.</p>
   <p>The coming July 4th celebration was also discussed at length. The proposed "safe and sane" fourth movement is supported by organizations of all other nationalities and our people owe it to the country and to themselves to put on a good show of man-power in the parade and to do all in their power to help make our Independence Day a safe and sane success. An appropriation of $125.00 was voted to cover the expense of a proper representation in the big parade and delegates were instructed to urge their respective organizations to put forth every effort to make a real showing for our Norwegian colony. Out athletic clubs, turner societies, lodges, choruses etc could, if they would, turn out and demonstrate to every other nationality that we are a group worthy of respect and consideration in all city wide (even state wide) activities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
