<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-04-08">Apr. 8, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">No Politics in the Matter</title><title level="a" type="sub">by John Jersin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-08">Apr. 8, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">NO POLITICS IN THE MATTER</title><title level="a" type="sub">by John Jersin</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A certain amount of criticism has been advanced concerning the appearance of a note referring to the municipal election, then close at hand, and the program announcing the annual festival of the Norwegian Home for Aged, copies of which were distributed in the churches. The statement objected to in these programs appeared at the bottom of the page, informing the readers that Alderman Beilfuss had paid for the printing of the annual report of the Home for Aged, and in addition a note reading "Vote for him on Tuesday".</p>
   <p>I beg to inform the readers of the Skandinaven that the Society for the Home for Aged and its board of directors are without blame in this matter. At the annual meeting I was requested to see to the publishing in pamphlet <pb facs="5423969_4_0162.jpg" n="2"/>form of the annual report, the supposition being that such publishing would be done without expense to the Society. It was suggested to me that Alderman Beilfuss might pay the cost of printing, and...his promise to do so was obtained. It was understood by Mr. Beilfuss that the report was to be distributed before the municipal election in which he was a candidate....I had explained this to the Alderman and suggested that his generosity in the matter would be made known to the people interested, to which he agreed.</p>
   <p>I then ordered the programs printed and added the note concerning the printing of the annual report of the Home for Aged. It did not occur to me that the matter might be given political significance; to me it was merely a word of appreciation for a generous act. Permit me to say that there were candidates for alderman at the past election whom I would not have permitted to touch the program, but in regard to Mr. Beilfuss I had no scruples although he is a Republican, and I have been voting for Mr. Cleveland whenever I had a chance to do so.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0163.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Naturally, the note put on the program did not obligate anybody to vote for Mr. Beilfuss.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
