<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1902-08-03">Aug. 3, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">The Case of Thombs</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0329</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0329.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1902-08-03">Aug. 3, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">THE CASE OF THOMBS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Governor Yates has refused to grant Louis Thombs a respite for the third time. This sign of returning decency in the executive chair at Springfield comes as an agreeable surprise to the people of Chicago who were prepared for another unwarranted delay of justice.</p>
   <p>The murder of Carrie Larson is the most brutal, the most heartless and revolting crime that has been committed in Chicago in many a day. It was a bloody deed of unspeakable horror, calling for stern and swift justice. The wretch had a fair and thorough trial. He was afforded every opportunity to establish his innocence. But the evidence of guilt was overwhelming and absolutely conclusive. There was no reason whatever for interference with the regular course of justice in this instance. Yet the Governor stayed the hand of justice not once, but twice. In the meantime a well-known attorney, whose specialty it is to pose as <pb facs="5423969_4_0330.jpg" n="2"/>a champion of the people while accepting fat retainers from trusts and other corporations, collected a large amount of money to enable the monster to drag his case through the lengths of the courts. If he should succeed in this effort the blame will rest largely upon the Governor whose undue leniency paved the way for the judicial farce.</p>
   <p>That foolish women waste sympathies, flowers and delicacies, upon red-handed murderers is bad enough; delay of justice on account of executive interference without valid reason is worse. Murders are more frequent in the United States than in any other civilized country, with one or two exceptions. The deplorable state of affairs is due largely to the sickly sentimentality of hysterical women who lionize criminals, to the unblushing practices of a certain class of lawyers, to the delay and uncertainty of justice in our courts of law, and to lack of backbone in those who are invested with the pardoning power.</p>
   <p>Punishment of crime, to effect its purpose, must be just, sure, and swift. With us it may be just; but it is neither swift nor sure.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
