<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-02-02">Feb. 2, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">[The Norwegian Society Sondmoringen Opens Drive for Aid to Victims of Aalesund Fire]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0239</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0239.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 10 (Swedish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-02-02">Feb. 2, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">[THE NORWEGIAN SOCIETY SONDMORINGEN OPENS DRIVE FOR AID TO VICTIMS OF AALESUND FIRE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the initiative of the Norwegian society Sondmoringen, a public meeting was held last Thursday evening at Wicker Park Hall. Norwegians had been specially urged to attend. The purpose of the meeting was to get started as quickly as possible on a drive for subscriptions for the [relief of the] many thousands of men, women, and children who became destitute as a result of the terrific fire which on January 23 devastated the thriving city of Aalesund, Norway. The meeting was called to order by Mr. H. Behrentz, the president of the Sondmoringen. Editor N. A. Grevstad was elected permanent chairman of the meeting. After a brief discussion, a working committee was appointed, consisting of the following seven members: H. Behrentz; John Anderson, publisher of the Skandinaven; H. A. Haugen, banker; Dr. A. Doe; Editor N. A. Grevstad; A. Hummeland; O. A. Thorp. Mr. Grevstad was elected chairman of the committee. He briefly outlined the program for the work of the committee and informed the meeting that an appeal to the Norwegian-Americans for aid had already been made through the various Norwegian papers in America; that <pb facs="5423969_4_0240.jpg" n="2"/>some money had already been sent, e.g. one thousand crowns contributed by the Skandinaven at the moment the news of the fire arrived. Mr. Grevstad took it for granted that the Norwegian churches in America would contribute generously to those in need in Aalesund. He then requested Banker Haugan to take up a collection among the people present; in a few minutes the amount of $688 had been gathered.....</p>
   <p>Svenska Nyheter expresses the hope that the Swedish-Americans in Chicago and elsewhere will also remember our destitute Norwegian brothers and sisters in the city of Aalesund, so terribly hit by the fire.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
