<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-01-17">Jan. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Home for the Aged</title><title level="a" type="sub">Secretary's Report to Annual Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0066</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0066.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-17">Jan. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN HOME FOR THE AGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Secretary's Report to Annual Meeting</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The protocal of the deliberations of the board of directors shows that twelve regular monthly meetings have been held during the year of 1908. There were three extraordinary meetings, called joint meetings since they included the Ladies' Aid Society. There were also two special meetings called "when the directors had mothing else to do." There was a quarterly meeting in October, an annual meeting in January, and several committee meetings, some held at the residence of Dr. [N. T.] Quales, some in the quarters of the Home for the Aged.</p>
   <p>Of the socials held during the year may be mentioned the spring concert at Wicker Park English Lutheran Church; the summer social at the Home, on June 27; the grand picnic at the Home, on August 29; the bazaar, October 12 to October 17.</p>
   <p>Among other significant occurrences it may be noted that the Young Peoples' Branch dissolved in June, through which event the board of directors lost an honored and</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0067.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>useful member, Dr. Enerson.</p>
   <p>President Quales took a well-deserved rest--a two month's tour to Norway, and during this period the board of directors had to do the required planning and acting without his assistance; but things went well. An annual report was published, in occordance with a resolution at the previous annual meeting, and this task was accomplished with a small financial profit. Of late many have expressed the hope that the living quarters of the Home would be enlarged--a new building constructed to house many more aged people. Tonight it will be determined whether the expectation is to be realized or whether it is to remain only an air castle.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
