<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-10-18">Oct. 18, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Strong for English</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1519</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1519.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-10-18">Oct. 18, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">STRONG FOR ENGLISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor of Skandinaven.</p>
   <p>Dear Sir: No one with common sense can doubt that the Scandinavian youth will sooner or later adopt the English language. On the playgrounds of every town or city, wherever young Scandinavians associate, observers will note that in nearly all cases they converse in English and not in their mother tongue, showing beyond the possibility of a doubt that the English language, when once learned, is the one most easily spoken. Learn first to read and write the language of our nation to perfection; then it is time enough to study your mother tongue. Why? First, because many honest and intelligent foreign-born citizens have been kept away from honorable and lucrative positions simply because of their foreign brogue. Second, because the literature of neither Norway, Denmark, or Sweden attains as high a standard as does that of the United States and England. Where was there a writer among the Scandinavians like Shakespeare? Who can equal <pb facs="5423969_4_1520.jpg" n="2"/>those thrilling pictures of Florence Percy? What author can produce the noble sentiments of Longfellow, where do we find Charles Kingsley's powers of description? All will admit that that which a person reads has something to do in shaping his destiny, and in if it be true that the English literature is the best, why should we not adopt the language which contains the fine gems of thought?</p>
   <p>Many a minister of the gospel throughout the length and breadth of our land will be found at the head of a parochial school attempting--not always in an ideal Christian manner--to implant the Scandinavian languages, to the confusion of the little ones, who are at the same time studying the English language in the public schools. Should any church member have the "grit" to assert that his children were to learn English first and other languages to follow, our reverend friend may be seen holding up his hands in holy-honor. Yet upon inquiry it may be found that the learned expounder of scripture is himself unable to read the English language. expounder of scripture is himself unable to read the English language. The time is not far distant when our Scandinavian youth will shake off their shackles, declare their independence and accept the English language in all the spheres <pb facs="5423969_4_1521.jpg" n="3"/>of life, knowing that they, by so doing, adopt the only method by which they can attain as much respect from their fellow-citizens as they deserve.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
