<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-10-06">Oct. 6, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Young America</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0326</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0326.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-10-06">Oct. 6, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG AMERICA</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Frenchman spoke the other day of the increasing lawlessness in Paris, and declared that unless the situation was taken in hand, Paris would sink down to the level of the most lawless large city in the world: Chicago.</p>
   <p>Whether such a severe judgment of Chicago is justified may be doubtful, but it is certain that Chicago has received a black mark, and also that offenses against the law occur woefully often here in the city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0327.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Especially is this true of crimes of violence: attacks, burglaries, manslaughter, murders. About 200 people are killed by deliberate attack every year here in Chicago. There are probably more murders in Chicago per year than in Norway, during a century.</p>
   <p>Who, then, are the criminals here?</p>
   <p>Municipal Judge Sadler, who has dealt with a mass of criminal cases, declares that at least 75 per cent of all crimes in Chicago are committed by men under 25 years of age, and that boys under 19 years of age commit one half of all the assaults and burglaries that take place in the city. This does not coincide with the doctrine put forth by so many of the self-satisfied "natives" who would like to lay the crimes at the doors of the immigrants. Many of the youthful criminals <pb facs="5423969_4_0328.jpg" n="3"/>mentioned by Judge Sadler are probably of foreign descent; many of them may have come to this country as children or youths. But they have absorbed the spirit of lawlessness here.</p>
   <p>Noticing how young America is behaving and is permitted to behave, it is not to be wondered at that so many turn out badly and become thieves and murderers. Teaching the young to honor the older people and to bridle their evil tendencies - in other words, bringing the children up under discipline and the precepts of the Bible - is considered antiquated doctrine, and is a discarded formula in many of the Chicago homes. For this reason, so many of the youths of Chicago are going astray; for this reason also, Chicago is one of the most lawless cities in the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
