<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, John Anderson Publishing Co., Chicago, Ill, <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp.199-201.
<title level="a">Scandinavian Young Men's Christian Association of Chicago West Division</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, John Anderson Publishing Co.,Chicago,Ill, <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp.199-201.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIAN YOUNG MEN'S CHRISTIAN ASSOCIATION OF CHICAGO WEST DIVISION</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 13, 1876 a meeting was held at the Tabernacle Church, corner Morgan and Indiana Streets, at which an earnest effort was made by Scandinavian men to start a Young Men's Christian Association which would be able to give signs of a stronger vitality that the one ignominously departed. Fifteen persons among those present agreed in writing, to unite their forces and work in harmony to this end. A committee of five was appointed to draw up a constitution and by-laws.</p>
   <p>At the next meeting this committee reported and further arrangments were made and thus was born the present strong and healthy Young Men's Christian Association. The first association was however not yet absolutely dissolved and it needed more time to liquidate its business before it finally closed its doors. Wise by its earlier experience the new association adopted this paragraph in its by-laws. It shall be absolutely prohibited to discuss denominational differences of the various <pb facs="5423969_4_0177.jpg" n="2"/>churches in this assocation. As the first officers of the association the following were elected: E. Johnson, president; S. C. Hansen, vice-president; O. Erickson, corresponding secretary; P.A.G. Moe, recording secretary; P. Peder, Sen. librarian; L. Ross, treasurer.The records from that time make it evident that the work from the beginning was started in dead earnest. Prayer meetings, Bible classes, Sunday evening entertainments, singing exercises, etc, were of weekly occurences.</p>
   <p>Before the first year of its existence had expired, serious dissensions began to arise about the doctrine of the atonement. No man of sufficient authority to explain or settle the difficulty was analable and as a result two members were expelled and one (the accused) resigned. All of them had been very enthusiastic and active workers for the association.</p>
   <p>One great step in the right direction was taken when the association bought the library of three hundred volumes which had belonged to the older association. Later lectures were given for the association by such men as Prof. R.B.Anderson, <pb facs="5423969_4_0178.jpg" n="3"/>P. Fisk, and Peter Hendriksen. A bazaar held in the hall of 1879 showed a net profit of $158.00. This and other incomes were greatly needed as the association was in debt in more than $100.00 for rents alone and was compelled to move from one locality to another. No wonder, therefore, that the idea of a building for the association ripened under such circumstances. The first step was to incorporate the association under the laws of the state. This was done on April 14, 1888 with three members as board of directors. These three were Stangeland, Pihl, and A. K. Malum, who seem to have been the only members who were naturalized citizens.</p>
   <p>At its sixteenth annual festival in June, 1892 it had a building fund of $2,654.00. Two years later, on a similar occasion the committee was able to report that the building lots on West Erie Street had been purchased and here finally the building was erected. It was dedicated with festivities on Nov. 5, 1899. The year consequently may be put down as the banner year in the annals of the association. The lots of No. 3151/2-317 West Erie Street cost $3,300.00 and the building and lots together totaled $11,500.00</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0179.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In 1906, a valuable addition to the association's library was also made. Rev. Torgersen had left a well selected library of nearly one-thousand volumes and as his widow could not make any use of it she offered the association the first opportunity to buy it at practically their own price. They now have a very good selection which proves of great interest to visitors and members.</p>
   <p>The following regulations may be of interest: The reading room is open every day from 9:00 A.M. to 9:00 P.M. with free admission to all. Newspapers and Magazines in different languages can be found on the tables. From the library which numbers over one-thousand volumes books are loaned under certain rules.</p>
   <p>Regular meetings every Sunday at 4:00 and 8:00 P.M. Bible classes every Tuesday except the first Tuesday in the month. The association has a choir of well trained voices.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
