<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1896-07-09">July 9, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Their Responsibility</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1553</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1553.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-07-09">July 9, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THEIR RESPONSIBILITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the Populists are willing to lay aside temporarily those principles which differentiate the Democratic and the Populist parties, they will claim a share in the responsibility for whatever may happen if Mr. Bryan should be elected. Whether they desire it or not, the work of the next administration would be accredited to the two elements in common. Populists and silver Democrats alike would come out of the situation four years hence, hand in hand as the administration party, and as such they might be inclined to stand together in the subsequent campaign. The amalgamating effect of four years of joint control in the White House and Congress would be very great.</p>
   <p>It all depends. The probability is that "four years of Bryan" would result even more disastrously than "four more years of Grover", and that Democrats and Populists <pb facs="5423969_4_1554.jpg" n="2"/>would vie with each other in disclaiming "a share of the responsibility".</p>
   <p>As everybody knows, the Wilson-Gorman law is the one great feat of the present administration. The Democrats and the Populists are jointly responsible for the law. But for the support of Populist Senators it could not have been enacted. However, it does not appear that the Populists are anxious to claim credit for their share in this un-American piece of legislation; on the contrary, their angry denunciations of the law are heard throughout the land.</p>
   <p>The Republicans of the House presented to the Democratic-Populist silver majority of the Senate a bill for an increase of revenue. It was a necessary measure, which, if adopted, would have put the treasury upon a sound footing and prevented more bond issues. But the Democrats and Populists wanted none of it, though the proposed law was to be only a temporary enactment.</p>
   <p>The treasury keeps on running behind and the gold reserve keeps on going down, as everyone, including silver Democrats and Populists, knew they would. But <pb facs="5423969_4_1555.jpg" n="3"/>it does not appear that either "element"is jealous of its share in the responsibility for the continued deficit or the prospective bond issue.</p>
   <p>Our Scandinavian voters should bear this in mind, and cast their votes accordingly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
