<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1899-07-09">July 9, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A Plea for the English Language</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1510</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1510.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-07-09">July 9, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A PLEA FOR THE ENGLISH LANGUAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I believe that it is perfectly right and proper to study the mother tongue, provided the English language has already received its share of attention, as the knowledge of mare than one language is of great value to us in our walk through life. It also tends to strengthen the intellectual faculties. I also believe that no one should deem it improper to speak the mother tongue where the exigencies of the hour demand it.</p>
   <p>But I still believe that a more extended use of English should be brought about, because speaking English is more becoming to an American citizen. Our forefather's future prospects in the mother country were not bright, but here they found a ready welcome after they had braved the stormy ocean in search of more congenial surroundings, and we, their descendants, being reared amid the free institutions of our land, certainly ought to have enough love for our staunch republic to use its language in daily life.</p>
   <p>In a former article I asserted that if English came into general use throughout <pb facs="5423969_4_1511.jpg" n="2"/>the Scandinavian groups, it would place us on a more intimate footing with our English-speaking neighbors. No critic can prove that this statement is erroneous. It seems to me that if an extended use of English were brought about it would have a tendency to unify the people of all the states; there would be less hatred and more brotherly feeling between man and man; in fact, the whole nation would be benefited thereby.</p>
   <p>How such daily use of English would cause us to forget--forget means to lose the remembrance of the mother tongue--is more than I can understand. The acceptance of the English language in all the spheres of life, in the home as well as in society, and in rural as well as in business life, would not tax our memories to such an extent that we would forget our native tongue. We would still be at liberty to study the Scandinavian languages.</p>
   <p>That Scandinavian employees who have become Americanized have better prospects in securing employment then have those who continually cling to old country <pb facs="5423969_4_1512.jpg" n="3"/>customs and languages, is so well known that it is unnecessary to go into details.</p>
   <p>The young people are already manifestly in favor of English, at least the majority of them. They admire the beauty of English and American literature; they find it easier to express themselves in English on present-day themes, and that language will, at an early date, be accepted by most Scandinavians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
