<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-12-21">Dec. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Norwegian Club Is Strong for the Norwegian Language</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_1470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-12-21">Dec. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO NORWEGIAN CLUB IS STRONG FOR THE NORWEGIAN LANGUAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The sentiment for maintenance of the Norwegian language in Chicago Norwegian Club proved so strongly prevailing at the meeting last Thursday evening that at present it would merely cause anger and division if the opposition continuously attempt to supplant English for the Norwegian which after all is the heart of the club. It is now certain that Norwegian will be maintained.</p>
   <p>The question came up for consideration in connection with a proposal presented by the law-committee that Norwegian and English be given equal standing relative to the official dealings of the club. Actually the proposal signified the suppression of Norwegian, since in a club in which constantly be accepted more and more members who do not speak Norwegian, the "equal standing" given to English and Norwegian would <pb facs="5423969_4_1471.jpg" n="2"/>inevitably bring about the adoption after a while of English as the official language of the club. Where conditions of this type prevail, it is necessary to protect the Norwegian language if it is to be maintained.</p>
   <p>For this reason a counter proposal was presented giving Norwegian and English equal standing in the club with the exception that the presiding officers shall conduct the official meetings of the club in Norwegian, and that the secretary use Norwegian in his records and reports. When the vote was taken, the majority proved strong in favor of this proposal but the proposal did not receive the required two thirds majority. The proposal brought forward by the committee did not either receive two thirds majority, and the whole question was returned to a conference committee consisting of representatives for both parties. Thus an armistice prevails between the two factions until the middle of January, and in the meanwhile, the committee will do its utmost for the best interests of the club.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_1472.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During the absence of the president, Captain Birger Osland and of the secretary, Mr. Anders Nesheim, the vice-president, Joachim Giaver functioned as moderator and Theodore Laws as secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
